<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Dollar Rises Modestly; Gold Declines a Bit in U.S.</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="336830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CURRENCY MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DB143CF931A15750C0A966958260" item-length="471" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Dollar Rises Modestly; Gold Declines a Bit in U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The dollar moved up modestly against most major currencies, including the yen, the pound and the West German mark, in slow trading yesterday, as traders sought a safe investment haven. Gold prices posted minor declines in domestic dealings after much larger losses overseas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The dollar moved up modestly against most major currencies, including the yen, the pound and the West German mark, in slow trading yesterday, as traders sought a safe investment haven. Gold prices posted minor declines in domestic dealings after much larger losses overseas.</p>
        <p>The dollar moved up modestly against most major currencies, including the yen, the pound and the West German mark, in slow trading yesterday, as traders sought a safe investment haven. Gold prices posted minor declines in domestic dealings after much larger losses overseas.</p>
        <p>One reason that investors sought safety was increasing tensions in Lithuania, which declared its independence from the Soviet Union on March 11. President Mikhail S. Gorbachev ordered Lithuanians yesterday to turn in their weapons, a day after the Baltic republic's Government demanded an end to Soviet military maneuvers.</p>
        <p>Despite Japan's one percentage point increase in a key interest rate on Monday, the dollar rose to 154.37 Japanese yen late in New York, from 154.20 yen late Tuesday. Tokyo markets were closed for Japan's national holiday on the vernal equinox.</p>
        <p>Effect of Uncertainties in Britain</p>
        <p>Also contributing to interest in the dollar was the uncertain outlook for Britain's governing Conservatives, because of rising prices, high interest rates, the deterioration of the Government-run health service and a new tax on every adult to finance municipal services.</p>
        <p>The British pound slipped to $1.5955 late in New York, a weakening from late Tuesday's $1.6005. The pound closed yesterday in London at $1.5965, down from Tuesday's $1.6105. It stood at $1.7145 on Feb. 22.</p>
        <p>Earl I. Johnson, a vice president at the Harris Bank in Chicago, said activity in the dollar was subdued, lacking significant corporate or interbank trading. Other late dollar rates in New York, compared with late quotes Tuesday, included: 1.7100 West German marks, up from 1.7048; 1.5225 Swiss francs, unchanged; 5.768 French francs, up from 5.7575; 1,259.75 Italian lire, up from 1,258.00, and 1.17875 Canadian dollars, up from 1.17765.</p>
        <p>Selected rates for the dollar late in Europe, compared with late Tuesday's levels, were: 1.7070 West German marks, up from 1.6965; 1.5192 Swiss francs, up from 1.5157; 5.7575 French francs, up from 5.7340; 1.9230 Dutch guilders, up from 1.9107; 1,257.25 Italian lire, up from 1,253.50, and 1.1769 Canadian dollars, down from 1.1792.</p>
        <p>Gold bullion prices fell back after traders took profits on the metal, which had crept above $400 an ounce on Monday.</p>
        <p>On New York's Commodity Exchange, gold for March delivery settled at $391.80 an ounce, 40 cents lower than Tuesday. Later, the Republic National Bank of New York quoted a bid of $391.90 for an ounce of gold, 50 cents lower than Tuesday's late bid.</p>
        <p>Gold closed in London, the major foreign market, at a bid of $391.75 an ounce, down from $398. Silver was mixed. In New York, silver bullion for March delivery closed at $5.055 an ounce, up from Tuesday's settlement of $5.043. Silver bullion traded late in London at $5.06, down from Tuesday's late bid of $5.09.</p>
        <p>CURRENCY MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
