<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hollywood Breathes In The Spirit of Sundance</title>
    <meta content="02JAME$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="905882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Sundance Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE2DA1E3AF931A35751C0A961958260" item-length="2552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hollywood Breathes In The Spirit of Sundance</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <dateline>PARK CITY, Utah</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sundance Film Festival, Park City, Utah, while continuing to focus on small independent films, has emerged as major movie venue, turning filmmakers into instant celebrities; Hollywood, in part because of festival's influence, has embraced independent films as never before; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT THE SUNDANCE FILM FESTIVAL, it was hard to walk down the street or negotiate your way through a party without being mowed down by a camera crew. Park City was full of them, but they weren't making movies; they were trying to mint new celebrities.</p>
        <p>ABC's ''Good Morning America'' was trailing Morgan J. Freeman (no relation to the actor), the director of ''Hurricane,'' an adolescent angst movie that went on to tie for this year's Audience Award. MSNBC was following the three partners in October Films, whose non-Sundance movies ''Secrets and Lies'' and ''Breaking the Waves'' are contenders for Oscar nominations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT THE SUNDANCE FILM FESTIVAL, it was hard to walk down the street or negotiate your way through a party without being mowed down by a camera crew. Park City was full of them, but they weren't making movies; they were trying to mint new celebrities.</p>
        <p>ABC's ''Good Morning America'' was trailing Morgan J. Freeman (no relation to the actor), the director of ''Hurricane,'' an adolescent angst movie that went on to tie for this year's Audience Award. MSNBC was following the three partners in October Films, whose non-Sundance movies ''Secrets and Lies'' and ''Breaking the Waves'' are contenders for Oscar nominations.</p>
        <p>Most ubiquitous was the crew from CBS's ''48 Hours,'' loyally dogging every step of Vin Diesel, a pumped-up New Yorker who wrote, directed and stars in ''Strays.'' At one dizzying moment, CBS was filming Diesel being filmed by the Sundance Channel.</p>
        <p>Even the hardest-nosed business people, the distributors who come here prepared to buy movies, now astutely describe this festival in terms of pop-culture celebrity. Their tone is usually stunned, as if visualizing money flying out of their pockets.</p>
        <p>''We're turning these guys into instant millionaires; they're like basketball players,'' Bob Aaronson, an acquisitions executive at 20th Century Fox, said of Sundance film makers. Fox Searchlight paid more than $2 million for ''Star Maps,'' an improbably funny yet moving film about a Latino would-be actor who sells maps to movie stars' homes and moonlights as a prostitute.  As Lindsay Law, president of Fox Searchlight, said, ''The film maker is the new rock star.''</p>
        <p>The irony is: this wasn't a very hot year at Sundance, either for commerce or for art. No matter. Every year a Saint Vitus's dance sets in; buyers were setting up clandestine screenings, and moviegoers were swarming into theaters like locusts. ''Noah Wyle's trying to cut in line,'' someone said about the actor from ''E.R.,'' who stars in ''The Myth of Fingerprints'' and was being led through a jammed corridor to see his film.</p>
        <p>Among these trappings of fame, no wonder it is now standard to ask, Has Sundance sold out to Hollywood? But a far more pertinent question is, Has Hollywood sold out to Sundance? And as this low-key, course-correcting year proves, beneath the glitz, the Sundance Film Festival (which ended last weekend) has remained remarkably focused on small independent films. Meanwhile the landscape has shifted all around it. Like the mountain going to Mohammed, Hollywood has expanded its range of vision to include the ideals that Sundance has long been fostering.</p>
        <p>Even with your eyes closed, it's not easy to confuse Rod Steiger with Robert Redford. Yet when Mr. Steiger stood on stage at the Golden Globe Awards recently, his words sounded eerily like those Mr. Redford had been saying for years. ''They're called independent films because of their financing, but they're independent because of their spirit,'' Mr. Steiger said, presenting a clip from ''Breaking the Waves,'' nominated for best drama. His words (in a ceremony televised on NBC, as mainstream as movie-gazing gets) suggest the direct link between Hollywood and Park City. In part because of the Sundance Film Festival's influence, Hollywood has embraced independent films as never before.</p>
        <p>Eight years ago, when ''Sex, Lies and Videotape'' became the first commercial hit out of the festival, the movie world was separated into gargantuan studio films and tiny, shoestring works. Since then, a huge middle ground has emerged, a gray area composed of major independent companies -- like Miramax, Sony Pictures Classics, Fine Line, October, Gramercy and Fox Searchlight -- releasing films like ''The English Patient'' and ''Shine.''</p>
        <p>''The independent world has staked out a turf,'' says Geoffrey Gilmore, Sundance's programming director. ''You can't say that film is either commercial or low-end now. There are a lot of models out there for how to make independent films.''</p>
        <p>And at the low end of the scale, almost anyone can get into the game. Investors have found that a movie made for less than $2 million will probably break even if there are some shrewd foreign, video and television sales. Practical factors as different as improved technology and New York union contracts that give breaks to independents have contributed to the glut of films at this festival and in the marketplace.</p>
        <p>Sundance's crucial role in this equation has been to raise the profile and expectations for independent movies. ''Six years ago at this festival, there would have been a lot of debate about whether any of these films had commercial potential,'' Mr. Gilmore says. Now the debate is about how much potential they have.</p>
        <p>But that development cuts two ways. It is easier for a new film maker to create a movie, and ever harder to find a distributor. As L. M. Kit Carson (who acts in and is a producer of ''Hurricane'') points out with a bluntness that is refreshing in this atmosphere of sensitive plants, there is also an unfortunate side to that trend: ''It leads people to think their dog can direct a movie.'' For every ''Shine,'' which is a success, there is a ''Spitfire Grill,'' which sold at Sundance last year for a calamitously overpriced $10 million. That price took what might have been a modest success and turned it into a major commercial failure.</p>
        <p>Still, directors come here inspired by the Sundance fairy tale and by films like ''The Brothers McMullen,'' which made Edward Burns a name director. ''People are thinking, 'I can do that. I can win Lotto!' '' said Robert Bella, a first-time director whose ''Colin Fitz'' was in the dramatic competition. He didn't win Lotto or a prize, but he did direct a deftly amusing dark comedy about security guards protecting the grave of a rock star. Its wit was a relief in a year more loaded than usual with coming-of-age stories.</p>
        <p>That's another deadening aspect of the independent explosion; every young film maker has a sexual awakening story. They blend together even though every possible variation was represented here: homosexual in the amateurish ''Delta,'' heterosexual in the slight but charming ''Mary Jane's Not a Virgin Anymore,'' lesbian in the vibrantly shot and acted ''All Over Me.'' The only thing missing was ''Babe's Not a Virgin Anymore'' with pigs and dogs.</p>
        <p>THE RELATIVE LACK OF daring in this year's films is dynamic proof that just because you can make a movie, doesn't mean you should. Vin Diesel became one of this year's object lessons. ''Strays,'' a rambling, distant relation of ''Mean Streets'' in which tough guys learn to love their moms, was almost universally considered one of the low points of the festival.</p>
        <p>There was, in fact, so much carping about weak selections this year that Robert Redford himself made a snarky comment in retaliation. After three feet of snow fell at his Sundance resort on Saturday, he was unable to get down the mountain to the awards ceremony in Park City. He sent a statement to be read, which included a line presumably in defense of Mr. Gilmore's much criticized program. ''Please don't shoot the messenger,'' Mr. Redford wrote. ''There are enough critics trying to do that.''</p>
        <p>There's no need for Sundance or Mr. Redford to be so defensive, or for buyers to be so unrealistic. After all, how often does a John Sayles or a David Lynch come along, establishing careers that viewers will want to follow for decades? How often does a ''Shine'' strike gold?</p>
        <p>There were, instead, plenty of films here that help define what good independent film making is about. ''The Myth of Fingerprints,'' an engaging and subtle family drama directed by Bart Freundlich, blurs the line between Hollywood and Sundance. It has recognizable stars, including Blythe Danner, Roy Scheider and Julianne Moore. Yet Mr. Wyle, playing one of several siblings who return home for Thanksgiving, is at the center of a father-son conflict that beautifully avoids a predictable Hollywood ending.</p>
        <p>Over lunch, Mr. Wyle sounded smart about his own career and about what makes an independent film independent. He could have parlayed his television success into a role in a Hollywood film, but he's aware that the cast of ''Friends'' have bombed out in movies that way.</p>
        <p>''I knew that a low-budget independent family drama was probably the best thing I could do, for my own sanity and professionally,'' he said. ''Independent film has now taken on the air of 'quality.' I wanted to structure my career to insure as much longevity as possible.''</p>
        <p>And he points out differences between the realism of ''The Myth of Fingerprints'' and a Hollywood melodrama. ''If this were a studio film, I wouldn't have pushed my father into a table, I would have beat him up. My father wouldn't have kissed my girlfriend; he would have raped her.'' Because the film came to Sundance with a distributor, Sony Pictures Classics, it was one of the few polished movies in competition, something even other distributors could admire.</p>
        <p>''There was not an ounce of fat on 'Myth of Fingerprints,' '' said Mr. Law of Fox Searchlight. ''Every year  film makers stand up and say, 'We just finished the film; you're the first audience to see it,' and I want to say, 'Don't do it!' This is no place for a dress rehearsal anymore.''</p>
        <p>True to its purpose, the festival has balanced smooth films with edgier work, including ''Star Maps'' (shown out of competition) and ''In the Company of Men,'' a tiny social comedy about two men who hatch a nasty plot to seduce and humiliate a deaf woman, retaliating for years of  abuse by females. People here argued about whether it was misogynistic or male-bashing, but both extremes seem wrongheaded. One man is a sociopath, the other a wimp.</p>
        <p>Because of its provocative subject, ''In the Company of Men'' at least got some attention. As the festival grows, and distributors prowl for commercial prospects, the danger is that less flamboyant films will get lost. A slow, lovely film like ''The Whole Wide World,'' which was in last year's festival (and is in theaters now), got scarcely any attention here. That hints at the scary notion that Sundance audiences may be as impatient as any others.</p>
        <p>Hardly anybody talked about this year's Grand Jury winner, ''Sunday,'' which deserved its prize. The film creates an elegant maze in which a middle-aged man living in a shelter in Queens is mistaken by a middle-aged actress for a famous director. Or is she mistaken after all? David Suchet, usually seen as the impeccable Hercule Poirot on PBS's ''Mystery,'' becomes this downtrodden man with complete credibility, and the film creates a playful mirror world even while examining the realistic texture of diminished lives and expectations.</p>
        <p>Directed by Jonathan Nossiter and written by him and James Lasdun, ''Sunday'' was the odd film out among so many kiddie flicks. ''This is a good film that would be dead without winning,'' said John Powers, the film critic for Vogue magazine and a member of this year's jury. ''Now it has a chance to find the audience it deserves.''</p>
        <p>Distributors are now circling around ''Sunday,'' but the festival is littered with the remains of Grand Jury winners that never found an audience. (Do ''Chameleon Street'' or ''Public Access'' sound familiar? Of course not.) The Audience Award is usually the better harbinger of mainstream interest. ''Hurricane'' shared the prize with the romance ''Love Jones'' (which came to Sundance with New Line as its distributor). ''Hurricane'' is not nearly as rich as ''Sunday,'' but it has a more viewer-friendly surface. Essentially it is one more variation on the coming-of-age film, in which a 15-year-old New York boy, being brought up by his grandmother while his mother is in prison, becomes carelessly involved in petty crime.</p>
        <p>While the competition films disappointed buyers hoping to find Hollywood's next flavor of the month, Mr. Lynch's ''Lost Highway'' is a film with enough glossy production values for Hollywood, enough enigmatic content for Park City, and enough artistry to explode all categories. To say it is a murder mystery without a solution is merely to hint at its many swerves and layers, as Bill Pullman plays a man accused of murdering his wife, played by Patricia Arquette. All the elements of film making come together as they could in no other form: haunting visual images, a story that has the thrust of film noir, an eclectic jazz-and-pop score.</p>
        <p>SO MANY THINGS IN life are abstractions, and cinema has a way of dealing with that,'' Mr. Lynch said, adding that the film, which includes a mysterious transformation from one personality to another, ''is not always intellectually understandable; it's an intuitive sort of understanding. People have to feel their way through.'' The remark makes sense coming from a man who started out as a painter and who resists describing ''Lost Highway.'' As he said, in a voice that is remarkably tiny coming from such a tall man: ''If you could say those 2 hours and 15 minutes in words, that would be beautiful, but usually the words fail.''</p>
        <p>If David Lynch is the epitome of a daring independent, the kind of film maker Sundance helps and hopes to breed, Steven Soderbergh has been the Sundance poster boy ever since ''Sex, Lies and Videotape.'' Yet this year he brought a new film literally across the street, to Slamdance, the rival festival that was started three years ago by film makers turned away from Sundance. There, the audience sits on folding chairs and some lie on sofa cushions on the floor. The existence of Slamdance is  proof of how establishment Sundance has become.</p>
        <p>Mr. Soderbergh's unexpectedly funny and strange ''Schizopolis'' is a screwball comedy about language and how it falls apart. The director himself stars in a deadpan role as a corporate executive who switches lives with a dentist and occasionally speaks gibberish. In an introduction, added recently to help loosen up the audience and prove ''this isn't some pretentious treatise,'' Mr. Soderbergh offers the droll commentary that all of civilization rests on the acceptance of his film.</p>
        <p>Mr. Redford has called Slamdance a parasite feeding off Sundance, which of course it is. Sundance's attitude toward Slamdance seems to be ''This town's not big enough for both of us.'' Actually, as Sundance grows, it's hardly big enough for one of them anymore. But don't expect Sundance to move to Hollywood; it has done an amazing job of luring Hollywood in the direction of Park City.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
