<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Basics of Building a Birdhouse</title>
    <meta content="CNCLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HOME CLINIC" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="905983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DF153DF931A35751C0A961958260" item-length="1040" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Basics of Building a Birdhouse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BUILDING a birdhouse may seem like a frivolous project to the serious homeowner. There are, however, a number of reasons to make the project. It's a good way for a beginning woodworker to practice using tools and learn the fundamentals of shaping wood. A simple birdhouse is also a good beginning project to introduce a youngster to the pleasures of woodworking. Also the completed project will serve as a nesting place for wild birds and can perhaps kindle an interest in ornithology.</p>
        <p>The birdhouse featured in this article is designed to attract either bluebirds, house wrens or finches. It may also attract English sparrows.The project is simple to construct because it has only six pieces: two sides, a top, a front panel, a back panel, and a bottom. You can make the birdhouse out of almost any wood, but pine is probably the best choice since it is relatively inexpensive, readily accessible and easy to work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BUILDING a birdhouse may seem like a frivolous project to the serious homeowner. There are, however, a number of reasons to make the project. It's a good way for a beginning woodworker to practice using tools and learn the fundamentals of shaping wood. A simple birdhouse is also a good beginning project to introduce a youngster to the pleasures of woodworking. Also the completed project will serve as a nesting place for wild birds and can perhaps kindle an interest in ornithology.</p>
        <p>The birdhouse featured in this article is designed to attract either bluebirds, house wrens or finches. It may also attract English sparrows.The project is simple to construct because it has only six pieces: two sides, a top, a front panel, a back panel, and a bottom. You can make the birdhouse out of almost any wood, but pine is probably the best choice since it is relatively inexpensive, readily accessible and easy to work.</p>
        <p>You will only need a few common shop tools to make the birdhouse: a rip saw, a backsaw (choosing and using handsaws was featured in the Home Clinic on June 25, 1995), a block plane, a ruler, pencil, try square, a drill with  1/2-inch and 1 1/2-inch bits, a hammer, a nail set, galvanized nails, sandpaper and a paintbrush.</p>
        <p>Pine is sold in select (also called clear) and common grades. The select grade is subdivided into A,B,C and D categories. Select A is free of knots splits, and other defects. Select D may have numerous small knots and some surface blemishes. Select B and C boards fit between these two extremes. Select boards are more expensive than common ones, but they have fewer defects and require less filling and finishing. Besides, only a small amount of lumber is needed for this project, so the expense should be minimal.</p>
        <p>You can also use plywood to construct the birdhouse. If you decide to use plywood, however, be sure that it is exterior-grade plywood. Interior-grade plywood is laminated to resist only normal interior dampness, and it will disintegrate when exposed to the elements. Plywood is available in various thicknesses, but for this project it's best to use either  5/8-  or  3/4-inch panels. One problem with plywood is that it is usually sold in 4 by 8 foot panels (some lumberyards may sell smaller sections). Obviously you don't need that much lumber to construct a small birdhouse.</p>
        <p>Redwood is good choice for any outdoor project since it is durable and weather-resistant. It is, however, harder to work than either pine or plywood and more expensive;  mistakes can be costly. Do not use pressure-treated boards to make the birdhouse, because the chemical preservatives in the wood make it unsuitable for use near food or animals.</p>
        <p>If you look at the accompanying diagram, you'll see that you will need one board 5 inches wide (for the back, front and bottom) and another board 6 1/2 inches wide (for the sides and top). Most lumberyards do not sell boards less than 8 inches wide; so buy a board 12 inches wide by 3 feet long (the extra few inches of length will allow you trim off the ends that may have splits or cracks), then rip (sawing along the grain) the two pieces from it.</p>
        <p>Sawing usually leaves unsightly cut marks on the wood. It's best to cut a little wide of the mark, then use the block plane to trim and smooth the edges of the sawn boards. Use the ruler to mark off the individual pieces, then draw straight lines across the face of the board with the try square. Cut along the pencil lines with the back saw.  Do not use the rip saw for these cuts, the coarse teeth will chew up the wood. When making these cuts, either clamp the board to the worktable or secure it in a vise. This will hold it steady so you can concentrate on making smooth accurate cuts.</p>
        <p>Use the backsaw to remove the corners on the bottom piece. These small cuts will create four drainage holes at the floor of the finished birdhouse. Once the pieces are all cut out, drill a 1 1/2-inch hole, the entry hole, in the front piece. You can either use a spade bit or a hole saw for this. Drill a  1/2-inch hole, the mounting hole, with a twist drill or narrow spade bit near the top of the back panel. At this point you are now ready to assemble the bird house.</p>
        <p>Use 4d galvanized (these will not rust) finishing nails (Nails were featured in the Home Clinic on Jan. 14, 1996). Nail the sides to the back piece, then nail the bottom in place. Position the front piece, but use only two nails, one on either side, to hold it in place. These two nails will act as swivel points so that you can pivot the front up and clean out the birdhouse at the end of the season. Place the top in position. The top will meet the back panel at a slight angle. Use the block plane to bevel the back edge of top and eliminate any gaps, then nail it in place. Countersink all nail heads with the nail set and fill the resulting holes with wood putty. Sand lightly, and finish the completed birdhouse with either exterior latex paint or polyurethane varnish. Choose either a matte or satin finish, because many birds are repelled by high gloss surfaces. To hang the finished birdhouse, drive a 30d nail into a tree about 8 to 10 feet up. Leave about two inches sticking out. Hook the birdhouse through the mounting hole on the nail. If possible the birdhouse should face the southeast. Most birds start looking for a nesting site in March, so the birdhouse should be up by then.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
