<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LONG ISLAND GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="2GUIDE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="LONG ISLAND GUIDE" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="905954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND GUIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E5D8173DF931A35751C0A961958260" item-length="1119" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LONG ISLAND GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FREE CHOICES</p>
        <p>TODAY The Islip Arts Council's Winter Concert series moves to Dowling College where the Minneswaska Chamber Music Society offers ''Classics to Jazz'' with music by Bolling. The weekly series continues through March 23 (224-5420).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FREE CHOICES</p>
        <p>TODAY The Islip Arts Council's Winter Concert series moves to Dowling College where the Minneswaska Chamber Music Society offers ''Classics to Jazz'' with music by Bolling. The weekly series continues through March 23 (224-5420).</p>
        <p>The Massapequa Philharmonic Orchestra plays a special Youth Concert at 2 P.M. at Berner Junior High School on Carmans Mill Road in Massapequa. Joo-Young will be the violin soloist in a program that includes works by Brahms, Mozart, Saint-Saens and Sarasate (795-4071).</p>
        <p>TOMORROW Nassau Comunity College begins a 10-part ''Traveling Professor Lecture Series'' when Reggie Tuggle, director of college-community relations, discusses ''Politics and Society in Cuba Today'' at 10 A.M. in the College Union Ballroom in Garden City. For a complete series schedule call 572-9634.</p>
        <p>WEDNESDAY Laurie Fendrich, who teaches fine arts and art history at Hofstra University, gets to give the Hofstra Distinguished Faculty Lecture. The abstract painter will ask, and presumably answer, ''Why Paint a Painting at the End of the 20th Century?'' Her talk is at 11:30 A.M. in the Cultural Center on the Hempstead campus (463-5400).</p>
        <p>After a mid-winter break, the Dowling Film Society resumes monthlong tributes to the American film industry with a salute to George Arliss. The series starts with ''Man Who Played God,'' and continues with ''Alexander Hamilton,'' Feb. 12; ''Voltaire,'' Feb. 19, and ''Old English,'' Feb. 26. The screenings are at 8 P.M. in the Instructional Resource Center on the Oakdale campus (666-9476).</p>
        <p>THURSDAY To show the uninitiated how it's done, Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory mavens lead a seminar, ''The Internet One Year Later: Surf with the Experts,'' at 8 P.M. at the lab's Banbury Conference Center on Banbury Lane (367-8455). SATURDAY Lawrence Block, the bestselling mystery writer, appears at the Book Revue on New York Avenue in Huntington at 8 P.M. to talk about and sign copies of his latest thriller, ''Even the Wicked'' (271-1442).</p>
        <p>BLACK HISTORY MONTH</p>
        <p>Celebrations of Black History Month begin this week with diverse programming throughout the Island. Musically today, the J. J. Evans Specials, a gospel choir, appears at 2 P.M. at the Long Beach Library, West Park Avenue (432-7201); Earl Huie, baritone, appears at 2 P.M. at the Massapequa Library on Harbor Lane in Massapequa Park (799-0770); Sydney Hendrix and Friends perform ''Motown and More'' at 2 P.M. at the Rockville Centre Library on North Village Avenue (766-6257), and Gospel Elders and Little Buster sing gospel during a reception from 3 to 6 P.M. at the Museums at Stony Brook on Route 25A (751-0066).</p>
        <p>Charlotte Blake Alston, a storyteller, performs African and African-American tales today at 2 P.M. at the Bryant Library on Paper Mill Road in Roslyn (621-2240), while also today  there will be a lecture, ''Self Determination: A Challenge for the 21st Century,'' by Alton Maddox, a lawyer-activist, at 2 P.M. at the Nassau County African-American Museum on North Franklin Street in Hempstead (572-0730) and a ''Celebration of African American Poets'' by Beverley Wiggins-Wells, a poet, at 2:30 P.M. at the Brentwood Library on Second Avenue (273-7883). On Thursday at 7:30 P.M. Dr. Gloria Holmes appears at the East Islip Library on East Main Street to discuss tolerance (581-9200).</p>
        <p>Films on tap include: Haile Gerima's ''Sankofa,'' a drama about an African-American model's spiritual journey, Tuesday at 8 P.M. at the Port Washington Library, Library Drive (883-4400); ''The USS Mason: The Ship that Sank Naval Segregation'' at 7 P.M. Tuesday at St. Joseph's College in Patchogue (447-3224), and ''Get on the Bus,'' Spike Lee's film about the Million Man March, at 9 P.M. Friday at the Staller Center on the Stony Brook camus of the State University (632- 7230).</p>
        <p>The Cinema Arts Center, Park Avenue in Huntingon, begins a monthlong African-American Histroy Month Film Festival Thursday with ''Cleopatra Jones''; brings ''Get on the Bus'' in on Friday for a four-day run; shows the African film ''The Camp at Thiaroye,'' Friday, and on Saturday, pays tribute to Gloria Foster, who will speak about her career during a reception at 8 P.M. Before the festival ends on March 6, there will be a concert by Taj Mahal, Feb. 14; the showing of films like ''Small Wonders,'' next Sunday and Feb. 10; ''Shaft,'' Feb. 10; '''Stormy Weather,'' Feb. 18 and 19, and ''Cabin in the Sky,'' Feb. 25 and 26 (423-7610).</p>
        <p>'SCHUBERTIADE 200'</p>
        <p>Franz Schubert's 600 art songs don't always get their due during the current celebration of his 200th birthday. This will be rectified today  when, under the auspices of the Island Consort and Madrigal Singers, a group of professional musicians offer their ''Schubertiade 200,'' a concert of his songs about love, nature and the divine. Joel Frederiksen, a bass and lutenist, who directs the Consort, performs with Christian Fletcher, tenor; Joan Petrella, soprano; Barbara Fusco-Spera, mezzo-soprano, and Robert Palin, pianist, at 4 P.M. at the First Parish Church on Sound Avenue in Aquebogue (749-2231).</p>
        <p>'ON BROADWAY'</p>
        <p>When Ben Vereen and Leslie Uggams get together to perform, it figures that their material would be found ''On Broadway,'' which is exaectly what happens Friday when the two veterans of stage, television and films appear at Tilles Center. The musical revue, created and directed, by Lary Alford will be offered at 8 P.M. at the theater on the C. W. Post campus in Brookville (299-3100).</p>
        <p>HARP TIMES TWO</p>
        <p>What's potentially more heavenly than one harp? Why, two, of course. At least that's what the Sea Cliff Chamber Players hope happens Saturday when they present ''The Enchanted Harp,'' an unusual concert that features two duos for harps: Franck's ''Prelude, Fugue and Variations,'' and Carlos Salzedo's ''Pentacle Suite.'' The harpists are Nancy Allen, an artist-member of the Players, and her sister, Barbara Allen, a member of the chamber group Parnassus. They will be joined by Ida Levin, violinist; Toby Appel, violist-violinist, and Peter Wyrick, cellist, in a program that also includes music by Beethoven, Handel and Saint-Saens. Preceded by a music talk at 7:15 P.M., the concert is at 8 P.M. at the Sea Cliff Theater on Carpenter Avenue (671-6263).</p>
        <p>MUSIC FROM FRANCE</p>
        <p>The Orchestre National de France, conducted by Charles Dutoit and with the duo-pianists Valentina Lisitsa and Alexei Keznetsoff as soloists, comes to Tilles Center Saturday under the banner of Friends of the Arts. The program at 8 P.M. includes works by Poulenc, Ravel and Rimsky-Korsakov (922-0061).</p>
        <p>BARBARA DELATINER</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND GUIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
