<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>China Austerity Drive Is Hurting U.S. Ventures</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="648993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FACTORIES AND INDUSTRIAL PLANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MULTINATIONAL COMPANIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, PATRICK E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Multinational Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D71038F932A25752C1A965958260" item-length="1560" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>China Austerity Drive Is Hurting U.S. Ventures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK E. TYLER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TYLER, PATRICK E</byline>
      <dateline>SHENYANG, China</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last summer, when thousands of regional Communist Party bankers were printing money to finance their capitalist dreams, China's leaders in Beijing clamped down with an austerity drive to rein in a runaway economy.</p>
        <p>Bank lending stopped suddenly under orders from central authorities to recoup tens of billions of dollars in state loans made in a frenzy of unauthorized investment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last summer, when thousands of regional Communist Party bankers were printing money to finance their capitalist dreams, China's leaders in Beijing clamped down with an austerity drive to rein in a runaway economy.</p>
        <p>Bank lending stopped suddenly under orders from central authorities to recoup tens of billions of dollars in state loans made in a frenzy of unauthorized investment.</p>
        <p>But China's four-month-old austerity cure may be worse than the disease, especially if it kills the investment momentum that is pouring about $1.5 billion in foreign investment into China each month.</p>
        <p>Already, the program has undermined production at some American corporate ventures and dried up bank credits that were financing new factories for other foreign partnerships.</p>
        <p>Here in the heart of China's northeastern industrial belt, a $100 million joint venture with the General Motors Corporation and the Jinbei Automotive Company to produce pickup trucks is at a virtual standstill because local governments that would be likely customers for the trucks do not have the money to buy them. And even if they did, Beijing has told Government agencies and state factories to stop buying new vehicles until the end of the year.</p>
        <p>The austerity drive's aim was simple: stop the wasteful spending on golf courses when power plants and dams were begging for funds; get control of the inflationary spiral that had broken through 20 percent in urban areas and was still climbing, and, finally, slow China's growth, which was highballing at 13.9 percent in the first half of the year.</p>
        <p>But because China's economy still largely runs by central command, the austerity drive froze the flow of money through the banking system.</p>
        <p>Financing problems also endanger another $100 million project: Pittsburgh-based PPG Industries' plan to join Japanese and Chinese partners in producing flat glass in nearby Dalian. PPG said its Chinese partners could not get the money they needed.</p>
        <p>And the Chinese partners of the big American pharmaceutical company Pfizer Inc. are also said to be having trouble getting money to finance a venture that began operating earlier this year at Dalian, producing antibiotics and other medical products.</p>
        <p>Western bankers here have begun telling European and American corporations to proceed cautiously into China and to gauge how the austerity program, might affect new projects.</p>
        <p>The lack of money for Government-owned factories, some of which are straining to meet their payrolls, and the shortage of bank financing for construction became such a crisis that in early October China's economic czar, Deputy Prime Minister Zhu Rongji, flew to Dalian to address the complaints of industrial managers and regional officials.</p>
        <p>One result was that the Government decided about a month ago to pump $5.2 billion nationwide into high-priority projects that were going begging for working capital. But this injection may fall well short of the overall demand.</p>
        <p>Almost $1 billion of the emergency money was designated for projects here in the northeast, where one foreigner said American joint-venture executives "have been yelling bloody murder" over arbitrary Government decisions to block access to letters of credit and other sources of guaranteed financing. Tight Credit Acknowledged</p>
        <p>Zhou Zhengqing, deputy governor of the People's Bank of China, acknowledged that credit was tight, a situation he said was caused both by excessive construction as well as the controls clamped on by Mr. Zhu.</p>
        <p>He said those controls "are not meant to tighten money" and that additional funds were being directed to important projects in the railway, coal, oil, power, communications and building-materials sectors.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Zhu, who has day-to-day management control over the economy, engineering a "soft landing" for China's economy is a test of his political skill and China's credibility.</p>
        <p>There have been persistent reports in recent weeks that President Jiang Zemin and other members of the Politburo, fearing a crash landing of the economy with Mr. Zhu at the controls, are ready to throw off the strictures of the austerity plan.</p>
        <p>In recent days, there have been reports that China's ailing senior leader, Deng Xiaoping, has grumbled that the austerity program is stunting the full-speed growth he insists is the only course.</p>
        <p>"It is better to make the pace faster," he was quoted by Wen Wei Po, a pro-Beijing newspaper in Hong Kong, "A slower pace of development is not correct." Then, the Communist Party released one of the old speeches by Mr. Deng to showcase his dictum that slowing growth leads to civil unrest. Fear of Institutional Suffocation</p>
        <p>A number of officials have suggested that the austerity program will be enveloped by a new set of changes aimed at overhauling the banking and taxation systems. This plan was reviewed by the Politburo in the summer and was scheduled for consideration at a Communist Party Central Committee leadership meeting.</p>
        <p>A new commercial banking sector could go a long way toward re-establishing credibility for joint-venture companies that are finding out that guaranteed letters of credit are not worth the paper they are written on if the People's Bank of China simply refuses to issue the funds.</p>
        <p>"Most of the joint ventures are solving their problems at considerable cost to themselves," said one person knowledgeable about the ventures. "Either they have brought in more money, or they have sent people down to Beijing to complain until they get something done."</p>
        <p>A spokesman for PPG Industries, John S. Ruch, said, "Our Chinese partners have not been able to obtain the funding they have been promised" for a $100 million assembly line. PPG hopes that by 1995 it will begin making 600 tons of glass a day for China and for export to Japan.</p>
        <p>"At this point," Mr. Ruch said, the plant remains on schedule, but he added that PPG had put its Chinese partners on notice that without a favorable response on the financing by the end of the year, "the project will be affected in the near future." He declined to say whether PPG would pull out. Feeling Pinched</p>
        <p>A Pfizer spokesman in New York, Michael W. Hodin, said the Government's decision to tighten credit had had the effect of "reducing the local funds available for companies to finance their operations."</p>
        <p>"This limits expansion opportunities," the statement continued, "and results in an increase in the cost of doing business for both local companies and joint ventures in China."</p>
        <p>He did not elaborate on how the tight credit would affect Pfizer's plan to begin operations this year at a 250-employee production line that would make a range of pharmaceuticals.</p>
        <p>As for the General Motors joint venture here in Shenyang, analysts say G.M. may be a victim not only of the austerity program, but also of some basic miscalculations about China's auto market. G.M.'s share of the $100 million venture is a $30 million upgrading and expansion of an antiquated assembly line belonging to the Gold Cup state auto maker, which is affiliated with Jinbei, a major commercial vehicle maker. '1920's Technology'</p>
        <p>The plan was to jump into the truck business here by assisting Gold Cup in producing its dowdy trucks temporarily while bringing in kits of G.M.-designed products: a light-duty S-10 pickup truck and the Jimmy and Blazer utility vehicles.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s first problem was that in the spring, the aged Gold Cup trucks, which one executive described as "1920's technology," began to lose their market among Chinese customers. At the same time, the S-10 truck was not creating the demand that had been expected. Of the 500 kits assembled since May 1992, the venture sold only 12, one analyst said.</p>
        <p>"This could just be a question of suitability to the market," one analyst said. "The S-10 is overengineered for the China market. It is too expensive and it has too many bells and whistles on it." G.M.'s pickup costs about $25,300 in China; competing models sell for 35 percent to 50 percent less.</p>
        <p>But the real blow came during the summer, when Mr. Zhu announced his austerity measures and ordered state enterprises to stop buying new vehicles for the rest of this year. Now most of the activity going on at the G.M. assembly line in Shenyang is training and waiting. G.M. in for Long Term</p>
        <p>In Hong Kong, a G.M. spokesman, David Bodkin, said, "We recognize the country had to do something to cool down an overheated economy, and regrettably, we may have to live through it." He would not say how many trucks the venture had sold. "But we did not go to China only to pull out after a year or two," he said. "We view this as a long-term project. We're definitely staying."</p>
        <p>Putting the best face on it, Mr. Bodkin pointed out that G.M. business in China was up this year, despite the Shenyang disappointment.</p>
        <p>[ In Detroit on Monday, G.M. confirmed a report in the trade press that Robert Stramy had been replaced as president of its joint venture with Jinbei. His successor is Stanford Clemens, who took over in October. G.M. said Mr. Stramy left because his job, which was to initiate the venture, had been completed. ]</p>
        <p>G.M.'s exports to China jumped from 3,600 units in 1992 to an estimated 9,000 units this year. Mr. Bodkin said G.M. still planned to redesign the S-10 truck and hoped to build 50,000 trucks a year by 1998 with Gold Cup.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
