<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Talk</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="473756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, MARIO M (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D61F3BF936A2575AC0A967958260" item-length="887" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Talk</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sam Howe Verhovek</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pre-emptive Cocktails</p>
        <p>Albany's legislative leaders and Gov. Mario M. Cuomo engaged in hand-to-hand political combat this spring over the state budget, an exercise that pushed budget adoption two months past its legal deadline and left everyone involved embittered and exhausted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pre-emptive Cocktails</p>
        <p>Albany's legislative leaders and Gov. Mario M. Cuomo engaged in hand-to-hand political combat this spring over the state budget, an exercise that pushed budget adoption two months past its legal deadline and left everyone involved embittered and exhausted.</p>
        <p>So why were they all mingling over cocktails and canapes together at the Governor's mansion one day last week? So they don't have to go through similar brinkmanship next spring, they hope.</p>
        <p>The Governor has convened several bipartisan task forces to discuss big budget issues like Medicaid cost containment and criminal-justice reform, even though it is more than six months before the 1992-93 state budget is to be adopted. Four of the six task forces met for the first time last Wednesday, followed at the end of the day by the conviviality session at the Governor's house.</p>
        <p>"Maybe nothing will come of it," the Governor said later to reporters with a small shrug. "But at least we're making a sincere effort."</p>
        <p>Legislative leaders seemed amenable to the new approach, though none said that any agreements were reached in the first round. Among them there was something less than optimism that peace would break out at the height of budget time next spring.</p>
        <p>"It's like chicken soup," said Saul Weprin, a Queens Democrat and the chairman of the Assembly's Ways and Means Committee. "It certainly won't hurt."</p>
        <p>Despite the bonhomie reported by many participants, it wasn't long before there was a bit of bipartisan sniping. Republicans, who control the State Senate, complained that several of their Medicaid cost-cutting ideas produced only glazed eyes among their Democratic counterparts. One idea was to institute a photo-identification system for program recipients in order to cut down on fraud. "We were the only ones who really brought anything to the table," said John Daly, a Republican State Senator from the Niagara Falls area. "The Democrats kept saying that we had to talk about long-term solutions, but there are plenty of things you could do right now." The Price of Incumbency</p>
        <p>Despite the recession, the price of a lot of things keeps going up. Take the price of holding on to a legislative seat in Trenton.</p>
        <p>A new study of primary campaign spending by the New Jersey Election Law Enforcement Commission, a state agency, has found that incumbent lawmakers, who spent just over $1 million on their primary campaigns in 1987, spent $1.6 million this year, an increase running above the rate of inflation.</p>
        <p>All told, incumbents spent twice what challengers did in the primaries last year, and the disparity appears to be growing. The last time that both the Senate and the General Assembly were up for election, in 1987, incumbents spent 51 percent of the total amount expended; last year it was 70 percent. And while total primary spending by incumbents shot up 63 percent in that period, the spending by challengers actually dropped 23 percent. A report by the agency on general-election spending is scheduled to be issued later.</p>
        <p>The top spender in a Senate primary was Thomas H. Paterniti, Democrat of Edison, who spent $198,000, although he wound up losing to a challenger who spent $130,000. Dick Kamin, Republican of Mount Olive, spent the most among Assembly members, $112,000, in a victorious effort.</p>
        <p>Even bigger numbers are expected in November, with several candidates having already received $300,000 in donations two months beforehand. Battle on the Thames</p>
        <p>The Thames River in eastern Connecticut, which forms part of the border between the 18th and 20th State Senate districts, has become a skirmish line in the fight over the state's new income tax.</p>
        <p>Democrats would like to change the river's political course to repay a debt. District 18 is home to Senator Steven Spellman, a Democrat who provided one of the swing votes needed to pass an income tax and a budget last month after weeks of deadlock with Gov. Lowell P. Weicker Jr. Democratic Party leaders, who mostly backed the Governor's budget overhaul plan, want to reward Mr. Spellman and help his re-election chances next year by changing the district lines. They would move the predominantly Democratic city of New London -- on the west bank of the Thames -- into Mr. Spellman's east bank district.</p>
        <p>Republican leaders would like to make the same change, but to settle a score. District 20, on the west bank, is home to Senator Lawrence J. Bettencourt, a Republican who also voted for the income tax, to the deep consternation of his party, which stood mostly united against it. Mr. Bettencourt is vitally concerned about keeping New London in his district because he believes residents there will gain from state programs paid for by the income tax, and thank him for his tax vote in the 1992 elections.</p>
        <p>In return for losing New London, Mr. Bettencourt's district could pick up several heavily Republican suburban towns that might not be as favorably disposed toward the income tax. Republican leaders said even before the tax vote that they would do all in their power to see that renegades like Mr. Bettencourt were punished, and their agenda in negotiating the redistricting plan has been driven by the notion that 1992 will mark the voters' revenge on all who strayed from the state's no-income-tax tradition.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
