<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Group Roams Chat Rooms to Talk to Gay Men About AIDS</title>
    <meta content="09AIDS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/09/technology/09AIDS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1245745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stop AIDS Project</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaither, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E3DE1F39F93AA35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1293" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Group Roams Chat Rooms to Talk to Gay Men About AIDS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS GAITHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gaither, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stop AIDS Project, nonprofit organization which has fought spread of HIV virus among gay population, expands its outreach to include Internet chat rooms, where sexual encounters are often arranged; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHERE men meet men for sex, health agencies are sure to follow. In San Francisco, the bars in predominantly gay neighborhoods teem with safe-sex posters, baskets of free condoms and fliers for counseling services. Health officials hope that their message sticks in the mind of a patron as he leaves with a willing partner.</p>
        <p>But what to do when the meeting place is virtual, yet the sex that follows is just as real? The Stop AIDS Project, a nonprofit agency that has fought the spread of H.I.V. in San Francisco since 1984, is expanding its outreach from the usual venues to include increasingly popular places for arranging sexual encounters: Internet chat rooms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHERE men meet men for sex, health agencies are sure to follow. In San Francisco, the bars in predominantly gay neighborhoods teem with safe-sex posters, baskets of free condoms and fliers for counseling services. Health officials hope that their message sticks in the mind of a patron as he leaves with a willing partner.</p>
        <p>But what to do when the meeting place is virtual, yet the sex that follows is just as real? The Stop AIDS Project, a nonprofit agency that has fought the spread of H.I.V. in San Francisco since 1984, is expanding its outreach from the usual venues to include increasingly popular places for arranging sexual encounters: Internet chat rooms.</p>
        <p>The San Francisco Department of Public Health last month gave Stop AIDS a $130,000 grant to expand its presence into chat rooms. The agency will train four disease-prevention counselors to roam through chat rooms popular with gay and bisexual men and answer questions about safe sex.</p>
        <p>Recent studies have concluded that gay men are more likely to use the Internet to find a sexual partner than lesbians and heterosexuals and that people who use the Internet to arrange sexual encounters are more at risk for sexually transmitted diseases (S.T.D.'s). Health officials say gay men online and in general are not disclosing their H.I.V. status as consistently as they once did.</p>
        <p>''If we're working where people are meeting to have sex,'' said Steven Gibson, program director for Stop AIDS, ''we have to find ways to work on the Internet.''</p>
        <p>While online, Marcel Miranda, the deputy director of outreach and organizing, chats under the moniker StopAIDSMM. He works on an old Macintosh Quadra 610 in the Stop AIDS office, which is between a pet groomer and an exotic leather shop in the mostly gay Castro neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda has answered dozens of queries from chat room participants in the last month. Many express surprise that Stop AIDS is online, then pepper him with sexually explicit questions about what constitutes risky behavior.</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda writes back in graphic prose rarely heard from most disease-prevention counselors.</p>
        <p>''We're not the sex police,'' reads his America Online profile, which any chat room participant can pull up. ''We just want to make sure you have the information to make informed choices.''</p>
        <p>In San Francisco, where city health officials estimate that 15 percent to 20 percent of the adult men are gay, the Internet has become a likely place to find willing sex partners. In chat rooms like one on America Online for gay San Francisco men, homosexuals can scan the profiles of potential dates and carefully choose partners by age, race or sexual interests. Suitors exchange telephone numbers or addresses, then often meet for sexual encounters in which the participants know little more than their partners' online nicknames, said Dr. Jeffrey Klausner, director of the sexually transmitted disease unit at the city's public health department.</p>
        <p>The efficiency of such a system worries health officials because it allows diseases to spread outside small groups of partners. In August 1999, San Francisco officials traced a cluster of six syphilis cases back to the AOL chat room. Some of the men with the disease said they knew their partners only by their online nicknames. America Online refused to divulge the men's names to health officials, so PlanetOut, a Web site for homosexuals, was dispatched to advise chat room members to seek disease testing.</p>
        <p>''Disease-prevention agencies are chronically understaffed and underfunded,'' Dr. Klausner said, ''so this new venue which facilitates disease transmission places new demands on an already overstretched prevention system.''</p>
        <p>In a study in San Francisco, which has not yet been published, one-third of the gay men surveyed by public health officials reported having met  sexual partners on the Internet in the last year, compared with 13 percent of heterosexual men and 6 percent of women.</p>
        <p>''We recognize that at least for some gay men, this is a very common way in which they hook up with other partners,'' said Dr. Ronald Valdiserri, deputy director of the AIDS division at the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>The Internet's role in the spread of sexually transmitted diseases is still a relatively small worry for health officials, Dr. Valdiserri said, noting that many people who were at risk could not even afford a computer. However, he said public health workers should present their programs wherever people were meeting for sex, including the Internet.</p>
        <p>''Our approaches to H.I.V. and S.T.D. prevention have to evolve as technologies evolve,'' he said. The Stop AIDS program ''is not, in practice, different from providing outreach services on a street corner where injecting drug users might hang out or in a public park after-hours where sex takes place.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miranda, 44, proposed the online outreach largely because in the gay chat rooms he visited, men would describe their physical features and sexual interests, but rarely disclosed their H.I.V. status.</p>
        <p>''There's a lot of assumption,'' Mr. Miranda said. ''We're not disclosing our H.I.V. status like we were a few years ago.''</p>
        <p>Several Web portals for homosexuals, like PlanetOut and Gay.com, offer chat sessions and H.I.V.-AIDS  resources, but the H.I.V.-AIDS resources are often limited to one section of the site.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Miranda and the project team he will soon assemble, the challenge will be getting closer to the action without disrupting the interaction. The grant from the San Francisco health department also includes money for 10 Stop AIDS moderated chat sessions, called cyberforums, and two real-life parties for chatters.</p>
        <p>Most Friday evenings around 7, Billy Axelrod, 29, tosses on a red Stop AIDS windbreaker and walks into a bar like the Giraffe, the Cinch or Reflections. He introduces himself to the bartenders, then strikes up conversations with the clientele. At the end of each conversation he asks the other man to fill out a Stop AIDS sex survey.</p>
        <p>He suspects that the denizens of an Internet chat room would find that behavior intrusive.</p>
        <p>''It's a different culture online -- it's a different etiquette,'' Mr. Axelrod said. ''We don't want to go into a chat room and change the nature of what's going on. We want to be a passive presence.''</p>
        <p>But that method raises concerns for some gay advocates. What's to stop someone with no training from masquerading as a Stop AIDS counselor?</p>
        <p>Elizabeth Kennedy, director of community for PlanetOut, said she appreciated the intentions of Stop AIDS but planned to watch how its counselors interacted on PlanetOut.</p>
        <p>''Our primary concern is to assure that accountability and reliability are kept a priority,'' she said. ''We'd want to put in systems where users can be assured that people are who they say they are.''</p>
        <p>Most nights on America Online there are five or six chat rooms specifically for gay and bisexual men in San Francisco, each with 23 slots. On a recent evening, all the rooms were full. A participant in one of the rooms said that Stop AIDS, if it conducted itself properly, should find a welcoming crowd.</p>
        <p>''As long as they aren't pushing themselves on people,'' the person wrote, ''I think it's a good thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
