<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Decade, Queens School District Slips From Desirable to Troubled</title>
    <meta content="09DIST$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/09/nyregion/09DIST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1245936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kershaw, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Celestine V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0DF1738F93AA35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Decade, Queens School District Slips From Desirable to Troubled</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH KERSHAW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kershaw, Sarah</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses decline of New York City Community School District 29 in Queens; citywide ranking has slipped, former superintendent Celestine V Miller has been charged with taking kickbacks and squabble over new leadership has arisen; residents cannot agree on cause, but some blame Miller, others look to overcrowding caused by arrival of new immigrants, which also holds down test scores because of language problems; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just a decade ago, Community School District 29 in southeastern Queens was one of the city's most desirable, in a largely middle-class black neighborhood of stout brick homes and tree-lined streets whose schools had high reading scores and calm classrooms.</p>
        <p>But now its citywide ranking has slipped, its former superintendent has been charged with taking kickbacks in a corrupt contract to supply schools with computers, and it is mired in a squabble over new leadership with Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just a decade ago, Community School District 29 in southeastern Queens was one of the city's most desirable, in a largely middle-class black neighborhood of stout brick homes and tree-lined streets whose schools had high reading scores and calm classrooms.</p>
        <p>But now its citywide ranking has slipped, its former superintendent has been charged with taking kickbacks in a corrupt contract to supply schools with computers, and it is mired in a squabble over new leadership with Schools Chancellor Harold O. Levy.</p>
        <p>Residents like Ronnie Rogers, a Postal Service shipping clerk who moved from tattered East New York to leafier Rosedale in pursuit of better schools for her children, are deeply disillusioned.</p>
        <p>''I ran out here because of the educational promises,'' said Mrs. Rogers, 49. ''I called and I checked around. But I was given false information.''</p>
        <p>Student test scores, which once ranked District 29 eighth among the city's 32 school districts, have declined or remained stagnant. The district now ranks 14th in the city, and 43 percent of the students meet state reading standards. Many schools are severely overcrowded. The same parents who rushed to enroll their children in the district -- Mrs. Rogers and many of her neighbors and friends -- are clamoring to find spots for them in other districts or in private schools if they can afford it.</p>
        <p>Compounding the sense of betrayal and turmoil for many in District 29 was the news last week that the previous permanent superintendent, Celestine V. Miller, was charged in a major bid-rigging scheme in which she is accused of steering millions of dollars to computer companies in exchange for hundreds of thousands of dollars in bribes. Among the results, investigators say, were that students were cheated out of equipment or given broken computers that had been poorly maintained.</p>
        <p>''We seem to be hopeless,'' said Anna L. Thompson, a retired director of a home health care agency who has lived in Hollis, Queens, since 1959. ''I don't see the kind of independence or the kind of quality to make this a good district again, to make it reflective of the people who live here. I do see a lost opportunity.''</p>
        <p>There is not much agreement on why the district is floundering. Many people place the blame on the shoulders of Ms. Miller, pointing to the scandal and saying her own self-interest put a district with great potential on a course to mediocrity. Many principals were appointed as acting principals and kept on temporary status for several years because Ms. Miller persuaded the board not to hire them full time, several people said. Ms. Miller rejects the criticism.</p>
        <p>Other district residents attribute changes in the district to the arrival of immigrants, a change that they say has strained and crowded the school system and helped hold down test scores, since many of the immigrant students are learning English as a second language. Another complaint is that the local school board, which had consistently supported Ms. Miller, was ineffective, mired in politics -- two of its members work for politicians -- or simply unresponsive to the pressing needs of a changing community.</p>
        <p>''The focus was not on student achievement,'' said Assemblywoman Barbara M. Clark, who represents several neighborhoods in District 29. ''I always had questions about the administration of the school district.''</p>
        <p>As an example, Ms. Clark mentioned overcrowding -- the district is at 112 percent of capacity -- saying the superintendent and the school board had been unable for years to select sites for new school buildings.</p>
        <p>The district of 26,000 students and 28 schools is about 75 percent black, 12 percent Hispanic, 11.5 percent Asian and about 2 percent white. There are pockets of deep poverty within its borders and a growing number of immigrants, particularly from the Caribbean, but District 29 still has some of the most stable and affluent neighborhoods in Queens.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's and 80's, white middle-class families left the district in large numbers, mostly from the once predominantly white areas of Rosedale and Queens Village, and there was a vicious battle over integration in Rosedale in 1981. But unlike some other urban districts, it had a well-established black middle class in Hollis, Laurelton and Cambria Heights, and white flight was not believed to necessarily lead to decay.</p>
        <p>The changing demographics ''did not sway our course,'' said Reginald Landeau, who served as the district's superintendent from 1984 to 1992 and is now a senior fellow at the Center for Educational Reform in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Indeed, when Mr. Landeau retired, the school district appeared to be in good shape, steadily scoring in the top 10 on reading scores and still attracting parents who could afford private school.</p>
        <p>Ms. Miller, who has pleaded not guilty to the charges of paying or accepting brides, larceny and conspiracy, contends that she continued to move the district along that course, and that toward the end of her tenure she reversed a decline in scores, restored arts programs and received a stream of awards for her academic changes.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Ms. Miller said a key factor in the decline in test scores was the loss of some of the district's brightest students to neighboring Community School District 26, which is the city's top scoring district.</p>
        <p>She insisted that the sense of turmoil that now pervades the district came about after she was fired in 1999 by the schools chancellor then, Rudy Crew. Ms. Miller, who was appointed superintendent in 1992, was ousted after she delayed reporting that a student took a loaded gun to one of her schools.</p>
        <p>''I was ambushed then and I'm being ambushed now,'' Ms. Miller said.</p>
        <p>Currently, the local school board is locked in a battle with Chancellor Levy over the appointment of a permanent superintendent. In fact, the district has gone almost two years without a permanent leader.</p>
        <p>Yet to many parents, the recent charges against Ms. Miller and the battle over the superintendency with Mr. Levy, while disturbing, are the least of their worries.</p>
        <p>Audrey Dennis, a school secretary at August Martin High School in Queens, moved to Hollis from Brooklyn nine years ago so she and her husband, a teacher's aide, could buy a house with a backyard and live near a good neighborhood school, Public School 118. She sent her children, now in fourth and fifth grade, to the school and has mostly felt satisfied with their education, although she noted that the school has had three principals in seven years.</p>
        <p>But her deepest concern is what to do about middle school. She has no  confidence in the closest one, Intermediate School 192, and so, she said, she spent several days last week calling parents and other people to find out how to enroll her children in another school district.</p>
        <p>''I've checked around,'' she said, ''and I'm hearing that ours is the worst district in terms of middle schools. I don't want to have to go too far from here, but if that's what I'm going to have to do to get my children a good education, I'll do it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
