<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Plans a Lottery System To Cut La Guardia Flights</title>
    <meta content="09AIRL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/09/nyregion/09AIRL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1245878"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">La Guardia Airport (NYC)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Aviation Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E3DA1638F93AA35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Plans a Lottery System To Cut La Guardia Flights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Aviation Administration plans to temporarily reduce number of flights at La Guardia airport to relieve congestion; FAA and Port Authority of New York and New Jersey will allocate takeoff and landing slots to airlines by lottery, forcing cancellation of 75 flights per day; lottery will favor carriers providing regional service; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Federal Aviation Administration said yesterday that it planned to reduce the number of flights at La Guardia Airport to relieve congestion until it could find a way to restructure airport fees nationwide to discourage gridlock during peak flying times.</p>
        <p>At La Guardia, the rationing plan is expected to force the cancellation of more than 75 flights a day, some that are already in operation and others that airlines have sold tickets for and that are scheduled to begin over the next three months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Federal Aviation Administration said yesterday that it planned to reduce the number of flights at La Guardia Airport to relieve congestion until it could find a way to restructure airport fees nationwide to discourage gridlock during peak flying times.</p>
        <p>At La Guardia, the rationing plan is expected to force the cancellation of more than 75 flights a day, some that are already in operation and others that airlines have sold tickets for and that are scheduled to begin over the next three months.</p>
        <p>The F.A.A. and the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, which operates the region's three largest airports, said they would not know which flights would be canceled for at least a month, until they begin to allocate takeoff and landing slots to airlines by lottery. A lottery has been used only rarely in the past to distribute precious landing slots at overcrowded airports.</p>
        <p>Federal officials acknowledged that the cancellation of flights would be painful, especially as the holiday season was approaching, but they said that it was the only way to bring some temporary relief to the airport, until a more sweeping solution could be found.</p>
        <p>''The F.A.A. recognized that if we did not act, this situation could only worsen,'' said Eliot Brenner, a spokesman for the agency. ''The reality of flying into La Guardia today is that a number of flights are getting canceled anyway because of the time length of the delays. So the issue of whether or not there might be flights canceled is -- I don't want to say moot -- but not as important as it might seem.''</p>
        <p>Federal officials said the Port Authority, which in September announced a moratorium on any more flights being added at La Guardia, had recently proposed the idea of using a lottery to ration slots.</p>
        <p>The F.A.A. agreed because of how rapidly conditions at La Guardia were worsening, contributing to delays at other airports across the country.</p>
        <p>The quick rise in flights at La Guardia began about six months ago, the result of a federal law passed in March that partly lifted flight restrictions at the busy airport. That measure created more slots, mostly for smaller regional jets that fly to underserved cities.</p>
        <p>Airlines rushed to grab the slots, the first new ones in decades because La Guardia's traffic had long been limited to about 600 daily flights under federal law. But the new flights began to swamp the airport.</p>
        <p>As of last week, about 100 new daily flights -- meaning 200 takeoffs and landings -- had been added at the airport, which was already near maximum capacity. Airlines had filed requests to add as many as 300 total new daily flights, and were beginning to schedule and sell some of those.</p>
        <p>But the plan announced yesterday would restrict the number of new flights to about 75. The lottery, which federal officials say they hope will be held at the end of this month in New York, would give priority to the newest airlines at La Guardia. It would also favor those carriers providing regional service, the kinds of airlines that were supposed to be helped by the federal legislation passed in March.</p>
        <p>The officials stressed, however, that the lottery rationing plan would be only temporary, probably lasting until the middle of September 2001. After that, the F.A.A. said, it plans to begin a nationwide plan for changing the way airlines are charged for takeoff and landings.</p>
        <p>The main idea being considered, known as congestion pricing, is a favorite of many economists and has been debated by the federal government and airports for years. In the late 1980's, Logan International Airport in Boston tried a version of it, imposing new landing fees to try to discourage private airplanes and small commercial airlines from using the airport during peak times. But the Reagan administration overruled that plan, saying that the fees illegally discriminated against the small planes and airlines.</p>
        <p>The Port Authority, which has been contending with increasing delays at all three of its airports, has long been considering some form of congestion pricing. The idea would be to charge airlines more for landing during peak times or to use other fees that would give airlines incentives, for example, to schedule flights during less busy times or to use larger planes. Traditionally, airport landing fees have been based on a plane's weight, with higher costs for larger planes.</p>
        <p>Airlines point out that higher fees during peak times would most likely be passed along to passengers.</p>
        <p>The fact that federal officials now seem to be seriously considering what they call market-based ways to reduce the nation's growing air delays is a clear indication of the extent of the problems nationwide.</p>
        <p>And the F.A.A. regards La Guardia as a kind of bellwether. During September, there were 9,000 flight delays at the airport, up from 3,108 in  the same month a year before. The delays were so extensive, in fact, that they accounted for fully a quarter of all the flight delays in the country in September.</p>
        <p>''These delays are translating into disrupted airline schedules, cancellations and frustrated air travelers across the U.S.,'' wrote Jane F. Garvey, the F.A.A. administrator, in a letter sent yesterday to Robert E. Boyle, the executive director of the Port Authority. Mr. Boyle characterized conditions at the airport as intolerable.</p>
        <p>The airlines that serve La Guardia reacted cautiously yesterday after a two-hour meeting in which they were presented with the lottery rationing idea by officials from the Port Authority and the F.A.A.</p>
        <p>In a prepared statement, Delta Airlines signaled gently that it questioned whether the F.A.A.'s plan violated the spirit, if not the letter, of the federal law that created more slots.</p>
        <p>''We're studying the proposal to determine whether an approach that would significantly reduce operations achieves our mutual goals and preserves the mandate of the legislation to increase access and service from La Guardia to small, underserved markets,'' the airline said.</p>
        <p>But F.A.A. officials emphasized yesterday that they were given power under the legislation to make changes if the amount of traffic created by the law began to overburden airports.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
