<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>IN THE REGION/Westchester; Pockets of Vigor in a Frail Market</title>
    <meta content="19wczo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/19/realestate/19wczo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20061126T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1805926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="In the Region | Westchester"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Signs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raney, Rebecca Fairley</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/In the Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Signs and Symbols</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Westchester County (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E0DB143EF93AA25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1181" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>IN THE REGION/Westchester; Pockets of Vigor in a Frail Market</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pockets of Vigor in a Frail Market</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>California developers have responded to cooling housing market by hiring 'sign twirlers,' teenagers making at least $9 per hour to twirl, flip and dance with large plastic signs directing traffic to nearby groups of new homes; surveys indicate that significant percentages of home buyers find sites through such 'human directionals'; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF Tip O'Neill had sold houses for a living, he might have declared that all real estate is local. That seems particularly true when the market is struggling. In some parts of Westchester, the market is clearly in a downturn, if not a full-blown real estate recession, and yet other locales seem relatively untouched.</p>
        <p>In most towns, villages and cities, real estate agents report flagging sales and increasingly frustrated sellers. Homes are staying on the market longer, inventory is building and buyers are biding their time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In some parts of Westchester, the real estate market is clearly in a downturn, but one place that seems to be holding up better than most is Larchmont.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF Tip O'Neill had sold houses for a living, he might have declared that all real estate is local. That seems particularly true when the market is struggling. In some parts of Westchester, the market is clearly in a downturn, if not a full-blown real estate recession, and yet other locales seem relatively untouched.</p>
        <p>In most towns, villages and cities, real estate agents report flagging sales and increasingly frustrated sellers. Homes are staying on the market longer, inventory is building and buyers are biding their time.</p>
        <p>In response, most brokers are exhorting sellers ''to get real,'' said Sona Davidian, a broker-owner at C. S. McClellan Real Estate in Pelham. That means cutting prices to reflect the market changes.</p>
        <p>Or as Diana Hellman, a sales agent with Merritt Associates in Larchmont, explained it: ''If a property is priced right, it will sell. It just may not sell for as much as one hoped for.''</p>
        <p>For the county as a whole, the number of sales of existing homes dropped 17 percent in the third quarter of this year from the corresponding quarter a year ago -- to 2,718 units from 3,278, according to figures from the Westchester-Putnam Multiple Listing Service.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the median sales price of a single-family home was higher than a year earlier, although barely, at $716,000, compared with $711,700 in the third quarter of 2005.</p>
        <p>But one place that seems to be holding up better than most is Larchmont. There, the number of sales for the first 10 months so far this year has exceeded the corresponding period in 2005, with 157 sales this year, up from 147 a year earlier, said Debbie Doern, manager of Century 21 Residential Brokerage. In addition, the median sales price during the period was slightly more than $1.1 million, up from $999,000 a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hellman at Merritt Associates attributed the village's relative resistance to a distinctive combination of assets: an architecturally varied and well-maintained housing stock from the 1920s and 1930s; a thriving downtown within walking distance of almost anywhere else in the village; a location next to Long Island Sound; and proximity to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Farther north, on the Village Green in Bedford, Missy Renwick, the broker-owner of Renwick &amp; Winterling, a family-owned real estate agency, reported that some towns -- among them Pound Ridge, Armonk and Bedford -- have so far remained relatively unscathed.</p>
        <p>''Gosh, everybody is saying the market is awful,'' Ms. Renwick said, ''but we just had the best October in a long time, with a $17 million sale, two $7 million sales and some for $5 million. At worst, we have a few low bidders out there looking at the leftovers.''</p>
        <p>In one segment of Westchester's market, that of new luxury condominium sales, the sales picture has been downright rosy. As Louis R. Cappelli, a Valhalla-based developer, observed, referring to condos he is building, ''there may be a slowdown in some locations, but we're certainly not seeing it in White Plains and New Rochelle.''</p>
        <p>Since the sales center opened last month, Mr. Cappelli said, contracts have been signed for more than a third of the units at his 44-story Residences at the Ritz-Carlton in White Plains -- where prices range from $750,000 to more than $6 million.</p>
        <p>At Trump Plaza in New Rochelle, which Mr. Cappelli is building in partnership with Donald J. Trump, more than 50 percent of the condos have sold since the spring, he said. The units there range from $500,000 for a one-bedroom to $1.4 million for a three-bedroom penthouse.</p>
        <p>As for new construction of single-family homes, there are few large tracts of land left in the county for major building projects. But at smaller in-fill projects, like the new town houses for sale on the south side of New Rochelle on Pelham Avenue near the Long Island Sound, none of the 10 units at AnnMar Gardens have sold since they went on the market early in the summer.</p>
        <p>Rose Bulfamante, an agent for Century 21 Mancuso, said that because of the slow market, the developer was considering dropping the asking prices -- $779,000 to $849,000 -- on the three-bedroom units and offering the incentive of a year's membership at a local beach club.</p>
        <p>In Bronxville, a fashionable village with a quaint downtown and a well-maintained housing stock, prices generally tend to be higher than in neighboring communities. But sales there have been slow in recent months, and houses are staying on the market for relatively long periods, said Leah Caro, broker-owner of Bronxville-Ley Real Estate.</p>
        <p>''Even a community like Bronxville doesn't exist in a vacuum when it comes to this market,'' she said. ''Some places may be more insulated than others, but only a rare few are altogether immune.''</p>
        <p>In many ways, Bronxville might be expected to attract to the same kind of people who are drawn to Larchmont. Ms. Caro speculated that potential buyers in Bronxville might be holding off until a villagewide revaluation of property is completed this winter.</p>
        <p>As for homeowners, they have seen the breathtaking prices that their neighbors' houses fetched last year, and they want the same. But like Sean and Lynn Leary, whose vintage 1920s colonial in Pelham Manor has been on the market since July, many have had to adjust their sights.</p>
        <p>The Learys' house came on the market for $1.289 million and sat without offers throughout the summer and early fall. The couple have since lowered the asking price to $1.199 million, and Mr. Leary has torn down the original two-gar garage, which was in poor condition, and is building a new one in its place.</p>
        <p>''Some people say it's an ego thing with sellers not wanting to accept lower offers,'' said Mr. Leary, a commercial real estate broker, ''but that's not really the case, at least with us. It's more about sellers like us who are just trying to understand what's happening. Sometimes, it feels like we're trying to catch a falling knife. We're trying to anticipate what's going to happen next.''</p>
        <p>At the offices of the Westchester County Board of Realtors in White Plains, P. Gilbert Mercurio, the chief executive, offered a general overview of the market. ''It's pretty clear to me that nationally we're seeing a pullback in the real estate market,'' he said. ''In some places, it's truly a burst bubble; in other places, like in Westchester and Putnam, it's more like a correction.''</p>
        <p>Over all, Westchester has fared better than many other places in the nation because there has not been the overbuilding in the new home market here that there has been elsewhere, Mr. Mercurio said.</p>
        <p>''And Westchester hasn't been a market driven by speculators,'' he said. ''What we had was a feverish market with very high prices, and we were due for some relief.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mercurio noted that unless a seller acquired a home last year, when prices were at an all-time high in the county, and had to sell this year, most homeowners are still sitting on profits, pricing pressure notwithstanding. ''They're not going to be hurt,'' he said, ''although they may not get as much as they hoped for.''</p>
        <p>In the Region | Westchester</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 26, 2006, Sunday  The ''In the Region'' article in some copies last Sunday about residential sales trends in Westchester County misstated the professional affiliation of Debbie Doern, one of the real estate experts interviewed. She is manager of Coldwell Banker Residential Brokerage, not Century 21 Residential Brokerage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 26, 2006, Sunday</p>
        <p>The ''In the Region'' article in some copies last Sunday about residential sales trends in Westchester County misstated the professional affiliation of Debbie Doern, one of the real estate experts interviewed. She is manager of Coldwell Banker Residential Brokerage, not Century 21 Residential Brokerage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
