<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sighing, a French Sound Endures</title>
    <meta content="18CLEM$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1054832"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clements, Marcelle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Azvanour, Charles</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Aznavour (Musical Revue)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7DC143AF93BA25753C1A96E958260" item-length="2814" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sighing, a French Sound Endures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCELLE CLEMENTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clements, Marcelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Marcelle Clements, author who studied music in France and US on French singer, songwriter and actor Charles Aznavour's upcoming solo performance on Broadway, in English and French, in Aznavour; history of French chanson traced; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN this country, the very idea of the French popular song usually triggers the most primitive faux snapshots of French culture: Maurice Chevalier waving his boater, or Edith Piaf -- the Little Sparrow -- alone on a dark stage, holding a note interminably while one or two melodies are dashed off on the accordion.</p>
        <p>These overexposed portraits are from a set of lingering 1950's cliches, most of them hovering under a striped cafe awning: the silly beret, the comical mustache, a toy poodle or two and intellectuals seated around outdoor tables bantering with women in low-cut dresses whose cleavages must be ogled with condescending concupiscence. Dispersed around the landscape is the perennial trio of perky French protuberances: the cigarette, the baguette and that frail filigreed phallus of an Eiffel Tower.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN this country, the very idea of the French popular song usually triggers the most primitive faux snapshots of French culture: Maurice Chevalier waving his boater, or Edith Piaf -- the Little Sparrow -- alone on a dark stage, holding a note interminably while one or two melodies are dashed off on the accordion.</p>
        <p>These overexposed portraits are from a set of lingering 1950's cliches, most of them hovering under a striped cafe awning: the silly beret, the comical mustache, a toy poodle or two and intellectuals seated around outdoor tables bantering with women in low-cut dresses whose cleavages must be ogled with condescending concupiscence. Dispersed around the landscape is the perennial trio of perky French protuberances: the cigarette, the baguette and that frail filigreed phallus of an Eiffel Tower.</p>
        <p>It is safe to say that some images of these ooh-la-la relics will be wafting in and out of public consciousness in the next two weeks with the arrival on Broadway of the French singer, songwriter and actor Charles Aznavour, who will be performing in both English and French during his new solo show. Entitled ''Aznavour,'' it begins a limited run  on Tuesday at the Marquis Theater.</p>
        <p>Though at 74, Mr. Aznavour may have more in common these days with the stars of international show business, his visit, one hopes, will serve as a reminder of the contributions to 20th-century popular song by several generations of French singer-songwriters.</p>
        <p>The French chanson is a tricky cultural artifact. Its text predominates and its images can arouse intense emotion in both singer and audience. A great chanson evokes a powerful melancholy that can make listeners experience longing and consolation, often simultaneously.</p>
        <p>For many Americans, the history and astonishingly rich content of the chanson have been obscured by stereotypes. But French listeners have become tired of it, too. The chanson has been said to be in decline, its musical and social framework exhausted. Others, however, insist that a French folk revival, that has been growing since the 1970's, is being ignored by the French media. But recently both have emerged as a focus for an argument in France between those who want to stay loyal to the French arts and others who feel that their preference for American imports is no evidence of disloyalty.</p>
        <p>On this side of the Atlantic, there is not enough data to join the debate. Aside from the iconic Chevalier and Piaf, only a few of the chanson's illustrious interpreters have become known here: Mistinguett, Yves Montand, Jacques Brel, among others, and, of course, Josephine Baker. Occasionally, some new young French singers, like Patricia Kaas or the now-defunct Les Negresses Vertes, receive notice.</p>
        <p>Almost unknown here are the early idols, like Frehel, Berthe Sylva and Lucienne Boyer, interpreters of the chanson realiste (the odd name for the melodramatic street-life narratives that formed the basis of the great chanson repertory). Boyer so excited her public that chairs were thrown and concert halls trashed.</p>
        <p>Charles Trenet, now 85, may have been the most deliriously loved performer of all. Like his mentor, Chevalier, Trenet seemed to embody lightheartedness and well being. Apparently, few noticed that his big hit of 1938, the jaunty ''Je Chante'' (''I Sing'') ended with a suicide -- shortly before the fall of the Leon Blum Government, the strikes, the franc's catastrophic devaluation and the anschluss.</p>
        <p>Strictly speaking, the word chanson needs no translation (just like lied, jazz, rock and rap). Larousse defines it, from the Latin cantio, as a small composition of populist character, either sentimental or satirical, divided into couplets. Dating to at least the 11th century, it combines poetry and protocamp, ditty, prayer, expletive, love song and documentary, but has almost always kept its simple verse refrain form. The early history of the chanson, according to the Harvard Dictionary of Music, ''is more ancient, fertile and musically important than that of any other nation's song literature.''</p>
        <p>For many French people, a first association to the chanson is not love but political engagement. The French Revolution had its own chansons, as did the Resistance in World War II and the protests of 1968. In the early years of this century, the chanson was still being sung on the streets of Paris by its authors, who would sell copies to passers-by in the form of sheet music. This can be viewed as either begging or a commercial art form par excellence: if a song did not make money, its creator did not eat. So the performer had to be charming, evocative and daring, to reach out to the audience through voice, eyes and body language with a story that urgently needed to be told.</p>
        <p>The chanson is a listener's medium. There is the play of language; the interplay of cerebration and sensuality; the respect for large appetites and tolerance of their consequences; the consuming interest in all that is naughty and risque; the boundless fascination with everything pertaining to desire, seduction and love and their aftermath; and, finally, the compulsion to explore the meaning of it all, and the lack of meaning of it all.</p>
        <p>This -- and much more -- is evident in an extraordinary set of CD's issued by the French company EPM. The ''Anthologie de la Chanson Francaise Enregistree,'' published over the last 10 years, is a collection of nearly 100 CD's, covering the century through 1980. Most Gallic, it includes index upon index, cross-referencing composers, performers, songs and dates.</p>
        <p>While there have been other compilations of late, nothing this comprehensive has ever been attempted, and the 20th-century span of the chanson can finally be grasped. The zenith of the form is often considered to have been reached by Trenet around 1936. But even in the earlier decades, its distinctive atmosphere and narrative intimacy can be heard on the CD's, as well as the tension between the tenderness of the voices and the harshness of the lives they describe.</p>
        <p>''C'est mon homme,'' sings Mistinguett. When her man orders her to come -- ''Viens!'' -- she follows, ''comme un chien'' (''like a dog''). Not much genteel vocalizing here, but plenty of the sort of truth-telling that gave rise to the chanson realiste.</p>
        <p>But reality moved on faster than the chanson. ''There is such a thing as decadence,'' French people say, pointing out that the masters are dead or retired: Georges Brassens, Leo Ferre, Serge Gainsbourg, the great poets often referred to as les classiques.</p>
        <p>Then, invariably, someone will mention a song: perhaps Gainsbourg's ''Je suis venu te dire que je m'en vais'' (''I came to tell you that I'm leaving you''), or Jacques Brel's ''Ne me quitte pas'' (''Don't leave me''). Then the conversation will segue to the speaker's identification with the song's passion, fear, pain and sorrow.</p>
        <p>When the French talk about the popular songs they grew up with, it isn't long before they tell you which ones make them cry. ''And still, after all this time, when I hear Serge Reggiani singing Baudelaire,'' a friend tells me, ''I die.'' Everyone has one or two that they can't resist. Some are great big heartbreakers like Edith Piaf's ''Hymne a l'amour,'' others are delicate masterpieces of nostalgia like Jacqueline Francois's ''Sous le ciel de Paris.'' People will admit they weep over the songs that made their parents cry or sheepishly reveal that they are still susceptible to ''Les Feuilles Mortes'' (''Autumn Leaves''). And some songs just get you, you don't know how or why, like the singer Barbara's ''L'aigle noir'' (''The Black Eagle'').</p>
        <p>If those who are reminiscing are in their 40's and 50's, someone will be sure to remark that Gainsbourg wrote songs for Edith Piaf. And then Charles Aznavour's name will come up and his astoundingly sexy songs; people will state their opinions as to whether he was secretly Piaf's lover.</p>
        <p>By then, anyone under 30 probably will have left the room. Like young Americans, most young French people have no interest in the chanson because, they will tell you, they prefer beat-oriented music. ''When I listen to music,'' a 24-year-old said to me, ''I expect to hear drums, unless it's classical music.'' Brought up with disco and funk, many now listen only to rap and world music. It is often French rap and Francophone world music, but still, they are often accused by chanson fans of succumbing to pressures by multinational entertainment companies that are perceived as eager to convert the French to American products.</p>
        <p>RECENTLY, when I asked a rap fan to comment on this view, he promptly agreed with it. ''It's true,'' he said. ''La chanson francaise est terminee.'' He added that he has never listened to French songs because his parents never played them at home. He tells me he doesn't know a single title or performer.</p>
        <p>''What about Brassens?'' I ask.</p>
        <p>''That's different,'' he says. ''He's a poet. Literary.''</p>
        <p>''Leo Ferre?''</p>
        <p>''Yes, I do know his records, which I love, but he's an exception.''</p>
        <p>''Gainsbourg?''</p>
        <p>''Oh. But you can't count Gainsbourg as mere chanson francaise. He's bigger. He's like Jim Morrison, a guy who wound up doing anything he wanted. He just didn't care. At that point you become mythic.''</p>
        <p>What he listens to, he tells me, is rap fused with Arab elements. ''It's completely inspired by America,'' he explains. ''Except for the text. Maybe 50 percent of them have really great, engaged lyrics'' -- by which he means political commitment. ''And it's great culture because it doesn't seem like culture.''</p>
        <p>But that is the definition of the 20th-century chanson. What is the chanson if not music of the era set to a text that reveals the issues of the era? Two of the top three rap creators in France more than fulfill this mandate, at either end of the spectrum -- the witty and elegant former linguistics student, MC Solaar, le dandy du rap; and the darker, passionately politicized Supreme NTM. Instead of the petty thieves and hookers of yore, there are pregnant teen-agers and heroin addicts; for the narrow streets of old Montmartre substitute today's vast, bleak Arab slums; and accordions have been traded in for some fancy electronic equipment. Optimists argue that African and North African singer-songwriters don't destroy but enrich the French tradition, however they may choose to perpetuate it.</p>
        <p>In other words, whether the chanson is nearing the end of the road or not depends on how you define it and with whom you are arguing. Certainly, on the EPM albums, you can feel the sudden dropoff in the early to mid-60's, with the arrival of the ye-yes -- the French version of rock-and-rollers. The decline of the chanson in France mirrored that of pop standards in America with the advent of rock-and-roll.</p>
        <p>Throughout its history, the chanson's harmonic devices have been limited but effective, just as the melodies have remained fresh after many hearings. But after May '68, les classiques began to record songs that were not sung but spoken, part Sprechstimme, part diatribe, part performance. It is possible to argue the merits of this sudden fissure in the tradition, but impossible to ignore the fact that it broke a pact with a form that had lasted some 700 or 800 years.</p>
        <p>AT the very least, the chanson is a window on a sensibility that remains unknown to most Americans, despite the many cliches surrounding it. Setting raunchiness, exploitation, class hatred, abuse, demoralization and despair to music was not the invention of late-20th-century rappers or even rock-and-roll. A performer like Juliette Greco makes Madonna look like Pollyanna, not because Madonna is devoid of lustful energy, but because, like most Americans, she has learned that it's a bad idea to be seen to be complaining. And here is what the French know: you can't talk -- or sing -- about desire without complaining, without sifting through regrets, mistakes of the past, and without noticing the passage of time and the falling leaves.</p>
        <p>Like the blues, the chanson often takes the form of a lament. But unlike the blues, it is verbose, which makes it out of sync with the American need for discretion and cool. It is revealing to hear a chanson performer take on English lyrics. Listen to Vanessa Paradis's version of the Rolling Stones song ''As Tears Go By'' on her 1994 album, ''Vanessa Paradis Live.'' You can hear how much more desolate and eloquent the words sound, without the white noise generated by Mick Jagger's attractively ambiguous -- and distracting -- sexual ennui.</p>
        <p>True, the language difference is a problem and, alas, the ''Anthologie de la Chanson Francaise'' does not provide any lyrics. An inadequate but valuable consolation are the photographs showing the artists, some of them looking as romantically wasted as their songs promise.</p>
        <p>But the language problem may not be insuperable. ''I had a Francoise Hardy period,'' an American friend who does not speak French confides. ''That's all I could listen to. It was so sad and beautiful, just like me. I was drinking, needless to say. That's when I started drinking framboise, while I listened to chansons and I waited.''</p>
        <p>''For what?'' I asked.</p>
        <p>''I don't know,'' she said. ''But there was something so sad, so tragic about my life as I drank framboise -- or was it mirabelle? -- and listened to her. I felt she understood the deep human sadness that characterized me, and that she, too, was waiting -- for something or other, yearning for whatever it was that was to come.''</p>
        <p>This blending of the chanson's raw emotion with the tremendous hunger of its audience for intense vicarious expression may be the most indelible aspect of the form.</p>
        <p>The real lives of the performers, even those who affected a cheerful and contented air, were often as tragic as those they sang of. For example, there was the well-known affair between Maurice Chevalier and his mentor, Mistinguett, the singer with the million-dollar legs (because her preternaturally attractive limbs were insured for that amount). Mistinguett, who was born in 1875 and starred at the Folies-Bergeres, the Moulin Rouge and the Casino de Paris, was considered the epitome of French glamour. But she is the one, remember, who sang ''Mon Homme.'' As she would later tell her biographer, David Bret, while complaining about Chevalier: ''I never found a single reason to justify loving him. He used me, and as soon as he got what he wanted, he dumped me . . . but his absence dominated the rest of my life.''</p>
        <p>That is what gets veiled in translation by all the charm and zany glamour -- the very real pain in the performers' lives, which, publicly known in their native country, becomes as much a part of the chanson as its melody. Gainsbourg's grim death in 1991 is often seen as the event that punctuated the end of the chanson. Those who most admire his work can detail his spectacular self-destruction: how many packs of Gitanes he smoked a day, how many women he slept with, how many times he had cirrhosis of the liver and how at the end he didn't even sing anymore but talked his songs, though they were no longer songs, they were assaults.</p>
        <p>Do we need to watch quite so much dangerous trapeze work from so many acrobats of the psyche? If part of what we do is wait for them to fall, they did not cheat us of the spectacle, as we are reminded this month by the 20th anniversary of the death of Jacques Brel at age 49 from lung cancer. Recently, too, the memoirs of Barbara have been posthumously published in France, detailing some of the miseries of her childhood and explaining that while she had felt happy as a singer, she had failed in her life as a woman.</p>
        <p>And what about those who preceded them, who sang so tenderly in such harsh times? Little Sparrows or not, Piaf and her comrades still cast big shadows on the stage, and one cannot listen to ''Hymne a l'amour'' without shivering on her behalf: the man she loved died in a plane crash, and the pain she felt was so intolerable that offstage she lost interest in life. So recalls her protege, Charles Aznavour, whose success she helped to create and was too unhappy to acknowledge.</p>
        <p>That's the power of the chanson. It's for real. When these performers make us cry, it's because they cried too. Or needed us to cry on their behalf.</p>
        <p>MUSIC Marcelle Clements, who studied music in France and the United States, is the author of ''The Improvised Woman: Single Women Reinventing Single Life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Marcelle Clements, who studied music in France and the United States, is the author of ''The Improvised Woman: Single Women Reinventing Single Life.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
