<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dancing Away the Havana Blues</title>
    <meta content="18SUKI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1054831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cafe Cantante (Havana, Cuba)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Medina, Narciso</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E1DD143AF93BA25753C1A96E958260" item-length="1057" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dancing Away the Havana Blues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUKI JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>HAVANA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at Cafe Cantante in Havana, Cuba, described; dance performances, begun three years ago by choreographer Narciso Medina, take place on Saturday afternoons and include professionals, young dance students and public; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A tropical rain cleanses the crumbling structures of old Havana as a motley group of dancers repairs to an underground sanctuary. Carrying donated costumes and worn audiotapes, they filter into an empty cabaret and begin to structure the afternoon lineup. A powerhouse modern dancer will present a new solo, a group of grade-school children will show a reconfigured mambo, a virtuosic teen-ager will accept a choreography prize and an ecstatic deejay wields a bootleg copy of last year's London techno hit. Two North American dancers will perform contemporary solos, making for truly exotic entertainment. Welcome to an Afternoon of Dance at the Cafe Cantante, where for a few hours the daily struggle is forgotten with the distinctly Cuban antidote to black-market blues: dance.</p>
        <p>The Cafe Cantante is housed in Havana's Teatro Nacional, a post-revolutionary structure nestled in the Plaza de la Revolucion, guarded by a three-story-tall wire relief of Che Guevara in his beret. The theater complex is a shrine to Cuban culture, built to foster art by and for the people. A kind of miniature Lincoln Center, it contains once-beautiful studios and workshops, two large proscenium stages and the Cafe Cantante.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A tropical rain cleanses the crumbling structures of old Havana as a motley group of dancers repairs to an underground sanctuary. Carrying donated costumes and worn audiotapes, they filter into an empty cabaret and begin to structure the afternoon lineup. A powerhouse modern dancer will present a new solo, a group of grade-school children will show a reconfigured mambo, a virtuosic teen-ager will accept a choreography prize and an ecstatic deejay wields a bootleg copy of last year's London techno hit. Two North American dancers will perform contemporary solos, making for truly exotic entertainment. Welcome to an Afternoon of Dance at the Cafe Cantante, where for a few hours the daily struggle is forgotten with the distinctly Cuban antidote to black-market blues: dance.</p>
        <p>The Cafe Cantante is housed in Havana's Teatro Nacional, a post-revolutionary structure nestled in the Plaza de la Revolucion, guarded by a three-story-tall wire relief of Che Guevara in his beret. The theater complex is a shrine to Cuban culture, built to foster art by and for the people. A kind of miniature Lincoln Center, it contains once-beautiful studios and workshops, two large proscenium stages and the Cafe Cantante.</p>
        <p>Theater and dance are still accessible to ordinary people, but the nightly cabaret cover charge at the Cafe Cantante is $10 American, prohibitively expensive for workers paid in Cuban pesos. Featuring some of the hottest bands in the country, the cafe harks back to the days of big daddies and fat cigars. Nocturnal tourists pay big money to be thronged by women whose intelligence and charm are matched only by their desperation. But once every two weeks, on Saturday afternoon, the cafe is reclaimed by the masses. The entry fee is 2 pesos (about 10 cents), and the crowd is decidedly local.</p>
        <p>Afternoons of Dance, as these Saturdays are called, was started three years ago by Narciso Medina, one of Cuba's most highly regarded contemporary choreographers. Mr. Medina, 35, opened the first self-supporting dance school since the revolution, building a studio out of what used to be his family's modest apartment in Havana's Vedado district. His company is known for involving the neighbors: half the barrio works on the production crew in one capacity or another. His company performs frequently on the street, where they focus on the dances of Santeria ritual, based in the Yoruba tradition of West Africa.</p>
        <p>Mr. Medina began the afternoons as a way to prepare emerging dancers for the stage and to further involve local residents in the making of art. The series combines polished performances, works in progress, improvisation, children's recitals and social dancing. ''The cafe audience is better than in the theaters; they're more opinionated and enthusiastic,'' Mr. Medina says. ''The conditions aren't perfect, but creativity abounds.''</p>
        <p>Rudimentary spotlights and tacky nightclub decor surround a small carpeted stage. The cheap tiles of the low ceiling are sometimes dislodged by dancers jumping high or being lifted. In front of the stage, a concrete floor provides space between tables for improvisers, brave souls who dance together without plan or structure. Drinks are sold in dollars, but black-market rum is the libation of preference.</p>
        <p>The afternoons are dance jams in which everyone participates, effectively blurring the boundary between audience and performer. In Cuba, where dance is central to culture and religion, aficionados are unafraid to share the floor with professionals. The whole intergenerational crowd jumps up to boogie between the acts, the most extroverted leaping to the stage while the merely enthusiastic flood the floor. By late afternoon the underground cave feels more like a huge party than a performance, with heat and rum burning off any remnants of stage fright that might hold back the timid few.</p>
        <p>One recent Saturday, the program began with a group of children from Mr. Medina's company school. Dressed in red and black, they depict Eleggua, one of the Orishas, or deities, of Santeria tradition. The dance is a study in simple technique, rhythm and floor patterns, designed to integrate performance skills into a lesson in Cuban folklore. The smallest dancer loses his way and, unfazed, creates his own variation of the dance.</p>
        <p>Throughout the day children of both sexes perform with natural ease. In Cuba there is little stigma attached to boys dancing, and many of the country's most celebrated dancers are men. But the division of labor is apparent from an early age: boys dance with strength and weight while girls wiggle and shake provocatively.</p>
        <p>Tomas Guidante, 28, a masterly soloist in Mr. Medina's troupe, performs a solemn, sculptural work in progress. Interrupting his ovation, he initiates a group improvisation set to imported New Age sounds. (Though their music is captivating, Cubans are fascinated by foreign recordings, perhaps because a decadeslong drought has been replaced by a glut.) Serendipity guides two women in black to the lip of the stage, where their eloquent gestures mingle in a celebration of the spontaneous. Suddenly the music changes to an explosive salsa. Three couples converge in a wheel, spinning through the latest version of ''salsa rueda.'' They change partners, dos-a-dos and bump pelvises, grinning. Men duck their heads under women's elbows, unwinding limbs just in time to change partners again.</p>
        <p>Los Morenos del Son, an ebullient band brandishing myriad percussion and brass instruments, launches into an infectious, updated folk song. The crowd responds energetically, old and young coordinating their moves. One hotshot after another embellishes a roosterlike strut, spinning, grabbing the air, twisting to the floor on one leg and rising up again. The wily lead singer creates a rap about the vicissitudes of life in Cuba. Several dancers hop on the stage and begin a Supremes-style chorus. They shimmy together and sing out: ''O la Habana! O la Habana!''</p>
        <p>When it's all over, the spent crowd spills out into the wet Plaza de la Revolucion. The Cafe Cantante turns back into a pricey nightclub. Dancers begin the long trek home, hitchhiking, walking or riding bicycles because buses overflow with passengers and taxis accept only dollars. They keep their eyes out for the rare snack they can afford, in pesos. O, la Habana, so rich and so poor.</p>
        <p>DANCE Suki John's ballet ''Sh'ma'' will have its American debut at the 92nd Street Y on Nov. 1.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Suki John's ballet ''Sh'ma'' will have its American debut at the 92nd Street Y on Nov. 1.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
