<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Food; Batter Up!</title>
    <meta content="18FOODLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="111" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1054772"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Essex County (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Livingston (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neill, Molly</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halper, Sharon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halper, Barry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EEDF1E3BF93BA25753C1A96E958260" item-length="1701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Food; Batter Up!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Molly O'Neill</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Neill, Molly</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Molly O'Neill Food article on fried zucchini, silk-handkerchief pasta and other specialties prepared by Sharon Halper in her Essex County, New Jersey, home, and enjoyed by many famous Yankees; photo; recipes; Barry Halper is limited partner in New York Yankees and has extensive collection of baseball memorabilia (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mint pesto was tickling his nose, like dust behind home plate, and Yogi Berra began to twitch. Seated at Sharon and Barry Halper's long marble dining table, he tucked a napkin into his waistband and said that eating is the best way to have dinner.</p>
        <p>''I'm 73 years old, and there's a few things I know,'' said the Hall of Fame Yankee catcher. He knows, for instance, that Sharon Halper is a superb cook. ''I can taste and tell.'' He also knows that Sharon's husband, Barry, has the most extensive collection of baseball memorabilia in the world. So why would he ever turn down an invitation to dinner?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mint pesto was tickling his nose, like dust behind home plate, and Yogi Berra began to twitch. Seated at Sharon and Barry Halper's long marble dining table, he tucked a napkin into his waistband and said that eating is the best way to have dinner.</p>
        <p>''I'm 73 years old, and there's a few things I know,'' said the Hall of Fame Yankee catcher. He knows, for instance, that Sharon Halper is a superb cook. ''I can taste and tell.'' He also knows that Sharon's husband, Barry, has the most extensive collection of baseball memorabilia in the world. So why would he ever turn down an invitation to dinner?</p>
        <p>Just as her husband developed a passion for baseball when he was very young, Sharon grew up in awe of her grandmother, an obsessed and talented home cook. She has studied extensively in Italy and has cooked for more baseball legends than she can count. Initially, they drop by to see the collection. But they stay -- and keep coming back -- for the kind of antipasti she served Yogi: salamis and olives and impeccable aged cheese; shrimp and roasted vegetables; thin-crusted pizza rich with olive oil; fresh tomatoes, basil and mozzarella; bowls of fried zucchini as delicate and crisp as starched lace.</p>
        <p>So addicted is Joe DiMaggio to Sharon's silk-handkerchief pasta that he accompanied the Halpers to Italy to study the technique. So comfortable is Bobby Murcer at the Halpers' table that when he retired, he invited 50 of his nearest and dearest to the couple's home in Essex County, N.J. ''They came in a bus,'' Sharon says. ''I was a little apprehensive.'' In general, however, she is unflappable.</p>
        <p>Tommy Lasorda calls Sharon Halper whenever he's headed to New York. You gonna cook me pasta? he asks. And she says, Well, O.K., but you'd better bring at least five good eaters. Throughout the major leagues, dinner at the Halpers is anticipated with the kind of enthusiasm usually reserved for four-star citadels.</p>
        <p>For their part, the Halpers have the soft-spoken nonchalance of people who have made a life of what they love. Barry, a limited partner in the New York Yankees, grew up in the shadow of Ruppert Stadium in Newark. By cleaning the clubhouse and running errands, he became a favorite of the triple-A Bears, as well as a frequent recipient of balls and bats and uniforms, which he started collecting at the age of 8.</p>
        <p>In 50 years, he has amassed 1,800 signed baseballs, 500 autographed bats and 1,068 uniforms, which are now displayed on an automated dry cleaner's carousel in his basement. His mania, he says, is not so much about objects as what they represent, each piece a little bit of history that allows him to separate baseball fact from baseball legend.</p>
        <p>Similarly unconcerned with hype, Sharon is more determined to please people than to set a trendy table. She is not sure why baseball and food meld so seamlessly in her kitchen, except for the obvious fact that for men who have been on the road, home cooking is like manna from heaven.</p>
        <p>Sharon Halper's Fried Zucchini</p>
        <p>1 3/4 cups all-purpose flour</p>
        <p>3/4 teaspoon salt</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>2 large eggs, separated</p>
        <p>Pinch freshly grated nutmeg</p>
        <p>1/3 cup dry white wine</p>
        <p>1 cup cold water</p>
        <p>Vegetable oil for deep frying</p>
        <p>3 medium zucchini, cut into 2-inch sticks</p>
        <p>Coarse salt</p>
        <p>Lemon wedges for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. Sift the flour into a large bowl. Add the salt, olive oil, egg yolks, nutmeg, wine and water, one ingredient at a time, stirring well after each addition. Stir until the batter is smooth. Cover and let stand in a cool place for 2 hours.</p>
        <p>2. Fill a heavy pot or deep fryer with 2 inches of vegetable oil. Place over high heat and heat to 360 degrees using a deep-fat thermometer.</p>
        <p>3. While the oil is heating, place the egg whites in a small bowl and beat them until they are stiff but not dry. Fold the whites into the batter.</p>
        <p>4. Working in batches, dip the zucchini sticks into the batter and carefully drop them into the hot oil. Fry the sticks, turning them occasionally, until they are golden, about 2 to 3 minutes. Remove them from the fat and drain on double-layered paper towels. Continue until all the zucchini is fried.</p>
        <p>5. Transfer the zucchini to a serving plate covered with a paper towel and sprinkle them with coarse salt. Garnish with lemon wedges and serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 appetizer servings.</p>
        <p>Silk-Handkerchief Pasta With Mint Pesto</p>
        <p>For the pasta:</p>
        <p>3 1/2 cups unbleached all-purpose flour</p>
        <p>Pinch salt</p>
        <p>1 cup dry white wine</p>
        <p>For the pesto:</p>
        <p>100 fresh mint leaves (about 1 1/2 lightly packed cups)</p>
        <p>20 large basil leaves</p>
        <p>12 sprigs Italian parsley</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons boiled and finely chopped spinach</p>
        <p>8 tablespoons unsalted butter at room temperature</p>
        <p>1/2 cup extra-virgin olive oil</p>
        <p>1/2 cup freshly grated Parmesan cheese, plus more for serving</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons salt</p>
        <p>Freshly ground black pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. To make the pasta, combine the flour and salt in a large bowl. Make a well in the center of the flour and add the wine. Using a fork, gradually incorporate the wine into the flour, starting in the center and slowly working out.</p>
        <p>2. Gather the dough into a ball. If it seems too dry, add more wine 1 teaspoon at a time; if it seems too wet, add a little more flour. Knead the dough until it feels smooth and very even in consistency, 1 to 2 minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Following the manufacturer's instructions for your pasta maker, stretch the dough out, ending with sheets as thin as possible. Using a sharp knife, cut the sheets into 5-inch squares and lay them on cotton dish towels, covering each layer with another dish towel.</p>
        <p>4. To make the pesto, combine all the ingredients in the bowl of a food processor and process until fairly smooth. Transfer the sauce to a small bowl and leave at room temperature while you cook the pasta.</p>
        <p>5. Bring a large kettle  full of salted water to a bowl. Cook the squares, 5 at a time, in the water for 3 minutes. Use a mesh strainer or skimmer to remove the cooked pasta and transfer to a large plate or platter. (A little water adhering to the noodles will keep them from sticking together.) Repeat until all the pasta is cooked.</p>
        <p>6. Add i cup of the boiling pasta water to the sauce and mix well. Drop 5 pasta squares on each plate so that they resemble dropped handkerchiefs. Top each serving with 2 to 3 tablespoons of the sauce and serve immediately with grated parmesan on the side.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 first-course servings.</p>
        <p>Osso Buco With Peas and Gremolada</p>
        <p>For the osso buco:</p>
        <p>6 tablespoons butter</p>
        <p>3 carrots, peeled and finely chopped</p>
        <p>2 stalks celery, finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 large red onion, peeled and finely chopped</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon minced garlic</p>
        <p>1/4 pound pancetta or prosciutto, diced</p>
        <p>1 28-ounce can tomatoes, drained and chopped</p>
        <p>6 veal shanks, each about 2 1/2 inches thick and tied with string</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground pepper to taste</p>
        <p>All-purpose flour for dusting meat</p>
        <p>6 tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>1 cup dry white wine</p>
        <p>2 cups beef stock</p>
        <p>1 cup fresh shelled peas</p>
        <p>For the gremolada:</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons finely chopped parsley</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon grated lemon zest</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon minced garlic.</p>
        <p>1. In a large casserole or Dutch oven with a tightly fitting lid, melt the butter over medium heat. Add the carrots, celery, onion, garlic and pancetta or prosciutto and cook, stirring frequently until the vegetables are tender, about 10 minutes. Add the tomatoes, raise the heat to high and cook, stirring constantly, until most of the liquid has evaporated, about 3 to 4 minutes. Remove from the heat.</p>
        <p>2. Season the veal generously with salt and pepper and dust it with flour, shaking off any excess. Place a large skillet over medium-high heat and add the oil. When very hot, add the veal and brown it on all sides. (You may need to work in two batches.)</p>
        <p>3. Place the browned veal on top of the vegetables in the casserole. Pour out any excess oil from the skillet and add the wine. Return the skillet to the heat and simmer the wine until it is reduced to 1/3 cup. Add the stock to the skillet and pour the mixture into the casserole.</p>
        <p>4. Cover the casserole and bring to a simmer over medium-high heat. Adjust the heat and simmer gently until the veal is very tender, about 2 hours.</p>
        <p>5. Remove the meat from the casserole and let rest on a platter. Pass the sauce remaining in the casserole through a food mill, discarding the solids. Wipe out the casserole, return the meat to it and pour the sauce over the meat. Simmer, uncovered, for an additional 15 minutes. Season to taste with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>6. Meanwhile, cook the peas in salted, boiling water until just tender, about 3 minutes. Drain and set aside. Make the gremolada by combining the parsley, zest and garlic. Set aside.</p>
        <p>7. Remove the meat from the casserole, transfer to a deep serving platter and remove the strings. Pour the sauce over the meat and garnish it with the peas and gremolada. Serve immediately with rice on the side.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Pistachio Sauce For Strawberries</p>
        <p>1 cup shelled, blanched, unsalted pistachios</p>
        <p>1/3 cup amaretto</p>
        <p>1/2 cup whole milk</p>
        <p>Pinch salt</p>
        <p>1 cup heavy cream</p>
        <p>5 tablespoons confectioners' sugar.</p>
        <p>1. In the container of a blender, combine the pistachios, amaretto, milk and salt and process until very smooth, about 1 to 2 minutes. Set aside.</p>
        <p>2. In a large bowl, whip the cream, gradually incorporating the sugar, until it holds soft peaks. Using a rubber spatula, fold the pistachio mixture into the whipped cream. Serve with fresh strawberries or other fresh fruit.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 1/2 cups.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
