<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Embattled Sex Shops Find A Survival Tactic Works</title>
    <meta content="18PORN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Claims Against Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohde, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E4D61F3AF93BA25753C1A96E958260" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Embattled Sex Shops Find A Survival Tactic Works</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID ROHDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohde, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adult businesses in New York City have won some legal victories in fight against Giuliani administration crackdown; 59 of 144 strip clubs and adult video stores have closed or shifted to nonadult entertainment, but industry has not been run out of residential neighborhoods as some had hoped; three judges have ruled that stores can remain open if adult entertainment is limited to less than forty percent of floor space or merchandise, and tactic has worked (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three months after a spate of highly publicized padlockings heralded the arrival of the Giuliani administration's crackdown on New York City's sex shops, a string of legal victories by adult business owners has turned what looked like a speedy rout into a war of attrition.</p>
        <p>Since the crackdown began in late July, 59 of the 144 strip clubs and adult video stores affected by a new zoning law have closed or shifted to nonadult entertainment, city officials said. But while the industry has clearly been wounded, it has not been run out of the city's residential neighborhoods as some had hoped.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three months after a spate of highly publicized padlockings heralded the arrival of the Giuliani administration's crackdown on New York City's sex shops, a string of legal victories by adult business owners has turned what looked like a speedy rout into a war of attrition.</p>
        <p>Since the crackdown began in late July, 59 of the 144 strip clubs and adult video stores affected by a new zoning law have closed or shifted to nonadult entertainment, city officials said. But while the industry has clearly been wounded, it has not been run out of the city's residential neighborhoods as some had hoped.</p>
        <p>To the frustration of sex shop opponents, state Supreme Court judges have continued to uphold a legal strategy that for now is allowing some shops and clubs to stay open under the new law. Three judges have ruled that if adult video stores, or in some cases strip clubs, limit adult entertainment to less than 40 percent of their floor space or merchandise, they can remain open.</p>
        <p>The continued survival of the adult businesses, even in a watered-down form, is a victory for the industry. But it remains to be seen how long the businesses can withstand what are believed to be plunging profit margins and soaring legal expenses.</p>
        <p>Herald Price Fahringer, the lawyer representing the majority of the 144 sex shops affected by the new law, said the sex shops were holding their own and in some cases gaining ground. He said the two Harmony Theaters in Manhattan that were closed in the first round of padlockings wanted to rebuild to meet the 40 percent standard and reopen.</p>
        <p>But he accused the Giuliani administration of denying the businesses the permits they need to reconfigure. Mr. Fahringer said he would file a lawsuit in Federal court within the next two weeks accusing the city of delaying building permits and harassing sex shops through repeated health and fire code inspections.</p>
        <p>''The city is interested in simply closing these business, not getting them to conform with the law,'' Mr. Fahringer said.</p>
        <p>Last month in Queens, Judge Alan LeVine ordered the reopening of Goldfinger's, a Rego Park strip club  padlocked under the new law, after lawyers for the club complained the city was dragging its feet in issuing a construction permit.</p>
        <p>The new law bars any business that devotes a ''substantial portion'' of its floor space or merchandise to adult entertainment from operating in residential areas or within 500 feet of a school, church or another sex shop. Department of Buildings guidelines define ''substantial portion'' as more than 40 percent.</p>
        <p>Over the objections of lawyers for the city, Judge LeVine ruled that Goldfinger's could reopen with only curtains cordoning off the 40 percent ''adult'' section of the bar, court officials said. The judge had ordered the club to build permanent walls but said that as long as the city failed to issue the building permit, it could reopen with only curtains.</p>
        <p>City officials denied any intentional delays. Gaston Silva, the city Buildings Commissioner, said his department was not withholding permits from sex shops. ''In no instance are we delaying anything,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Steven M. Fishner, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's criminal justice coordinator, said health and fire inspectors were visiting the sex shops but said the businesses had not been made targets. ''We're treating them as we treat all other businesses,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fishner said that in the last six weeks the city had also issued criminal summonses at 11 sex shops it says violate the new zoning law. The summonses, unlike the lengthy nuisance abatement court actions the city is using in efforts to padlock the clubs, can only result in fines.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fahringer, the lawyer for the sex shops, cited the court actions and summonses as examples of unusual tactics of the Giuliani administration and pointed out that zoning violations were usually resolved with administrative hearings.</p>
        <p>Despite sex shop owners' legal victories, the crackdown has succeeded in changing the tone of New York's once burgeoning sex shop industry to tepid from bawdy. Many adult video stores have torn down their more overt signs and constructed adult back rooms that make up less than 40 percent of their floor space.</p>
        <p>Strip clubs have been hit much harder, and many have had to lay off dancers. Still-employed dancers complain that their earnings plummeted when they began dancing with bikinis on to avoid having the clubs considered ''adult.''</p>
        <p>But in a ruling on Sept. 23, Judge Steven W. Fisher of Queens presented what could prove to be salvation for the strip clubs. Causing angry protests from local residents, Judge Fisher allowed Wiggles, another Rego Park strip club, to reopen after it built new cigar and television rooms and restricted nude dancing to a room that made up less than 40 percent of its floor space. It was the first ruling to apply the 40 percent standard to strip clubs.</p>
        <p>And last week, Judge Arthur W. Lonschein of Queens ruled that the formerly all-adult Fair Theater in East Elmhurst, Queens, could remain open because it was now showing adult films in less than 40 percent of its theaters. The rulings all come in the wake of an August ruling by Judge Stephen G. Crane of Manhattan that the 40 percent standard was valid in adult video stores.</p>
        <p>But city officials pointed to other rulings in their favor, and warned that the city might appeal rulings it disagrees with. Watered-down sex shops, Mr. Fishner predicted, will not prove to be economically viable.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
