<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Editorial Observer; My Honorable Opponent, the Ax Murderer...</title>
    <meta content="18SUN3$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'Amato, Alfonse M (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schumer, Charles E (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Collins, Gail</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EED81E3AF93BA25753C1A96E958260" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Editorial Observer; My Honorable Opponent, the Ax Murderer...</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GAIL COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Collins, Gail</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial Observer on this year's Senate campaign in New York as pretty deep in mud, with Charles Schumer calling Alfonse D'Amato a liar on every channel in state, and D'Amato telling upstaters that Schumer cares more about Mongolia than he does about them</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Back in 1828, when President John Quincy Adams was running for re-election, supporters of Andrew Jackson felt compelled to find some way to undermine the incumbent's reputation as a terrific diplomat. They settled on spreading a story that Adams, who had served as Ambassador to Russia, had gotten on the czar's good side by offering up his children's nanny as a royal mistress. It was not a very convincing story -- anyone who looks at Adams's portrait will instantly perceive that this was no good-time Charlie. But the President was called ''the Pimp of the Coalition'' throughout the campaign, and when Jackson won, he made the editor who invented the slander part of his kitchen cabinet.</p>
        <p>The moral of this story is that there are negative campaigns and then there are really, really negative campaigns. This year's Senate race in New York strikes some voters as pretty deep in the mud. Representative Charles Schumer has been calling Senator Alfonse D'Amato a liar on every channel in the state, and Mr. D'Amato has been telling upstate voters that Mr. Schumer cares more about Mongolia than he does about them. This weekend Mr. Schumer unleashed a new ad called ''Mother'' in which the narrator starkly announces that ''D'Amato opposes abortion rights even in cases of rape and incest, even if the mother would die.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Back in 1828, when President John Quincy Adams was running for re-election, supporters of Andrew Jackson felt compelled to find some way to undermine the incumbent's reputation as a terrific diplomat. They settled on spreading a story that Adams, who had served as Ambassador to Russia, had gotten on the czar's good side by offering up his children's nanny as a royal mistress. It was not a very convincing story -- anyone who looks at Adams's portrait will instantly perceive that this was no good-time Charlie. But the President was called ''the Pimp of the Coalition'' throughout the campaign, and when Jackson won, he made the editor who invented the slander part of his kitchen cabinet.</p>
        <p>The moral of this story is that there are negative campaigns and then there are really, really negative campaigns. This year's Senate race in New York strikes some voters as pretty deep in the mud. Representative Charles Schumer has been calling Senator Alfonse D'Amato a liar on every channel in the state, and Mr. D'Amato has been telling upstate voters that Mr. Schumer cares more about Mongolia than he does about them. This weekend Mr. Schumer unleashed a new ad called ''Mother'' in which the narrator starkly announces that ''D'Amato opposes abortion rights even in cases of rape and incest, even if the mother would die.''</p>
        <p>But on a scale of 1 to 10, this one hardly registers a 6. (A 10 would be the effort in 1856 to depict the Republican Presidential candidate as a cannibal.) The defining adjective for the D'Amato-Schumer battle is actually not ''negative'' but ''close.'' Most polls show Mr. D'Amato and Mr. Schumer running neck-and-neck, a condition that tends to bring out the vicious streak in any candidate. Close and mean is better than a gentlemanly runaway any day. Gov. George Pataki is miles ahead in the polls, and his ads are so sunny they might be mistaken for margarine commercials. His campaign consultants spent years training to be political Road Warriors, and now they're stuck doing Walt Disney, rolling out one production after another in which Mr. Pataki appears surrounded by children and scenic vistas. If his lead gets any wider, he will approach the camera with a puppy at his feet and the Bluebird of Happiness circling overhead.</p>
        <p>The D'Amato-Schumer contest, meanwhile, is a sort of Steel Cage Match of politics, in which the last guy standing wins. Mr. Schumer's ''too many lies'' campaign was fairly effective -- Mr. D'Amato's gray ethical aura is his weakest spot. But the lying the ad referred to was actually just Mr. D'Amato's habit of fluffing up his own reputation and calling his opponents ''liberal.'' The hyper-cynical voting public expects ''lie'' to means something like concealing a criminal record or a couple of surplus wives.</p>
        <p>After casting about from one insult to another -- ''liberal'' didn't work, ''from Brooklyn'' was only so-so -- Mr. D'Amato fell back on the classic ploy of adding up Mr. Schumer's missed votes. As in the Andrew Jackson campaign, Mr. D'Amato's strategists wanted to undermine their opponent's proudest boast, and Mr. Schumer is running on his reputation as an effective legislator. The attack was trivial -- you can skip quite a lot in Washington without missing anything. But it was fair. Mr. Schumer missed the votes, and he has to accept the consequences.</p>
        <p>None of this stuff would get a mention in the annals of low moments in political history. It does not even rank very high this year, when one Illinois gubernatorial candidate is basically calling another a murderer, and in South Carolina, Senator Ernest Hollings just had to apologize for saying his opponent was ''a [expletive deleted] skunk.'' But with just two weeks to go until the election, New Yorkers deserve something substantial, even if it is delivered in the rhetorical equivalent of a screech. Mr. Schumer's new ads, while rough, hit an important issue, since polls show most voters do not know that Mr. D'Amato is a staunch opponent of abortion. But the life-of-the-mother element is a bit of a stretch -- it is based mainly on Mr. D'Amato's 1983 vote for a constitutional amendment that would put the abortion issue back under the control of the states.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato's office did not return calls about the content of his upcoming ads. (The Senator has been avoiding me ever since the 1980 campaign, when I asked him to name the last five books he had read.) But we are eagerly awaiting the next volley. It has been a long time since New York has hosted an election in which we did not know the name of the winner weeks before the first absentee ballot hit the mails. It is worth hearing a lot of nasty commercials to get a contest in which everyone can imagine that his vote might really count.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
