<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poised Pak Completes a Wire-to-Wire Victory</title>
    <meta content="18LPGA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1018067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mcdonald's Lpga Championship</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Se Ri Pak</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Clifton</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980518T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E6D81F30F93BA25756C0A96E958260" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poised Pak Completes a Wire-to-Wire Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFTON BROWN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brown, Clifton</byline>
      <dateline>WILMINGTON, Del., May 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Se Ri Pak wins McDonald's LPGA Championship; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was difficult to determine what was most intriguing about Se Ri Pak -- her poise, her performance or her potential.</p>
        <p>As a 20-year-old rookie, Pak handled the final-round pressure of a major championship like a 20-year veteran. Whenever challenged, she responded. When problems arose, she solved them. And by winning the McDonald's L.P.G.A. Championship, Pak insured that her first victory in the United States would leave a lasting impression.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was difficult to determine what was most intriguing about Se Ri Pak -- her poise, her performance or her potential.</p>
        <p>As a 20-year-old rookie, Pak handled the final-round pressure of a major championship like a 20-year veteran. Whenever challenged, she responded. When problems arose, she solved them. And by winning the McDonald's L.P.G.A. Championship, Pak insured that her first victory in the United States would leave a lasting impression.</p>
        <p>Shooting a three-under-par 68 today, and shooting an 11-under-par 273 for the tournament, Pak earned $195,000 and cruised to a convincing three-stroke victory over Donna Andrews and Lisa Hackney at the DuPont Country Club.</p>
        <p>Pak's winning score was the best since the tournament moved to DuPont five years ago, breaking the 10-under-par mark of Kelly Robbins in 1995.</p>
        <p>Leading the tournament from the first round to the last, Pak played with machine-like precision that rarely wavered. She seemed almost oblivious to the pressure, the galleries that grew larger each day and the huge expectations that people have for her in her native South Korea.</p>
        <p>After this performance, and her 30 victories in South Korea as an amateur, those expectations will only increase. But after raising her arms in triumph, and throwing her golf ball into the stands as she approached the scorer's tent after her final putt at No. 18, Pak could finally celebrate.</p>
        <p>''This is an awesome feeling,'' Pak said. ''I'm really, really happy.''</p>
        <p>Pak also proved that she is really, really talented. Her best previous finish in nine L.P.G.A. events this year was a tie for 11th, but this proved to be her breakthrough week. Pak started the day tied for first with Hackney at eight under par. With 10 golfers within three strokes of the lead, many people believed Pak would crack.</p>
        <p>But she started quickly, making a birdie on No. 1 to take a one-stroke lead. Hackney pulled even with a birdie at No. 11, but bogeyed No. 13 to give Pak a one-stroke lead again.</p>
        <p>Then Pak put the exclamation point on her performance. Her second shot at No. 15 was an 8-iron that landed 20 feet from the hole. Pak needed to make the next putt for birdie, and putting had been the lone inconsistent part of her game throughout the tournament.</p>
        <p>But after watching Pak on television, David Leadbetter, her coach, telephoned her Saturday night and suggested that she shorten her backswing. Pak took the advice, and she made the 20-footer to take a two-stroke lead. On the next hole, Pak went three strokes ahead, using her power to reach the green of the par-5, 465-yard hole in two shots, then two-putting from 20 feet for birdie.</p>
        <p>At that point, Pak had a three-stroke lead with two holes to play. The way Pak was playing, the rest of the field knew it was over.</p>
        <p>''She had her game face on, and she didn't let the pressure get to her,'' said Andrews, who shot a 69 today, but who never got closer than two strokes on the back nine. ''I think a lot of the overseas players, especially the Japanese and the Koreans, are used to having so much media attention that they are not bothered when they are at the top of the leader board.</p>
        <p>''They commented on the fact she can't putt. I've played with her, and she can putt. She may not have made all the ones she could have, but she just has a good, solid game. To see a young player like that, I think it's great. Those of us near the top say, 'Hey, if we can't win, we would like to see her win.' ''</p>
        <p>Pak became the first rookie to win a major title since Liselotte Neumann won the United States Women's Open in 1988. And Pak became the third-youngest player to win a major, next to Betty Hicks, who won the 1937 Western Open when she was 17, and Patty Berg, who won the 1937 Titleholders Championship when she was 19. Pak is the youngest to ever win the L.P.G.A. Championship.</p>
        <p>Pak tried to spend the final 24 hours leading up to her victory as normally as possible, but it was not easy. She had her customary dinner at a local Outback restaurant on Saturday night. Pak is superstitious, and after eating at the Outback every day since her arrival in town, she tried a different restaurant Friday night, then shot her tournament-worst 72 on Saturday. After returning to her hotel, her manager, Sung-Yong Kil, had her phone blocked so she could get some sleep. The former president of South Korea, Chun Doo Hwan, phoned Pak early this morning, but he could not get through to Korea's hottest sports celebrity.</p>
        <p>A contingent of Korean journalists had been calling since Pak took the tournament lead on Thursday, and some of them arrived by the weekend. There were also Korean supporters in Pak's gallery, and she said the support inspired her.</p>
        <p>''I think they are more happy than me,'' Pak said. ''They want me to be the best golfer in the world.''</p>
        <p>Pak said she understood why people would start comparing her to Tiger Woods, but she wants her own recognition. For the record, Pak is even younger (20) than Woods was (21) when he won last year's Masters. With one major championship already on her resume, Pak's future looks even brighter than it did a month ago.</p>
        <p>''Maybe we didn't expect to win this quickly, but we expected to win this year,'' said Jim Cable, Pak's caddie. ''She's only going to get better. But this was a great start.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
