<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>London Falling: Khannouchi Breaks World Record</title>
    <meta content="15LOND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/04/15/sports/othersports/15LOND.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1384418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="MARATHON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">London Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Morocco</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">London (Eng)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khannouchi, Khalid</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Radcliffe, Paula</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Morocco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Khannouchi, Khalid</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFDA103CF936A25757C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>London Falling: Khannouchi Breaks World Record</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Khannouchi Breaks World Record</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Moroccan-born runner Khalid Khannouchi wins men's race in London Marathon; England's Paula Radcliffe wins women's race in marathon debut; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the world record-holder, Khalid Khannouchi had been curiously discounted by many before the London Marathon. Because of injury and miscalculation, his career had slipped into uncertainty. While almost everyone expected a world record in today's race, almost no one expected it to be set by him.</p>
        <p>Yet Khannouchi maintained a steady, blistering pace to drop the two greatest track runners in history and won in 2 hours 5 minutes 38 seconds, four seconds faster than the record he had set at the 1999 Chicago Marathon. In the women's race, Paula Radcliffe of England ran her first marathon in 2:18:56, nine seconds off the world record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Khalid Khannouchi won the London Marathon in 2 hours 5 minutes 38 seconds, four seconds faster than the record he set in 1999 in Chicago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the world record-holder, Khalid Khannouchi had been curiously discounted by many before the London Marathon. Because of injury and miscalculation, his career had slipped into uncertainty. While almost everyone expected a world record in today's race, almost no one expected it to be set by him.</p>
        <p>Yet Khannouchi maintained a steady, blistering pace to drop the two greatest track runners in history and won in 2 hours 5 minutes 38 seconds, four seconds faster than the record he had set at the 1999 Chicago Marathon. In the women's race, Paula Radcliffe of England ran her first marathon in 2:18:56, nine seconds off the world record.</p>
        <p>Eight years ago, Khannouchi went to Buffalo for the World University Games and did not return to his native Morocco. Instead, he washed dishes and worked as a busboy in Brooklyn. Haile Gebrselassie of Ethiopia and Paul Tergat of Kenya, meanwhile, built ascendant careers that brought 15 world records and 2 Olympic gold medals at 10,000 meters for Gebrselassie and five world cross-country championships and two Olympic silver medals for Tergat.</p>
        <p>Khannouchi moved to Ossining, N.Y., became an American citizen in 2000 and dreamed of beating these men from whom he drew inspiration at the distance he felt most comfortable -- 26.2 miles. He did today, with patience and resolve on a chilly, clear morning in what many considered the greatest marathon in history.</p>
        <p>Tergat set a Kenyan record in finishing second in 2:05:48, the third-fastest time ever run. Gebrselassie, the favorite, who led for most of the race, set an Ethiopian record and a debut record in taking third place in 2:06:35, but his left calf muscle seized and he fell back in the final miles.</p>
        <p>For the women, Radcliffe broke away at seven miles and ran alone, nearing the world record set by Catherine Ndereba of Kenya last October at the Chicago Marathon. Radcliffe delivered the second-fastest marathon time and became only the third woman to run under 2:20. Her victory was made even more impressive by the fact that the women ran alone, without any pacing assistance from male runners, and that the pace clock on the truck was broken.</p>
        <p>Previously, the 28-year-old Radcliffe had been known here as ''poor, brave Paula'' for her gutsy style of running at the front of track races, only to be passed on the last lap by Derartu Tulu of Ethiopia, the 1992 and 2000 Olympic champion at 10,000 meters. Today, Radcliffe took no chances on being caught. She threw in splits of 5:07 in Mile 14, 5:08 in Mile 15 and 5:06 in Mile 25, completing the final half of the race in an astonishing 1:07:51 -- only five minutes slower than the men, who were on a world-record pace.</p>
        <p>''At the beginning, I didn't want to run on my own, but I didn't feel comfortable and I wanted to run faster,'' Radcliffe said of the slow pace. ''I felt relaxed. I thought, 'Why not?' ''</p>
        <p>While Radcliffe won by more than three and a half minutes, the race was so fast that the top four women finished under 2:23. Svetlana Zakharova of Russia took second in 2:22:31, while her countrywoman Lyudmilla Petrova took third in 2:22:33. Tulu, the defending champion, seemed distressed from the beginning and faded to ninth in 2:28:37, nearly 10 minutes behind Radcliffe.</p>
        <p>''In my professional career, this is the greatest marathon I've ever seen, men and women, including the Olympics and world championships,'' said Carey Pinkowski, race director of the Chicago Marathon.</p>
        <p>The men's world record came on a course that was thought to be inhospitable to such a performance because of the many turns and cobblestone stretches in the latter half of the race.</p>
        <p>The victory was particularly satisfying and redemptive for Khannouchi. Against any advice that would be considered wise, he ran the 2000 London Marathon with a wrenched ankle and exacerbated the injury, preventing him from participating in the Olympic marathon trials as an American citizen. Last summer, he did represent the United States at the world championships in Edmonton, Alberta, but he dropped out at Mile 16, complaining of blisters.</p>
        <p>''I felt I betrayed a lot of people,'' the 30-year-old Khannouchi said.</p>
        <p>His failures robbed him of all motivation, he said. Still, he persevered through a winter of hard altitude training in Albuquerque and Mexico City. Last month, he won a half-marathon in Japan in a mediocre 1:02:16, but, more important, Khannouchi's slight body came through the winter uninjured for the first time in two years.</p>
        <p>Today's pace suited him perfectly. Gebrselassie asked the pacemakers to carry him through the midway point in 1:02:30, but they arrived 17 seconds late. This allowed Khannouchi, at the back of a lead pack of 15 runners, to reach 13.1 miles in 1:02:50 or so, just as he planned. He knew he had to remain near Gebrselassie to have a chance to win, but he did not have to exhaust himself to remain in the lead group.</p>
        <p>In his inexperience, Gebrselassie said he became confused, wondering whether the pace was quick enough. The more seasoned Khannouchi simply kept up his rhythmic, metronomic consistency. He would run the second half of the race in essentially the same time that he ran the first.</p>
        <p>At Mile 20, Gebrselassie surged with a 4:44 split and his pursuers were winnowed to Khannouchi and Tergat. No more great charges followed, only the unbroken determination of men who are all legs and heart and lungs. Then Gebrselassie began to weaken. In his first marathon, Gebrselassie drank only water, not replenishing sports drinks. And his bouncing stride, along with the unevenness of the cobblestones, caused a cramp in his calf. Between Miles 24 and 25, Gebrselassie dropped back, leaving Khannouchi and Tergat to sort out the victory.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to change gears, but it didn't work,'' said Gebrselassie, the world record-holder at 5,000 and 10,000 meters. ''It's too new for my body.''</p>
        <p>With their tremendous kicks, Gebrselassie and Tergat believed they could draw away from Khannouchi. But he maintained his form while the others grew heavy in the legs. He did not wilt before Gebrselassie, and he did not wilt before Tergat, pulling away in the final mile. At the finish, Khannouchi knelt, kissed the ground and said a prayer. He had set a world record, defeating the men who became his running idols when he was an unknown dishwasher in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''It's difficult to call someone the greatest,'' Khannouchi said modestly. ''You can be one of the greatest, but you can't be the only one.''</p>
        <p>MARATHON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
