<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Congressional Lines Open New York Doors</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="49" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="536098"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICAL NOTES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAPPORTIONMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STATE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SKELOS, DEAN G (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRISA, DANIEL (ASSEMBLYMAN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANNON, KEMP (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reapportionment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DD1330F937A25755C0A964958260" item-length="848" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Congressional Lines Open New York Doors</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In embracing a state court plan for Congressional redistricting over a competing proposal from a Federal court, New York State lawmakers opted to protect more Congressional incumbents.</p>
        <p>But with last week's surprise resignation of one incumbent, Representative Raymond J. McGrath, a Long Island Republican, another potential explanation has emerged for why state lawmakers prefer the state plan: the opportunities it provides for state lawmakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In embracing a state court plan for Congressional redistricting over a competing proposal from a Federal court, New York State lawmakers opted to protect more Congressional incumbents.</p>
        <p>But with last week's surprise resignation of one incumbent, Representative Raymond J. McGrath, a Long Island Republican, another potential explanation has emerged for why state lawmakers prefer the state plan: the opportunities it provides for state lawmakers.</p>
        <p>A potential contender for the seat left open by Mr. McGrath is State Senator Dean G. Skelos, a Nassau County Republican. Under the Federal plan, though, it would be unlikely for Mr. Skelos to run because he would be in the same district with Representative Norman Lent, a fellow Republican. With the state court plan, approved by the Legislature last week, he faces no such dilemma.</p>
        <p>Mr. Skelos is a co-chairman of the Legislature's redistricting panel. But he says that he had no advance knowledge of Mr. McGrath's resignation and that he's not even sure he wants to run for Congress.</p>
        <p>"I would consider it, but I don't know," he said, adding that he wanted to talk the matter over with his family and county political leaders.</p>
        <p>Two other state lawmakers who could benefit from the state plan are Assemblyman Daniel Frisa, who is interested in running and lives in the McGrath district, and Senator Kemp Hannon. Mr. Frisa had threatened to challenge Mr. Hannon if there was no redistricting plan he liked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hannon says he has no thoughts of running for Congress: "Nope, they abolished all the perks," he joked in an interview. Sour Coda for City's Anthem</p>
        <p>Having announced in recent weeks that New York City had unexpected budget surpluses and would abandon a plan to raise various taxes, and then producing a new budget a month ahead of schedule, Mayor David N. Dinkins may be resurrecting a familiar campaign theme in 1993: Happy days are here, or at least near, again.</p>
        <p>But recent remarks by Rudolph W. Giuliani, the former United States Attorney, and the City Council President, Andrew J. Stein, both likely to run against Mr. Dinkins in the next mayoral election, indicate both men think things are just as bad as ever.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani denounced the Mayor's new $29.5 billion budget, saying Mr. Dinkins had botched a chance to reduce the size of government dramatically and to freeze spending.</p>
        <p>The budget "doesn't address any of the fundamental problems that make New York one of the largest spending engines in the United States," Mr. Giuliani said at a City Hall news conference a few days after the City Council adopted the budget.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Stein dismissed the budget in an open letter to the city's newspapers.</p>
        <p>"The important issue for the city's future is not the timing of the budget but its substance," he said. He said the budget failed the city's schoolchildren by allotting money that should have gone to the Board of Education to municipal workers' pay increases.</p>
        <p>Mayoral aides said they were unfazed by the criticism. "If I were a political porter," said Mr. Dinkins's spokesman, Leland T. Jones, "I would much rather be carrying the light bags of David Dinkins than the unbelievably heavy baggage of Andy (The Whine) Stein or Rudy (The Republican) Giuliani." Ready, Aim, Shoot Your Foot</p>
        <p>Readers of this column may remember the recent saga of Howard C. Nolan Jr., a State Senator from Albany who voted for the controversial bill that would give semiautomatic weapons to New York City police officers on the very same day that he sent a letter to Police Commissioner Lee P. Brown assuring him that he would oppose the measure.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. Nolan took the Senate floor to explain his vote. It was all a mistake, he said, one of those busy days when he did not realize that the measure had actually come up for a so-called "fast roll call" vote -- in which all Senators listed as present are recorded with an "aye" if they do not raise their hands when the bill is announced -- and he was unable to get back to change his automatic yes to a no. "If I had been in this chamber," he told his colleagues, "I would have voted in the negative."</p>
        <p>The Senate's deputy majority leader, Ronald B. Stafford, a Plattsburgh Republican, said: "That's all right, Howard. We're all mad anyway because you got your picture in the paper." Loosening the Fiscal Belt</p>
        <p>Eighteen months after voluntarily cutting his salary 5 percent in a show of shared suffering over fiscal belt-tightening in New York City, Fernando Ferrer, the Bronx Borough President, has announced that he will begin drawing his full $95,000 salary again in July.</p>
        <p>"Now that the city is back on course and the budget is pretty stable, the Borough President decided to go back to his statutory salary," Mr. Ferrer's spokesman, Clint Roswell, said yesterday. "It's not like he's getting a raise."</p>
        <p>Mayor Dinkins started a flurry of salary-cutting among the city's elected officials in October 1990 when he imposed a 5 percent reduction on himself and 800 other senior administration officials. Mr. Dinkins rescinded that cut last December.</p>
        <p>POLITICAL NOTES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
