<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Transplant Learns Los Angeles the Hard Way</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="536093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">KCBS-TV (LOS ANGELES)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOROWICZ, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5DB1230F937A25755C0A964958260" item-length="615" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Transplant Learns Los Angeles the Hard Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHERINE S. MANEGOLD,</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Michael Horowicz, a transplanted New York television news producer who joined KCBS-TV in Hollywood in 1990, says he "left New York for some peace and quiet." He and his wife, Jane Velez-Mitchell, a former news anchor for WCBS-TV in New York, settled in to life in the comparatively slow lane.</p>
        <p>Then, in the wake of the Rodney G. King verdict last month, came the riots.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Michael Horowicz, a transplanted New York television news producer who joined KCBS-TV in Hollywood in 1990, says he "left New York for some peace and quiet." He and his wife, Jane Velez-Mitchell, a former news anchor for WCBS-TV in New York, settled in to life in the comparatively slow lane.</p>
        <p>Then, in the wake of the Rodney G. King verdict last month, came the riots.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Horowicz, the sudden upheaval was a shock. In New York, he had found he could not escape the city. In Los Angeles, he could not find it.</p>
        <p>"I was out of touch," he said. "There's no subway here. There's no great equalizer. Here, everybody drives because they have their house, which is their own private country club, and they have their cars, and they drive on these highways and they don't see because they don't have to see." A Turning Point</p>
        <p>Pacing about in the windowless office of his news director, Mr. Horowicz fingered a purple silk tie and spoke of the riots as a turning point. "My life really changed after the riots," he said. "I find myself questioning more stories now. Do the viewers really care about some star-studded event when they are having trouble putting food on the table?"</p>
        <p>He did not have to weigh those questions in New York. "In New York," he said, "you live the city. You breathe it. You know what's going on."</p>
        <p>Mr. Horowicz remembers New York as the rudest, roughest, most competitive television market in the nation. At WABC, he remembers having reporters illegally set off fire alarms to check on the response time of the fire department, something he claims he would never do here.</p>
        <p>Once, he said, when WABC was broadcasting its nightly newscast from Shea Stadium in Queens during baseball season, "Our boss ordered a helicopter to hover over the stadium for the whole newscast just to try to screw up their sound feed." Polite Journalism</p>
        <p>By comparison, he finds Los Angeles news coverage almost, well, tame. "You can get away with a lot more in New York," he said. "The press is much more rabid. Here, everyone is always so</p>
        <p>polite</p>
        <p>."</p>
        <p>That attitude extends to the newsrooms. After the riots, the NBC affiliate in Los Angeles ran an hourlong special on those who did good deeds in the midst of the chaos. The program showed citizens assisting the police and firefighters, aiding victims and helping neighbors. Most of the footage was produced by news crews at the scene during the riots' peak.</p>
        <p>But instead of ending up on the video-age equivalent of the cutting room floor, the program was beamed out as balm for the city's troubled soul.</p>
        <p>"Crime is a very hot story because people want to keep themselves safe," said Nancy Valenta, KNBC's news director. "But you can't just do crime, crime, crime, crime. You have to give people a hope, really, that things can get better. We have been trying to do stories to show that people are taking steps." Other Priorities</p>
        <p>But there are other priorities, too.</p>
        <p>"Today, our reporters wanted to do a 'think' piece on the national political campaign," John A. Lippman, the news director at KCBS, said just days before the California primary on June 2. "But that lost out in favor of a house in danger of falling."</p>
        <p>Suddenly, he lept to his feet. On one of the three televisions in his office, a car chase involving the police and a tow truck was playing out live on his own station. He grabbed a telephone and called an editor not 50 feet away. "Great. A</p>
        <p>car chase</p>
        <p>! Oh, good. Stay on it. Stay</p>
        <p>on</p>
        <p>it!"</p>
        <p>The sound of sirens filled the newsroom. The police caught the tow truck. Everyone was fine.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, in Hollywood, even newscasts seem like fiction and, already, the riots can fade far away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
