<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The City by the Bay Holds Its Collective Breath</title>
    <meta content="Y15BANK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980417T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1009838"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Personnel</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Charlotte (Nc)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bankamerica Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nationsbank Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Willie (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina/Charlotte</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E6DF163CF936A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The City by the Bay Holds Its Collective Breath</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markoff, John</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Many residents of San Francisco are wondering if BankAmerica Corp's dominating presence in the city will fade with merger of BankAmerica and Nationsbank Corp; are disturbed by reports that merger might cost 5,000 to 8,000 jobs nationally; bank's middle-management jobs are obvious candidates for relocation from San Francisco, one of nation's most expensive cities, to Nationsbank's headquarters in Charlotte, NC, where cost of living is much lower; Mayor Willie Brown calls deal 'economic disaster' for the city (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For almost three decades the BankAmerica Corporation's 52-story headquarters has been a dominating presence on this city's skyline, but in the aftermath of the bank's planned $60 billion merger with the Nationsbank Corporation many people here are wondering if that presence will fade to a shadow.</p>
        <p>Word that the largest bank merger in history might remove a financial institution intertwined with San Francisco's rich history dating to the 1906 earthquake has rocked the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For almost three decades the BankAmerica Corporation's 52-story headquarters has been a dominating presence on this city's skyline, but in the aftermath of the bank's planned $60 billion merger with the Nationsbank Corporation many people here are wondering if that presence will fade to a shadow.</p>
        <p>Word that the largest bank merger in history might remove a financial institution intertwined with San Francisco's rich history dating to the 1906 earthquake has rocked the city.</p>
        <p>Reports that the merger might cost 5,000 to 8,000 jobs nationally were interpreted here to mean that San Francisco was particularly vulnerable. The bank's middle-management jobs are obvious candidates for relocation from San Francisco, one of the nation's most expensive cities, to Nationsbank's headquarters in Charlotte, N.C., where the cost of living is much lower.</p>
        <p>Still, today nobody could state with authority what the actual job impact of the merger would be.</p>
        <p>When he was awakened with the news Monday morning, Mayor Willie Brown called the deal an ''economic disaster'' for San Francisco. By the afternoon, however, after speaking with the BankAmerica chairman, David A. Coulter, the Mayor had changed his mind and suggested to reporters that there was a potential for new jobs.</p>
        <p>The combined bank's vision as it was announced is a formidable power with twin centers, in which Charlotte will be the headquarters and San Francisco will serve as the hub of an expanding international presence. Indeed, Mr. Coulter said he planned to remain in San Francisco, and most analysts consider him the leading candidate to succeed Hugh L. McColl Jr., who will become the merged banks' chairman.</p>
        <p>However, many San Franciscans view the city's almost century-long relationship with the bank as intricate and intimate, and the symbolic departure of its headquarters to the East Coast was cause for alarm.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the bank's founder, A. P. Giannini, had twin visions of creating a bank that was national in scale but attentive to the needs of the ''little people,'' reflecting San Francisco's blue-collar roots.</p>
        <p>''In one sense he'd be thrilled and in an another sense he'd be spinning in his grave,'' said Warren Hellman, chairman of Hellman &amp; Friedman, a private equity fund and a descendant of the family that created the Wells Fargo Bank, BankAmerica's main California rival.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the city has been transformed from its origins as a seaport and manufacturing town at the turn of the century into the financial center of the Pacific Rim.</p>
        <p>But San Francisco has maintained a love affair with the image of Mr. Giannini setting up his bank outside on a rough-hewn desk in the ruins of the 1906 earthquake and fire to help finance the rebuilding of the city.</p>
        <p>The banker took that passion to finance the state's agricultural, movie and oil businesses in the first half of the century.</p>
        <p>''When grandpa started the bank he went up and down California's Central Valley telling the farmers, 'Put your money in my bank and you'll make money,' '' said Virginia Hammerness, who is Mr. Giannini's granddaughter.</p>
        <p>The merger represented a betrayal of Mr. Giannini's dream, she said.  ''They sure sold out San Francisco,'' she said. ''I'm hung up on loyalty and there isn't any here.''</p>
        <p>A number of the city's leaders expressed similar concerns about losing a powerful financial institution and corporate citizen -- BankAmerica contributed $5 million to San Francisco organizations in 1997. The bank has been a significant contributor in areas from the American Conservatory Theater to the city's welfare-to-work program, from financing projects ranging from the Golden Gate Bridge to the Hetch Hetchy water project.</p>
        <p>''I'm pessimistic,'' said Michael Yaki, a member of the San Francisco Board of Supervisors. ''I'm worried that those decisions will be relocated to Charlotte and have an impact on the health of our civic and social institutions.''</p>
        <p>BankAmerica's magnet effect has created a financial climate that will be difficult to duplicate, he said.</p>
        <p>''Their corporate headquarters has meant mega-jobs and mega-deals and has made the city a financially hip place to be,'' he said. ''That's something you can't replace.''</p>
        <p>Despite San Francisco's anxiety over BankAmerica's future, its relationship with the bank has in recent years become more strained. The main reason is a whistle-blower lawsuit brought by more than 250 cities and the State of California accusing the bank of defrauding the public by taking more than $1 billion from Government bank accounts to pay for salaries, consultants and other expenses.</p>
        <p>''It was like finding out that your best friend has been cheating with your wife,'' the deputy city attorney, Marc Slavin, said. He attributed the change to a modern economy in which corporations lose touch with their home communities.</p>
        <p>''It's a symptom of the globalization of the economy,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That fact struck home directly with Tom Lieser, the executive director of the University of Los Angeles at California Anderson Forecast, a regional economic forecasting group. As a teen-ager in 1956, Mr. Lieser opened a passbook savings account with Home Federal Savings in Tulsa, Okla. On Monday, after that bank was merged for the sixth time, Mr. Lieser's account was finally taken over by BankAmerica.</p>
        <p>''It's a microcosm of what's happened in this industry,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 17, 1998, Friday  An article in Business Day on Wednesday about the impact of a planned merger between BankAmerica and Nationsbank on BankAmerica's home, San Francisco, misstated the university affiliation of Tom Lieser, an economic forecaster who was quoted on such consolidation. It is the University of California at Los Angeles (not the University of Los Angeles at California).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 17, 1998, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in Business Day on Wednesday about the impact of a planned merger between BankAmerica and Nationsbank on BankAmerica's home, San Francisco, misstated the university affiliation of Tom Lieser, an economic forecaster who was quoted on such consolidation. It is the University of California at Los Angeles (not the University of Los Angeles at California).</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
