<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Commercial Property/Suburban Mall Competition; Stamford Town Center Pins Hopes on New Addition</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="698454"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOPPING CENTERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">STAMFORD (CONN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">STAMFORD TOWN CENTER (STAMFORD, CONN, MALL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHARLES, ELEANOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E4D9163FF933A25754C0A962958260" item-length="1280" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Commercial Property/Suburban Mall Competition; Stamford Town Center Pins Hopes on New Addition</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHARLES, ELEANOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUBURBAN mall development is reviving in Westchester and Fairfield Counties now that the economy is recovering. But a question rising above the clang of construction is what affect these developments will have on long-term efforts to expand shopping opportunities in downtown Stamford, Conn.</p>
        <p>One new mall in White Plains is already in construction. Another has been proposed across the street. In Stamford, financing is being sought for the extension of an existing mall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUBURBAN mall development is reviving in Westchester and Fairfield Counties now that the economy is recovering. But a question rising above the clang of construction is what affect these developments will have on long-term efforts to expand shopping opportunities in downtown Stamford, Conn.</p>
        <p>One new mall in White Plains is already in construction. Another has been proposed across the street. In Stamford, financing is being sought for the extension of an existing mall.</p>
        <p>The mall owners have already had two extensions from city government, and are operating against a deadline on a third.</p>
        <p>The Stamford project involves a proposed 400,000-square-foot addition to the existing 874,000-square-foot Stamford Town Center. The center is one of the country's most successful malls. Will it be choked off from its customers to the south by the new projects in Westchester, as some planners and retailers suggest? It is already limited on the north and east by existing Connecticut malls that have expanded over the years.</p>
        <p>The 1.5-million-square-foot Danbury Fair Mall, the largest in New England -- is anchored by Lord &amp; Taylor, Filene's, Sears, Macy's and J.C. Penney and has 217 satellite shops. The million-square-foot Trumbull Shopping Park has 200 stores, with Lord &amp; Taylor, A &amp; Straus and Filene's as anchors.</p>
        <p>The Stamford Town Center opened in 1982. At present its tenancies are in transition. J.C. Penney, one of three original anchors, will move out this month, and Filene's, the 33-store New England-New York chain founded in Boston in 1851, will move in. The May Company of St. Louis, owner of the Filene stores since 1988 when Filene's Basement became a separate entity, will completely renovate the 183,000 square-foot Penney's space for an opening around next Christmas.</p>
        <p>Early next month, the Eighth Stamford New Urban Corporation, an arm of F.D. Rich Company of Stamford, must come up with financing for its proposed $222 million expansion of the center or face withdrawal of the authorization for the expansion by the Stamford Urban Redevelopment Commission. In the process, it could lose ownership of a 4 1/2-acre parcel on Tresser Boulevard where the addition would be built. By failing to grow, the center could fall behind in the accelerating competition among the region's malls.</p>
        <p>Next March, The Westchester, an 830,000-square-foot, 150-shop mall under construction in White Plains by the O'Connor Group of Manhattan, is scheduled to open on the site of the former B. Altman and Neiman-Marcus complex, anchored by Nordstrom and Neiman-Marcus.</p>
        <p>A year or two later The Westchester could find itself across the street from Westchester Place, a proposed 820,000-square-foot mall. The developer, Alex Conroy of Greenwich, expects to file applications for rezoning and site plan approval this summer. Using the existing Saks Fifth Avenue site on Maple Avenue and Bloomingdale Road, and the Nynex site behind it, the mall would have 175 shops and Saks and Bloomingdale's as its anchors.</p>
        <p>"I HAVE bought the Nynex property," said Mr. Conroy, "and I have a partnership agreement with Saks. This is a trade area of 900,000 people with an average income of $100,000 a year. After all of us are up and running the market will still be understored."</p>
        <p>Bloomingdale's would move to the new mall from its current location on Bloomingdale Road -- a blow to Stamford, which lost its 243,000-square-foot, 36-year-old Bloomiingdale's in 1990. The store was closed because of financial troubles at the parent company, Federated Department Stores, and the taint of a murder that occurred in the parking lot.</p>
        <p>A third White Plains mall, the 880,000-square-foot Galleria, anchored by A &amp; S and J.C. Penney, opened in 1980 and recently completed a major renovation.</p>
        <p>"There will be an overlap of stores," said Al Messer, general manager of the Stamford Town Center, "and there is no question that there will be competition. Certainly we are concerned, but I don't think they will seriously impact our business."</p>
        <p>The price that the May Company will pay for the Penney store has not been disclosed, but it is assessed at $9.7 million, a figure that will rise in three years to $10.8 million under a newly phased-in revaluation. The current market value is about $15.4 million, according to Peter Sebastian, Stamford's assessor for commercial property.</p>
        <p>"When the Stamford Town Center opened no one knew what the market would eventually be," said Mr. Messer, "so we covered them all with Penney's, Macy's and Saks Fifth Avenue as anchors and 130 small shops to support them. Over the years the upper-echelon stores emerged as the dominant market, cutting support for Penney's and some of the lower-end shops."</p>
        <p>"Sales never measured up to the company's expectations," said Nancy Dickson, spokeswoman at the Penney headquarters in Plano, Tex., "so an opportunity to sell was the most advantageous option." J.C. Penney will continue to operate its stores in the Danbury Fair Mall, the Galleria, and the Trumbull Shopping Park.</p>
        <p>"We believe the mall expansion is the best use for the property in question," said Elizabeth Saunders, chairman of the Stamford Urban Redevelopment Commission, "and my hope is that Rich will be able to get his act together or find someone to stand in his stead."</p>
        <p>At its June 9 meeting the commission denied Rich's Eighth Stamford New Urban Corporation any additional extensions of time beyond Aug. 9 to find financing.</p>
        <p>Rich bought the land from the commission in 1983 for $811,000. If Eighth Stamford cannot go forward with the expansion the land will be subject to repossession by the commission.</p>
        <p>"WE purchased it years ago in a condemnation proceeding," said Ms. Saunders, "and conveyed it to the Rich organization with the caveat that it be developed as an extension to the mall. That committment has not been met, therefore we are empowered to take it back at no cost, but the commission is not enthusiastic about reclaiming it and starting all over again."</p>
        <p>But, said F.D. Rich 3d, senior vice president of Eighth Stamford, "we don't necessarily concur with the commission's interpretation of the contract." His lawyer, Lawrence Gochberg, added that "this is a very involved legal process which will take a long time to unravel."</p>
        <p>Crucial to the financing is Eighth Stamford's application to the Connecticut Development Authority for a guaranteed $46 million loan under the Tax Increment Financing Statute, a piece of 1992 enabling legislation by which bonds may be floated and the debt service paid with sales-tax revenues. A decision on whether to approve the application is expected within the next week or two.</p>
        <p>"So far tax increment financing has never been used," said Joseph Cohen, spokesman for the state's Department of Economic Development, "and it is difficult to justify its use based solely on new retail sales taxes to be generated within a large project like the Stamford Town Center."</p>
        <p>He noted that the Taubman Company of Bloomfield Hills, Mich., co-owner of the Stamford Town Center, had not been able to secure tax increment financing for a proposed extension of the Chapel Square Mall in New Haven and subsequently bowed out of the venture.</p>
        <p>"We and the Rich organization are going to give this our best effort," said Christopher J. Tennyson, vice president of corporate affairs for Taubman, referring to the brief period for raising funds, "to protect the center's position as a premier regional shopping center."</p>
        <p>"I think there will be a winner and a loser," said Mr. Conroy, promoter of Westchester Place. "It will be Stamford or White Plains. We hope to solidify White Plains as the dominant fashion market."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
