<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CABARET GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="27CABA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/27/arts/music/27CABA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1451699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021227T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2D6103CF934A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CABARET GUIDE</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cabaret Guide</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Holden</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend and New Year's Eve. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>* BLOSSOM DEARIE, Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133. This wry, wistful minimalist has never sounded better. An ageless singer and pianist, she brings a light but knowing touch to songs like ''The Ladies Who Lunch'' and the Dave Frishberg classics ''Peel Me a Grape'' and ''I'm Hip.'' And her own ballad ''Bye-Bye Country Boy'' (a kind of answer to Leon Russell's ''Superstar''), with lyrics by Jack Segal, deserves to be a standard. A Brazilian pulse animates many of the arrangements. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7; Sunday at 6:15 p.m. Cover: $25, with a $15 minimum; a $54.50 dinner-and-show package is available.Also at Danny's: tonight and tomorrow night from 9 to 1 and Tuesday, Jerry Scott, singer and pianist. Cover: none to $25; two-drink minimum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend and New Year's Eve. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend and New Year's Eve. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>* BLOSSOM DEARIE, Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133. This wry, wistful minimalist has never sounded better. An ageless singer and pianist, she brings a light but knowing touch to songs like ''The Ladies Who Lunch'' and the Dave Frishberg classics ''Peel Me a Grape'' and ''I'm Hip.'' And her own ballad ''Bye-Bye Country Boy'' (a kind of answer to Leon Russell's ''Superstar''), with lyrics by Jack Segal, deserves to be a standard. A Brazilian pulse animates many of the arrangements. Tonight and tomorrow night at 7; Sunday at 6:15 p.m. Cover: $25, with a $15 minimum; a $54.50 dinner-and-show package is available.Also at Danny's: tonight and tomorrow night from 9 to 1 and Tuesday, Jerry Scott, singer and pianist. Cover: none to $25; two-drink minimum.</p>
        <p>* MICHAEL FEINSTEIN, Feinstein's at the Regency, Park Avenue at 61st Street, (212) 339-4095. The singer and pianist's new cabaret show, ''A Holiday Keepsake,'' finds this fervent pop traditionalist successfully incorporating boogie-woogie and blues flavors into his repertory of styles. And while Mr. Feinstein is no flailing Jerry Lee Lewis jack-in-the-box, the contrast between the creamy crooner of ''Have Yourself a Merry Little Christmas'' and the polished cutup of ''Boogie Woogie Santa Claus'' adds depth to his act. The show deftly balances Christian, Jewish and novelty numbers. A pop-jazz sextet led by John Oddo pumps life into the songs. The singer Gloria Reuben is Mr. Feinstein's special guest. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30 and 11. Cover: tonight at 8:30 and tomorrow at 8:30 and 11, $75; tonight at 11, $45; $30 minimum. New Year's Eve at 7:30 and 10: Steve Tyrell. Cover: $115; $30 minimum for the first show, $60 at 10.</p>
        <p>ANDREA MARCOVICCI, the Oak Room of the Algonquin Hotel, 59 West 44th Street, (212) 840-6800. For her 15th season at the Oak Room, Ms. Marcovicci focuses her nostalgic radar on the life and love songs of Cole Porter. Her anecdotes about his privileged life are delicious, and her selection of songs is a fine blend of obscure gems and beloved standards. As always, Ms. Marcovicci lives in the moment of every song she sings, and the program includes more than two dozen numbers. But her singing, technically limited in the best of times, has deteriorated noticeably. Her immense charm and passionate commitment to the material cannot always carry her over the vocal hurdles. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9 and 11:30. Cover: $50; $50 prix fixe dinner for performances at 9; late shows, $20 minimum. On Tuesday, the Algonquin celebrates 100 years of New Year's Eve parties with Ms. Marcovicci and, in the lobby, Vince Giorgano and the Nighthawks. At 10, with four-course dinner at 8:30. Cover: $500 a person, including champagne toast at midnight; dinner in the Round Table Room and dancing in the lobby, $250, including Champagne toast at midnight.</p>
        <p>STEVE ROSS, Stanhope Park Hyatt, 995 Fifth Avenue, at 81st Street, (212) 650-4737. This dapper singer and pianist, who seems to have been born in a tuxedo, has landed in an invitingly intimate restaurant setting across the street from the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Although he occasionally ventures into contemporary territory, Mr. Ross is most at home interpreting the wittier lyrics of Cole Porter, Noël Coward and Lorenz Hart and bringing alive an idealized dream world of Manhattan high life 60 years ago. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30 and 10:30; New Year's Eve from 7 to 1. Cover: $35, with dinner required at the early shows and a $20 minimum at the late shows. New Year's Eve, $299.</p>
        <p>* BOBBY SHORT, Cafe Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. It's a huge stretch from Cole Porter to Bessie Smith, but Mr. Short, as ebullient as ever, makes it look easy. This is the singer and pianist's 34th fall season at Cafe Carlyle, and he is accompanied by an eight-member swing band whose bubbly arrangements match his high spirits. The program includes a witty, crowing version of ''I Can't Get Started'' that emphasizes some of the song's lesser-known lyrics; Porter's ''Just One of Those Things,'' which has been become Mr. Short's theme song; and a wonderfully rowdy version of ''Gimme a Pig Foot'' in which the singer virtually channels the Empress of the Blues. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:45 and 10:45; Tuesday at 11:15, with dinner at 9. Cover: $75; no minimum. New Year's Eve, $500 a person, including dinner and a Champagne toast at midnight.</p>
        <p>BEMELMANS BAR, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. Loston Harris Trio. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9:30, and Tuesday night at 10. Cover: $20 for tables, $10 at the bar; no minimum. New Year's Eve, $50 a person.</p>
        <p>CAFE PIERRE, Fifth Avenue at 61st Street, (212) 940-8195. Kathleen Landis, singer and pianist, performs songs from Hollywood films of the 1930's and 40's. Tonight and tomorrow night at 8:30; New Year's Eve at 8, with dinner. Sunday and Monday nights at 8:30, Nancy Winston, singer. No cover; $20 minimum. New Year's Eve: $485 a person.</p>
        <p>JUDY'S, 169 Eighth Avenue, at 18th Street, Chelsea, (212) 929-5410. ''New Year's Eve Groove-a-Thon,'' with the Lounge-o-Leers. Tuesday night at 10. No cover; $12 minimum.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
