<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10FSUM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1447496"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DEEDE173AF933A25751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1153" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-20</p>
        <p>Early Look at Iraqi Report Forced by U.S. Pressure  The United States has taken first possession of a copy of Iraq's declaration of its weapons programs, after persuading the four other permanent members of the Security Council to back it in insisting on seeing the document immediately, American officials said. In doing so, the United States circumvented a decision that Security Council members had made to wait to see the document until information that could possibly have been used to make a nuclear weapons had been removed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Heavy Inspection Schedule  United Nations weapons inspectors picked up the pace of their work, sending the largest team of nuclear inspectors yet for the third inspection in a week of the giant al-Tuweitha nuclear complex south of Baghdad.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-20</p>
        <p>Early Look at Iraqi Report Forced by U.S. Pressure  The United States has taken first possession of a copy of Iraq's declaration of its weapons programs, after persuading the four other permanent members of the Security Council to back it in insisting on seeing the document immediately, American officials said. In doing so, the United States circumvented a decision that Security Council members had made to wait to see the document until information that could possibly have been used to make a nuclear weapons had been removed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Heavy Inspection Schedule  United Nations weapons inspectors picked up the pace of their work, sending the largest team of nuclear inspectors yet for the third inspection in a week of the giant al-Tuweitha nuclear complex south of Baghdad.</p>
        <p>A22</p>
        <p>Deadly Mexico Border Region  At least 280 women and girls have been killed in Ciudad Juárez, near the American border, since 1993. State authorities say at least 76 of them fell prey to serial killers. Women's leaders say that the real total of women and girls raped, killed and missing is closer to 600.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Turkey Seeks Help on Europe  Recep Tayyip Erdogan, the leader of Turkey's Justice and Development Party, is expected to ask President Bush for help in securing the agreement of the European Union in giving Turkey a date to begin negotiations for membership.</p>
        <p>A23</p>
        <p>U.S. to Sell Weapons to Algeria  The Bush administration will sell equipment to the military-backed government of Algeria to help combat Islamic militants who have engaged in a violent uprising since a militant Islamic party was banned in the early 1990's, administration officials said.</p>
        <p>A20</p>
        <p>Joint U.S. Effort With Canada  The United States and Canada announced a broadening of their military cooperation to include the possibility that troops of one country would cross into the other in case of a terrorist attack or natural disaster.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A26-33</p>
        <p>Cheney Allowed to Keep Energy Records Secret  Vice President Dick Cheney won a major legal victory when a federal district judge threw out a suit brought by Congress's General Accounting Office to require him to release records of the Bush administration's energy task force.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Treasury Secretary Named  President Bush named John W. Snow as the next Treasury secretary. Mr. Snow quickly reached out to lawmakers as the administration prepares to send Congress new proposals to shore up the economy.</p>
        <p>A30</p>
        <p>Airport Screening Changes  The Transportation Security Administration will require most airline passengers to obtain boarding passes before they arrive at the security checkpoint, the goal is to free workers to screen checked bags rather than screen passengers.</p>
        <p>A24</p>
        <p>Lott Apologizes for Remarks  Trent Lott, the Senate Republican leader, apologized for his speech at the 100th birthday party of the retiring Senator Strom Thurmond, which critics said was an implicit endorsement of segregation.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>Shredded Documents at Issue  Congressional investigators are looking into the shredding and destruction of documents in the office of Janet Rehnquist, inspector general of the Department of Health and Human Services.</p>
        <p>A33</p>
        <p>Scholar Considered for Court  President Bush may name Douglas W. Kmiec, the dean of the law school at Catholic University and a prominent social conservative scholar, to a federal appeals court.</p>
        <p>A32</p>
        <p>New Policy on Failing Schools  The Department of Education said school districts that lacked space for children wishing to transfer out of failing public schools must forge agreements with other districts to accept those students.</p>
        <p>A26</p>
        <p>Corzine Gets Democratic Post  Senate Democrats put Senator Jon Corzine of New Jersey in charge of their effort to recapture the Senate in 2004.</p>
        <p>A28</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>Bloomberg Unveils Plan In Case of Transit Strike  Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg made clear that he expected ingenuity and an ample dose of neighborly kindness from each citizen to keep the city functioning if there is a transit strike. Under the mayor's plan, drivers would stop at specific zones to pick up strangers, the back seats of taxis would be shared, and the 108th mayor would pedal his way downtown on a 10-speed.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Luxury Shops Try New Tactics  It was a pitch that used to come only from stores trying to unload cheap sofas and stereo equipment. But these days, even a customer trying on a $10,000 sapphire ring at Tiffany's flagship store on Fifth Avenue is likely to hear it: ''No money down, zero interest for 90 days.''</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>A Record Share for Housing  The Bronx and Brooklyn emerged from the last decade with a dubious distinction: Analysts of recent census data say more homeowners in those two boroughs spend more income on housing than people anywhere else in the country.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases</p>
        <p>B5</p>
        <p>SCIENCE TIMES</p>
        <p>F1-8</p>
        <p>Health &amp; Fitness</p>
        <p>F5</p>
        <p>ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>Strong Sales for La Bohème  ''La Bohème,'' the Australian director Baz Luhrmann's hipster take on the Puccini opera, had strong sales at the box office after opening Sunday night to strong reviews. Producers of the show were expecting close to $1 million in ticket sales by day's end, a solid indication that an Italian-language opera can succeed on Broadway.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-7</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>C19</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-18</p>
        <p>United Files for Bankruptcy  United Airlines became one of the largest American companies ever to seek bankruptcy protection. With lenders pressuring it to cut costs, United said it would turn once again to its workers for deep concessions.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>New Rules for Pension Plans  President Bush is supporting new rules that will allow companies to save money by converting their pension plans to cash-balance plans. Critics say cash-balance plans strip benefits from older workers.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Dow Drops 2 Percent  In its sharpest decline in a month, the Dow Jones industrial average fell 172.36 points, or 2 percent. The Nasdaq composite index slid 55.3 points, or 3.9 percent.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Merck Seeks Settlement  Merck &amp; Company agreed to pay $42.5 million to settle long-running class action lawsuits against its pharmacy-benefit unit, but lawyers for the plaintiffs were split over whether to accept the agreement.</p>
        <p>C11</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A34-35</p>
        <p>Editorials: Two versions of John Snow; Iraq in the dock; when Nike speaks; Philip M. Boffey on smallpox.</p>
        <p>Columns: Paul Krugman, Nicholas D. Kristof.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E4  TV Listings</p>
        <p>E9  Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2  Weather</p>
        <p>D8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
