<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For New Media, an Old-Time Forum</title>
    <meta content="01DINN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19970502T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="926661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Guttenberg, Jonathan M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gjertsen, Janice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE2DD1131F932A35756C0A961958260" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For New Media, an Old-Time Forum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Jonathan M Guttenberg and Janice Gjertsen, on-line design experts, frequently hosting dinner discussions concerning Internet; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The invitation, as usual, came via electronic mail, 24 hours in advance: cocktails and dinner for a group of Internet experts at the Flatiron Diner and Baking Company on West 18th Street in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''In the spirit of the 1920's Algonquin Roundtables, I am inviting you to an evening of witty discussion and thoughtful social interaction,'' the message began.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The invitation, as usual, came via electronic mail, 24 hours in advance: cocktails and dinner for a group of Internet experts at the Flatiron Diner and Baking Company on West 18th Street in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''In the spirit of the 1920's Algonquin Roundtables, I am inviting you to an evening of witty discussion and thoughtful social interaction,'' the message began.</p>
        <p>''New media is rife with old and new metaphors fighting for preeminence,'' it went on, in prose that read slightly slower than 28,800 bits per second. ''Well, it's not the metaphors that are fighting, but rather people selling products and services fighting to lodge their vision of the Net in our heads.''</p>
        <p>It was not exactly the type of material usually associated with a culture that created cybercafes, chat rooms and interactive games. It was the agenda for another installment of a dinner series that has become, to some, the New York place to mull the mercurial new media industry.</p>
        <p>For a business that can sometimes be as impersonal as the America Online voice that blurts out, ''You've got mail,'' the dinners, usually held every few weeks in Silicon Alley in lower Manhattan, are a chance for people to meet and talk about ideas.</p>
        <p>''There are salons, and then there are salons,'' said Emily Davidow, president and founder of Digital Elements, an Internet design company in New York. ''This is for the heavy hitters; it's like the council of elders. There's this shared spirit of pioneering, because we're all in this together.''</p>
        <p>Leading the way are the dinner's regular hosts: Janice Gjertsen, 32, director of new business development at Digital City Studio, producers of the popular on-line guide Total New York, and Jonathan M. Guttenberg, 33, vice president of new media at Bantam Doubleday Dell.</p>
        <p>Ms. Gjertsen and Mr. Guttenberg started their dinners two years ago. Now, perhaps, no regular event has the cachet of these gatherings, sometimes referred to as ''The Janice and Jon Dinners.''</p>
        <p>In recent months, the dinners have featured topics such as community building, proprietary content, Java technology and ''push media'' -- a current hot idea that means content providers ''push'' information based on the user's preferences, such as providing information only on sports.</p>
        <p>''We're so used to dealing with the day-to-day,'' Ms. Gjertsen said. ''We need to pull back and talk at this level. But we can't just walk into the town square and bump into people. We need a method of communication, and the best way is in real-space interaction.''</p>
        <p>The metaphor of the Algonquin, which brought together such writers as Dorothy Parker and Robert Benchley, may be a bit of a stretch. But the guests say there is a palpable sense of fun and frontiersmanship.</p>
        <p>For each of the dinners, guests are expected to come prepared to discuss the evening's topic.</p>
        <p>At the recent dinner at the Flatiron Diner, a wood-paneled restaurant with bicycles and toasters nailed to the walls, the guests complained about losing styluses for the Pilot electronic organizer, the technological toy of the moment. Others joked about talented programmers from Russia, India and Israel.</p>
        <p>''So I heard that Netscape and Yahoo merged and they're moving to Israel,'' said Chan Suh, a principal at Agency.com, an Internet advertising agency. ''They're calling themselves Netanyahu.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gjertsen introduced the evening's moderator, Jerry Michalski, managing editor of Release 1.0, an on-line newsletter about high-tech issues. Then Mr. Michalski handed out something he called ''Janice's list,'' which outlined the details for the night's debate, with the questions: Which of the following metaphors best explains cyberspace to the average person? Traditional media with a twist? Interactive television, Web zines such as Slate? Physical space? File folders? Conceptual space? Virtual cities? Chat? Multiplayer games? Brands and advertising?</p>
        <p>''The metaphor I see here is the Internet as a self-sustaining ecosystem,'' offered Howard Greenstein, a co-founder of the World Wide Web Artists Consortium, who recently joined Microsoft. ''One reason that the ecosystem grew so well is that the animal used to be Delphi, and now that it's dead, we're feeding off its carcass.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenstein's comments about Delphi, an Internet venture by Rupert Murdoch that largely fizzled, brought laughs.</p>
        <p>''We can talk about what metaphors work and don't work, but we can't underestimate the users of this technology,'' said Michael Wolfson, a partner in Element Studios Inc., which creates content for the World Wide Web. ''At the end of the day, things survive because of natural selection. If you create something great, then it's going to succeed.''</p>
        <p>Such talk made some impatient.</p>
        <p>''Why are we trying to talk about ecosystems and carcasses?'' said Kyle Shannon, Mr. Suh's business partner at Agency.com. ''We should talk about Janice's list. What is the best method for people to figure out what we're excited about?''</p>
        <p>And so it went until the discussion faded at 11 P.M.; there were families to return home to and electronic mail messages to check.</p>
        <p>''I'll call you,'' Ms. Gjertsen said with a smile. ''No, wait. I'll E-mail you.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 2, 1997, Friday</p>
        <p>A picture caption yesterday about a dinner series for leaders in the new-media industry misidentified the man shown at the far left. He was Jerry Michalski, not Jonathan M. Guttenberg.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 2, 1997, Friday</p>
        <p>A picture caption yesterday about a dinner series for leaders in the new-media industry misidentified the man shown at the far left. He was Jerry Michalski, not Jonathan M. Guttenberg.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
