<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki Supports Rent Protection for Middle-Income Tenants</title>
    <meta content="01PATA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="926719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">D'Amato, Alfonse M (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rent Control and Stabilization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E0DF1E31F932A35756C0A961958260" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki Supports Rent Protection for Middle-Income Tenants</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <dateline>ALBANY, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Gov George Pataki says that he agrees with Senator Alfonse D'Amato that rent protections should be maintained for middle income tenants (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In another indication that he is seeking a middle ground in the fierce battle over state rent laws, Gov. George E. Pataki said today that he agreed with Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato that rent protections should be maintained for middle-income tenants, though both men have failed to explain just how they would do that.</p>
        <p>The Governor also said that he would consider it ''horrible and inappropriate'' if the laws were simply allowed to expire on June 16, which Mr. Pataki's fellow Republicans in the State Senate have vowed to let happen if Assembly Democrats do not accept major revisions to the rules. But the Governor, who says he wants to mediate a compromise between the two houses, would not elaborate on what he would do to prevent the laws from lapsing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In another indication that he is seeking a middle ground in the fierce battle over state rent laws, Gov. George E. Pataki said today that he agreed with Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato that rent protections should be maintained for middle-income tenants, though both men have failed to explain just how they would do that.</p>
        <p>The Governor also said that he would consider it ''horrible and inappropriate'' if the laws were simply allowed to expire on June 16, which Mr. Pataki's fellow Republicans in the State Senate have vowed to let happen if Assembly Democrats do not accept major revisions to the rules. But the Governor, who says he wants to mediate a compromise between the two houses, would not elaborate on what he would do to prevent the laws from lapsing.</p>
        <p>The Governor's remarks, like those of Mr. D'Amato earlier this week, seemed intended to distance him from the position of the Republican Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, who has called for abolishing most of the rent laws within the next few years.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Pataki said today that ''there are extreme positions on both sides of the issues,'' which seemed like a criticism not only of the Assembly Democrats, who have called for maintaining the rent regulation system unchanged, but also Mr. Bruno, who is his strongest ally in the Legislature.</p>
        <p>John McArdle, a spokesman for Mr. Bruno, a Republican from Rensselaer County, said the majority leader was not offended by Mr. Pataki's comments. ''A number of people have said it was extreme,'' Mr. McArdle said about Mr. Bruno's plan to phase out the system in two to four years. ''Senator Bruno's position is, 'I'm flexible, I'm reasonable.' But the Democrats have not been.''</p>
        <p>Earlier this week Mr. D'Amato, widely considered the state's most powerful Republican, staked out a significantly more moderate position on the rent rules than Mr. Bruno. Mr. D'Amato, who in the early 1980's called for abolishing the rent laws, said on Monday that he could support ending rent protections for wealthier tenants but would oppose lifting such protections from elderly, disabled or middle-income tenants.</p>
        <p>Mr. D'Amato also said he could support a process known as vacancy decontrol, under which tenants maintain rent protections for as long as they stay in their current apartments but landlords can raise rents to market levels when units are vacated. Under such a process, the entire system would eventually become decontrolled. But Mr. D'Amato said he would not want to see the laws phased out quickly, saying that even 10 years would be too fast.</p>
        <p>The laws limit rent increases on 1.2 million apartments, almost all of them in New York City, and establish rights and protections for tenants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki has been purposefully vague about his position on the laws, saying he will be better able to arbitrate a compromise if he does not say how the laws should be changed. But in the past he has said he supports vacancy decontrol, calling it a reasonable way of phasing out regulations. Like Mr. D'Amato, he has called for ending protections for the wealthy, while maintaining them for disabled, elderly and poor tenants. Today, he expanded that group to include middle-income people.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki also said he thought some changes were inevitable this year, suggesting that he would not be willing to accept a proposal offered by some Democrats to temporarily extend the current laws while setting up a commission to study ways of revising the rent system.</p>
        <p>Tenants groups said they were pleased that Mr. Pataki and Mr. D'Amato appeared to be moving away from Mr. Bruno's position. But they said they did not consider either man's position moderate, since both  advocate vacancy decontrol, a process that would eventually lead to the end of most or all rent protections.</p>
        <p>''They've tried to position it so it looks like a middle ground compromise,'' said Billy Easton, executive director of New York State Tenants and Neighbors Coalition, the state's largest tenant group, ''when it is in fact a total elimination of the rent laws, one that would provide an incentive to landlords to run tenants out of their homes so they could get a massive rent increase.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
