<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putin Will Use Ex-K.G.B. Men To Battle Graft</title>
    <meta content="24PUTI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1186324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Kgb (Soviet Security Police)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Michael R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Putin, Vladimir V (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koppel, Ted</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E0DC153DF937A15750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putin Will Use Ex-K.G.B. Men To Battle Graft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL R. GORDON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gordon, Michael R</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, March 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vladimir V Putin says that if he is elected president in March 26 election, he will use trusted group of former colleagues from KGB to tackle Russia's endemic corruption; in brief interview with Ted Koppel of ABC News program Nightline, Putin seeks to assure the West that his intelligence connections will be used to build a more fair and even-handed system (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If he is elected president on Sunday, as everyone expects he will be, Vladimir V. Putin says he will use a trusted group of former colleagues from the K.G.B. to tackle Russia's endemic corruption.</p>
        <p>''I am bringing into my inner-circle people from law enforcement bodies who are in no way connected with the people and structures which may be associated with any form of corruption,'' the acting president said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If he is elected president on Sunday, as everyone expects he will be, Vladimir V. Putin says he will use a trusted group of former colleagues from the K.G.B. to tackle Russia's endemic corruption.</p>
        <p>''I am bringing into my inner-circle people from law enforcement bodies who are in no way connected with the people and structures which may be associated with any form of corruption,'' the acting president said.</p>
        <p>A former officer of the K.G.B., the Soviet intelligence service, and later head of Russia's domestic intelligence service, Mr. Putin made a rapid ascent in the Kremlin, stirring concerns among Russians who fear he may try to roll back the nation's hard-won freedoms.</p>
        <p>But in a brief interview with Ted Koppel of the ABC News program ''Nightline,'' Mr. Putin sought to assure the West that his intelligence connections would be used to build a more fair and even-handed system. A transcript of the interview, which will be broadcast on Friday night, was made available to The New York Times.</p>
        <p>''Yes, I have brought some of them to the Kremlin,'' he said of his K.G.B. colleagues. ''I have known them for many years and I trust them. It has nothing to do with ideology. It's only a matter of their professional qualities and personal relationships.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin did not name the intelligence officials he plans to use in his ''inner circle.'' The F.S.B., the successor to the K.G.B., already includes a deputy director who owes his position to Mr. Putin and who has been criticized for persecuting dissidents under Soviet rule. And former intelligence officials run Russia's security council and serve as mid-level aides to Mr. Putin.</p>
        <p>Many top positions, however, are held by holdovers from the administration of Boris N. Yeltsin and officials with no background in intelligence. It remains to be seen how that mix may change when, as virtually everyone expects, Mr. Putin is elected.</p>
        <p>Filmed during his visit to Nizhny Novgorod, a picturesque city on Russia's Volga River, the brief interview was one of few the Russian leader has given to the Western press. The answers Mr. Putin provided appeared intended to dispel his image as a wily survivor who is determined to rebuild Russia's influence and might.</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin insisted that his recent flight to Grozny in the back seat of a SU-27 fighter was not a campaign stunt, designed to demonstrate his support for a reinvigorated military. It was, he said, simply the cheapest, fastest and safest way to travel.</p>
        <p>''Frankly speaking,'' he said, straightfaced, ''the last thing I think about is symbols.''</p>
        <p>Rampant corruption has been a monumental problem for Russia and there have been allegations that it reached into the higher echelons of the government when Mr. Yeltsin was in power. Mr. Putin has taken few steps as prime minister or acting president to combat it.</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Putin cast corruption as little more than a passing phase for a nation still trying to  extract itself from the ruins of the Soviet Union. And he all but pledged to banish bribery and make Russia safe for foreign investors after he is handed the reins of power.</p>
        <p>''During the period of transitional economy the government often fails to guarantee equal opportunities for all participants of the market,'' he acknowledged somberly. ''There are those who take advantage of their proximity to political, governmental and regional leaders.''</p>
        <p>Describing what actions his government might take, Mr. Putin couched them in the context of strengthening the role of the state: ''First, we will focus on guaranteeing the full rights of owners and investors,'' he said. ''The right of ownership must become a priority in Russia. We will strive to make the position of the state crystal clear in its legislation. We will need to make the state strong enough to guarantee implementation of these rights.''</p>
        <p>''And finally, '' he added, ''we will do our best to ensure equal opportunity for all the participants of the market.''</p>
        <p>I hope that if these fundamental principles are observed,'' he told Mr. Koppel, ''we will not have to bring up the issue of corruption in Russia the next time we meet.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Putin's remarks about the K.G.B. and its successors appeared intended to counter the dark connotations the intelligence agency still has in the West.</p>
        <p>Speaking to an American audience, however, Mr. Putin seemed to be at pains to portray himself as an enlightened former intelligence official who was committed to streamlining government and fighting corruption, not rolling back the clock on human rights.</p>
        <p>When asked by Mr. Koppel about a comment he reportedly made at a gathering of intelligence officers to the effect that they had ''succeeded in our first effort to infiltrate the Kremlin,'' Mr. Putin replied:</p>
        <p>''Of course it was a joke -- though I have to say that a gathering of employees of intelligence agencies and former leaders of those agencies is not unusual, even in the West.''</p>
        <p>In speaking to Russian interviewers, he has boasted that he approached the K.G.B. as a schoolboy in the hope of beginning a career as a spy. He fulfilled his dream in 1975 when he was recruited into the K.G.B., where he reached the rank of lieutenant colonel before resigning. Mr. Putin was named to head the F.S.B., domestic successor to the K.G.B, in 1998.</p>
        <p>As the interview approached the eight-minute mark, an aide appeared to signal the acting president that he had given the American interviewers enough.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
