<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rescuers Are Called Target Of 2d Explosion in Atlanta</title>
    <meta content="18BLAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="902402"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Bomb Plots</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlanta (Ga)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Abortion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E6D8143BF93BA25752C0A961958260" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rescuers Are Called Target Of 2d Explosion in Atlanta</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA, Jan. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Investigators say second blast at site of abortion clinic near Atlanta, Ga, was aimed at rescue workers and law-enforcement officers who responded to first explosion, one hour earlier; experts on terrorism note that two bombs, placed in same general area and strategically timed to hurt rescuers and law-enforcement people, are common tactic of terrorists overseas; second bomb went off between trash bin and police cars that had recently been parked there; investigators feel cars absorbed blast and saved lives of people standing nearby; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although evidence and common sense point to an abortion clinic as the target of the first bomb blast at a suburban Atlanta office complex on Thursday, there is little doubt among investigators that a second blast, an hour later and 100 feet away, was aimed at rescue workers and law-enforcement officers who responded to the first explosion.</p>
        <p>Two cars parked near the location of the second bomb, beside a large trash bin at one corner of the adjoining parking lot, absorbed much of the force of that second explosion and shielded the people in the crowded parking lot -- including police officers, firefighters, reporters and agents from the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms -- from greater harm.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although evidence and common sense point to an abortion clinic as the target of the first bomb blast at a suburban Atlanta office complex on Thursday, there is little doubt among investigators that a second blast, an hour later and 100 feet away, was aimed at rescue workers and law-enforcement officers who responded to the first explosion.</p>
        <p>Two cars parked near the location of the second bomb, beside a large trash bin at one corner of the adjoining parking lot, absorbed much of the force of that second explosion and shielded the people in the crowded parking lot -- including police officers, firefighters, reporters and agents from the Federal Bureau of Investigation and the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms -- from greater harm.</p>
        <p>''These were two very powerful bombs,'' said Kent B. Alexander, the United States Attorney here. ''To me, the most remarkable thing about this case so far is no one was killed.''</p>
        <p>Six people were hurt in that second blast outside the Sandy Springs Professional Building north of Atlanta, but no one was seriously injured and only one -- an F.B.I. agent who received a bruise at the base of his brain -- was still hospitalized on Friday.</p>
        <p>But at least one person, standing near the site of the second bomb, might have died if the cars -- including one belonging to the Fulton County police department -- had not been parked there, beside the bin, investigators said. The bomb went off between the bin and the cars, knocking several people to the ground and cutting at least two people with flying shrapnel.</p>
        <p>''It was sheer fortuity,'' Mr. Alexander said of one car, which had been moved from another parking space and placed, by pure chance, in the path of the blast, apparently just minutes before. ''But for that car absorbing this blast, I think people would have died.''</p>
        <p>Investigators today combed the area around the blast site, finding pieces of shrapnel blocks away and some metal pieces of the roof of a seven-story office building nearby.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander, acting as a spokesman for the combined agencies, said investigators would be cautious about releasing information about the makeup of the bomb and other details in the inquiry because it might hinder prosecution.</p>
        <p>No one has taken responsibility for the attack, which is unusual in abortion clinic bombings. Mr. Alexander said investigators have received ''a myriad of leads, much of what you'd expect, ranging from anti-abortion to militia.''</p>
        <p>''So far,'' he said, ''we've received over 200 calls. From those calls, a number of good leads are developing.''</p>
        <p>He said investigators are not assuming that the clinic was the target of the first blast at the office building, which also houses dentists, lawyers and other professionals.</p>
        <p>The first bomb exploded without warning at 9:30 A.M., just outside the the first-floor Atlanta Northside Family Planning Services clinic, where abortions, among other services, are provided. The blast wrecked the operating room and waiting room, and gouged out a section of the outside wall.</p>
        <p>Then, as investigators and television news crews filled the parking lot, the second blast sent them running. Apparently no one checked the area beside the trash bin.</p>
        <p>''If we were expecting a second bomb, we wouldn't have been there,'' said Louis Graham, the Fulton County Police Chief. Like others, he said he believed the second bomb was intended for investigators.</p>
        <p>''It tells me that they really are not all that concerned with innocent victims,'' said J. Angelo Corlett, an assistant professor of philosophy at Georgia State University and an expert on political terrorism, referring to the bombers.</p>
        <p>No patients were scheduled at the clinic that day. Only two people were inside; neither was hurt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander and other investigators said there was no reason to think there was a second bomb nearby, which explains why the parking area was filled with people.</p>
        <p>But two bombs, placed in the same general area and strategically timed to hurt rescuers and law-enforcement people, are a common tactic of terrorists overseas, experts on terrorism say.</p>
        <p>Anti-terrorist groups call them ''sucker bombs.'' The bomber draws a crowd with one device, purely to detonate a second, often more powerful device in their midst. That was apparently the plan of the bomber at the office complex, no matter whether the bomb was aimed at the abortion clinic, Federal agents or someone else, the experts said.</p>
        <p>As bombings go, this one seemed particularly cold-blooded, investigators said.</p>
        <p>''They aren't taking credit for it,'' said Mr. Corlett, the professor at Georgia State. ''They are not explaining why it happened. There was no forewarning, so no one knows how many innocent people could have been harmed by that.</p>
        <p>''I think they would say that none of these people in America, none of these people who aren't in our group, is innocent.''</p>
        <p>Such bombs also leave a more vivid image, he said. ''You not only see the destruction after the fact'' of a first bomb, ''but in a few seconds you experience it, if the cameras actually catch it as they did yesterday,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Alexander said investigators would know soon whether this bomb was similar in makeup to the one used in the still unsolved bombing in Centennial Olympic Park last summer.</p>
        <p>Because of that blast, people in Atlanta were particularly sensitive to this attack. Some employees in and around the building said they were frightened to go back to work. And Mayor Bill Campbell asked police officials to send officers to guard Atlanta abortion clinics.</p>
        <p>The Feminist Majority Foundation reported on Thursday that a survey of 312 clinics around the country showed that 30 percent reported acts of violence last year, a decrease from 39 percent in 1995.</p>
        <p>But while the numbers of incidents has slightly declined, the degree of violence has not, said Eleanor Smeal, the foundation's president.</p>
        <p>''I have noticed a general trend of escalation'' in anti-abortion commentary, she said, that has turned into tragic fact. ''The first shooting of a doctor was just of the doctor. Then they said if you are assisting the doctor, then you are a problem, too. The next time, they shot the doctor and his escort. Then they started talking about a war zone. Anybody in the war zone could be shot,'' she said, ''and anybody protecting the war zone.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
