<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conoco Is Said to Be Close To Buying Texas Gas Field</title>
    <meta content="18GAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="902380"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Transtexas Gas Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Conoco Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salpukas, Agis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DB143BF93BA25752C0A961958260" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conoco Is Said to Be Close To Buying Texas Gas Field</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AGIS SALPUKAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salpukas, Agis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>TransTexas Gas Corp, major natural gas producer, reportedly will sell Lobo Trend field to Conoco Inc for about $1.2 billion (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The TransTexas Gas Corporation, a major natural gas producer, is close to an agreement to sell one of its largest and most productive natural gas fields to Conoco Inc. for about $1.2 billion, people close to the transaction said yesterday.</p>
        <p>A purchase by Conoco would be  unusual because it and other major oil companies have been selling some of their large domestic oil and gas fields in recent years as they shift their investment and exploration efforts overeas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The TransTexas Gas Corporation, a major natural gas producer, is close to an agreement to sell one of its largest and most productive natural gas fields to Conoco Inc. for about $1.2 billion, people close to the transaction said yesterday.</p>
        <p>A purchase by Conoco would be  unusual because it and other major oil companies have been selling some of their large domestic oil and gas fields in recent years as they shift their investment and exploration efforts overeas.</p>
        <p>But with natural gas prices on the rise this winter because of high demand, properties in the United States have become attractive to big oil companies, which are cash rich. Some analysts said they expected more such transactions.</p>
        <p>Conoco, a subsidiary of E. I. du Pont de Nemours, is based in Houston and operates in about 30 countries.</p>
        <p>TransTexas Gas, which is also based in Houston and which has made some major domestic discoveries of natural gas and oil in the last two years, hired investment bankers last August to help find buyers for its Lobo Trend natural gas field, which has long been its prime producing field.</p>
        <p>The company has had great success in drilling there, with one out of five wells turning out to be productive. That field now has 800 producing wells and an 1,100-mile pipeline system that connects with other major systems.</p>
        <p>''It is very profitable and still largely undeveloped,'' said Adam Leight, an analyst with Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette who has followed TransTexas closely.</p>
        <p>He said that because of its size and with much drilling left to do, only major oil companies had the financial strength to bid for the field.</p>
        <p>''It's one of the last concentrations of reserves left in one place to attract a major,'' he said. He added that Conoco was already producing natural gas in the area and thus it would be able to keep its costs down.</p>
        <p>Simon Ward, who is in charge of investor relations at TransTexas Gas, said the company would have no comment on whether it had reached an agreement to sell the field.</p>
        <p>Carleton Adams, a public affairs spokesman for Conoco, said that ''we just don't talk about any of our worldwide negotiations on our business opportunities until we have something substantive to report.''</p>
        <p>But industry sources said the agreement was expected to be announced in the next few days.</p>
        <p>TransTexas Gas said it would use the proceeds to reduce some of its  $800 million in secured debt and to finance the development of its Bob West field, which was discovered two years ago in Texas. That field now produces close to 300 million cubic feet of gas a day.</p>
        <p>As the new field was developed, the company's dependence on the Lobo Trend field was greatly reduced. TransTexas has also drilled several promising oil wells in North Dakota.</p>
        <p>The company closed yesterday at $16.25, up 50 cents, in Nasdaq trading.</p>
        <p>According to TransTexas, the Lobo Trend field had an average production of about 280 million cubic feet a day in 1995 and had proven reserves of close to 800 billion cubic feet.</p>
        <p>''There is a lot left to do,'' Mr. Leight, the analyst, said. ''It's a known producing basin. It's not rocket science.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
