<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. to Weigh Iraqi War Crimes Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="393624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="MIDEAST TENSION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAR CRIMES AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JERUSALEM</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDF1739F932A15753C1A966958260" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. to Weigh Iraqi War Crimes Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PAUL</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Oct. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The United States has agreed with the four other permanent members of the Security Council to support a resolution calling for the collection of evidence that war crimes have been committed by Iraqi occupation forces in Kuwait.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The United States has agreed with the four other permanent members of the Security Council to support a resolution calling for the collection of evidence that war crimes have been committed by Iraqi occupation forces in Kuwait.</p>
        <p>The United States has agreed with the four other permanent members of the Security Council to support a resolution calling for the collection of evidence that war crimes have been committed by Iraqi occupation forces in Kuwait.</p>
        <p>The resolution, intended to criticize and embarrass President Saddam Hussein of Iraq, also calls for an international list of claims for financial damages resulting from his invasion, diplomats say.</p>
        <p>The plan, set out in a draft Security Council resolution that the Council's five permanent members have now all accepted, is seen by Washington as a way of shifting world attention away from the quarrel over Israel that has errupted at the United Nations and refocusing it on the task of ousting Iraq's forces from occupied Kuwait. The full 15-nation Council is expected to approve the resolution late next week.</p>
        <p>But before it considers this new plan, the Bush Administration must decide on Monday whether to veto another resolution assailing Israel for not cooperating with the Council's efforts to investigate the shootings by Israeli policemen in Jerusalem on Oct. 8, which killed 21 Palestinians.</p>
        <p>This resolution, introduced by the Council's Arab and nonaligned members Friday, also instructs the Secretary General of the United Nations to press ahead with a report on the killings even though Israel has said it will not receive his investigators.</p>
        <p>Further Tension With Israel</p>
        <p>This report on the Jerusalem shooting promises to create further tension between the Security Council and Israel because it may also contain practical proposals for safeguarding Palestinians in the occupied territories against further violence by the Israeli security forces.</p>
        <p>Although this requirement is set out only in a nonbinding statement by the Council's President and not in the binding resolution calling for the report, it is still supported by a majority of Council members.</p>
        <p>But Israel considers Jerusalem as its capital and regards the investigation as an infringement of its sovereignty. Its Cabinet has said the Government will not cooperate with any United Nations investigators. Israel has said the United Nations may have the report of Israel's own investigation of the shootings and of the stoning by Palestinians of Jews praying at the Western Wall at the time of the clash.</p>
        <p>The United States, supported by Britain, wants to turn the United Nations spotlight away from the occupied territories and back onto Iraq and the Persian Gulf crisis, but without encouraging the Arabs to press for similar sanctions against Israel.</p>
        <p>The new anti-Iraq draft resolution, which has been accepted by the United States as well as the Council's other permanent members - Britain, France, the Soviet Union and China -for the first time ''invites states to collate information from any source of grave breaches of the Fourth Geneva Convention and to make this available to the Council.''</p>
        <p>This convention, drawn up in 1949 and accepted by Iraq, defines the rights of civilians caught in war, prohibiting their summary execution, torture or deportation as well as the taking of hostages and any discriminatory or humiliating treatment.</p>
        <p>Liability to Compensation</p>
        <p>The new draft resolution also ''affirms the liability of Iraq to make full restitution or compensation for any loss, damage or injury arising in regard to Kuwait and third states, and their nationals and corporations, as a result of the illicit invasion and occupation of Kuwait by Iraq.''</p>
        <p>It then ''invites states to collect all relevant information regarding their claims, and those of their nationals and corporations, with a view to such arrangements for the discharge by Iraq of its liability to make restitution or compensation as may be established.''</p>
        <p>But the proposed resolution does not go as far as Britain originally wanted, avoiding any specific commitment to earmark Iraq's frozen overseas assets for compensation payments or create a war crimes tribunal.</p>
        <p>This is because the Bush Administration fears that if it asks the Council to approve new punitive action against Iraq at the moment, Arab nations will press for similar moves against Israel in retaliation for its occupation of the West Bank and other Arab lands.</p>
        <p>Plight of Those Trapped</p>
        <p>Instead, the new resolution stresses the plight of Kuwaitis and foreigners trapped in Kuwait as well as of diplomats still in their embassies there.</p>
        <p>It ''demands that Iraq immediately cease and desist from deporting Kuwaiti nationals, taking third-state nationals hostage, murdering, mistreating and oppressing Kuwaiti and third state nationals, destroying Kuwaiti demographic records, settling foreigners in Kuwait, confiscating hospital supplies and equipment and carrying out unlawful and wonton destruction of public and private property.''</p>
        <p>The resolution also demands that Iraq provide food, water and basic necessities to the foreigners it is holding hostage as well as to the foreign embassies still functioning in Kuwait. And it warns that if Iraq refuses to comply, ''the Council will take futher enforcement measures under the Charter.''  MIDEAST TENSION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
