<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The World;   Arabs Ponder Ways To Fix Arab Problems</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="393716"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, JUDITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GHALI, BOUTROS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D81339F932A15753C1A966958260" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The World;   Arabs Ponder Ways To Fix Arab Problems</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDITH MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MILLER, JUDITH</byline>
      <dateline>AMMAN, Jordan</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: While most of the world is trying just to muddle through the crisis in the Persian Gulf, a few Arab thinkers - some would say dreamers - have begun drafting proposals to meet the widespread yearning of poorer Arabs in this undemocratic and inegalitarian region for greater democracy and a more equitable distribution of wealth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: While most of the world is trying just to muddle through the crisis in the Persian Gulf, a few Arab thinkers - some would say dreamers - have begun drafting proposals to meet the widespread yearning of poorer Arabs in this undemocratic and inegalitarian region for greater democracy and a more equitable distribution of wealth.</p>
        <p>While most of the world is trying just to muddle through the crisis in the Persian Gulf, a few Arab thinkers - some would say dreamers - have begun drafting proposals to meet the widespread yearning of poorer Arabs in this undemocratic and inegalitarian region for greater democracy and a more equitable distribution of wealth.</p>
        <p>''I think that in the wake of this great crisis, this great shock to the region, there will be a sense of humiliation among the Arabs,'' said Boutros Ghali, the Egyptian Minister of State for Foreign Affairs. ''So a consensus is growing that we will have to present some new ideas to help restore the Arab image and reignite a sense of confidence in the region and its future.''</p>
        <p>In capitals whose governments have adopted radically different approaches toward getting Iraq out of Kuwait, specific and remarkably similar proposals are being crafted. Mr. Ghali, for example, has suggested the creation of an Arab parliament and an Arab ''petrobank,'' ideas he said he discussed with Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d during a visit to the United States two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ghali asserts that a pan-Arab parliament - perhaps under the aegis of the 21-member Arab League - would be less threatening than domestic parliaments, a concept anathema to conservative gulf monarchies. A pan-Arab forum would give these states experience in a democratic institution, and might diminish suspicion of parliaments in their own states, he said.</p>
        <p>But only a few Arab countries have functioning parliaments, almost none in the Western sense. While Egypt and Jordan have parliaments, power resides primarily with President Hosni Mubarak in Egypt and with King Hussein and his court.</p>
        <p>Ahmed Khatib, who helped lead the democratization movement in Kuwait before Iraq's invasion, noted that pressure from Saudi Arabia and other gulf states helped prompt the ruling al-Sabah family in Kuwait to dissolve its own obstreperous parliament in 1986. He said the gulf states were not likely to approve of an experiment in parliamentary democracy anytime soon.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the meeting of Arab League foreign ministers in Tunis last week reflected the disarray in the most enduring Arab organization, which was created in 1945 to enhance cooperation and unity. The session, called to discuss Israel's bloody suppression of Palestinian rioting in Jerusalem, nearly collapsed when a dispute over the wording of a resolution condemning Israel, but not the United States, led half of the delegates to walk out for several hours.</p>
        <p>''The Arab League is in shambles,'' said a senior Arab foreign minister. Given the turmoil in this oldest of Arab cooperation groups, it was not likely that the states would agree to a new pan-Arab assembly.</p>
        <p>Yet the allure of such a forum remains. The re-establishment of a real parliament was discussed last weekend by some 700 Kuwaitis in Jidda, Saudi Arabia. And the need to restore Kuwait's quirky version of democracy was conceded in principle by Crown Prince Sheik Saad al-Abdullah al-Sabah, who pledged unspecified democratic reforms once the government is restored. Moreover, Jordanian officials credit their parliament, first freely elected last year and dominated by Islamic fundamentalists, with helping to defuse political tensions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ghali's suggestion that the Arabs establish a regional ''petrobank'' has had far greater Arab resonance, particularly among representatives of poor, non-oil producing states like Jordan. In an interview last week, King Hussein called for such a development fund ''to bridge the gap between haves and have nots'' in this region, where, the World Bank says, annual per capita income figures ranged in 1988 from $15,770 in the United Arab Emirates to $480 in Mauritania and the Sudan. ''We need such an institution,'' the King said, ''so that a million Sudanese will not die of hunger this year while millions are being wasted.''</p>
        <p>The King's younger brother, Crown Prince Hassan, proposed several years ago what he called an oil stabilization and development fund consistent with the spirit of Mr. Ghali's petrobank proposal. Under Crown Prince Hassan's proposal, Arab oil states would put a designated percentage of oil revenues over a specified price per barrel into a joint fund. If the market price dipped below that level, the money would be used to compensate for the revenue losses. But if the market went above the marker, excess revenues would go to development projects in poorer Arab countries.</p>
        <p>King Hussein knows first-hand the risks of the current system of distribution of oil wealth - based on the whim of fellow Arabs. Between 1978 and 1988, the Arab states pledged billions to Jordan. Qatar and Abu Dhabi stopped making payments in 1983, Algeria made only one payment, and Libya never paid at all, aides to the King said. By 1988, Jordan's $6 billion deficit - equal to the money pledged and spent but never paid - was jeopardizing the country's economic stability, so the King appealed to Sheik Jaber al-Ahmed al-Sabah, the Emir of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>The Emir was unsympathethic. ''His answer to me was: 'It's your fault. You're not a gulf state. You're not an oil-producing state,' '' King Hussein recounted. '' 'Why do you have these ambitious development plans, the universities and all that? You can't afford them.' ''</p>
        <p>Jordan, the Sudan, and other poor Arab states have grown increasingly resentful of these humiliating appeals for handouts from fellow Arab ''oilogarchies,'' as one Jordanian called the oil-producing nations. While Kuwaiti officials have expressed an interest in an Arab petrobank, gulf states that have not been invaded have been silent, and few are likely to endorse the concept.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ghali says the mood has shifted. ''Everyone in the Arab world in the wake of this crisis now understands that things must change.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
