<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NCNB Grows (but Profits Don't)</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="458404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PROFITS (INDUSTRY-WIDE)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NCNB CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCOLL, HUGH L JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DC1739F93AA35754C0A967958260" item-length="1484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NCNB Grows (but Profits Don't)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS C. HAYES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, July 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The NCNB Corporation's Hugh L. McColl Jr., hailed as a savvy regional banker who is reshaping the industry, has an impressive track record at invading and succeeding in new markets, but his record at generating profits in some of these conquests has been unimpressive lately.</p>
        <p>The McColl formula is to buy banks, convert them to NCNB's aggressive sell-sell-sell sales culture and get the troops out there scrambling for market share. Along the way, profits can take a back seat for a while.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The NCNB Corporation's Hugh L. McColl Jr., hailed as a savvy regional banker who is reshaping the industry, has an impressive track record at invading and succeeding in new markets, but his record at generating profits in some of these conquests has been unimpressive lately.</p>
        <p>The McColl formula is to buy banks, convert them to NCNB's aggressive sell-sell-sell sales culture and get the troops out there scrambling for market share. Along the way, profits can take a back seat for a while.</p>
        <p>"Hugh McColl has proven that he's willing to sacrifice profitability for market share," said Alen R. Smith, president of Allen C. Ewing &amp; Company, a brokerage in Tampa, Fla., that specializes in Southeastern banks. "But he wouldn't tolerate nonprofitability for a long time."</p>
        <p>Aggressive selling and price cutting sometimes lead to bad loans. And bad loans eat into profits quickly. Last year, after two years of record profits, NCNB's earnings slipped for the first time since 1987, falling 18.2 percent, to $365.7 million. This year profits are still lagging, having fallen by 8.3 percent in the first quarter, to $128.4 million.</p>
        <p>The problem is rising loan troubles in the two states where NCNB has operated for several years: Florida, where it was the first out-of-state bank to invade, in 1982, and in NCNB's home state of North Carolina.</p>
        <p>By being an aggressive real estate lender in Florida, where it is now the third-largest bank, NCNB tried to gain ground on bigger rivals by offering easier credit terms. But recession and a real estate glut last year exposed the risks of such liberal lending policies.</p>
        <p>Bad loans in Florida rose to a profit-draining 5.4 percent of NCNB's loans in the state at the end of March and caused a loss of $8.1 million in the unit last year. This year, the Florida division bounced back with a profit of $19 million in the first quarter, according to reports filed by Federal regulators. NCNB does not publicly report results of its banking operations by individual states.</p>
        <p>In North Carolina, the loan portfolio has also taken its lumps. While Charlotte-based NCNB holds a bigger share of total deposits than its rivals, the Wachovia Corporation and the First Union Corporation, Mr. McColl, NCNB's chairman and chief executive, nearly doubled the loan-loss reserve for NCNB in the 12 months ended in March, to $309 million, because of growing problem loans. As a result, profits slumped at the North Carolina bank to $25.9 million in the first quarter, from $32 million a year ago.</p>
        <p>Lately, according to Salomon Brothers, NCNB's profitability as measured by bankers and analysts slipped below the average for major regional banks last year, after NCNB had outpaced the group through the late 1980's.  Brighter Future Seen</p>
        <p>Kenneth D. Lewis, president of all non-corporate banking activities at NCNB, acknowledged in an interview today that NCNB's aggressive steps had pared its profitability compared with that of some rivals, but added that the benefits of the strategy would soon be apparent.</p>
        <p>"When things settle down sometime during this decade, we're going to show that we can grind it out with the best of them," he said. "This is not a sprint, it's a marathon. Given all the things we've done, the record is rather remarkable."</p>
        <p>Robert B. Albertson, senior banking analyst at Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, thinks NCNB has made the right moves. He said that while Mr. McColl is best known for leading NCNB's expansion beyond the Carolina borders, the 56-year-old former marine has assembled an organization that has proved masterful in wringing costs from merged banks. "That to me is the new wave of banking, not new products," Mr. Albertson said.</p>
        <p>The company's bright spot has been its celebrated entrance in Texas in 1988, where it took over 40 failed banks of the First Republicbank Corporation with billions of dollars in Federal assistance. The prospering Texas unit, with half of NCNB's total assets of $66 billion, has been shielded from major losses so far by Mr. McColl's 1988 deal with Federal regulators.</p>
        <p>NCNB requested and received a key ruling from the Internal Revenue Service that would allow losses piled up at the failed First Republicbank to provide a huge tax shelter for NCNB. The practical effect has been to reduce NCNB's taxes and increase profitability, giving it an invaluable edge over rivals that often find it difficult to match NCNB's terms for pricing new loans and other business. Last year, NCNB paid an unusually low tax rate of 16 percent on its income compared with an average of 34 percent for most banks.</p>
        <p>Thomas H. Hanley, banking analyst at Salomon Brothers, estimated that NCNB would pay little tax on its Texas profits through 1994 because of the more than $500 million it retains in unused tax benefits obtained from First Republicbank.</p>
        <p>NCNB also has an unusually small portfolio of bad loans in Texas, thanks to an arrangement with Federal bank regulators that allowed NCNB to dump $8 billion in bad loans inherited from the First Republicbank into a separate "bad assets" unit that it manages at a profit for the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation.  Merger Under Study</p>
        <p>Platoons of loan examiners from the C&amp;S/Sovran Corporation will have to weigh all this as they examine NCNB's books to determine whether a combination of the two Southeastern banking companies will be profitable for them. One question is whether banking troubles in Florida and North Carolina will worsen this year or are about to abate, as NCNB executives maintain and many Wall Street analysts believe.</p>
        <p>A gloomy report would give directors of C&amp;S/Sovran one of the few practical reasons for rejecting NCNB's merger bid. C&amp;S/Sovran, weakened by real estate loan troubles in the Washington area, would become part of a super-regional powerhouse in the Southeast and Texas by casting its lot with NCNB. Together, the bank, which Mr. McColl wants to rename Nationsbank, would be the second largest in the United States, with $116 billion in assets, behind Citicorp, which has $216 billion in assets.</p>
        <p>Nationsbank would also be the dominant lender in North Carolina, Georgia, Virginia and Texas, and a major force in Florida.</p>
        <p>But C&amp;S/Sovran stockholders have been down the aisle before with not too pleasant memories. They saw the value of their shares plunge this spring after the merger of the Citizens &amp; Southern Corporation, Georgia's biggest bank, and the Sovran Financial Corporation of Norfolk, Va. Executives at C&amp;S/Sovran have cautioned that bad loans will continue to mount, and that a dividend cut is possible when C&amp;S/Sovran's board meets on July 16.</p>
        <p>Thus C&amp;S/Sovran shareholders, including company directors, risk a falling market value again if NCNB's earnings tumble following a marriage of the two banking companies. Mr. McColl's initial terms apparently call for C&amp;S/Sovran stockholders collectively to own 47 percent of NCNB following an exchange of three-fourths of a share in NCNB for each share of C&amp;S/Sovran. Analysts say Mr. McColl might sweeten the deal to just under 50 percent of NCNB total shares.  Rise in Earnings Expected</p>
        <p>Most analysts doubt that NCNB will stumble in its effort to contain the loan troubles in Florida and North Carolina. "We believe the asset-quality deterioration will slow considerably in 1991," said Mr. Albertson of Goldman, Sachs. He added that a slowdown in problem loans should result in smaller increases in loss reserves and higher profits. Mr. Hanley of Salomon Brothers estimated that NCNB's earnings would rise by more than 13 percent next year.</p>
        <p>NCNB established a troubled-asset division in the Southeast modeled after its Texas "bad assets" unit and stepped up its classifications of bad loans in the third quarter last year. Non-performing loans over all rose by 3 percent in the first quarter, to $759 million, the lowest percentage increase in five quarters.</p>
        <p>But Charles W. Peabody, a bank analyst at Kidder, Peabody &amp; Company in New York, is one critic of NCNB who believes that problem loans will rise in the second half of the year, and fester longer than the troubles at C&amp;S/Sovran.</p>
        <p>"Right now, C&amp;S/Sovran is viewed as being more risky than NCNB" by investors, he said. "But that's the fickleness of the market. In the second half of this year, people will change their view of NCNB. There are still fundamental problems in their loan portfolio."</p>
        <p>He said banks that compete with NCNB in the Southeast, like Suntrust, C&amp;S/Sovran and First Union, have reported bigger increases than NCNB in bad construction loans this year, which Mr. Peabody said raised the question in his mind of whether NCNB had been slow in recognizing similar problems.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lewis of NCNB would not rule out any increase in nonperforming loans later this year. But for now, he said, "the rate of increase in nonperformers has dramatically declined."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
