<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COLLEGE HOCKEY REPORT</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="839670"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E6DC1539F93BA15750C0A960958260" item-length="924" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COLLEGE HOCKEY REPORT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vermont</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vermont</p>
        <p>All eyes will be on Tim Thomas, the Vermont goalie, when the National Collegiate Athletic Association's tournament starts today in Cincinnati. The Catamounts (27-6-4) play Colorado College (32-4-4) in a semifinal match. The Tigers are regarded by many as the most formidable team in the Final Four because of their scoring depth.</p>
        <p>Vermont's four lines lack that scoring potential. So the emphasis will be on Thomas to hold off the Tigers while Vermont waits for a goal from either Eric Perrin or Martin St. Louis, the two talented and speedy Catamount forwards.</p>
        <p>Thomas, a junior from Davison, Mich., whose draft rights belong to the Colorado Avalanche, had a save percentage this season of .923, best among all Division I goalies.</p>
        <p>Perrin and St. Louis, each 5 feet 9 inches and 165 pounds and linemates since midget days at home in Laval, Quebec, have scored 56 of Vermont's 146 goals this season, 28 apiece, and 9 of the 19 in five playoff games. They, and their 6-4, 210-pound center, John Christian Ruid, complement one another well.</p>
        <p>"And we have six defensemen who can play," Coach Mike Gilligan said. "With Tim, we are a decent defensive team. I just hope we can keep up with Colorado College."</p>
        <p>Colorado College</p>
        <p>The Tigers, from a college with an enrollment of 1,850, have been the best team in the Western Association for the past three years. They were passed over  for the N.C.A.A. tournament two years ago and eliminated by Minnesota in the West Regional last year.</p>
        <p>"That left a sour taste," Coach Don Lucia said. "But we've gotten over it. We've been consistent."</p>
        <p>They were voted No. 1 in the nation in the five polls throughout the season and their four losses -- none at home -- were all by one goal. Eight of their players were named to all-WCHA teams and nine have scored 10 or more goals. The  big gun is Peter Geronazzo, who scored 66 points. The goaltender, Judd Lambert,  had the best goals against average, 2.15, in Division I.</p>
        <p>Boston University</p>
        <p>When the Terriers get going, they fly. But they are not always flying. "We have to stay focused," Coach Jack Parker said, "keep our poise."</p>
        <p>B.U. (30-6-3), the defending champion, led Division I in scoring average, 6.17 goals a game. Michigan was second, 5.68; Colorado College third at 5.49, and Vermont tied for 20th, 3.91.</p>
        <p>The Terriers' semifinal opponent will be Michigan (32-7-2), the Central Association champion. "They can play at both ends of the rink," Parker said. "They have so many offensive weapons, and nobody gets to the goal too often."</p>
        <p>B.U. has two potent scorers in Jay Pandolfo and Chris Drury, who make up the  first line along with 240-pound Mike Grier. Tom Noble has done well in goal although Parker said of the Final Four competition, "We've got to be better defensively."</p>
        <p>Michigan</p>
        <p>Brendan Morrison is the first-line center and scoring leader, with Jason Botterill and Bill Muckalt on the wings. They have scored 84 of the team's 232 goals. Marty Turco has done all of the goaltending and has a .894 save percentage.</p>
        <p>Coach Red Berenson said: "I like our chemistry: defense, offense, goaltending and special teams. Like the others, we were a little bit fortunate and a little  bit deserving."</p>
        <p>A lesser player in the spotlight will be Mike Legg, who scored an unusual goal in the quarterfinal victory over Minnesota. Legg, standing behind the Minnesota net, picked up the puck on his stick, then twirled it like a lacrosse  stick. The puck stuck. Then he whirled around the net and shot it into the Gopher goal, like a lacrosse shot.</p>
        <p>This was a trick he had picked up in practice, but had never tried in a game. Hockey purists were startled and some predict the rules committee will outlaw such a shot. The puck is supposed to stay closer to the ice.</p>
        <p>Slap Shots</p>
        <p>Six of the 10 finalists for the Hobey Baker award will be skating at Cincinnati -- Eric Perrin and Martin St. Louis of Vermont, Peter Geronazzo of Colorado College, Chris Drury and Jay Pandolfo of Boston University and Brendan  Morrison of Michigan. The award's winner, as college hockey's player of the year, will be announced tomorrow. The championship game is Saturday afternoon at Riverfront Coliseum. . . . The Final Four field has one team from each of the four Division I conferences and all finished first, or tied for first, in regular-season standings. Each was seeded No. 1 or No. 2 at the regional tournaments and all had a bye through the first round. Their quarterfinal opponents had played the night before. So the legs of the Lake Superior State skaters were not so fresh late against Vermont. The same was true for Minnesota  against Michigan and UMass-Lowell against Colorado College. "Someone has to take a hard look at the way this thing is set up," said Bruce Crowder, the UMass-Lowell coach. . . . Attendance at the quarterfinals was 6,043 at East Lansing, Mich., and 11,542 at Albany.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM N. WALLACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
