<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cougars and Lawyers Win in California Ballot Measures</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="839728"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILE INSURANCE AND LIABILITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGAL PROFESSION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFERENDUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HUNTING AND TRAPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISTRICT  ATTORNEYS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOUNTAIN LIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION RESULTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIMARIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GARCETTI, GIL (DIST ATTY)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LYNCH, JOHN (DEPUTYDIST ATTY)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hunting and Trapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">District Attorneys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Insurance and Liability</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Profession</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DC1539F93BA15750C0A960958260" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cougars and Lawyers Win in California Ballot Measures</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">AYRES, B DRUMMOND JR</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, March 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While Senator Bob Dole's victory in Tuesday's California primary was a predictable political yawn, considerably less predictable was voters' wholesale  rejection of three ballot propositions that, if passed, would have put California in the forefront of the much-disputed national movement to reduce court litigation.</p>
        <p>The defeat of the measures, in the face of a sharp-edged and expensive advertising campaign that painted lawyers as greedy shysters, was another demonstration of the political resilience and resourcefulness of the trial lawyer lobby.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While Senator Bob Dole's victory in Tuesday's California primary was a predictable political yawn, considerably less predictable was voters' wholesale  rejection of three ballot propositions that, if passed, would have put California in the forefront of the much-disputed national movement to reduce court litigation.</p>
        <p>The defeat of the measures, in the face of a sharp-edged and expensive advertising campaign that painted lawyers as greedy shysters, was another demonstration of the political resilience and resourcefulness of the trial lawyer lobby.</p>
        <p>And it was an even more impressive defense, coming in a state that is one of the most litigious in the nation, home to some of the nation's priciest and most flamboyant lawyers.</p>
        <p>Notable, too, on Tuesday were several other voter decisions -- on whether to  protect mountain lions, whether to open future primaries to all voters regardless of party affiliation, and whether to grant a second term to District  Attorney Gil Garcetti, Los Angeles County's chief trial lawyer and the chief strategist of the unsuccessful prosecution of O. J. Simpson.</p>
        <p>The mountain lions won. The next primaries will be "open." And Mr. Garcetti failed to win 50 percent of the vote and now faces a fall run-off against one of his deputies.</p>
        <p>The three litigation propositions, designed to curtail both the frequency and cost of suits, were pushed aggressively by state and national corporations and political conservatives. They were opposed adamantly by state and national trial lawyers and consumer organizations, including Ralph Nader's group.</p>
        <p>Especially at issue were the increasing number of suits that involve automobile insurers, companies whose stock often fluctuates and individuals whose lawyers' fees are contingent on the outcome of suits.</p>
        <p>Proponents of the three measures argued that the first would reduce insurance premiums because it called for the adoption of the "no fault" form of restitution, with hardly any suits permitted, no matter which driver might be at fault.</p>
        <p>The second measure, its backers said, would encourage business activity in California, especially formation of risky but often highly profitable high-technology companies, because it would require anyone suing a company over  the performance of its stock to pay the cost of the company's defense should the company prevail in the suit.</p>
        <p>And the third measure, proponents said, would reduce the burden of legal costs on companies and individuals because it would encourage out-of-court settlements, with lawyers' fees capped at 15 percent rather than the usual 30 or 40 percent.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the measures, including Mr. Nader, who flew to the state several times from Washington to lobby against them, argued that they were "lawyer bashing" and designed to deny consumers their traditional right to sue.</p>
        <p>The first two measures were defeated by margins of roughly 3 to 2. But the third measure lost by only a couple of points.</p>
        <p>Seeming undeterred by Tuesday's defeats, proponents of tort reform are talking about trying to put their measures back on the ballot in November for a  second round of voting, hardly an unexpected move in a state where ballot propositions are a favorite political tool for settling disputes.</p>
        <p>"They'd be fools to try," said Bill Carrick, a Democratic political consultant who helped direct the opposing forces. "It's obvious that California  voters and consumers are tired of being trampled by big business interests."</p>
        <p>But Ken Khachigian, a Republican consultant on the other side of the dispute, saw the Tuesday defeat in a more optimistic light.</p>
        <p>"We've been around on this stuff before and this time the vote showed us doing better," he said. "We're closing the gap."</p>
        <p>Whatever the merits of the arguments on either side of the issue, the sharp edge of the debate and the money spent by each camp to make its point was a good measure of the intensity that infuses the tort reform movement, under way in the country now for two decades, off and on, with neither side yet showing any sign  of prevailing, either at the state level or at the Congressional level in Washington.</p>
        <p>In all, proponents and opponents of the California tort propositions spent more than $25 million on television and other types of advertising to promote and defeat the three measures, with each side accusing the other of greed and duplicity about its goals.</p>
        <p>That was a large media "buy" even by the political standards of the nation's  most populous state. Further, significant amounts of the money came from out of  state.</p>
        <p>In the other significant votes on Tuesday, a proposal to make future Golden State primaries more competitive by opening them to all voters was solidly approved, doing away with the current "closed" system that permits only Democrats to vote in Democratic primaries, only Republicans to vote in Republican primaries, and so forth.</p>
        <p>Both Democratic and Republican leaders in the state opposed the proposition as "meddling." Its supporters argued that open voting would result in more moderate, more electable nominees.</p>
        <p>As for the mountain lion proposal, which called for lifting a 24-year ban on  sport hunting of cougars, it was easily defeated.</p>
        <p>Cougars are relatively rare California creatures. But now and again, as suburban development encroaches on their territory, they tangle with humans. Over the past two years, at least two people have been fatally mauled.</p>
        <p>The Garcetti vote?</p>
        <p>Facing sharp criticism of his office by five challengers, he mounted a $1 million advertising campaign and managed to come in first -- but with a 38 percent plurality rather than the required simple majority.</p>
        <p>In the fall he will face the second-place finisher, John Lynch, one of his deputies.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
