<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Poor Lands Treating Far More AIDS Patients</title>
    <meta content="27AIDS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1645277"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Zambia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Health Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lafraniere, Sharon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Zambia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Pharmaceutical, Biotechnology and Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Zambia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Third World and Developing Countries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E1DF173BF934A15752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1163" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Poor Lands Treating Far More AIDS Patients</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHARON LaFRANIERE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lafraniere, Sharon</byline>
      <dateline>BLANTYRE, Malawi, Jan. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>World Health Orgn reports 60 percent increase in number of AIDS patients receiving life-saving drug treatment in poor or middle-income nations in past six months; cites huge influx of international aid funds and growing determination by governments to confront pandemic; some of most determined countries are least equipped to deal with crisis; Zambia is treating nearly as many people as South Africa, even though South Africa has much better health care system and more than five times as many people in need of anti-retroviral drugs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The number of AIDS patients receiving life-saving drug treatment in poor or middle-income nations rose 60 percent in the past six months, the World Health Organization said Wednesday, largely because of a huge influx of international aid funds and a growing determination by governments to confront the pandemic.</p>
        <p>The number of people receiving anti-retroviral therapy in less developed countries jumped to 700,000 in December, up from 440,000 last June. Much of the gain occurred in sub-Saharan Africa, where an additional 160,000 people received therapy, the organization said in a 64-page report.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The number of AIDS patients receiving life-saving drug treatment in poor or middle-income nations rose 60 percent in the past six months, the World Health Organization said Wednesday, largely because of a huge influx of international aid funds and a growing determination by governments to confront the pandemic.</p>
        <p>The number of people receiving anti-retroviral therapy in less developed countries jumped to 700,000 in December, up from 440,000 last June. Much of the gain occurred in sub-Saharan Africa, where an additional 160,000 people received therapy, the organization said in a 64-page report.</p>
        <p>Still, anti-retroviral treatment reaches only one in eight needy people in the developing world, leaving an estimated 5.1 million people without such protection. Last year, the disease took more than three million lives, three-fourths of them in sub-Saharan Africa.</p>
        <p>Expanding AIDS treatment is the most complex public health challenge the world has ever faced, Jim Yong Kim, who heads the H.I.V.-AIDS division of the World Health Organization, said in a telephone interview from Geneva. With cemeteries overflowing in some nations, he said, ''this is not a report to celebrate.''</p>
        <p>But the last six months have shown that even some of the world's poorest nations can save significant numbers of people, he said, even where there are few health care workers and weak health infrastructure.</p>
        <p>''What we are seeing now is not only is treatment possible in areas like sub-Saharan Africa, but treatment scale-up is possible,'' he said. ''People are figuring how to scale up and they are doing it. I am really encouraged by that aspect of it.''</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the United States Food and Drug Administration for the first time approved three generic AIDS drugs from a South African company, potentially opening the way for American aid to be used to treat many more people, because generic drugs are usually relatively cheap.</p>
        <p>''The limiting factor on treatment now isn't the money in the budget to pay for drugs,'' Ambassador Randall L. Tobias, global aids coordinator for the Bush administration, said. ''It's the lack of doctors, nurses and laboratories.''</p>
        <p>In mid-2002, health officials around the world set a goal of extending drug therapy to three million people in low- and middle-income countries by the end of 2005 -- just over half of those in need. Last June, the organization's officials complained of slow progress, saying that the selected countries were 60,000 short of their interim target of enrolling 500,000 patients in treatment programs.</p>
        <p>Since then, however, a number of nations have made huge strides, led by Thailand, where more than a third of the 114,000 people in need of treatment now receive it.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, some of the most determined countries are the least equipped to deal with the crisis. Zambia, for instance, is treating nearly as many people as South Africa, even though South Africa has a much better health care system and more than five times as many people in need of anti-retroviral drugs.</p>
        <p>''A bigger commitment from South Africa, Nigeria and India is crucial if the developing world is to meet this year's treatment goals,'' Dr. Kim said. Together, these countries account for 41 percent of the unmet need, the report found. ''There have been some encouraging signs from those countries but the bottom line is they have to get moving,'' he said. ''They have to put their plans and declarations into action.''</p>
        <p>The organization defines the developing world as more than 100 nations in Africa, Asia, the Middle East, Eastern Europe, Latin America and the Caribbean. It includes middle-income countries like China, Brazil and Russia.</p>
        <p>Stephen Lewis, the United Nations' special envoy on AIDS in Africa, last week said Malawi illustrates the ''superhuman efforts'' some nations are making to address the AIDS crisis. Speaking at a press briefing in New York, he said that the government of that African nation of 11 million people employs only 103 doctors and 5 pharmacists, needs three times the number of nurses it now has and has filled only one-third of the jobs at the national health ministry.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he said, the government has trained teams of one doctor, one nurse and one counselor to dispense anti-retroviral drugs at 54 sites, with the aim of reaching 80,000 patients, nearly half of those in need, by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>''Nothing will stop them,'' Mr. Lewis said, according to a transcript of his remarks released by his office. ''They are as a nation obsessed.''</p>
        <p>Despite frustrating delays in some nations, he said, he senses ''the possibility that we're on the threshold of a breakthrough against the pandemic'' on the African continent.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the World Health Organization report concluded that the efforts to expand treatment had largely bypassed children with AIDS. One in every six people who die of AIDS is under 15 -- more than half a million deaths a year, the report said. Yet children account for fewer than 1 in 20 of those who get treatment, the organization found.</p>
        <p>''The scenario for children is, quite simply, doomsday,'' said Mr. Lewis. Anti-retroviral medication in syrups for children is expensive and in short supply.</p>
        <p>But fears that poor nations would be unable to enforce the treatment regime required for anti-retroviral drugs -- and would therefore encourage the rise of drug-resistant strains of AIDS -- have so far proven unfounded, the organization said.</p>
        <p>A study of one poor South African township showed that 90 percent of those on anti-retorviral therapy took their pills on schedule more than 95 percent of the time, according to the report. Treatment success rates in the developing world are as high as in Europe and the United States, with more than 9 in 10 patients alive 15 months after starting drug therapy.</p>
        <p>The report endorsed a number of strategies to reach more people more quickly, among them encouraging routine tests for H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS, at prenatal clinics and health centers and employing existing tuberculosis clinics to dispense AIDS drugs. It recommended that lay people be trained to perform tasks reserved for doctors and nurses in richer countries.</p>
        <p>One reason for the progress is a surge of funds unleashed by the Global Fund to Fight AIDS, Tuberculosis and Malaria, by President Bush's Emergency Plan for AIDS Relief and by the World Bank and other donors. As of last month, the Global Fund had received $6 billion in pledges, approved $3.3 billion in proposals and paid out $860 million to nations in need. The United States spent $2.4 billion fighting AIDS last year, mainly in Africa, and Congress has approved $2.9 billion for the current fiscal year.</p>
        <p>Ambassador Tobias said the United States is paying for the treatment of 155,000 people in 15 poor countries, and hopes to reach two million by 2008.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
