<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush Portrays Iraq Vote as Step In a Global March to Freedom</title>
    <meta content="27PREX$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/27/politics/27prexy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1645356"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE CONFLICT IN IRAQ: ELECTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ukraine</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Saudi Arabia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rice, Condoleezza</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DD173BF934A15752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush Portrays Iraq Vote as Step In a Global March to Freedom</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Portrays Iraq Vote as Step in a Global March to Freedom</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER and RICHARD W. STEVENSON; Robin Toner contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E; Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush calls elections in Iraq 'grand moment in Iraqi history' that will be part of global march toward freedom, news conference; acknowledges that Iraqis themselves have not yet taken initiative in defending their country; says criticism of his Iraq policy leveled by Democrats in Senate proceedings to confirm Condoleeza Rice as secretary of state might cause Iraqis to doubt Washington's will to prevail against insurgency; expanding on his Inaugural Address, he tries several times to place administration's strategy in Iraq into broader context, noting that elections there will follow elections in Ukraine and Afghanistan, and among Palestinians; in response to questions, he stops short of saying he would put leaders of Russia, China or Saudi Arabia on notice that freedom would be main measure of their relationship with Washington; seems to signal that he will be patient with countries that fail to liberalize quickly; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush said Wednesday that the elections this weekend in Iraq would be ''a grand moment in Iraqi history'' that he described as part of a global march toward freedom. Yet he acknowledged that Iraqis themselves had not yet taken the initiative in defending their country and might doubt Washington's will to prevail against the insurgency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's assessment, in the first news conference of his second term, was made on the deadliest day of the war for American forces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush said Wednesday that the elections this weekend in Iraq would be "a grand moment in Iraqi history."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush said Wednesday that the elections this weekend in Iraq would be ''a grand moment in Iraqi history'' that he described as part of a global march toward freedom. Yet he acknowledged that Iraqis themselves had not yet taken the initiative in defending their country and might doubt Washington's will to prevail against the insurgency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's assessment, in the first news conference of his second term, was made on the deadliest day of the war for American forces.</p>
        <p>''The story today is going to be very discouraging to the American people,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I understand that. We value life. And we weep and mourn when soldiers lose their life. But it is the long-term objective that is vital, and that is to spread freedom. Otherwise, the Middle East will continue to be a caldron of resentment and hate, a recruiting ground for those who have this vision of the world that is the exact opposite of ours.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was peppered with questions about his main domestic priority: revamping the Social Security system to create private accounts. But he declined to be specific about how he would propose to pay for the introduction of the new system, which could cost more than $1 trillion in the next decade.</p>
        <p>Instead, he focused on making the case for the need to overhaul the system that has been in place for decades, saying, ''if you're a 20-year-old person and you look at the math, you realize that you will inherit a bankrupt system.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush used much of his hastily called news conference in the White House press room to explain -- but not always to reinforce -- the arguments that he made last Thursday in his Inaugural Address, which appeared to put the United States on an aggressive course of promoting liberty around the world.</p>
        <p>Asked whether that meant he would make advances in personal liberty the main measure of relations with nations like Russia, China or Saudi Arabia, Mr. Bush stopped short of saying he would put the leaders of those nations on notice that freedom would be the main measure of their relationship with Washington.</p>
        <p>''I don't think foreign policy is an either/or proposition,'' Mr. Bush said in answer to a question about how a country's progress in advancing freedom might be balanced against other American interests, such as securing China's aid in disarming North Korea. ''I think it is possible, when you're a nation like the United States, to be able to achieve both objectives.'' He said, for example, that he would work with China on the ''practical objective'' of getting North Korea to give up its nuclear weapons even while pressing Beijing to allow free speech and democracy to flower.</p>
        <p>When meeting Chinese leaders, he said, ''I will constantly remind them of the benefits of a society that honors their people and respects human rights and human dignity.'' He noted that he had brought up the repression of Tibet and China's efforts to suppress Catholicism, and said that he would remind President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia that ''if he intends to continue to look west, we in the West believe in Western values.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bush seemed to signal that he would be patient with countries that failed to liberalize quickly. ''There won't be instant democracy,'' he said, adding later, ''That's why I said we're talking about the work of generations.''</p>
        <p>Expanding on his Inaugural Address, Mr. Bush tried several times on Wednesday to place the administration's strategy in Iraq into a broader context, noting that the elections in Iraq on Sunday will follow elections in Ukraine and Afghanistan, and among the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>He dismissed the criticisms of his Iraq policy leveled by Democrats in Senate proceedings to confirm Condoleezza Rice as secretary of state, arguing that the debate in the United States could leave the Iraqi people ''wondering whether or not this nation has the will necessary to stand with them as a democracy evolves.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Bush said ultimate success or failure lay with a new generation of Iraqi leaders. ''Listen, this problem will eventually be solved when the Iraqis take the initiative, and the Iraqi people see Iraqi soldiers willing to defend them,'' he said. ''And so -- and the American people, when they see the Iraqis step up and begin to fight, will see progress being made toward an objective which will make this world a better place.''</p>
        <p>On domestic policy, Mr. Bush said he would work to persuade Congress and the public to follow his lead on Social Security, saying it is worth the political risk, despite growing concern in his own party on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>He met later with a group of House Republicans to discuss the issue before Congressional Republicans meet on Friday in West Virginia, where how to proceed on Social Security will be at the top of the agenda.</p>
        <p>A poll done for House Republicans and distributed Wednesday on Capitol Hill fleshed out the reasons for the jitters among Republicans. It found that voters were increasingly open to making major changes to Social Security, and that younger voters in particular favored personal accounts.</p>
        <p>But it also found that voters trust Democrats to address the problem more than they trust Republicans, that a majority of voters 55 and older think the policies of the administration and Congressional Republicans have hurt the elderly and that those older voters -- projected to be 40 percent of the electorate in the 2006 midterm elections -- oppose private accounts by a solid majority.</p>
        <p>On Social Security, Mr. Bush did not provide any details of the approach he has in mind. In particular, he did not discuss the likelihood that it would include cuts to the government-paid benefits scheduled under current law. He said he would disclose more about his thinking in the State of the Union address next Wednesday and in appearances around the country afterward. The White House has hedged on whether Mr. Bush will ultimately make a detailed proposal.</p>
        <p>In recent days Democrats have challenged the White House to say whether it agrees with Representative Bill Thomas, the California Republican who is chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee, that Congress should consider factors like race and sex in looking at how Social Security operates.</p>
        <p>''What you're hearing a little bit is whether or not it is worth the political price,'' Mr. Bush said. ''I think it is. And I'm looking forward to leading the Congress. And I'm looking forward to taking the case to the American people.''</p>
        <p>After meeting with Mr. Bush late in the afternoon, Republican members of the House Ways and Means Committee said that he had made clear to them that he was serious about doing what it takes.</p>
        <p>Representative Paul D. Ryan of Wisconsin, a leading proponent of partial privatization of the system, said, ''He talked about how invested he was in the issue, how important this was to him, to the country.''</p>
        <p>The first phase of the White House's strategy for Social Security has been to convince the nation that there is no choice but to act now, a message the president sought to drive home at his news conference. He used the word ''bankrupt'' three times to describe the condition Social Security would face within decades, and generally portrayed the system as on a course that would leave future retirees in financial danger.</p>
        <p>''The system will be in the red in 13 years, and in 2042 the system will be broke,'' Mr. Bush said.</p>
        <p>But the severity of the system's financial troubles is open to debate. Social Security takes in more in payroll taxes than it pays out in benefits. In their most recent analysis of the system's condition, the Social Security trustees projected that benefit payments would begin to exceed payroll tax revenues in 2018. For 24 years after that, the system is expected to be able to pay full benefits by drawing on the Social Security trust fund, which is in essence the promise by the government to repay the current excess revenues that are now going to the pot used to cover general government spending.</p>
        <p>After 2042, Social Security could still afford to pay nearly three-quarters of benefits promised by current law. Some economists, especially liberals, say that even after 2042 there is a good chance Social Security could pay full benefits, because the economic assumptions underlying the system's financial projections are extremely conservative.</p>
        <p>Asked if he would consider raising the levels of wages subject to the Social Security payroll tax -- currently $90,000 -- or eliminating the wage ceiling, Mr. Bush appeared to rule out such a change. But his answer was vague enough that it could be interpreted as leaving open the possibility of increasing the wage cap without changing payroll tax rates.</p>
        <p>''I look forward to a fruitful discussion of all ideas, with the exception of raising the payroll tax,'' he said.</p>
        <p>THE CONFLICT IN IRAQ: ELECTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
