<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Next Mia Hamm May Be Heather O'Reilly</title>
    <meta content="29SOCC$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1436120"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Concacaf Gold Cup</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Reilly, Heather</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hamm, Mia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DA153FF93AA15753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Next Mia Hamm May Be Heather O'Reilly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK BELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bell, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Heather O'Reilly, 17-year-old member of Concacaf Gold Cup US team, is already being compared to Mia Hamm (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is no doubt, the girl can play.</p>
        <p>HEATHER O'REILLY is the only high school player on the United States roster for the Concacaf Gold Cup, which is the regional qualifying tournament for next year's Women's World Cup in China. The two finalists from the two four-nation groups advance automatically to the finals. O'Reilly, 17, plays, sporadically these days, for East Brunswick (N.J.) High School.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is no doubt, the girl can play.</p>
        <p>HEATHER O'REILLY is the only high school player on the United States roster for the Concacaf Gold Cup, which is the regional qualifying tournament for next year's Women's World Cup in China. The two finalists from the two four-nation groups advance automatically to the finals. O'Reilly, 17, plays, sporadically these days, for East Brunswick (N.J.) High School.</p>
        <p>In Sunday's 3-0 victory over Mexico in the opener for the United States -- the Americans play Trinidad and Tobago tonight in Fullerton, Calif. -- O'Reilly entered the game late in the second half as a substitute for MIA HAMM. Comparisons did not start there.</p>
        <p>''There will never be another Mia Hamm,'' O'Reilly said yesterday by telephone from California. ''She's a player that when her playing career is finished, her legacy will not be passed on to any one person. What she has done will never be done again. All I can hope for is to have the success she's had.''</p>
        <p>Practice by practice, game by game, goal by goal, O'Reilly is evolving into perhaps the next golden girl of American soccer.</p>
        <p>''It is flattering to be mentioned in the same sentence as Mia,'' she said. ''It has been great to see how down to earth all the players really are. You have to remember that in 1999 I was watching the World Cup in my living room. Look, all I can be is Heather O'Reilly.''</p>
        <p>That is not too bad these days.</p>
        <p>''O'Reilly has stepped up to make this roster,'' United States Coach APRIL HEINRICHS said. ''You see a young player like O'Reilly and she does very well because she has played in front of 40,000 people before.''</p>
        <p>That was in the final of the first under-19 world championships, won by the United States in Edmonton, Alberta, in September. O'Reilly scored four goals in the tournament as one blade of the Americans' so-called triple-edged sword, combining with KELLY WILSON and LINDSAY TARPLEY to score 19 of the United States' 26 goals.</p>
        <p>ENGLAND</p>
        <p>BRAD FRIEDEL, the United States national team goalkeeper, was the man of the match in Blackburn's defeat of Arsenal on Saturday at Highbury. It was Arsenal's third loss in eight days; coincidentally, all three rivals wear blue shirts.</p>
        <p>Friedel turned away 12 shots as Rovers finished the match with 10 men.</p>
        <p>''We were under pressure, but collectively as a team we did an outstanding job defensively,'' Friedel said on Blackburn's Web site. ''The goalkeeper was a little bit busy today, but that is going to happen when you go and play one of the best clubs in the world.''</p>
        <p>Friedel nearly did not play against the Gunners after injuring a knee before the match.</p>
        <p>''His cartilage popped out in warm-ups,'' Blackburn Coach GRAEME SOUNESS said. ''He managed to sort it out and play on, and he was excellent. We've known about Brad for a long time. We think he's the best goalkeeper in the country. But he's going to have to have an operation now, whenever we can find the right time.''</p>
        <p>The next test for Friedel and Rovers will come Thursday when they play Celtic in Glasgow in the first leg of a second-round UEFA Cup match.</p>
        <p>CORNER KICKS</p>
        <p>Only the most optimistic landscaper believes the grass field at Giants Stadium in East Rutherford, N.J., will need to be watered in the spring. An official decision to replace the tray system (the contract expires on Dec. 31) with artificial turf will not be made until after the N.F.L. season. Unofficially, it will probably be replaced with FieldTurf or RealGrass. It costs the New Jersey Sports Authority up to $800,000 a year to maintain the current field, which is in abysmal condition. A new artificial surface would cost up to $750,000 to install. Do the math. The ultimate decision will be left to the stadium's tenants, and that does not mean the MetroStars. ... BOB BRADLEY, the new MetroStars coach, will oversee his first practice Thursday.</p>
        <p>Chicago Fire defender CARLOS BOCANEGRA has arrived in Rotterdam, the Netherlands, for a two-week trial at Feyenoord. According to the club's Web site, Bocanegra, 23, will train with the second team and could be a transfer target because Feyenoord's starting left side defender, RAMON VAN HAAREN, is out for a month with a muscle tear in his upper left leg.</p>
        <p>Herkimer (N.Y.) County Community College advanced to its 13th straight National Junior College Athletic Association championship with victories (2-0 versus Hudson Valley, and 4-0 over North Country) last weekend. The national tournament, which will be played Nov. 9-10 at Nassau Community College in Garden City, N.Y., has been won by Herkimer in two of the last three years. Herkimer is still working on an incredible 114-game home winning streak. ... In Division I, St. John's (11-1-4) has regained the top ranking in the nation in the coaches' poll.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow's scheduled Champions League match in Moscow between Spartak and Basel of Switzerland has been put off a week in deference to the victims of last week's siege of a Moscow theater by Chechen guerrillas.</p>
        <p>MetroStars defender CRAIG ZIADIE has been called to the Jamaican national team for tomorrow's match against Guatemala.</p>
        <p>In the Major Indoor Soccer League last Friday, defending champion Philadelphia lost its coach and then lost a game to undefeated Milwaukee (6-0). OMID NAMAZI was hired by the San Diego Spirit of the Women's United Soccer Association. Namazi had been the Kixx's player-coach.</p>
        <p>JACK BELL</p>
        <p>SOCCER: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
