<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Talk; Pentagon Bargain Prices* (*An Additional Cost for Wars)</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="742984"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DE143FF931A25751C0A963958260" item-length="697" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Talk; Pentagon Bargain Prices* (*An Additional Cost for Wars)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the low, low price of $264 billion, the Pentagon's budget this year trains and equips 1.6 million troops, buys new warships and fighter jets and builds new barracks. Wars? Sorry, those are extra.</p>
        <p>In a financing quirk that has existed for years but is only now drawing many lawmakers' attention, the American military does not budget for battle, humanitarian missions or peacekeeping operations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the low, low price of $264 billion, the Pentagon's budget this year trains and equips 1.6 million troops, buys new warships and fighter jets and builds new barracks. Wars? Sorry, those are extra.</p>
        <p>In a financing quirk that has existed for years but is only now drawing many lawmakers' attention, the American military does not budget for battle, humanitarian missions or peacekeeping operations.</p>
        <p>"We appropriate a quarter of a trillion dollars for the military budget, but if we want to actually use the military we have to pay again?" a nonplussed Representative David R. Obey, Democrat of Wisconsin, asked Pentagon officials at a House subcommittee hearing last month.</p>
        <p>That is right. "We do not put money in our budget to wage war," explained the Pentagon's comptroller, John Hamre. "We put money in our budget so that we can go to war if we have to."</p>
        <p>Mr. Obey, still amazed at the idea, said, "It's like hiring a doctor for $1,000 a year, but if you actually go to him then it would cost you more."</p>
        <p>This accounting oddity came to light because Defense Secretary William J. Perry has come to Congress in recent weeks, hat in hand, asking for an additional $2.6 billion to pay for unanticipated military missions in Haiti, Kuwait, Cuba and Rwanda.  Without the extra money, the military will suffer dire consequences, warned Mr. Perry and Gen. John M. Shalikashvili, the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff. Air Force jets and bombers would halt training, marines would quit marching, Navy ships would stop sailing and Army spare parts would dwindle.</p>
        <p>In the past, the armed services typically paid for small, unplanned operations out of their training budgets. When a big conflict came along, like the Persian Gulf war, few in Congress quibbled afterward for paying the United States's $7 billion bill. (The allies paid the other $54 billion.)</p>
        <p>But in the last two years, the number of unexpected missions has soared and so have their costs. At the end of the 1994 fiscal year on Sept. 30, some military accounts ran out of money, and many rear-echelon units had to stop training.</p>
        <p>To avoid a recurrence this year, the Pentagon said it needed the additional money by March 31. Congress has grudgingly agreed to approve the request to avoid a readiness meltdown, but many lawmakers are questioning why it has come to this.</p>
        <p>Why doesn't the Pentagon just earmark some money for wars and humanitarian missions? Former Defense Secretary Les Aspin tried to create a special contingency fund two years ago, but lawmakers, wary the Defense Department was trying to start a slush fund or circumvent Congress's power of the purse, rejected the idea.</p>
        <p>Even if Congress consented, Pentagon officials said it would be difficult to predict where the military might be needed 18 months in the future.</p>
        <p>Why, lawmakers ask, doesn't the military just trim $2.6 billion from its $264 billion budget to pay for the additional operations? Pentagon officials say nearly one-third of the fiscal year is already gone (meaning that money is spent) and various laws and regulations limit which accounts they can dip into.</p>
        <p>"I don't think it's possible to get the subtlety of this argument across to the public," Mr. Perry told the House subcommittee last month. "My biggest challenge is to get the argument understood within the Government."</p>
        <p>And that is a major task, particularly with lawmakers new to Washington. Many have pledged to slash the size of Government, balance the Federal budget and cut pork-barrel spending.</p>
        <p>"I personally would like to see a list of how we can cut $2.56 billion of spending, what the bottom 1 percent of the priorities are in the Defense Department, so that we can make decisions based on the good of the future of this nation," said Representative Mark Neumann, a freshman Republican from Wisconsin.</p>
        <p>One problem is that lawmakers have added at least $1 billion of the money at the bottom of the Pentagon budget for pet projects to enhance their districts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hamre, the Pentagon comptroller, gave Mr. Neumann a look of, "how naive can you be," before responding politely: "A dollar cut of this magnitude is going to be politically difficult."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
