<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Southwestern Bell to End Test of Data 'Gateway' Offer</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="327445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONIC INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEPHONES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOUTHWESTERN BELL CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMS, CALVIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DD1E31F934A25751C0A966958260" item-length="575" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Southwestern Bell to End Test of Data 'Gateway' Offer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMS, CALVIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Southwestern Bell Corporation said yesterday that it plans to end its test offering of a ''public information gateway'' that allows computer users to tap into a variety of data bases by dialing one number from a telephone line.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Southwestern Bell Corporation said yesterday that it plans to end its test offering of a ''public information gateway'' that allows computer users to tap into a variety of data bases by dialing one number from a telephone line.</p>
        <p>The Southwestern Bell Corporation said yesterday that it plans to end its test offering of a ''public information gateway'' that allows computer users to tap into a variety of data bases by dialing one number from a telephone line.</p>
        <p>The gateway provides access to electronic information services, sometimes called videotex, that have long been envisioned as a way to transform American lives by offering instant communications, shopping, banking and travel reservations from a keyboard in the home.</p>
        <p>Southwestern Bell, a regional Bell telephone company based in St. Louis, said its Houston trial of gateway services will end next month, when the scheduled one-year test period is over. The telephone company, said it would study data collected during the trial to determine whether it would offer the service in other areas.</p>
        <p>Analysts See Disappointment</p>
        <p>''We have a lot of data to examine, but in general we are pleased with consumers' response,'' said Joe Elstner, a Southwestern Bell spokesman. ''It will take us several weeks to decide whether we will make a general gateway offering.''</p>
        <p>But industry analysts said that Southwestern Bell's decision not to extend the test was an indication that the company was disappointed that consumers who signed up for the service, called Sourceline, used it infrequently.</p>
        <p>Analysts estimate that Southwestern Bell lost about $8 million on the trial of the gateway, which had as many as 16,000 subscribers.</p>
        <p>Negotiating Terms Seen as Poor</p>
        <p>Analysts said that Southwestern Bell had not priced the service competitively and that the company had done poorly in negotiating terms with the providers of the electronic information, in particular U.S. Videotel, a private company based in Houston that offers electronic information, like weather, sports and a talk line. Analysts said too much of the revenues from Sourceline went to U.S. Videotel and not to Southwestern Bell.</p>
        <p>Joshua Harris, president of Jupiter Communications, a New York-based market research firm, said that 80 percent of Southwestern Bell's gateway revenues were coming from 20 percent of the customers that were using U.S. Videotel's services.</p>
        <p>U.S. Videotel announced yesterday that it plans to expand its electronic information services in the Houston area, now that Southwestern Bell is ending its gateway test. Mark Swank, president of U.S. Videotel, said that the company would offer its own information services package to current Sourceline customers and that it would include interactive services that were not previously available.</p>
        <p>Assessment Called Premature</p>
        <p>Many analysts had expected that the information gateways offered by the Baby Bells would succeed where others had failed, in part because of the marketing power of the giant telephone holding companies.</p>
        <p>But that has not been the case. Six of the nation's seven regional Bell companies, which were created at the breakup of the American Telephone and Telegraph Company in 1984, have introduced or announced plans to offer gateway services. None of the initial videotex offerings by the ''Baby Bells'' are profitable, and they have had little acceptance.</p>
        <p>Some analysts suggested that the trial had convinced Southwestern Bell not to enter the videotex market. But Mr. Elstner, a company spokesman, said: ''It's really premature to make an assessment like that. We are strongly committed to the development of the information services industry.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
