<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trade Gap Reaches 5-Year Low</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="327444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BALANCE OF PAYMENTS AND TRADE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMERCE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DE1E31F934A25751C0A966958260" item-length="909" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trade Gap Reaches 5-Year Low</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr., Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The nation's trade deficit narrowed sharply in December to $7.2 billion, the smallest gap in five years, the Commerce Department reported today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The nation's trade deficit narrowed sharply in December to $7.2 billion, the smallest gap in five years, the Commerce Department reported today.</p>
        <p>The nation's trade deficit narrowed sharply in December to $7.2 billion, the smallest gap in five years, the Commerce Department reported today.</p>
        <p>The latest figures brought the full-year deficit to $108.6 billion, a reduction of $9.9 billion from the 1988 total. This improvement, however, was far less than the $33.6 billion reduction achieved in the preceding year.</p>
        <p>And while the December performance was considerably better than expected, most private analysts said that the deficit would likely widen again in coming months unless the economy sinks unexpectedly into recession.</p>
        <p>Trend for '90</p>
        <p>''I think the trend is for little, if any, improvement'' for 1990, said Gary E. Schlossberg, an economist and trade specialist at Wells Fargo Bank.</p>
        <p>Just over three-quarters of the December narrowing was the result of lower imports, a phenomenon that is mostly welcomed but that also implies a weakening domestic economy. This was quite consistent with the department's report last month that gross national product in the fourth quarter grew by a skimpy five-tenths of 1 percent.</p>
        <p>The remainder of the December improvement reflected higher exports, but these were largely the result of a rebound in aircraft sales after the 48-day strike at the Boeing Company was settled Nov. 21.</p>
        <p>Export Momentum Slows</p>
        <p>''Export momentum continues to decline'' after helping to pace economic expansion for much of the past three years, said Bruce Steinberg, senior economist at Merrill Lynch, .</p>
        <p>Currency traders focused on the sluggishness suggested by the decline in imports and the dollar fell against most major currencies. [Page 44.]  The report had little impact on the credit or stock markets. [Page 38.]  A number of analysts, however, took some heart from the December trade figures. The $3.1 billion drop from November's $10.3 billion deficit was significant, said Jerry J. Jasinowski, president of the National Association of Manufacturers, precisely because - not in spite of - the drop in imports.</p>
        <p>''For the first time there are clear indications that in the face of slowing domestic demand, imports of manufactured goods are declining,'' he said. ''The drop in imports of capital equipment at a time when exports of capital goods and machine tools are rising was particularly noteworthy.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Jasinowski said he disagreed with those who are predicting little further improvement in trade this year. In addition to the gains made by American producers competing with imports, he cited a ''massive boom'' in European demand for American goods and a declining dollar that he expected would bring sustained increases in exports.</p>
        <p>Michael R. Darby, Under Secretary of Commerce for Economic Affairs, called the report ''quite encouraging'' while cautioning that trade figures are subject to especially large short-run gyrations that make it hard to spot emerging trends.</p>
        <p>Deficit With Japan</p>
        <p>The latest figures show, for example, a second straight sizable decline, to $3.5 billion, in the American deficit with Japan, but analysts remained wary of concluding that this represents fundamental improvement. They noted that the declines of 12 percent in December and 18 percent in November were preceded by a 19 percent jump in October. Imports of Japanese cars rose in December to $1.9 billion, from $1.6 billion in November, the report showed.</p>
        <p>For the year, the United States deficit with Japan totaled $49 billion, down 11.6 percent from the 1988 total of $55.4 billion.</p>
        <p>The trade balance with Western Europe swung in December to a $550 million surplus, from a $750 million deficit, with $100 million of the improvement accounted for by a smaller trading imbalance with West Germany.</p>
        <p>There was some further shrinkage in the American deficit with the newly industrialized countries of the Far East - Taiwan, South Korea, Hong Kong and Singapore. The combined deficit was $1.4 billion in December, down from $2.1 billion in November and $2.8 billion in October. Lower imports accounted for somewhat more than half the December improvement.</p>
        <p>Bill for Oil</p>
        <p>The nation's bill for imported oil eased $300 million, to $4.1 billion, in December, as a 27-million-barrel reduction in volume more than offset a 64-cent price increase. This occurred despite record December cold, suggesting that refiners drew down inventories during the month. Analysts expect a huge January increase in the oil bill, which during December represented 56.9 percent of the total trade deficit.</p>
        <p>For the year, oil imports surged 27.2 percent, to $48.94 billion - the highest amount since 1984, when the bill for oil was $52.4 billion.</p>
        <p>December's exports rose 2.4 percent, to $31.1 billion, while imports fell 5.9 percent, to $38.3 billion, the report showed. The $7.2 billion deficit was the lowest since the $6.8 billion posted in December 1984.</p>
        <p>November's deficit, initially reported at $10.5 billion, was revised to $10.3 billion but remained the worst deficit of 1989.</p>
        <p>Capital goods accounted for the biggest changes on both sides of the equation for December - a $1 billion increase in exports, three-quarters of it aircraft, and a $1.1 billion decline in imports.</p>
        <p>Without seasonal adjustment, the deficit dropped even more - to $6.4 billion from $10.6 billion, the report also showed. The three-month seasonally adjusted moving average now stands at $9.2 billion, down from $9.7 billion in November and from $10.2 billion in December 1988.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
