<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Our Towns; Big Crowd For Pageant? Don't Bet on It</title>
    <meta content="11TOWN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="956662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beauty Contests</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Miss America</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Atlantic City (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nieves, Evelyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Our Towns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Atlantic City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty Contests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beauty</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Contests and Prizes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DB1239F932A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Our Towns; Big Crowd For Pageant? Don't Bet on It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nieves, Evelyn</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Our Towns column discusses lack of interest in recent years concerning Miss America Pageant in Atlantic City (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A GREAT seat was had by all at the first big night of the Miss America preliminary competition. This was good news and, maybe, bad news.</p>
        <p>The good news: five minutes before show time, Gladys and Alan Kantrowitz of Brooklyn, with $200 in booty from the slots at Trump Plaza, decided to take their chances on getting tickets. ''We were going home,'' Mrs. Kantrowitz said. ''Then he says, 'Let's see what's going on there. What do we got to lose?' '' They thought themselves pretty lucky to discover that they could still buy orchestra seats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A GREAT seat was had by all at the first big night of the Miss America preliminary competition. This was good news and, maybe, bad news.</p>
        <p>The good news: five minutes before show time, Gladys and Alan Kantrowitz of Brooklyn, with $200 in booty from the slots at Trump Plaza, decided to take their chances on getting tickets. ''We were going home,'' Mrs. Kantrowitz said. ''Then he says, 'Let's see what's going on there. What do we got to lose?' '' They thought themselves pretty lucky to discover that they could still buy orchestra seats.</p>
        <p>Which is also the bad news, maybe. The old Convention Hall -- that's what it's always called these days, the old Convention Hall -- was at least half empty. ''When I asked the guy in the counter, 'You got any tickets left?' I see a stack as thick as a deck of cards,'' said Mr. Kantrowitz. This made him feel sort of the way Groucho Marx felt about any club that would have him as a member. ''I'm thinking maybe this isn't such a good deal.''</p>
        <p>Well, here it is, the Miss America pageant sneak preview, and where are all the throngs of adoring admirers? The Kantrowitzes were able to scoot down from their seats in Section S, Row G all the way down to Row B. (''Not a good sign,'' Mr. Kantrowitz said.)</p>
        <p>Of course, this was a production where the mistress of ceremonies for the night, Tawny Little, Miss America in 1976, could earnestly announce that ''everyone will be  a winner.'' So it's no surprise that pageant officials stood ready to pronounce the 6,000-seat arena as half full. And it is true that the preliminaries are rough cuts of the polished pageant to be shown Saturday night.</p>
        <p>STILL, time was, the pageant, preliminary shows and all, was the biggest thing to happen in Atlantic City. The city, ever the gracious host and major sponsor, still hangs demure little Miss America banners on lampposts all along the casino zone. For a full week before the pageant, there are public displays of contestants, and press conferences galore. On Monday, the new Miss America Rose Walk was unveiled on the Michigan Avenue sidewalk, with plaques commemorating 77 years of pageant history.</p>
        <p>But these days, the pageant has lots of competition for attention in its hometown. During the preliminaries, there were crowds at the slot machines in Caesar's Wild Wild West casino that would've created a fire hazard in Convention Hall. And when Tawny Little asked the audience if there were people here who had straggled in from the casinos, two-thirds of the audience raised their hands. (The rest were cheering sections the contestants brought from back home. Miss Illinois, Katherine Shindle, who is from New Jersey, must have brought 50 people.)</p>
        <p>No wonder the Miss America pageant is trying all sorts of gimmicks. If the audience for the pageant is blase in Atlantic City, then imagine the rest of the country.  This year's big first, allowing the 51 contestants to wear their choice of swimsuits, including two-piece suits, is just the most naked attempt for more attention.</p>
        <p>THE enduring symbol of the old, quaint Atlantic City is also trying to connect with the new Atlantic City. It's issuing commemorative $5 chips bearing the likeness of the outgoing Miss America, Tara Dawn Holland, and allowing contestants over 21 to gamble.</p>
        <p>Robert Ruffolo, chairman of the Atlantic City Historical Museum and an expert on Miss America's history, says the pageant ''is still a good thing for Atlantic City.''</p>
        <p>''The pageant is a big part of the history,'' he said Wednesday in his jam-packed bookstore on Atlantic Avenue. ''The city bends over backward to make it work.''</p>
        <p>Hard to say what will register with the casino crowd, though. During Tuesday night's preliminary competition, a good part of the audience walked out after the swimsuit competition, near the beginning of the three-hour show. Gertie and Sylvia Paycheck, sisters from North Jersey who were sitting next to the Kantrowitzes, stayed awake, but with an effort.</p>
        <p>''The women are lovely, and it's good that they win scholarships,'' Sylvia Paycheck said. ''But the pageant is too long.''</p>
        <p>''I'm glad Miss New Jersey won swimsuit, because she's short and I'm short,'' said Gertie, who is 4 feet 8 inches tall. ''But I've seen enough.'' The Kantrowitzes, who each bought $10 programs and $10 cardboard binoculars, missed quite a bit. Both fell asleep during the program. ''Well, we did get up early to drive here,'' Mrs. Kantrowitz said.</p>
        <p>''I'd never fall asleep playing 21,'' Mr. Kantrowitz said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
