<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nervous Suburb Joins Police in Silence on Missing Exxon Official</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="525116"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSING PERSONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MORRIS TOWNSHIP (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION (FBI)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">EXXON CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RESO, SIDNEY J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANLEY, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MURPHY, W MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920501T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDB1E31F932A35756C0A964958260" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nervous Suburb Joins Police in Silence on Missing Exxon Official</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HANLEY, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>MORRIS TOWNSHIP, N.J., April 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The disappearance of the president of Exxon International, Sidney J. Reso, remained a mystery today and authorities refused to discuss the status of their investigation.</p>
        <p>Throughout the day, there was a flurry of activity outside the house of Mr. Reso, who left for work at 7:30 A.M. Wednesday but never arrived at his office in Florham Park, a 15-to-20-minute drive from here. His car was found facing the road at the foot of the 250-foot driveway, the engine idling and the driver's door open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The disappearance of the president of Exxon International, Sidney J. Reso, remained a mystery today and authorities refused to discuss the status of their investigation.</p>
        <p>Throughout the day, there was a flurry of activity outside the house of Mr. Reso, who left for work at 7:30 A.M. Wednesday but never arrived at his office in Florham Park, a 15-to-20-minute drive from here. His car was found facing the road at the foot of the 250-foot driveway, the engine idling and the driver's door open.</p>
        <p>Telephone company trucks arrived in late morning and laborers, overseen by supervisors in white helmets and shirts and ties, spent several hours working on telephone lines outside the Reso home and on a pole a few hundred yards away.</p>
        <p>The head of the investigation, W. Michael Murphy, the Morris County Prosecutor, declined to talk about the work on the telephone lines or on any other aspect of the investigation, which his office is conducting with the F.B.I., local and state police, and the Corporate Security Division of Exxon International. "At the present time, the investigation is being classified as a missing-persons matter," Mr. Murphy said in a brief statement issued by his office at about 5 P.M.</p>
        <p>John F. Dempsey, the Deputy Chief of Investigation for the Prosecutor, refused to elaborate on the statement or to say whether any ransom demands or any communications about Mr. Reso's whereabouts had been received during the day. "We're not going to take any questions," Mr. Dempsey said. "We have nothing new to add to the investigation."  Police Cars and Plain Clothes</p>
        <p>About two dozen cars, including several unmarked police cars with radio antennas on their trunks, were parked throughout the day outside the Reso home, which is at the end of a cul-de-sac with only three other homes nearby, all set amid woods. In midafternoon, about a dozen men walked down the side yard of the home, apparently as part of a search, and then returned to their parked cars about a half-hour later.</p>
        <p>"Usually, the only cars you see are real-estate agents'," said Dannette Merchant, who has lived in the neighborhood for two years.</p>
        <p>She said that she and her husband, a physician, had never met the Resos, adding that this wasn't surprising. "A lot of people are corporate executives," she said. "They travel a lot or they work long hours. When they get home, they want to relax. They don't want to socialize. It's all very private."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Merchant learned of the disappearance the way many of her neighbors had: through the F.B.I. agents who swarmed into the neighborhood on Wednesday and interviewed as many people as they could.</p>
        <p>Today residents expressed some concern for their own safety in an area that combines the comforts and trappings of an upper-class suburb with the isolation of rural areas.</p>
        <p>Referring to the possibility that Mr. Reso was kidnapped, a woman who refused to give her name said: "If they can do it to him, they can do it to us." 'They're Busy People'</p>
        <p>A neighbor across the street, Janet V. Boni, said the police had asked her not to say anything about the case. Interviewed by phone, she said she didn't know very much about the Resos or the case. "They're busy people," she said of Mr. Reso and his wife, Patricia. "And our children are not at the ages that we meet people that way any more."</p>
        <p>She said that neither her family nor her home had become a headquarters for the investigation but that her life had changed in small ways since the police blocked off normal access to her end of the street.</p>
        <p>"We're not getting our paper, and our deliveries haven't been getting through," she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reso, a vice president of the Exxon Corporation, is president and a member of the management committee of the Exxon Company International. He has worked for Exxon since 1957 in various assignments in the United States, Australia and London. He has been president of the Exxon Company International since 1988. The division is responsible for Exxon's oil and gas operations outside North America. News Kept From Mother</p>
        <p>In New Orleans, where Mr. Reso grew up, a cousin who is a lawyer, Jerome Reso Jr., said the family was keeping the news of the disappearance from Sidney Reso's mother, who is seriously ill.</p>
        <p>Describing himself as shocked by the disappearance, Jerome Reso said: "I thought, 'It just looks like an abduction.' It's just out of the question he would disappear by himself.</p>
        <p>"He is a genuine, nice guy. It's hard to find the right adjectives to describe someone like that. His career at Exxon demonstrates how well he's been perceived by his peers in business."</p>
        <p>Mr. Reso was in New Orleans Feb. 2 for a luncheon honoring him as Alumnus of the Year at Brother Martin High School, which merged with the school from which he graduated in 1952, St. Aloysius.</p>
        <p>Sister Joan, who works at Brother Martin High School, said in an interview that she would try to find out what Mr. Reso said at the ceremony and what was said about him. But she called back later to report that Mr. Reso's brother "told me not to give out any information and to refer all calls to Exxon International."</p>
        <p>At Exxon's offices on Park Avenue in Florham Park, security guards in green blazers politely turned away reporters' questions and distributed a slim packet of information. It contained a photograph of Mr. Reso, a four-paragraph statement from the Morris County Prosecutor announcing a missing-persons investigation and a short biography of Mr. Reso.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
