<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Checking and Repairing Your Porch</title>
    <meta content="CNCLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HOME CLINIC" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="937193"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Repairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Porches</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipinski, Edward R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E1DB143FF936A25755C0A961958260" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Checking and Repairing Your Porch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipinski, Edward R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Home Clinic column on porch repairs; drawings (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you have a large porch on your home, it is important to inspect it annually. Porches are open structures, and they are especially vulnerable to the extremes of weather and insect attack. These could cause problems that, left unchecked, could affect its structural integrity.</p>
        <p>The inspection should begin with the substructure of the porch. This is important because any problems in this area could, if not corrected, develop into major headaches. Unfortunately, this part of the inspection is usually the most unpleasant because it involves venturing into the crawl space beneath the porch. This area is apt to be dark and damp, and it often serves as a shelter for spiders, snakes, bats and skunks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you have a large porch on your home, it is important to inspect it annually. Porches are open structures, and they are especially vulnerable to the extremes of weather and insect attack. These could cause problems that, left unchecked, could affect its structural integrity.</p>
        <p>The inspection should begin with the substructure of the porch. This is important because any problems in this area could, if not corrected, develop into major headaches. Unfortunately, this part of the inspection is usually the most unpleasant because it involves venturing into the crawl space beneath the porch. This area is apt to be dark and damp, and it often serves as a shelter for spiders, snakes, bats and skunks.</p>
        <p>In the crawl space, you can examine the piers and footings that support the weight of the porch. The piers may be of wood, stone, brick or concrete. Ideally they should rest on concrete footings situated below the frost line. With older porches, the pier may rest directly on the ground or on a bed of rubblestone. Piers in contact with the ground are  susceptible to rot and water damage.</p>
        <p>Wooden piers with relatively minor damage can sometimes be repaired by bolting two sturdy boards of structural lumber to the original piece. This technique, known as sistering, should not be attempted if the damage is extensive, because the repaired pier may not be able to support the weight of the porch. In this case the entire pier should be replaced with pressure treated lumber of the same dimension. Before replacing the pier, consider installing a footing so the new pier will not stand on the ground.</p>
        <p>Inspect the mortar joints around masonry piers. Cracks in these joints can allow water to penetrate into surrounding brick or stone. When the water expands during the seasonal freezing and thawing cycles, it will split the masonry and cause it to flake off. This process, known as spalling, can be stopped by chiseling out the old mortar and repointing it. Applying a good masonry sealer can also help prevent spalling.</p>
        <p>Check also to see if the porch is resting firmly on the piers. There should be no gaps. It is tempting to fill gaps with a wooden wedge. Before doing so, however, try to determine the reason for the void. Possibly one of the piers has settled. This can throw the porch out of its proper alignment and cause it rise off the opposite piers. Its best to jack up the porch to level it, then it build up.</p>
        <p>Next examine the floor joists and supporting beams for signs of deterioration. Look for evidence of insect damage, small holes in the wood, or shelter tubes on the surfaces leading from the ground as well as rot. You can repair damaged sections by sistering, but replace those beams that have serious structural damage.</p>
        <p>It is not enough to repair damaged pieces, you must also correct the underlying causes of the damage. Consult with a licensed pest control expert to help keep insects under control. Wood rot, however, can usually be controlled with a little preventive maintenance. Make sure that the ground slopes away from the porch. This will keep rain water from collecting under the porch.</p>
        <p>To control ground moisture, install a vapor barrier of 4-mil polyethylene sheets under the porch. Also make sure that the shrubs and plants near the porch are trimmed back. This will increase air circulation and keep rainwater from dripping off the leaves onto the porch.</p>
        <p>The floor boards should also be examined from the crawl space, because often the first signs of rot occur below. If you have to replace any floor boards, you can usually find three-inch-by five-quarter, tongue-in-groove floor boards at the local lumber yard. If possible, choose boards made of Douglas fir. It is a tough, close-grained softwood that will wear better than other softwoods. Be sure to coat these new floor boards with a wood preservative.</p>
        <p>The panels mounted below the porch between the piers are called aprons. They mask the unattractive crawl space and keep small animals from taking up residence there. The aprons are susceptible to water damage because they are close to the ground. Inspect them for damage and deterioration and make any repairs.</p>
        <p>Some aprons have solid panels, but most have a lattice design that allows air to circulate under the porch. Ideally, the spaces in the lattice work should be narrow enough to keep out small rodents. Still its a good idea to install screening behind the lattice work as an extra deterrent.</p>
        <p>After examining the substructure and aprons, you can inspect the floor boards from above. Look near the edges of the floor. The end grain of the boards is very porous, and it often absorbs moisture that can rot the boards. In most cases, you can use an epoxy filler (it should only be used to make cosmetic repairs). Never use epoxy to correct defects in structural members to make this repair. One way to keep the end grains from absorbing water is to reshape the edges with a router. Use either a chamfer or a round-over bit to minimize the amount of exposed end grain, then seal the ends with preservative.</p>
        <p>Where the floor meets the house there should be an expansion gap about  1/8-inch wide. The gap allows the floor to expand during the hot summer. It is important to caulk it periodically.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
