<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Zimmer Takes On Torricelli in Ad That Mimics TV News</title>
    <meta content="09JERS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="882215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pulley, Brett</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zimmer, Richard A (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Torricelli, Robert G (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DF143EF93AA35753C1A960958260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Zimmer Takes On Torricelli in Ad That Mimics TV News</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRETT PULLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pulley, Brett</byline>
      <dateline>LAWRENCEVILLE, N.J., Oct. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard A Zimmer's campaign unveils controversial new television advertisement for his race for United States Senate seat in New Jersey; advertisement uses format of television newscast to 'report' list of allegations about his Democratic opponent Robert G Torricelli (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Richard A. Zimmer's campaign unveiled a new television advertisement for his race for a United States Senate seat in New Jersey, but before it was even broadcast, it had created a stir.</p>
        <p>The new ad from Mr. Zimmer, a Republican Congressman, uses the format of a television news program to ''report'' a list of allegations about the Democratic candidate, Representative Robert G. Torricelli.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Richard A. Zimmer's campaign unveiled a new television advertisement for his race for a United States Senate seat in New Jersey, but before it was even broadcast, it had created a stir.</p>
        <p>The new ad from Mr. Zimmer, a Republican Congressman, uses the format of a television news program to ''report'' a list of allegations about the Democratic candidate, Representative Robert G. Torricelli.</p>
        <p>With an actress in the anchor's chair and the words ''breaking news'' scrolling across the screen, the 60-second ad uses photographs of actual newspaper clippings and footage from an actual network news telecast to create a mock report dubbed ''Torricelli Scandal.''</p>
        <p>Two television stations -- one in New York and one in Philadelphia -- debated whether to run the ad because it looked too much like their own news programs. But they eventually agreed to run the spot, according to a consultant with the Zimmer camp. At least one station, though, WCBS-TV in New York, said it would run its own disclaimer because the disclaimer that was put in the spot by the campaign -- as required by Federal law -- can hardly be noticed by the average viewer.</p>
        <p>''It will air in an amended form,'' said a WCBS-TV official who was involved in the decision but spoke only on condition of anonymity. ''The nature of the ad is very unusual.''</p>
        <p>The advertisement, which was produced by Mr. Zimmer's Princeton-based consultant, Lawrence Weitzner, and paid for by the Zimmer campaign and the Republican National Committee, also created consternation in Mr. Torricelli's camp, where it was dismissed as an attempt to get news organizations to revisit the warmed-over issues reported in the ad. ''It's a media ruse,'' asserted Josh Isay, a spokesperson for Mr. Torricelli's campaign.</p>
        <p>The CBS affiliate in Philadelphia, KYW, also expressed concern that the spot would be too difficult for viewers to distinguish as a paid campaign advertisement, said Barbara Abar, a media buyer based in Alexandria, Va., who is in charge of buying air time for the Torricelli campaign. ''It does look like a news report, so stations like KYW were concerned,'' Ms. Abar said. Officials at KYW could not immediately be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>The charges from Mr. Torricelli's camp that the spot is not intended to reach voters directly but is really aimed at news organizations is underscored by the limited amount of air time that the Zimmer campaign has bought on major networks to show the ad. So far, the spot is scheduled to run only three or four times on stations like WCBS and WABC in New York and KYW in Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>That is far less than the number of times spots typically run to reach voters. Mr. Weitzner, who produced the ad, defended the decision to buy so little network air time, saying the ad will run extensively on cable channels, where rates, and viewership, are much lower. He said ''a couple hundred thousand'' was spent on time for the ad and more network time for it may be bought later.</p>
        <p>But Kathleen Hall Jamieson, dean of the Annenberg School for Communication at the University of Pennsylvania and author of ''Dirty Politics,'' a book on campaign advertising, agreed that the limited amount of air time for the ad could signal ''simply an attempt to get it into the news agenda.'' She noted that the stations that were considering not running the spot were probably forced by Federal laws that demand that stations give the candidates access.</p>
        <p>Though all of the items used in the ad are actual news stories from the last few weeks, at least one news organization lashed out at the Zimmer campaign for the ad. The Record, a Bergen County newspaper that is quoted in the Zimmer campaign spot as having reported that Mr. Torricelli ''concealed his financial dealings'' with an F.B.I. fugitive, issued a statement today saying its news article was misrepresented in Mr. Zimmer's mock news report. ''The Record did not report that Torricelli concealed his financial dealings'' with the fugitive, said Glenn Ritt, the newspaper's editor.</p>
        <p>In a close race waged mainly through attack ads on television, Mr. Zimmer and Mr. Torricelli have gained attention from concerned groups. In closed meetings today, the Black Ministers Council of New Jersey met for 45 minutes with each candidate, and appealed to them to clean up their campaign attacks.</p>
        <p>''This is one of the worst campaigns we have seen in memory in New Jersey,'' said the Rev. Reginald T. Jackson, the council's executive director.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
