<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anthony Smith, 86, Environment Leader and Labor Lawyer</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Obituaries" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="512264"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEATHS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, ANTHONY WAYNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAMBERT, BRUCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Obituary (Obit)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Obituaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DD143DF934A35750C0A964958260" item-length="326" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anthony Smith, 86, Environment Leader and Labor Lawyer</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAMBERT, BRUCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anthony Wayne Smith, a onetime labor lawyer who became an environmental leader at the forefront of efforts to preserve seashores and national parks, died last Saturday at Georgetown University Hospital in Washington. He was 86 years old and lived in Washington and on a farm that he and his wife ran near Mercersburg, Pa.</p>
        <p>The cause of death was cancer, his family said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anthony Wayne Smith, a onetime labor lawyer who became an environmental leader at the forefront of efforts to preserve seashores and national parks, died last Saturday at Georgetown University Hospital in Washington. He was 86 years old and lived in Washington and on a farm that he and his wife ran near Mercersburg, Pa.</p>
        <p>The cause of death was cancer, his family said.</p>
        <p>As head of the National Parks and Conservation Association, Mr. Smith led campaigns to preserve parks like Assateague Island in Maryland and Virginia, Padre Island in Texas and Point Reyes in California, as well as major seashores like those on Cape Cod and Fire Island. He also organized a coalition of groups that blocked a plan by the Army Corps of Engineers to build dams and reservoirs along the Potomac River. Counsel for C.I.O.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith was born in Pittsburgh and graduated from the University of Pittsburgh and Yale Law School. After three years with the Manhattan law firm of Donovan, Leisure, Newton &amp; Irvine, he left for Washington in 1937 to join the headquarters of the Congress of Industrial Organizations. He remained there 19 years, serving as assistant general counsel and in many other posts and working with labor chiefs like John L. Lewis, Philip Murray and Walter P. Reuther.</p>
        <p>As president of the conservation association from 1958 to 1980, he expanded its membership eightfold, to 55,000. Among his many campaigns with the group was his successful opposition to plans for a large jetport in the Florida Everglades. After retiring as president, he remained active in environmentalism.</p>
        <p>In his long and varied career, Mr. Smith served as a delegate to United Nations conferences on laws governing the oceans and the environment, and helped draft the statute authorizing credit unions in Pennsylvania, Federal labor legislation and the law that created the Atomic Energy Commission.</p>
        <p>Surviving is his wife of 62 years, the former Anya Freedel.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
