<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Microsoft Picks England as Site Of Research Lab</title>
    <meta content="18SOFT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="937898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cambridge (Eng)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cambridge University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lohr, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Needham, Roger (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/Cambridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DE163EF93BA25755C0A961958260" item-length="1093" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Microsoft Picks England as Site Of Research Lab</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lohr, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Microsoft Corp plans to spend $80 million to set up research laboratory in Cambridge, Eng, in collaboration with Cambridge University; will also invest $16 million in venture fund to back technology start-ups in area; lab will be headed by Prof Roger Needham, computer systems research pioneer, and eventually employ 40 research fellows, mostly from Europe; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Microsoft Corporation, intent on building a world-class research team, has decided that it needs to be a bit more worldly.</p>
        <p>The company took a significant step in that direction yesterday when it announced that it would spend $80 million to set up a research laboratory in Cambridge, England, in collaboration with Cambridge University. The lab will be headed by Roger Needham, a Cambridge professor and a research pioneer in computer systems, and will eventually employ 40 full-time research fellows, mostly from Europe. Microsoft will also invest $16 million in a venture fund to back technology start-ups in the area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Microsoft Corporation, intent on building a world-class research team, has decided that it needs to be a bit more worldly.</p>
        <p>The company took a significant step in that direction yesterday when it announced that it would spend $80 million to set up a research laboratory in Cambridge, England, in collaboration with Cambridge University. The lab will be headed by Roger Needham, a Cambridge professor and a research pioneer in computer systems, and will eventually employ 40 full-time research fellows, mostly from Europe. Microsoft will also invest $16 million in a venture fund to back technology start-ups in the area.</p>
        <p>The Cambridge venture is Microsoft's first overseas research lab. The move was prompted by the sobering realization at the company's headquarters in Redmond, Wash., that rain, Starbucks coffee and even the millionaire-making prospect of Microsoft shares have not been sufficient in luring some leading computer scientists.</p>
        <p>''There are tons of smart people who, for whatever reason, aren't going to come to Seattle,'' said Nathan Myhrvold, Microsoft's chief technology officer. ''Going to Europe gives us a way to hire people who bring new talents and new perspectives to our work that we couldn't get any other way.''</p>
        <p>The Cambridge lab is part of an ambitious campaign by Microsoft -- which is no longer content to rule its industry by skillfully refining the computing inventions of two decades ago -- to build one of the world's great research operations. Over the last few years, the company has recruited about 200 leading computer scientists, a number it intends to triple over the next three years or so.</p>
        <p>The Microsoft research group's mission is not to fashion nifty features for next year's spreadsheet software or Internet browser but mainly to think about larger issues such as how people interact with computers and how software is written. The resulting products might be computers that listen to people and talk back, a programming Esperanto or virtual helpers. Some of those products may not appear for five or 10 years, or not at all -- that is the risk inherent in the basic research Microsoft is pursuing.</p>
        <p>The research community views Microsoft's venture as another sign that the software giant is exceptional in an era of deficit reduction and corporate belt-tightening -- a time when the Federal Government and most companies are curbing their spending on basic research.</p>
        <p>''Under the guise of re-engineering and downsizing, corporate America is pulling back from basic research -- and it's shortsighted,'' said Michael Dertouzos, director of the M.I.T. Laboratory for Computer Science. ''But Microsoft is conspicuously running counter to the trend.''</p>
        <p>In its push for basic research, Microsoft can be seen as successor to AT&amp;T, I.B.M. and Xerox. Over the years, they have all taken some of the profits from their dominance in their markets -- telephones, computers and copiers, respectively -- to pay for fundamental research. The results included the transistor, data bases, disk storage, the computer mouse and point-and-click graphic icons. All three companies retain formidable research groups, and I.B.M., for one, has 1,100 researchers scattered across five countries.</p>
        <p>''Microsoft is now picking up that leadership challenge in research,'' said Ed Lazowska, chairman of the computer science and engineering department at the University of Washington. ''Microsoft is taking advantage of its de facto monopoly to build one of the world's great research organizations. And I think it's going to affect the nation in really important ways.''</p>
        <p>Yet the history of basic research is filled with examples of breakthroughs developed by one company but ignored, only to be commercialized by another. The transistor was invented at AT&amp;T's Bell Laboratories in 1947, but putting it into microchips was done by others in Silicon Valley. In the 1970's, Xerox's Palo Alto Research Center came up with the idea of using graphic icons instead of arcane computer commands to make personal computers easier to use -- a concept first mimicked in Apple's Macintosh and later, and more profitably, by Microsoft's Windows program.</p>
        <p>Only time will tell what effect Microsoft's Cambridge venture will have. But the move seems to be setting up the potential for an intriguing study in contrasting styles. Microsoft's corporate culture is ultra-American -- a meritocracy of intelligence, to be sure, but also known as an ''irony-free zone,'' a place where talking fast is interpreted as thinking well. Being blunt and direct is valued as a form of communication, a way of fostering the intellectual friction that fuels creativity.</p>
        <p>In Britain, at least in a stronghold of elite education like Cambridge, the cultural style is decidedly different. It is a place where understatement, the ironic phrase and the self-deprecating aside are art forms, and where bluntness is sometimes regarded as being more rude than honest. Ending a meeting with ''Let's have lunch sometime,'' while not a brushoff, is more a way of saying goodbye -- though certainly not an open invitation to share a meal.</p>
        <p>If there is a single person who most belies the notion of Microsoft employees as being narrow, grim and driven, it is the man mainly responsible for setting up the Cambridge lab, Mr. Myhrvold. The irreverent, red-bearded Mr. Myhrvold, 37, has wide-ranging interests and tastes, comfortable discussing cosmology or competing in the world barbecue contest, as he has done in recent years, winning once.</p>
        <p>Mr. Myhrvold, who has a Ph.D. in theoretical physics, is familiar with Cambridge, having done postdoctoral research in cosmology and quantum field theory under Stephen Hawking, the Cambridge professor and author of the best-selling ''A Brief History of Time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Myhrvold communicates regularly with Mr. Hawking by E-mail, and his former mentor arranged meetings for Mr. Myhrvold with Cambridge officials in February after Microsoft decided to establish a European research center. Other sites, including ones in France, Germany and Scandinavia, were considered briefly, Mr. Myhrvold said. But early on, the decision was made to settle on Cambridge, a respected research university for centuries.</p>
        <p>His personal connection with Mr. Hawking helped, Mr. Myhrvold said, adding, ''But this was not an old-school-ties deal.''</p>
        <p>Still, he said a moment later, ''I should probably tell you that Stephen's son, Robert, is a programmer at Microsoft.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
