<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TECHNOLOGY: Digital Commerce; A captive audience is seen for the receipt and payment of monthly bills on line.</title>
    <meta content="16DIGI$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1062659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caruso, Denise</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Personal Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E1D71031F935A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TECHNOLOGY: Digital Commerce; A captive audience is seen for the receipt and payment of monthly bills on line.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Denise Caruso</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caruso, Denise</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Electronic billing systems that enable consumers to get and pay monthly bills on line are expected to be next big area in Internet commerce; could save merchants and banks billions of dollars in printing, paper and postage costs, save time and deliver new level of convenience for consumers; merchants and banks, unlikely to build E-bill technology themselves, may be forced to yield precious customer data to technology or service provider; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PREPARE for the next Internet feeding frenzy. Sharks from several industries are already circling the nascent market for products and services that will enable consumers to receive and pay their monthly bills on line.</p>
        <p>Electronic billing systems are expected not only to save merchants and banks billions of dollars in printing, paper and postage costs, but also to save time and deliver a new level of convenience for consumers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PREPARE for the next Internet feeding frenzy. Sharks from several industries are already circling the nascent market for products and services that will enable consumers to receive and pay their monthly bills on line.</p>
        <p>Electronic billing systems are expected not only to save merchants and banks billions of dollars in printing, paper and postage costs, but also to save time and deliver a new level of convenience for consumers.</p>
        <p>And the customer base is already a captive audience. By some reports, 60 percent of the 62 billion pieces of first-class mail delivered annually by the United States Postal Service are bills.</p>
        <p>Calculating, verifying, creating, mailing, collecting and processing those 37 billion statements have been estimated to cost $370 billion -- an average of $10 a bill, according to the report ''On Bills, Banks and Bill (Gates),'' published by Diamond Technology Partners (www.diamtech.com), a Chicago-based consulting firm.</p>
        <p>Diamond estimates that presenting and paying bills electronically could save 10 percent of that amount -- a huge incentive for large companies, in particular, to embrace E-billing. Merchants have already said they would be willing to pay as much as 40 cents a bill for such a service, instantly creating a market with a $15 billion potential.</p>
        <p>Last week, the Netscape Communications Corporation announced plans to offer Web-based E-billing software for on-line sellers. Transpoint, a joint venture of the Microsoft Corporation, the First Data Corporation and Citigroup, plans to introduce its E-bill service this quarter.</p>
        <p>And the Integrion Financial Network, a consortium of banks, financial services and technology companies including Checkfree, I.B.M., RSA Data Security and Visa USA, is preparing to start an E-bill pilot with one of its owners, Bank One, in January.</p>
        <p>One version of an E-bill system would allow merchants to send monthly bills in an E-mail format that could be forwarded directly to a customer running bill-payment software like Quicken from Intuit. Another would allow consumers to view all their bills from one Web site.</p>
        <p>But the potential impact of E-bills could be much more significant than cost savings and simple convenience.</p>
        <p>William Fenimore, the chief executive and managing director of Integrion, says although E-bills are inevitable, such sweeping change comes slowly to big financial institutions. ''The biller community is further ahead than the banking community in terms of distributing these bills and getting them paid,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And that disparity presents an opportunity for the law of unintended consequences to kick in.</p>
        <p>That is because the Internet has given many different kinds of companies -- from Microsoft and Intuit, to brokerage firms and insurance companies -- the ability to offer financial services more cheaply and without the regulations, including those governing consumer privacy, that banks and other financial institutions must obey.</p>
        <p>Because merchants and financial institutions are unlikely to build E-bill technology themselves, many will be forced to yield their precious customer data to a technology or service provider -- Microsoft's Transpoint venture, for example -- to run the system for them.</p>
        <p>Clearly, companies like Integrion, with owners that are almost all banks, are a hedge against that. But that hedge may not hold. Once companies start delivering digital bills, says Gordon Bell, a senior researcher for Microsoft, other opportunities present themselves rather quickly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bell says he has for years encouraged Microsoft's chairman, William H. Gates, to create a version of the Checkfree service. ''The other thing is to give WebTV away to do just this kind of thing, with a bank account or whatever,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Some analysts say that such opportunities will forever change the balance of power between customers and merchants.</p>
        <p>Referring to software applications, Chunka Mui, a partner in Diamond Technology, said, ''The real reason this is a killer app is because the technology provides a  platform for doing other things,''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mui predicts that E-bill systems will start a new ''aggregator'' business that enables people to pay all their bills on line in one place, rather than with individual merchants all over the Web -- as well as allowing those merchants to deliver precisely aimed junk advertising.</p>
        <p>''All these folks are talking about how this becomes the marketing machine from heaven,'' he said. ''What they don't understand is that once these bills are in digital form, they are infinitely controllable by the customer. It won't take 25 seconds for someone to realize, 'I could make a lot of money selling a filter for this junk.' ''</p>
        <p>What is more, he said, ''It would only take another 25 seconds to say, 'Hey, if I work for the customer and not for the merchants, maybe I can create an alliance of consumers.' ''</p>
        <p>To date, there are few consumer bill aggregators. One new start-up, Cyberbills.com in Santa Clara, Calif., recently began a consumer service that sends customers all their bills electronically.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mui says that such a service -- started as a cost-saver for merchants -- is actually ''stealth technology,'' a first step in returning the power over personal information to consumers who are tired of being bombarded with E-mail spam and junk advertising in all media.</p>
        <p>''It's about aggregating power,'' says Mr. Mui. ''It's not about selling information to merchants. It's about going to the people and saying, 'I know what you've bought -- let's do price comparisons for shopping, let's provide a direct connection to the seller when you have problems, things like that. This bill becomes the interface for so much -- it's a tremendous window onto the electronic world.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
