<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Daze Rallies Chicago</title>
    <meta content="16NHL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1062808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="N.H.L.: ROUNDUP"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981116T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E1D61E31F935A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Daze Rallies Chicago</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senators 2, Blackhawks 2</p>
        <p>Eric Daze's power-play goal at 5 minutes 47 seconds of the third period lifted Chicago to a 2-2 tie with the Ottawa Senators last night, but the Blackhawks' streak of games without a victory still reached 10 (0-8-2).</p>
        <p>Daze converted a deflection from the slot 49 seconds after Ottawa's Shaun Van Allen had given the Senators a 2-1 lead with a short-handed breakaway goal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senators 2, Blackhawks 2</p>
        <p>Eric Daze's power-play goal at 5 minutes 47 seconds of the third period lifted Chicago to a 2-2 tie with the Ottawa Senators last night, but the Blackhawks' streak of games without a victory still reached 10 (0-8-2).</p>
        <p>Daze converted a deflection from the slot 49 seconds after Ottawa's Shaun Van Allen had given the Senators a 2-1 lead with a short-handed breakaway goal.</p>
        <p>Tony Amonte also had a power-play goal for Chicago, which did manage to snap a four-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Amonte's 12th goal tied him for the league lead with Edmonton's Bill Guerin.</p>
        <p>Lance Pitlick also scored for the Senators, who have not won in their last six games (0-3-3).</p>
        <p>The Blackhawks have not won since a 5-4 victory at home over Nashville on Oct. 24.</p>
        <p>Although Ottawa outshot Chicago by 12-4 in the first period, the game remained scoreless after 20 minutes thanks to Blackhawks goaltender Mark Fitzpatrick.</p>
        <p>He was tested late in the period, stopping David Oliver on a close chance and several other Senators during an Ottawa power play.</p>
        <p>Pithck opened the scoring at 3:07 of the second period when he drove to the net to finish a give-and-go with Alexei Yashin.</p>
        <p>Amonte, however, tied it at 6:12 with a power-play goal, the first allowed by Ottawa in four games.</p>
        <p>He shoveled a shot past Damian Rohodes after Pal Coffey's drive for the slot deflected off Daze's Stick.</p>
        <p>Van Allen gave the Senators a 2-1 lead at 4:58 of the third period. He raced the length of the ice ad beat Fitzpatrick o the stick side after Doug Gilmur lost the puck at the right point during a Chicago power play.</p>
        <p>But 49 seconds later - and during the same Blackhawks manpower advantage - Daze tied it at 2-2 by redirecting in Glour's shot for the left point.</p>
        <p>Igor Kravchuk apparently scored with 3:35 left in regulation to give Ottawa a 3-2 lead, but the goal was disallowed after video review showed that the Senators' Andras Johansson was in the crease.</p>
        <p>The game was officiated by two referees, Dennis LaRue ad Lance Roberts.</p>
        <p>N.H.L.: ROUNDUP</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
