<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sun Aims to Extend a Lead</title>
    <meta content="25SUN.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/25/technology/ebusiness/25SUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1378672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sun Microsystems Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Microsoft Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Sun Microsystems Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Microsoft Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E1DC143BF936A15750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sun Aims to Extend a Lead</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sun Aims to Extend Its Lead</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markoff, John</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, March 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sun Microsystems plans ambitious effort for wireless Internet, market in which its Java programming language is already widely used; will roll out new set of Web services standards intended as alternative to Microsoft's .Net and announce wide range of alliances with global lineup of wireless carriers and handset makers; at stake is potentially huge market for interactive mobile services; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In federal court, Sun Microsystems has portrayed Microsoft's Internet services software effort -- known as .Net -- as a virtually unstoppable monopoly. On Monday, Sun will try to cast itself as a Microsoft beater.</p>
        <p>Sun, a major producer of software and hardware, plans to announce an ambitious effort for the wireless Internet -- a market in which Sun's Java programming language is already widely used and Microsoft's .Net is barely an also-ran.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>At its annual JavaOne conference, Sun will roll out a set of Web services standards intended as an alternative to Microsoft's .Net.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In federal court, Sun Microsystems has portrayed Microsoft's Internet services software effort -- known as .Net -- as a virtually unstoppable monopoly. On Monday, Sun will try to cast itself as a Microsoft beater.</p>
        <p>Sun, a major producer of software and hardware, plans to announce an ambitious effort for the wireless Internet -- a market in which Sun's Java programming language is already widely used and Microsoft's .Net is barely an also-ran.</p>
        <p>At its annual JavaOne conference, which opens here on Monday, Sun will roll out a new set of Web services standards intended as an alternative to Microsoft's .Net. Sun will also announce a wide range of alliances with a global lineup of wireless carriers and handset makers.</p>
        <p>At stake is the potentially huge market for interactive mobile services. Those services include messaging, games and so-called location-based electronic commerce. Sun's Java software has been adopted by the United States' five major wireless carriers, three leading European wireless carriers and the three leaders in Japan.</p>
        <p>''If you compare the phones with Java installed to Microsoft's Smart Phone software, there's a tremendous disparity,'' said Alan Reiter, publisher of Wireless Internet and Mobile Computing, in Chevy Chase, Md.</p>
        <p>Industry executives and analysts say Microsoft is being hampered by its continued PC-centric view of the world, as well as by persistent fear that the company will try to dominate the software portion of the wireless communications industry.</p>
        <p>''Microsoft still has the philosophy that you take the PC desktop and put it in the wireless handset,'' said Andrew Seybold, publisher of Andrew Seybold's Outlook 4Mobility newsletter. ''Their bigger problem is that the wireless industry hates Microsoft.''</p>
        <p>Last week, Microsoft quietly replaced the executive in charge of its wireless initiative, Ben Waldman, who has taken personal leave. He was succeeded by Kevin Shields, a longtime executive in the company's hand-held computing division.</p>
        <p>Microsoft has recently made pacts with Deutsche Telekom and its United States wireless subsidiary, Voicestream, to support Microsoft's .Net initiative. But industry analysts said Microsoft was still lagging badly in the wireless world. There are currently more than 12 million Java-based phones in the Japanese market, and European handset makers like Nokia, Seimens and Ericsson plan to ship tens of millions of Java phones this year.</p>
        <p>In the United States, analysts have been predicting that wireless data services will be slow in coming because the nation's cellular carriers have drastically limited their network-technology spending in the sluggish economy.</p>
        <p>But Sun's chairman and chief executive, Scott G. McNealy, predicts that wireless data services will arrive more quickly than the skeptics say they will. ''People are communicating more and traveling less,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Moreover, telecommunications companies are looking to new wireless data services, which include messaging and games, as a lucrative way out of the increasingly competitive voice market.</p>
        <p>Carriers see advanced services as ''the silver bullet to ward off collapsing fees'' from wireless voice communications, said David Readerman, a partner at Thomas Weisel Partners, a San Francisco investment firm.</p>
        <p>Sun's Java-based wireless initiative is expected to receive endorsements on Monday from Sprint Communications, Research in Motion, Nextel, Motorola, Nokia, Ericsson and Vodaphone, among others.</p>
        <p>Research in Motion is the Canadian maker of the popular Blackberry hand-held electronic mail communication system used by 13,000 corporations. The company, which recently announced a new version of its device that includes a cellular telephone, plans at JavaOne to introduce a software development kit that will make it possible for corporations and cellular carriers to produce custom software applications to run on the Blackberry.</p>
        <p>''We think the game changer is how these wireless devices will become platforms for software developers,'' said Jim Balsillie, chairman and co-chief executive of Research in Motion of Waterloo, Ontario.</p>
        <p>Examples of cellular software applications for wireless data services include programs being developed by companies like the Mapinfo Corporation, a Troy, N.Y., developer of location-based software, which is intended to let cellular phone users select restaurants, hotels or other businesses and then immediately see maps of their locations on their phone displays.</p>
        <p>At JavaOne, Sun plans to announce a set of standards for delivering Web services that have been tailored to the version of Java that is designed to run on cellular phones, palmtop organizers, set-top boxes and cars.</p>
        <p>TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
