<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Backs Giuliani's Way Of Assigning Workfare Hours</title>
    <meta content="19WORK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1047548"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E2DE1530F93AA2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Backs Giuliani's Way Of Assigning Workfare Hours</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FINDER</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York appeals court upholds way New York City calculates number of hours that welfare recipients must work in order to receive benefits; overturns lower court ruling that Giuliani administration's calculations, based on minimim wage, are unfair (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A state appeals court has upheld the way New York City calculates the number of hours that welfare recipients must work in its workfare program to receive benefits.</p>
        <p>The State Appellate Division in Manhattan, in a ruling released on Thursday, overturned a lower court decision that said the city's method of calculation, which is based on the minimum wage, was unfair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A state appeals court has upheld the way New York City calculates the number of hours that welfare recipients must work in its workfare program to receive benefits.</p>
        <p>The State Appellate Division in Manhattan, in a ruling released on Thursday, overturned a lower court decision that said the city's method of calculation, which is based on the minimum wage, was unfair.</p>
        <p>Since the Giuliani administration created its version of workfare in 1995, city officials have been calculating participants' hours so that their benefits are roughly equal to the minimum wage. A welfare recipient who receives the equivalent of $100 a week in benefits, for example, must work about 20 hours a week in workfare. The minimum wage is $5.15 an hour.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for several workfare participants challenged the city's approach in court. In May 1997, Justice Jane S. Solomon of State Supreme Court ruled that the city must base its calculations on what it pays regular city workers for similar tasks, as much as $8 to $10 an hour.</p>
        <p>More than 32,000 New Yorkers are enrolled in workfare, known formally as the Work Experience Program. Most of them sweep city streets, clean parks or perform clerical tasks in return for their welfare benefits.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for workfare participants had praised Justice Solomon's ruling as a breakthrough that might mean workfare participants would be treated more like other workers. They also said that if the ruling was upheld the city would either have to reduce sharply the number of hours workfare participants put in each week or increase welfare benefits.</p>
        <p>But in its unanimous decision, the Appellate Division noted that state law specifically authorizes paying the minimum wage to workfare participants. ''Moreover, there is a historical recognition that public-assistance recipients performing tasks in exchange for benefits are not public employees,'' the court said.</p>
        <p>Randy L. Levine, the Deputy Mayor for economic development, praised the decision yesterday. ''It's a very sound ruling, a common-sense ruling, because it recognizes what the Mayor has been saying for a long time: welfare is a temporary situation, unionization is a permanent situation,'' Mr. Levine said. ''It's like apples and oranges.''</p>
        <p>Marc Cohan, the lawyer representing workfare participants in the case, could not be reached for comment late yesterday.</p>
        <p>In another court ruling on workfare, a state judge has temporarily blocked the city's Human Resources Administration, which oversees welfare, from changing its rules determining which welfare recipients enrolled in college can be ordered into workfare.</p>
        <p>The city agency recently decided that welfare recipients enrolled in college work-study programs -- some of whom had been exempt from workfare -- would now have to participate. Lawyers for welfare recipients challenged the new rule, and on Wednesday, Justice Richard F. Braun of State Supreme Court issued a preliminary injunction against the city. Justice Braun said the city must individually assess students' skills and work history before assigning them to workfare.</p>
        <p>The city will appeal the decision, said Debra Sproles, a spokeswoman for the city agency.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
