<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saving the Ship That Revolutionized War at Sea</title>
    <meta content="02MONI$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971206T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="977237"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monitor (Ship)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War (US) (1861-65)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cape Hatteras (Nc)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, William J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War (US) (1861-65)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7D71F3AF931A35751C1A961958260" item-length="2441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saving the Ship That Revolutionized War at Sea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broad, William J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Government is taking its first major steps to save remains of the Monitor, one of history's most celebrated warships, now a mass of deteriorating wood and metal, half buried in sand, 230 feet down treacherous waters off Cape Hatteras, NC; experts say ship could fall apart at any time; diagrams (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Federal Government is taking its first major steps to save what remains of the Monitor, one of history's most celebrated warships, now a mass of deteriorating wood and metal, half buried in sand, 230 feet down in treacherous waters off Cape Hatteras, N.C.</p>
        <p>Experts say the famous ship could fall apart at any time. So the Government is proposing to lift about a quarter of it, including the engine, the propeller, the massive iron turret, two nine-foot guns and some of the heavy armor belt that still girds the sunken warship. The artifacts would be treated to try to reverse the corrosive effects of time and sea water, then displayed in a museum.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Federal Government is taking its first major steps to save what remains of the Monitor, one of history's most celebrated warships, now a mass of deteriorating wood and metal, half buried in sand, 230 feet down in treacherous waters off Cape Hatteras, N.C.</p>
        <p>Experts say the famous ship could fall apart at any time. So the Government is proposing to lift about a quarter of it, including the engine, the propeller, the massive iron turret, two nine-foot guns and some of the heavy armor belt that still girds the sunken warship. The artifacts would be treated to try to reverse the corrosive effects of time and sea water, then displayed in a museum.</p>
        <p>As schoolchildren know, the Monitor was an ironclad gunship whose advanced design changed the course of history. It fought a famous Civil War battle in the waters of Hampton Roads, Va., against another ironclad, the Confederate ship Virginia, formerly the U.S.S. Merrimack. Later, the Monitor foundered off North Carolina, but its success marked the end of wooden men-of-war and the beginning of the age of armored battleships.</p>
        <p>''Within two days of learning the news from Hampton Roads, the Royal Navy, the world's pre-eminent naval force, canceled the construction of all further wooden warships,'' says James Fertius deKay, a naval historian, in ''Monitor,'' a popular history of the warship recently published by Walker &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>The National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, which guards the venerated wreck in a marine sanctuary off Cape Hatteras, presented the proposed recovery plan to Congress on Nov. 6. Officially, the options include simply trying to preserve the Monitor in place as well as hauling it up completely, which would cost more than $50 million.</p>
        <p>Trying to pinch pennies, the agency is proposing a compromise that would save the Monitor's turret and some of the ship's stern, which are wasting away after more than a century of briny and human abuse. Though limited in scope, the proposed action would still cost more than $22 million, making the venture a hard sell financially and politically. Experts say that nothing so ambitious has ever before been tried by marine archeologists; no scholarly recovery effort has been done in such deep water and been so extensive.</p>
        <p>A similar effort in 1959 raised the Vasa, a Swedish warship that sank in Stockholm harbor in 1628. But it lay in water only 100 feet deep, about the limit for recreational scuba divers and less than half as deep as the Monitor's resting place.</p>
        <p>Despite the cost and difficulty of saving the ironclad, many experts, including naval historians and marine archeologists, applaud the proposed recovery as almost obligatory.</p>
        <p>''It's time to do something,'' said Richard W. Lawrence, undersea archeologist for the State of North Carolina. ''We've studied options for two decades. It's time to go ahead and take action.''</p>
        <p>Mr. deKay said a rescue mission was overdue.</p>
        <p>''It is a vastly important American artifact,'' he said in an interview. ''To my mind, it's on the level with the Wright brothers' airplane. It was certainly the most important naval technological development of the 19th century worldwide.''</p>
        <p>John D. Broadwater, manager of the Monitor sanctuary, said the legendary ship was fading fast.</p>
        <p>''Every time we send down a diver, another deck plate has fallen away,'' he said in an interview. ''It's taken us a long time to work up to the word crisis. You don't want to do the Chicken Little thing. But I think we honestly have a crisis on our hands. Every season counts. We have to assume that any season could be our last.''</p>
        <p>The Monitor was a marvel of technology when first sent to sea. Still, she was but one of a growing number of ships clad in armor plating, though clearly the best of her kind and arguably the most advanced fighting ship of her day.</p>
        <p>Among her innovations were the world's first revolving naval gun turret and one of the first propellers. Low in the water, the Monitor also had one of the first flush toilets on a ship and was apparently the first to have all crew members quartered below the waterline.</p>
        <p>Her steam engines turned the screw, a ventilation system and the turret, which was 22 feet wide, weighed 120 tons and was made of iron plate eight inches thick. The guns were two of the most powerful ever mounted on a ship and fired solid iron balls weighing 180 pounds.</p>
        <p>The U.S.S. Monitor was built in the Greenpoint section of Brooklyn and launched into the East River on Jan. 30, 1862; it measured 172 feet long. An emergency project to help counter Southern shipping, the ship was ridiculed by Union skeptics as an iron coffin and by Confederate seamen as a ''Yankee cheese box on a raft.''</p>
        <p>That judgment changed on March 9, 1862. In the waters of Hampton Roads, Va., where the James River meets the Chesapeake Bay, the Monitor, with 58 crewmen on board, fought a four-hour duel with the Confederate ship Virginia, a steam frigate covered with iron plates.</p>
        <p>Neither ship sank the other. But the Monitor decisively stopped a bloody rampage against Union ships that the Virginia had started the day before.</p>
        <p>It was history's first battle between ironclads and the most famous naval engagement of the Civil War.</p>
        <p>The draw was an important victory for the North because it prevented the Virginia from shattering the Union blockade and helped keep France and Britain out of the war. The South hoped to sell its cotton to Europe in exchange for industrial supplies.</p>
        <p>After the battle, the major navies of the world quickly copied the Monitor's design, building ironclad warships equipped with propellers and revolving gun turrets. Instantly obsolete were tall ships carrying up to 120 guns and anywhere from 500 to 1,200 men.</p>
        <p>Late the following December, after repairs and much feting in Washington, the Monitor was heading south for blockade duty off Wilmington, N.C., when she encountered gales and turbulent seas off Cape Hatteras, an area notorious for treacherous weather.</p>
        <p>Foundering, she went down on Dec. 31, 1862, exactly 11 months after her launching. Lost were 16 crewmen and the ship's cat, which a sailor had tried to shelter in the barrel of one of the guns.</p>
        <p>For more than a century, the ship lay in an area known as the graveyard of the Atlantic, so numerous are the shipwrecks.</p>
        <p>In 1973, scientists hunting 16 miles off Cape Hatteras found the Monitor's remains lying upside down, covered in sand and sponges, clams and coral. The ship's heavy iron turret lay off to one side, having come loose during the sinking and been pinned down near the wreck's stern.</p>
        <p>An analysis of the remains suggested that in World War II, Navy ships had mistaken the ironclad for a German submarine and dropped depth charges, blasting apart hull plates and beams.</p>
        <p>Overall decay was hastened by the ship's resting place, where the warm Gulf Stream meets icy currents, agitating the waters. The constant churning, abetted by a rich supply of dissolved oxygen, had worked for more than a century to rust some of the ship's massive iron plates.</p>
        <p>In 1975, the Secretary of Commerce, who oversees the ocean agency, designated the remains of the Monitor as a National Marine Sanctuary, the first of a dozen such protected areas. In 1983, the ship's anchor, weighing 1,300 pounds, was recovered and placed on display in the Mariners' Museum in Newport News, Va.</p>
        <p>In 1991, a private fishing boat anchored on the wreck. Later analysis suggested that the incident damaged the Monitor's hull. And commercial fishing gear has repeatedly been found tangled in the hulk over the years, signaling the threat of more damage.</p>
        <p>In 1995, scientists planned to lift the Monitor's two-ton, four-bladed propeller, which is nine feet wide, but they were foiled by a hurricane.</p>
        <p>Over the years, more than 150 small artifacts have been raised up, including wine bottles, condiment and apothecary jars, an ironstone dinner plate, brass oarlocks for the Monitor's boats and the remains of an iron hull plate.</p>
        <p>A lengthy report on the ocean agency's new recovery plan, dated October and given to Congress in November, says that since its discovery, the Monitor ''has suffered notable deterioration of almost every portion of its hull, with the most extensive damage occurring in the stern.''</p>
        <p>The rescue bid would involve a flotilla of advanced gear. The salvage project would include undersea robots and a floating barge equipped with cranes, winches and a special habitat for deep divers. Living under pressure and breathing special gases that curb illnesses, divers would descend to the wreck in a diving bell. From there, they would plunge into the cold water to work for extended periods on the celebrated wreck.</p>
        <p>In the first phase, the entire shipwreck would be carefully mapped,  and smaller items from areas expected to become inaccessible later would be recovered for conservation and display.</p>
        <p>Next, the goal would be to shore up the ship's port side, which is suspended up to 10 feet above the seabed by the massive iron turret. The gap is stressing the hull and threatening to break the wreck in two, destroying much of what remains. Divers would fill the gap with such things as sandbags, pumped-in sand, mechanical jacks and bags of grout, which would harden like cement.</p>
        <p>Archeologists and divers would then do the main rescue work, first recovering the propeller and engine, then the turret and its guns. The turret would probably fall apart under its own weight so the plan is to lift it in a support cradle.</p>
        <p>Sections of armor belt and hull removed during the recovery process would either be left on the seabed or lifted up to the surface for conservation.</p>
        <p>Most artifacts would go to the Mariners' Museum, which already displays the iron anchor and a brass signal lantern as well as Monitor plans, photographs, illustrations and memorabilia. Other items might go into traveling exhibitions.</p>
        <p>Experts and advocates say the plan is heavy with uncertainties, not the least of which is Mother Nature.</p>
        <p>''There are strong currents and sudden storms,'' said Mr. Broadwater, the sanctuary manager. ''It's just not the kind of place that's conducive to long operations. That's a worry.''</p>
        <p>Another question is whether the recovery can be pulled off even if the weather cooperates. Similar recovery efforts have failed: The Civil War gunboat U.S.S. Cairo, sunk in the Mississippi River, was ripped apart in 1965 when cables slung under its hull cut through water-damaged wood.</p>
        <p>The biggest challenge is financial. The whole sanctuary program of the ocean agency has a budget this year of $14 million, and the Monitor effort, at $22 million, would dwarf that. So the agency is looking for public and private allies to contribute money, gear and enthusiasm.</p>
        <p>Officials are upbeat.</p>
        <p>''We've been pleasantly surprised by the extent and the intensity of the support,'' said Stephanie Thornton, head of the sanctuaries program. ''There's tremendous interest out there.''</p>
        <p>One potential partner is the Navy, which in theory could lend a lot of assistance. So far, however, it is offering only analytical aid.</p>
        <p>Experts say the service may eventually come around to playing a larger role in the effort to rescue the legendary ship that it built.</p>
        <p>''The Navy is proud of its high-tech history,'' said Mr. deKay, author of the Monitor book.</p>
        <p>''I sense that they would do anything to bring her up, to save her in whatever form that can be done.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 6, 1997, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Tuesday about a plan to save what remains of the Civil War ironclad Monitor misspelled the middle name of a naval historian who wrote a popular history of the ship. He is James Tertius deKay, not Fertius.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 6, 1997, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in Science Times on Tuesday about a plan to save what remains of the Civil War ironclad Monitor misspelled the middle name of a naval historian who wrote a popular history of the ship. He is James Tertius deKay, not Fertius.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
