<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; The Giants' Little Big Man Is Short, Not Small</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="713136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON REDSKINS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, DAVE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MEGGETT, DAVE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2D91E3BF93AA2575AC0A962958260" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; The Giants' Little Big Man Is Short, Not Small</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDERSON, DAVE</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SNEAKING into the end zone like a mouse among redwood trees, David Meggett had scored the touchdown that would assure the Giants' 31-23 victory over the Redskins and now, his shaved head high in a Throwback Weekend helmet with "NY" on it, he was returning to the sideline where linebacker Corey Miller embraced him.</p>
        <p>"I love you," Miller said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SNEAKING into the end zone like a mouse among redwood trees, David Meggett had scored the touchdown that would assure the Giants' 31-23 victory over the Redskins and now, his shaved head high in a Throwback Weekend helmet with "NY" on it, he was returning to the sideline where linebacker Corey Miller embraced him.</p>
        <p>"I love you," Miller said.</p>
        <p>That love is not unrequited. That love was shared by his teammates, his coaches and 77,298 parishioners yesterday as the Giants streaked to a 3-0 start on David Meggett's two goal-line touchdowns and his 16-yard touchdown pass to tight end Aaron Pierce.</p>
        <p>"He's been the most valuable person on this team," Miller was saying now at his locker. "Nobody has the heart he does. He gives me inspiration. He's a leader. He's not vocal, but if you watch what he does on the field, that leadership pays off."</p>
        <p>If a child shall lead them in the Bible, the Giants' shortest player is leading them now.</p>
        <p>Notice the word "shortest," rather than "smallest." David Meggett is short, but he's not small. Not with 198 rock-hard pounds on his 5-foot-7-inch chassis. Until now he had been primarily a third-down receiver, an occasional rusher and a spectacular punt returner and kickoff returner.</p>
        <p>But ever since Rodney Hampton was unavailable in the third quarter of last week's victory in Arizona because of a bruised kidney, Meggett has been much more visible as a heavy-duty runner.</p>
        <p>In his sixth season, with Phil Simms and Lawrence Taylor no longer around, Meggett is suddenly a giant among the Giants, not only to his teammates but to their fans. Some teammates have been in the National Football League longer, but only William Roberts, Erik Howard, Doug Riesenberg and Jumbo Elliott have been Giants longer. And none of them ever handle the ball.</p>
        <p>Meggett handled it on 31 of the Giants' 72 offensive plays: 26 carries for 82 rushing yards, 4 receptions for 52 yards, plus that option pass for a touchdown. In each of the two games against the Redskins last season, he also threw a touchdown pass, 42 yards to Mike Sherrard and 21 to Chris Calloway. But yesterday's play started as a handoff rather than a pitchout.</p>
        <p>"When the safety charged up," Meggett was saying now, "Aaron just got behind him."</p>
        <p>Wearing a purple sport shirt, Meggett had arrived at the interview podium not long after Dan Reeves explained how he had not been apprehensive about using him that much, saying, "If you were worried about somebody getting hurt, you wouldn't put even put him in the game." Now, noticing Meggett near him, the Giants coach smiled and asked, "Any injuries?"</p>
        <p>"No, I'm cool," Meggett said.</p>
        <p>Meggett also had not been apprehensive about having to endure 26 carries, by far the most of his career. His previous high was 15 a week ago in Arizona; he had 10 in the 1990 N.F.C. championship game in San Francisco and 9 in Super Bowl XXV against the Buffalo Bills. But he breezed through 26 carries as if it were a no-pads practice.</p>
        <p>"If I had any doubts," he said firmly, "I'd be back in Charleston, S.C."</p>
        <p>He remembered having 32 carries in a game as a Towson (Md.) State running back.</p>
        <p>"I don't feel banged up," he said. "It's a different challenge for me."</p>
        <p>It was a different challenge for the Redskins' linemen and linebackers. Short running backs such as Meggett might have some disadvantages in size and strength, but they also have one advantage.</p>
        <p>"He's hard to find," William Roberts explained. "He gets lost behind us big guys. The other team can't find him."</p>
        <p>Barry Sanders of the Lions has that advantage now; Mike Garrett of the Chiefs had that advantage a generation ago. But for all of Meggett's success, he'll return to spot duty when Hampton is healthy, possibly in New Orleans a week from next Sunday when the Giants, who have a bye this week, resume their Super Bowl XXIX playoff quest as the N.F.L.'s surprise team.</p>
        <p>"We think we can conquer the world," Meggett said. "This started out as David vs. Goliath; new guys in key positions won't work."</p>
        <p>The new guy in the key position, quarterback Dave Brown, had another poised performance: 14 of 19 passes for 221 yards, including a 30-yard dart to wide receiver Sherrard for a touchdown, with no interceptions. But the Giants' retooled defensive secondary was riddled by Redskin quarterback John Friesz, who completed 32 of 50 for 381 yards.</p>
        <p>"They played just like Dallas," said cornerback Phillippi Sparks, referring to the pass plays of Coach Norv Turner, formerly the Cowboys' offensive coordinator. "Their routes have even more timing patterns. As they make their cut, the ball is there."</p>
        <p>If the Redskins' adopted offense was that effective, will the Giants' defense be able to thwart the Cowboys' offense with Emmitt Smith, Troy Aikman and Michael Irvin on Nov. 7 in Texas Stadium in what looms as a Monday night showdown for first place in the N.F.C. East?</p>
        <p>For all of David Meggett's theatrics, that's the question these Giants still must answer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
