<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where to Drop a Lisp Or Pick Up an Accent</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="628086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPEECH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK SPEECH IMPROVEMENT SERVICES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHWAT, SAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930811T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D8153EF932A2575BC0A965958260" item-length="1017" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where to Drop a Lisp Or Pick Up an Accent</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Weeks into an attempt to expunge her German accent, Marietta Maxime was still struggling with her sitchoovashun.</p>
        <p>"Tell me," she implored of her speech therapist, Sam Chwat, "is it sit-OO-a-shon? Or situ-A-tion?" Frustration mounted. She tried the sentence again. "Tell me about the sit-CHoo-a-ton."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Weeks into an attempt to expunge her German accent, Marietta Maxime was still struggling with her sitchoovashun.</p>
        <p>"Tell me," she implored of her speech therapist, Sam Chwat, "is it sit-OO-a-shon? Or situ-A-tion?" Frustration mounted. She tried the sentence again. "Tell me about the sit-CHoo-a-ton."</p>
        <p>Mr. Chwat patiently coaxed the vowel sounds from Ms. Maxime, who is Swiss, and like hundreds of other transplanted and native New Yorkers, turned to him to eliminate an accent.</p>
        <p>He took the South away from Julia Roberts. He exorcised Brooklyn from Robert De Niro's speech. Kathleen Turner, Gregory Hines and the Olympic ice skater John Curry have passed through his office in search of speech. 'A Drive to Conformity'</p>
        <p>He teaches senators how to drop their regional accents when they are in Washington, and how to pick them up again on the campaign trail. He extracts Puerto Rico, Poland and Bensonhurst from executives, making linguistic footnotes from their dropped R's and soft J's.</p>
        <p>"I couldn't thrive elsewhere," said Mr. Chwat, (pronounced shh-WATT, or before a session, CHA-wit) director of New York Speech Improvement Services, a 15-year-old center at 253 West 16th Street. "This is a city where ethnic communities are clashing and there is a drive to conformity, and people with accents are typecast."</p>
        <p>"This business wouldn't work in Miami," he said. "Ethnic is in there."</p>
        <p>Ms. Maxime, who thought she needed to lose her accent to get a job as a talk show host, represents two groups of clients: immigrants who believe that they are discriminated against because of their accented English and actors looking to learn an accent for a role.</p>
        <p>Ms. Maxime seemed fluent enough, but Mr. Chwat said, "German accents don't go over too well here. The last time her manager told someone she was Swiss they said, 'Yeah, that's what they all say.' "</p>
        <p>He trained her to press her tongue farther back, hoping to make her T's more comprehensible. Somehow, the lesson digressed into a conversation about dating. "I would not go out with a guy with a speech problem; it would get on my niffs," Ms. Maxime said. Replacing Some Consonants</p>
        <p>Mr. Chwat, whose 45-minute sessions cost "a couple hundred dollars for a lisp to several hundred dollars" for a brand-new accent, considers Meryl Streep his fantasy client and Joey Buttafuoco an accented archetype: he watched with fascination the spate of Amy Fisher television movies last fall in which a variety of Long Island accents were tried, and evaluated their authenticity.</p>
        <p>"New Yorkers come because they feel the nasal accent characterizes them as sloppy or uneducated," he said. "Only an obscurely oriented person would want to actually learn a New York accent."</p>
        <p>His first client was a Puerto Rican executive who wanted to "replace some consonants for business." The business grew to 12 therapists and a star-studded client list that he says expands mostly by word of mouth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chwat, who earned a linguistics degree from Sarah Lawrence College, sees a handful of clients who are neither actors nor executives.</p>
        <p>Like the towering C.I.A. agent with a New York accent who demanded to learn a Chinese one. He mastered it in 10 sessions. "I never asked him why he needed it, but he went away very happy and sounding Chinese," Mr. Chwat said. A few come to acquire British accents. "They think it makes them sound distinctive, elegant."</p>
        <p>His disciples sit opposite him in his small office, which is cluttered with books on every language, a poster from the film "Sleeping With the Enemy," an old-fashioned tin of Accent spice, teeth and ear molds and books like "Never Be Nervous Again."</p>
        <p>Darby Townsend, a stage actress, was successful with British, French and German accents, and now she is working on an Irish brogue. She sat, eyes closed and nodding, in Mr. Chwat's office on a recent afternoon, as he encouraged her to test-drive her new accent with cashiers at Macy's before trying it out at work. "Taxi drivers are the best," she said.</p>
        <p>As they read together from a script from an upcoming play Ms. Townsend will be in, Mr. Chwat turned her "dance" into "dahance" and helped her L's to stand up. She too, suffered tongue problems. "It wants to do Italian," Mr. Chwat explained.</p>
        <p>"She's very good, right?" he asked a visitor.</p>
        <p>"He's great!" countered Ms. Townsend, gazing at him in the way some people admire their therapist after a particularly compelling moment of analysis. Critics, an Exception</p>
        <p>Mr. Chwat loves everything about speech therapy ("I consider myself very lucky to have this job") and everybody ("I have a great deal of job satisfaction because people show results very quickly.") Except, occasionally, critics.</p>
        <p>A review in The New York Times of the Robert De Niro film "This Boy's Life," called the actor's "curious accent that sounds as if it had a lot of unexplained Irish in it." That comment infuriated Mr. Chwat, who wrote a letter to the editor detailing the many hours he had spent with Mr. De Niro, flattening his A's and sharpening his R's to make him sound more like the Northwest.</p>
        <p>When asked about it, Mr. Chwat pooh-poohed his irritation. "The reporter must've gotten his notes crossed," he said. "He must have been thinking about his interview with the Scottish director."</p>
        <p>Mr. Chwat is not exceptionally tolerant of those who are critical of accent elimination. He recalled a conference during which some people said that by helping immigrants change their accents, he was attacking cultural heritages.</p>
        <p>"I was, shocked, really outraged," he said. "America pretending to be a democracy is not very respectful of differences in business. Being understood clearly is the priority. Political arguments are cop-outs."</p>
        <p>Mr. Chwat is quick to point out that accents do not reflect intelligence, simply origin, though that alone seems to motivate people to push themselves during a session. When Ms. Townsend was having a problem with her vowels, he hinted that she sounded a bit like Amy Fisher. A flash of horror crossed her face and she quickly corrected it, and moved on to soften her R's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
