<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Mount Vernon, Black Woman Is Rejected for Sake of Diversity</title>
    <meta content="25COUN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1004818"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mount Vernon (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">West, Debra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Watts-Cave, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">City Councils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DE1E38F936A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="1187" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Mount Vernon, Black Woman Is Rejected for Sake of Diversity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA WEST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">West, Debra</byline>
      <dateline>MOUNT VERNON, N.Y., March 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Karen Watts-Cave, who three years ago lost bid for Mount Vernon, NY, City Council by just 105 votes, is rejected for vacancy on council because she is black; city's black Democratic leaders say that they are looking to appoint white person for sake of racial diversity; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three years ago, Karen Watts-Cave lost a bid for the City Council here by just 105 votes. So, when she learned that the woman who had defeated her was leaving, Ms. Watts-Cave quickly sent a note to her party chairman asking to replace her.</p>
        <p>But in an odd twist on affirmative action,  Ms. Watts-Cave, who is black, was told by the black Democratic leaders of this largely black city that she was the wrong color for the job. The Democrats, who control the City Council, wanted to promote a white person, she was told.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three years ago, Karen Watts-Cave lost a bid for the City Council here by just 105 votes. So, when she learned that the woman who had defeated her was leaving, Ms. Watts-Cave quickly sent a note to her party chairman asking to replace her.</p>
        <p>But in an odd twist on affirmative action,  Ms. Watts-Cave, who is black, was told by the black Democratic leaders of this largely black city that she was the wrong color for the job. The Democrats, who control the City Council, wanted to promote a white person, she was told.</p>
        <p>''It's an awkward position for me,'' said Ms. Watts-Cave, 45, a party loyalist and ardent Mount Vernon booster. ''I think perhaps I am in the wrong place at the wrong time.''</p>
        <p>The man who gave her the news, Reginald A. LaFayette, the chairman of the city's Democratic Party, said in an interview this week that he was seeking to keep diversity on the City Council. When the lone white on the five-member City Council, Colleen Duffy, was appointed to a city judgeship last month, Mr. LaFayette openly announced that the position needed to be filled by a white man or woman.</p>
        <p>''I met with district leaders and I said, 'I am going to recommend a white person,' '' said Mr. LaFayette, who is also the City Clerk. ''I don't know why anybody was shocked. The city is not just made up of one ethnic group, and the Council already has one ethnic group. It's not like I just said, 'All good white people apply.' We're looking for a white Democrat who has been active in the community. The most important thing is that the person care about the city of Mount Vernon.''</p>
        <p>Mount Vernon, a city just north of the Bronx with wide streets, gracious homes and pockets of poverty and despair, elected the state's first black Mayor, Ronald A. Blackwood, in 1985. The city's white population has declined during the last two decades and now is about 40 percent. Most live in one small neighborhood, the Fleetwood section.</p>
        <p>Steven D. Horton, the City Council President, recalled long discussions among Democrats who said that a white person could not easily be elected in Mount Vernon anymore. Ms. Duffy, the only white elected official in city government, won in 1995 because she ran on the same slate with Mr. Horton and the popular black Mayor, Ernest D. Davis, Mr. Horton said.</p>
        <p>Party leaders said they feared that unless they appointed a white person, the city would be sued by disgruntled white voters calling for a change from citywide elections for City Council to ward districts based along racial lines. Many communities throughout the country have changed from at-large electoral systems to districts because of suits brought under the Federal Voting Rights Act.</p>
        <p>''Believe me, myself and my colleagues felt like we were in a Fellini movie,'' said Mr. Horton, 42, who is also executive director of the New Rochelle Municipal Housing Authority. ''Here we were, a room full of black leaders sitting around and saying we need to find someone white. It kind of stands the world on its head a bit.''</p>
        <p>A spokesman for the State Attorney General's office said officials had never heard of a similar case and intended to look into its legality.</p>
        <p>An official of the New York Civil Liberties Union called a race-based appointment inappropriate.</p>
        <p>''The Supreme Court has sent down some very strong signals against the use of race as a factor'' in appointments, said Arthur N. Eisenberg, the legal director of the New York Civil Liberties Union, who, coincidentally, grew up in Mount Vernon. ''There is a strong presumption that no matter what the race, it is inappropriate.''</p>
        <p>But so far, it appears few in Mount Vernon's political world are troubled by the decision. Four people, including Ms. Watts-Cave, applied for the part-time position, which pays $18,000 a year, Mr. Horton said. Three of the four are black and were told they would probably not be considered. Mr. LaFayette said that everyone understood and would not ''argue with fairness.'' He said a nomination would be made in April, and then the four City Council members would vote on the nominee.</p>
        <p>Ms. Watts-Cave, a recreation supervisor for the Town of Greenburgh, said she wanted to do what was best for the city. ''I certainly do not want to be a force that said, 'No, you should not include a whole segment of the population in government,' '' she said. ''If the people who are currently on the City Council, who I elected, think this is the right thing to do, than I think it is the right thing to do.''</p>
        <p>While the city government has quietly and without much fuss seen its leadership change from white control to black since Mr. Blackwood was elected, the school board has been embroiled in nasty and seemingly endless racial conflict.</p>
        <p>For nearly 50 years, the school board was controlled by a white majority who were sponsored by the Italian Civic Association. Then last year, a coalition of black school board trustees, sponsored by the Coalition for the Empowerment of People of African Ancestry, won a five-member majority on the nine-member school board. The racial composition of the board may have changed, but the arguments are as heated as ever.</p>
        <p>Anthony Mosca, the former Police Commissioner of both Mount Vernon and Westchester County and now a member of the Board of Education,  said he was surprised that the city's Democratic leaders would favor a white person for the City Council.</p>
        <p>''I was shocked when I heard,'' Mr. Mosca, 58, said. ''But when I thought about it, I thought it was a smart move. The City Council probably gets a lot more work done than we do on the school board.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
