<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Flushing, Home Is Where the Perfect E.R.A. Is</title>
    <meta content="06CHAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/06/sports/06CHAS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1291227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rusch, Glendon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Arizona Diamondbacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Flushing</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Milwaukee</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Montreal</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Chicago</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Houston</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Arizona Diamondbacks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Rusch, Glendon</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Maddux, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E1DF1F38F935A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Flushing, Home Is Where the Perfect E.R.A. Is</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murray Chass column examines why New York Mets pitcher Glendon Rusch has low earned run average at home but abysmal 15.43 in road games; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Maybe it's the air in Flushing. No, on second thought, it can't be the air in Flushing. Maybe it's the rhythmic rumble of the No. 7 train that chugs by periodically beyond the right-field fence. No, cross that one off, too. The planes flying overhead? Be serious. They would pose more of a distraction than anything.</p>
        <p>So why has Glendon Rusch pitched so much more effectively at Shea Stadium this season than he has on the road? He said yesterday he doesn't really know. Furthermore, he said, he doesn't pay any attention to the difference in his results home and away. But how could he not? It is that striking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Maybe it's the air in Flushing. No, on second thought, it can't be the air in Flushing. Maybe it's the rhythmic rumble of the No. 7 train that chugs by periodically beyond the right-field fence. No, cross that one off, too. The planes flying overhead? Be serious. They would pose more of a distraction than anything.</p>
        <p>So why has Glendon Rusch pitched so much more effectively at Shea Stadium this season than he has on the road? He said yesterday he doesn't really know. Furthermore, he said, he doesn't pay any attention to the difference in his results home and away. But how could he not? It is that striking.</p>
        <p>Rusch pitched seven innings against the Arizona Diamondbacks yesterday at Shea, allowing only an unearned run as the Mets won, 8-1. He had made two other starts at Shea this season, pitching seven innings in each of those games, too. And the run the Diamondbacks scored in the third inning yesterday, courtesy primarily of Todd Pratt's catcher's interference and immediately ensuing passed ball, was the first of any kind Rusch had given up at home.</p>
        <p>Only one other major league starter has a 0.00 earned run average at home this season, and his name is more synonymous with a low E.R.A. than Rusch's. Guy name of Greg Maddux. But Maddux has pitched only two games, total of 17 innings, at home. Advantage, Rusch.</p>
        <p>Rusch didn't want to dwell on his perfect home E.R.A.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't mean anything to me,'' he said. He certainly didn't want anyone to compare him with Maddux.  But until one of them gives up an earned run at home (Maddux, too, has permitted an unearned run), their names will be linked on the list of league leaders that is provided daily.</p>
        <p>Where Rusch doesn't appear (Maddux just missed making the list yesterday) is among the leaders in road E.R.A. That's because the dual personality of Rusch's left arm has emerged when he has pitched in alien parks.</p>
        <p>''I'd be much happier,'' he said, ''if I had the same E.R.A. on the road as I do at home.''</p>
        <p>In three games on the road, Rusch has a 15.43 E.R.A., having allowed 16 earned runs in nine and a third innings. He has not lasted more than four innings in any of those starts. He made his two starts before yesterday's in Milwaukee and St. Louis and pitched a total of six and a third innings.</p>
        <p>''I think I did a better job today of staying on the corner down and away, got some ground balls,'' Rusch said. ''I'm obviously not a sinkerball pitcher, but I need to be down and on the outside corner to be successful. I did a better job of that today than I had in the past couple starts.''</p>
        <p>So it's not the air or the noise or some other secret home ingredient, but execution?</p>
        <p>''I feel good here,'' Rusch said. ''I like pitching here. It's a fun place to pitch. I like the fans. They're great. They get into the game. When you get in a jam, they're rooting you on. That's home-field advantage, I guess. In general, Shea is one of the better pitchers' parks in the league. For the most part, the ball doesn't carry really well here.''</p>
        <p>Last month Rusch made two of his first three starts against Montreal. In Montreal he lasted three innings and gave up five runs, all earned. At Shea 11 days later he shut out the Expos for seven innings.</p>
        <p>''My job is to go out and pitch the best I can, whether I'm pitching in Chicago or Houston or New York,'' he said. ''This year, for me, it's been back and forth between the road and home. I don't really think much about it. It's only a month into the season. At the end of the year, if the numbers are that much different at home and on the road, I might be able to explain it, but I don't really think about it too much. It's the same mound, same catcher, same distance. Everything's the same. It's not the same ballpark, but you need to go out and pitch the same no matter where you are.''</p>
        <p>Maybe it's the blades of grass or the reddish infield dirt, the orange and blue and green and red seats. Maybe it's the corny red big apple just on the other side of the center-field fence that rises out of its shell when the Mets hit a home run. Maybe it's the 10 commercial signs on the blue outfield fence or the many other advertisements that adorn various stadium structures or the banners above the right-field fence representing the Mets' six playoff seasons.</p>
        <p>Maybe Rusch should stick a photo of Shea under his cap when he pitches on the road. Maybe he should carry a few blades of infield grass and a pouch of dirt from the mound, too. Don't leave home without it.</p>
        <p>By the way, Glendon, which is the real Rusch, the one with the 0.00 home E.R.A. or the one with the 15.43 road mark?</p>
        <p>''I hope it's the one that's pitching at home,'' he said.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
