<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Faster Than Owl Express, Potter Fans Write Their Own Stories</title>
    <meta content="06POTT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1291081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: RIVERDALE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E6DB1038F935A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="368" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Faster Than Owl Express, Potter Fans Write Their Own Stories</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEENA YELLIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For all Harry Potter's wizardry, he lacks the power to release his books more quickly. So some fans have taken matters into their own hands. Members of the Harry Potter club at SAR Academy, a yeshiva elementary school in Riverdale, are writing what they think should be the sequel to ''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire,'' the fourth volume of the series, published last July. The club members, all sixth graders, meet weekly at lunchtime to read aloud chapters they wrote at home, critique one another's work and propose new ideas.</p>
        <p>''Everybody has really great plots,'' said Chana Wolpoe, adding that she had written so many chapters she had lost count. In one of her versions, American students join Hogwarts because sorcery schools in the United States provide an inferior education.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For all Harry Potter's wizardry, he lacks the power to release his books more quickly. So some fans have taken matters into their own hands. Members of the Harry Potter club at SAR Academy, a yeshiva elementary school in Riverdale, are writing what they think should be the sequel to ''Harry Potter and the Goblet of Fire,'' the fourth volume of the series, published last July. The club members, all sixth graders, meet weekly at lunchtime to read aloud chapters they wrote at home, critique one another's work and propose new ideas.</p>
        <p>''Everybody has really great plots,'' said Chana Wolpoe, adding that she had written so many chapters she had lost count. In one of her versions, American students join Hogwarts because sorcery schools in the United States provide an inferior education.</p>
        <p>Talia Lavin, who has read each of the Potter books about 50 times, has also contributed chapters. Her efforts include a romance between Harry's godfather and a new magic teacher at the school.</p>
        <p>Club members hope to finish their sequel by the end of the school year. J. K. Rowling, the author of the Harry Potter books, is still writing the real one, according to Scholastic, her publisher. Other fans around the country are also busy writing chapters.</p>
        <p>The club was founded last September by Rabbi Moshe Rosenberg, a Talmud teacher.  ''Instead of satisfying their hunger with merchandise and flimsy substitutes, I thought this could be a constructive impetus to get them to use their imaginations and write,'' said the rabbi, who has come up with five chapters himself. ''I think one of my unspoken reasons for making the club is because I felt like writing it myself.''</p>
        <p>As Orthodox writers, some students were tempted to tie Judaism into the plot. But Talia felt there would be too many conflicts between wizardry and Jewish law. ''How would they get kosher food all the way to Hogwarts?'' she asked. The Sabbath poses other questions. ''Can you carry your wand and ride a broomstick on the Sabbath?'' Talia asked.</p>
        <p>DEENA YELLIN</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: RIVERDALE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
