<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gay Church Again Rejected By National Council Group</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="570675"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTIANS AND CHRISTIANITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMOSEXUALITY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL COUNCIL OF CHURCHES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSAL FELLOWSHIP OF METROPOLITAN COMMUNITY CHURCHES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEVESI, DENNIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D8113FF936A25752C1A964958260" item-length="644" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gay Church Again Rejected By National Council Group</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DENNIS HEVESI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HEVESI, DENNIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After more than a decade of trying, a church composed mostly of gay and lesbian congregants has again been rejected in its bid to establish ties with the National Council of Churches, the nation's largest ecumenical organization.</p>
        <p>In a 90-to-81 vote on Thursday at its annual convention in Cleveland, the top policy-making body of the National Council of Churches chose not to grant observer status to the church, the Universal Fellowship of Metropolitan Churches, a denomination that has 50,000 members in 264 congregations around the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After more than a decade of trying, a church composed mostly of gay and lesbian congregants has again been rejected in its bid to establish ties with the National Council of Churches, the nation's largest ecumenical organization.</p>
        <p>In a 90-to-81 vote on Thursday at its annual convention in Cleveland, the top policy-making body of the National Council of Churches chose not to grant observer status to the church, the Universal Fellowship of Metropolitan Churches, a denomination that has 50,000 members in 264 congregations around the country.</p>
        <p>The announcement touched off an emotional demonstration by members of the church at the hotel where the meeting was held, as well as by gay and lesbian representatives from denominations that already belong to the council. The ecumenical officer of the Fellowship of Metropolitan Churches, the Rev. Nancy Wilson, stepped to the microphone in the meeting room and said, "It's easier to get into heaven than into the N.C.C."</p>
        <p>Protesters waved banners throughout the hall and broke into an anthem of the gay rights movement, "Singing for Our Lives." Others lined up at floor microphones to recount how they had left their original churches because they had been made to feel unwelcome.</p>
        <p>The National Council of Churches, composed of Protestant and Eastern Orthodox churches, represents 32 denominations with about 45 million members.  Effort Began in '81</p>
        <p>The Fellowship of Metropolitan Churches first applied for membership in the National Council in 1981, said J. Martin Bailey, a spokesman for the council. A year later, the council's membership committee tabled a decision on the membership application and began talks with members of the denomination.</p>
        <p>Since then, Mr. Bailey said, representatives of the Fellowship have attended every meeting of the council's general board and participated in its programs.</p>
        <p>"Last year, recognizing that the homophobia in the churches of the United States and in society was such that the council would not be able to receive them, they decided that they would apply for observer status in the council," Mr. Bailey said of the Fellowship. It was that application for observer status that the council's general board tabled indefinitely Thursday in favor of continued dialogue with the Fellowship.</p>
        <p>In a written statement, the Fellowship of Metropolitan Churches said that it "can't wait any longer for recognition by the National Council of Churches."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bailey said, "Observer status would have given them, essentially, an opportunity to be present at any meeting without a vote, and they could be invited to speak at any time by the chairperson."  Threats of Defection</p>
        <p>Mr. Bailey said the primary opponents to granting observer status had been the Eastern Orthodox churches, some of the African-American denominations and the Korean Presbyterian Church in the United States. "There were 12 denominations which, according to an informal poll in the corridors, said that if observer status were granted they would be forced to leave the council," he said.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Leonid Kishkovsky, immediate past president of the council and ecumenical officer of the Orthodox Church in America, said that most of the opponents "were trying to articulate the traditional understanding -- and, we feel, Biblical understanding -- of sexual ethics, and particularly that homosexual practice is sinful."</p>
        <p>"There were certainly many who believed that it could seem to imply an affirmation of homosexual practice," Father Kishkovsky added.</p>
        <p>In its written statement, the Fellowship said: "By not recognizing us today as observers, the N.C.C. and its members have taken an unprecedented action to try to deny our very existence. The N.C.C. took its actions in order to preserve the unity of their organization. The result is not Christian unity but unholy and false unity."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
