<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Playoff Protocol: Parcells Wrote Book</title>
    <meta content="30JETS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1073432"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parcells, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litsky, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E4D8123FF933A05751C1A96E958260" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Playoff Protocol: Parcells Wrote Book</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coach Bill Parcells, who will take New York Jets into their first playoffs with him as coach, has long history of success in spurring players to win big games; his current and former players comment on his techniques, including stress on hard practices; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You have heard the litany over and over: the pro football playoffs are starting. It is a new season. The intensity level rises. Players must rise with it or be left behind.</p>
        <p>All of the above are true. And many football people will say that one other truism applies: no coach can get players to rise to the occasion better than Bill Parcells.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You have heard the litany over and over: the pro football playoffs are starting. It is a new season. The intensity level rises. Players must rise with it or be left behind.</p>
        <p>All of the above are true. And many football people will say that one other truism applies: no coach can get players to rise to the occasion better than Bill Parcells.</p>
        <p>In his 13 previous years as a National Football League head coach, notably with two Super Bowl titles with the Giants and an American Football Conference crown with the New England Patriots, Parcells has made his players understand how to win the big games, especially the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Now he faces the same task with his Jets, who take a 12-4 record into their playoff game on Jan. 10, their first with Parcells as the coach.</p>
        <p>How does Parcells get his players to become more intense?</p>
        <p>Listen to Carl Banks and Steve DeOssie, who played for him in the past, and Pepper Johnson, David Meggett and Keith Byars, key players for him then and now. They remember what Parcells did before and think they know how he will prepare the Jets for the playoffs.</p>
        <p>''Everybody says you have to step it up a notch now,'' Johnson said, ''but we've been pushing it the last five or six weeks. You don't have to push any more. You know how long we've been waiting for this? He won't let anybody slack up now.</p>
        <p>''We've gotten better because we practice hard. A lot of teams are like a country club. Our practices are physical. I remember Bill saying years ago: 'There are 28 teams in this league. If we practice harder than the other 27, we will win.' ''</p>
        <p>In Johnson's rookie season of 1986, the Giants won Super Bowl XXI.</p>
        <p>''Phil Simms and Harry Carson and other veterans told us then that the intensity rises, the sense of urgency rises and it better rise with everyone,'' Johnson said. ''Because if those other guys on your team aren't fighting as hard as you are, it doesn't matter how hard you're trying. We aren't there yet. We aren't anywhere. Joe Namath has a Super Bowl ring with the Jets. We don't.''</p>
        <p>Banks, an old Giants hero, is now in the Jets' front office.</p>
        <p>''At playoff time your attention has to go up another notch,'' he said. ''It just doesn't happen quickly. You build all year. This time of year he lets you know it isn't O.K. if you drop a ball, that mistakes are not O.K. because it's a one-game elimination.</p>
        <p>''He'll tell you he won't take a chance on you in the playoffs if he's not sure. He'll say point blank, 'If you're not ready, I'm not going to play you.' That's not a passing comment. That's in your face. If you're not practicing well, you're in trouble.''</p>
        <p>Banks remembered his rookie season in 1984, when the Giants played a wild-card playoff game in Los Angeles against the Rams.</p>
        <p>''I was on the punt-return team,'' he said, ''and I drew a roughing penalty. Bill shot me a look and he followed me off the field with his eyes until I got to the bench. Then he said: 'You sit there the rest of the game. Don't move.' I was sure I was going to lose my job. He just wanted me to know penalties are unacceptable this time of the year. I didn't ever want to see that look again, and I don't think I ever did that again.''</p>
        <p>Meggett said Parcells did not climb over veterans who had been through the playoff grind.</p>
        <p>''To some of us,'' Meggett said, ''he doesn't do much. He lets you exercise your responsibilities because he feels confident in you. He hasn't treated the younger guys different yet, and I'm not sure if he will. I don't think they need a whole lot of minding. Guys on this team don't. They've been playing big games. But Bill Parcells is going to be Bill Parcells. He's a different coach at playoff time.''</p>
        <p>DeOssie, now a sports broadcaster in Boston, said Parcells's preparation involved a building process rather than flicking a switch.</p>
        <p>''The way they played Buffalo the week before last, so physically, that was a step up,'' DeOssie said. ''He tries to make you understand the closer you get to the playoffs, the more you've got to step up, even if you think you have stepped up already.</p>
        <p>''Every day, he puts pressure on guys a little more. He'll rely on Pepper Johnson, Curtis Martin, Bryan Cox and Dave Meggett, guys who have playoff experience. He'll get them to explain to the other guys what's going on.''</p>
        <p>DeOssie recalled when the Giants won Super Bowl XXV in Jumbo Elliott's second pro season.</p>
        <p>''Jumbo had to play against Richard Dent and Pierce Holt in the playoffs and Bruce Smith in the Super Bowl,'' DeOssie said. ''I remember Bill telling Jumbo: 'What we do in the playoffs depends on you. If you play up to your capabilities, we will win the Super Bowl. It's all on you.' Bill was on him every day, and Jumbo responded and dominated those three great defensive ends. Jumbo got edgy, but you want your guys on edge. Football is not a game for the relaxed.''</p>
        <p>Byars said that Parcells has made it easy to understand why he does what he does.</p>
        <p>''If you don't keep winning in the playoffs,'' Byars said, ''some people say, 'Wait till next year.' But next year never comes. You've got to start meeting the opportunities now.''</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
