<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mayor Sticks to Shelter Plan Aimed at Councilman</title>
    <meta content="30HOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1073416"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dibrienza, Stephen (Councilman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E2D9123FF933A05751C1A96E958260" item-length="1111" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mayor Sticks to Shelter Plan Aimed at Councilman</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City officials, after day of mixed signals, stand by plan to evict state-run psychiatric center from city-owned Brooklyn building and open homeless shelter there; Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani says site was chosen for shelter because Councilman Stephen DiBrienza, who represents area, sponsored bill regulating homeless shelters; DiBrienza holds city has empty beds in existing shelters and does not need new ones; says Council will amend bill to make sure it does not force existing large shelters to close (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a day of mixed signals, officials in the Giuliani administration said last night that they were standing by their plan to evict a state-run psychiatric center from a city-owned building in Brooklyn and open a homeless shelter there.</p>
        <p>The officials said they would help the state find a new location for the center before forcing it out of the building, at 250 Baltic Street in Cobble Hill, sometime next month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a day of mixed signals, officials in the Giuliani administration said last night that they were standing by their plan to evict a state-run psychiatric center from a city-owned building in Brooklyn and open a homeless shelter there.</p>
        <p>The officials said they would help the state find a new location for the center before forcing it out of the building, at 250 Baltic Street in Cobble Hill, sometime next month.</p>
        <p>At an afternoon news conference, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani acknowledged that the site was chosen for a new shelter because the neighborhood's Council representative, Stephen DiBrienza, sponsored legislation regulating homeless shelters.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, as members of the City Council were loudly assailing the plan to evict the psychiatric center, it looked as if the Giuliani administration might back down. Several city and state officials said that the eviction papers had been served in error and that the psychiatric center would be able to take as much time as it needed to relocate.</p>
        <p>But at the end of the day, Joseph J. Lhota, the Deputy Mayor for Operations, said the eviction order, which requires the psychiatric center to vacate the Baltic Street building by late January, remained firmly in place. ''We have got to start this process,'' he said in an interview. ''This is the first of many new homeless shelters that we will be building due to population demands.'' Mr. Lhota said the psychiatric center should not have been surprised by the eviction notice because the city had informed it two weeks ago that it would have to relocate eventually.</p>
        <p>The administration's decision to evict the psychiatric center was the latest twist in an unusually dramatic confrontation between the Mayor and the Council, focused on Mr. DiBrienza's bill regulating homeless shelters.</p>
        <p>The Mayor adamantly opposed the measure, objecting in particular to a provision that limited the size of most shelters to 200 beds. There are seven shelters in New York that have more than 200 beds, and Mr. Giuliani warned that he would have to order as many as six of them shut to comply with the law.</p>
        <p>Council members insisted that the bill was written in a way to insure that none of those shelters would have to close. But Mr. Giuliani warned them that if they passed the bill over his veto, he would build new shelters in the districts of Council members who defied him.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, both Mr. Giuliani and Mr. Lhota said their decision to put the homeless shelter in Mr. DiBrienza's district was indeed sparked by the Councilman's support of the bill.</p>
        <p>''The City Council member there is the City Council member who sponsored the limitation on the number of people in homeless shelters,'' Mr. Giuliani said at the news conference. ''So the assumption is that he's speaking for his community -- that his community in essence supports what he did, otherwise he wouldn't be their City Council member.''</p>
        <p>Councilman DiBrienza and several other politicians insisted yesterday that the city did not need new homeless shelters. More than 400 of the 7,352 beds in the city's homeless shelters are now empty, Mr. DiBrienza said, and by ordering a new shelter to be opened in Cobble Hill, the Mayor was practicing ''the politics of personal punishment.''</p>
        <p>The psychiatric center, affiliated with the state's South Beach Psychiatric Facility on Staten Island, has provided medicine and counseling to about 500 mentally disabled people a week for almost 25 years. In addition to the center, the building on Baltic Street houses a center for the elderly and a community board office, the Councilman said.</p>
        <p>''I am at a loss to understand what is going on here,'' Mr. DiBrienza said in a hastily convened news conference yesterday. ''It's bewildering, particularly because there is no need for a single additional shelter.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DiBrienza's bill set off a fierce battle between the Council and Mr. Giuliani, who said the legislation was an intrusion into his executive powers. He vetoed it on Dec. 7, accusing the Council of trying to micromanage the city's Department of Homeless Services by imposing such ''burdensome and unnecessary'' rules on it as requiring quarterly reports by the department and mandating case management for shelter residents. But Mr. Giuliani's strongest objection -- which he did not bring up until the day before the Council voted to override his veto of the bill -- was to the provision that limited the size of most shelters to 200 beds.</p>
        <p>The Council plans to pass an amendment early next month to make sure that the bill will not force existing shelters to close, Mr. DiBrienza said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lhota acknowledged yesterday that the amendment would ''remedy the poor draftsmanship of the original bill'' and allow most of the city's existing large shelters to remain open.</p>
        <p>But two shelters -- one at the Kingsbridge Armory in the Bronx, with 107 beds, and the 30th Street Men's Shelter in Manhattan, with 850 beds -- were scheduled to close anyway, Mr. Lhota said. The Mayor's office referred questions about why those two shelters were closing to the city's Homeless Services Department. Susan Wiviott, a spokeswoman for the department, declined to provide an explanation.</p>
        <p>As news of the eviction spread yesterday, people affiliated with the psychiatric center predicted dire consequences. Because of zoning regulations, it would be nearly impossible to find a new location in Cobble Hill, they said. And if the center moved out of the neighborhood, many of the mentally ill people who attended its programs would stop seeking treatment, they said.</p>
        <p>''If you take away the building that these people are used to visiting every day for their treatment, they will regress and their attendance will drop off dramatically,'' said Ralph Perfetto, president of the Board of Visitors for the South Beach Psychiatric Facility, which monitors South Beach's outpatient centers. ''They will be the ones to suffer because of this fight between the Mayor and the Council.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lhota said the psychiatric center, which is run by the State Office of Mental Health, would have no problem finding a new site nearby. ''We will continue working with the state to find a location for the facility,'' he said, ''and it will probably be in the same community that they are currently in.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
