<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Things to Sing About</title>
    <meta content="21LOTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="63" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1287620"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="FOR YOUNG VIEWERS"/>
      <identified-content/>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7D61030F931A15757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="280" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Things to Sing About</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kathryn Shattuck</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Sheira and Loli's Super Duper Dittydoodler Special'' will welcome a new cast of characters into the musical world of Professor Eeky Eeky Kronk (Steve Roberts, above center) and the Funkins this morning at 8:30 on Channel 21. Among the newcomers are Molly the artist (Gia Henderson, next to the professor) and her sidekick, Doodles; Toot and Whistle, who sound off when something big is about to happen; and Zippy the Kwirk, a chaotic creature who threatens to ruin the fun for everyone.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Sheira and Loli's Super Duper Dittydoodler Special'' will welcome a new cast of characters into the musical world of Professor Eeky Eeky Kronk (Steve Roberts, above center) and the Funkins this morning at 8:30 on Channel 21. Among the newcomers are Molly the artist (Gia Henderson, next to the professor) and her sidekick, Doodles; Toot and Whistle, who sound off when something big is about to happen; and Zippy the Kwirk, a chaotic creature who threatens to ruin the fun for everyone.</p>
        <p>Starring Sheira and Loli, the twins with a twist, ''Dittydoodle Works'' -- short musical segments positioned throughout WLIW's children's programming blocks -- have been encouraging young viewers to find their voices and sing out strong since they were introduced last fall. The special is a step toward ''Dittydoodle Works'' becoming the station's first exclusive series in spring 2002, with a curriculum that focuses on rhyming, spelling, counting, creative play and art.</p>
        <p>Of course, the heart of ''Dittydoodle Works'' -- music -- will not be forgotten, especially since the songs of Sheira and Loli are written and performed by the real-life twin sisters Sheira Rosenberg and Leora Mechanic, award-winning songwriters based in the New York area.</p>
        <p>Roy Hammond, the show's executive producer with cory Rosenberg, Sheira's husband, expects great things from his duo of mop-tops. ''I think the appeal is that the characters are very wholesome and the music is absolutely terrific,'' he said. ''The Funkins are the things the kids really love, but the parents love the ditties.''</p>
        <p>Kathryn Shattuck</p>
        <p>FOR YOUNG VIEWERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
