<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Safety for Those Who Wander</title>
    <meta content="22CLAS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1287406"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retirement Communities and Assisted Living</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alzheimer's Disease</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Yonkers (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Memory Support and Alzheimer's Care Center (Yonkers, Ny)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuchs, Marek</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Alzheimer's</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement Communities and Assisted Living</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alzheimer's Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DA1730F931A15757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1191" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Safety for Those Who Wander</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAREK FUCHS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuchs, Marek</byline>
      <dateline>YONKERS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Memory Support and Alzheimer's Care Center in Classic Residence by Hyatt, housing complex for elderly in Yonkers, NY; center, which opened in September and is secure facility devoted to those suffering from Alzheimer's disease, described; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE glass memory boxes lead them home.</p>
        <p>Beside the doors where doorbells would normally be, the boxes are filled with mementos so meaningful that, despite the disease that preys upon the residents' minds, there are still glimmers of recognition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE glass memory boxes lead them home.</p>
        <p>Beside the doors where doorbells would normally be, the boxes are filled with mementos so meaningful that, despite the disease that preys upon the residents' minds, there are still glimmers of recognition.</p>
        <p>These boxes are in the Memory Support and Alzheimer's Care Center in Classic Residence by Hyatt, a housing complex for the elderly in Yonkers.</p>
        <p>Walking the halls, you see in the boxes an enlarged photo of a grandchild whose eyes follow you, a King of Hearts playing card, family photos taken when everyone was well, stuffed animals and photos of parents from the early 1900's, faded but still able to grab the attention of their children, in spite of Alzheimer's.</p>
        <p>Built as a joint venture with Forest City, a development and management company, the 18-story Classic Residence offers several levels of assisted living. The second floor, which opened in September, is devoted entirely to those who suffer from Alzheimer's, a disease of the mind.</p>
        <p>Each resident has his own studio apartment. Since the memory boxes don't always work, there is a different color carpet in front of each door. And if the color-coded carpet fails, a staff member will help residents find their way home. Although furnishings are available from Classic Residence, most residents bring their own.</p>
        <p>Since those with Alzheimer's frequently wander, the floor is secure. The hallways are set up in jagged formation, so that the patients will have a better feel of movement than they would by simply pacing back and forth in a straight hall.</p>
        <p>Besides being served their food, residents are reminded to snack when they pass the refrigerators, which have glass fronts. There are no busy patterns, which would serve only to confuse.</p>
        <p>And since people with Alzheimer's are commonly afraid of crowds, the floor is divided into wings or ''neighborhoods.'' There is the ''Upper West Side,'' the ''Upper East Side,'' ''Midtown'' and ''Times Square.'' Even within the neighborhoods, gathering spots are divided into small areas to keep crowds to a minimum. Right now, only one wing is occupied; six people live there. As more residents move in, the other wings will open. The floor can accommodate 36 residents with Alzheimer's.</p>
        <p>Lorrin Johnson's 80-year-old mother, Sheila Levine, came here after living alone proved unworkable. She was leaving the toaster on, couldn't make phone calls and was wandering out of the house. Mrs. Johnson realized that unless she devoted her life to taking care of her, she could not keep her safe. ''Being a caretaker,'' Mrs. Johnson said, ''is an overwhelming task.''</p>
        <p>There was a problem when Mrs. Levine first came to Classic Residence: she kept putting on clothes. No matter what she was wearing, if she saw another outfit, she would put it on. Mrs. Johnson said Classic Residence worked with her to solve this problem. The staff rebuilt Mrs. Levine's armoire. Now, only a day's worth of clothes hang in the smaller portion of the armoire, which is unlocked; the rest of her clothes are locked away on the other side.</p>
        <p>Small touches make the floor more comfortable for residents. Each apartment door, for example, has a lock. Though it does not work, it gives the resident a feeling of safety and privacy. The nursing staff wears recognizable uniforms, but stays clear of traditional white, which would make the floor feel like a hospital. And since it's sometimes easier for those with Alzheimer's to have their food cut for them, the staff will cut their food but then reassemble it so it looks as it should.</p>
        <p>Steve Cohen, the executive director of Classic Residence, explained that though there is a full medical staff, Classic Residence is modeled after a hotel rather than a hospital. This is especially important for Alzheimer's patients, who are frequently in good health otherwise. As Mrs. Johnson said, ''My mother's not ill other than Alzheimer's,'' so taking care of her is more of a managerial task than a medical one.</p>
        <p>Until a decade ago, Mr. Cohen managed hotels, but found it unfulfilling. Relationships with customers were ''brief and disjointed.'' So he joined the growing numbers of hoteliers who run retirement homes and is very happy.</p>
        <p>''One thing about a retirement community,'' he said, ''they'll hug you.''</p>
        <p>Vivian Apuzzo has spent nearly her whole life in Yonkers, across the street from where Classic Residence now stands. She opposed its construction because it would block her view.</p>
        <p>''It was up to the sky,'' she said.</p>
        <p>By the time it opened, her 95-year-old mother, who has Alzheimer's, Rose DeSimone, was in a nursing home for what Mrs. Apuzzo hoped would be a short stay until she could renovate her house so her mother could move in.</p>
        <p>In the nursing home, her mother seemed like ''a number,'' Mrs. Apuzzo said. It was also very medically oriented, ''but she needed custodial care, not skilled nursing.''</p>
        <p>In the end, it was impossible to adapt her home. ''I have lots of steps in my house and I'm a senior citizen myself,'' she explained. So Mrs. Apuzzo went to Classic Residence and ''asked them please to evaluate Mama.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. DeSimone soon moved in, and Mrs. Apuzzo says that both she and her mother became part of the community on the floor.  She said that she has made friends with family members of other residents and that the staff knows her well. She also goes on trips with residents, who are taken by bus to shop or visit museums.</p>
        <p>Her mother has thrived. She even enjoys physical therapy, though Mrs. Apuzzo is quick to point out that it's not the exercise she likes. ''She loves the therapists, because they are young men.''</p>
        <p>With her mother across the street, she said that though most people call it a ''nursing home or assisted living center or an Alzheimer's unit, I always say that it was a building built for my mother.'' She hopes to celebrate her mother's 100th birthday there.</p>
        <p>The specialized service comes at a price.  After praising the Alzheimer's floor effusively, Mrs. Johnson notes its cost. The monthly fee ranges from $4,575 to $5,000, with a special-care option for those who need it adding $950 a month.</p>
        <p>During a visit, only one thing was amiss.  It was raining outside, but a board where news is posted featured a smiling sun on it next to the word ''warm'' in capital letters. Had someone neglected to change it?</p>
        <p>''No,'' Mr. Cohen said, before motioning quietly toward all six Alzheimer's sufferers, eating dinner together in a common dining room. ''For them, we always let it be warm and sunny.''</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
