<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Randolph Says He's Doubtful Team Will Prevail on Protest</title>
    <meta content="02TARP$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/02/sports/baseball/02tarp.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1669490"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Randolph, Willie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E5DB1F31F931A35756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Randolph Says He's Doubtful Team Will Prevail on Protest</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Randolph Doubtful His Protest Will Take</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY GLIER</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph did not sound optimistic about his protest of the Mets' rain-shortened 5-3 loss to the Washington Nationals on Saturday night at R.F.K. Stadium.</p>
        <p>Randolph was upset about the grounds crew's inability to put the tarpaulin on the field during an eighth-inning downpour. The game was called and ruled official before the Mets had their final turn at bat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph did not sound optimistic about his protest of the Mets' rain-shortened 5-3 loss to the Washington Nationals on Saturday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Manager Willie Randolph did not sound optimistic about his protest of the Mets' rain-shortened 5-3 loss to the Washington Nationals on Saturday night at R.F.K. Stadium.</p>
        <p>Randolph was upset about the grounds crew's inability to put the tarpaulin on the field during an eighth-inning downpour. The game was called and ruled official before the Mets had their final turn at bat.</p>
        <p>''It was just the formality of filing,'' he said. ''It'll get to whoever it gets to, I guess. I've turned the page on that. I'm not going to make a big deal about it; I don't believe in all that.''</p>
        <p>The grounds crew poured one and a half tons of a drying agent, Soilmaster Red, on the dirt playing surface to soak up some of the rainfall, which lasted for much of the game.</p>
        <p>When it was apparent that the absorbent would not be a remedy, the crew was ordered to pull the rain-soaked tarpaulin over the field, but the job took 31 minutes.</p>
        <p>The Mets filed a protest Sunday, claiming a violation of Rule 4.16, which says, ''A game shall be forfeited to the visiting team if after it has been suspended, the orders of the umpire to the groundskeeper respecting preparation of the field for resumption of play are not complied with.''</p>
        <p>The Mets had been down, 5-0, but rallied in the downpour in the top of the eighth on Cliff Floyd's two-out three-run double. After the last out of the half-inning, the crew chief, Joe West, suspended play and ordered the tarp on the infield.</p>
        <p>But by the time the tarp was installed, the infield had become a quagmire. West called the game after a 37-minute delay, deeming the field unplayable.</p>
        <p>''If the grounds crew had defied me and not tried to put the tarp on, then, yes, I would have had grounds to declare a forfeit,'' West said. ''They didn't do that. Everybody saw how hard they were trying to get the tarp on the field.''</p>
        <p>Washington Manager Frank Robinson was ejected after arguing that the game should have been stopped because of the rain before the Mets' three-run rally in the top of the eighth. Robinson, as well as the Mets, complained that the field was dangerous.</p>
        <p>''The only pitcher that complained was Mike DeJean,'' West said. ''We asked players, what do you want us to do? Tell us, let us know what do you think. If they had said there is a problem, we would have stopped it and fixed it. If they would have said the resin is too wet, we would have gotten them another one.''</p>
        <p>The game was also suspended for 30 minutes in the sixth, and the field was covered. When the rain slowed, then stopped, West ordered that the tarp be taken off so play could resume.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Mets right fielder Mike Cameron had one hit in three at-bats for the Class A St. Lucie Mets on Sunday as he continued his rehabilitation assignment. Cameron also walked in the 11-10 loss to the Daytona Cubs. More important, he did not feel any pain in his left wrist. Cameron has not played this season because of tendinitis in the wrist.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
