<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Russian Main Course Served With a French Dessert</title>
    <meta content="02BALT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/02/arts/music/02balt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1669382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Symphony</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Midgette, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kremer, Gidon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Classical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Classical Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Baltimore Symphony Orchestra</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E1D61E31F931A35756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Russian Main Course Served With a French Dessert</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Russian Main Course Served With a French Dessert</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anne Midgette reviews Baltimore Symphony concert featuring violinist Gidon Kremer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were two concerts at Carnegie Hall on Friday night. Both were presented under a single rubric: the Baltimore Symphony Orchestra comes to town. The first was a satisfying, delightful program featuring the violinist Gidon Kremer in ''Lonesome,'' an evocative recent piece by Giya Kancheli, and Shostakovich's First Violin Concerto. The second took place after the intermission and consisted of not-very-impressive performances of Debussy's ''La Mer'' and Ravel's ''La Valse,'' which the Baltimore's music director, Yuri Temirkanov, conducted as if they had both been written by Tchaikovsky.</p>
        <p>It was too bad that these two concerts were presented as one. A listener might have left happy and enthusiastic at intermission, but the French part of the evening left a sour taste.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A listener might have left happy and enthusiastic with the performances of works by Giya Kancheli and Shostakovich, but the French part of the Friday's program left a sour taste.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were two concerts at Carnegie Hall on Friday night. Both were presented under a single rubric: the Baltimore Symphony Orchestra comes to town. The first was a satisfying, delightful program featuring the violinist Gidon Kremer in ''Lonesome,'' an evocative recent piece by Giya Kancheli, and Shostakovich's First Violin Concerto. The second took place after the intermission and consisted of not-very-impressive performances of Debussy's ''La Mer'' and Ravel's ''La Valse,'' which the Baltimore's music director, Yuri Temirkanov, conducted as if they had both been written by Tchaikovsky.</p>
        <p>It was too bad that these two concerts were presented as one. A listener might have left happy and enthusiastic at intermission, but the French part of the evening left a sour taste.</p>
        <p>One wonders at times what the function is, in today's world, of midsized American orchestras like the Baltimore. The first half of the program seemed to provide a clear answer: to bring fine musicians together to offer compelling performances of compelling music. Mr. Kancheli's piece lived up to its name, sending out mournful, wistful tendrils of sound, evoking the minor sonorities of a cowboy ballad, building on slim beginnings into massed orchestral outpourings -- now hopeful, now despairing, generally lyrical. Mr. Kremer manages to be at once virtuosic and self-effacing, pulling himself into the music so that even the fierce fiddling in the extended cadenza of the Shostakovich remains more than a tightrope act. It didn't hurt that Mr. Temirkanov lived up to his reputation as a leading Shostakovich interpreter.</p>
        <p>But the second half of the evening showed a decent but not great orchestra in a couple of familiar pieces, and the point of the exercise was less clear. The orchestra just didn't sound good enough to be playing ''La Mer'' at Carnegie Hall. Landing a major player like Mr. Temirkanov as music director looked like a big coup for Baltimore when it happened in 2000, but it seemed possible, listening to a performance of ''La Mer'' that was a little routine, even leathery, that he has not achieved a particularly meaningful connection with these players. Communication makes up for a lot, particularly at this level, and it wasn't clear that it was taking place. For all of Mr. Temirkanov's dramatic sweeps and sensitive phrasing, the strings sounded dry, the brass two-dimensional and Debussy's ocean lacked its signature mysterious shimmer. And the Ravel was less elegant than simply strident.</p>
        <p>In showcasing recent works, the Baltimore still excels; Mr. Temirkanov is not renowned for his work with contemporary music, but the Kancheli was the best thing on the program. However, an orchestra like the Baltimore must also serve a museum function, presenting the famous classical pieces its audience wants to hear. That is supposed to be Mr. Temirkanov's strong suit, but from this evidence, a little remedial curating may be in order.</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
