<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraqis Getting Together</title>
    <meta content="24thu1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/24/opinion/24thu1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1719958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Arab League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE1D91631F937A15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraqis Getting Together</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Iraqis Getting Together</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Iraqi Factions Seek Timetable for U.S. Pullout'' is hardly the kind of headline the White House wants to read these days. But it refers to a joint statement by Arab Shiite, Arab Sunni and Kurdish political leaders at a conference sponsored by the Arab League in Cairo this week that represents one of the more encouraging developments in Iraqi politics in quite some time.</p>
        <p>That it was, remarkably, agreed to by all three ethnic and religious factions raises hopes that these same groups might yet be able to agree on mutually acceptable constitutional amendments after next month's parliamentary elections. Almost as heartening, it came as the result of the most constructive and successful effort so far by Iraq's Arab neighbors to assume some responsibility for guiding Iraq toward a peaceful political settlement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The conference sponsored by the Arab League in Cairo was a notable step in the right direction that now needs to be followed up.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Iraqi Factions Seek Timetable for U.S. Pullout'' is hardly the kind of headline the White House wants to read these days. But it refers to a joint statement by Arab Shiite, Arab Sunni and Kurdish political leaders at a conference sponsored by the Arab League in Cairo this week that represents one of the more encouraging developments in Iraqi politics in quite some time.</p>
        <p>That it was, remarkably, agreed to by all three ethnic and religious factions raises hopes that these same groups might yet be able to agree on mutually acceptable constitutional amendments after next month's parliamentary elections. Almost as heartening, it came as the result of the most constructive and successful effort so far by Iraq's Arab neighbors to assume some responsibility for guiding Iraq toward a peaceful political settlement.</p>
        <p>And finally, it filled in no specific dates for the desired timetable, thereby bridging the gap between Sunnis, who favor an early pullout, and Shiites, who want to see any American withdrawal tightly linked to the achievement of clear security milestones, including the recruitment and training of capable Iraqi security forces. In the past, that kind of difference would have guaranteed bitter divisions. This time, both sides made crucial efforts to draft acceptable compromise language.</p>
        <p>It is, of course, easier to draft vaguely worded statements at international conferences than it is to work out tough practical issues like power-sharing, minority and women's rights, and relations between civil and religious law at home. The situation on the ground in Iraq these days is scarcely encouraging. But the Cairo conference was a notable step in the right direction that now needs to be followed up, both in the discussions on constitutional revision and in a larger, Arab League-sponsored conference scheduled to take place inside Iraq next February.</p>
        <p>This page has not supported a precipitous United States troop withdrawal from Iraq based on an arbitrary American timetable. We have encouraged Iraqis to recognize the need for speedy, measurable progress in taking control of their own security, and for a spirit of constructive compromise in agreeing on constitutional amendments to guarantee democracy, human rights and national inclusiveness.</p>
        <p>At least some Iraqi leaders now seem to be moving in that direction.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
