<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets' Owner Tells Players That Edwards Will Stay Put</title>
    <meta content="24johnson" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/24/sports/football/24johnson.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1720000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crouse, Karen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Woody</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edwards, Herman</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Woody</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Edwards, Herman</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E0D81631F937A15752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="726" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets' Owner Tells Players That Edwards Will Stay Put</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jets Owner Says Edwards Will Remain</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN CROUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crouse, Karen</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Nov. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>JETS' OWNER TELLS PLAYERS THAT EDWARDS WILL STAY</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After being buffeted for days by rumors that their coach may bolt for Kansas City after this season, the Jets received a welcome reprieve Wednesday. The team's owner, Woody Johnson, usually a behind-the-scenes presence, stepped forward after practice to vigorously reassure his players that Coach Herman Edwards was not going anywhere.</p>
        <p>''He told us Herm's staying, and that's what it is,'' linebacker Jonathan Vilma said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Jets' owner stepped forward after practice Wednesday to vigorously reassure his players that Coach Herman Edwards was not going anywhere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After being buffeted for days by rumors that their coach may bolt for Kansas City after this season, the Jets received a welcome reprieve Wednesday. The team's owner, Woody Johnson, usually a behind-the-scenes presence, stepped forward after practice to vigorously reassure his players that Coach Herman Edwards was not going anywhere.</p>
        <p>''He told us Herm's staying, and that's what it is,'' linebacker Jonathan Vilma said.</p>
        <p>Among the players, Johnson's pronouncement had roughly the same impact as if he had informed them that Thanksgiving would still be celebrated. Center Pete Kendall and other players said that they assumed Edwards was coming back because he told them last week that he intended to honor his contract, which runs through 2007.</p>
        <p>''I had asked Herm myself last week because the rumors were something that was eating at me,'' receiver Laveranues Coles said. ''And he said, 'I'm not going anywhere.' Those were his exact words. And I slept easy.''</p>
        <p>The other clouds hovering over the 2-8 Jets will not be so easily dispersed. They have 10 players on injured reserve and are so thin on offense that their starting tight end, Doug Jolley, is also their emergency quarterback.</p>
        <p>Johnson's announcement appeared largely for the benefit of the news media. He speaks to his players on a regular basis, but it had been at least two years since Johnson had granted a group interview at the team's practice facility.</p>
        <p>''I think he's performed fabulously,'' Johnson said of Edwards, who had a 35-29 record in his first four seasons at the helm of the Jets. The Jets made the playoffs in three of those seasons. ''We're not winning, but he's doing everything he can to win, and I think the team's doing everything they can.''</p>
        <p>Johnson bought the team in 2000, the year before Edwards became coach, with the stated goal of ending the cynicism and negativity that had taken root during three decades of nonchampionship seasons.</p>
        <p>''You don't want to lose,'' Johnson said, ''but losing is inevitable if you're in this sport long enough. What Herm is doing is trying to build a culture of winning. If we have a bad year, we're still building the culture.''</p>
        <p>Johnson added: ''We're trying to do everything we can to win. I have confidence that with this coaching staff, they will give it everything they have and the players will give it everything they have.''</p>
        <p>Johnson declined to discuss the possibility of awarding Edwards a contract extension now, the better to stave off possible suitors later.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to talk about contracts and so on,'' Johnson said. ''I can't make it any clearer. I think Herm's great. I think he's been great for this team. I personally like him. I think the players respond to him.''</p>
        <p>Johnson will not get an argument from Coles, who was traded back to the Jets in March after leaving for Washington as a free agent after the 2002 season.</p>
        <p>''I just don't see myself playing for many other coaches,'' Coles said. ''I've taken a walk on the wild side by leaving. Now I'm back and it's like, O.K., now I'm back with the guy. Let me stay with him. If I could finish my career playing for him, I think I'd be all right.''</p>
        <p>The Jets practiced in pads Wednesday. That they did so with smiles was a tribute to Edwards, Coles said.</p>
        <p>''He makes you feel good about doing tough things,'' Coles said. ''That's what I think makes him the exceptional coach that he is. In times of crisis, he's still cool, he's still excited about us competing and playing ball. He's still pushing us forward.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
