<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'The Life,' 'Steel Pier' and 'Chicago' Lead the Pack in Tony Nominations</title>
    <meta content="06TONY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19970508T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="927936"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gems, Pam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hare, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uhry, Alfred</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foote, Horton</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Life, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Steel Pier (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Titanic (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Juan Darien (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chicago (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Candide (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Stanley (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Skylight (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Last Night of Ballyhoo, the (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Young Man From Atlanta, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/Tony Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tony Awards (Theater Awards)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E4DE1330F935A35756C0A961958260" item-length="1577" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'The Life,' 'Steel Pier' and 'Chicago' Lead the Pack in Tony Nominations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GRIMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nominations for Tony Awards are announced; two new American musicals, The Life and Steel Pier, each collect more than 10 nominations, while Titanic and Juan Darien receive five nominations each; among musical revivals, highly acclaimed Chicago receives eight nominations, while Candide receives four; in nonmusical plays, two plays from Britain, Pam Gems's Stanley and David Hare's Skylight, get nominations for best play as well as for best actor, best actress and best director; also nominated for best play are Alfred Uhry's The Last Night of Ballyhoo and Horton Foote's The Young Man From Atlanta; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a theater season teeming with new American musicals, ''The Life'' and ''Steel Pier'' broke away from the pack when the nominations for this year's Tony Awards were announced yesterday. Each of the shows collected more than 10 nominations, far outdistancing their nearest competitors among the new musicals, ''Titanic'' and ''Juan Darien,'' which received five nominations each. Among musical revivals, the highly acclaimed ''Chicago'' received eight nominations, double the total for its nearest rival, ''Candide.''</p>
        <p>In nonmusical plays, the British, true to form, made a strong showing, picking up two of the four nominations for best play, with Pam Gems's ''Stanley'' and David Hare's ''Skylight''; three nominations for best actor; two for best actress, and three for best director.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a theater season teeming with new American musicals, ''The Life'' and ''Steel Pier'' broke away from the pack when the nominations for this year's Tony Awards were announced yesterday. Each of the shows collected more than 10 nominations, far outdistancing their nearest competitors among the new musicals, ''Titanic'' and ''Juan Darien,'' which received five nominations each. Among musical revivals, the highly acclaimed ''Chicago'' received eight nominations, double the total for its nearest rival, ''Candide.''</p>
        <p>In nonmusical plays, the British, true to form, made a strong showing, picking up two of the four nominations for best play, with Pam Gems's ''Stanley'' and David Hare's ''Skylight''; three nominations for best actor; two for best actress, and three for best director.</p>
        <p>Two new American plays, ''The Last Night of Ballyhoo'' by Alfred Uhry and ''The Young Man From Atlanta'' by Horton Foote, won best-play nominations and accounted for five acting nominations.</p>
        <p>The awards will be given out during a nationally televised ceremony on June 1. The nominations, announced by Alec Baldwin, Rosie O'Donnell and Raquel Welch at Sardi's restaurant in the theater district, included only a few mild surprises, in stark contrast to last year's nominations, which entirely overlooked ''Big,'' the season's most expensive musical, and touched off a furor by limiting ''Victor/Victoria'' to one nomination. Julie Andrews, nominated as best actress in a musical, withdrew her name in protest.</p>
        <p>''It looks like a very fair list, given the season, which had a lot of shows and no one musical production standing out, except 'Chicago,' '' said James Freydberg, the producer of ''Big.'' ''There are disappointments, but nothing that allows you make a case about the committee's intentions.''</p>
        <p>This year, Frank Langella was overlooked as best actor for ''Present Laughter,'' as was Rip Torn for ''The Young Man From Atlanta.'' Wendy Wasserstein, a favorite with Tony voters, did not make the cut this year with ''An American Daughter,'' which picked up only one nomination, for Lynne Thigpen as best supporting actress. Deborah Findlay, who won the Olivier Award for her performance in ''Stanley'' in London, did not receive a Tony nomination.</p>
        <p>Although the best-actor category was highly contentious this year, Mr. Langella stands out as a truly hard-luck case. He failed to earn a nomination last year for his highly praised performance in ''The Father,'' and this year, despite winning over the critics in ''Present Laughter,'' he lost out again. People familiar with the deliberations of the nominating committee said that Mr. Langella lost a tie-breaker vote to Antony Sher in ''Stanley.'' The other nominations went to Christopher Plummer, generally regarded as a shoo-in for ''Barrymore,'' Michael Gambon for ''Skylight'' and Brian Bedford for ''London Assurance,'' a play that opened on the last day of the season.</p>
        <p>Janet McTeer and Lia Williams, both British, received best-actress nominations for ''A Doll's House'' and ''Skylight,'' respectively. They were joined by Julie Harris for ''The Gin Game'' and Shirley Knight for ''The Young Man From Atlanta.''</p>
        <p>Nominations for the season's new musicals were watched with a keen eye. None of the seven new musicals that opened this season earned strong enough reviews to stamp them as hits, so this year's nominations mean everything to shows struggling to reach an audience. ''The Life'' and ''Steel Pier'' now have bragging rights.</p>
        <p>In addition to being nominated as best musical, ''The Life'' earned nominations for Pamela Isaacs as best actress, Lillias White as best supporting actress (''featured performer,'' in Tony-speak), Chuck Cooper and Sam Harris as best supporting actor and Michael Blakemore as best director. The show also received nominations for book, score, costumes, lighting, choreography and orchestration.</p>
        <p>''Steel Pier'' picked up nominations for Daniel McDonald as best actor, Karen Ziemba as best actress, Joel Blum as best supporting actor, Debra Monk as best supporting actress and Scott Ellis as director. It also was nominated for book, score, scenic design, choreography and orchestration.</p>
        <p>Although ''Play On!'' received nominations for Tonya Pinkins as best actress and Andre De Shields as best supporting actor, it needed and did not get a best-musical nomination, leaving its commercial prospects in doubt. The producers of ''Titanic,'' which received a cool reception from the critics and now the Tonys, will have to make the most of its nomination for best musical. ''Jekyll &amp; Hyde,'' although it won a best-actor nomination for Robert Cuccioli, was more or less rebuffed by the nominating committee, losing the precious best-musical nomination in a tie-breaker to ''Juan Darien.'' ''Dream'' picked up only one nomination, for Wayne Cilento's choreography.</p>
        <p>Among musical revivals, ''Chicago,'' as expected, crushed the competition; among its nominations were Bebe Neuwirth for best actress, James Naughton for best actor, Marcia Lewis for best supporting actress, Walter Bobbie for best director and Ann Reinking for best choreographer. ''Annie'' and ''Once Upon a Mattress'' received no nominations other than best revival, a foregone conclusion since there were only four musical revivals this season.</p>
        <p>In a tactical error, the producers of ''Chicago'' did not petition to have Joel Grey's status changed to supporting actor rather than lead, a move allowable under Tony rules within 10 days of a play's opening. ''You know the last scene in 'Chicago,' when my character asks for his exit music and it doesn't come?'' Mr. Grey asked. ''Now I know how he feels.''</p>
        <p>The producers of ''A Doll's House,'' on the other hand, applied to have Owen Teale shifted to the supporting-actor category and were rewarded with a nomination.</p>
        <p>The American Theater Wing, which administers the Tonys, revised the rules after last year's uproar. It increased the size of the nominating committee to 26 from 14. The committee is made up of knowledgeable theatergoers, some of them professionals, who do not have a direct interest in the current season's productions.</p>
        <p>The Theater Wing also did away with weighted votes, in which a nominator's vote for first place counted four points, second place two points and so on. Instead, nominators proposed up to four names in each category, all of which were given equal weight. The new rules also limited the prevote discussion to two hours. But the committee voted not to hold any discussion at all. This year's nominations included a new category, best orchestration.</p>
        <p>The big winner of the day may have been Roger Berlind, who, as producer of ''Steel Pier'' and co-producer of ''The Life'' and ''Skylight,'' had a hand in three of the day's most nominated shows.</p>
        <p>Tony ballots will be mailed this week to 763 journalists and people who work in the theater. The awards will be presented at Radio City Music Hall, where a special Tony will be given to the Berkeley Repertory Theater of Berkeley, Calif. The ceremony will be dedicated to Bernard B. Jacobs, the former president of the Shubert Organization, who died this year. He will be honored with a special Tony for lifetime achievement.</p>
        <p>Broadway's Best: Tony Award Nominations</p>
        <p>Play</p>
        <p>''Skylight''</p>
        <p>''Stanley''</p>
        <p>''The Last Night of Ballyhoo''</p>
        <p>''The Young Man From Atlanta''</p>
        <p>Musical</p>
        <p>''Juan Darien''</p>
        <p>''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>''The Life''</p>
        <p>''Titanic''</p>
        <p>Book of a Musical</p>
        <p>''Jekyll &amp; Hyde''</p>
        <p>''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>''The Life''</p>
        <p>''Titanic''</p>
        <p>Original Score</p>
        <p>''Juan Darien''</p>
        <p>''Steel Pier,''</p>
        <p>''The Life,''</p>
        <p>''Titanic.''</p>
        <p>Revival of a Play</p>
        <p>''A Doll's House''</p>
        <p>''London Assurance''</p>
        <p>''Present Laughter''</p>
        <p>''The Gin Game''</p>
        <p>Revival of a Musical</p>
        <p>''Annie''</p>
        <p>''Candide''</p>
        <p>''Chicago''</p>
        <p>''Once Upon a Mattress''</p>
        <p>Leading Actor in a Play</p>
        <p>Brian Bedford, ''London Assurance''</p>
        <p>Michael Gambon''Skylight''</p>
        <p>Christopher Plummer, ''Barrymore''</p>
        <p>Antony Sher, ''Stanley.''</p>
        <p>Leading Actress in a Play</p>
        <p>Julie Harris, ''The Gin Game''</p>
        <p>Shirley Knight, ''The Young Man From Atlanta''</p>
        <p>Janet McTeer, ''A Doll's House''</p>
        <p>Lia Williams, ''Skylight''</p>
        <p>Leading Actor in a Musical</p>
        <p>Robert Cuccioli, ''Jekyll &amp; Hyde''</p>
        <p>Jim Dale, ''Candide''</p>
        <p>Daniel McDonald, ''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>James Naughton, ''Chicago''</p>
        <p>Leading Actress in a Musical</p>
        <p>Pamela Isaacs, ''The Life''</p>
        <p>Bebe Neuwirth, ''Chicago''</p>
        <p>Tonya Pinkins, ''Play On!''</p>
        <p>Karen Ziemba, ''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>Featured Actor in a Play</p>
        <p>Terry Beaver, ''The Last Night of Ballyhoo''</p>
        <p>William Biff McGuire, ''The Young Man From Atlanta''</p>
        <p>Brian Murray, ''The Little Foxes''</p>
        <p>Owen Teale, ''A Doll's House''</p>
        <p>Featured Actress in a Play</p>
        <p>Helen Carey, ''London Assurance''</p>
        <p>Dana Ivey, ''The Last Night of Ballyhoo''</p>
        <p>Lynne Thigpen, ''An American Daughter''</p>
        <p>Celia Weston, ''The Last Night of Ballyhoo''</p>
        <p>Featured Actor in a Musical</p>
        <p>Joel Blum, ''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>Chuck Cooper, ''The Life''</p>
        <p>Andre De Shields, ''Play On!''</p>
        <p>Sam Harris, ''The Life''</p>
        <p>Featured Actress in a Musical</p>
        <p>Marcia Lewis, ''Chicago''</p>
        <p>Andrea Martin, ''Candide''</p>
        <p>Debra Monk, ''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>Lillias White, ''The Life''</p>
        <p>Scenic Design</p>
        <p>John Lee Beatty, ''The Little Foxes''</p>
        <p>Stewart Laing, ''Titanic''</p>
        <p>G. W. Mercier and Julie Taymor, ''Juan Darien''</p>
        <p>Tony Walton, ''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>Costume Design</p>
        <p>Ann Curtis, ''Jekyll &amp; Hyde''</p>
        <p>Judith Dolan, ''Candide''</p>
        <p>William Ivey Long, ''Chicago''</p>
        <p>Martin Pakledinaz, ''The Life''</p>
        <p>Lighting Design</p>
        <p>Ken Billington, ''Chicago''</p>
        <p>Beverly Emmons, ''Jekyll &amp; Hyde''</p>
        <p>Donald Holder, ''Juan Darien''</p>
        <p>Richard Pilbrow, ''The Life''</p>
        <p>Choreography</p>
        <p>Wayne Cilento, ''Dream''</p>
        <p>Joey McKneely, ''The Life''</p>
        <p>Ann Reinking, ''Chicago''</p>
        <p>Susan Stroman, ''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>Direction of a Play</p>
        <p>John Caird, ''Stanley''</p>
        <p>Richard Eyre, ''Skylight''</p>
        <p>Anthony Page, ''A Doll's House''</p>
        <p>Charles Nelson Reilly, ''The Gin Game''</p>
        <p>Direction of a Musical</p>
        <p>Michael Blakemore, ''The Life''</p>
        <p>Walter Bobbie, ''Chicago''</p>
        <p>Scott Ellis, ''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>Julie Taymor, ''Juan Darien''</p>
        <p>Orchestration</p>
        <p>Michael Gibson, ''Steel Pier''</p>
        <p>Luther Henderson, ''Play On!''</p>
        <p>Don Sebesky and Harold Wheeler, ''The Life''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Tunick, ''Titanic''</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 8, 1997, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about the Tony Award nominations misstated the showing for the musical ''Big'' last year. It received nominations in five categories, though not for best musical; it was not entirely overlooked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 8, 1997, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about the Tony Award nominations misstated the showing for the musical ''Big'' last year. It received nominations in five categories, though not for best musical; it was not entirely overlooked.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
