<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>North Korea's Famine Strains Quality of Mercy</title>
    <meta content="06KORE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="928002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Famine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">North Korea-International Relations-South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">North Korea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/North Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Famine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970506T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E0DF1030F935A35756C0A961958260" item-length="1489" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>North Korea's Famine Strains Quality of Mercy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Growing number of South Koreans are willing to overlook North Korea's past to save its people from famine, but line between humanitarian concerns and political realities remains tough to draw; question remains whether South should feed enemy that vows to destroy it but is also its brother; South has seesawed from impulsive generosity to cool stinginess and seems to have settled on aid in controlled doses; fears too much aid too soon could let North off hook and feed its 1.1 million-member army; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of Kwan Young Bom's brothers was killed fighting North Korea in the Korean War and another lost some fingers. But standing outside Seoul Station, where volunteers were collecting money for North Korean famine relief, Mr. Kwan explained why he had given a donation.</p>
        <p>''When I was a child, Korea was a very poor country and we suffered together, North and South,'' said Mr. Kwan, 61. ''We should help North Koreans more than the refugees in Africa.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of Kwan Young Bom's brothers was killed fighting North Korea in the Korean War and another lost some fingers. But standing outside Seoul Station, where volunteers were collecting money for North Korean famine relief, Mr. Kwan explained why he had given a donation.</p>
        <p>''When I was a child, Korea was a very poor country and we suffered together, North and South,'' said Mr. Kwan, 61. ''We should help North Koreans more than the refugees in Africa.''</p>
        <p>Like a growing number of South Koreans, Mr. Kwan is willing to overlook North Korea's past to save its people from famine. But for South Korea the line between humanitarian concerns and political realities is a tough one to draw. Should South Korea feed an enemy that vows to destroy it but is also its brother?</p>
        <p>How South Korea answers this question is likely to affect the world's response to the food shortage in the Communist North, which is said to be already claiming lives. If South Korea and other wealthy neighbors of North Korea like Japan do not give aid, it is unrealistic to expect the rest of the world to do so in a big way.</p>
        <p>So far, South Korea has seesawed from impulsive generosity to cool stinginess and seems to have settled on aid in controlled doses. Worried about being perceived as insensitive, it is about to make another donation, probably $10 million worth of corn, through the United Nations World Food Program.</p>
        <p>But South Korea and the United States are trying to entice North Korea into peace negotiations by offering food. Too much aid too soon could let North Korea off the hook and feed its 1.1 million-member army.</p>
        <p>Seoul is also trying to keep private donations in check. ''Last year they went out preventing people from trying to give aid,'' said Stephen Linton, chairman of the Eugene Bell Foundation, an American nonprofit group.</p>
        <p>This year, he and others said, some restrictions have been lifted. But Seoul, which does not let citizens have contact with North Korea, requires that all donations be funneled through South Korea's Red Cross, which, fund-raisers complain, is slow and costly. And they say the Seoul Government is discouraging outdoor fund-raising rallies.</p>
        <p>''Such rash moves for sentimental reasons might mislead the North,'' the Government's Unification Minister, Kwon O Kie, said.</p>
        <p>The Government is also discouraging corporate contributions, fearful that South Korea's giant companies will try to outdo one another -- not out of genuine humanitarian concern but to win the inside track on doing business in the North in the future.</p>
        <p>Political considerations have also stopped the flow of aid from Japan, which has a stockpile of surplus rice, some of it rotting from age, that is large enough to wipe out all of North Korea's food shortfall.</p>
        <p>But Japan is not offering aid because of reports, still unconfirmed, that North Korea kidnapped Japanese citizens, including a 13-year-old girl who vanished 20 years ago.</p>
        <p>The World Food Program of the United Nations has raised only $34 million of the $95 million in food aid it is seeking for North Korea. ''Time is running out,'' a spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>Catherine Bertini, executive director of the World Food Program, said that on a recent visit to North Korea she saw few children with distended bellies, a sign of starvation. But many children were lethargic and stunted in growth. ''Children who we thought were 2 years old were actually 4,'' she wrote in the Yomiuri Shimbun, a Japanese newspaper.</p>
        <p>The famine is a result of two years of flooding that devastated farmland in North Korea, and of the nation's  economic collapse. One reason the floods were so damaging is that North Korea cleared trees from mountains to get firewood and to make space for crops.</p>
        <p>Most agree that the biggest reason for the dearth of aid is North Korea's belligerence. When South Korea shipped 150,000 tons of rice in 1995, North Korea never said thank you. Instead, it insisted that the South Korean ship hoist the North Korean flag and arrested a crew member as a spy for taking photographs of the harbor.</p>
        <p>Lack of access to the secretive North means there are virtually no photographs of pitiable children to tug at donors' hearts.</p>
        <p>It also leads to doubts that the problem is as bad as advertised. South Korean officials point out that China and Russia do not think people are dying of hunger. Officials in Seoul say North Korea might be appealing for aid to save the money it usually spends on grain imports.</p>
        <p>Others say North Korea should help itself first before asking others. On April 15, it staged an elaborate celebration for the birthday of its  ''Great Leader,'' Kim Il Sung, unveiling a huge new statue and flying in entertainers from many countries.</p>
        <p>''Why should they spend $100 million to $200 million to celebrate a dead man's birthday?'' a senior South Korean official said.</p>
        <p>There is also fear that food aid will be diverted to the military. Some point out that if North Korea cut 5 percent from its military budget, estimated at $5 billion or more, it could buy enough grain to alleviate the famine.</p>
        <p>Seoul and Washington make a distinction between ''humanitarian aid,'' meaning small-scale assistance offered through organizations like the World Food Program, and bilateral aid, in which larger amounts of food are shipped directly to North Korea.</p>
        <p>The two Governments say the food aid will not be tied to politics. The United States has donated $25 million through the World Food Program. South Korea is expected shortly to announce a new contribution on top of $6 million offered two months ago.</p>
        <p>But the World Food Program appeal would raise enough money to buy only 200,000 metric tons of grain, less than 10 percent of what it estimates is a 2.3 million ton shortfall in North Korea.</p>
        <p>So the big donations will have to be directly from governments. And for that, the United States and South Korea have insisted that North Korea agree to enter negotiations aimed at forging a peace treaty to replace the fragile armistice that ended the Korean War in 1953.</p>
        <p>If the North takes part in the talks and agrees to some interim measures to reduce tensions, South Korea would provide hundreds of thousands of tons of grain, an official said.</p>
        <p>But at recent talks in New York, North Korea balked at taking part in the talks unless it was guaranteed 1.5 million tons in advance. ''The North had the wherewithal to open that gate and they just didn't,'' an American diplomat said.</p>
        <p>But while the South Korean Government waits, private citizens are stepping up aid.</p>
        <p>''You see this new fervor -- incredible,'' said Dr. Lee Yoon Gu of World Vision International, an aid group based in California. ''The whole national sentiment is there now, despite all the political anxieties.''</p>
        <p>The South Korean Red Cross said it has collected about $3.5 million since 1995, but nearly a third of that came in April alone.</p>
        <p>Roman Catholic and other religious groups and students have been most active. The Buddhist Sharing Movement Center hopes to get 100,000 people to agree to skip lunch every Friday and donate the money saved to famine relief. Some students at Seoul National University ate only one bowl of corn soup a day for four days to experience hunger.</p>
        <p>One factor for the increased flow is that a few weeks ago the Government began allowing the private aid to include rice, which had been banned because it is easier than other foods to stockpile for the military. It is also letting aid groups arrange their own food purchases, though the final delivery must still be made by the Red Cross.</p>
        <p>''If we give the money to the South Korean Red Cross it takes at least two months to deliver to the North,'' said Jung An Sook of the Buddhist Sharing Movement. She said the Red Cross paid five times more than it needed to because it bought flour in South Korea rather than in China.</p>
        <p>The private aid is not likely to be enough to eliminate the need for government assistance. So if North Korea does not agree to take part in peace talks, Washington and Seoul might face a big decision: whether to let North Korean people starve to punish them for the actions of their Government, over which they have little control.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
