<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Union Made</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="815069"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ISSERMAN, MAURICE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALMOND, JOHN A</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GASTONIA 1929 (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E0D81F39F933A25751C1A963958260" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Union Made</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Maurice Isserman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ISSERMAN, MAURICE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GASTONIA 1929 The Story of the Loray Mill Strike. By John A. Salmond. Illustrated. 226 pp. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press. $24.95.</p>
        <p>THE 1920's were grim years for organized labor -- with the possible exception of the 1980's, the worst in this century. Saddled with inept leaders, helpless in the face of a sophisticated antiunion campaign by employers, divided internally along racial, ethnic and political lines, the American Federation of  Labor (A.F.L.) dithered and floundered, all the while hemorrhaging members.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GASTONIA 1929 The Story of the Loray Mill Strike. By John A. Salmond. Illustrated. 226 pp. Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press. $24.95.</p>
        <p>THE 1920's were grim years for organized labor -- with the possible exception of the 1980's, the worst in this century. Saddled with inept leaders, helpless in the face of a sophisticated antiunion campaign by employers, divided internally along racial, ethnic and political lines, the American Federation of  Labor (A.F.L.) dithered and floundered, all the while hemorrhaging members.</p>
        <p>Nowhere were prospects grimmer for the labor movement than in the Southern textile industry, as John A. Salmond, a professor of history at La Trobe University in Australia, suggests in his briskly told study, "Gastonia 1929." At the start of the decade, tens of thousands of workers in the Piedmont region had joined the A.F.L.'s United Textile Workers. But labor militancy soon collapsed in the face of employer intransigence, the violent opposition of police, state militias and vigilantes, and a severe economic downturn.</p>
        <p>Textile employers cut costs with what workers called "stretch-out" tactics, increasing the pace of work and the rigor of supervision while substituting piecework for regular wages. In the Loray Mill in Gastonia, N.C., the largest textile mill in the South, wages fell 25 to 50 percent in the late 1920's.</p>
        <p>Across the Carolinas in the spring of 1929, thousands of desperate textile workers finally rebelled in spontaneous and short-lived strikes little noticed outside the immediate region. In terms of public attention, Gastonia proved the  exception. Not that the strike at the Loray Mill was notably more successful; begun on April 1, it effectively collapsed by midmonth. What made it different was the fact that hundreds of native-born white Southerners were willing to accept leadership from the Communist Party-led National Textile Workers Union. Thus, despite the brevity of the strike, Gastonia took on mythic proportions in  subsequent years -- depending on your point of view, either as the symbol of left-wing attempts to subvert the "Southern way of life" or as the welcome harbinger of the radical ferment of the 1930's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Salmond denies that he is offering any "overarching thesis" in his book.  A "well-told story," he declares in his preface, "has a justification of its own." Yet implicit throughout "Gastonia 1929" is the counterfactual proposition  that had someone other than the Communists played the leading role in the strike -- some group equally dedicated and self-sacrificing, but shrewder, less burdened by dogma and more sensitive to local mores -- then Gastonia might have  proved a triumph rather than a tragedy.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Salmond, "There is no doubt that the constant emphasis on the alien, menacing nature" of the National Textile Workers Union organizers, "the threat that they posed to basic traditions and values, did contribute to the growing climate of violence in Gaston County and gave sanction to the violent incidents that did occur."</p>
        <p>The violence included police assaults on picket lines, vigilante attacks on the union's headquarters and, finally, the gunning down of Ella May Wiggins, a millworker and mother of nine, and the balladeer of the Gastonia strike. There was also a shoot-out between armed strikers and deputy sheriffs that resulted in the death of Gastonia's chief of police and the subsequent arrest of dozens of union supporters and organizers for conspiracy. In the ensuing trials, union leaders were sentenced to prison terms of up to 20 years; Ella May Wiggins's accused killers, on the other hand, were acquitted by a local jury after less than 30 minutes' deliberation.</p>
        <p>THE Communists who came to Gastonia in 1929 brought with them more than their share of ideological delusions and organizational shortcomings -- their celebration of the Soviet Union, their addiction to inflammatory revolutionary rhetoric, their self-proclaimed atheism (though also, it should be remembered, their equally unpopular commitment to racial equality). But was any other outcome to the strike possible? The subsequent record of unremitting failure racked up by the A.F.L., and later by the Congress of Industrial Organizations (C.I.O.), suggests otherwise. Gastonia's strikers faced overwhelming odds; the fact that they were willing to risk livelihoods and lives -- under whatever fallible leadership presented itself to them at the time -- stands only to their credit.</p>
        <p>Maurice Isserman, a professor of history atHamilton College, is writing a biography of Michael Harrington.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Maurice Isserman, a professor of history atHamilton College, is writing a biography of Michael Harrington.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
