<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FUNDS WATCH</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="815215"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="MUTUAL FUNDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PENSIONS AND RETIREMENT PLANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUTUAL FUNDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOULD, CAROLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E1D61F39F933A25751C1A963958260" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FUNDS WATCH</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOULD, CAROLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gauging the Cost Of 401(k) Plans</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gauging the Cost Of 401(k) Plans</p>
        <p>The amount paid for 401(k) plans can vary widely, according to the Butler Index, begun recently by the Pension Dynamics Corporation of Lafayette, Calif.</p>
        <p>The index shows what 12 mutual fund and other companies would charge for a plan with $1 million in assets and 50 employees -- in other words, a small plan. The annualized costs are divided into the amount paid by the employer and that paid cumulatively by the 50 employees. Though they may not realize it, employees who check on their plans will generally find that a portion is deducted from the accounts of individual participants.</p>
        <p>For a plan of this size, the lowest-cost providers were Principal Financial,  T. Rowe Price Century Plan and Vanguard, according to the index.</p>
        <p>Along with costs, a critical factor is investment performance. "A vendor may  say that, although its costs and fees are above average, you are being awarded with superior investment performance," said Stephen J. Butler, president of Pension Dynamics. "Don't take this claim on faith. Check the performance of your prospective vendors' investments in a respected source, such as Morningstar."</p>
        <p>Best of the Bonds? Corporates and Munis</p>
        <p>Buying shares in a Government bond fund is easier than buying small quantities of Government bonds. But most Government funds lag behind their benchmarks. They're expensive, and there are better alternatives, John Rekenthaler, editor of the Morningstar Investor, wrote in the most recent issue.</p>
        <p>About 85 percent of Government Treasury and mortgage bond funds trail the Lehman Brothers Government index, and they don't compensate by showing lower risk. The reason is that the market is very efficient, and fund managers are handicapped by expenses, which average 1.05 percent of assets a year.</p>
        <p>Best bets for investors are the low-cost Vanguard funds, Mr. Rekenthaler concludes. Other options are Strong Government Securities, which stretches the definition of Government to include unusual mortgages and some corporate bonds,  and Sit U.S. Government Securities, which owns mobile-home mortgages.</p>
        <p>Otherwise, investors in low tax brackets should now go with corporates, Mr. Rekenthaler argues. They are less costly and their market is less efficient. FPA New Income has beaten the Government indexes for a decade with less risk, he said. Other funds he recommends: Loomis Sayles Bond, Dodge &amp; Cox Income and Harbor Bond.</p>
        <p>For people taxed at 28 percent or more, municipal bond funds, especially single-state funds, are the way to go. Exempt from Federal and state tax for in-state residents, the single-state funds yield more without sacrificing long-term performance. Best bets are run by Vanguard, Fidelity Investments, T. Rowe Price and Scudder, Stevens &amp; Clark, Mr. Rekenthaler says.</p>
        <p>Because long-term munis carry a lot of interest-rate risk, cautious investors might consider intermediate-term muni funds even though yields are lower.</p>
        <p>A Rift Over Money Funds</p>
        <p>A proposal by the Securities and Exchange Commission to force money market funds to report their holdings quarterly is running into opposition from the industry.</p>
        <p>The Investment Company Institute, the mutual-fund trade group, says the proposal is neither "necessary nor appropriate" and would result in unnecessary  costs.</p>
        <p>Not so, says Glen King Parker, publisher of the Income Fund Outlook, an investment newsletter in Deerfield Beach, Fla. Many institutional money funds already publish portfolios monthly and make them available to shareholders, he said, and those that sell to the general public should provide more disclosure.</p>
        <p>In fact, he would prefer reporting monthly instead of quarterly. "Money funds have become quasi-banks," he said, "and I don't think that there's anything wrong with an increased level of scrutiny."</p>
        <p>A Portfolio Thinks Small</p>
        <p>James Oberweis, manager of the $135 million Oberweis Emerging Growth fund, is starting the Micro-Cap Portfolio, which will invest in very, very small stocks.  The average market capitalization of the stocks in the Emerging Growth portfolio is $400 million to $500 million; in the new fund it will be less than $100 million.</p>
        <p>The new fund is being structured to let investors get in at the starting gate. Money will be collected from mid-December, but it won't be invested until  the fund begins operating on Jan. 2.</p>
        <p>To stay true to his small-cap mission, Mr. Oberweis plans to close the fund when it reaches $50 million in assets. Even existing shareholders won't be allowed to add new money, though they can reinvest their earnings.</p>
        <p>More New Funds</p>
        <p>Robertson, Stephens &amp; Company, San Francisco, is adding three funds. Its Information Age fund, managed by Ron Elijah, who already runs the company's Value and Growth fund, will concentrate on small-capitalization technology companies with unusual offerings in multimedia, wireless communications, networking, software and the like. Global Natural Resources will be managed by Andy J. Pilara Jr., who also manages the Partners and Contrarian funds. Global Low Priced Stock will buy overlooked companies with share prices of $10 or less.</p>
        <p>Bank of America has started three Time Horizon funds with stated maturity dates in the life-style category. The funds aim to maximize total return and then emphasize capital preservation as the fund approaches its maturity date. Time Horizon Portfolio 1 is for investors with a financial goal near the year 2005, Portfolio 2 for 2015 and Portfolio 3 for 2025.</p>
        <p>Fidelity Investments has added to its international lineup with six aggressive growth funds that invest in single countries and regions abroad. All  the funds carry a 3 percent sales charge and a 1.5 percent redemption fee on shares held less than 90 days. They are Fidelity France, Germany, Hong Kong and  China, Japan Small Companies, Nordic and United Kingdom.</p>
        <p>New Management</p>
        <p>Ernst H. Von Metzsch, who picked up the Vanguard Wellington fund after the death of Vincent Bajakian in September, has been named the permanent manager.</p>
        <p>Catherine Dudley left Phoenix Growth to join Chancellor Investments. She is replaced at the fund by William J. Newman, the company's chief investment strategist.</p>
        <p>In Brief</p>
        <p>Fidelity Investments plans to make all its prospectuses available soon on the Internet. The company has 83 prospectuses there now (http://www.fid-inv.com) and expects to put the remainder there by early next year.</p>
        <p>MUTUAL FUNDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
