<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Lose the Game And a Valuable Rookie</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="831809"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY DEVILS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FLORIDA PANTHERS FLORIDA PANTHERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEYDEVILS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">YANNIS, ALEX</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Florida Panthers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DD1039F931A15751C0A960958260" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Lose the Game And a Valuable Rookie</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YANNIS, ALEX</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Feb. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Devils suffered their second consecutive loss tonight, a 4-1 decision to  the Florida Panthers, and lost Petr Sykora, their terrific rookie center.</p>
        <p>Sykora pulled a muscle in his lower back in his first shift and missed the balance of the game at Continental Arena.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Devils suffered their second consecutive loss tonight, a 4-1 decision to  the Florida Panthers, and lost Petr Sykora, their terrific rookie center.</p>
        <p>Sykora pulled a muscle in his lower back in his first shift and missed the balance of the game at Continental Arena.</p>
        <p>I tried to come back, but I couldn't skate," said the 19-year-old Sykora, the Devils' best center in their winter of discontent. "I'll see if I can skate  tomorrow. I want to make sure I'm ready to play."</p>
        <p>This is a crucial time for the Devils if they want to defend their Stanley Cup. They are barely hanging on to the last playoff spot in the Eastern Conference. It was their fourth loss in five meetings with the Panthers.</p>
        <p>The victory put the Panthers (35-17-7) just 2 points behind the division-leading Rangers (34-14-11) and 19 points ahead of the Devils (25-25-8), who are making things difficult for themselves in their drive for a playoff spot.</p>
        <p>Martin Brodeur faced only 20 shots in absorbing his second loss in three days. It was his 28th consecutive appearance in goal.</p>
        <p>Brodeur, who was relieved by Corey Schwab in the 4-1 loss to the Flyers on Monday in Philadelphia, can be blamed only for Radek Dvorak's goal that gave the Panthers a 3-0 lead, 2 minutes 40 seconds into the last period. Brodeur ventured out of his goal near the boards to his left for a loose puck, but Dvorak beat him to it and hit the open net from a sharp angle.</p>
        <p>"That was his only mistake," Coach Jacques Lemaire said. Brodeur's record dropped to 22-22-8 with five shutouts.</p>
        <p>Lemaire said he was pleased with his team after it suffered a lackadaisical loss to the Flyers on Monday afternoon.</p>
        <p>"The guys were up for the game," Lemaire said. "They wanted to win this game, but we lost our best centerman early in the game."</p>
        <p>Bobby Holik scored the lone goal for the Devils, against Mark Fitzpatrick, who faced 31 shots and improved his record to 15-6-2 with no shutouts.</p>
        <p>Scott Melanby opened the scoring with his 28th of the season with 3:27 left in the second before Stu Barnes gave the Panthers a 2-0 lead with his 16th just  over a minute later to the accompanying jeers from the crowd of 15,872.</p>
        <p>The jeers got louder as the Devils headed to the dressing room for the second intermission, just moments after Mike Peluso was assessed a penalty for fighting and a game misconduct for retaliating against Dvorak, who appeared to have slashed Randy McKay.</p>
        <p>Holik narrowed the gap for the Devils with his seventh of the season shortly  after Dvorak's goal before Hough iced it with an empty-net goal.</p>
        <p>Mike Hough scored the last goal for the Panthers with 15.2 seconds left in the game while the Devils had pulled Brodeur for an extra attacker.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>NEAL BROTEN missed his third game with a sprained right ankle and VALERY ZELEPUKIN missed his second game with a bruised right foot for the Devils. Zelepukin said he was ready to play, but Broten said he didn't believe he would  be ready until next month.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
