<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Peter Pan' Stops By On Way to Broadway</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="403667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHUBERT THEATER (NEW HAVEN, CONN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEIN, ALVIN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PETER PAN (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D81039F936A15752C1A966958260" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Peter Pan' Stops By On Way to Broadway</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alvin Klein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLEIN, ALVIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Broadway-bound shows, the historic Shubert Theater in New Haven once represented the big stop before the big time. If only for the next two weeks, theater lovers can imagine the rebirth of that aspect of a golden age. And what more fitting show to fire one's fancy than the one about youth recaptured in Never-Never Land?</p>
        <p>It can all come back, if you wish it so, on Tuesday, when " Peter Pan" - starring Cathy Rigby in the title role - opens at the Shubert, where it is to run through Dec. 9. Two nights after the New Haven closing, the musical is to begin a six-week engagement at a Broadway theater, the Lunt-fontaine, on 46th street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For Broadway-bound shows, the historic Shubert Theater in New Haven once represented the big stop before the big time. If only for the next two weeks, theater lovers can imagine the rebirth of that aspect of a golden age. And what more fitting show to fire one's fancy than the one about youth recaptured in Never-Never Land?</p>
        <p>It can all come back, if you wish it so, on Tuesday, when " Peter Pan" - starring Cathy Rigby in the title role - opens at the Shubert, where it is to run through Dec. 9. Two nights after the New Haven closing, the musical is to begin a six-week engagement at a Broadway theater, the Lunt-fontaine, on 46th street.</p>
        <p>In reality, the show's two-week stopover in New Haven is part of a national tour that began in Boston last December and is to end in Los Angeles next July. Even so, the production is being refurbished for the Shubert in preparation for a splashy Broadway opening, said the show's producer, Thomas P. McCoy.</p>
        <p>For Ms. Rigby, who retired from her celebrated career in gymnastics in 1972, playing Peter Pan is real wish-fulfillment. In 1974, at the threshold of a theatrical career, she was a pretend Peter, lip-synching all the way.</p>
        <p>'I Flew in Arenas'</p>
        <p>"That was a 'Disney On Parade' extravaganza sort of thing, more like a circus than theater, and we toured all over the country for seven months,' Ms. Rigby said last week before a matinee performance in Baltimore.</p>
        <p>"I flew in arenas, but the singing and speaking were prerecorded by Yvonne Green and that was my entry into the entertainment field. It was then that an actor told me, 'Cathy, if you're really going to compete in this arena, be ready, be prepared. It's not nice to take jobs from actors."</p>
        <p>And prepare she did, with singing lessons, speech lessons and acting lessons. Finally, in 1981, Ms. Rigby made her stage debut - for real - in a touring production of the musical 'Paint Your Wagon,' staring Gordon MacRae. She had the romantic lead opposite MacRae, who became her second husband. They have been married eight years.</p>
        <p>In 1986, Ms. Rigby returned to the role of Peter Pan, the boy who refuses to grow up. She said the role symbolizes the interlocking of her professional, personal and fantasy lives.</p>
        <p>"if ever a part was perfect for me, this is it," she said. "Obviously the athletic background helps when you're trying to act fearless while doing flips on a balance beam, hand stands, jumping off rocks and flying and spinning through the air with breakneck speed. But I don't do a lot of gymnastics, only when it's appropriate, and there's no slapstick for the sake of a joke."</p>
        <p>"This is a whole new ball game for me. I know people come in with their arms crossed saying, 'You're an athlete.' But that was over 17 years ago, and this is not a fluke."</p>
        <p>Image of Youth</p>
        <p>In case anyone assumes that it is a fluke, however, Ms. Rigby explained her own Peter principles: "I grew up in a sport that didn't allow you to grow up. There was always the threat of younger competition. So you had to maintain the image of youth."</p>
        <p>After winning 12 medals in interntional competitions, Ms. Rigby left gymnastics at the age of 19.</p>
        <p>"When you're on the Olympic team at 15, you don't do anything else," she said. "There's no normal social development, and your decisions are made for you.</p>
        <p>"With all the tremendous pressure, you stuff a lot inside, and the result is denial - like Peter who can be heartless and self-absorbed. He puts his fingers in his ears and cuts people off when there's something he doesn't want to hear."</p>
        <p>"In this version, there are added scenes that show ominous, scary moments and the dark side of Peter - and we've eliminated the song 'Mysterious Lady,' which was a showpiece for Mary Martin," who starred in the original Broadway production of this version of "Peter Pan" and repeated the role on television.</p>
        <p>Children on Tour</p>
        <p>Ms. Rigby said that her height has been variously listed as 4 feet 10 inches, 4 feet 11 inches and 5 feet, and she wants it known that she is 5 feet tall.</p>
        <p>"If she said 5 feet, she's lying," Mr. McCoy said during a later interview. "She's 4 11-3/4. She likes to stretch it."</p>
        <p>Ms. Rigby said that having two sons 'Taught me more about being mischevious, manipulative and dear." The 37-year-old Ms. Rigby has four children; Bucky, 15, and Ryan, 10, from her first marriage to Tommy Mason, a professional football player, and Theresa, 8, and Kathy, 5. The three youngest have been accompanying her on tour.</p>
        <p>"Now Kathy says, 'I wanna be a boy like you,"' Ms. Rigby said.</p>
        <p>Peter Pan has traditionally been played on stage by a woman. Sir James M. Barrie's creation has been a handy metaphor for eternal youth and a model of escapism since its first theatrical incarnation in 1904. It has also been described as middle age's own tragicomedy.</p>
        <p>Although the play was made into a musical in 1950, with songs by Leonard Bernstein and Jean Arthur in the title role, it is the 1954 version that was created for Miss Martin - with music contributed, separately, by Moose Charlap and Jule Styne (vocal) and Trude Rittman and Elmer Bernstein (instrumental) that is considered the classic song-and-dance adaptation. Ms. Rigby said the current staging, which is advertised as a 35th-anniversary production, should now be regarded as a tribute to Miss Martin, who died on Nov. 3.</p>
        <p>About the tour, Mr. McCoy, who has remained in California where Ms. Rigby's eldest son is attending high school, said:</p>
        <p>"We started out for 25 weeks, and it grew to more than 80 - and it may be extended again. Our weekly grosses have been between $325,000 and $375,000.</p>
        <p>"This not only reminds people of their youth, but it's an opportunity for youngsters to witness theater for the first time, not Ninja Turtles, not 'Star Wars.' They're inundated with playback. This is real theater.</p>
        <p>Concerning the show's New Haven look, he added:</p>
        <p>'We had the scenery gutted and now we have a new Never Land, a new nursery, a new pirate ship, new fabrics, new flowers, new rocks, a new London drop, new fiber optic lights, a new crocodile. I put another $100,000 into this just for New Haven and New York. This is the best the show can look, and opening night in New York will be exactly like opening night in New Haven.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
