<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Containing Colombia's Troubles</title>
    <meta content="15MON2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/15/opinion/15MON2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1263089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colombia-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Latin America-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Colombia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latin America</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Colombia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E0DB123DF936A25752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="578" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Containing Colombia's Troubles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>containing colombia's troubl</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While the myriad problems of Colombia dominate the headlines from South America, most of Colombia's neighbors in the Andean region are experiencing less dramatic forms of turmoil. The problems are different in each nation and vary in their immediate causes. But all could be exacerbated by a spillover of the war from Colombia -- and from Plan Colombia, Washington's new military aid program.</p>
        <p>The Andean nations have always been troubled, and lag behind the Southern Cone of South America in developing efficient state institutions. The lack of rule of law has led to autocratic leadership in Venezuela, Bolivia and, until Alberto Fujimori's recent resignation, in Peru as well. Ecuador struggles with constant economic crisis and its fifth government in five years. Brazilian officials worry that they cannot fully control their thousand-mile Amazon border with Colombia. They have already begun to move police, river patrols and airplanes into the region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While the myriad problems of Colombia dominate the headlines from South America, most of Colombia's neighbors in the Andean region are experiencing less dramatic forms of turmoil. The problems are different in each nation and vary in their immediate causes. But all could be exacerbated by a spillover of the war from Colombia -- and from Plan Colombia, Washington's new military aid program.</p>
        <p>The Andean nations have always been troubled, and lag behind the Southern Cone of South America in developing efficient state institutions. The lack of rule of law has led to autocratic leadership in Venezuela, Bolivia and, until Alberto Fujimori's recent resignation, in Peru as well. Ecuador struggles with constant economic crisis and its fifth government in five years. Brazilian officials worry that they cannot fully control their thousand-mile Amazon border with Colombia. They have already begun to move police, river patrols and airplanes into the region.</p>
        <p>The spillover from Colombia's war could gradually threaten the stability of its neighbors. Already, nearly two million people have fled battle zones to settle in the slums around Colombia's major cities. Now some are beginning to cross into other nations. Rebels have long crossed into Panama, Ecuador and Venezuela to resupply and rest, but Larry Rohter recently reported in The Times that fighting between Colombian guerrillas and paramilitaries has now surfaced in Ecuador. In October, Ecuador accused the Colombian guerrillas of kidnapping 10 foreign oil workers.</p>
        <p>The cocaine trade that has fueled Colombia's war is also becoming more internationalized. Cocaine processing and coca growing have often shifted from nation to nation. When Bolivia and Peru began to have success in reducing coca under cultivation, the crop moved to Colombia, which now grows more than half the world's coca leaf. Cocaine processing is even more portable. In at least one border town in Ecuador, Colombians are buying land and the chemicals used to process cocaine.</p>
        <p>New American-trained and equipped antidrug battalions in Colombia plan to enter Putumayo, the zone of southern Colombia that is both a battlefield and a coca-growing region. Their mission is to destroy labs and eradicate coca plantations. Ironically, the more successful they are, the worse the headache they are likely to cause for Colombia's neighbors.</p>
        <p>Increased military action will likely intensify the war, producing more refugees. But if the plan is successful in reducing coca cultivation in Putumayo, coca will simply move to other areas of Colombia and to other nations. Peru and Bolivia may see areas they thought were coca-free go back under cultivation, and Ecuador, Venezuela and Brazil may see their first significant coca crop.</p>
        <p>That would expose these countries to the destructive side-effects of coca production. Wealthy criminal groups are sure to move in, corrupting officials, killing off police and each other, and eroding the state's control. In anticipation of such a spillover and resistance from the other Andean countries, Plan Colombia contains $180 million for the neighbors. Just over half the money is in the form of security aid.</p>
        <p>This aid is insufficient. Ecuador, where the police frequently cannot afford bullets for their guns, needs far more than $20 million. Drug trafficking, squashed in one region, simply pops up in another. The United States needs a regional plan -- one that gives Colombia's neighbors more aid to strengthen their police and courts and help peasants stay away from coca.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
