<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Writing About Rape</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="572046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOVACH, BILL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENEDICT, HELEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">VIRGIN OR VAMP (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DA1E3DF931A15752C1A964958260" item-length="1022" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Writing About Rape</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bill Kovach;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOVACH, BILL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>VIRGIN OR VAMP</p>
        <p>How the Press Covers Sex Crimes. By Helen Benedict. 309 pp. New York: Oxford University Press.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>VIRGIN OR VAMP</p>
        <p>How the Press Covers Sex Crimes. By Helen Benedict. 309 pp. New York: Oxford University Press.</p>
        <p>DON'T take the title of this book at face value. While "Virgin or Vamp: How the Press Covers Sex Crimes" does detail how the press covers sex crimes, it is really about how the press</p>
        <p>should</p>
        <p>cover sex crimes.</p>
        <p>Three decades of feminist scholarship have laid the foundation for this work. Helen Benedict's purpose is not just to put an end to public ignorance about women and the concerns of women, but, more important, to provide prescriptions for change -- change based on the findings of books like Susan Brownmiller's "Against Our Will: Men, Women and Rape."</p>
        <p>Ms. Benedict, who teaches journalism at Columbia University, builds on this scholarship. While she breaks little new ground, she makes a powerful case for a new approach to the coverage of sex crimes by daily newspapers.</p>
        <p>At first Ms. Benedict describes her book as "a critique of the way the print press covers sex crimes," but she soon discards this limitation to conclude, "Ultimately, the purpose of my book is to show reporters and editors how to cover sex crimes without further harming the victims."</p>
        <p>She examines in careful detail the attitude of the press toward rape as disclosed in coverage of four celebrated criminal trials. The cases span the dozen years during which awareness of the issue has grown and matured. In Ms. Benedict's view, each case uncovered yet another layer of biased attitudes toward sex crimes.</p>
        <p>The 1979 Greta and John Rideout case in Oregon publicized the then relatively new crime of marital rape. However, Ms. Benedict contends, the press had difficulty recognizing marital rape as an act of domestic violence and focused on sexual relationships. A jury acquitted John Rideout.</p>
        <p>In both the 1983 case involving a gang rape in New Bedford, Mass., and the 1986 trial in New York City of Robert Chambers for the murder of Jennifer Levin, the strategy of defense lawyers was to put the victim on trial. In each case, Ms. Benedict writes, press coverage focused heavily on the behavior of the victim. In the New Bedford case, juries convicted four men of aggravated rape in connection with an assault on a 22-year-old mother of two on a barroom pool table; two other men were acquitted of a lesser charge. Robert Chambers, charged with second-degree murder in the slaying of 18-year-old Jennifer Levin, pleaded guilty to manslaughter and burglary charges and was sentenced to 5 to 15 years in prison.</p>
        <p>The coverage of the 1989 gang rape of the Central Park jogger, Ms. Benedict argues, shows that the press is easily distracted from issues of sexual violence in favor of those of racism. The victim was white; the eight adolescents accused of assaulting her were black or Hispanic. The memory of the lynching of black slaves, which was motivated by white sexual fears, led some in the minority-community press to describe the trial in terms of race, not crime.</p>
        <p>By analyzing in detail the newspaper coverage of these trials and interviews with the reporters and editors involved, Ms. Benedict builds a record of the ease with which even well-intentioned journalists accept prejudices embedded in the system. One of her lessons is the extent to which the press has yet to digest the new awareness of the character of rape as an act of violence in which sex is the weapon.</p>
        <p>"As a result of the rape myths," Ms. Benedict writes, "a sex crime victim tends to be squeezed into one of two images -- she is either pure and innocent, a true victim attacked by monsters -- the 'virgin' of my title -- or she is a wanton female who provoked the assailant with her sexuality -- the 'vamp.' "</p>
        <p>The result, she writes, is coverage that falls in one of the two frameworks: "The woman, by her looks, behavior or generally loose morality, drove the man to such extremes of lust that he was compelled to commit the crime," or "the man, a depraved and perverted monster, sullied the innocent victim, who is now a martyr to the flaws of society."</p>
        <p>Ms. Benedict concludes: "Both of these narratives are destructive to the victims of rape and to public understanding of the subject. The vamp version is destructive because it blames the victim of the crime instead of the perpetrator. The virgin version is destructive because it perpetuates the idea that women can only be Madonnas or whores."</p>
        <p>Coping with these attitudes by examining them through the single prism of press treatment of rape occasionally leads the author to place the press in an untenable position. For example, she argues that if a reporter publishes less than flattering details of a rape victim's personal life those details are immediately used against her. On the other hand, she writes, if a reporter chooses to suppress those details to protect the victim from being persecuted, then the reporter is committing biased journalism. Such contradictions aside, the detail of her analysis makes a powerful case for reform in the way the daily press approaches its coverage of sex crimes.</p>
        <p>The most important part of the book is its reform agenda. The need for much of what she proposes, such as exercising greater care with the language used in covering sex crime stories, is made painfully obvious by the examples cited in her text. More women and members of minority groups are present in the newsroom than ever before, and this increased diversity is slowly, oh so slowly, having the expected effect.</p>
        <p>Maybe the most important immediate reform suggested is that someone be assigned to do weekly analysis of the coverage of celebrated and extended sex crime stories. The analysis, written by a writer not involved in daily coverage, would serve as a monitor and provide the space and opportunity to enlighten as well as inform the reader. This writer could introduce the most recent research on sex crimes; explain technicalities of the charges; examine the myths of rape; describe what the lawyers are doing and why, and guarantee a balance of reporting.</p>
        <p>Such an approach could generate better journalism. It might even sell more papers.</p>
        <p>Bill Kovach is curator of the Nieman Foundation for Journalists at Harvard University.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Bill Kovach is curator of the Nieman Foundation for Journalists at Harvard University.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
