<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="671491"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E3D6173AF93BA15751C0A962958260" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>International A2-9 ISRAEL TO RESTRICT SETTLERS Israel ordered tough measures to restrict the activities of militant Jewish settlers, responding to Arab anger and international concern after the slaying of more than 40 Palestinians in the West Bank. A1 THE PATH TO THE MOSQUE Dr. Baruch Goldstein prayed in the Cave of the Patriarchs the night before he returned there and opened fire on Arab worshipers. He was beaten to death by the crowd. A1 The U.S. criticized an offer for U.N. help to protect Palestinians. A8 Yasir Arafat said Israel's actions did not go far enough. A8 An explosion in a church killed nine people in Lebanon. A9 Syria, Jordan and Lebanon broke off talks with Israel, diplomats said.A9 TIES WITH RUSSIA FRAGILE The tension between the United States and Russia over Bosnia and over Russia's spying have made it clear that the post-cold-war partnership between the two countries seems to be crumbling. A1 U.S. PACKING UP IN SOMALIA The United States troops are preparing to leave Somalia, and the mood is considerably less upbeat than when they arrived because the country is caught between a fear of anarchy and hope for a political solution. A3 DISPUTE ON MEXICO TALKS The Mexican Government negotiator and a mediator reported agreement on outlines of an accord, but a Zapatista rebel leader later said there was none.  A3 A U.S. human rights official met with China's top dissident. A2 Altdorf Journal: The Swiss put up roadblocks to European union.  A4 The Red Cross plans to call for the ban of anti-personnel mines. A6 National A12-14, B6-8 THE HEALTH CARE STRUGGLE In the pushing and pulling over health care, Representative Jim Cooper is the leading figure going in one direction, while Representative Jim McDermott is the main one yanking in the other.  A1 DIABETIC PROGRAM ATTRACTS FEW Despite the announcement that with a strict medical regimen diabetics can measurably slow the onset and maybe even prevent the dire complications of the disease people have been slow to respond.  A1 PREPARING FOR A NEW S.A.T. Jittery about a new version of the Scholastic Assessment Test, high school students are attending coaching sessions in record numbers, even as educators debate the effectiveness and fairness of the preparatory courses.  A12 OLLIE NORTH EMBATTLED (AGAIN) Opposition to Oliver L. North's candidacy for the United States Senate has been more intense than even the most partisan Democrats may have imagined, and it has been joined by a number of Republicans.  A12 JURY SEATED IN DOCTOR'S KILLING A jury of seven women, five men and two female alternates was sworn in and sequestered in the trial of a man accused of murdering a doctor at an abortion clinic in Pensacola, Fla., last March.  A13 WACO VERDICT DEEPENS MYSTERY At the end of the seven-week trial of 11 Branch Davidians, the jury sent an unmistakable message that there was significant fault on both sides, issuing a verdict that will only deepen the mysteries of Waco.  A14 Two of the acquitted seem bemused by the fuss.  A14 TARGET OF RECALL EFFORT A recall effort has begun in California against State Senator David A. Roberti, who infuriated gun owners and conservatives with his push for a ban on assault weapons.  B6 MISSING IN NEW ORLEANS Getting lost in New Orleans has long had a certain cachet. But the mystery of a missing Italian traveler is distinctive even by New Orleans standards.  B6  Metro Digest B1 A THROWBACK HOSPITAL In a city where even many private hospitals are also old and crumbling, Kings County Hospital has been a symbol of inefficiency and decay, even to the medical personnel who remain dedicated to the place. A1 Business Digest D1 Sports C1-10 Baseball: Orioles have high expectations for Fernandez.  C8 A turning point for Franco.  C8 Basketball: Suns trounce Knicks.  C2 Nets topple Mavericks.  C2 Indiana loses by 50 points.  C3 Columns: Vecsey on the Olympics C5 Anderson on Willie Randolph C8 Hockey: Keenan looking for grit.  C9 Olympics: Sweden wins hockey gold in dramatic fashion.  C1 Tomba rallies to take silver.  C1 U.S. bobsled team disqualified.  C4 Obituaries D9 Arts/Entertainment C11-18 The state of Russian films.  C11 Chaplin's 'Circus' with the original score.  C11 Theater: "The Mayor of Boys Town." C15 Music: Jose van Dam.  C11 Korean funeral rituals.  C14 Wonder Stuff.  C16 Music from Lebanon.  C18 Critic's Notebook C18 Books: "Zlata's Diary." C15 Television: Dennis Byrd's story.  C16 "In Search of Human Origins." C16 Editorials/Op-Ed A16-17 Editorials A wrongheaded amendment. Don't sell out WNYC. Russia's struggle within. Letters Anthony Lewis: A new ball game. William Safire: Peacemaking after Hebron. Yuri N. Afanasyev: Russia's vicious circle. Neediest Cases B3 Chronicle B4  Bridge C14 Crossword C15</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>International A2-9 ISRAEL TO RESTRICT SETTLERS Israel ordered tough measures to restrict the activities of militant Jewish settlers, responding to Arab anger and international concern after the slaying of more than 40 Palestinians in the West Bank. A1 THE PATH TO THE MOSQUE Dr. Baruch Goldstein prayed in the Cave of the Patriarchs the night before he returned there and opened fire on Arab worshipers. He was beaten to death by the crowd. A1 The U.S. criticized an offer for U.N. help to protect Palestinians. A8 Yasir Arafat said Israel's actions did not go far enough. A8 An explosion in a church killed nine people in Lebanon. A9 Syria, Jordan and Lebanon broke off talks with Israel, diplomats said.A9 TIES WITH RUSSIA FRAGILE The tension between the United States and Russia over Bosnia and over Russia's spying have made it clear that the post-cold-war partnership between the two countries seems to be crumbling. A1 U.S. PACKING UP IN SOMALIA The United States troops are preparing to leave Somalia, and the mood is considerably less upbeat than when they arrived because the country is caught between a fear of anarchy and hope for a political solution. A3 DISPUTE ON MEXICO TALKS The Mexican Government negotiator and a mediator reported agreement on outlines of an accord, but a Zapatista rebel leader later said there was none.  A3 A U.S. human rights official met with China's top dissident. A2 Altdorf Journal: The Swiss put up roadblocks to European union.  A4 The Red Cross plans to call for the ban of anti-personnel mines. A6 National A12-14, B6-8 THE HEALTH CARE STRUGGLE In the pushing and pulling over health care, Representative Jim Cooper is the leading figure going in one direction, while Representative Jim McDermott is the main one yanking in the other.  A1 DIABETIC PROGRAM ATTRACTS FEW Despite the announcement that with a strict medical regimen diabetics can measurably slow the onset and maybe even prevent the dire complications of the disease people have been slow to respond.  A1 PREPARING FOR A NEW S.A.T. Jittery about a new version of the Scholastic Assessment Test, high school students are attending coaching sessions in record numbers, even as educators debate the effectiveness and fairness of the preparatory courses.  A12 OLLIE NORTH EMBATTLED (AGAIN) Opposition to Oliver L. North's candidacy for the United States Senate has been more intense than even the most partisan Democrats may have imagined, and it has been joined by a number of Republicans.  A12 JURY SEATED IN DOCTOR'S KILLING A jury of seven women, five men and two female alternates was sworn in and sequestered in the trial of a man accused of murdering a doctor at an abortion clinic in Pensacola, Fla., last March.  A13 WACO VERDICT DEEPENS MYSTERY At the end of the seven-week trial of 11 Branch Davidians, the jury sent an unmistakable message that there was significant fault on both sides, issuing a verdict that will only deepen the mysteries of Waco.  A14 Two of the acquitted seem bemused by the fuss.  A14 TARGET OF RECALL EFFORT A recall effort has begun in California against State Senator David A. Roberti, who infuriated gun owners and conservatives with his push for a ban on assault weapons.  B6 MISSING IN NEW ORLEANS Getting lost in New Orleans has long had a certain cachet. But the mystery of a missing Italian traveler is distinctive even by New Orleans standards.  B6  Metro Digest B1 A THROWBACK HOSPITAL In a city where even many private hospitals are also old and crumbling, Kings County Hospital has been a symbol of inefficiency and decay, even to the medical personnel who remain dedicated to the place. A1 Business Digest D1 Sports C1-10 Baseball: Orioles have high expectations for Fernandez.  C8 A turning point for Franco.  C8 Basketball: Suns trounce Knicks.  C2 Nets topple Mavericks.  C2 Indiana loses by 50 points.  C3 Columns: Vecsey on the Olympics C5 Anderson on Willie Randolph C8 Hockey: Keenan looking for grit.  C9 Olympics: Sweden wins hockey gold in dramatic fashion.  C1 Tomba rallies to take silver.  C1 U.S. bobsled team disqualified.  C4 Obituaries D9 Arts/Entertainment C11-18 The state of Russian films.  C11 Chaplin's 'Circus' with the original score.  C11 Theater: "The Mayor of Boys Town." C15 Music: Jose van Dam.  C11 Korean funeral rituals.  C14 Wonder Stuff.  C16 Music from Lebanon.  C18 Critic's Notebook C18 Books: "Zlata's Diary." C15 Television: Dennis Byrd's story.  C16 "In Search of Human Origins." C16 Editorials/Op-Ed A16-17 Editorials A wrongheaded amendment. Don't sell out WNYC. Russia's struggle within. Letters Anthony Lewis: A new ball game. William Safire: Peacemaking after Hebron. Yuri N. Afanasyev: Russia's vicious circle. Neediest Cases B3 Chronicle B4  Bridge C14 Crossword C15</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
