<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Reminder Of What Politics Breeds</title>
    <meta content="18MATTERS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/18/nyregion/18matters.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1665883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Metro Matters"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anti-Semitism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Fulani, Lenora B</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EFD81E3EF93BA25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Reminder Of What Politics Breeds</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Reminder of What Politics Breeds</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE PURNICK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE latest flap over remarks of a top Independence Party official almost makes one nostalgic for the wily old Liberals. Don't tell anyone we said that.</p>
        <p>The official, Lenora B. Fulani, has a way of saying things that offend lots of people, and she has done it again -- letting, almost encouraging, old words to come back and haunt her. Among remarks attributed to her in the past, in the late 1980's, are these: That Jews ''had to sell their souls to acquire Israel'' and had to ''function as mass murderers of people of color'' to keep it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The latest flap over remarks of top Independence Party official Lenora B. Fulani almost makes one nostalgic for the wily old Liberals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE latest flap over remarks of a top Independence Party official almost makes one nostalgic for the wily old Liberals. Don't tell anyone we said that.</p>
        <p>The official, Lenora B. Fulani, has a way of saying things that offend lots of people, and she has done it again -- letting, almost encouraging, old words to come back and haunt her. Among remarks attributed to her in the past, in the late 1980's, are these: That Jews ''had to sell their souls to acquire Israel'' and had to ''function as mass murderers of people of color'' to keep it.</p>
        <p>Asked about the comments last week, Dr. Fulani asked on NY1 News, ''What is anti-Semitic about it?'' And: ''It's raising issues that I think need to be explored.''</p>
        <p>Saying whatever she wants is her right. But Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg, who had the party's support four years ago, gave the party $250,000 last year and wants its endorsement again, found himself repeatedly criticizing Dr. Fulani's inflammatory words this weekend, calling them ''phenomenally offensive.''</p>
        <p>But he did not distance himself from the party, drawing a distinction between Dr. Fulani and the party.</p>
        <p>That is a neat trick, since the party's profile is pretty much hers. She is its most well-known official, its face and voice. Speeches and statements by Dr. Fulani and photographs of her figure prominently on the Web site of the New York City Independence Party: www.ipnyc.org.</p>
        <p>Why would the mayor want support from a party whose most prominent official courts controversy? Why have Senator Charles E. Schumer, Gov. George E. Pataki, Council Speaker Gifford Miller and Attorney General Eliot Spitzer accepted Independence Party support in the past?</p>
        <p>Votes. Third parties endure in New York because they mean votes. They attract votes from the unorthodox, the disaffected or those just unhappy with the two-party system. Votes are votes.</p>
        <p>In reality, the two main parties in the city are more alike than not. New York Republicans, like Mr. Bloomberg and Rudolph W. Giuliani, are inevitably progressive on large social issues. Otherwise, they wouldn't stand a chance in an overwhelmingly Democratic city.</p>
        <p>But there are still Democrats who cannot bring themselves to pull the Republican lever. The oft-quoted saying still remembered by older Jewish voters is that their finger would wither if they pulled a Republican lever.</p>
        <p>Enter the convenience of a third party.</p>
        <p>The most influential used to be the Liberal Party -- neither, it has often been said, liberal nor really a party. But Democrats and Republicans used to assiduously court the Liberals. The party didn't stand for much other than its power to endorse. It endorsed major-party candidates rather than running its own, and in return got patronage and status.</p>
        <p>In 2002, the Liberals didn't get enough statewide votes in the race for governor to remain an official party. Henry J. Stern, chairman of the Liberal Party, wants to revive it, perhaps with help from Mr. Bloomberg. If it got a ballot line, it could also endorse Mr. Bloomberg. But that would require gathering thousands of valid signatures and surviving the inevitable scrutiny of nit-picking election lawyers.</p>
        <p>FOR now, that leaves the Independence Party -- the third largest in the state -- with considerable influence. Its politics are more pragmatic than ideological. The party has endorsed Republicans (Mr. Pataki) and liberals (Ralph Nader for president).</p>
        <p>The platform of New York County's Independence Party is pretty much apple pie, calling for an end to budget deficits, ''restoring democratic choice and electoral accountability,'' discouraging teenage pregnancy and ''diminishing the pervasive and pernicious role of campaign contributions.''</p>
        <p>It is courted not for its platform, of course, but for its potentially influential endorsements. The Independence line might have made the difference for Mr. Bloomberg four years ago. City Board of Elections figures show that he drew 744,757 votes, and 59,091 were cast on the Independence line. These represented more than his margin of victory: He defeated Democrat Mark Green by 35,489 votes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bloomberg might have won anyway, mind you. More people might have voted for him on the Republican line. But in a tight race, he wasn't taking any chances. More is always better in campaigns.</p>
        <p>Naturally, there is a consequence to choosing pragmatism over principle. If Dr. Fulani's party plays kingmaker again, it -- and she -- can become only more powerful. They, and the people of New York, will have only the mayor to thank.</p>
        <p>In politics, there is always a price.</p>
        <p>Metro Matters</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
