<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Former WorldCom Executives Refuse to Testify to Congress</title>
    <meta content="Y09TELE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/09/business/09TELE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1406882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="CORPORATE CONDUCT: THE HEARINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fifth Amendment (US Constitution)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Self-Incrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Worldcom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Andersen, Arthur, &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Salomon Smith Barney</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cooper, Cynthia</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Norris, Floyd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ebbers, Bernard J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, Scott D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dick, Melvin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grubman, Jack B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sidgmore, John W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Bert C Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waters, Maxine (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandlin, Max (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oxley, Michael G (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutional Amendments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (State)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">WorldCom Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Romero, Simon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7DD1730F93AA35754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1200" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Former WorldCom Executives Refuse to Testify to Congress</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2 Former WorldCom Executives Refuse to Testify to Congress</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO with FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon; Norris, Floyd</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>WorldCom's former chief executive Bernard J Ebbers and former chief financial officer Scott D Sullivan, who played pivotal role at company before huge accounting irregularities were disclosed, refuse to testify before House Financial Services Committee, while Melvin Dick, former lead auditor for WorldCom for Arthur Andersen, and Jack B Grubman, leading telecommunications analyst from Salomon Smith Barney, say they had no hints of irregularities before they were disclosed by company; Ebbers outrages some members of committee by saying he did nothing wrong but then refusing to answer questions, invoking his Fifth Amendment right to avoid self-incrimination; Worldcom revises earlier statement to Securities and Exchange Commission, which says Sullivan asked Cynthia Cooper, internal auditor who discovered irregularities, to delay her audit; audit led to Sullivan's firing and WorldCom's saying it overstated pretax profits by $3.8 billion in 15-month period; WorldCom chief executive John W Sidgmore and chairman Bert C Roberts are subjected to tough questioning by committee members; Repr Maxine Waters says 'this cowboy capitalism must stop'; Repr Max Sandlin says Ebbers should be held in contempt of Congress; committee chairman Repr Michael G Oxley says he will consider Sandlin's request; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two former top executives of WorldCom who played a pivotal role at the company before huge accounting irregularities were disclosed last month refused to testify today, while the company's auditor and Wall Street's most prominent WorldCom analyst said they had no hints of the irregularities before they were disclosed by the company.</p>
        <p>Bernard J. Ebbers, WorldCom's former chief executive, outraged some members of the House Financial Services Committee by saying he had done nothing wrong but then refusing to answer any questions, invoking his Fifth Amendment right to avoid self-incrimination.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two former top executives of WorldCom who played a pivotal role at the company before huge accounting irregularities were disclosed last month refused to testify today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two former top executives of WorldCom who played a pivotal role at the company before huge accounting irregularities were disclosed last month refused to testify today, while the company's auditor and Wall Street's most prominent WorldCom analyst said they had no hints of the irregularities before they were disclosed by the company.</p>
        <p>Bernard J. Ebbers, WorldCom's former chief executive, outraged some members of the House Financial Services Committee by saying he had done nothing wrong but then refusing to answer any questions, invoking his Fifth Amendment right to avoid self-incrimination.</p>
        <p>Scott D. Sullivan, the company's former chief financial officer, also refused to testify, remaining silent and largely expressionless throughout the hearing.</p>
        <p>Separately, WorldCom revised an earlier statement submitted to the Securities and Exchange Commission, which said that Mr. Sullivan had asked Cynthia Cooper, the internal auditor who discovered the irregularities, to delay her audit. That audit led to Mr. Sullivan's firing and to WorldCom's saying it had overstated pretax profits by $3.8 billion in a 15-month period.</p>
        <p>At the hearing, which began at 1 p.m. and continued into the evening after only a brief break, the refusal of the two WorldCom executives to answer questions did not stop legislators from asking questions of them. Each time, each man invoked his right to avoid self-incrimination.</p>
        <p>Scheduled to testify last evening after the break were Bert C. Roberts, WorldCom's chairman, and John W. Sidgmore, who took over as chief executive at WorldCom in April after Mr. Ebbers resigned under pressure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sidgmore has blamed the previous management for WorldCom's accounting problems. In remarks prepared ahead of his testimony, Mr. Sidgmore said the company was one of the nation's ''last hopes'' to realize the intended benefits of competition in the telecommunications industry. He said WorldCom continued to talk with its lenders to try to secure lines of credit to keep the company solvent.</p>
        <p>Some members of the committee recommended jail terms for the executives responsible for WorldCom's accounting irregularities. Others questioned the moral fiber of the WorldCom executives and Jack B. Grubman, a leading telecommunications analyst from Salomon Smith Barney, and Melvin Dick, the former lead auditor for WorldCom for Arthur Andersen, who were also invited to testify.</p>
        <p>''This cowboy capitalism must stop,'' said Maxine Waters, Democrat of California, saying ''the shameful corporate culture of old-boy relationships'' was partly to blame for WorldCom's accounting irregularities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ebbers, who resigned from WorldCom in late April after a steep decline in the company's stock price and a deterioration in its financial situation, surprised the committee with a pithy statement before he invoked his right against self-incrimination. The committee, which usually requires copies of statements 48 hours in advance of hearings, was not expecting any comments from Mr. Ebbers.</p>
        <p>''I believe that no one will conclude that I engaged in any criminal or fraudulent conduct during my tenure at WorldCom,'' Mr. Ebbers, dressed in a conservative dark suit and turquoise watch and cufflinks, said to the committee. ''I am proud of the work that I did at WorldCom.''</p>
        <p>Representative Max Sandlin, Democrat of Texas, said Mr. Ebbers should be held in contempt of Congress. Mr. Sandlin argued that Mr. Ebbers waived his Fifth Amendment protection by delivering the statement defending his actions.</p>
        <p>Representative Michael G. Oxley, the Ohio Republican who is the committee's chairman, said he would consider Mr. Sandlin's request. Mr. Oxley unsuccessfully tried to excuse Mr. Ebbers from today's hearing after he refused to testify. But after other committee members demanded that Mr. Ebbers remain, Mr. Oxley said he would allow the committee's lawyers to review a request that Mr. Ebbers be required at some point to answer questions related to his brief statement.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Ebbers and Mr. Sullivan effectively silent for much of the hearing, the members of the committee turned much of their attention to the actions of Mr. Grubman, the telecommunications analyst, and Mr. Dick, the former auditor from Andersen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grubman was scrutinized for his unusually close ties to Mr. Ebbers and other top executives at WorldCom and for the profitably intricate investment banking relationships Salomon Smith Barney maintained with WorldCom while his analysis of the company's prospects were among the most glowing on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Questioned by Mr. Oxley whether he had attended board meetings at WorldCom, Mr. Grubman admitted that he attended ''maybe two or three'' during his time covering the company. Mr. Grubman said he took part in the meetings to provide the company with analyses of potential investor reaction to securities transactions managed by Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>''At those board meetings I was privy to material nonpublic information that was then released and publicly disseminated, usually within one to two days after those board meetings, after which then I was able to conduct my business as normal,'' Mr. Grubman said.</p>
        <p>Asked if WorldCom officials had lied to him, Mr. Grubman replied, ''If what was allegated is true, then I was deceived.'' He said he had trusted WorldCom's published financial statements. ''There were no red flags'' that an analyst should have caught, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grubman said that his total compensation from Salomon Smith Barney over the past four years averaged $20 million a year, and said that one factor in setting the amount was his contribution to investment banking business. But he said he was not specifically paid for his role in any one transaction, and said that pay did ''not cloud my judgment,'' adding, ''I care about my reputation with investors.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grubman said he had no advance knowledge of WorldCom's accounting irregularities even though he lowered his rating on its stock just days before WorldCom disclosed the problem on June 25. ''I found WorldCom's announcement of accounting fraud to be extremely disturbing,'' Mr. Grubman said.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Dick, the former auditor from Andersen, told the committee that he could not say whether WorldCom committed any crime by improperly accounting for expenses he invoked the wrath of several committee members.</p>
        <p>''Oh, stop giving us these happy horsefeathers!'' said Gary L. Ackerman, a Democrat from New York. ''You still feel the need to cover up for these guys? I thought you were off the job. Would you certify their audits today?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dick, who resigned from Arthur Andersen at the beginning of June to become the chief financial officer of Coldwater Creek, an apparel company, replied, ''Not based on the information I know today, no.''</p>
        <p>In any case, members of the committee seemed unconvinced today that WorldCom would be the end of a series of recent accounting scandals.</p>
        <p>''The imperative of meeting analysts' quarterly projections has trumped the interests of shareholders and, indeed, threatened the long-term prospects of the companies themselves,'' said John J. LaFalce of New York, the committee's highest-ranking Democrat.</p>
        <p>CORPORATE CONDUCT: THE HEARINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
