<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baby, It's Cold Outside</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Men's Fashions of The Times Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="714007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPECIAL SECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HATS AND CAPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCARVES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GLOVES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MULLEN, JIM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUBENSTEIN, HAL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2DD1538F936A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baby, It's Cold Outside</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jim Mullen and Hal Rubenstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MULLEN, JIM; RUBENSTEIN, HAL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>You can buy the thickest shearling or the downiest anorak -- you can even buy a chinchilla trench (though please don't). But fail to protect everything else your new coat doesn't, and you're going to freeze your everything else off. Cold hands, warm heart is a cute aphorism. Try getting past it when you're out of fire logs. Winter's accessories aren't options anymore. Gloves</p>
        <p>* Unlined gloves are devilishly sexy, but not warm. Cashmere and wool-lined are, and since the price isn't much higher for what's softer and lighter, go cashmere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>You can buy the thickest shearling or the downiest anorak -- you can even buy a chinchilla trench (though please don't). But fail to protect everything else your new coat doesn't, and you're going to freeze your everything else off. Cold hands, warm heart is a cute aphorism. Try getting past it when you're out of fire logs. Winter's accessories aren't options anymore. Gloves</p>
        <p>* Unlined gloves are devilishly sexy, but not warm. Cashmere and wool-lined are, and since the price isn't much higher for what's softer and lighter, go cashmere.</p>
        <p>* Double-lined gloves are bulkier but warmer still because they're really two gloves: a wool one inside a leather one.</p>
        <p>* The worst lining for gloves is rabbit fur. It feels oily, and you'll sweat until the fur mats like an untended toupee.</p>
        <p>* Wool gloves offer variety, weightlessness and -- essential for those who keep losing lefts -- economy. Scientists, however, claim the most efficient hand covers are mittens. They would. Try reading a paper, finding a token, dialing a pay phone or driving anything, and you'd sooner wear handcuffs left overnight in the refrigerator.</p>
        <p>* How should gloves fit? Take a guess. A clue, just in case: That extra space at the end of the fingers isn't supposed to be there unless you're expecting sudden surges of growth. Scarves</p>
        <p>* They were designed to keep your neck warm, not to be worn like secular prayer shawls.</p>
        <p>* If one doesn't wrap around your neck at least twice, don't bother.</p>
        <p>* Go gently into that bad night. The neck is wrapped in thin, easily irritated skin. Cashmere, silk, cotton and viscose blends are kind. Polyester, shetland or lamb's wool costs less, but may turn the vicinity of your Adam's apple into a topographical map of the lunar surface. This is not how you exhibit bravado. John Wayne wore cotton kerchiefs.</p>
        <p>* It's a lot harder to pull off two coats than two scarves.</p>
        <p>* Can't duplicate those intricate knots in the ads? Take a long scarf. Double it. Hang it around your neck. Pull the loose ends through the curve on the opposite side. Fling both ends over opposite shoulders. If you've done it right, you'll look like a Lillehammer Olympian. If you've done it wrong, you'll look as if you and Bea Arthur were separated at birth. Hats</p>
        <p>* You lose so much body heat through your head that any covering is fine. Should you look great in hats, it's time to shine. If you're like most who don't, put it this way: You're not going to look so great with blue lips and a red nose anyway. Cut your losses.</p>
        <p>* Everyone makes fun of ear flaps. Until they wear them. Let them call you Elmer Fudd. How often did he catch the flu?</p>
        <p>* Fedoras blow away. Baseball caps are thin and often perforated. A watch cap is as good as it gets. Don't wear it like a yarmulke. Pull it over the ears and down the forehead. Cashmere watch caps are almost too cool for this lifetime.</p>
        <p>* Fur hats work. Ask Solzhenitsyn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
