<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Little Bit Of Inflation Could Go A Long Way</title>
    <meta content="02VIEW$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/02/business/yourmoney/02VIEW.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1397234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ECONOMIC VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic View</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenspan, Alan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EED9173AF931A35755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Little Bit Of Inflation Could Go A Long Way</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Little Bit of Inflation Could Go a Long Way</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM REDBURN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EVERYBODY knows it's possible to have too much of a good thing. Too much rich food leads to indigestion; too many e-mail messages can drive you to the delete button.</p>
        <p>The same is true of the Federal Reserve's long crusade to eliminate inflation from the American economy. That campaign, begun courageously by Paul Volcker in 1979 when prices were spiraling higher at double-digit rates and carried on brilliantly by Alan Greenspan over the last 15 years, is one of the great success stories of economic policy, helping to lay the foundation for much of the prosperity of recent years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everybody knows it's possible to have too much of a good thing. The same is true of the Fed's long crusade to eliminate inflation from the American economy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EVERYBODY knows it's possible to have too much of a good thing. Too much rich food leads to indigestion; too many e-mail messages can drive you to the delete button.</p>
        <p>The same is true of the Federal Reserve's long crusade to eliminate inflation from the American economy. That campaign, begun courageously by Paul Volcker in 1979 when prices were spiraling higher at double-digit rates and carried on brilliantly by Alan Greenspan over the last 15 years, is one of the great success stories of economic policy, helping to lay the foundation for much of the prosperity of recent years.</p>
        <p>But enough is enough.</p>
        <p>The danger is not just that the economy could fall into a deep deflationary pit, as it did in the Depression or as Japan's economy is doing today. The Fed will do everything in its power to prevent that. The more subtle risk is from the conventional view -- particularly among bond market vigilantes -- that zero inflation is the ideal and should be pursued without question. That stern attitude blocks the modest upward creep in the overall price level that is needed to properly grease the wheels of commerce.</p>
        <p>Some Fed officials, even those long identified with a hawkish anti-inflationary stance, have begun to recognize this danger.</p>
        <p>''I always think of myself as pretty resolute when it comes to inflation,'' Robert Parry, president of the Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco, said in a mid-May talk. ''But perhaps a little bit of inflation,'' he added, ''is a little bit safer than zero.''</p>
        <p>William McDonough, the president of the Federal Reserve Bank of New York, was even more explicit about his willingness to tolerate a small amount of inflation. Not long ago, when consumer price inflation was running at 1.4 percent, he said, ''If that's not price stability, what is?''</p>
        <p>This unusually candid talk, coming from central bankers inculcated by their own code of silence never to say a kind word about inflation, is a positive sign. But even an inflation rate somewhat higher than today's would be nothing to fear. Indeed, it would be welcome.</p>
        <p>Already, inflation, by just about every important indicator, is low and headed lower.</p>
        <p>''One is a lovely number,'' James Glassman, senior economist at J. P. Morgan Securities, wrote in a recent report. ''Most measures of inflation have eased into a range that brackets 1 percent annually. Only the core C.P.I. inflation rate stands apart from the crowd of inflation measures, but it too is easing slightly from last year's 2.7 percent.''</p>
        <p>With inflation so low, however, prices for most goods are still falling. The only signs of price increases are in housing and in services, particularly for medical services where past gains from managed care are beginning to erode. As a result, corporate profits in many sectors remain depressed, retarding the revival of investment needed to sustain a healthy economic recovery.</p>
        <p>It is important to remember that a market economy works through price fluctuations that respond to changes in supply and demand. In the absence of inflation, the only way to signal relative differences across the full range of goods and services is for some prices to fall in absolute terms even as others are rising.</p>
        <p>A modicum of inflation allows this price signaling to occur without squeezing so many producers to cut prices. As long as the central bank does not allow it to get out of control, this kind of modest upward price movement creates an environment more conducive to economic growth than a determination to squelch inflation at all cost.</p>
        <p>FORTUNATELY for the economy, Fed officials are recognizing that overall price stability is not an unalloyed virtue. ''Policy actions,'' said Myles Zyblock, a Brown Brothers Harriman economist, ''appear to have shifted from one of restraining price increases to reflating demand.''</p>
        <p>And with inflation tame, Mr. Glassman said, ''the Fed will have little fear of allowing the economy to regain its stride.''</p>
        <p>What's good for the economy, though, will probably not help the stock market regain its vitality. Indeed, perhaps the greatest single prop underlying the almost uninterrupted market boom of 1980's and 90's was the secular decline in interest rates that accompanied disinflation. Not only did corporate profits rise sharply, but investors found it easy to value stocks at unprecedented multiples to earnings.</p>
        <p>That movement has now run its course. ''A flattening-out of inflation trends,'' Mr. Zyblock wrote in a recent investment report, ''suggests that the up trend in price-to-earnings ratios that began in the early 1980's is over.''</p>
        <p>But don't cry for your lost investment gains. Given a choice, a thriving Main Street beats a swaggering Wall Street anytime.</p>
        <p>ECONOMIC VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
