<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Koreans Vote, Seeking Rescue From Economic Crisis</title>
    <meta content="18KORE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="981335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kristof, Nicholas D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kim Dae Jung</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee Hoi Chang</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EFD8103FF93BA25751C1A961958260" item-length="998" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Koreans Vote, Seeking Rescue From Economic Crisis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICHOLAS D. KRISTOF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kristof, Nicholas D</byline>
      <dateline>SEOUL, South Korea, Thursday, Dec. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>South Koreans vote amid economic crisis to choose President to preside over far-reaching industrial overhaul; candidates, including front-runners, Kim Dae Jung and Lee Hoi Chang, seek to portray selves as reassuring figures able to lead nation to recovery; Kim victory would mark first peaceful transfer of presidency to opposition party in modern Korean history; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Voters began casting their ballots this morning for a new President to rescue this nation from its financial crisis and preside over a far-reaching industrial overhaul during the next five years.</p>
        <p>As the candidates finished their campaigning on Wednesday night, bellowing in hoarse voices to shoppers in the markets, the election came to be widely seen as a milestone in Korean history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Voters began casting their ballots this morning for a new President to rescue this nation from its financial crisis and preside over a far-reaching industrial overhaul during the next five years.</p>
        <p>As the candidates finished their campaigning on Wednesday night, bellowing in hoarse voices to shoppers in the markets, the election came to be widely seen as a milestone in Korean history.</p>
        <p>It is a bit like the American Presidential election of 1932, during the Great Depression, and each candidate is trying to portray himself as a reassuring Roosevelt-like figure able to lead the country to economic recovery.</p>
        <p>The two leading candidates, Kim Dae Jung (pronounced kim-day-joong) and Lee Hoi Chang (pronounced ee-hweh-chahng), were neck and neck in opinion polls, but they come from very different backgrounds. Mr. Lee is a former judge and the epitome of the establishment, while Mr. Kim is a legendary democracy campaigner in Asia whom past South Korean Presidents repeatedly tried to kill.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Kim wins, it will be the first peaceful transfer of the presidency to the opposition party in modern Korean history. Just 10 years ago, when Mr. Kim was also running, the country was rife with rumors that his victory would provoke a military coup. Now there are no such rumblings.</p>
        <p>In any case, this will probably be the closest and most democratic election Korea has ever had, and the dominant issue is simply who will be able to resolve the national crisis and restore South Korea to greatness.</p>
        <p>''I ran three times before in presidential elections, and this is surely my last chance,'' Mr. Kim declared as campaigning ended on Wednesday. ''I thank the public for reserving me until today, when the nation truly needs a strong and capable leader.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim also warned that if Mr. Lee was elected, ''the nation will plunge into deeper crisis.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee responded by suggesting that the financial markets would effectively punish Korea if it chose Mr. Kim. ''If a figure lacking credibility with the international community takes office, there would be a further exodus of our meager foreign capital,'' Mr. Lee declared, referring to Mr. Kim.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Lee and Mr. Kim have lived in the United States and speak fairly good English, and each portrays himself as the international candidate with the ties to Washington that can help resolve the crisis.</p>
        <p>Both candidates now say they favor far-reaching economic changes in accordance with the International Monetary Fund's bailout of South Korea.</p>
        <p>Financial analysts said that the stock market would probably react better to a win by Mr. Lee, as he is regarded as more of a pro-business candidate, while Mr. Kim is seen as a populist who might be reluctant to close bankrupt companies and put people out of work.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Mr. Kim has far more credibility with labor unions, and with the poor and disenfranchised. If Mr. Kim backs a far-reaching restructuring program, he may be able to do it more easily than anyone else.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lee is gambling that voters will be angry at the governing party but fearful of turning to the untested opposition at a moment of crisis, and he has spoken under the banner of ''stability against turmoil.''</p>
        <p>''Since the economy is experiencing difficulties and the country is unstable, the entire nation must be led by a responsible and stable political force,'' Mr. Lee declared on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kim is hoping that the public will be so disgusted by the Government's mishandling of the crisis that it will punish Mr. Lee and the governing party, and he tells voters, ''the country needs a shift of power.''</p>
        <p>Traditionally, South Korea has been fiercely divided by regional rivalries that go back many centuries but have been exacerbated in recent decades. Mr. Kim is the hero of the Cholla provinces in the southwest, and he normally gets almost all of the votes there but few in the rest of the country, particularly the southeast.</p>
        <p>Those rivalries are still evident in this election, but they may have subsided a bit. There is no candidate from the southeast this time, for Mr. Lee was born in what is now North Korea.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Lee made a campaign swing to Kwangju, in the heart of Cholla, as a show of broad-mindedness. During his two-hour visit, he was heavily protected by riot-equipped policemen and by guards sent by Mr. Kim's supporters, who feared that any clashes could be used against their candidate. In the end, the visit went smoothly.</p>
        <p>''A national leader should not neglect any city or province,'' Mr. Lee thundered in his speech in Kwangju, which chafes at the neglect it has suffered from the Government for several decades.</p>
        <p>The campaign has also been remarkable for its historical ironies. In a tribute to pragmatism or opportunism, depending on one's analysis, Mr. Kim has allied himself with an erstwhile rival who symbolizes the military dictatorship that tried to kill Mr. Kim in the 1970's.</p>
        <p>He has struck a deal with Kim Jong Pil, who has strong support in the southeast but was the founder of the Korean Central Intelligence Agency and was a top adviser to President Park Chung Hee in the 1960's and 1970's.</p>
        <p>President Park's Government tried to murder Kim Dae Jung several times, and the K.C.I.A. once kidnapped him while he was visiting Tokyo, apparently with the idea of drowning him in the ocean. Western governments intervened, and Kim Dae Jung's life was spared.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement between the two men, Kim Dae Jung would become President initially, but South Korea could then move to a parliamentary system headed by Kim Jong Pil.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
