<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Ramsey Case Revisited</title>
    <meta content="18CARR$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="981300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boulder (Colo)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, Caleb</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ramsey, Jonbenet</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado/Boulder</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Special Prosecutors (Independent Counsel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4DB103FF93BA25751C1A961958260" item-length="853" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Ramsey Case Revisited</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Caleb Carr</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carr, Caleb</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caleb Carr Op-Ed article on Dec 1996 murder of JonBenet Ramsey, 6, in Boulder, Colo; urges state to name special prosecutor to convene grand jury and probe crime (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The passage of time rarely has a salutary effect when it comes to solving crimes. Leads peter out, trails grow cold, witnesses' recollections fade, evidence becomes scattered and tainted. And, perhaps most pernicious of all, public outrage exhausts itself.</p>
        <p>The investigation into the death of 6-year-old JonBenet Ramsey in Boulder, Colo., last Christmas currently suffers from all of these problems. With the one-year anniversary of her death a week away, we seem as far from a solution, or even a vigorous prosecution of the crime, as we were when her body was first discovered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The passage of time rarely has a salutary effect when it comes to solving crimes. Leads peter out, trails grow cold, witnesses' recollections fade, evidence becomes scattered and tainted. And, perhaps most pernicious of all, public outrage exhausts itself.</p>
        <p>The investigation into the death of 6-year-old JonBenet Ramsey in Boulder, Colo., last Christmas currently suffers from all of these problems. With the one-year anniversary of her death a week away, we seem as far from a solution, or even a vigorous prosecution of the crime, as we were when her body was first discovered.</p>
        <p>Many possible reasons have been cited for this: shoddy police work, internal Colorado politics, the usual competition between law enforcement agencies, the wealth and importance of the girl's family. But it's clear that a greater effort needs to be mounted. And a sound beginning would be the appointment of a special prosecutor by the State of Colorado, and for that prosecutor to convene a grand jury to investigate the matter. There are extraordinary aspects of the case that make such moves appropriate.</p>
        <p>In the days after JonBenet's death, her parents, John and Patsy Ramsey, stopped actively cooperating with the police and hired lawyers and their own investigative team. They also refused to allow law enforcement officials to formally interrogate their 9-year-old son, Burke, who they say was the only other person in the house that night, besides themselves and JonBenet.</p>
        <p>The Ramseys emerged from seclusion only once in those first weeks, on Jan. 1, giving an unexpected interview to CNN and offering their interpretation of what had happened to their daughter. ''There is a killer on the loose,'' Patsy Ramsey said. ''There's someone out there.''</p>
        <p>The statement played nicely to the American taste for seeing ghouls lurking in every shadow, and it seemed to suggest that there were many possible explanations for JonBenet's death. But in fact, as law enforcement officials claim, only one of two things could have happened in the Ramsey house that night. The first possibility is that someone entered the house through unknown means, brutally yet elaborately killed JonBenet, changed her clothes, hid her body, sat down to write a lengthy note to her parents, then left without leaving any trace of himself or herself -- all without being heard or seen at any point by anyone in the house. The second is that the crime was committed by someone who was in the house that night.</p>
        <p>A grand jury -- apart from investigating how law enforcement agencies have handled (or mishandled) the case -- could compel the kind of testimony from vital witnesses that has so far been lacking. To force cooperation from those witnesses, however, a grand jury would typically grant them some kind of immunity from future prosecution for anything uncovered in their testimony.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors would therefore be unlikely to summon Patsy or John Ramsey, who are both considered to be under ''an umbrella of suspicion,'' as Comdr. Mark Beckner of the Boulder police stated earlier this month.</p>
        <p>But summoning Burke Ramsey is another matter. According to the City of Boulder's communications director, Leslie Aaholm, the Ramseys have not allowed law enforcement officials to conduct what would ordinarily have been a routine interrogation of their son. He was questioned once, briefly, when the police first arrived at the scene. He was later interviewed by a child psychologist, who talked to him generally about life in the home, but did not ask questions related to JonBenet's death.</p>
        <p>From the prosecutor's point of view, bringing Burke Ramsey before a grand jury might seem risky. There is always the chance that a witness given immunity will implicate himself and thereby prevent his testimony from being used against him. But even if that witness confesses to a crime, prosecutors can still press the case using evidence other than that confession. If this crime was committed by someone else, however, the chance that Burke Ramsey saw or heard something crucial is also certainly worth bringing him into court.</p>
        <p>But the Boulder District Attorney, Alex Hunter, has thus far shown no taste for such a move, and the case festers endlessly. Of course, there have been famous cases in which dogged police or prosecutorial work produced an arrest and a conviction years after the crime. These cases, though, have typically been unraveled by officers privately obsessed with finding solutions.</p>
        <p>Such characters have yet to enter the tale of JonBenet Ramsey, and the case shows signs of slipping away into the files of the unsolved. Once there, it can only further inure us to such painful episodes and sharpen our already considerable cynicism about equal justice for all.</p>
        <p>Caleb Carr is the author of ''The Alienist'' and ''The Angel of Darkness.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Caleb Carr is the author of ''The Alienist'' and ''The Angel of Darkness.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
