<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kasparaitis Is a Symbol Of a Team Gone Soft</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="650220"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DB143EF936A25752C1A965958260" item-length="451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kasparaitis Is a Symbol Of a Team Gone Soft</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I., Nov. 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When a team slumps as thoroughly as the Islanders have, it is misleading to blame only one struggling player for the widespread malaise. Nevertheless, some seem to stand out as symbols.</p>
        <p>For the Islanders, the symbol of the day is Darius Kasparaitis. Last season, when Kasparaitis was a rookie, his jolting body checks and ebullient personality were the essence of a surprisingly successful team that overachieved into the third round of the Stanley Cup playoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When a team slumps as thoroughly as the Islanders have, it is misleading to blame only one struggling player for the widespread malaise. Nevertheless, some seem to stand out as symbols.</p>
        <p>For the Islanders, the symbol of the day is Darius Kasparaitis. Last season, when Kasparaitis was a rookie, his jolting body checks and ebullient personality were the essence of a surprisingly successful team that overachieved into the third round of the Stanley Cup playoffs.</p>
        <p>This season, his problems on and off the ice have come to symbolize a team with a 4-12-1 record, good for last place in the Atlantic Division. When the Islanders lost by 5-2 at home to Boston on Saturday night, Kasparaitis was benched. More precisely, he sat in a luxury box and watched the team lose its third consecutive game and its fifth in its last six. Plus/Minus, More or Less</p>
        <p>Part of the reason for his benching is statistical. Kasparaitis has no goals and no assists and a minus 12 in the plus/minus category, meaning opponents have scored 12 more goals than the Islanders when Kasparaitis is on the ice during even-strength situations.</p>
        <p>Another reason for the benching is his attitude.</p>
        <p>"It's time for Kaspar to take a step back and assess his play and also assess his work habits, his dedication and determination for the game," said Coach Al Arbor.</p>
        <p>Management wasn't pleased last summer when Kasparaitis was arrested and charged with driving while intoxicated, a case still pending in Suffolk County. He didn't win any praise for showing up at training camp 15 pounds overweight. Slimming down seemed to reduce the force of his body checks for the first few weeks of the season.</p>
        <p>His teammates say his work habits haven't changed all that much from last season. He is still one of the last to show up for practice and one of the first to leave. Hey, he's a busy guy with things to do. The other day after working out, he dashed into Manhattan to marry Irina Kouznetsova at City Hall.</p>
        <p>As is often the case with the 21-year-old from Lithuania, it was an eye-opening adventure in Big City, U.S.A.</p>
        <p>"Somebody told me go to New York City because it's faster," Kasparaitis said. "It went too fast. Two minutes. Nobody speaks English. People were speaking Spanish and German."</p>
        <p>Returning to the subject of hockey, Kasparaitis said, in his rapidly improving English: "I've got good weight, I'm in good shape. I work hard every practice. I take care of myself."</p>
        <p>"Maybe Al thinks I go out every night," Kasparaitis said.</p>
        <p>He conceded that he started with more energy last season and that this season he was building more gradually. "I play every game much better," he said. "I hit people every game. Make my hits."</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
