<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supreme Court Roundup; Justices to Rule on Challenges by Career Criminals</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="640831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RAILROADS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRESS (HUMAN)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMOSEXUALITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KIDNAPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KIDNAPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MENTAL HEALTH AND DISORDERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY (CIA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Stress (Human)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stress (Human)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DE1F3DF930A25753C1A965958260" item-length="1210" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supreme Court Roundup; Justices to Rule on Challenges by Career Criminals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court agreed today to decide whether Federal defendants who face sentencing as career criminals can challenge the validity of the earlier state court convictions that subject them to stiff Federal minimum sentences.</p>
        <p>Under the Armed Career Criminal Act, a person with three previous convictions for violent felonies or serious drug offenses must receive a sentence of at least 15 years, with a maximum of life in prison, if subsequently convicted of owning or transporting a gun.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court agreed today to decide whether Federal defendants who face sentencing as career criminals can challenge the validity of the earlier state court convictions that subject them to stiff Federal minimum sentences.</p>
        <p>Under the Armed Career Criminal Act, a person with three previous convictions for violent felonies or serious drug offenses must receive a sentence of at least 15 years, with a maximum of life in prison, if subsequently convicted of owning or transporting a gun.</p>
        <p>The law, aimed at violent multiple offenders, is one of the most potent in the growing Federal arsenal of laws that carry mandatory minimum sentences.</p>
        <p>The lower Federal courts disagree on an important aspect of the law: whether the previous convictions that are the basis for the mandatory sentence can be subject to constitutional challenge long after the convictions had become final and sentence had been served. Was Counsel Effective?</p>
        <p>In the appeal the Court accepted today, the lower courts ruled that a Maryland man could not try to make the case that previous convictions for robbery and burglary were invalid. The man contended that the earlier state court convictions should not be used as the basis for a Federal mandatory minimum sentence because he had not had effective counsel and had not been fully informed of the consequences of his guilty plea.</p>
        <p>The Federal District Court in Maryland and the United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit, in Richmond, held in this case that the defendant, Darren J. Custis, could challenge the earlier convictions only if he had had no legal representation at all in the state proceedings.</p>
        <p>Other Federal courts have permitted challenges on broader grounds, including inadequate legal representation and an invalid guilty plea. The Justice Department, while telling the Justices that the lower courts in the Custis case were correct, supported the appeal on the ground that only the Supreme Court could resolve the confusion.</p>
        <p>Without evidence of the earlier state convictions that Mr. Custis argues were constitutionally flawed, he faced a sentence of about three years under the Federal sentencing guidelines for his new Federal convictions on charges of cocaine and gun possession. Once placed in the armed career criminal category, however, he was sentenced to just under 20 years.</p>
        <p>The Armed Career Criminal Act is only one of several Federal laws that carry mandatory minimum sentences. One frequently used Federal narcotics law that provides for enhanced sentences for multiple offenders explicitly permits defendants to challenge the validity of the earlier convictions. By contrast, the Armed Career Criminal Act is silent on the question.</p>
        <p>The Court's decision in this case, Custis v. United States, No. 93-5209, could also have important implications for the Federal sentencing guidelines. Across the spectrum of criminal sentences, the guidelines provide longer sentences for people with previous criminal convictions.</p>
        <p>As in the case of the Armed Career Criminal Act, the Federal courts disagree over whether those earlier convictions are subject to challenge at the new sentencing hearing. A ruling by the Supreme Court in the Custis case that defendants have a constitutional right to bring such challenges would apply in the sentencing-guidelines context as well.</p>
        <p>There were these other developments at the Court today: Railroad Stress</p>
        <p>The Court agreed to decide whether railroad workers can sue their employers, in this case Conrail, for emotional as well as physical injuries.</p>
        <p>The case, Consolidated Rail Corporation v. Gottshall, No. 92-1956, will resolve a longstanding ambiguity under an 85-year-old Federal law, the Federal Employers Liability Act. The law allows railroad workers to go to Federal court to sue railroads for negligence.</p>
        <p>While some Federal courts have limited the scope of the law to negligence that results in physical injury, the United States Court of Appeals for the Third Circuit in this case said that the law also applied "when it is reasonably foreseeable that extended exposure to dangerous and stressful working conditions" will cause serious emotional distress.</p>
        <p>The appeals court, which is based in Philadelphia, applied its test in favor of railroad workers in two cases. In one, a member of a track repair crew suffered a nervous breakdown when he witnessed the death of a fellow worker on a 97-degree day; the crew was ordered back to work while the body was covered and left to await the arrival of the coroner. The Third Circuit permitted that case to go to trial, which has not yet taken place.</p>
        <p>In the second case, a dispatcher in a supervisory position suffered a breakdown after being required to work 15-hour days for 13 straight days in midst of a staff reduction. The Third Circuit upheld a jury award of $386,500.</p>
        <p>In its Supreme Court appeal, Conrail is arguing that the Third Circuit's standard opens the door to liability for a railroad whenever workers have a physical manifestation of stress. Gay Agent</p>
        <p>Without comment, the Court refused to hear an appeal filed by a gay man who worked for the Central Intelligence Agency for nine years before the agency learned of his homosexuality and dismissed him in 1982.</p>
        <p>The man, identified in Court papers as John Doe because he served in an undercover position, argued that he had a constitutional right to continued employment as long as he complied with all security regulations. He said he had breached no regulations, had not compromised any classified information, and that as an openly gay man, was not liable to blackmail. He challenged a "blanket ban" by the C.I.A. on employing homosexuals.</p>
        <p>The man had earlier lost his case before the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit, which ruled earlier this year that the C.I.A. did not appear to have a general policy of that sort, but rather had dismissed him based on an "individualized determination that his own case represented a threat to the national security mission of the Agency."</p>
        <p>Justice Ruth Bader Ginsburg did not vote in the case, Doe v. Woolsey, No. 92-2025, presumably because she served on the appeals court when the case was there. Bounty Hunters</p>
        <p>The Court asked for the Clinton Administration's views on whether to hear a case brought by a Canadian woman whose husband was kidnapped by Florida bounty hunters from a Toronto street 12 years ago and brought to Florida to stand trial on a land fraud charge. The bounty hunters, who were later prosecuted in Canada, had been hired by a Florida bail bond company after the man, Sidney Jaffe, had fled the state and forfeited a $137,500 bond.</p>
        <p>Ruth Jaffe, Mr. Jaffe's wife, sued the bail bond company in the Canadian courts and won a $2.5 million judgment against it, which the Florida courts have refused to enforce. The Government of Canada joined Mrs. Jaffe's appeal, Jaffe v. Snow, No. 93-241, urging the Court to hear the case and order Florida to honor the Canadian judgment. In its brief, the Canadian Government called the abduction of Mr. Jaffe "a blatant infringement of Canadian territorial sovereignty" that violated the extradition treaty with the United States and international law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
