<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Big Board protects speculators from a worthless stock.</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="640893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS (CORPORATE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKRUPTCIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER PROTECTION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">JWP INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STOCK EXCHANGE (NYSE)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN STOCK EXCHANGE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORRIS, FLOYD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DB133FF930A25753C1A965958260" item-length="656" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Big Board protects speculators from a worthless stock.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Floyd Norris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORRIS, FLOYD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHARES in JWP Inc. are worthless. And, for a change, you can't easily trade them.</p>
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange halted trading in the company, the former Jamaica Water Properties, as soon as the company announced that a prepackaged bankruptcy plan would result in the cancellation of the shares.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHARES in JWP Inc. are worthless. And, for a change, you can't easily trade them.</p>
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange halted trading in the company, the former Jamaica Water Properties, as soon as the company announced that a prepackaged bankruptcy plan would result in the cancellation of the shares.</p>
        <p>In recent years, the specter of ignorant investors paying absurdly high prices for stocks that were worthless, or all but worthless, has been both profitable and embarrassing to the New York and American Stock Exchanges.</p>
        <p>The Amex allowed Continental Airlines to trade for several weeks after the company filed its plan to cancel its shares, making them worthless but allowing traders who understood what was happening to profit at the expense of ignorant speculators. More recently, securities in LTV continued to trade on the Big Board, fetching prices many times the pennies they were worth under that company's reorganization plan.</p>
        <p>But in this case, it appears that the Big Board will not allow any more trading. The stock is under review for possible delisting, an exchange spokeswoman said yesterday. It is unlikely to survive such a review.</p>
        <p>JWP's talks with creditors had been going on for months, and last June the company said creditors were likely to get large amounts of stock to satisfy their debt. (Now, all the new stock will be owned by the creditors.) Volume was heavy, but the price never fell below $1 a share.</p>
        <p>Traders who were canny enough to see the carnage that was coming sold the stock short, correctly betting on a decline. The short position in early September, the latest report available, was 3.8 million shares, or about 9 percent of the outstanding shares.</p>
        <p>The disappearance of JWP shares also created a problem for the Standard &amp; Poor's 500, of which it had been the smallest member. Standard &amp; Poor's said late yesterday that Pioneer Hi-Bred, the seed company, will replace JWP at the close of trading today. In the meantime, the published figures for the index are slightly overstated, simply because the price being used for JWP is $1.125, its final trading price on Friday -- giving it a now-vanished market value of $46 million. Adjusting that price to zero would bring the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 down about 0.0066 point, meaning that yesterday's published value of 461.12 probably should have been 461.11.</p>
        <p>The market value of Pioneer is $3 billion, and its addition to the index could conceivably have a negative effect on the market today. Index funds will have to buy Pioneer, and their only source of funds to pay for those shares will be the sale of small portions of their stakes in the other 499 companies.</p>
        <p>When JWP is out of the index, Fedders, the air-conditioner company, will be the smallest member of the S.&amp; P. 500, with a market value of $100 million. General Electric, the biggest company in the index, has a market value of $81.6 billion. The Joke Indicator</p>
        <p>Wall Street may not always be a funny place, but there are usually a lot of jokes to be heard among traders. Many, to be sure, are of questionable taste. For those not on the circuit, one way to keep up is with a monthly publication put out by the Leuthold Group, an institutional research firm in Minneapolis, which includes a "joke of the month."</p>
        <p>The October issue, alas, reports that no good jokes came in during the prior month. We got to wondering whether a lack of Wall Street humor might itself be a market indicator and found out than in the last five years the only other issues in which Steve Leuthold, the report's proprietor, could not come up with a joke were May 1991 and May 1992. As it happens, stocks rose in both Mays but then fell the next month. The Dow Jones industrial average fell 2 percent in one June and 4 percent in the other, while the Nasdaq composite showed losses of 4 percent and 6 percent.</p>
        <p>If that pattern holds, prices will rise this month and then sink in November.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
