<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Decade Later, It's Torvill and Dean Again</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="640957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="COUNTDOWN TO LILLEHAMMER: FIGURE SKATING:"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1994)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINTER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIGURE SKATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ICE DANCING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TORVILL, JAYNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEAN, CHRISTOPHER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DD1F31F930A25753C1A965958260" item-length="1943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Decade Later, It's Torvill and Dean Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLAREY, CHRISTOPHER</byline>
      <dateline>MILTON KEYNES, England</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is early yet, but the 1990's have not been kind to comebacks. Bjorn Borg hauled his wood racquet out of the closet and got whacked. Mark Spitz hauled out his skimpy bathers and got lapped. Magic Johnson gathered up his courage and caught flak.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to Jayne Torvill and Christopher Dean, onetime darlings of the British Isles and the international skating world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is early yet, but the 1990's have not been kind to comebacks. Bjorn Borg hauled his wood racquet out of the closet and got whacked. Mark Spitz hauled out his skimpy bathers and got lapped. Magic Johnson gathered up his courage and caught flak.</p>
        <p>Which brings us to Jayne Torvill and Christopher Dean, onetime darlings of the British Isles and the international skating world.</p>
        <p>Nobody ever danced better on ice than they did on Valentine's Day in Sarajevo at the 1984 Winter Olympics. No couple has done more to push the sport's envelope over the last nine years as professionals.</p>
        <p>What on earth then do they have to gain by dusting off their compulsories and attempting to duplicate perfection at the 1994 Olympics next February in Lillehammer?</p>
        <p>"We have come full circle," said the 35-year-old Dean, who if he makes it to Norway will be older than every other skater except his 36-year-old partner. "I think if somebody had asked us to do this two or three years ago, we would have said 'no.' But we feel as if we have done all there is to do in the professional world. It will have been 10 years since Sarajevo, a decade gone by. That number has some significance for us as well."</p>
        <p>It bears reiterating that until recently, luminaries like Torvill and Dean, who also won four world championships from 1981 to 1984, did not have the option of throwing caution to the wind. But ever since the International Skating Union announced last year that professionals would be allowed to regain amateur status, several high-profile skaters have elected to put their egos and financial futures on the line.</p>
        <p>"It's true that the amateur scene generates a big interest that makes it attractive to be part of again," Dean said. "People always said to us, 'What have you been doing the last few years?' We've been out there, doing shows and live performances, but if you're not on the TV box once a year winning a world championship, they think you're finished."</p>
        <p>Other former gold medalists who have thrown their hats back in the Olympic ring include Brian Boitano, Katerina Witt, Viktor Petrenko and the Russian pairs of Yekaterina Gordeyeva-Sergei Grinkov and Natalya Mishkutenok-Artur Dmitriev.</p>
        <p>"We didn't lobby like Brian did for this," Torvill said. "The first time we heard it was real was in June 1992 at the I.S.U.'s 100-year anniversary in Davos. The night before we left, they decided they were going to allow professionals back in."</p>
        <p>Dean had clearly considered the possibility, however. The next morning, he was already talking to Torvill about coming back.</p>
        <p>"I thought he was crazy," Torvill said. "But then he went on to all the positive reasons why we should do it, and he got me all excited about it. Then he changed his mind, of course."</p>
        <p>"I went cold on her," Dean said.</p>
        <p>"As soon as I agree with something, he disagrees," Torvill said. "That's normal." Completing Choreography For the Main Event</p>
        <p>This is how Torvill and Dean talk in front of strangers. They have been skating together for nearly 20 years (they met as teen-agers at a local rink in Nottingham) and like many involved in a happy relationship, they have a habit of trading gibes and finishing each others' sentences. More often than not, Dean does the interjecting, which seems appropriate because he is the driving creative force.</p>
        <p>"Chris comes up with all the ideas and steps, and I try to tell him what works and doesn't work," Torvill said.</p>
        <p>It was Dean who painstakingly choreographed their stunning interpretation of Ravel's "Bolero" in 1984, a freestyle program that earned them the maximum number of perfect 6.0's for artistic impression and a cascade of long-stemmed roses from the Sarajevo audience.</p>
        <p>It is Dean who has choreographed the routines throughout their professional career, which has encompassed numerous television specials and three lengthy tours of their own, including two ice-breaking and groundbreaking tours with Soviet skaters. He already has finished work on their freestyle program for Lillehammer, a program that will remain under wraps until the British national ice-dancing championships on Jan. 7-8 in Sheffield. Those championships were pushed back almost two months specifically to give Torvill and Dean enough time to prepare.</p>
        <p>"The federation didn't want to pressure them into a decision to come back, but I think we all had our fingers crossed," said Eileen Anderson, vice chairman of the British dance committee. "This could be an enormous boost for British skating. We basically have been losing ground since 1989. Until then, Jayne and Chris had kept it going because what they were doing was still in the public eye."</p>
        <p>Assuming Torvill and Dean win their seventh national title in Sheffield (not exactly a leap of faith) and claim Britain's single dance spot in Lillehammer, they will perform their freestyle program just once more before the Olympics: at the European championships in Copenhagen.</p>
        <p>"We want the free dance to have an impact on the judges -- as if they are seeing it for the first time," Dean said.</p>
        <p>Though practice sessions at their new training site in Milton Keynes are closed to ensure secrecy, one middle-aged woman showed up last week and got past the guard by explaining she was a close friend of the skaters. After she watched an entire run-through, it turned out that Torvill and Dean had never seen her before. The door policy has since become more selective.</p>
        <p>"We have a nightclub next to here with a suite that looks down on the ice," said the arena manager, Eddie Mahoney. "Our site manager has been offered a fair sum of money on different occasions to open up that suite." Something to Offer Beyond Nostalgia</p>
        <p>Those who have seen the program by less covert means say it is much faster and jazzier than "Bolero." Dean will only say that "we're trying to be very technical with our steps and intricate with our feet and, at the same time, lift the audience with something approaching romanticism."</p>
        <p>Please note Dean's use of the word "approaching." As one of those who jolted ice dancing out of the ballroom and toward high drama, he now reserves the right to play revisionist.</p>
        <p>"There have been too many deaths on the ice in recent years," he said. "The top skaters are wonderful and they can carry it off, but when you get past sixth or seventh place, they are trying to be so deep-thinking about everything that it just doesn't work and ends up looking comical. It had become an evening of poor tragedies. We're trying to move in a different direction.</p>
        <p>"This is not about nostalgia. We are coming back because we feel we still have something to give the skating world. We also feel we can still be very competitive."</p>
        <p>The consensus is that they will achieve that goal, although the reigning world champions, Aleksandr Zhulin and Maya Usova of Russia, are certainly a major obstacle to a second Olympic gold medal.</p>
        <p>"I think Chris and Jayne are better than they were in 1984," said their long-time coach, Betty Calloway. "All these years, they have been doing their own shows, going on and off several times a night so one four-minute program is not going to be a problem physically. As for their technical level, they have never taken the easy option and just done programs that were simple and pleasing to the public. They have always stretched themselves as professionals and put in a lot of difficulty." The Maturity Factor Is in Their Favor</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, it is surely comforting to know that unlike Boitano and Witt, who will have to contend with triple and perhaps quadruple jumps, Torvill and Dean will never have to lift their venerable bones off the ice.</p>
        <p>"Ice dancing is, I think, unique in that it lends itself to maturity as opposed to athleticism," Dean said. "You still have to be fit to get through what we're doing. But I think choreographically, experience is vital. And I think when people see us skating out there, it's not two people who have been skating together for a couple of years. There are 18, almost 19 years going into that four minutes, and there is a persona that comes from that."</p>
        <p>Another point in their favor is that unlike Borg, who had lost total touch with the competitive tennis world, Dean has remained very involved with amateur skating. From 1987 to 1992, he choreographed for the French-Canadian ice dancers Isabelle and Paul Duchesnay. Dean and Isabelle were married in May 1991, two months after she and Paul won the world championship. Before turning professional, they went on to take silver at last year's Olympics in Albertville, France, with a Dean program set to the music of "West Side Story."</p>
        <p>But while the scenario was strictly storybook, the Dean-Duchesnay marriage was not. Isabelle filed for divorce early this year, citing, among other reasons, incompatible career plans.</p>
        <p>"It just didn't work out," said Dean, who acknowledged that his decision to try the Olympic comeback was one of many factors that led to the relationship's deterioration. "At the end of the day, with all the pressures, it was just a bad choice of personalities being together. It's sad, but it was the right thing to happen."</p>
        <p>Dean then promptly and uncharacteristically went out and became a national tabloid staple by striking up a romance with the American skater Jill Trenary, the 1990 world champion. The story ("Star Chris Falls For Another Ice Maiden") had reporters sleeping in their cars outside the Milton Keynes arena and eventually forced Dean to call a news conference to avoid further harassment.</p>
        <p>"We had a few front covers, didn't we," said Dean.</p>
        <p>"We didn't," Torvill said with a grin. "Not we."</p>
        <p>The original idea for Torvill and Dean was to prepare the comeback by training in Norway until January, but that proved too expensive, and they stayed only three weeks. Enter Milton Keynes, which is an hour's drive north from London but light years removed from the architectural splendor of Trafalgar Square. This is a city of traffic circles -- "roundabouts" if you're speaking the Queen's English -- and modern structures. Few could be more modern than the MK Leisure Plaza, which has all the charm of a highway-hugging, middle-American shopping mall.</p>
        <p>Here are the well-polished lanes of the Quasar "Super Bowl," and the ill-named High Society discotheque, and, for those in search of world-famous ice dancers, the Blade Runner Arena, one of a handful in Britain with an Olympic-sized ice surface.</p>
        <p>"People don't always believe us when we tell them that Torvill and Dean are here," said Carlyne Wright, a 19-year-old behind the ticket counter.</p>
        <p>Even when people are aware of their comeback, Dean said, they respond with the reserve famous in the land of understatement and stiff upper lips. "The British people are great because there is basically no attention," Dean said. "It's like, 'Oh, you're doing the Olympics again, are you? Good luck.' "</p>
        <p>The audience will be more demanding come February. Those who got goose pimples from "Bolero" will be crowded around their television screens, waiting for more magic and more big, round numbers from the judges.</p>
        <p>"I suppose nobody can take away what we did in 1984, but we know that we are standing up to be accountable again," Dean said. "One of the biggest decisions we had to make was who is this going to affect the most, and it is really going to affect us the most, isn't it? People will watch, and if we're not as good, they will notice it, then forget about it and move on to more important things. The only ones who will have to live with it forever are the two of us, and I think we're big enough to handle that."  COUNTDOWN TO LILLEHAMMER: FIGURE SKATING:</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
