<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Reservoir at Drought Level</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="640842"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WANAQUE RESERVOIR (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEWARK (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HACKENSACK WATER CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANLEY, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DC173CF930A25753C1A965958260" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Reservoir at Drought Level</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HANLEY, ROBERT</byline>
      <dateline>WANAQUE, N.J., Oct. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Northern New Jersey's biggest reservoir, the Wanaque, has been drawn down to its lowest level since the drought of the mid-1960's, and the agency that operates it wants the state to order a stop to heavy demands on it.</p>
        <p>In the water-supply world's version of a run on the bank, the city of Newark and the Hackensack Water Company, which own two of the biggest shares of the reservoir, regularly drew out their legal share of the Wanaque's water during the hot, dry summer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Northern New Jersey's biggest reservoir, the Wanaque, has been drawn down to its lowest level since the drought of the mid-1960's, and the agency that operates it wants the state to order a stop to heavy demands on it.</p>
        <p>In the water-supply world's version of a run on the bank, the city of Newark and the Hackensack Water Company, which own two of the biggest shares of the reservoir, regularly drew out their legal share of the Wanaque's water during the hot, dry summer.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Newark and Hackensack Water, a privately owned company, have used their own individual reservoir systems more conservatively than they did during northern New Jersey's severe water shortages in 1980-81 and 1985.</p>
        <p>The withdrawals, combined with a rainfall in the Wanaque's watershed that was 7.7 inches below average from May through September, have reduced the reservoir to about 29 percent of its capacity of 29 billion gallons. (The capacity is that of about 580 million bathtubs.)</p>
        <p>By comparison, Newark's five reservoirs in Passaic and Sussex Counties were 72 percent full and Hackensack Water's four reservoirs in Bergen and Rockland Counties stood at 54.4 percent of capacity before today's heavy rains.</p>
        <p>The summer's heavy use of the Wanaque poses two challenges for a system that supplies water for about two million people in northern New Jersey. Will it thrive as a truly regional reservoir without its owners sliding into squabbles about dividing up its waters? And will the Wanaque, together with a new sister reservoir, the Monksville, and about $200 million in new water pumps and pipelines, all built since the 1985 drought, fulfill planners' dreams of ending northern New Jersey's chronic water shortages and preventing the mandatory water rationing of 1980-81?</p>
        <p>Partly because of the Wanaque's dwindling supplies, New Jersey's Department of Environmental Protection and Energy declared a drought warning in parts of six counties in northern New Jersey on Sept. 21. Residents were asked to voluntarily conserve water. The drought warning gives it the authority to order transfers of water among various reservoir systems and to force a more balanced use of reservoirs.</p>
        <p>The commission that operates the Wanaque, the North Jersey District Water Supply Commission, plans to ask state authorities at a hearing on Wednesday in Wayne to relax pressures on the Wanaque and to require more use of the other reservoirs in northern New Jersey. A decision is not expected for at least a week.</p>
        <p>Newark and the Hackensack Water Company deny the existence of a water war.</p>
        <p>"Newark is being made the culprit, and we're not," said Dan Berardinelli, manager of Newark's Water/ Sewer Utility. "All we have been doing is taking the allotment of water we're entitled to. We're not doing any different from everybody else. Everybody took their full share." 'Just Taking What We Own'</p>
        <p>Frank Sudol, acting director of Newark's Department of Engineering, said the city paid a flat rate of $7 million to $8 million annually for the Wanaque's water, and this is the first year it took its full share of water. "We're just taking what we own," he said.</p>
        <p>Hackensack Water says much the same thing.</p>
        <p>"It's been our responsibility to insure we have a safe and ample supply," said Richard Henning, a company spokesman. "That's the most compelling reason for us to continue taking our share."</p>
        <p>The current strains are the first since the state allowed the Hackensack Water Company to begin sharing the Wanaque after the 1985 water shortage. Hackensack Water invested about $70 million for improvements at the reservoir, including construction of the 7-billion gallon Monksville Reservoir and some big pumping stations and pipelines that transfer water from the Pompton and Passaic Rivers to the Wanaque. Hackensack owns those improvements 50-50 with the North Jersey District Water Supply Commission and is entitled to 40 million gallons of water a day.</p>
        <p>Newark owns 40.5 percent of the Wanaque Reservoir and by contract is entitled to 50 million gallons on most days and 75 million a day in certain emergencies. The cities of Paterson, Clifton and Passaic, as partners in the Passaic Valley Water Commission, own another 37.75 percent of the reservoir and can draw 35 million gallons a day to augment their principal supply source, the Passaic River. The other owners are Kearny, Montclair, Bloomfield and Glen Ridge.</p>
        <p>The principal owners sell Wanaque water to scores of other communities in the six counties now under the state's Sept. 21 drought warning: Bergen, Essex, Passaic, Hudson, Morris and Union. 200 Million Gallons Daily</p>
        <p>In recent days, the Wanaque's various owners and other users have been taking 200 million gallons a day from the reservoir. The system is designed to provide a daily average of 173 million gallons safely. To help meet the demand, officials late last week began transferring 110 million gallons a day from the new Monksville Reservoir to the Wanaque by pipeline.</p>
        <p>But Phil White, a spokesman for the North Jersey District Water Supply Commission, says the Wanaque cannot continue providing 200 million gallons a day, even with the back-up water from the Monksville Reservoir.</p>
        <p>The commission's concern, however, is not universally shared. Wendell Inhoffer, chief engineer for the Passaic Valley Water Commission, said the Wanaque and the Monksville together hold about 16 billion gallons now, which is more than the amount still in either Hackensack Water's or Newark's own reservoir system. Each of them holds a maximum of about 14 billion gallons.</p>
        <p>"I'm surprised by all this talk of intrigue," Mr. Inhoffer said. "Newark is doing what it has a right to do. Nobody is squirreling water. It only looks that way."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
