<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Franks Comes Out Swinging in New Jersey Governor Debate</title>
    <meta content="15DEBA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/15/nyregion/15DEBA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010616T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1301831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Halbfinger, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franks, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schundler, Bret D (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4D91731F936A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Franks Comes Out Swinging in New Jersey Governor Debate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HALBFINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Halbfinger, David M</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, June 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Republican gubernatorial aspirants Bob Franks and Bret D Schundler come out swinging as they participate in second televised debate; attacks and accusations of lying abound after Franks sets tone with dramatic opening statement; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From his first breath tonight, Bob Franks laced into Bret D. Schundler with an unrelenting intensity in the second televised debate between the Republican candidates for governor of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Over and over, Mr. Franks, the former United States representative, accused Mr. Schundler, the mayor of Jersey City, of lying about both men's records, forcing his rival to defend himself throughout much of their hourlong encounter. He even insinuated that Mr. Schundler had stolen money from needy children.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From his first breath tonight, Bob Franks laced into Bret D. Schundler with an unrelenting intensity in the second televised debate between the Republican candidates for governor of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Over and over, Mr. Franks, the former United States representative, accused Mr. Schundler, the mayor of Jersey City, of lying about both men's records, forcing his rival to defend himself throughout much of their hourlong encounter. He even insinuated that Mr. Schundler had stolen money from needy children.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schundler retaliated well at times, denigrating Mr. Franks as having no management experience, no concrete proposals and no credibility as an outsider or reformer after a career in politics, much of it spent in Trenton.</p>
        <p>But it was Mr. Franks who was most effective, and even theatrical. He used most of his opening statement to warn that ''a dark shadow'' had been cast over Mr. Schundler's campaign, referring to an administrative law judge's finding last week that Mr. Schundler controlled a children's scholarship fund that spent $885,000 on television advertisements last year featuring his face and voice.</p>
        <p>''This is not conjecture,'' Mr. Franks said. ''This is a fact, found by a judge.'' He warned that the Democratic candidate, James E. McGreevey, ''would use this issue to devastate our Republican Party this fall.''</p>
        <p>''Bret, taking money away from needy children and using it for your own political purposes is just wrong,'' Mr. Franks continued. ''I call on you tonight to give the money back. Return it so needy children can finally get all of the scholarship money they deserve.''</p>
        <p>In their three prior debates, two of them on radio, Mr. Schundler had often gotten the better of Mr. Franks. But he seemed thrown by Mr. Franks's aggressiveness tonight, and he never quite relaxed and gained his footing. Mr. Schundler was cut off in midsentence during his own opening, and frequently thereafter, and he rarely addressed the camera directly, instead looking at his off-camera questioners.</p>
        <p>He also waited through two rounds of questions, answers, rebuttals and follow-up questions before finally responding to Mr. Franks's opening barrage. ''The judge didn't find any such thing, and we'll see that as we go forward,'' Mr. Schundler said.</p>
        <p>''The reality is that we raised money specifically to educate the public about the fact that if you pass tax credits for scholarship-giving, we can raise more scholarships and help a lot more families be able to make  choices for what's best for their children,'' he said. ''There is nothing wrong with that. By having tax incentives for that kind of giving, even Bob might be willing to help.''</p>
        <p>The debate was sponsored by The New York Times and the New Jersey Network, and was shown live on the state network and on C-Span.</p>
        <p>Both men resorted to props, to good effect. Mr. Franks brandished a National Review article that said Mr. Schundler had missed opportunities to cut property taxes. He held up a page of figures showing the state aid that Jersey City had received over the years, saying, ''I challenge you to tell me they're not true.''</p>
        <p>And Mr. Franks waved a letter that Mr. Schundler had sent to the city's residents in 1995, warning that he might have to impose a new payroll tax. It took Mr. Schundler two chances at rebuttal to complete his explanation: the tax was never actually imposed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schundler, in turn, flashed a direct-mail ad by the Franks campaign that depicted Mr. Schundler as a pickpocket, and said it showed the lengths to which Mr. Franks would go to vilify him. ''He actually changed the quote,'' Mr. Schundler said. ''When the actual quotation in a state audit of Jersey City used the word 'management,' he put the word 'mismanagement' in his flier.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schundler was at his best when he attacked Mr. Franks for having no real platform, while trumpeting his own proposals on eliminating parkway tolls, reversing sprawl and preserving open space. ''Bob has been against all of those proposals,'' he said. ''I've proposed specific solutions. Bob Franks has talked about getting an auditor to look at the problem -- maybe he can figure it out. The bottom line? In Jersey City, I did figure it out.''</p>
        <p>But at other times Mr. Schundler, who often referred to his notes, was obscure, delving deep into the specifics of complex issues like auto insurance reform and structural budget deficits.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Schundler struggled to keep his rebuttals short, Mr. Franks got the last word in crucial moments. After Mr. Franks teed off on a question on term limits, a plank in his own platform, Mr. Schundler pointed to Mr. Franks as the type of ''career politician'' who would be removed by such limits, and said Mr. Franks had just ''got himself a job as a lobbyist to lobby his old friends in government.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Franks, who did work briefly for a lobbying firm before entering the race, tried to draw a distinction by saying he had not actually registered as a lobbyist. ''Bret, that's a lie,'' he said. ''I was never a lobbyist. I never chose to register, never would.''</p>
        <p>Referring to his campaign against Senator Jon S. Corzine last year, Mr. Franks said: ''You know, Bret, last year I ran against someone who would spend anything to get elected. This year I think I'm running against someone who will say anything to get elected.'' Mr. Schundler had no chance to respond.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 16, 2001, Saturday  An article yesterday about the televised debate between candidates for the Republican nomination for New Jersey governor misstated the rule on using props. In fact they are prohibited. Bob Franks broke the rule by brandishing papers to discredit Bret D. Schundler, and Mr. Schundler responded in kind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 16, 2001, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about the televised debate between candidates for the Republican nomination for New Jersey governor misstated the rule on using props. In fact they are prohibited. Bob Franks broke the rule by brandishing papers to discredit Bret D. Schundler, and Mr. Schundler responded in kind.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
