<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'Testosterone'</title>
    <meta content="RV232110" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/10/movies/10TEST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1610303"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="FILM IN REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moreton, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sutcliffe, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Testosterone (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Testosterone (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E6DD1530F933A2575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'Testosterone'</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">With Nothing Left but Heartbreak, It's Time to Play Sleuth</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephen Holden reviews movie Testosterone, directed by David Moreton and starring David Sutcliffe; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Directed by David Moreton  Not rated, 105 minutes</p>
        <p>The protagonist of ''Testosterone,'' a shaky comic noir larded with soft-core sex, is a successful graphic novelist with writer's block. Ambling around, delivering wisecracks in the genial raised-eyebrow style of James Garner telling a yarn, Dean Seagrave (David Sutcliffe), who narrates the film, hardly acts like a man with a broken heart. He insists, nevertheless, that the overnight disappearance of Pablo (Antonio Sabato Jr.), his live-in boyfriend of 10 months, has left him devastated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Testosterone," a shaky comic noir larded with soft-core sex, is a movie for connoisseurs of male eye candy. It wants to be much more.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Directed by David Moreton  Not rated, 105 minutes</p>
        <p>The protagonist of ''Testosterone,'' a shaky comic noir larded with soft-core sex, is a successful graphic novelist with writer's block. Ambling around, delivering wisecracks in the genial raised-eyebrow style of James Garner telling a yarn, Dean Seagrave (David Sutcliffe), who narrates the film, hardly acts like a man with a broken heart. He insists, nevertheless, that the overnight disappearance of Pablo (Antonio Sabato Jr.), his live-in boyfriend of 10 months, has left him devastated.</p>
        <p>Dean may not be dislikable, but he's annoyingly shallow. His description of his loss sounds more like a petulant whine of hurt pride over the loss of an A-list cutie (Mr. Sabato used to be a Calvin Klein underwear model) than a cry of despair. At an art gallery, he runs into Pablo's imperious mother (Sonia Braga), who refuses to acknowledge him until he makes a scene. She tells him that Pablo has gone home from Los Angeles to Argentina where he belongs. Determined to have one final confrontation, Dean hops on a plane to Buenos Aires and spends the rest of the movie playing sleuth.</p>
        <p>''Testosterone,'' based on a novel by James Robert Baker, represents a big, awkward step into the unknown for its director, David Moreton, whose debut film, ''Edge of Seventeen,'' about the sexual initiation of a gay Ohio teenager, stands as one of the more heartfelt coming-out stories brought to the screen. Here the director aspires to stir up an elusive blend of black comedy and film-noir atmosphere. But the movie's narrative momentum is too tentative and its plot too muddled for the pieces of its story to fit or for its styles to jell.</p>
        <p>The movie's vision of Buenos Aires evokes a city filled with mystery, dark shadows and furtive sex. Pablo's mother is a wealthy, conservative pillar of the community, and when Dean knocks on the door, she promptly summons the police. Later she has Dean followed by two menacing goons. In the meantime, he strikes up a wary friendship with Sofia (Celina Font), a pretty young woman who works in the coffee shop next door to Pablo's home, and her handsome brother, Marcos (Leonardo Brzezicki), who turns out to be Pablo's ex-boyfriend.</p>
        <p>Marcos has orders from somewhere to kill Dean, but because he's attracted to him, he resists, and the two have a one-night fling in the palatial country house of Pablo's family, to which the brother and sister have access. And yes, after the protracted tease, Dean finally confronts Pablo.</p>
        <p>''Testosterone,'' which opens today in New York, makes no psychological sense. Even within the convoluted realm of film noir, the development of the relationships defies any logic. Strictly for its soft-core value, the movie throws in another pretty man in the person of Guillermo (Dario Dukah), the lecherous bellboy in Dean's hotel, who seduces Marcos while Dean watches. ''Testosterone'' is a movie for connoisseurs of male eye candy. It wants to be much more.</p>
        <p>STEPHEN HOLDEN</p>
        <p>FILM IN REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
