<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Falling Into the Doughnut Hole</title>
    <meta content="06fri2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/06/opinion/06fri2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1795083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Aged</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED61530F935A35753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Falling Into the Doughnut Hole</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Falling Into the Doughnut Hole</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial warns that millions of elderly Americans enrolled in new Medicare drug program are approaching notorious 'doughnut hole,' gap in coverage that will force them to pay high out-of-pocket expenses until they qualify for catastrophic coverage; says hole makes little medical or insurance sense but is inevitable result of trying to please middle-class elderly voters while controlling costs somewhat</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Millions of elderly Americans enrolled in the new Medicare prescription drug program are approaching the notorious ''doughnut hole,'' a gap in coverage that will force them to pay for their medicines out of pocket until they qualify for catastrophic coverage. Many of the heaviest users of prescription medications have already fallen into the hole -- an unwelcome surprise for the many who do not pay much attention to the fine print of their policies.</p>
        <p>The hole makes little sense from a medical or insurance perspective. Rather, it is the inevitable result of designing a program with political rather than programmatic aims in mind. And the danger is that some who are ailing, suddenly faced with higher drug bills than they expected, will forgo needed medications and get sicker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The new Medicare prescription drug program contains a gap in coverage that will force millions of elderly Americans to pay for their medicines out of pocket until they qualify for catastrophic coverage.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Millions of elderly Americans enrolled in the new Medicare prescription drug program are approaching the notorious ''doughnut hole,'' a gap in coverage that will force them to pay for their medicines out of pocket until they qualify for catastrophic coverage. Many of the heaviest users of prescription medications have already fallen into the hole -- an unwelcome surprise for the many who do not pay much attention to the fine print of their policies.</p>
        <p>The hole makes little sense from a medical or insurance perspective. Rather, it is the inevitable result of designing a program with political rather than programmatic aims in mind. And the danger is that some who are ailing, suddenly faced with higher drug bills than they expected, will forgo needed medications and get sicker.</p>
        <p>The Medicare drug program was designed to serve three overlapping purposes. The two most important features are designed to help the elderly in greatest need. One subsidizes medication for low-income people. The other provides catastrophic coverage that pays the vast bulk of the bills for the heaviest users of prescription drugs, after they have paid $3,600 of their own money for their medications. Those elements alone justify the program and are the reason we endorsed it from the beginning.</p>
        <p>But at the same time, Congress insisted that the program provide benefits to all eligible Americans by covering their initial drug purchases (except for deductibles and co-payments) up to a specified limit, at which point they fall into the ''doughnut hole'' until reaching the threshold for catastrophic coverage. In a perfect world, all elderly Americans should share in the benefits of the prescription drug plan. But given the fiscal realities in Washington, trying to include everyone was irresponsible.</p>
        <p>The decision to offer shallow initial coverage to all beneficiaries was largely an effort to please the millions of middle-class elderly voters who had been led to expect they would benefit from the drug plan. But with nowhere near enough money in deficit-ridden Washington to pay for all this, the doughnut hole emerged as the only way to combine politics with some modicum of cost control.</p>
        <p>A more rational approach would certainly have been to begin with complete coverage for the needy and spread that benefit to higher income levels as the money becomes available. As it stands now, reputable surveys suggest that at least three million Americans will fall into the hole by year's end.</p>
        <p>Those who can afford to may want to pay an additional premium for a Medicare drug plan that provides coverage for the gap, although the plan frequently covers only generic drugs. The plan offerings for next year will include more options to buy coverage to fill the gap. The good news is that contrary to some analysts' expectations, the number of available plans are going to expand rather than shrink. The bad news for Medicare recipients who have become confused by the wide range of options is that beneficiaries in all but two states will be able to choose from among more than 50 free-standing drug plans for next year.</p>
        <p>Despite the irritation over the doughnut hole and some serious start-up problems, the new program seems in general to have found its stride. It is delivering benefits at lower cost than initially projected and ranks high in surveys of consumer satisfaction. The average number of drugs covered by insurers next year will increase by 13 percent, to 4,390. And the average premium for those who remain in their current plan will remain at roughly the same level, about $24 a month. But those already enrolled in a plan would be wise to check for any changes when full details of next year's offerings are posted. In some cases, premiums are rising and drugs previously on the formularies have been dropped.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
