<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Lose a Game, First Place and Kocur</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="430988"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PITTSBURGH PENGUINS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">YANNIS, ALEX</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Pittsburgh Penguins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DD1E3BF93BA25750C0A967958260" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Lose a Game, First Place and Kocur</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YANNIS, ALEX</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers not only fell out of first place in the Patrick Division for the first time in 155 days yesterday, losing by 4-2 to the Pittsburgh Penguins at Madison Square Garden; they also lost the pugnacious Joey Kocur, whom they traded for March 5 in hopes of solving their Stanley Cup puzzle, for the rest of the regular season.</p>
        <p>The setback was the sixth in a row for the Rangers (34-28-12), who have six games left, one fewer than the Penguins (38-30-5), who reached the top of the division on the strength of six victories and a tie in their last seven games.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rangers not only fell out of first place in the Patrick Division for the first time in 155 days yesterday, losing by 4-2 to the Pittsburgh Penguins at Madison Square Garden; they also lost the pugnacious Joey Kocur, whom they traded for March 5 in hopes of solving their Stanley Cup puzzle, for the rest of the regular season.</p>
        <p>The setback was the sixth in a row for the Rangers (34-28-12), who have six games left, one fewer than the Penguins (38-30-5), who reached the top of the division on the strength of six victories and a tie in their last seven games.</p>
        <p>"They've been on a roll and we've been on a downslide and that's exactly what happened in this game," Darren Turcotte of the Rangers said in comparing the recent games of the two teams.</p>
        <p>"We can be back in first by Thursday," said Roger Neilson, the Rangers' coach, referring to the game between the teams. "Nobody said we had to be in first every game. I think the team is determined to get it back. We play them two more times, so we can do it."</p>
        <p>The Rangers were playing well two weeks ago when they acquired Kocur from Detroit at the league's trading deadline. But his presence with the Rangers has thus far been a total disaster.</p>
        <p>Going into the game yesterday, Kocur had been scheduled to start a four-game suspension on Saturday, at Philadelphia. The league suspended Kocur on Friday for hitting Ed Belfour, Chicago's goaltender, with his stick March 10.</p>
        <p>But Kocur's ineffectiveness reached its zenith yesterday, when he was assessed a five-minute major and an automatic game misconduct for spearing Ulf Samuelsson. The infraction cost the Rangers dearly as the Penguins capitalized once during the penalty to Kocur. He drew an automatic three-game suspension starting with the next game, Thursday in Pittsburgh, because the spearing infraction was his fourth stick-related major penalty of the season.</p>
        <p>One reason the Rangers had decided to have Kocur start the original suspension on Saturday was so that they could have him for three games against the Penguins, including yesterday's and the one Thursday.</p>
        <p>Kocur was supposed to come back for the last game of the regular season, which is against the Penguins at the Garden on March 31. But after yesterday, Kocur, who must miss a total of seven games, is out for the rest of the regular season and the first game of next season.</p>
        <p>Regular-season suspensions are not applicable to the playoffs, unless the league takes special action against Kocur because of his record of suspensions. He has been suspended five times this season.</p>
        <p>The Rangers were trailing by a goal yesterday when Kocur got his big penalty; he had a fighting major and also a minor earlier. It was during his last penalty that Mario Lemieux's second goal of the game sealed the victory for Pittsburgh. Lemieux's 14th of the season, which closed the scoring with three seconds left in the second period, was the third power-play goal in the game for the Penguins.</p>
        <p>Kevin Stevens also had two goals, his 34th and 35th of the season, and Mark Recchi had three assists for the Penguins, who took 30 shots at Mike Richter, and were never in serious trouble after Kocur's penalty.</p>
        <p>"Our job now is to stay there," Bob Johnson, the Penguins' coach, said about first place. "We fought our way here by beating some good clubs along the way. This was a big one for us, but we have another big one Tuesday."</p>
        <p>Johnson was referring to the game against the Devils in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Mark Janssens (9th) and Mike Gartner (42d) scored the goals for the Rangers against Tom Barrasso, who faced 26 shots and is undefeated in his last seven starts.</p>
        <p>Brian Leetch's assist on Gartner's power-play goal was his 66th of the season and broke the record set by Mike Rogers in the 1981-82 season. The point was also Leetch's 82d of the season and tied the record for points by a defenseman that was set by Brad Park in the 1973-74 season. Bruins 3, Flyers 1</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA (AP) -- Reggie Lemelin, the Boston goalie, turned away 23 of 24 shots.</p>
        <p>The 36-year-old goalkeeper is unbeaten in his last three games and has just two losses in his last nine starts.</p>
        <p>Philadelphia, which has managed just one victory in its last nine games and lost five of its last six, remained 1 point ahead of Washington and New Jersey in third place in the Patrick Division.</p>
        <p>Ken Hodge, a rookie, gave the Bruins a 3-1 lead with a short-handed goal at 7:08 of the final period. Nevin Markwart drove to the net, taking two Flyers with him, and delivered a perfect drop pass to Hodge. All three players skated into the Philadelphia goalie Pete Peeters, who was helpless as Hodge snapped the puck in for his 26th goal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
