<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey Ends Practice Of Dumping Sludge in Sea</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="431079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WATER POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEWERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WASTE MATERIALS AND DISPOSAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ATLANTIC OCEAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Waste Materials and Disposal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DE1130F93BA25750C0A967958260" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey Ends Practice Of Dumping Sludge in Sea</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the first time in more than 65 years, no New Jersey community is dumping treated sewage into the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
        <p>Yesterday was the state's deadline for discontinuing dumping, and conservationists and government regulators consider the end of the practice a long-overdue victory over marine pollution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the first time in more than 65 years, no New Jersey community is dumping treated sewage into the Atlantic Ocean.</p>
        <p>Yesterday was the state's deadline for discontinuing dumping, and conservationists and government regulators consider the end of the practice a long-overdue victory over marine pollution.</p>
        <p>"This really is a milestone in the history of the environment," said William Muszynski, deputy regional administrator of the Federal Environmental Protection Agency. "There are not too many times when you stop using oceans as a cesspool."  New Processing Equipment</p>
        <p>But the achievement comes at great cost for the six northern New Jersey sewage authorities that have had to find a place on land for four million tons of treated sewage each year -- an amount that would more than fill one World Trade Center tower. Two authorities alone have spent more than $100 million in the last two years on new processing equipment.</p>
        <p>In the next 15 months, sewage authorities in New York City and Nassau and Westchester Counties will also have to stop ocean dumping of treated sewage, known as sludge, and find land-disposal alternatives. The city's program is expected to cost more than $1 billion over the next eight years.</p>
        <p>At a cost several times that of dumping sludge from barges 106 miles out to sea, five of the six New Jersey sewage authorities are shipping sludge by truck or rail to landfills or mines in Texas, Pennsylvania and Ohio, where disposal space is more plentiful. Later this decade, the authorities may try to sell processed sludge as fertilizer or, if that proves impossible, incinerate it.</p>
        <p>A visit to the Passaic Valley Sewerage Commissioners' treatment plant in Newark, one of the nation's largest, shows the lengths to which the authorities must go to dispose of sludge.</p>
        <p>Every day for the next five years, 40 to 50 trailers will be filled with sludge at the treatment plant. Trucks carry the trailers to a nearby rail siding, where they are hoisted by crane onto rail cars and pulled to Conrail's Newark rail yard. Over the next eight days, Conrail and Southern Pacific trains haul the sludge trailers to a landfill 1,450 miles away in Tyler, Tex. The price tag: an extra $26 million a year in operating costs.</p>
        <p>The sewage authorities have no choice. Congress voted in late 1988 to force them to stop most ocean dumping by the end of 1991, following beach washups of debris that provoked a public outcry that summer. New Jersey's legislature required the six authorities to end dumping by yesterday, and they have met that deadline. The nine authorities in the metropolitan area have been the only ones in the United States that still dump sludge in the ocean.</p>
        <p>Some New Jerseyans will pay for the transition in higher sewer charges.</p>
        <p>Many households connected to the Middlesex County sewage treatment plant in Sayreville may find sewer charges of $70 to $120, 20 percent higher than last year. Fees assessed by the Bergen County Utilities Authority to many of the 43 municipalities connected to its plant in Little Ferry will rise by 40 percent. Passaic Valley's sludge disposal costs will increase more than four times.</p>
        <p>But people who advocated ending ocean dumping say the metropolitan-area jurisdictions were paying artificially low rates because ocean disposal was comparatively cheap.  Dumpers Resisted the Change</p>
        <p>"We're not asking them to do something the rest of the state, and for that matter, the rest of the country, is not already doing," said Cindy Zipf, executive director of Clean Ocean Action, a coalition of New Jersey conservation and fishing groups. For example, households in Camden County, which moved from ocean dumping to land disposal in the early 1980's, are paying $250 to $300 a year in sewer charges, Ms. Zipf said.</p>
        <p>Sludge, the end product of the sewage-treatment process, is composed of sewage solids, water and contaminants like copper and cadmium. Until 1987, sludge was dumped only 12 miles offshore. After studies showed that nearly nothing was left alive there, Federal regulators shifted the dump area to more than 100 miles off New Jersey and New York.</p>
        <p>The metropolitan-area dumpers had long resisted changing to land disposal, mostly because of the higher costs. Congress insisted ocean dumping of sludge be phased out following the summer of 1988, even though sludge was not part of the mix of garbage that wreaked havoc at beach communities. It is too early to determine if dumping at the 106-mile site has harmed the marine environment there.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muszynski, of the Environmental Protection Agency, said that the New York State jurisdictions are on schedule to end their dumping. Nassau County must comply by July 1 and Westchester County by Jan. 1, 1992. New York City has agreed to halt 20 percent of ocean dumping by Jan. 1, 1992, and the remainder by July 1, 1992.</p>
        <p>The major question is what can be done in the longer term. New Jersey has already produced a backlash from other states for trucking its regular garbage to out-of-state landfills, so the sewage authorities are unlikely to find long-term burial sites for their sludge. There is also big resistance to incineration because of concern about air pollution, building costs and ash disposal.</p>
        <p>Instead, a consensus has been forming in New Jersey among government regulators, the sewage authorities and environmental groups that sludge be reclaimed as a resource like fertilizer, rather than buried or burned.</p>
        <p>Sludge contains nutrients that can make it useful as a fertilizer. But much of it from the metropolitan area contains heavy metals like cadmium and copper. The metals get into the sludge through industrial waste and leaching from household pipes. Sewage treatment plants cannot filter the metals from the sewage.</p>
        <p>Too much metal rules out the agricultural use of sludge. So some authorities have to figure out how to cut heavy metal discharges.</p>
        <p>"How far could we go without closing down industry?" asked Carmine T. Perrapato, executive director of the Passaic Valley Sewerage Commissioners. "Some industries have come to us and said if you go any further, we can't operate."</p>
        <p>If sludge quality cannot be improved, incineration may have to occur. The commissoners would prefer another disposal approach, Mr. Perrapato said.</p>
        <p>One New Jersey sewage authority administrator said his operation had anticipated the need to clean up sludge six years ago, and has successfully reduced heavy-metal contamination by working with companies to reduce metals discharges.</p>
        <p>As a result, Middlesex County sludge can be used as cover for a landfill the authority operates and also as fertilizer, said Frederick H. Kurtz, executive director of the county utilities authority.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
