<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Agassi Is Firing His Forehand Again</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="615286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TENNIS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WIMBLEDON TENNIS TOURNAMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINN, ROBIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AGASSI, ANDRE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wimbledon Tennis Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DC123AF937A25755C0A965958260" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Agassi Is Firing His Forehand Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FINN, ROBIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He may be wearing even more white than is necessary, in the form of a bandage to soothe his ailing right wrist, but Andre Agassi, the undisputed peacock of the male tennis circuit and the unlikely defending champion of Wimbledon, has vowed to return to the scene of his greatest career triumph and attempt to defend his first and only Grand Slam crown.</p>
        <p>A week from today, Agassi, who transcended his baseline heritage last year to defeat Goran Ivanisevic in a stirring five-set Wimbledon final, expects to commence his title defense despite being unable, as recently as last Monday, to hit his favorite stroke, the forehand blast, because of pain in his right wrist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He may be wearing even more white than is necessary, in the form of a bandage to soothe his ailing right wrist, but Andre Agassi, the undisputed peacock of the male tennis circuit and the unlikely defending champion of Wimbledon, has vowed to return to the scene of his greatest career triumph and attempt to defend his first and only Grand Slam crown.</p>
        <p>A week from today, Agassi, who transcended his baseline heritage last year to defeat Goran Ivanisevic in a stirring five-set Wimbledon final, expects to commence his title defense despite being unable, as recently as last Monday, to hit his favorite stroke, the forehand blast, because of pain in his right wrist.</p>
        <p>But after a blazing nocturnal workout in Las Vegas, Nev., Saturday evening, Agassi pronounced himself fit to return to competition, which he'll do tomorrow at a Wimbledon tune-up in Halle, Germany. The strenuous practice session, his first since April, served as a test vehicle to determine the effectiveness of a cortisone injection Agassi received directly into his wrist at the Seattle offices of Dr. Edward Almquist last Monday. 'The Wrist Feels Good'</p>
        <p>"The pain is the indicator, and if the cortisone worked, I shouldn't have any pain, and right now the wrist feels good for the first time I can remember," Agassi said by telephone from his home in Las Vegas Saturday night.</p>
        <p>"Now the decision comes down to me, to try and get through one or two rounds in Germany and see if the wrist can handle the big punishment -- it's an all-or-nothing thing," Agassi said. He described his treatment as a last-gasp attempt to solve his problem before resorting to surgery to remove the scar tissue that has formed around "slight tears" in the wrist ligaments.</p>
        <p>"And the next step is amputation," joked the 23-year-old Agassi, who described himself as being terrified before Saturday's workout and infinitely relieved afterward.</p>
        <p>Agassi's right-wrist soreness, which began at the end of January and dramatically worsened last month, forced him to withdraw from the French Open. Until one test last week pinpointed the source of his discomfort, the pain jeopardized his chances of returning to Wimbledon.</p>
        <p>"But that to me would have been devastating, not to go and defend my title there," said Agassi, who has dropped to No. 13 in the world ranking. "It could be a once-in-a-lifetime thing." Dispelling a Rumor</p>
        <p>Agassi emphatically denied a rumor that he was using his wrist injury as an excuse to avoid the pressures inherent in title defense.</p>
        <p>"Whoever thinks that about me definitely doesn't know what they're talking about," he said. "It would be arrogant of me to go back to Wimbledon and expect to repeat, but that doesn't mean I don't want to try more than anything in the world.</p>
        <p>"But I have to be honest: defending at Wimbledon is extremely important to me, but I'm not sure it would be worth doing a year of damage to my wrist. I'll settle for discomfort, but if the pain comes back to the point where it affects my capability of playing, I'm not sure where I'll stand."</p>
        <p>Agassi said it was possible that he might receive another cortisone injection before Wimbledon, should the trouble flare up once he begins competing at Halle, where he is seeded fourth. But he said his primary physician, Dr. Richard Westbrook of El Paso, did not favor that route of treatment.</p>
        <p>According to Westbrook, Agassi's condition is dorsal capsulitis of the right wrist, which the physician said indicated an "overuse syndrome that causes an irritation of the joint, and pain, that we've so far tried to treat with conservative management. The cortisone will either settle it down or it won't."  All This, and Free Throws, Too</p>
        <p>Before the cortisone injection, Agassi said he was unable to hit a forehand, assume a push-up position or shoot a basketball from the free-throw line. As of Saturday, he was able to resume all of those athletic endeavors, "including putting a little spin on my shots from the free-throw line."</p>
        <p>Agassi hasn't played an ATP Tour event since April 9, when he was defeated in the quarterfinals at Barcelona, Spain, by Sergi Bruguera, who dethroned Jim Courier in the final of the French Open on June 6.</p>
        <p>The player said his lack of practice time wasn't daunting him. "I didn't play for two weeks before Wimbledon last year and look what happened," he said.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
