<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vice Problem? Round Up The Usual Detectives!</title>
    <meta content="30JAME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="TELEVISION REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="886509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bochco, Steven</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Public Morals (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DD1239F933A05753C1A960958260" item-length="498" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vice Problem? Round Up The Usual Detectives!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Caryn James reviews Steven Bochco's new sitcom Public Morals, on CBS television (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sometimes a little scandal doesn't hurt a show. Months ago, when CBS stations saw the pilot of ''Public Morals,'' Steven Bochco's new sitcom set in the vice squad of the New York City Police Department, there was a mini-outcry about the show's vulgar language and salacious content. The truly offensive aspect of the show, though, was that it was excruciatingly unfunny.</p>
        <p>Tonight's toned-down premiere offers a different episode, one that is pointedly and atypically stripped of sexual content, as the squad raids a bar serving minors. That strategy manages to make a bad series even worse. The premiere is still not funny, and it doesn't even have the conviction of its crass but titillating taste. Instead of sexual innuendo, there is some trashy name-calling: the police call the minors ''little idiot tramps,'' and in return they are called ''meter maids'' and ''fat Nazi pig bouncers.'' This is so not-clever, you expect the next line to be, ''Your mother wears Army boots.''</p>
        <p>An even bigger problem is that the show features a squad room full of stereotypes so predictable and dull that ''Public Morals'' seems like ''Barney Miller'' about to overdose on Valium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Sometimes a little scandal doesn't hurt a show. Months ago, when CBS stations saw the pilot of ''Public Morals,'' Steven Bochco's new sitcom set in the vice squad of the New York City Police Department, there was a mini-outcry about the show's vulgar language and salacious content. The truly offensive aspect of the show, though, was that it was excruciatingly unfunny.</p>
        <p>Tonight's toned-down premiere offers a different episode, one that is pointedly and atypically stripped of sexual content, as the squad raids a bar serving minors. That strategy manages to make a bad series even worse. The premiere is still not funny, and it doesn't even have the conviction of its crass but titillating taste. Instead of sexual innuendo, there is some trashy name-calling: the police call the minors ''little idiot tramps,'' and in return they are called ''meter maids'' and ''fat Nazi pig bouncers.'' This is so not-clever, you expect the next line to be, ''Your mother wears Army boots.''</p>
        <p>An even bigger problem is that the show features a squad room full of stereotypes so predictable and dull that ''Public Morals'' seems like ''Barney Miller'' about to overdose on Valium.</p>
        <p>There is Schuler, the boor; Crawford, the womanizer; Ruggs, the uptight African-American, and Biondi, the not-too-bright Tony Danza clone. The two women on the force include Vandergroodt, the tough and smart brunette, and O'Boyle, the tough and sexy blonde.</p>
        <p>Only Bill Brochtrup rises above this amateurish mess, playing John Irvin, the same efficient and gushingly loyal administrative assistant he played on ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.'' (He was the blond guy upstairs who gave haircuts.) Of course, he is inhabiting a stereotype, too: the gay man with exquisite taste. But Mr. Brochtrup creates a likable individual beneath the purposefully cliched manner; he defines the difference between edgy, politically incorrect humor and the doltish attempts at it that surround him.</p>
        <p>Next week's episode returns the show to its hard-core subject, when O'Boyle's boyfriend is arrested for picking up a prostitute who happens to be Vandergroodt undercover. Crawford ends up drooling over the dejected O'Boyle. The show proves that with or without its smarmy coating, ''Public Morals'' has no idea where to find a funny line.</p>
        <p>PUBLIC MORALS</p>
        <p>CBS, tonight at 9:30  (Channel 2 in New York)</p>
        <p>Created by Steven Bochco and Jay Tarses. Dayna Flanagan and Stephen C. Grossman, producers; Lisa Albert, co-producer; Don Scardino, director; Ken Lamkin, director of photography; Mindy Roffman, art director. Produced by Steven Bochco Productions. Jay Tarses, executive producer.</p>
        <p>WITH: Donal Logue (Ken Schuler), Julianne Christie (Corinne O'Boyle), Justin Louis (Mickey Crawford), Jana Marie Hupp (Val Vandergroodt), Joseph Latimore (Darnell ''Shag'' Ruggs), Lawrence Romano (Richie Biondi), Bill Brochtrup (John Irvin) and Peter Gerety (Neil Fogarty).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
