<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Law Graduate Is Charged With Drug Smuggling</title>
    <meta content="18GRAD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jamaica</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Zolta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fried, Joseph P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Jamaica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E7DE1330F93BA25754C0A96E958260" item-length="395" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Law Graduate Is Charged With Drug Smuggling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH P. FRIED</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fried, Joseph P</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Zolton Williams, recent graduate of Columbia University Law School, is charged with smuggling cocaine with an associate who carried two pounds of the drug in 100 swallowed condoms on flight to US from Jamaica; some of the cocaine leaked and made the associate ill; agents say Williams did legal research in effort to avoid detection at Customs (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A recent graduate of Columbia University Law School was charged yesterday with smuggling cocaine into the United States last year in a scheme that failed despite what drug agents said was his legal research in an effort to avoid detection.</p>
        <p>The enterprise failed, the agents said, when an associate who carried the cocaine into the country from Jamaica in about 100 swallowed condoms became ill after some of the contents leaked into the associate's stomach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A recent graduate of Columbia University Law School was charged yesterday with smuggling cocaine into the United States last year in a scheme that failed despite what drug agents said was his legal research in an effort to avoid detection.</p>
        <p>The enterprise failed, the agents said, when an associate who carried the cocaine into the country from Jamaica in about 100 swallowed condoms became ill after some of the contents leaked into the associate's stomach.</p>
        <p>The man arrested yesterday, Zolton Williams, 28, of Brooklyn, who received his law degree from Columbia two months ago, was accused in Federal District Court in Brooklyn of importing more than two pounds of cocaine into the United States in June 1997, between law school terms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams and the second person, who was not identified, flew from Jamaica to New York, where the associate was to get $10,000 once the cocaine was sold, according to an agent of the Federal Drug Enforcement Administration. But the confederate became ill and started hallucinating, apparently from the leaking cocaine, the agent, J. Michael Smith, said in a court affidavit.</p>
        <p>He said the associate was taken to a hospital and, after the condoms were surgically removed, was arrested, later pleading guilty to Federal narcotics charges in a deal that involved cooperating with the Government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said that before going to Jamaica, the associate had asked Mr. Williams how likely it was that they would be caught upon returning to Kennedy International Airport, and that Mr. Williams, then in the midst of his law school studies, ''suggested that they go to a law library and do research about 'profiles' used by Customs to stop and search airline passengers.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams, who was an intern for several months in the Brooklyn District Attorney's office, was not required to enter a plea when he was arraigned yesterday on drug importing and conspiracy charges by Magistrate Judge Steven M. Gold, who  ordered him jailed pending further court action. His lawyer, Douglas Morris of the Legal Aid Society, later declined to comment on the charges. If convicted, Mr. Williams would face up to eight years in prison, said Timothy A. Macht, an assistant United States attorney in Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
