<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; A Job, A Dream, A Title Fight</title>
    <meta content="18BERK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032546"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delvalle, Lou</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Roy Jr</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E7D61230F93BA25754C0A96E958260" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; A Job, A Dream, A Title Fight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times column on Lou DelValle, who will fight Roy Jones Jr for chance to become undisputed light-heavyweight champion of the world; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DO you think Louie has a chance?'' asked Jose, a porter in a large apartment building on Manhattan's East Side.</p>
        <p>''The odds are 15-1,'' said Sid, a doorman in the same apartment building. ''That's really an underdog.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DO you think Louie has a chance?'' asked Jose, a porter in a large apartment building on Manhattan's East Side.</p>
        <p>''The odds are 15-1,'' said Sid, a doorman in the same apartment building. ''That's really an underdog.''</p>
        <p>''Even if Louie gets his butt kicked,'' said Eddie, a maintenance man there, ''he'll still make $850,000. He was getting $24,000 a year here.''</p>
        <p>For three years, starting in 1989, Lou DelValle was employed as a porter in the building, a building in which I reside. And then he left to seek his fortune, and try to avoid a punch in the nose, in the bargain. He became a professional prize fighter. Tonight he fights Roy Jones Jr. for the chance to become the undisputed light-heavyweight champion of the world.</p>
        <p>DelValle has compiled a formidable professional record of 27 victories, 1 loss and 19 knockouts. His lone defeat was in a disputed 15-round decision for the World Boxing Association light-heavyweight title in 1996 against the champion Virgil Hill, in Hill's hometown of Grand Forks, N.D. DelValle had been a 20-1 underdog.</p>
        <p>''I got robbed,'' DelValle said. ''I dropped him in the second round and should have finished him. But I still felt I had won the decision. Just about everyone else there except the judges saw it the same way.''</p>
        <p>Although coming into the the Theater at Madison Square Garden as a decided underdog against Jones, the World Boxing Council champion with a record of 36-1 with 31 knockouts, DelValle does not appear to be intimidated.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to beat him,'' he said. ''I have the style to beat him. He's strong and can punch, but the best part of my game is movement. And I can crack, too. If he gets stupid, he's going to get it. But it's like pitching. Against Roy Jones, you can't throw a bad pitch, or he'll hit it out of the park, like McGwire, or Griffey. Jones is a great fighter. I have to pitch a perfect game to win, and I have a perfect game in me.''</p>
        <p>I knew Louie, as everyone called him, as a personable, confident, red-headed young man with, at 6 feet and 175 pounds, an athletic build. And Louie had dreams -- he was 20 when he first came to work in the building -- but most young men have dreams. Many, however, do not have the skill or forbearance to realize those dreams.</p>
        <p>Was Louie different? I'd see him sweeping the lobby floor, or on the way to the garbage disposal. We talked frequently. ''I have bigger goals in my life than being here,'' he had told me. He wanted to be a professional boxer, he said. He wanted to become a world champion.</p>
        <p>He wore the green shirt and pants that were standard for the building's laborers, but he also wore around his neck a pair of miniature gold gloves with a single diamond, emblematic of the Golden Gloves light-heavyweight championship he won in 1989 at the Garden.</p>
        <p>In 1990, he lost in the Gloves finals. And it was in this loss that it became apparent that Louie might have a future, because of his work ethic. In the apartment building, he worked the 4-to-12 evening shift. This caused a trial in his training. He grew up in the Queensbridge projects in Long Island City, and after work would run home over the 59th Street Bridge.</p>
        <p>''It wasn't so great, with all the fumes,'' he recalled recently, ''but I had no choice. I needed the money at work and I needed to fit in the training when I could. But I lost in the finals because I got tired.''</p>
        <p>Louie, a southpaw, decided to put his fists where his dreams were, and turned pro. In his debut on Jan. 12, 1992, he beat Worthy Hendricks in a four-round decision. And he was off. Last September he knocked out Eddy Smulders in the eighth round to win the W.B.A. light-heavyweight title.</p>
        <p>''I love boxing,'' Louie said. ''I love the challenge. And I wanted to make something of myself. When I was younger, I got into a lot of trouble. Fights, drugs -- doing drugs, selling drugs -- jail time. It was a tough neighborhood, and that was the life. And sometimes I'd fall back. Like after the Hill fight. I was discouraged, frustrated. I hung out, I ballooned to 228, then I got myself back together again. Right now, I'm 175 and in the best shape of my life.''</p>
        <p>Louie recalls that his uncle, Rocky Candelaria, a maintenance man in the building, got him the job there as a young man. ''That changed my life,'' Louie said. ''Got me off the streets.''</p>
        <p>But it was Louie, now 30 years old, who through dedication and intelligence made himself into a respected professional. And regardless of the outcome of the Jones fight, it is unlikely that any of that will change.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
