<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Leading Democrat's Theme: It's a Long, Long Time From Now Till November</title>
    <meta content="Y09FROS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1045003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE CAMPAIGNS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Frost, Martin (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E2D8133EF93AA3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Leading Democrat's Theme: It's a Long, Long Time From Now Till November</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, Sept. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with US Repr Martin Frost, 10-term Democratic Congressman from Texas who faces two months of campaigning over uncertain ground for party whose leader is steeped in scandal; says situation is impossible to gauge and that Democrats still have several shots of wresting seats from Republicans; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Martin Frost, chairman of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, finds himself facing two months of campaigning over uncertain ground for a party whose leader is up to his eyeballs in scandal.</p>
        <p>''All I can say is that the situation is impossible to gauge,'' said Mr. Frost, a 10-term Congressman. ''We'll know a lot more in the next couple of weeks. But I think it's going to be a very late-developing election.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Martin Frost, chairman of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee, finds himself facing two months of campaigning over uncertain ground for a party whose leader is up to his eyeballs in scandal.</p>
        <p>''All I can say is that the situation is impossible to gauge,'' said Mr. Frost, a 10-term Congressman. ''We'll know a lot more in the next couple of weeks. But I think it's going to be a very late-developing election.''</p>
        <p>His main sources of solace, he says, are that he thinks the Democrats still have several shots at wresting seats from Republicans, that campaign fund-raising does not seem to have been affected by the scandal and that the ground is just as uncertain for his opponents, who must guard against appearing to place partisanship above statesmanship.</p>
        <p>The calls Mr. Frost has been getting in recent days from nervous and excited candidates have tended to fall into two categories, he said.</p>
        <p>''Incumbents are concerned about what's going to happen in the next month, with the release of Ken Starr's report and what Congress might do about it,'' he said. ''The new candidates, who are just trying to get into office, want to talk about the issues we've developed and how they're resonating in the campaign.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Frost, a lawyer and former journalist who represents the heavily black and Hispanic neighborhoods of south Dallas and south Fort Worth along with a bunch of white suburbs in between, said he had better answers for the newcomers than  for the incumbents.</p>
        <p>''The reality is that you can't tell at this point what's going to happen in the next month,'' he said. ''And I don't know -- nobody knows -- how the people are going to respond to whatever comes out.''</p>
        <p>Not long ago, many Democrats were predicting that the strong national economy combined with widespread disapproval of Mr. Starr's approach to his investigation of President Clinton would redound in the party's favor, helping win back a few more of the seats that were lost in the conservative Republican landslide of 1994. Democrats even harbored hopes of retaking control of the House, where a net gain of only 11 seats would restore their majority.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frost says that his position throughout the year has been that the Democrats stand a 50-50 chance of winning back House control, and that he sees nothing as yet to cause that outlook to change. But voicing optimism is part of Mr. Frost's job as head of the party's Congressional campaign effort, and even he is not immune to the unease that is growing among Democrats with Mr. Starr's report to Congress expected as early as this week.</p>
        <p>''The question is whether Democrats will turn out in November,'' Mr. Frost said. ''Most people's view about the Clinton investigation seems to be, Can't we get this behind us, can't we get this over with? People are just turned off politics. Thus, it becomes an issue of which side can get its base into the voting booth.''</p>
        <p>He rattled off the uncertainties: How much of the Starr report will be made fully public? Will Congressional impeachment hearings be held, and, if so, will they begin before or after November? What further sordid details might come out? Will the President say more than he already has? And, most perplexing of all in a climate where the President's job approval ratings have remained high despite all the disclosures, will any of it make the slightest difference to voters?</p>
        <p>''There's no way to tell how it's going to go,'' Mr. Frost said.</p>
        <p>For Labor Day, Mr. Frost's staff had him on a busy campaign kickoff in and around his home district: a breakfast with labor leaders at a downtown Dallas hotel, a barbecue lunch with an auditorium full of  workers at a union hall in a suburb north of Fort Worth, then a sun-baked picnic in a wooded area called Flagpole Hill in the urban sprawl of northeast Dallas.</p>
        <p>As in most political circles, the  fallout from the President's troubles was a matter of much debate. Former Speaker Jim Wright, who for 35 years represented the Fort Worth district where the union hall is situated, was knocking back a plate of  barbecue on the other side of the hall while Mr. Frost worked the room.</p>
        <p>''I'll tell you, the situation is so volatile it's hard to make an intelligent judgment,'' said Mr. Wright, who resigned from the Speakership and from Congress while under fire  over ethics in 1989. ''I don't think I've ever seen a situation quite like this one.''</p>
        <p>In one measure of the President's political health, Mr. Frost asserted that requests from candidates for Mr. Clinton to visit their districts had held fairly steady: some candidates want him to come, some do not. It depends on the district and the dynamics of the race.</p>
        <p>The Democrats' Congressional campaign committee is in the midst of a series of joint fund-raising events with the party's Senate campaign committee and the Democratic National Committee; the next one is planned for next Monday in New York. That event had a goal of $3 million, but some $3.2 million has already been raised for it, Mr. Frost said, leading some to predict that as much as $3.5 million will eventually come in.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Frost said his reports from the field showed that those Republican seats the Democrats believe they have the strongest chance of winning continued to be within reach.</p>
        <p>''We've been fortunate in several instances that Republicans who got elected in 1994 promising to abide by six-year term limits are now just two years away from when they'd either have to drop out or break their promise,'' he said. ''So some of them are leaving early to run for another office, opening up some promising opportunities for us.''</p>
        <p>TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE CAMPAIGNS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
