<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheers and Jeers Greet Clinton in Suburbs</title>
    <meta content="Y09CLIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1045002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maryland</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clines, Francis X</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glendening, Parris N (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E2D8133EF93AA3575AC0A96E958260" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheers and Jeers Greet Clinton in Suburbs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clines, Francis X</byline>
      <dateline>SILVER SPRING, Md., Sept. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton receives mixed reception in Silver Spring, Md, during visit to promote education; some Democrats rally to his side, but Gov Parris Glendening, who is seeking re-election, shuns affair in protest against Clinton's behavior in Lewinsky affair; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Standing on her sun-dappled lawn, Celia Winter politely dismissed President Clinton as ''a farce'' as his motorcade arrived from the White House on a mission of preaching education in this bastion of suburban values.</p>
        <p>''I'm just disgusted with him,'' Mrs. Winter said. ''This is a man who campaigned with his family, with Hillary, on the theme of family values. And now it's all shot to hell.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Standing on her sun-dappled lawn, Celia Winter politely dismissed President Clinton as ''a farce'' as his motorcade arrived from the White House on a mission of preaching education in this bastion of suburban values.</p>
        <p>''I'm just disgusted with him,'' Mrs. Winter said. ''This is a man who campaigned with his family, with Hillary, on the theme of family values. And now it's all shot to hell.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Winter spoke more in sadness than anger, but her neighbor down the block, Maureen Callahan, took the more demonstrative step of tacking a hand-lettered, black-and-white announcement on her neat picket fence for the advent of Mr. Clinton: ''Embarrassed. Disheartened. Disgusted by Our President.''</p>
        <p>''He shouldn't be here with young children,'' Mrs. Callahan, who has a young child, said as she stared disapprovingly toward Pine Crest Elementary School, where students were assembled to cheer Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>''I'm thrilled Mr. Glendening chose not to come,'' she said of the Maryland Governor, Parris N. Glendening, a Democrat seeking re-election who shunned the event in protest of Mr. Clinton's behavior in the Lewinsky scandal.</p>
        <p>Other Democrats rallied to the President's side, but with never a word of the Lewinsky inquiry in two hours of speechifying about education, nor of a possible impeachment inquiry, five miles to the south inside the Washington Beltway.</p>
        <p>''I'm very pleased to have the President here to talk about one of the real issues,'' said Representative Albert R. Wynn, Democrat of Maryland, who led the applause for Mr. Clinton. In an interview, the Congressman insisted that it was ''time to move on'' from the Lewinsky scandal. ''In my district, folks are not interested in hype, they are not interested in scandal,'' Mr. Wynn said.</p>
        <p>The President, energetically working the scene of cheering students as if it were a stop in some vital new political campaign, beamed before his invited audience of 120 teachers, parents and other advocates for improvements in education.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes when things are going really, really well for people, they get a little self-indulgent and basically just want to kick back and relax,''  Mr. Clinton declared in warning against the neglect of education needs.</p>
        <p>''Congressman Wynn committed the truth up here when he said that the first time we talked, he was hitting on me for more Federal funds for education,'' Mr. Clinton added.</p>
        <p>The event amounted to a respite from the investigatory travail of Washington. But for every bit of encouragement -- ''We love you!'' shouted one supporter as the President stepped up to speak -- there was a disapproving word or a blunt sign being offered by surrounding residents. ''Liar! Liar!'' the homeowner at 8 Woodmoor Drive announced to the motorcade in a sign propped up by a statue of St. Anthony.</p>
        <p>A half-dozen pro-impeachment pickets who have been dogging the President in Washington journeyed here to hold up a sign proclaiming, ''Mr. President, stay away from our daughters.'' But other outsiders came to express support.</p>
        <p>''Most of his critics come across as puritanical,'' said Susan Rohrer of Beltsville, watching the motorcade route with her two daughters, ages 3  and 5. ''What they're doing is negating all the good he's done.''</p>
        <p>Outside the school, Maureen Hanley, a local resident, said flatly: ''He's here because of spin control. He's got to win the public back again. Forgive me, but I think he's a liar, and you can watch it in his facial expressions, trying to get this to blow over. But it's not blowing over.''</p>
        <p>Inside the school, the President received repeated rounds of applause as he spoke up for higher spending on school construction and teacher training and warned children about hollow promises.</p>
        <p>''The child will turn on the television and hear every politician like me saying children are the most important things to our future, education is the most important issue,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''The actions that the child sees walking up the steps to school every day are louder than all the words to the contrary of the politicians.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Winter, watching as the Presidential caravan glided through this sylvan tableau of family value politicking, contended that the President was violating his own action-over-words caution. ''He's just here in a continuation of his latest marketing scheme,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But the President was obviously cheered by the meticulously planned journey beyond the Beltway, spending extra time to meet the children assembled at his departure. In his speech, he related their needs to a wide variety of pending issues.</p>
        <p>''The Senate is going to get another chance to do the right thing on campaign finance reform,'' he said. ''I wish they would. I'd like to see all my successors be able to spend less time raising money and more time helping you raise your kids.''</p>
        <p>TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
