<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Change Seen at Fed On Rates</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="366236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTEREST (MONEY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL RESERVE SYSTEM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D6153CF935A35754C0A966958260" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Change Seen at Fed On Rates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Despite pressure from the White House and Congress to lower interest rates quickly to try to prevent a recession, the Federal Reserve apparently decided at a policy meeting this week to hold rates unchanged for the time being.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Despite pressure from the White House and Congress to lower interest rates quickly to try to prevent a recession, the Federal Reserve apparently decided at a policy meeting this week to hold rates unchanged for the time being.</p>
        <p>Despite pressure from the White House and Congress to lower interest rates quickly to try to prevent a recession, the Federal Reserve apparently decided at a policy meeting this week to hold rates unchanged for the time being.</p>
        <p>That was the assessment yesterday by some top Government officials outside the Fed and by Wall Street economists who monitor the central bank's activity. But the Fed's governing body did reportedly give some ground, the officials said, adopting a resolution that expressed a new willingness to lower rates. Such a resolution means that action could come this month if fresh data show that the economy is indeed sliding toward recession.</p>
        <p>The secretive Fed gave no hint of what its policy makers - its governors and the presidents of its regional banks - decided at the meeting on Monday and Tuesday in Washington. No sign of sympathy toward lower rates showed in the Fed's dealings in the Treasury securities markets yesterday. And Joseph Coyne, a Fed spokesman, declined to comment on reports that the policy makers had approved a new ''bias toward easing'' rates.</p>
        <p>New Bias May Have No Effect</p>
        <p>The new bias, in fact, may never be converted into lower rates. But in the arcane language of the Fed, the resolution expressed a greater willingness to lower rates than existed at the last policy meeting, in mid-May - if the mounting anecdotal evidence of a weakening economy also shows up in fresh statistical data. Since early this year the Fed has expressed no special inclination either to raise or lower rates.</p>
        <p>''This is a very dicey time,'' said Robert Di Clemente, a Fed watcher at Salomon Brothers Inc. ''It could be we are on the verge of a recession, but the signals are mixed. It isn't as if the economy is going down in a straight decline.''</p>
        <p>The first test of the central bank's intentions could come today, with the Labor Department's release of June employment numbers. Jobs have been growing much more slowly this year than last, and if the June figures show more weakness, the Fed might act.</p>
        <p>What the Fed Could Do</p>
        <p>If the Fed did act, it would do so by increasing bank reserves, thus setting off a chain of events that would lower interest rates. The chain of events set off by this action would lower interest rates on a variety of consumer and business loans. The lower rates usually encourage more borrowing to finance purchases and investment, thus stimulating the economy. Sometimes the rising activity pushes prices up, making the inflation rate rise.</p>
        <p>But weak employment numbers might not be enough to make the Fed act, in the view of many experts. As recently as mid-June, Alan Greenspan, the Fed chairman, said publicly that while the American economy was growing sluggishly, recession was a declining prospect, not a growing one.</p>
        <p>Fear of a recession prompted the Fed to lower interest rates slightly in early November and again in late December. Shortly afterward, however, Government data showed strong activity in home construction and a sharply rising inflation rate, a surge in economic activity that lasted through the first quarter. But data released in May and June indicated that retail sales had deteriorated, along with consumer spending and construction activity. The only clearly strong sector was exports of manufactured goods.</p>
        <p>'A Widespread Uneasiness'</p>
        <p>''You don't find the confidence in the economy that you once did, at any level, in the small towns or the cities,'' said Representative Lee H. Hamilton, Democrat of Indiana and chairman of Congress's Joint Economic Committee, who traveled in the Midwest this week. ''There is a widespread uneasiness; that's the best word to describe it.''</p>
        <p>Apart from the state of the economy, the pressure on the Fed to lower rates stems from President Bush's new proposal to bleed roughly $50 billion from the budget deficit in a single year through a combination of increased tax revenues and reductions in Government spending. The twin actions would weaken the economy, by taking spending money from taxpayers' pockets and by reducing Government outlays for a wide range of activities.</p>
        <p>The Bush proposal is now the key element in budget negotiations with Congress. But such a cutback in activity would set off a recession, many economists and politicians say, unless the Fed offset the cutback by lowering rates.</p>
        <p>Traditional Focus on Inflation</p>
        <p>The Fed traditionally concentrates on reducing inflation, which it tries to accomplish by manipulating bank reserves in such a way that rates rise for a variety of consumer and business loans. The high rates - home equity loans and long-term mortgage rates, for example, stand at 10 percent or more - are intended to discourage purchases and investments made on credit. Less of such activity, in turn, makes price increases less likely.</p>
        <p>But when recession threatens, the central bank comes under pressure to reduce rates to encourage the borrowing that finances spending and investment, even at the risk of higher inflation. And right now Congress and the Bush Administration are campaigning vigorously for lower rates.</p>
        <p>Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady, for example, criticized the Fed yesterday for sticking stubbornly to inflation-fighting. ''In the United States it is not wise to emphasize an undying attack on inflation if it hampers economic growth,'' he said in a breakfast meeting yesterday with reporters.</p>
        <p>Other Voices for Lower Rates</p>
        <p>Michael J. Boskin, chairman of the Council of Economic Advisers, and Richard G. Darman, the budget director, have also called on the central bank in recent days to lower rates to stimulate a sluggish economy in danger of recession. And in a rare attack on the Fed, Pete V. Domenici of New Mexico, the ranking Republican on the Senate Budget Committee, said in a Senate speech on June 18 that the Fed was fighting the wrong battle.</p>
        <p>''What is the Federal Reserve trying to fix?'' he asked. ''If it is inflation, currently there is little evidence in the numbers that it needs fixing. Looking at the economic numbers, it is clear that adequate real growth, not inflation, should be our major concern.''</p>
        <p>The inflation rate as measured by the Consumer Price Index has hovered around 4.5 percent a year for several years, although it jumped to an annual rate of more than 5 percent in the first quarter of this year.</p>
        <p>Greenspan's Argument</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan has argued that a plan to reduce the budget deficit significantly - a plan persuasive enough to make it credible to the the public and the financial markets -would result in lower interest rates without any Fed action. Among other things, chronic deficits raise expectations of inflation, and as these deficits subside, so do the interest rates that lenders charge to offset inflation, Mr. Greenspan and other economists argue.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Brady said yesterday that Mr. Greenspan should help the deficit reduction negotiations along by taking the lead in lowering rates and not waiting for them to fall on their own. ''I've said to him that I don't think we should wait around,'' Mr. Brady said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
