<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Showdown and Shutdown: The Basics Over the Budget</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="818896"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="BATTLE OVER THE BUDGET: THE DETAILS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1DD1239F93AA15751C1A963958260" item-length="2149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Showdown and Shutdown: The Basics Over the Budget</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seems irrational. Some Government offices are closed, but many more are open. Some Government workers have been furloughed, but they have been promised  they will be paid for not working. Others are working at full pay. Still others  are at work but will draw only half a paycheck this week.</p>
        <p>Congress, meanwhile, is in recess. Many top Administration officials are on vacation. President Clinton is planning his annual New Year's weekend in South Carolina. Speaker Newt Gingrich says no break in the deadlock over the Federal budget is possible until the middle of next week at the earliest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seems irrational. Some Government offices are closed, but many more are open. Some Government workers have been furloughed, but they have been promised  they will be paid for not working. Others are working at full pay. Still others  are at work but will draw only half a paycheck this week.</p>
        <p>Congress, meanwhile, is in recess. Many top Administration officials are on vacation. President Clinton is planning his annual New Year's weekend in South Carolina. Speaker Newt Gingrich says no break in the deadlock over the Federal budget is possible until the middle of next week at the earliest.</p>
        <p>The plot is so convoluted, the developments are so incremental and the characters seem so agitated when they speak that even avid followers of the political script often have trouble figuring out what is going on and who is at  fault. If you are confused and want to know the basics about the budget conflict, here they are:</p>
        <p>The Shutdown</p>
        <p>Six annual spending bills have not been enacted -- that is, have not been passed by Congress and signed by the President, or have not been passed over his veto. They hold the money to operate nine Cabinet departments and many other Government agencies in the fiscal year that began on Oct. 1.</p>
        <p>In the departments and agencies without funds, only employees designated essential are on the job, although in some offices that is all or most of the work force.</p>
        <p>The White House and the Capitol are open, and their employees working because laws providing their funds have been enacted. The same is true of the Departments of Defense, the Treasury and Transportation.</p>
        <p>Three bills that have not been enacted -- those for the District of Columbia, foreign operations and the Departments of Labor, Education, and Health and Human Services -- are stuck in Congress for one reason or another.</p>
        <p>Three other annual spending bills have been vetoed by the President: one for  the Departments of Commerce, Justice and State and the Federal judiciary, another for the Interior Department and the third for the Department of Veterans Affairs, the Department of Housing and Urban Development and agencies like the Environmental Protection Agency that are not part of any Cabinet department.</p>
        <p>The President has also vetoed the vast long-term bill that is the keystone of the Republican Congressional majority's plan to balance the budget in seven years. This legislation would limit spending for Medicare, end the 60-year-old Government guarantee of Federal assistance to the poor, turn over Medicaid and most other welfare programs to the states, scrap many existing farm programs and cut taxes for middle-income families with children and for investors.</p>
        <p>The Republican majority in Congress is much too small to override the vetoes.</p>
        <p>When annual spending bills have not become law by the beginning of the fiscal year, Congress routinely approves a temporary measure called a continuing resolution that keeps the departments and agencies functioning until legislation providing their funds can be enacted. That has already happened twice this fall.</p>
        <p>But Republicans are using the current Government shutdown as leverage to pressure Mr. Clinton into signing their long-term budget bill. If the budget bill does not become law, much of their revolution will be thwarted: taxes will  not be cut, and benefit programs like Medicare will continue without change.</p>
        <p>For some Federal workers, the effect of the partial shutdown will be felt in  paychecks on Friday. In offices without funds, even those who have been working  cannot be paid for the days since the shutdown began.  But because the shutdown  started midway through many employees' pay period, these employees -- whether working or ordered not to work -- will draw one week's pay in what would normally be a two-week paycheck.</p>
        <p>Congressional leaders promise that any pay lost during this period of turmoil will be restored once the impasse is eventually broken. The Negotiations</p>
        <p>Before the 1996 fiscal year began on Oct. 1, Congress passed and the President signed a continuing resolution extending the Government's spending authority through Nov. 13. When that measure expired, the first partial shutdown began. It lasted for six days until, on a Sunday night, negotiators from the White House and Congress struck a deal on a new temporary spending resolution, to last through Dec. 15.</p>
        <p>The agreement that reopened the Government was intentionally ambiguous. Both  sides agreed to work on legislation to balance the Federal budget by 2002 as measured by the calculations of the Congressional Budget Office. They also agreed to "provide adequate funding" for Medicare, Medicaid, education and other programs the Clinton Administration favors.</p>
        <p>Since then, the two sides have done little but shadowbox. Republicans have argued that by not using the Congressional Budget Office's economic assumptions  in drawing up his own latest plan to balance the budget in seven years, the President reneged on his part of the agreement. The President has blamed Republicans, declaring that they failed to offer enough money for programs like Medicare.</p>
        <p>On Dec. 19, four days into the latest shutdown, President Clinton and the Congressional leaders -- Mr. Gingrich and Senator Bob Dole -- seemed to reach an accord to open the Government through the holidays.</p>
        <p>But at a televised news conference, Vice President Al Gore appeared to contradict the Republican account of the accord, which was that the President had agreed to negotiate, by the end of the year, a balanced budget based on Congressional Budget Office calculations. It is not clear whether Mr. Gore misspoke or was intentionally trying to throw sand in the gears.</p>
        <p>In any case, on Dec. 20 Republicans in the House scuttled the agreement reached the night before. They maintained that the Vice President's statement had made clear that the White House would not negotiate in good faith, although  this may have been mostly an excuse to justify their hard line.</p>
        <p>The President and the Republicans who control the Senate favor reopening the  Government while the political dispute is being resolved, but they have been unable to do so because of the rigid position taken in the House.</p>
        <p>Occasional talks have gone on at various levels since then, but nothing of substance has been accomplished. Congress is basically in recess until Jan. 3, and Leon E. Panetta, the White House chief of staff and main Administration budget negotiator, has been on vacation.</p>
        <p>The President and Congressional leaders are supposed to meet on Friday. But as best anyone on the outside can tell, they are no closer to resolving their differences than they were when the fiscal year began three months ago.</p>
        <p>The Issues</p>
        <p>The President insists on preserving Medicare for the elderly and the social safety net for the poor. Congressional leaders demand a balanced budget in seven years. If all that were at stake was the amount of money separating them, they could certainly split the difference and be done with it.</p>
        <p>But beneath the political oratory, the impasse is grounded in one fundamental, possibly insurmountable disagreement. The Republicans want to diminish the importance of the Federal Government in American life. The President does not, and, in some instances, would expand the Government's role.</p>
        <p>Thus, the Republicans want not only to restrain spending but to cut taxes as  well. They want to convert Medicare eventually to a voucher system in which the  Government would give retirees money with which to purchase their own health insurance. They would also give the states primary responsibility for Medicaid and cash assistance, limit Federal contributions to other programs for the poor  like food stamps, cut spending for education, weaken a variety of environmental  safeguards, permit much more commercial development and use of Government land,  cut Government research programs and give the Government less say about what farmers produce.</p>
        <p>President Clinton opposes all those policies. He favors only a modest tax cut. He would basically maintain Medicare and Medicaid as they are now, and he has promised to veto a welfare bill already approved by Congress. In the case of education, environmental protection and technological development, he supports a substantial expansion of the Federal Government's spending and influence.</p>
        <p>Listing the basic disagreements understates the extent of the divide. In each area, there are dozens of specific policy differences between the two sides. In  the case of Medicare, to take just one example, they range from major issues like how much premiums should be increased to relatively minor ones like the payment for administering blood-clotting factor to hemophiliacs.</p>
        <p>The Politics</p>
        <p>Politics is usually like a sporting event in which one team is ahead and the  other is trying to catch up. The budget impasse is one of the rare instances when both sides believe they have the political edge.</p>
        <p>Republicans, especially those in the House, believe they were elected into the majority last year because they had promised fundamental changes in the ways of Washington. They see compromise and deal-making as elements of the old ways that the public was fed up with. As long as they stand fast, they believe, they  will come out ahead politically, not just in the long term but in next year's elections as well.</p>
        <p>The President and his Democratic allies have returned to the well that has sustained the party for half a century. Most Republicans opposed Social Security in the 1930's and Medicare in the 1960's, and Democrats have never let them forget it. As they have countless times in the past, Democrats have positioned themselves this year squarely on the side of the elderly.</p>
        <p>In next year's election campaign, expect each side not so much to defend its  own stand as to attack the other's.</p>
        <p>Republicans will describe Democrats as supporting ever higher taxes and opposing a balanced budget because they cannot control their appetite for profligate spending. Democrats will picture Republicans as calloused fat cats who want to gut Medicare for the elderly and the disabled to pay for tax cuts for the affluent.</p>
        <p>The election results may well turn on which side can make the charge stick.</p>
        <p>Public opinion polls show that the President's standing has improved as the budget war has dragged on. But poll results are notoriously ephemeral. The dominant public view in December 1995 could well change by January, to say nothing of November.</p>
        <p>The Outlook</p>
        <p>Here are three safe bets:</p>
        <p>*The Government will stay partly closed at least until next Wednesday, when Congress returns from its holiday.</p>
        <p>*Sooner or later, Government offices will reopen, furloughed workers will be  paid for their days off, and those whose pay has been docked will be made whole.</p>
        <p>*When that happens, each side will blame the other for the shutdown and the inconveniences it entailed.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, little can be predicted with confidence.</p>
        <p>Behind the scenes at the White House and in Congress, some strategists favor  compromise to resolve the budget differences. Others, as in a game of chicken, favor sitting tight and waiting for the opposition to swerve.</p>
        <p>Even if both sides decide that compromise is the best course, it could take weeks to sort out the myriad issues that divide them. The best that can probably be hoped for in the short run is that the White House and Congress will agree to a basic framework and use that as the basis for putting the Government back to work while the meat and the muscle are put on the skeleton.</p>
        <p>For the long term, it is hard to imagine Republicans relenting on their demand for policies that can be shown on paper to lead to a balanced budget in seven years. It is equally difficult to imagine the President relinquishing his hole card: a basically unchanged Medicare system.</p>
        <p>If neither side blinks, the President and Congress may be able to find some way for the Government to operate in 1996 while all the issues are fought out on the campaign trail. But how they can do that is anyone's guess.</p>
        <p>BATTLE OVER THE BUDGET: THE DETAILS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
