<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reclamation Effort by Isles Starts Too Late to Matter</title>
    <meta content="X08ISL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/08/sports/hockey/08ISLE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1349486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Blackhawks</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Caldwell, Dave</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Chicago Blackhawks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E3D7113CF93BA35751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reclamation Effort by Isles Starts Too Late to Matter</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Reclamation Effort by Isles Starts Too Late</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE CALDWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Caldwell, Dave</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, Dec. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chicago Blackhawks defeat New York Islanders, 4-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oleg Kvasha scored on a fierce wrist shot, then Brad Isbister banged in a rebound two and a half minutes later, and suddenly, what had been disintegrating into a rare lopsided loss for the Islanders somehow became salvageable.</p>
        <p>Too bad the Islanders, dead-legged for so long tonight, had flipped the switch so late. By the time Kvasha and Isbister scored power-play goals early in the third period, Chicago's Éric Dazé already had a hat trick, and the Blackhawks held on for a 4-3 victory over the Islanders before 16,113 at United Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>By the time Oleg Kvasha and Brad Isbister scored power-play goals in the third period, Chicago's Éric Dazé already had a hat trick, and the Blackhawks held on for a victory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oleg Kvasha scored on a fierce wrist shot, then Brad Isbister banged in a rebound two and a half minutes later, and suddenly, what had been disintegrating into a rare lopsided loss for the Islanders somehow became salvageable.</p>
        <p>Too bad the Islanders, dead-legged for so long tonight, had flipped the switch so late. By the time Kvasha and Isbister scored power-play goals early in the third period, Chicago's Éric Dazé already had a hat trick, and the Blackhawks held on for a 4-3 victory over the Islanders before 16,113 at United Center.</p>
        <p>The Islanders (16-8-4-1), who will not play again until Tuesday at home against Ottawa, were outshot, 35-13. The 13 shots were a season low for the Islanders, who had only 3 shots in the first period and 7 shots after two.</p>
        <p>''We didn't have our legs, for whatever reason, and they skated by us,'' Coach Peter Laviolette said.</p>
        <p>The Islanders came into tonight's game with the third-best road record in the N.H.L., but the Blackhawks (15-9-7-0) have made the United Center an intimidating place for more than just its thunderous organ. Chicago has the best home record in the league (11-1-3-0), and the Blackhawks looked as if they wanted to pounce on the Islanders.</p>
        <p>They pounced a little too hard. Thirteen seconds into the game, Kyle Calder rammed Kvasha face-first into the boards. Calder was given a penalty as Kvasha got up slowly and skated back to the Islanders' bench. Kvasha returned 14 seconds after that, and Aleksei Yashin scored a power-play goal 37 seconds into the game.</p>
        <p>Yashin unleashed a slap shot from the left face-off circle that whizzed past Chicago goaltender Jocelyn Thibault. It was Yashin's 16th goal. As Thibault twisted to stop the shot, he was clipped by the stick of one of his own players.</p>
        <p>Thibault stayed in the game, and the Blackhawks gave him a rest by pummeling Garth Snow, the Islanders' goaltender, with 15 shots in a row.</p>
        <p>''We knew how Chicago plays,'' Snow said. ''They throw everything at the net.''</p>
        <p>Snow was at his cantankerous best. He stopped six shots on one Chicago power play, including two by Calder from two feet away. He flung his stick at a shot that came too close to him. Unfortunately for the Islanders, Claude Lapointe tripped Michael Nylander at the same time, and the Blackhawks had another power play.</p>
        <p>Alex Zhamnov took a shot from inside the blue line that was hard enough to carom off Snow's left pad. Dazé, who has 17 goals this season, swept the rebound between Snow's legs at 16 minutes 32 seconds of the first. The Islanders allowed 18 shots in the period, tying a season high, and took only 3, tying a season low.</p>
        <p>''I can't speak for the other guys in here, but it seemed like we were second to almost every loose puck,'' said Michael Peca, the captain. ''When that happens, it's difficult to create a lot of chances.''</p>
        <p>Chicago could not keep up its attack in the second period, but the Islanders could not mount a comeback. Dave Scatchard tried to provide the Islanders some juice by fighting Mark Bell. But that only served to take one of the Islanders' few energetic players off the ice.</p>
        <p>With Peca in the penalty box for elbowing, Igor Korolev was allowed to skate with the puck along the goal line right at Snow. He appeared to lose the puck in front of Snow, but Dazé was there to put it in at 15:15 of the second.</p>
        <p>It was the 28th shot for Chicago. The Islanders had seven shots at the time. The Islanders had not allowed more than one power-play goal in a game since Nov. 19, when they beat Dallas, 3-2.</p>
        <p>''I think Snow kept us in the game the whole night,'' defenseman Kenny Jonsson said. ''He was our best guy out there.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders had one more chance as the second period ended. Zhamnov was given a five-minute spearing penalty and a game misconduct while Lapointe received only two minutes for roughing. The Islanders would have a three-minute power play if they could kill the penalties to Snow and Lapointe.</p>
        <p>But Dazé redirected a shot past Snow 30 seconds into the third. Steve Sullivan added an unassisted goal 47 seconds later. Little did the Blackhawks know they would need both of those goals.</p>
        <p>''It's like we got some of our emotion back,'' Yashin said of the comeback.</p>
        <p>But that, Laviolette said, was just an illusion. ''There were no signs we were about to take control of the game,'' he said.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
