<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Actresses, Greek Tragedy Offers Many Happy Endings</title>
    <meta content="29GREE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1050147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greece</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Theater of Greece</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mccarter Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Blue Light Theater Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Classic Stage Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wanamaker, Zoe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bloom, Claire</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carroll, Pat</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karabeti, Karyofyllia</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Electra (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Oedipus (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Medea (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Greece</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E3D71039F93AA1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1099" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Actresses, Greek Tragedy Offers Many Happy Endings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Actresses are taking stage this season in remarkable number of Greek tragedies; McCarter Theater in Princeton is presenting Sophocles' Electra, featuring Zoe Wanamaker, Claire Bloom and Pat Carroll; Blue Light Theater Co is staging Oedipus, new play written and directed by Dare Clubb, at Classic Stage Co in East Village; National Theater of Greece has just presented six performances of Medea at City Center in Greek, with Karyofyllia Karabeti in title role; actresses are grateful for roles in which they can be direct and assertive rather than resorting to stereotypical machinations and manipulations; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pat Carroll was attracted to the role of the Chorus of Mycenae in Sophocles' ''Electra'' because of its spareness, its necessity, its raw and relentless candor. ''There is no subtext,'' Ms. Carroll said. ''What is said is what is meant.''</p>
        <p>She was also grateful for the part, period, because she is 71, and there are few female roles of comparable force for women her age. ''That's another reason why, over the past 12 years I have done nothing but classical work,'' Ms. Carroll said. ''You aren't categorized into an age category. You are free to be any age you want to be.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pat Carroll was attracted to the role of the Chorus of Mycenae in Sophocles' ''Electra'' because of its spareness, its necessity, its raw and relentless candor. ''There is no subtext,'' Ms. Carroll said. ''What is said is what is meant.''</p>
        <p>She was also grateful for the part, period, because she is 71, and there are few female roles of comparable force for women her age. ''That's another reason why, over the past 12 years I have done nothing but classical work,'' Ms. Carroll said. ''You aren't categorized into an age category. You are free to be any age you want to be.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Carroll is one of many women who are taking the stage this season in leading roles in Greek tragedies. The sheer number of productions is remarkable.</p>
        <p>Through Sunday, the McCarter Theater in Princeton, N.J., is presenting Sophocles' ''Electra,'' featuring Zoe Wanamaker in the title role, Claire Bloom as Clytemnestra and Ms. Carroll.</p>
        <p>At the Classic Stage Company in the East Village, the Blue Light Theater Company is staging ''Oedipus,'' a new play written and directed by Dare Clubb, featuring Billy Crudup in the title role and Frances McDormand as Merope that runs through Oct. 25.</p>
        <p>The National Theater of Greece has just presented six performances of ''Medea'' at City Center in Greek with English translation, with the actress Karyofyllia Karabeti in the title role. And from Oct. 14 through Oct. 18, the New Wave Festival at the Brooklyn Academy of Music will feature ''The World Mysteries: The Mysteries of Eleusis,'' a play by Vasilios Calitsis and Tasos Roussos based on the myth of Demeter and Persephone.</p>
        <p>Two plays by Euripides have been combined as ''The Iphigenia Cycle,'' which is to begin performances in January at the Theater for a New Audience with JoAnne Akalaitis as director. And The Williamstown Theater Festival in Williamstown, Mass., recently presented Euripides' ''Hecuba,''  starring Olympia Dukakis.</p>
        <p>Why the sudden deluge of Greek drama? Some of the artists involved in those productions say they were attracted by the plays' emotional energy. And a number of them cite the nation's political climate.</p>
        <p>''The real meaning of classicism is necessity and urgency,'' said David Leveaux, who is directing ''Electra.'' ''We obviously live in necessary and urgent times; therefore we're looking for drama that will match that.''</p>
        <p>Timberlake Wertenbaker, who translated and adapted the ''Hecuba'' recently produced at Williamstown, said: ''Playwrights at the time, particularly Euripides and Sophocles, were totally disenchanted with the political system. I think that when that happens -- and we may be in a similar period now -- people tend to turn toward women not because women behave better than men but because they're more truthful about what they do and why they do it.</p>
        <p>''I think playwrights were turning to these women characters to try to understand something, to try to find passion against hypocrisy and double talk,'' Ms. Wertenbaker added. ''They didn't look down on women and didn't give them stupid small roles. The great flaw of modern plays is they always try to make women nice. These women are terrible, and they have the courage of their horror.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, the brazenness and potency of the women in ''Electra,'' in which Electra avenges her father's murder by her mother, Clytemnestra, was the main reason Mr. Leveaux said he decided to direct the play. ''It's unusual to find a play that pits that number of ferociously powerful women against each other,'' he said. ''You can see in characters like Electra and Clytemnestra the antecedents of other great female roles in later Western drama, from Hedda Gabler to Lady Macbeth.''</p>
        <p>''These elemental women appear in this play compressed and utterly uncompromising,'' Mr. Leveaux continued. ''There is no time for the walk to the mantelpiece, so what you get is pure argument.''</p>
        <p>The actresses involved said they were grateful for roles in which they could be direct and assertive rather than resort to stereotypical machinations and manipulation.</p>
        <p>''You absolutely have to find the cleanest possible way of delivering the greatest truths,'' said Ms. Bloom, who plays Clytemnestra in ''Electra.'' ''So that we can't really bring post-Freudian analysis, as one brings to most other plays.''</p>
        <p>Anne Dudek, a 23-year-old actress fresh out of Northwestern University who plays the title character in ''The Iphigenia Cycle,'' said she loves Iphigenia's combination of defiance and surrender. In the first play of the cycle, ''Iphigenia at Aulis,'' Iphigenia agrees to die at her father's hand for the sake of the war. In the second, ''Iphigenia in Tauris,'' she is full of bitterness at having been sacrificed.</p>
        <p>''The core of the first play is this intense longing for life, which dictates all the decisions she makes,'' Ms. Dudek said. By the end, she added: ''She's this incredibly hardened saddened character. But I think the anger comes out of a hope.''</p>
        <p>Because of the depth and pitch of their characters, women in these plays say they find the performances especially taxing. ''By the end of a six-hour rehearsal session,'' Ms. Carroll said, ''I'm ready for two weeks in the south of France.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Akalaitis said the material was also draining to direct. ''It's very hard for me to rehearse these plays,'' she said, ''because I actually cry all the time.''</p>
        <p>Whether contemporary audiences would go for all this Greek tragedy did not worry the artists involved. Instead, they focused on the timeless themes and suspenseful plots. ''It's a thriller, basically,'' Ms. Wanamaker said of ''Electra.'' ''And it moves like an express train.''</p>
        <p>Niketi Kontouri, who is directing ''Medea,'' described the title role as a compelling amalgam of universal characteristics that will resonate with today's audiences. ''She's a witch, she's a barbarian; but at the same time she uses speech as a man -- she uses laws,'' Ms. Kontouri said. ''All people may have a hint of Medea in themselves. All of us.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, it is the contradictions of the female characters in Greek tragedy that actresses playing them seem to appreciate most. Ms. Wanamaker described Electra, for example, as being ''a fury, a killer, a luminous heroine, a terrorist and an inconsolable angel'' all at once.</p>
        <p>''And we can be appalled by her, and we can be moved by her, Ms. Wanamaker said, ''but we cannot resist her or the magnificent humanity that rages within her.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
