<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milosevic's Old Foe Riding High Again in Kosovo</title>
    <meta content="Y06KOS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/06/world/06KOSO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1245092"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gall, Carlotta</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rugova, Ibrahim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DF1239F935A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1261" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milosevic's Old Foe Riding High Again in Kosovo</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARLOTTA GALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gall, Carlotta</byline>
      <dateline>PRISTINA, Kosovo, Nov. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Ibrahim Rugova, longtime political leader of Albanians in Kosovo, who is again on rise after his Democratic League of Kosovo emerged winner in local elections; many regard victory as protest against unsavory behavior of many former rebels since end of war in Kosovo, but it still attests to Rugova's political stamina and enduring appeal as Gandhi-like father figure for many Albanians; he says people wanted to see more stable and experienced leadership than rebels offered; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ibrahim Rugova, long the political leader of the Albanians in Kosovo, is once more in the ascendant after his party, the Democratic League of Kosovo, emerged the winner in local elections.</p>
        <p>Sitting in his elaborately furnished home in Pristina, the enigmatic Mr. Rugova seemed quietly elated. Although he lost some popularity during the armed rebellion led by younger Albanians against the Serbs in 1998 and 1999, this historian of literature has always insisted that he is the elected president of Kosovo Albanians. He emerged the undisputed winner of makeshift elections -- held in homes and garages because of Serbian police harassment -- in 1992 and again in 1998, but now he is much more sure of that claim.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ibrahim Rugova, long the political leader of the Albanians in Kosovo, is once more in the ascendant after his party, the Democratic League of Kosovo, emerged the winner in local elections.</p>
        <p>Sitting in his elaborately furnished home in Pristina, the enigmatic Mr. Rugova seemed quietly elated. Although he lost some popularity during the armed rebellion led by younger Albanians against the Serbs in 1998 and 1999, this historian of literature has always insisted that he is the elected president of Kosovo Albanians. He emerged the undisputed winner of makeshift elections -- held in homes and garages because of Serbian police harassment -- in 1992 and again in 1998, but now he is much more sure of that claim.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rugova's party won nearly 60 percent of the vote in the Oct. 28 municipal elections organized by the foreign officials who run Kosovo, gaining majority control of 21 of the 30 municipalities. He eclipsed the younger leaders: Hashim Thaci, the former political leader of the Kosovo Liberation Army, the rebel force that fought the Serbs, and Ramush Haradinaj, a former rebel commander.</p>
        <p>Even if, as many suggest, the vote was more a protest against the unsavory behavior of many former rebels since the Kosovo war ended in June 1999, the result showed Mr. Rugova's political stamina and enduring appeal as a Gandhi-like father figure for many Albanians in Kosovo.</p>
        <p>If, as now expected, Mr. Rugova wins the general elections that could be held next year, he will most likely find himself negotiating Kosovo's future status within Yugoslavia, the Balkans and Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rugova, 54, headed the Writers' Union in Kosovo before the majority Albanians were stripped of or quit their jobs in state administration a decade ago. They established a life parallel to that of the minority Serbs, who formally ran the province while the Albanians set up schools and hospitals in private homes and founded most of Kosovo's shops and small businesses.</p>
        <p>He formed his political party in 1990 and essentially headed a long campaign against Slobodan Milosevic, who as president of Serbia abolished Kosovo's autonomy in 1989.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rugova, a bookish man who spends hours with his collection of rocks and minerals from all over Kosovo and speaks excellent French and some English, has sometimes been branded as too passive. During the war over Kosovo last year, when he had a still unexplained meeting with Mr. Milosevic, he was almost deemed a traitor.</p>
        <p>Now, Mr. Rugova said in an hourlong interview conducted with an Albanian translator in which he parried all questions about that meeting, support has swung back to him. ''Eventually people wanted to see a more stable and experienced leadership'' than the rebels, he said.</p>
        <p>He appeared almost chipper, relaxed and laughing, speaking confidently of Western understanding of his desire for Kosovo's independence from Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>He urged rapid international recognition of independence while the NATO-led peacekeeping force and the United Nations mission are still in charge of the province.</p>
        <p>''It would finally clarify things,'' Mr. Rugova said. ''You have to understand there is still among Albanians anxiety and fear of Belgrade, and that fear comes from decades-long experience of repression by the regime in Serbia. With independence, then people would have much more respect for minorities and their rights.''</p>
        <p>''But right now people are not sure what will happen,'' he said, apparently alluding to the killing and violent harassment of Serbs in Kosovo, which was the heart of the Serbs' medieval empire and is central to their national mythology.</p>
        <p>He cares little, he said, whether Belgrade agrees with him, indicating that international support was more important. ''If the U.S. has a say, then eventually Belgrade will have to comply,'' he said. ''Kosovo is a de facto international issue and I have been saying we are de facto independent already.''</p>
        <p>Exactly how he will achieve international recognition for independence is not clear since the United Nations Security Council resolution that governs the foreign presence in Kosovo says the province is part of Yugoslavia and foreign powers -- for various reasons -- are wary of shifting Balkan borders.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Rugova said it was a priority to get freedom of movement for Serbs in Kosovo who live trapped in enclaves protected by peacekeepers, he has never called on his people in any convincing manner to stop the revenge and violence.</p>
        <p>He said it was too early to think of meeting the new Yugoslav president, Vojislav Kostunica, and opposed allowing Kosovo Serbs to vote in the Serbian elections of Dec. 23, arguing that they should no longer look to Belgrade.</p>
        <p>On a practical level, he talks of restoring Kosovo's infrastructure, creating jobs and building democratic institutions. Yet critics say he has not always been cooperative in helping the United Nations build local and provincial administrations. His parallel political structures before the war were not particularly effective, those critics say.</p>
        <p>One Western diplomat grimaced at the prospect of Mr. Rugova and his party leading Kosovo through the next years. ''Many of them would far rather sit in cafes talking than actually run things,'' he said.</p>
        <p>There is similar criticism among ordinary Albanians, and even within his own party. There were calls for a leadership contest after the war, which claimed the lives of many activists, in particular Fehmi Agani, Mr. Rugova's right-hand man and reputed political brains.</p>
        <p>Mahmut Bakalli, a Communist-era leader of Kosovo, now retired, and  among the Kosovo Albanians' most gifted politicians, describes Mr. Rugova as an arrogant man who cannot accept other people's opinions. He, like a number of intellectuals and professionals in Pristina, supports the idea of a new leader from the younger generation.</p>
        <p>In defense of his inactivity in the last 14 months, Mr. Rugova said he had to take a back seat since the United Nations was running things. His party, he said, ''has been working quite hard but in silence.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rugova also referred obliquely to the threat of violence from former members of the Kosovo Liberation Army who seized power in many districts and threatened and even killed some members of his  party. ''Immediately after the war there were too many people who were armed and out of control.'' he said.</p>
        <p>''It did take time for KFOR to take control,'' he added, referring to the NATO-led peace force, ''and for ourselves to establish more control through the joint administrations.''</p>
        <p>The socially conservative Kosovo Albanians have, however, given Mr. Rugova the benefit of the doubt. They have also been understanding of his meeting with Mr. Milosevic  during the NATO bombing campaign.</p>
        <p>There is no question the meeting  took place under duress. The Serbian police had occupied his house in Pristina, forcing the whole family to live in the living room, where photographs of Mr. Rugova with President  Clinton and Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright now hang.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rugova spent half an hour with Mr. Milosevic as cameras whirred. He refused to say what they discussed. ''I was certainly forced to go to Belgrade, otherwise I would have been killed or something,'' he said. ''All the talk was entirely unimportant. Their intention was to discredit me. But thanks to friends I was released.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps even more mysterious than the meeting and his later departure for Italy -- still during the war -- was his delay in returning home, a subject he also declined to discuss.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
