<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jets Have Lost Their Winning Touch in the Fourth Quarter</title>
    <meta content="06JETS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/06/sports/06JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1245152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6D81239F935A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1202" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jets Have Lost Their Winning Touch in the Fourth Quarter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Nov. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Vinny Testaverde knew as soon as he released the ball, off balance and still under pressure, that the Jets' final offensive play in a 30-23 loss to Denver would fail.</p>
        <p>After a week in which Coach Al Groh had publicly challenged his quarterback to reduce his interceptions and his secondary to reduce big plays against them, those twin demons had put the Jets into a hole again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Vinny Testaverde knew as soon as he released the ball, off balance and still under pressure, that the Jets' final offensive play in a 30-23 loss to Denver would fail.</p>
        <p>After a week in which Coach Al Groh had publicly challenged his quarterback to reduce his interceptions and his secondary to reduce big plays against them, those twin demons had put the Jets into a hole again.</p>
        <p>But the Jets had clawed back from a 17-point deficit in the first half -- then from a 10-point deficit early in the fourth quarter -- so that Testaverde could lead one more drive in an attempt to tie the score as regulation time dwindled.</p>
        <p>The first four completions of the drive had come so quickly that the chain gang and statistics crew had as much trouble keeping up with the Jets' offense as the Broncos' defense. But then three consecutive pass plays from the 2-yard line failed.</p>
        <p>The Jets, who had no timeouts remaining, felt that a running play was too risky with less than a minute to play. Now Testaverde needed to use a stiff arm to create space between him and the blitzing Denver linebacker Glenn Cadrez.</p>
        <p>Testaverde eked out a few inches but he could not see if there was more pressure coming. As he rolled to his right, Testaverde saw Richie Anderson wide open on the right side of the end zone. The Jets quarterback made the instant decision to throw before he had the chance to set his feet. Anderson, who appeared to slip as he made a move to come back for the ball, went down while reaching for the ball, which flopped on the ground.</p>
        <p>And the Jets, who not long ago were 6-1, are now 6-3 and, with Miami having beaten  Detroit, have suddenly been jarred from first place in the American Football Conference East.</p>
        <p>In addition, they face a treacherous stretch with consecutive road games against division rivals Indianapolis and Miami.</p>
        <p>''It's a terrible feeling, especially when the game is on the line,'' Anderson said. ''I wish I could have it back.''</p>
        <p>The Jets, no doubt, wish they could take back this entire game. They find themselves shriveling, with two straight losses for the first time since early last December, at a most critical time in their season.</p>
        <p>They had desperately wanted to avoid a second loss now, with the most difficult stretch of their schedule upon them. But they seem to have run short of the miracle comebacks.</p>
        <p>They fell short last week against Buffalo and then, today, the same weaknesses that Groh had pointedly said must be shored up in the second half of the season made their return.</p>
        <p>''We turned the ball over, we gave up some deep plays in the secondary and we couldn't get off the field on third down,'' Groh said. ''Then it is really hard to make enough good plays to win.''</p>
        <p>The Jets' offense has been bedeviled by turnovers. Testaverde was intercepted twice today and a botched pitch to Curtis Martin was scored as a Testaverde fumble, leading to 13 of Denver's 20 first-half points.</p>
        <p>Testaverde, who has been intercepted 13 times this season, nearly double his total in 1998, completed 21 of 42 passes for 293 yards today. Meanwhile, the Jets' running game has stalled for three straight games. Today, the Jets had only 17 carries  for 88 yards.</p>
        <p>The Jets' defense gave up 447 yards of offense and was picked apart by Denver quarterback Brian Griese, who completed 22 of 35 passes for 327 yards. A healthy Terrell Davis ran for 115 yards in his return from an ankle injury.</p>
        <p>Ominously, the Jets' secondary, a source of concern since the preseason, is showing little sign of progress.</p>
        <p>Today, four Broncos had catches of longer than 20 yards and receivers Ed McCaffrey and Rod Smith each had receptions of more than 45 yards.</p>
        <p>The inability to stop the long ball was especially glaring on third down.</p>
        <p>The Broncos converted a stunning 12 of 18 third-down chances, but the three most critical came in the second half, after the Jets had scored 10 points -- on a 1-yard touchdown run by Martin and a 45-yard John Hall field goal to make a horrible first half seem respectable with a 10-point deficit at halftime.</p>
        <p>The Jets had needed all of 10 minutes in the third quarter to score 10 points (a 1-yard touchdown catch by Anthony Becht and a 26-yard Hall field goal) to tie the score, 20-20.</p>
        <p>But on third-and-6 with the ball on Denver's 28-yard line, Griese saw Smith in the middle of the field, a route the Broncos ran over and over again. He threw the ball and cornerback Marcus Coleman was out of position to make the tackle.</p>
        <p>Smith caught the ball and was gone, streaking down the sideline, with Victor Green in pursuit. When Green's angle finally coincided with Smith, he had already gone 49 yards, as part of a 10-play, 71-yard drive that ended with a 23-yard field goal that gave the Broncos a 23-20 lead as the third quarter ended.</p>
        <p>Then, after the Jets had to punt on their first drive of the fourth quarter, the Jets seemed to have held the Broncos, pinning them at their 34-yard line on third and 9.</p>
        <p>Had the Jets forced the Broncos to punt, they would have done so into the famously brutal wind of Giants Stadium. Instead, Griese picked apart the middle again, completing a 13-yard pass to tight end Dwayne Carswell. But the Jets' defense held again, and the Broncos were faced with third down and 4 from the Jets' 47-yard line. A punt against seemed imminent. But Griese dropped back in the pocket and pumped his arm once. It was a fake, but it drew cornerback Aaron Glenn to take a few steps forward. McCaffrey streaked by him and was wide open on the right side when Griese's pass found him for a 47-yard touchdown that gave the Broncos a 30-20 lead.</p>
        <p>''It's been a continuing story all year,'' Coleman said of long passes. ''Until we find a way to stop it, people will continue to take shots on us. Until we stop it, it's going to continue to keep happening.''</p>
        <p>And the Jets will continue to lose. Martin could see Testaverde's final pass fall to the ground, inches from a touchdown and overtime. The desperation comebacks have turned, simply and suddenly, to desperation.</p>
        <p>The air of invincibility that had puffed the Jets up in previous comebacks has gone out of them.</p>
        <p>''It's deflating,'' Martin said of the final pass. ''It's like someone took a pin and busted the balloon.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
