<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="836537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E5DE1639F937A25750C0A960958260" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORK</p>
        <p>Lobbying in Albany on Rise  Corporations and interest groups spent $46.9 million to lobby state government in New York last year, a 20 percent increase over 1994 and the largest rise in nearly two decades, a state commission said. Hospitals are among the companies at the top of the list, and unions for state workers and teachers also made large expenditures. [Page B1.] The most sought-after lobbyist in Albany is Robert J. Malito, a longtime friend  of Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato. [B8.]</p>
        <p>A Skirmish With a History  Long before it erupted in murder, the domestic violence case against Benito Oliver was just another skirmish in a simmering feud between the Brooklyn District Attorney's office and Judge Lorin Duckman. Prosecutors compiled courtroom comments and decisions by Judge Duckman that prosecutors said documented his bias toward defendants and hostility toward young assistant district attorneys. [B1.]</p>
        <p>Opposition to Hospitals Plan  When the first three city-run hospitals were put up for sale, officials did not  anticipate that advocates for the hospitals would rise up to fight the sales. By most accounts, the efforts have proved to be one more stumbling block to the Mayor's attempts to sell or lease some or all of the city's 11 municipal hospitals. [B1.]</p>
        <p>Fighting an Eviction  Gus Eppinga and Jim Davis are among some 20 residents left at two single-room-occupancy hotels on lower Lexington Avenue that are to be razed to make room for an expansion of Baruch College. But the two men aren't budging. They think they were hoodwinked by state officials who pledged in 1991 to build  replacement apartments. About New York by David Gonzalez. [B1.]</p>
        <p>Brain-Dead Girl's Heart Stops  Mariah Scoon, the brain-dead infant whose parents fought to keep her on a mechanical ventilator after she was pronounced legally dead, was disconnected from the machine after her heart stopped beating despite the artificial support. Authorities conducted an autopsy, which prosecutors had sought as part of a criminal investigation of the parents. The results will not be available for several weeks. [B3.]</p>
        <p>Adelphi Head Faces Students  The president of Adelphi University, under fire for his high salary, told students at a forum that he had no plans to resign and dismissed his legal problems as of no importance to them. He did not respond to questions concerning an investigation by the State Attorney General's office into his compensation and perquisites. [B7.]</p>
        <p>School Drops an AIDS Book  For four years, students taking health classes at Horace Greeley High School in  Chappaqua, N.Y., have read Magic Johnson's 1992 book, "What You Can Do to Avoid  AIDS." But a group of parents complained that the book's depictions of sex were  inappropriate for 14- and 15-year-olds. As a result, the district decided to stop using the book. [B7.]</p>
        <p>Nassau Sues L.I.R.R. on Cuts  The Nassau County Executive and other county officials have filed suit against the Long Island Rail Road to block the closing of 15 ticket offices and 2 stations in Nassau. The suit contends that the cutbacks would violate an agreement with the county to maintain service. [B7.]</p>
        <p>A Rift Widens in Albany  The chief of Governor Pataki's security detail took away the Lieutenant Governor's state trooper escort after receiving complaints that she had used the troopers to chauffeur her on personal errands. [B6.]</p>
        <p>Brooklyn Shootout Kills Man  A wild shootout that erupted on a street in Bedford-Stuyvesant, Brooklyn, left one man dead and four others injured, including a 14-year-old boy who was seriously hurt by the gunfire, the police said. [B2.] Building a Better Watchdog Legal experts say the New York City School Construction Authority has developed  one of the most promising anticorruption programs to arise in years, one that offers fresh ideas to a corporate community that is facing a host of new pressures to police its own ranks. Business Day. [D1.]</p>
        <p>For the first time since New York City's teachers rejected a proposed contract,  union and school representatives are to sit down with a state arbitrator. [B2.]</p>
        <p>Members of two Bronx community school boards who were recently suspended for allegations of corruption will face little opposition in the May 7 elections. [B6.]</p>
        <p>NEW JERSEY</p>
        <p>On the Right to Bear Backpacks In a half-hour of testimony in court, a 14-year-old girl from Hamilton Township, N.J., defended her defiance of her school's ban on backpacks and argued that only those misusing them should be penalized.  She left the witness chair unruffled, even after some verbal jousting with the school board's lawyer. [B7.]</p>
        <p>Clinton Pledge on Light Rail The Clinton Administration pledged to seek Congressional financing to build the  first half of a light rail system that would run along the Hudson River from Ridgefield to the Bayonne Bridge. [B7.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
