<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After a Triumph, a Night of Moderation at Christie's Sale</title>
    <meta content="12AUCT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="972517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Christie's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vogel, Carol</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ganz, Victor</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ganz, Sally</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CE4DD1F39F931A25752C1A961958260" item-length="1042" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After a Triumph, a Night of Moderation at Christie's Sale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL VOGEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vogel, Carol</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Christie's, after magical auction on Monday when 20th-century art collection of Victor and Sally Ganz sold for record $206.5 million, is brought back to reality after only 51 of 70 works of Impressionist and modern art are sold; auction totaled $69.9 million, below its estimate of between $79.1 million and $109.4 million; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christie's came back to earth last night. After a magical auction on Monday, when the 20th-century art collection of Victor and Sally Ganz sold for a record $206.5 million, Christie's sale of Impressionist and modern art was sobering.</p>
        <p>The sale had all the bumps of a regular auction. To be sure, there were high points, but there were also many high-priced works that failed to sell. Of the 70 artworks offered for sale, 51 sold. The auction totaled $69.9 million, below its estimate of $79.1 million to $109.4 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Christie's came back to earth last night. After a magical auction on Monday, when the 20th-century art collection of Victor and Sally Ganz sold for a record $206.5 million, Christie's sale of Impressionist and modern art was sobering.</p>
        <p>The sale had all the bumps of a regular auction. To be sure, there were high points, but there were also many high-priced works that failed to sell. Of the 70 artworks offered for sale, 51 sold. The auction totaled $69.9 million, below its estimate of $79.1 million to $109.4 million.</p>
        <p>''With brilliant marketing, Christie's made Ganz a household name, and that's what people were buying,'' said Barbara Guggenheim, a dealer who divides her time between California and New York. ''Tonight's sale didn't have that advantage.''</p>
        <p>Nor did it have the consistently high quality that single-owner sales sometimes have. Last night's offerings were a mixed bag of paintings and sculptures. Monday night's rare Picassos and exceptional examples of work by contemporary masters like Jasper Johns and Robert Rauschenberg were a hard act to follow.</p>
        <p>Last night's star painting was Monet's ''Waterloo Bridge in the Mist'' (1903), a view of the Thames painted from the artist's room at the Savoy Hotel in London. It sold for $8.2 million, well above its $6 million high estimate. The buyer was David Nash, the former director of Impressionist and modern art at Sotheby's, who now runs a gallery and art advisory service with his wife, Lucy Mitchell-Innes. In the last few years, Monet's late paintings have become more popular as collectors' tastes have shifted, and last night four bidders fought hard for ''Waterloo Bridge.'' By contrast, another Monet, ''Regatta at Argenteuil'' (1874), a sun-dappled scene of sailboats that was expected to bring $6 million to $8 million, failed to sell. Nobody was willing to go higher than $4 million. In 1984, the painting sold at Sotheby's in New York for $800,000.</p>
        <p>Perhaps ''Waterloo Bridge'' fared as well as it did because it came with a distinguished provenance. The painting came from the estate of Gabrielle Oppenheim-Errera, a Frankfurt collector. The Monet, bought by Mrs. Oppenheim-Errera's first husband, Dr. Paul Oppenheim, in 1916, was still in its original frame and in pristine condition.</p>
        <p>Other works from her estate up for sale included Pissarro's ''Primrose Hill, Regent's Park'' (1892), painted on the artist's third trip to London. The painting went to an unidentified telephone bidder for $717,500, below its low estimate of $800,000.</p>
        <p>(Final prices include the auction house's commission, 15 percent of the first $50,000 and 10 percent of the rest. Estimates do not reflect commissions.)</p>
        <p>Pissarro's ''Chestnut Tree in Louveciennes'' (1872) had also been in one family for a long time, since 1952. The arresting landscape, painted at the height of Impressionism, was expected to sell for $2 million to $3 million. It squeaked above its low estimate, selling to an unidentified American collector bidding by telephone for $2.2 million.</p>
        <p>Good modern sculptures were particularly popular, and Christie's had some exceptional ones. Several bidders tried to buy Brancusi's ''Sleeping Muse II,'' one of the few examples of its series still in private hands. Estimated at $4 million to $6 million, it eventually sold to an unidentified telephone bidder for $6.6 million.</p>
        <p>Two Giacomettis were also among the evening's most sought-after works. Raymond D. Nasher, a collector and real estate developer who is financing a sculpture garden next to the Dallas Museum of Art, spent $2.4 million for ''Woman of Venice IV,'' one of a group of 15 standing female figures the artist made in 1956. It had been expected to sell for $1.4 million to $1.8 million. And Giacometti's ''Head of Diego in a Turtleneck'' (1951) was sold to an unidentified telephone bidder for $882,500, well above its $600,000 high estimate.</p>
        <p>Among the evening's failures was Matisse's ''Still Life With Fruit and Flowers'' (1924), one of the artist's Nice period paintings. Bidding stopped at $3.5 million, well below the estimate of $4.5 million to $6.5 million, and gasps were audible from the audience.</p>
        <p>Another expensive work that didn't sell was Pissarro's ''Church at Saint-Jacques in Dieppe in the Morning Sun,'' (1901). In 1988, it had sold at Christie's for $3 million, but last night nobody was willing to bid more than $2.6 million, just under its $3 million low estimate.</p>
        <p>By contrast, a small but beautifully executed example of Fauve painting, Derain's ''Boats in the Port of Collioure'' (1905), was one of the evening's most popular works and one of the highest-quality paintings in the sale. Three people vied for the colorful 14-by-18-inch painting, which sold for $2.2 million, above its $1.8 million high estimate.</p>
        <p>A group of works by Redon from the estate of the Marquis de Gonet, a well-known French collector who died in 1925, was being sold by his descendants last night. Selling 10 works by the artist, who tends to appeal more to Europeans' taste than to Americans', was a gamble, especially for an artist whose work has never performed particularly well at auction. Last night, five of his works didn't sell, including the one with the highest estimate, ''Apollo's Chariot'' (1907-08). Nobody was willing to pay more than $600,000 despite an estimate of $1 million to $1.5 million. Mr. Nash bought two Redons: ''Black Pegasus'' (1909-1910), for which he paid $882,500, less than its $900,000 low estimate, and ''Flowers,'' the most attractive of the group, for which he paid $772,500, well above its high estimate of $400,000.</p>
        <p>''All the Impressionist painting we didn't think would sell did fairly well,'' said Desmond Corcoran, a London dealer.</p>
        <p>''But I was surprised the Matisse didn't sell. There was really no logic to this sale at all.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
