<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Line in the Water</title>
    <meta content="26COAS$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1395338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Coast Guard (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2D91138F935A15756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="2866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Line in the Water</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on US Coast Guard, which has become US's front line of defense in war on terrorism; focuses on likelihood that this summer's recreational boating season in waters off New Jersey and elsewhere will be even more undisciplined than usual, with reduced law enforcement and spotty maintenance of navigational aids; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EACH day, hundreds of cargo ships and tankers from around the globe glide in and out of ports in the metropolitan area. Every ship has the capacity to be the vehicle of the next terrorism disaster.</p>
        <p>In the Port of New York and New Jersey alone, about 11,000 vessels haul 3 million shipping containers and nearly 30 million gallons of oil and petroleum products every year, while about 450 commercial ships enter Long Island Sound, hauling 18.9 million tons of cargo to Connecticut ports. The the bulk of it, 10.6 million tons, goes to New Haven.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EACH day, hundreds of cargo ships and tankers from around the globe glide in and out of ports in the metropolitan area. Every ship has the capacity to be the vehicle of the next terrorism disaster.</p>
        <p>In the Port of New York and New Jersey alone, about 11,000 vessels haul 3 million shipping containers and nearly 30 million gallons of oil and petroleum products every year, while about 450 commercial ships enter Long Island Sound, hauling 18.9 million tons of cargo to Connecticut ports. The the bulk of it, 10.6 million tons, goes to New Haven.</p>
        <p>Long Island ports see little commercial traffic these days. But with the Memorial Day weekend here and the summer boating season about to get into full swing, pleasure craft by the thousands will be slicing through the bays, coves and inlets -- some undoubtedly under the questionable control of weekend sailors who will be keeping the summer sun at bay with a six-pack not far from the helm. Other craft may well be under the control of far more dangerous hands.</p>
        <p>Yet the Coast Guard, the underappreciated stepchild of the defense establishment, now finds itself on the nation's front line of defense in this new kind of war on terrorism. And it is finding itself stretched thin.</p>
        <p>No one knows, of course, if the Coast Guard will be called on -- and prove itself able -- to prevent a terrorist attack. But at the least, given the diversion of personnel and equipment to prevent a new attack, it seems clear that this summer's recreational boating season is going to be even more undisciplined than usual, with reduced law enforcement and spotty maintenance of navigational aids.</p>
        <p>''We've been doing a service almost around the world with an organization that is smaller than the New York City Police Department,'' said Chief Warrant Officer Stephen Lyons, commander of the station at Sandy Hook, N.J.</p>
        <p>Administered by the Department of Transportation, not the Department of Defense like its military siblings, the Coast Guard has aging equipment that frequently breaks down and an active-duty force of only 37,000 -- not many more than it had last Memorial Day. Coast Guard crews must board ships outside of port in search of weapons, and they also patrol vital complexes like the container ports at Port Newark and Port Elizabeth, the nuclear plants at Indian Point, Oyster Creek, Salem and Millstone, the submarine base at Groton and the marinas and beaches of Long Island.</p>
        <p>Before Sept. 11, the Coast Guard focused its efforts on search-and-rescue operations, boating safety and drug enforcement, and on stopping illegal immigrants, catching vessels that spill oil, enforcing fishing quotas and maintaining countless buoys and lighthouses. After Sept. 11, about 2,900 reservists were called up to help fill the ranks, but Congress did not appropriate enough money to keep them on active duty after Oct. 1, the end of the fiscal year. For now, about 1,700 of the reservists remain on duty.</p>
        <p>Ken Knutsen, a 41-year old bridge maintenance supervisor for the New York State Bridge Authority, is one of these reservists. Called at noon on Sept. 11 to report to his duty station, the Coast Guard Group/Marine Safety Office in New Haven, Mr. Knutsen, a boatswain's mate second class who served for four years in the early 1980's, will be deactivated at the end of this month.</p>
        <p>''They had us go to Station New London and had us patrolling the security zone around the submarine base,'' he said. ''They had us there to December.''</p>
        <p>Asked why he was returning to civilian life, he said: ''A lot of this is due to the budget. We just don't have enough money to go around.''</p>
        <p>Stephen E. Flynn, a retired Coast Guard commander who is a senior fellow at the Council on Foreign Relations, said there were currently no resources for keeping reserve coast guardsmen on active duty.</p>
        <p>''A significant proportion are not going to be able to finish off the fiscal year and will not be available next year,'' Mr. Flynn said.</p>
        <p>The Coast Guard is seeking a 36 percent budget increase next year.</p>
        <p>On close examination, it is not hard to see why the Coast Guard is feeling stretched. While only 1 percent of its resources were dedicated to port security before Sept. 11, more than 50 percent of all coast guardsmen are now focused on homeland security -- and with good reason.</p>
        <p>As recently as Tuesday, the chairman of the Senate Intelligence Committee confirmed that the Coast Guard and other agencies had learned that a group of Middle Eastern men -- ''extremists,'' as he referred to them -- might have entered the United States in recent weeks aboard container ships that docked in Florida, California and Georgia.</p>
        <p>''Given that the Coast Guard had been downsized throughout the 90's,'' Mr. Flynn said, ''there wasn't a whole lot of capacity for it essentially to pick up this new mission without it impacting significantly on its traditional missions.''</p>
        <p>More evidence that the Coast Guard was being stretched thin was recently presented by Kenneth M. Mead, the inspector general of the Department of Transportation, who testified in March before a Senate subcommittee on oceans, atmosphere and fisheries.</p>
        <p>''In response to the Sept. 11 attacks, the Coast Guard deployed 58 percent of its resources to port safety and security missions,'' Mr. Mead said.</p>
        <p>And, he added, the deployment ''came at the expense of other important core missions, including drug interdiction.'' He noted that the resources devoted to stopping illegal drugs dropped to 7 percent from 18 percent before Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>Despite its lack of resources, the Coast Guard has conducted 4,000 boardings, checking vessels that might constitute a threat. It has also sent out more than 35,000 security patrols and 3,500 air patrols since Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>During a recent patrol of the Arthur Kill separating Staten Island from New Jersey, Alano Demurguiondo, a boatswain's mate third class who was in the pilothouse of a 41-foot utility boat, the Coast Guard's workhorse, gave a long, hard look at two men in a small boat anchored next to the Outerbridge Crossing.</p>
        <p>At one time, Mr. Demurguiondo might have waved and assumed they were fishermen. Now, he said, he and his crew take nothing for granted.</p>
        <p>''Before, we'd come down this river, and I would be checking out the other mariners.'' he said as the boat idled not far from an oil refinery on the Perth Amboy shore. ''But now, I'm not only looking at the other mariners more. I'm paying attention to what's on the shoreline. You never know.''</p>
        <p>Sailing out of the Sandy Hook station on this sunny afternoon, passing clammers and some recreational boaters, Mr. Demurguiondo and his crew made sure no fishing vessels or pleasure boats passed within the security zone set up around Naval Station Earl, the Navy's weapons depot, whose long pier juts into the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Since Sept. 11, the Coast Guard has been guarding security zones around naval installations, and for the first time since World War II has been escorting naval vessels in and out of port.</p>
        <p>Passing between New Jersey and Staten Island, the crew trained their eyes on a shore dotted with sprawling oil refineries, chemical plants and a power station, all potential terrorist targets.</p>
        <p>''We're a lot more aware of boats hanging out and going into certain areas like the Earl pier,'' Mr. Demurguiondo said, ''or maybe if they're hanging around bridges, or if they're at anchor for a certain amount of time, or if they're hanging out at the Arthur Kill or the Kill Van Kull.''</p>
        <p>But according to the inspector general's report, increased patrols in the First Coast Guard District, which covers the waters from Toms River, N.J., to the Canadian border, also meant that no fishery enforcement patrols were conducted from Sept. 11 through Dec. 31.</p>
        <p>''Other missions, such as recreational boating safety, aids to navigation, commercial fishing vessel safety and migrant interdictions were also hard hit,'' the inspector general said.</p>
        <p>Although Coast Guard members are reluctant to admit that their increased security duties are cutting into traditional missions, others like Capt. Craig T. Bone of the Port of New York and New Jersey said that the Coast Guard was overextended.</p>
        <p>''I am able to apply the resources I have to the highest risk, but I don't have enough equipment and people to do all the mission areas at this point, to support security operations at an increased level while maintaining other missions,'' Captain Bone said.</p>
        <p>Perhaps one of the most pressing examples is that of the Indian Point nuclear plant, on the Hudson at Buchanan, N.Y., 30 miles north of Manhattan. Immediately after the Sept. 11 attacks, the Coast Guard posted three cutters there around the clock, and about a month later reduced the number to one cutter.</p>
        <p>''We wanted 24-hour protection at Indian Point,'' said Senator Charles E. Schumer. ''They did it for a while, but they basically said they didn't have the resources to do it constantly.''</p>
        <p>By the end of last year, the Coast Guard withdrew the one vessel, despite objections from officials and anxious Westchester County residents, including many who said they wanted the plant closed permanently. Coast Guard officials said the cutter was redeployed after operators of the Indian Point plant adopted a more stringent security plan and patrols by law enforcement agencies like the Westchester County Police Department were increased.</p>
        <p>William Rehm, first deputy commissioner of the Westchester County police, said his agency's marine unit would be in full force during the summer, along with units from several municipalities on both sides of the Hudson.</p>
        <p>Lt. j.g. Marc Sennick, assistant operations officer for Coast Guard Group Moriches, which patrols the South Shore of Long Island (the New Haven group patrols the North Shore), said his outfit worked with marine units from the Nassau and Suffolk County Police Departments, the harbor masters, bay constables and recreational boaters in watching for suspicious activity.</p>
        <p>''They have a better grasp of what is normal and not normal,'' Lieutenant Sennick said. ''Any day, we have 10,000 boaters on the South Shore, 250,000 over the summer. They're our eyes and ears.''</p>
        <p>Vessels from Group Moriches ply the inshore waters from Rockaway Inlet in Queens to Montauk Point, plus Gardiners Bay and Great Peconic Bay.</p>
        <p>Although there are some sensitive sites to patrol -- for instance, the Plum Island Animal Disease Center at the tip of the North Fork, the only location in the country where research on foot-and-mouth disease is permitted -- the main duties for Group Moriches remain search and rescue, maintenance of almost 400 navigational aids, and boating safety, which includes boarding recreational vessels.</p>
        <p>''We don't have nuclear power plants, but we do have a lot of waterways that could lead people to stage things,'' Lieutenant Sennick said.</p>
        <p>Group/Marine Safety Office Long Island Sound, based in New Haven, provides the same services to North Shore boaters and the rest of Long Island Sound shipping, including traffic at the commercial ports of New Haven, Bridgeport and New London, along with security for the Navy's submarine base in Groton and the Millstone nuclear plant in Waterford.</p>
        <p>In and around New York Harbor, inspecting larger commercial vessels has become more common. For several weeks after Sept. 11, the Coast Guard boarded every ship that came into the Port of New York and New Jersey. Since then, it has implemented a program requiring commercial ships to give the Coast Guard information about crews and cargo at least 96 hours before docking. The National Vessel Movement Center in Martinsburg, W.Va., an office created after Sept. 11, receives the information, which it shares with Coast Guard intelligence in Maryland and checks it against the criminal and immigrant databases of other agencies.</p>
        <p>''With this information, the Coast Guard decides which ships to board based on risk management,'' Cmdr. Daniel A. Ronan, the chief of the waterways management division in the New York command, said as he stood in the Vessel Traffic Service Center on Staten Island, a large, dimly lighted room where about 20 black-and-white video screens and 16 color monitors track every vessel that enters the port.</p>
        <p>''We're taking a look at the risks associated with each vessel, and basically on that information -- where they're coming from, what was the last port of call, what cargoes are on there, who are the shipping companies, where are the crew members from, are they from a country that were concerned about, Middle East counties, somewhere else that would cause us some concern,'' he said. ''We determine what their risk is and who we're boarding.''</p>
        <p>Since Sept. 11, 700 of the 4,000 ''high-interest'' vessels boarded nationwide were in the New York area. But Cmdr. Michael McAllister, the chief of the marine response division in the New York command, said the new program had sharply reduced the number of ships boarded.</p>
        <p>''If it's a particularly high-interest vessel, we'll get the U.S. Customs Service involved,'' Commander McAllister said. ''We'll get the Immigration and Naturalization Service involved.''</p>
        <p>In other situations, the Coast Guard might dispatch boats to escort vessels to shore, or call in the Sea Marshals, a new unit created after Sept. 11 to guard vessels' engine rooms and bridges against hijackers.</p>
        <p>''Vessels carrying liquefied natural gas and other explosive elements are routinely boarded,'' said Chief Warrant Officer Lyons of the Sandy Hook station. ''Like an aircraft, one of these things can be used as a weapon of mass destruction.''</p>
        <p>After a three- to four-hour check of the ship's crew and inspecting safety features like its gas detection system, a 110-foot cutter takes up an escort position at the bow while a utility boat follows at the stern, ready to warn other vessels off or in a worse-case situation, attack an other vessel trying to ram the fuel-carrying ship, Mr. Lyons said.</p>
        <p>Containers stacked in holds -- like the ones in which the two dozen Middle Eastern men are said to have entered the United States illegally -- are not easily accessible at sea; once in port, only 3 percent of the containers get opened by the Customs Service, which says it does not have the manpower to open every container.</p>
        <p>For now, the authorities are exploring ways to make sure that weapons and stowaways are intercepted at the port of origin, and they are trying to develop new technology to track each piece of cargo along the way to ensure it is not tampered with.</p>
        <p>Mr. Flynn of the Council on Foreign Relations says this is the way to go, rather than trying to open every container. ''It's too late when you discover a weapon of mass destruction in port,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Despite the new precautions now in place, Capt. Tony Regalbuto, the chief of the Coast Guard's office of policy and planning, has been outspoken in interviews and on Capitol Hill in seeking better equipment, like sensing devices to locate weapons.</p>
        <p>One measure being adopted is the use of dogs to sniff out weapons, much as they do in detecting narcotics.</p>
        <p>In addition, Representative Frank A. LoBiondo, the New Jersey Republican who is chairman of the House subcommittee on the Coast Guard and maritime transportation, is sponsoring a measure that would give the Coast Guard an additional $75 million a year to assess security at foreign ports, improve ship surveillance and draft security plans for ports in this country.</p>
        <p>''What we saw before 9/11 was a Coast Guard that was taken for granted,'' Mr. LoBiondo said.</p>
        <p>But that is about to change.</p>
        <p>The Coast Guard is seeking a $1.9 billion increase over this fiscal year's budget of $5.3 billion to finance new coastal patrol boats, increase security operations, upgrade communications equipment and create more marine safety and security teams -- new highly mobile Coast Guard SWAT teams.</p>
        <p>In addition, plans are afoot to replace or modernize 92 vessels and 209 aircraft as well as associated communication and navigation systems.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Lt. Pamela Garcia, a spokeswoman for the New Haven group, said the Coast Guard was trying to make itself more visible.</p>
        <p>''Since 9/11, particularly in the areas of the ferry terminal, people have told us they are reassured by our presence,'' Lieutenant Garcia said. ''Probably the most striking thing is they're still telling us that nine months later. We're doing what the name implies. We're literally guarding the coast.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
