<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="28GUID$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1337676"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800EED81531F93BA15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>Three years ago, at the age of 50, Caroline Rob Zaleski decided to ''make preserving older architecture and design my life.'' So Ms. Zaleski, then a medical journalist, went back to school at Columbia University to earn a master's degree in architectural preservation, which she received last year. Since then, she has been researching European Modernism in the New York area, surveying how many significant buildings and sites from the modern movement  have survived on Long Island, and advocating their preservation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Best Bet</p>
        <p>Three years ago, at the age of 50, Caroline Rob Zaleski decided to ''make preserving older architecture and design my life.'' So Ms. Zaleski, then a medical journalist, went back to school at Columbia University to earn a master's degree in architectural preservation, which she received last year. Since then, she has been researching European Modernism in the New York area, surveying how many significant buildings and sites from the modern movement  have survived on Long Island, and advocating their preservation.</p>
        <p>So far, Ms. Zaleski who divides her time between New York and Amagansett, has catalogued at least 12  homes on the North Shore and in the Five Towns built between the early 1930's and the mid-50's. They include four by Marcel Breuer, two by Jose Luis Sert and one by Edward Durell Stone. The latter home, the Conger Goodyear House in Old Westbury, is one of only two in the United States on the World's Monuments Watch (the other is in West Hollywood) and is the subject of a last-minute effort by local preservationists to prevent it from being torn down.</p>
        <p>''Modernism is something people don't understand,'' said Ms. Zaleski, ''and what's happening now is similar to what happened in the 1950's and 1960's when developers tore down old Victorian homes, including 20 Tiffany houses, because they were so dark. Just think of how much those Tiffanies would be worth now.''</p>
        <p>In ''Endangered Modernism on Long Island: Icons of the Recent Past,'' an illustrated lecture today at 3 p.m., Ms. Zaleski will bring her passion and the results of her study to the headquarters of the Society for the Preservation of Long Island Antiquities on Main Street in Cold Spring Harbor. The talk is the first of two on Long Island architecture that the society will offer this year. On Dec. 8, Richard Schneider, supervisor of the photographic preservation section of the National Archives and Records Administration, will discuss ''The Long View'' (631) 692-4664.</p>
        <p>Masur at Tilles</p>
        <p>On Saturday, local music fans get to say goodbye to Kurt Masur when he leads the New York Philharmonic at Tilles Center on the C. W. Post campus of Long Island University in Brookville. This is Mr. Masur's last season with the orchestra and for this concert at 8 p.m. he and the Philharmonic will be joined by Susan Botti, soprano; Christopher Lamb, percussionist; and Olli Mustonen, pianist, in a program of works by Liszt, Prokofiev and Rachmaninoff. Information: (516) 299-3100.</p>
        <p>A Trio at Coe Hall</p>
        <p>Friends of the Arts opens its season of Concerts at Coe Hall today with the Trio Solisti. Featuring Maria Bachmann, violinist; Alexis Pia Gerlach, cellist; and Jon Klibanoff, pianist, the chamber ensemble performs works by Beethoven, Morevec and Smetana at 2:30 p.m. in the mansion on the grounds of the Planting Fields Arboretum in Oyster Bay. Information: (516) 922-0061.</p>
        <p>Music in Southold</p>
        <p>The North Fork has a new classical music series, the Adams Foundation Piano Recital Series. The series is a national pilot project from the California-based group, which aims to re-establish piano and two-piano recitals in small American communities.</p>
        <p>Under the auspices of the Arts in Southold Town and the Oysterponds Historical Society, the series gets under way on Saturday with Richard and John Contiguglia. The two are known for their expertise in four-hand music by Franz Liszt. They  gave his unpublished ''Grosses Konzerstuck uber Mendelssohn's 'Lieder ohne Worte' '' its first complete performance in 1986 the Netherlands, to mark the 100th anniversary of the composer's death.</p>
        <p>The Contiguglias will play that piece, along with works by Mozart, Schubert and Schumann, at 7:30 p.m. at Southold High School on Main Road. Information: (631) 734-7696.</p>
        <p>Double Feature</p>
        <p>Every once in a while, Tilles and Staller Centers book the same acts, giving Long Islanders a clear choice of venues, or the chance to catch a favorite act twice. This week, devotees  of ethnic dance are in luck. They can see Bayanihan, the Philippine National Dance Company, at Staller on the State University at Stony Brook at 8 p.m. on Saturday, (631) 632-2787, or at Tilles on the C. W. Post campus in Brookville at 7 p.m. next Sunday,  (516) 299-3100. The program of the 45-member company, which was founded in 1957 to bring together Philippine ethnic rites, tribal folklore and national ways, will be the same, featuring ''Mountain Suite,'' ''Muslim Suite,'' ''Maria Clara'' and a selection of Philippine dances.</p>
        <p>Still Haunting</p>
        <p>Pumpkin carving is right up there in Halloween activities, so today, in honor of the holiday, Wheatley Plaza, off Northern Boulevard in Greenvale, is holding its annual Giant Pumpkin Carving. From noon to 4 p.m., Hugh McMahon will turn a 650-pound specimem into a scary creature. There will also be a complimentary pumpkin patch for youngsters under 12 and a raffle of carved pumpkins to benefit Long Island Riding for the Handicapped. Information: (516) 627-2277.</p>
        <p>Also today, V.O.I.C.E.S. performs ''Frankenstein'' at the Babylon Library at 2 p.m., (631) 669-1624, while  Southaven County Park in Brookhaven offers ''Bats for Halloween: Stellaluna Storytime!'' at 3 p.m., (631) 854-4980.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, the Babylon Library is planning a talk by Mark Lyons on ''Wicca and Witchcraft'' at 7 p.m., (631) 669-1624, and in Seaford preschoolers can have some ''Halloween Fun,'' courtesy of the Seatuck Environmental Center, whose naturalists hold a session of outdoor activities and crafts at 10 a.m. at Tackapausha Preserve, (631) 581-6908.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Halloween itself, activities include these films at the Cinema Arts Center in Huntington: ''The 5,000 Fingers of Dr. T,'' with a party for children at 3:30 p.m., and ''Rosemary's Baby,'' with a costumed dinner for adults at 6 p.m., (631) 423-7611. Also on Wednesday, the Long Beach Library is planning a ''Haunted Halloween'' literature session with Robert James at 8 p.m., (516) 432-7201, while the Magic Curtain Players is to perform a ''Mad Monster Party'' at 7:30 p.m. at the Stage Theater on Hewlett Avenue in Merrick, (516) 868-6400.</p>
        <p>In Patchogue, Lorena Doherty, a storyteller, offers ''Celtic Tales for Halloween'' at 7 p.m. at the library, (631) 654-4700, and in Plainview Dr. Arthur Liebman and Joyce Ann Liebman recreate ''Ghouls by Gaslight -- Vampires and Villains of Victorian London'' at the library at 8 p.m., (516) 938-0077.</p>
        <p>From 2 to 5 p.m. at the Stony Brook Village Center, there will be a Halloween Festival (631) 751-2244.</p>
        <p>Showing the Flags</p>
        <p>The Sea Cliff Village Museum's newe exhibition, ''All About Old Glory,'' features American flags from different eras. The largest is a 24-foot-high, 30-foot-long flag with 45 stars that the village received from its citizens on July 4, 1899. The museum is on Summit Avenue and is open from 2 to 5 p.m. weekends,  (516) 671-0090.</p>
        <p>In Bellport, at the Bellport-Brookhaven Historical Society on Bellport Lane, ''The History of the Amercan Flag'' includes items from an American 15-star handsewn flag to a 42-star bunting naval ensign flag. The museum is open from 1 to 4 p.m. Thursdays through Saturdays (631) 288-0888.</p>
        <p>Free Choices</p>
        <p>TODAY -- The library circuit includes: Dance Visions in ''Visionaries, Revolutionaries and Mavericks: A Century of Modern Dance'' at 2:30 p.m. at the Jericho Library,  (516) 935-6790; the Musiker Ensemble playing klezmer at 2 p.m. at the Long Beach Library, (516) 432-7201. And Opera Pro Voce singing Puccini's ''Tabarro'' and ''Gianni Schicchi'' at 2:30 p.m. at the Westbury Library, (516) 333-0176.</p>
        <p>New music fans can go to the State University at Stony Brook and hear the Computer Music Studio or the Contemporary Chamber Players appear on Wednesday. Both concerts are at 8 p.m. in Staller Center, (631) 632-2787.</p>
        <p>TUESDAY -- Nassau Community College continues its series ''After the Attack'' with ''Achieving Peace and Security in the World: A Moslem's Perspective'' with Hussein Hassouna, ambassador of the League of Arab States to the United States and United Nations, at 1 p.m. in the College Center on the Garden City campus, (516) 572-7153.</p>
        <p>Arthur Schwartz, one of the first male newspaper food editors in the country, comes to the Landmark on Main Street in Port Washington, via the local library, at 8 p.m., for, of course, ''A Culinary Evening With Arthur Schwartz.'' Information: (516) 883-4400.</p>
        <p>BARBARA DELATINER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
