<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Rabbi Has His Day In Court</title>
    <meta content="28COLU$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1337743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cherry Hill (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Galant, Debra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neulander, Fred J (Rabbi)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neulander, Carol</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E7DB1331F93BA15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Rabbi Has His Day In Court</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA GALANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Galant, Debra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Debra Galant Jersey column on reaction of Jewish community in Cherry Hill, NJ, to trial of Rabbi Fred J Neulander, 60, accused of arranging 1994 murder of his wife, Carol (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE is a theater group in New Jersey that re-enacts famous trials, sometimes in the very courtrooms in which they took place. This month, Century Productions was in the stately, white-columned courthouse in Flemington, acting out the trial in which Bruno Richard Hauptmann was convicted of kidnapping and murdering the child of Charles and Anne Morrow Lindbergh.</p>
        <p>The Lindbergh kidnapping trial was the first of its kind in the genre of media circuses, attracting hundreds of reporters and spectators alike who waited in long lines for a chance to sit inside the courtroom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE is a theater group in New Jersey that re-enacts famous trials, sometimes in the very courtrooms in which they took place. This month, Century Productions was in the stately, white-columned courthouse in Flemington, acting out the trial in which Bruno Richard Hauptmann was convicted of kidnapping and murdering the child of Charles and Anne Morrow Lindbergh.</p>
        <p>The Lindbergh kidnapping trial was the first of its kind in the genre of media circuses, attracting hundreds of reporters and spectators alike who waited in long lines for a chance to sit inside the courtroom.</p>
        <p>In the southern part of the state, another trial is now taking place. New Jersey v. Neulander, better known as the Cherry Hill Rabbi trial, will decide the fate of Fred J. Neulander, the 60-year-old Reform rabbi accused of arranging the murder of his wife in 1994. At the time of the murder, Rabbi Neulander happened to be having an affair with Elaine Soncini, a Philadelphia radio talk show host who had met the man of the cloth just before her husband's death a year earlier.</p>
        <p>The Camden County Hall of Justice, a modern, brown-brick building where the trial is unfolding, doesn't have the architectural splendor of the Flemington courthouse, but just the same there is a small plaza with hot dog vendors where jurors and lawyers often eat lunch. Court TV has a small white tent set up there where it interviews legal experts and lawyers involved in the case. And news vans encircle the plaza.</p>
        <p>But, unlike the Lindbergh case, there are no throngs. It is easy enough to get a seat in the windowless courtroom on the third floor, even if you arrive five minutes before the session starts. And if you want to relax, there's an overflow room on the fourth floor that carries the trial on a television monitor.</p>
        <p>It is there that journalists -- spread out with their feet up -- read the sports pages. Cell phones are allowed to ring, and the audience snickers when the defense attorney, Dennis Wixted, who slightly resembles Harrison Ford, gets off a question that is funny and vicious at the same time.</p>
        <p>I have been sent to Camden not so much to cover the intricacies of the case -- there are serious reporters for that, and you can watch it yourself on Court TV -- but to write  about how the Jewish community of Cherry Hill is reacting to this lurid mixture of the sacred and profane.</p>
        <p>If I were Isaac Bashevis Singer, I could undoubtedly give you quite a story. In his 1962 collection of short stories, ''In My Father's Court,'' the famous Yiddish author created just such an atmosphere surrounding the Beth Din, the rabbi's court, where grudges were settled and divorces granted.</p>
        <p>But the first-person narrator of the Singer stories is the rabbi's son, who is always quietly in the background, crouching and listening.</p>
        <p>''Krochmalna Street seethed,'' the narrator says in one story. ''Women wept, wrung their hands, wiped their eyes with their aprons.''</p>
        <p>There was no such public outpouring on Springdale Road in Cherry Hill, where you can find both the Betty and Milton Katz Jewish Community Center and Classic Cakes, the bakery once owned by the rabbi's wife. Women stride into the center with their gym bags, seemingly disinterested in their own home-sewn drama.</p>
        <p>Even teenagers working the counter at Classic Cakes know better than to talk to a reporter about the Carol Neulander case. The community circles its wagons, politely but firmly declining to be interviewed.</p>
        <p>They're even more tight-lipped in the hallway outside of the courtroom, where you can see the rabbi's daughter, Rebecca, during breaks.</p>
        <p>If you want big mouths, if you want yentas, you must rely on the blow-dried blondes on Court TV.</p>
        <p>''It's the war between the liars,'' Court TV's anchor for this spectacle, Nancy Gray, said the other day, speaking both of the hit man and the rabbi.</p>
        <p>These days, if you want commentary, you can't rely on the shtetl fishmonger. You need experts. I found one in Marie Fortune, a pastor in Seattle, who has written a book, ''Is Nothing Sacred?'' (Pilgrim, $17) about the destruction caused by members of the clergy who have had sexual affairs with congregants.</p>
        <p>Although she has not followed the Neulander case closely enough to have an opinion about the rabbi's innocence or guilt, she believes that his affair with someone who called him in need is troubling enough.</p>
        <p>When clergy use their power over vulnerable people, ''always there's damage,'' she said. ''The trust-betrayal thing is the fundamental issue.''</p>
        <p>JERSEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
