<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Melville Has Never Looked Better</title>
    <meta content="28DELBANT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/28/books/review/28DELBANT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1337527"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delbanco, Andrew</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Moby-Dick (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Melville, Herman</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E2D9153EF93BA15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="2696" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Melville Has Never Looked Better</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Melville Has Never Looked Better</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Delbanco</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Delbanco, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Andrew Delbanco essay on ups and downs of Herman Melville's career in light of 150th anniversary of his novel, Moby-Dick; discusses book's underlying meanings and how they may shed light on today's terrorist attacks; describes how Melville has risen from obscurity in his time to almost cult status in our own and and how book has survived as classic; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE HUNDRED FIFTY years ago this month Herman Melville's ''Moby-Dick'' was first published, to mixed reviews and, as they say in the trade, disappointing sales. In our own moment of horror and heroism, it is a book more salient than ever -- unflinchingly honest about the human capacity for hate and brutality, yet filled with an undiscourageable love of humanity. In its own day, it was received by many critics as a half-mad rant.</p>
        <p>According to a failed and now forgotten novelist, Henry F. Chorley, chief critic of The Athenaeum in London, ''Mr. Melville has to thank himself only if his horrors and his heroics are flung aside by the general reader, as so much trash belonging to the worst school of Bedlam literature.'' Chorley was right -- for a while. ''The Whale,'' as the book was called upon its publication in London in October 1851 (it appeared the following month in New York as ''Moby-Dick or The Whale''), marked both the artistic high point and the commercial downturn of Melville's career.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In our own moment of horror and heroism, Herman Melville's "Moby-Dick" is a book more salient than ever</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE HUNDRED FIFTY years ago this month Herman Melville's ''Moby-Dick'' was first published, to mixed reviews and, as they say in the trade, disappointing sales. In our own moment of horror and heroism, it is a book more salient than ever -- unflinchingly honest about the human capacity for hate and brutality, yet filled with an undiscourageable love of humanity. In its own day, it was received by many critics as a half-mad rant.</p>
        <p>According to a failed and now forgotten novelist, Henry F. Chorley, chief critic of The Athenaeum in London, ''Mr. Melville has to thank himself only if his horrors and his heroics are flung aside by the general reader, as so much trash belonging to the worst school of Bedlam literature.'' Chorley was right -- for a while. ''The Whale,'' as the book was called upon its publication in London in October 1851 (it appeared the following month in New York as ''Moby-Dick or The Whale''), marked both the artistic high point and the commercial downturn of Melville's career.</p>
        <p>The career had begun auspiciously in 1846, when, at 27, Melville published his first book, ''Typee,'' about the month he had spent held captive by a cannibal tribe in the South Pacific. ''Get it and read it by all means,'' was the recommendation of The New York Illustrated Magazine -- and a good many people did. (''Typee'' sold roughly 6,000 copies in its first two years -- not a best seller, but a respectable sale for a first book.) In the ensuing four years, Melville continued to draw on memories of his beachcombing days, producing on the average one book per year (''Omoo'' in 1847, ''Mardi'' in 1849, ''Redburn'' in 1849 and ''White-Jacket'' in 1850), the last two of which felt to him like ''jobs, which I have done for money -- being forced to it, as other men are to sawing wood.''</p>
        <p>Now just past 30, and settled into marriage in New York City with the daughter of a Boston jurist, he felt a surge of creative power uncontainable within the confines of the young-man-goes-to-sea genre -- or, it would seem, of any single work. In December 1850, having moved to a Berkshire farmhouse with his wife and baby boy, he wrote to his friend the New York editor Evert Duyckinck, ''Can you send me about fifty fast-writing youths? . . . If you can, I wish you would, because . . . I have planned about that number of future works &amp; can't find enough time to think about them separately.''</p>
        <p>When he wrote that letter, Melville's scattered ambitions had already consolidated into a single and singular effort. He had been seized, as every writer begs to be once, or -- if the muse is exceptionally generous -- twice, in a lifetime, by what he had called, during an earlier burst of creative energy, a ''blast resistless.'' We shall never know precisely when the idea for ''Moby-Dick'' crowded out its competitors in his mind; but we do know that he was stirred by his reading of Shakespeare, by his intellectual and personal encounters during the summer of 1850 with Nathaniel Hawthorne (who, he wrote, ''dropped germinous seeds into my soul'') and by the foreboding, felt by many men in their 30's, that the sap has begun to ebb and the moment for untried things is slipping away.</p>
        <p>''Give me a Condor's quill!'' he demanded. ''Give me Vesuvius' crater for an inkstand!'' In the winter of 1850-51, his wife later recalled, he worked on the new book ''at his desk all day not eating anything till 4 or 5 o'clock'' and then, according to his own account, retired for the evening to his room ''in a sort of mesmeric state.'' By the spring of 1851, with the book moving toward its apocalyptic conclusion, the smallest interruptions angered him; his mother, having packed up and left after a testy visit, complained: ''Herman I hope returned home safe after dumping me &amp; my trunks out so unceremoniously at the Depot -- Altho we were there more than an hour before the time, he hurried off as if his life had depended upon his speed.'' And while those around him savored the renewed warmth and light as ''spring begins to open upon Pittsfield,'' Melville, unused to the sun and habituated to daytime reclusiveness, wrote to Duyckinck that ''like an owl I steal about by twilight, owing to the twilight of my eyes.''</p>
        <p>What was taxing him was the labor of creating what we would now call a multicultural human universe aboard the whaleship Pequod -- from the serene and selfless harpooneer Queequeg, whom Melville likens to ''George Washington cannibalistically developed,'' to the blasphemously jolly third mate, Flask, ''so utterly lost . . . to all sense of reverence'' that for him ''the wondrous whale was but a species of magnified mouse, or at least water-rat.'' Initially, their tale is told by a young sailor named Ishmael -- a close relative of the sailor boys who had been in charge of Melville's previous books -- but the first-person narrative soon fractures into multiple voices contending with each other as if taking turns in a stage play. Littered with truncated episodes that Melville left in the final text as tantalizing fragments of what might have been, ''Moby-Dick'' is a restlessly experimental book -- by turns playful, ironic, somber and uproariously funny, sometimes dropping into bawdy comedy, sometimes soaring into soliloquies worthy of ''King Lear.'' One of its themes is the overwhelming improvisational power of its author.</p>
        <p>There are hints in the text, which Melville never revised with an eye toward concealing false starts, that he was not sure at first who would emerge as the principal character. Early on, a Southern-born sailor of noble bearing is introduced as if he were destined for a leading role, but is last seen standing at the helm as the Pequod heads out to sea, in a ''six-inch chapter'' that serves as his ''stoneless grave.'' One by one, contenders for primacy in the drama fall away as Melville finds himself gripped above all by the idea and image of the Pequod's ''moody stricken'' captain with a ''crucifixion in his face.'' He called this ''ungodly, god-like'' man Ahab, after the Israelite king who worshiped the pagan sun god Baal.</p>
        <p>At first, Melville's Ahab is known to his crew only by legend and rumor. Until the Pequod has been guided out to sea by the Nantucket pilot, he keeps himself hidden below decks. When he finally emerges, scarred and peg-legged, he looks ''like a man cut away from the stake, when the fire has overrunningly wasted all the limbs without consuming them,'' and makes an impression on the expectant crew that Melville summarizes in the wonderfully compressed phrase, ''Reality outran apprehension.'' But Ahab waits still longer to reveal the true objective of the voyage: to wreak vengeance upon the great white whale ''athirst for human blood'' that on a previous voyage had dashed his boat to splinters and ripped him half to death. In another brilliantly brief formulation, Melville gives the essentials of Ahab's history since his encounter with the whale: ''For long months of days and weeks, Ahab and anguish lay stretched together in one hammock'' as ''his torn body and gashed soul bled into one another; and so interfusing, made him mad.''</p>
        <p>From what searing experience did this extraordinary story arise? Ahab had his precedents. There is a sketch in ''Omoo'' of a ''dark moody savage'' who, when he misses a whale with an errant harpoon, pulls his boat close to the frantic animal and, in a preview of Ahab's final death-grapple with Moby Dick, leaps upon its back, clawing and stabbing at it in a blur of blood and foam; and there is, in ''Redburn,'' a brooding sailor ''full of hatred and gall,'' who regards everyone and everything with poisonous resentment, ''as if all the world was one person, and had done him some dreadful harm, that was rankling and festering in his heart.''</p>
        <p>These deranged characters were modeled, no doubt, on men Melville had known at sea; but Ahab is less a character than an embodied idea -- a conception of hate incarnate. Sometime in late 1850, Melville had probably come upon Coleridge's shrewd remark about ''Hamlet,'' that ''one of Shakespeare's modes of creating character is to conceive any one intellectual or moral faculty in morbid excess, and then to place himself . . . thus mutilated or diseased, under given circumstances.'' ''Moby-Dick'' derives much of its power from the improbably persuasive empathy with which Melville placed himself in the circumstance of a mutilated man swearing vengeance against the beast that ''dismasted'' him. This species of madness -- what we would call obsession or compulsion -- was known in the 19th century as ''monomania,'' and had been a psychological theme in the stories by Hawthorne that Melville admired. Now he undertook his own meditation on monomania -- on how, in his ''frantic morbidness,'' Ahab came to identify with the whale ''not only all his bodily woes, but all his intellectual and spiritual exasperations,'' until ''all the subtle demonisms of life and thought; all evil, to crazy Ahab, were visibly personified, and made practically assailable in Moby Dick.''</p>
        <p>The public was baffled. Sales in the first few months amounted to a mere 2,000 copies, and though the book remained in print in an era when unsold inventories were less a burden to publishers than they are today, total sales during Melville's lifetime barely exceeded 3,000. When he poured invective at publishers and public into his next book, ''Pierre or The Ambiguities'' (1852) -- another story of a madman on a private crusade -- the critics were confirmed in their negative judgment. One newspaper ran its notice of ''Pierre'' under the headline, ''Herman Melville Crazy.'' In what was left of the 1850's, he wrote several haunting stories and novellas, including ''Bartleby, the Scrivener'' (1853) and ''Benito Cereno'' (1855), but though he lived another 35 years, his bitter burlesque, ''The Confidence Man'' (1857), marked the end of his career as a publishing novelist. When he died in 1891, with the exquisite ''Billy Budd'' left unfinished in manuscript, an obituary in The New York Press registered the depth of oblivion to which he had fallen: ''Probably, if the truth were known, even his own generation has long thought him dead, so quiet have been the later years of his life.''</p>
        <p>TODAY, Melville and his whale have resurfaced and seem to be everywhere -- in popular as well as high culture, in the arts as well as the academy, in this country as well as abroad. Some six million American homes tuned in to the recent USA Network version of ''Moby-Dick,'' and the book has lately inspired a critically acclaimed opera, a dramatic piece by the performance artist Laurie Anderson, a series of artworks by Frank Stella and a widely read novel written from the point of view of Ahab's long-suffering wife. Throughout the world, patrons sipping latte in Starbucks pay unwitting homage to the coffee-drinking first mate of the Pequod; outside the medieval Belgian city of Ghent, a favorite local brothel is called Moby Dick Fun Pub. The lead singer of the rock band Papa Roach has named himself Coby Dick, and, in imitation of what Melville calls Ahab's ''terrific, loud, animal sob,'' belts out, ''I am a mess! I've made a huge mess! I can't control myself.'' And if the first words of ''Moby-Dick,'' ''Call me Ishmael,'' are universally familiar, its last words -- then all collapsed, and the great shroud of the sea rolled on as it rolled 5,000 years ago'' -- have currency too: a reporter for Slate.com quoted them recently to describe Pamela Anderson's breasts after her implants were removed.</p>
        <p>As for Melville's standing in the academy, ''Moby-Dick'' is one of the few books whose reputation as a classic not only survived the so-called canon wars but has actually been enhanced. A new journal, Leviathan, is devoted solely to his work; the Melville Society is thriving, and there are conferences galore. Ever since the 1930's, when the poet and avid Melvillean Charles Olson, hoping to glimpse Melville's creative process, began searching for surviving volumes from his personal library (some had stayed in the family and were eventually donated to the Houghton Library at Harvard; others were sold by his wife to a Brooklyn bookseller), scholars have tried to track down every check mark, underlining and marginal jotting in every book whose pages he may have turned. In Olson's day, when comments in the margins were found to be erased, the only recourse was to turn the paper to and fro so that different rakings of light might reveal to the naked eye (aided, at best, by a magnifying glass) indentations left by the erased pencil. Today, Melville's copy of Thomas Beale's ''Natural History of the Sperm Whale,'' which he read while composing ''Moby-Dick,'' is laid out like the Shroud of Turin in the conservation laboratory of the Fogg Art Museum under an infrared camera capable of discerning microscopic traces of graphite left behind by the wielder of the eraser -- who, some think, may have been Melville himself.</p>
        <p>Within, and beyond, the academy, the resurgence of Melville from obscurity in his time into almost cult status in our own has been astonishing. It was led by such literary masters as D. H. Lawrence and E. M. Forster, who saw in ''Moby-Dick'' a work of startling modernity ahead of its time. Long before Joyce or Woolf made their formal innovations, here was a writer who jumped from omniscient to first-person to choral narration, who mixed the proper speech of well-bred officers with the obscene songs of illiterate sailors and, anticipating the modernist technique of stream-of-consciousness, wrote of repressed memory and sublimated desire as forces of the unconscious. By rendering in meticulous detail the art and craft of whaling, he paid homage to ordinary men engaged under duress in the dangerous work of cutting up majestic animals into commodities. Yet he also satisfied the human craving for an allegorical dimension to life -- for finding large meanings in small quotidian events -- without resting those meanings on religious beliefs that had become implausible already in his day.</p>
        <p>For modern readers, ''Moby-Dick'' forecast the future in which they found themselves living. Melville took as his subject the first international industry dominated by the United States, and thereby bore witness to the ''manifest destiny'' of a nation just beginning during his lifetime to grow from a continental into a world power. In recounting the love between an American boy (Ishmael) and a tattooed cannibal (Queequeg), he intimated, long before it was common to think so, that human sexuality ranges freely along a continuum of desire and cannot be contained within established norms. In his grisly account of the business of killing whales, he anticipated today's environmentalist indignation at people who have a purely instrumental relation to nature; but he also treated all pieties and pietists with proto-postmodern irony -- as when he asks, ''With what quill did the Secretary of the Society for the Suppression of Cruelty to Ganders formerly indite his circulars?'' And with eerie prescience, he foresaw in ''Moby-Dick'' the most gruesome phenomenon of modern times -- of which we have been so terribly reminded by recent events -- how a demagogue can fuse his personal need for vengeance with the popular will by promising his followers a huntable enemy in which evil was ''made practically assailable.''</p>
        <p>The superstitious sailors who regarded the great white whale as ''not only ubiquitous, but immortal (for immortality is but ubiquity in time)'' turn out to have been spectacularly right. Melville's brutal but ineffably sad masterpiece -- filled with the stench of rotting whale carcasses, yet lyrical and tender -- is one of those books from which the critic should step back and say, as Melville said of the sperm whale's brow, ''I but put that brow before you. Read it if you can.''</p>
        <p>ESSAY Andrew Delbanco's ''Writing New England: An Anthology from the Puritans to the Present,'' has just been published. He is at work on a book entitled ''Melville's World.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Andrew Delbanco's ''Writing New England: An Anthology from the Puritans to the Present,'' has just been published. He is at work on a book entitled ''Melville's World.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
