<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dance; Finding Their Focus Far From New York</title>
    <meta content="28REIT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/28/arts/dance/28REIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1337608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Garth Fagan Dance Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reiter, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Rochester</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Joyce Theater</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Fagan, Garth</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07EED91731F93BA15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1394" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dance; Finding Their Focus Far From New York</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Finding Their Focus Far From New York</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN REITER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reiter, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>ROCHESTER</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Susan Reiter article on Garth Fagan Dance Company of Rochester, which will be in New York City for annual two-week season at Joyce Theater; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THEY take to the stage like a breed apart: unusually fluid and contained, displaying their exemplary control and resilience with a distinctively cool yet intense focus. There is no mistaking Garth Fagan's dancers for those of any other company. As they run through his new ''Music of the Line/Words in the Shape,'' they display a finely honed virtuosity, encompassing elements of diverse dance techniques that Mr. Fagan has spent three decades melding into his own idiosyncratic style. Within that style, there is room for the dancers to be gracefully awkward, quietly meditative and exuberantly explosive. They connect deeply with the earth, but they can also seem calmly suspended in the air.</p>
        <p>When they speak about being part of Garth Fagan Dance, the company's members express a strong and deeply personal commitment to Mr. Fagan's work. An important aspect of that commitment involves living and working in this pleasant, manageable city of 220,000, which has been the company's home since 1970. Here, more than 300 miles north of the hub of dance activity in New York, they find, as Mr. Fagan has, a place both soothing and sophisticated, a suitable setting in which to work with the kind of focus and intensity that the company requires.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Garth Fagan's dancers commit themselves to living and working in Rochester, away from the hub of dance activity in New York City.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THEY take to the stage like a breed apart: unusually fluid and contained, displaying their exemplary control and resilience with a distinctively cool yet intense focus. There is no mistaking Garth Fagan's dancers for those of any other company. As they run through his new ''Music of the Line/Words in the Shape,'' they display a finely honed virtuosity, encompassing elements of diverse dance techniques that Mr. Fagan has spent three decades melding into his own idiosyncratic style. Within that style, there is room for the dancers to be gracefully awkward, quietly meditative and exuberantly explosive. They connect deeply with the earth, but they can also seem calmly suspended in the air.</p>
        <p>When they speak about being part of Garth Fagan Dance, the company's members express a strong and deeply personal commitment to Mr. Fagan's work. An important aspect of that commitment involves living and working in this pleasant, manageable city of 220,000, which has been the company's home since 1970. Here, more than 300 miles north of the hub of dance activity in New York, they find, as Mr. Fagan has, a place both soothing and sophisticated, a suitable setting in which to work with the kind of focus and intensity that the company requires.</p>
        <p>Beginning Tuesday they will be in New York for their annual two-week season at the Joyce Theater. The two programs span nearly two decades of Mr. Fagan's choreography, and feature the New York premiere of ''Music of the Line/Words in the Shape,'' set to both electronic and acoustic compositions by John Adams. Mr. Fagan has also responded to the events of Sept. 11 by reworking a meditative section of a 1998 dance into a piece titled ''In Memoriam: The Innocent, the Brave, the Hands, the Minds, All Mankind,'' dedicated to the victims and survivors of the attacks.</p>
        <p>On a brilliantly sunny late-September Sunday, the 11 dancers in the troupe arrived at the downtown studio to hone the new work, which had its premiere in June at the American Dance Festival in Durham, N.C. The abbreviated day was not part of their usual work schedule but an opportunity for some extra rehearsal before the next day's departure on a short tour. Instead of the regular two-hour class that begins full rehearsal days, the dancers spread out in the studio, an expansive space that was once a Knights of Columbus meeting hall, to warm up according to their individual needs. Between stretches, several discussed the particular challenges and rewards of dancing for Mr. Fagan.</p>
        <p>Company veterans -- and there are six whose tenure exceeds a decade -- tend to tell tales that reflect a similar sense of inevitability. At times when they were searching for meaningful dance experiences, initial encounters with Mr. Fagan's choreography clarified their futures -- sometimes before they even realized what was happening -- and led them to Rochester.</p>
        <p>Natalie Rogers, who joined the company in 1989 and quickly became one of its leading performers, was a Juilliard graduate who spent eight years as a freelance dancer in New York before becoming disillusioned with the scene. She moved to Texas and, while working there as a fitness trainer, saw Garth Fagan Dance perform. ''I knew instantly -- I saw my whole future in a flash,'' she said. ''I went backstage, introduced myself, and said, 'I have to study with you.' As soon as he said yes, I packed up everything I owned and moved to Rochester and never looked back. The work was exemplary. I knew inside that this was what I should be doing, because it challenges every aspect of yourself.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rogers, originally from Trinidad and Tobago, felt she ''needed to get back to a more personal type of environment.''</p>
        <p>''The advantage of being here is that we can concentrate,'' she continued. ''To do this type of dancing, you have to get rid of all your distractions. The more focus you have, the easier the work becomes.''</p>
        <p>Having assisted Mr. Fagan when he choreographed for companies like New York City Ballet and Alvin Ailey American Dance Theater, Ms. Rogers appreciated the rapport between professional dancers in New York. ''Here, we're kind of isolated in that sense,'' she said. ''But in a way we have to be, to get Garth's work in perspective, without being sidetracked.''</p>
        <p>Sharon Skepple, a company member since 1988, said: ''Garth knew what he was doing when he decided that Rochester would be the place to have a dance company. I understand that, from having gone back and forth to New York City. Distraction is not a bad thing, but it's there. If we didn't have this place, we would be amid the hustle and bustle, and that takes away a little from what we're trying to prepare. We can really put all our attention on the dancing -- on taking care of our bodies, our minds, and putting everything we have into the work.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Skepple, who is from the Virgin Islands, was a student at the North Carolina School of the Arts when she saw a video of the Fagan company in class. ''I knew I had to find these people,'' she said. ''I fell in love with the calmness, the fluidity of the bodies, the way they let the movement speak for itself.'' She found her way to a summer workshop with Mr. Fagan, and after one day he asked her when she would be finished with college. ''I told him, right now -- if you want me here, I'm out,'' she said, and before long she made the move.</p>
        <p>About a decade later, a student at Howard University had a similar epiphany while watching a Fagan video. ''A friend in the dance department had the 'Griot New York' tape,'' said Erin Barnett, one of the newer company dancers, who joined in 1999. ''That was my introduction to Garth Fagan Dance, and it changed my life. It combined every form of dance that I love. There was never another company I wanted to dance for. But it takes a special person. We have some people come and go; you know right away if this isn't the thing for you, because it's very demanding, and it takes sacrifice.''</p>
        <p>Chris Morrison, a Fagan dancer since 1990, was with the National Dance Theater Company of Jamaica when he first saw the company on a PBS special. That same year Mr. Fagan, who is originally from Jamaica, was visiting on vacation, and Mr. Morrison had the opportunity to approach him. ''Once I saw the work, I realized that was something I really wanted to aspire to,'' Mr. Morrison said. ''It didn't look like balletic movement, or Caribbean folk movement, or African movement, but it looked like all of these combined.''</p>
        <p>A couple of years as part of the New York dance scene convinced Mr. Morrison that his artistic destiny lay with Mr. Fagan. ''I looked at other work, but I didn't see that ease of movement, that centered, internal, spiritual thing I saw in Garth's work,'' he said. Encountering Mr. Fagan during a Joyce season, he soon came here for the type of informal tryout the company tends to use rather than mass auditions.</p>
        <p>''I came up for a weekend in May and by June I had moved here,'' Mr. Morrison said. ''I like the fact that Rochester is so far north, because I get a chance to concentrate on my work. I have so many friends living in New York who go from company to company. They never really learn a technique or hone whatever it is they're working on. I've gotten the chance to do that here -- to learn, to really understand this technique.''</p>
        <p>While his devoted dancers can appreciate Rochester's geographic and psychic distance from New York, it is not for everyone, Mr. Fagan acknowledged. ''It's a very sophisticated city, as far as quality of life goes, but if they're looking for life in the big city, this is not it,'' he said. ''They've got to be pretty centered and focused to want to do this.''</p>
        <p>Susan Reiter's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the Australian dance company Chunky Move.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Susan Reiter's most recent article for Arts &amp; Leisure was about the Australian dance company Chunky Move.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
