<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Richter's Hard Work Allows Rangers to Snatch a Victory</title>
    <meta content="28RANG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/28/sports/hockey/28RANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1337977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boston Bruins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Boston Bruins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Boston</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Rangers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Richter, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E5DF1630F93BA15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Richter's Hard Work Allows Rangers to Snatch a Victory</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Richter's Hard Work Allows Rangers to Snatch a Victory</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Oct. 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers defeat Boston Bruins, 2-1, Boston; photo (M)1</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It seemed as if it would take a shutout from Mike Richter for the Rangers to snap an ugly three-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Richter came within 4 minutes 59 seconds of accomplishing just that tonight. But before Richter, the Rangers' 35-year-old goaltender, could close out the team's first shutout since Feb. 26, 1999, the Rangers allowed a power-play goal to Boston's Sergei Samsonov.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Richter came within 4 minutes 59 seconds of accomplishing a shutout, but the Rangers had to battle in overtime to top the Bruins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It seemed as if it would take a shutout from Mike Richter for the Rangers to snap an ugly three-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Richter came within 4 minutes 59 seconds of accomplishing just that tonight. But before Richter, the Rangers' 35-year-old goaltender, could close out the team's first shutout since Feb. 26, 1999, the Rangers allowed a power-play goal to Boston's Sergei Samsonov.</p>
        <p>Finally, Theo Fleury put the slide to rest by scoring with 24.2 seconds left in overtime, on the rush off a pass from Brian Leetch. The Rangers eked out a 2-1 victory in a game the Bruins dominated from the start.</p>
        <p>It was the first home loss in five games this season for Boston (5-3-2-1).</p>
        <p>Only Richter's outstanding play -- he stopped 45 shots as the Rangers were outshot, 46-28 -- enabled the Rangers to even their record to 5-5-1-0 with their third overtime victory. But that was hardly surprising. The Rangers' goaltenders, Richter and the 18-year-old rookie Dan Blackburn, have been their only consistent bright spots this season.</p>
        <p>Without Richter's efforts, the Rangers could have easily given up at least five goals for the fourth consecutive game.</p>
        <p>''No one should walk out of here thinking we would ever be in this game without Ricky,'' the Rangers' Eric Lindros said.</p>
        <p>Coach Ron Low said he was happy with his players' commitment against the Bruins and praised his goalie. ''It was a great game by Richter,'' Low said. ''We really needed that.''</p>
        <p>Fleury has three goals this season, and two of them have won games in overtime. That helped make up for the Rangers' continued weak performance on the power play: they were 0 for 6 tonight and have not scored in their past 25 power plays.</p>
        <p>Fleury said the goal really was not his, that Leetch's pass went off the stick of the Bruins' Brian Rolston.</p>
        <p>''I told the referee it was Leetch's goal,'' Fleury said, ''but he just shrugged.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers were reeling from three consecutive losses in which they were outscored by an aggregate of 15-4. But defensemen Igor Ulanov and Dale Purinton returned from their seven-game suspensions for cross-checking hits to the heads of two Washington players on Oct. 10. As a result, the Rangers went with 11 forwards and 7 defensemen, and Low mixed and matched his forward combinations and defensive pairings all night.</p>
        <p>Earlier in the day, the Rangers reassigned two of their youngest players, the 22-year-old defenseman Peter Smrek and the 21-year-old forward Barrett Heisten, to Hartford of the American Hockey League.</p>
        <p>The Rangers recalled forward Richard Scott from Hartford and placed defenseman Dave Karpa (shoulder) on injured reserve, retroactive to last Tuesday. Tonight's game was the first in the N.H.L. for the 23-year-old Scott, who had no points and 55 penalty minutes in 7 games at Hartford this season.</p>
        <p>With Scott and Purinton in the lineup, Low was hoping the Rangers would play with a little more snarl. ''I haven't liked our response to anything that's gone on this season,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Through the first two periods, however, most of the Rangers did not play physically.</p>
        <p>Once again, the Rangers were thoroughly outplayed in the first period. They did not test Boston goalie Byron Dafoe until defenseman Darren Van Impe's one-timer, which Dafoe gloved 17 minutes 32 seconds into the game.</p>
        <p>Through their first 11 games, the Rangers have yet to take a lead into the second period. There was a silver lining tonight, though. Despite being outshot by 12-5 in the first period, the Rangers did not surrender a goal, the first time they did not allow an opponent to score in the opening period all season. For only the fifth time, the Rangers did not enter the second period trailing.</p>
        <p>Even though the Rangers did not play significantly better in the second period, they did something they had accomplished only once before this season: they scored the game's first goal.</p>
        <p>It came on a screened wrist shot by Andreas Johansson from above the right-wing circle. The last time the Rangers had a 1-0 lead was in their home opener on Oct. 7, a 5-4 overtime victory over Buffalo.</p>
        <p>Johansson's second goal of the season came at 3:28 of the second period, off a Mark Messier pass. Johansson had used Jozef Stumpel to screen Dafoe. Dafoe never saw the puck, which whizzed past him on the stick side.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
