<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Through the Grapevine</title>
    <meta content="28DINE$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1337732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Foro Italico (Elmwood Park, Nj, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corcoran, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E5DC1331F93BA15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1096" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Through the Grapevine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CORCORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Corcoran, David</byline>
      <dateline>ELMWOOD PARK</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Corcoran reviews Foro Italico restaurant in Elmwood Park, NJ; photo (M)7</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE best thing about this otherwise unremarkable restaurant is its wine list. If that sounds like faint praise, read on.</p>
        <p>If you go, you will want to consider a designated driver. You will not want to have other plans for the evening. And you will want to spend some quality time with Foro Italico's wine guy, Joseph Muscaglione.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE best thing about this otherwise unremarkable restaurant is its wine list. If that sounds like faint praise, read on.</p>
        <p>If you go, you will want to consider a designated driver. You will not want to have other plans for the evening. And you will want to spend some quality time with Foro Italico's wine guy, Joseph Muscaglione.</p>
        <p>Mr. Muscaglione, 38, is the stepson of the chef and owner, Rosario Sangiorgio. He was born in this country but spent seven years in Italy, mastering the arcane byways and crevices of its wine industry. He did so well that he became the wine buyer for the renowned Mario Batali, of Babbo in Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>For the past three years Mr. Muscaglione has been developing one of the state's most unusual wine lists. What sets it apart is not the $1,100 bottle of Barbaresco or even the relatively short but lovingly assembled selection of wines from regions as diverse as Oregon, New Zealand, Sicily and the Rhône Valley. The most impressive thing about this list is the full page marked, simply, ''$15 Reds'' and ''$15 Whites.''</p>
        <p>Many of the wines on this page are unusual, like a grenache from southeastern Australia, a pinotage from South Africa, a vermentino from Sardinia. A few are old friends. What unites them is a rare determination to demystify the wine experience, to make it accessible to the 99 percent of us to whom wine is a few familiar, if boring, islands in a vast, forbidding sea.</p>
        <p>At Foro Italico, wine becomes a communal experience, made comforting by the low financial stakes. These are good wines, not great ones. But at $15, what's the risk in ordering a bottle you've never heard of?</p>
        <p>At one meal our table ordered four entrees: linguine marechiara, rack of lamb, lamb chops and sausage with broccoli rape. In most restaurants, my wine strategy at this point would be to bail -- to let my fellow diners fend for themselves, choosing from whatever the bar is pouring by the glass. Here, the diversity of dishes became a challenge for the wine steward. Mr. Muscaglione rattled off the pros and cons of half a dozen choices on the $15 list, then urged us to try a red, the Villa del Borgo refosco from Friuli, in Northern Italy. It was as advertised. Clean, focused, acidic, it had something to contribute to each of our dishes. As we complimented Mr. Muscaglione for having a wine to suit every dish, a fellow diner remarked dryly, ''But then you'd probably have a wine for scrambled eggs.''</p>
        <p>The wine guy didn't miss a beat. ''Scrambled eggs?'' he replied. ''Get a sauvignon blanc.''</p>
        <p>Wine this good deserves a better ride from the kitchen. On each visit, our hopes were raised by a hearty giveaway appetizer -- bruschetta one night, potatoes and hot peppers in a potent, earthy broth on another -- but were steadily let down as the evening went on.</p>
        <p>The combination of roasted potatoes, fennel and oranges with the grilled cuttlefish called seppie sounded irresistible, but the dish was soggy and bland. The same fate befell another enticing combination, a tall, cylindrical lentil salad with beets and goat cheese. Lacking nearly enough beets or cheese, the dish proved less a salad than a leaning tower of lentils. An appetizer portion of gonfalone, ravioli with a filling of shrimp, sun-dried tomatoes and arugula, tasted of overripe seafood and little else.</p>
        <p>These lapses were all the more disappointing when measured against some excellent appetizers, an unequal distribution of wealth that set off pangs of jealousy at our table. Ditalini, the tiny elbow pasta, came in a lovely, meaty broth accented with plenty of sweet fresh peas. Bluepoint oysters were baked under a buttery breading that didn't conceal their freshness and brine. Mussels, also fresh and tender, bathed in a garlic-scented liquor. And while these successes might suggest that simpler is better here, the kitchen surprised us with a rich, comforting eggplant napoleon with layers of spinach, mozzarella and ricotta over a good tomato sauce.</p>
        <p>Main courses were a similar patchwork of hits and misses. Rigatoni came in a robust tomato sauce with plenty of hot pepper, sausage and basil. Four lamb chops, tasty if a little tough, were accurately broiled and set atop a sweet caponata.</p>
        <p>But linguine marechiara, with tender shrimp and clams, was undone by the sting of salt in its broth, and rack of lamb by the sogginess of its breading. Four thick slices of filet mignon sat under a beckoning mantle of wild mushrooms, but the thick brown sauce tasted disconcertingly canned. Swordfish in a fine, assertive Livornese sauce was soft, as if it had sat around a day too long. And a Texas-size veal chop should have been better trimmed; its coating of fontina cheese concealed unappetizing pockets of fat.</p>
        <p>Except for a subpar crème brûlée with a nasty topping of overburned sugar, desserts were fine, in particular a warm, dark flourless chocolate cake, a cranberry-poached pear, strawberries with creamy cold zabaglione, and an espresso-scented flan.</p>
        <p>On both of our visits, Foro Italico had the slightly forlorn air of a place that wasn't clicking. Even on a Saturday night, many tables were empty; on a Wednesday, most of them were. The all-white décor looked tired. In an interview, Mr. Muscaglione acknowledged that the restaurant was having a hard time staying afloat. After 17 years in Elmwood Park -- 14 of them as a more mainstream place on Route 46 -- the owners are still trying to find an audience that will respond to a smart, well-tuned combination of food and wine.</p>
        <p>They should hang in there. I suspect that with a little more consistency in the kitchen, word of mouth will take over and turn Foro Italico into the busy, exciting destination its owners are dreaming about.</p>
        <p>Foro Italico  235 Elm Street, Elmwood Park  (201) 796-2282</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE Subdued contemporary Italian.  SERVICE Professional, and better than that when it comes to wine.  SMOKING Allowed at the bar.  WINE LIST Exceptionally intelligent and balanced, with a full page of bargains.  RECOMMENDED DISHES Oysters, mussels, ditalini with peas, eggplant napoleon; lamb chops, rigatoni Calabrese, sausage with broccoli rape; chocolate cake, poached pear, flan.  PRICE RANGE Appetizers: $4.95 to $9.95; pastas and entrees: $11.95 to $28.95. Desserts: $7.  HOURS Open daily, 5 to 11 p.m.  CREDIT CARDS All major.  RESERVATIONS Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS On one level.  RATINGS Poor, Fair, Satisfactory, Good, Very Good, Excellent, Extraordinary.  Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
