<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sorenstam Outshined By Winner And Wie</title>
    <meta content="31LPGA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/31/sports/golf/31LPGA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1476986"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kraft Nabisco Championship</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meunier-Lebouc, Patricia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arkush, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sorenstam, Annika</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Meunier, Patricia</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Wie, Michelle</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3D71239F932A05750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sorenstam Outshined By Winner And Wie</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sorenstam Outshined in Kraft Nabisco Championship</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL ARKUSH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arkush, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>RANCHO MIRAGE, Calif., March 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Meunier-Lebouc wins Kraft Nabisco Championship (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There will surely be better days for Michelle Wie, who showed that she was 13.</p>
        <p>There will also be better days for Annika Sorenstam, who showed again that she was vulnerable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Patricia Meunier-Lebouc, a 30-year-old Frenchwoman, held off Annika Sorenstam by a stroke to capture the L.P.G.A's first major of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There will surely be better days for Michelle Wie, who showed that she was 13.</p>
        <p>There will also be better days for Annika Sorenstam, who showed again that she was vulnerable.</p>
        <p>But there may never be a better day for Patricia Meunier-Lebouc, who showed that she could win a major championship against the best players in the world.</p>
        <p>With a solid back nine at Mission Hills Country Club, Meunier-Lebouc held off Sorenstam by a stroke today to capture the Kraft Nabisco Championship, the L.P.G.A's first major of the season.</p>
        <p>Meunier-Lebouc, a 30-year-old Frenchwoman, closed with a one-over-par 73 for a total of seven-under 281, edging Sorenstam, who shot a 71. The rookie Lorena Ochoa was third, two shots back.</p>
        <p>Wie, an eighth-grader from Hawaii who seized the spotlight this weekend, faltered with a four-over 76 to finish at even par for the tournament, tying for ninth. Playing in the final group in her first appearance in a major, Wie managed to keep things together with an even-par 36 on the front, then gave away four shots on the back. Wie, who had only one birdie all day, three-putted Nos. 12, 14 and 16.</p>
        <p>Meunier-Lebouc started the day with a three-stroke advantage, but was passed when Sorenstam birdied No. 12.</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, the two-time defending champion, seemed poised to make it three straight. But her three-putt bogey on No. 13, coupled with Meunier-Lebouc's 18-foot birdie putt from the fringe, resulted in a two-shot swing that gave Meunier-Lebouc a lead she never relinquished.</p>
        <p>She parred the next four holes while Sorenstam, who bogeyed No. 14, failed to apply pressure down the stretch for the second tournament in a row. She tied for third last week in Phoenix, finishing four strokes behind Se Ri Pak.</p>
        <p>After signing her scorecard, Meunier-Lebouc, along with her husband, Antoine, and her caddie, took the traditional plunge into the greenside lake.</p>
        <p>The triumph is her second since joining the L.P.G.A. Tour in 2001. She was also a member of the victorious 2000 European Solheim Cup team.</p>
        <p>''I just can still not believe it, but I did it,'' said Meunier-Lebouc, who earned $240,000. ''That's why my husband came to me and said: 'You did it. You just did it.' And I said, 'Yes.' I felt so good.''</p>
        <p>Sorenstam, who was unable to break 71 after opening the tournament with a 68, was a bit frustrated with her inability to make putts.</p>
        <p>''Unfortunately, I made two mistakes on 13 and 14,'' said Sorenstam, who won 11 Tour events in 2002. ''After that I was just trying to chase her the last few holes. I tried all week and have not made a lot of putts. I've hit a lot of lips and sometimes at these tournaments, you need some good breaks.''</p>
        <p>For Wie, who has been on her spring break, it was a week that she and many spectators will not soon forget. After making the cut with rounds of 72 and 74, she came through with a brilliant six-under 66 on Saturday, tying the lowest score for an amateur in an L.P.G.A. major. Remarkably, as she headed to the back nine, she still had a chance to win the tournament, trailing by three.</p>
        <p>''I think I played pretty well all day,'' said Wie, whose father, B. J., was her caddie. ''I think I played extra well on the third day, so I was really happy about that score.''</p>
        <p>The 6-foot Wie also picked up another admirer.</p>
        <p>''She has a lot of talent,'' Sorenstam said. ''She has a wonderful swing. She has a great future ahead of her.''</p>
        <p>Another with a great future is Ochoa, the clear favorite to be the Tour's rookie of the year. She was in excellent shape to win the tournament until she shot a 42 on the back nine on Saturday, putting her seven shots behind Meunier-Lebouc. But with a four-under 68, Ochoa, a native of Mexico, bounced back.</p>
        <p>''I'm extremely happy with the way I finished,'' Ochoa, who birdied Nos. 16 and 17, said. ''This will give me a lot of confidence.''</p>
        <p>But the day belonged to Meunier-Lebouc, whose previous victory came in last year's State Farm Classic.</p>
        <p>''It's an achievement,'' she said. ''I think that's how you call it. I really work hard and give a lot to be able to be coming here, competing on the L.P.G.A. If it's my day, I deserve it. So if it's my day, I'll take it. It gives me even more motivation to work and just keep going.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
