<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Purchasers Find Drop In Growth</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19881004T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="184735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRIAL PRODUCTION INDEX</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PURCHASING MANAGEMENT, NATIONAL ASSN OF</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EICHENWALD, KURT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DC113BF930A35753C1A96E948260" item-length="705" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Purchasers Find Drop In Growth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KURT EICHENWALD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">EICHENWALD, KURT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The nation's economy grew in September at the slowest pace in six months, the National Association of Purchasing Management said in a monthly report that is scheduled to be released today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The nation's economy grew in September at the slowest pace in six months, the National Association of Purchasing Management said in a monthly report that is scheduled to be released today.</p>
        <p>The nation's economy grew in September at the slowest pace in six months, the National Association of Purchasing Management said in a monthly report that is scheduled to be released today.</p>
        <p>Signs of slower growth are welcome by many economists and Washington officials, who have expressed fears that the rapid pace earlier this year could lead to an overheated economy, increasing inflation. To slow the growth rate, the Federal Reserve increased the discount rate by half a point, to 6.5 percent, on Aug. 9. Low Growth in Production</p>
        <p>Production continued to grow at a healthy pace, but the rate of increase was the lowest in five months. Orders for new exports, a key element of recent economic growth, grew faster than in August, but less than they had during most of the year, the report said.</p>
        <p>Prices continued to increase, but at their lowest rate since May 1987. Employment also increased, for the fourth month, by a small amount.</p>
        <p>The report surveys managers at more than 250 companies representing 21 industries. Economists consider its findings to be a preliminary indicator of economic performance.</p>
        <p>The association's composite index, reflecting the declines for September, slipped to 54.8 percent, compared with 56.2 percent in August. It was the third monthly decline for the index. An index above 50 percent indicates that the economy is expanding, while a reading below that implies a contraction, the group says. Nine-Month Average at 56.1%</p>
        <p>September was the 26th consecutive month that the index, which is seasonally adjusted, exceeded 50 percent. The September results bring the average for the first nine months of 1988 to 56.1 percent.</p>
        <p>Robert J. Bretz, the chairman of the association's business survey committee and the director of materials management at Pitney Bowes Inc., said that, despite the September figures, the group was expecting continued economic growth.</p>
        <p>''Virtually all indicators confirm a slowing growth in the economy,'' Mr. Bretz said. ''Nonetheless, the high level of new orders suggests continued growth in October.''</p>
        <p>New orders rose in September for the 40th straight month, after normal seasonal variations were taken into account. But, reflecting the slowing in the economy, the index for new orders fell to 58.4 percent, from 59.9 percent the previous month. 34% Say Orders Are Up Thirty-four percent of the purchasers reported an increase in new orders, and 11 percent reported a decline. The others reported no change.</p>
        <p>Of the association's members that export goods, 27 percent reported higher export orders, up from 20 percent in August but much lower than the 37.8 percent for the previous seven months. Six percent reported lower export orders, an increase from 4 percent in August.</p>
        <p>The report also indicated that the rate of growth in production slowed in August. The index for production fell to 56 percent, from 58.2 percent the previous month, and is at its lowest level since March. Twenty-six percent of the managers reported higher production, while 12 percent said that production was lower.</p>
        <p>Inventories, which had risen significantly in July, declined in September for the second month, according to the report. The index for inventory was 49.6 percent in September.</p>
        <p>Purchasers continued to report slower deliveries by vendors. For the 24th straight month, the index for vendor deliveries exceeded 50 percent, which the report says is an indication that the economy is expanding. The rate of slowing has decreased during the last three months. Slower Price Increases</p>
        <p>Prices rose for the 26th consecutive month, after seasonal variations are considered. But the report said that prices were increasing at a slower pace.</p>
        <p>The index for prices fell to 72.2 percent in September, from 78.7 percent in August, and is at its lowest level since March. The report described the results as ''a welcome sign of abating inflation.''</p>
        <p>The report said that the prices of aluminum, steel, grain-related foods, sugar, vegetable oils, apples, bearings and fuel oil had risen in September. Also showing cost increases were polyethylene, caustic soda and vinyl fabric.</p>
        <p>Shortages were reported in goods that included aluminum, steel, caustic soda and ethylene.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 4, 1988, Tuesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>A table in Business Day yesterday listing current interest rates misstated the prime rate and the discount rate. The prime rate, which banks charge on loans to large corporations, is 10 percent. The discount rate, which the Federal Reserve charges on loans to depository institutions, is 6 1/2 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 4, 1988, Tuesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>A table in Business Day yesterday listing current interest rates misstated the prime rate and the discount rate. The prime rate, which banks charge on loans to large corporations, is 10 percent. The discount rate, which the Federal Reserve charges on loans to depository institutions, is 6 1/2 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
