<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>H-BOMBS DREAMS</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="325652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RHODES, RICHARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLUMBERG, STANLEY A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PANOS, LOUIS G</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EDWARD TELLER: GIANT OF THE GOLDEN AGE OF PHYSICS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDD113CF932A25751C0A966958260" item-length="2108" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>H-BOMBS DREAMS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD RHODES; Richard Rhode's books include ''The Making of the Atomic Bomb,'' for which he won a Pulitzer Prize.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RHODES, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>EDWARD TELLER</p>
        <p>Giant of the Golden Age of Physics.</p>
        <p>By Stanley A. Blumberg and Louis G. Panos.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 306 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Charles Scribner's Sons. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>EDWARD TELLER</p>
        <p>Giant of the Golden Age of Physics.</p>
        <p>By Stanley A. Blumberg and Louis G. Panos.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 306 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Charles Scribner's Sons. $24.95.</p>
        <p>EDWARD TELLER</p>
        <p>Giant of the Golden Age of Physics.</p>
        <p>By Stanley A. Blumberg and Louis G. Panos.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 306 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Charles Scribner's Sons. $24.95.</p>
        <p>Edward Teller is the Richard Nixon of American science. Dark, brooding, rummaging indefatigably among apocalyptic forces, he has influenced our lives even more profoundly, and across a longer span of years, than the former President has. In 1939, Mr. Teller was one of the trio of Hungarian emigres who encouraged Albert Einstein to alert Franklin D. Roosevelt that it was possible to harness the power of nuclear fission to make a devastating new explosive. In 1944 and 1945 he helped solve the problem of detonating plutonium efficiently, a solution demonstrated implacably at Nagasaki.</p>
        <p>He championed the hydrogen bomb from its early theoretical development in 1941 and 1942 through its first full, megaton-scale realization at Eniwetok atoll in 1952. Mr. Teller's secret disclosures to the F.B.I. in 1952 were the basis for the most serious charges J. Robert Oppenheimer faced at his security hearing before the Atomic Energy Commission in 1954. And Mr. Teller's testimony at that hearing supported the subsequent denial of Oppenheimer's security clearance.</p>
        <p>The exceptional safety record of the United States' commercial nuclear reactors owes much to Mr. Teller's postwar leadership. In the 1970's he drafted a grandiose scheme of coal gasification and reactor proliferation for Nelson Rockefeller, which would later become Gerald Ford's project for energy independence. And in 1983 Mr. Teller used his authority as a scientist to assure Ronald Reagan that strategic defense was feasible. Indeed, as the authors of this slapdash new biography emphasize, Mr. Teller has been ''the dominant figure in the development of the strategic defense initiative.''</p>
        <p>Stanley A. Blumberg, the coauthor, with Gwinn Owens, of ''Energy and Conflict,'' another biography of Mr. Teller, and Louis G. Panos, a columnist for The Baltimore Sun, have patched together a slavish, misinformed apologia that relies almost entirely on secondary sources and self-serving interviews with Mr. Teller and his friends. Its sole virtue is that it reveals more of the physicist than he has chosen to reveal before. Though he professes to abhor secrecy, he is as much a riddle wrapped in a mystery inside an enigma as was Stalinist Russia. Any revelations, however inadvertent, must be welcomed.</p>
        <p>Garbled stories abound in ''Edward Teller,'' far too many to list. Suffice it to say that most of the physics and many of the historical details are simply wrong. For instance, even though the authors claim that Mr. Teller was among those physicists who ''pleaded'' for demonstrating the atomic bomb to the Japanese rather than dropping it on them in a surprise attack, they later quote without comment Mr. Teller's statement, in a July 1945 letter to his Hungarian colleague Leo Szilard, that ''actual combat use might even be the best thing.''</p>
        <p>Worse than the mistakes are the myths the book perpetuates about the history of the hydrogen bomb - most notably the myth that Oppenheimer conspired to delay American development of the hydrogen bomb, thereby allowing the Soviets to get there first. Mr. Blumberg and Mr. Panos have assembled an anthology of hearsay testimony to argue that the Soviet Union beat the United States to the hydrogen bomb. But the official history of the Atomic Energy Commission, written with full access to the secret record, emphatically asserts the contrary: ''The Soviet scientists had not detonated a 'true' hydrogen weapon within nine months after [the first megaton-scale American test in 1952] . They had not developed an airborne thermonuclear weapon before the United States. And it was not true that the Americans had taken the wrong path in using deuterium [in early tests]  while the Russians had struck out directly for the more practical lithium-deuteride approach.''</p>
        <p>Work toward an American H-bomb actually originated in September 1941 when Enrico Fermi suggested to Edward Teller the idea of using nuclear fission to kindle a thermonuclear explosion. Fermi thought that the heat of fission might energize atoms of heavy hydrogen (deuterium or tritium) enough to fuse them, releasing vastly more energy than fission alone. In Mr. Teller this idea found a dedicated advocate. The following summer, he promoted it at a conference on atomic-bomb physics that was organized by Oppenheimer at the University of California at Berkeley. Since the proposed H-bomb offered the possibility that the destructive power of a fission bomb could be multiplied with cheap and plentiful deuterium (rather than expensive and rare uranium) it captured the attention of the senior physicists for most of the conference.</p>
        <p>A letter from Mr. Teller to Oppenheimer, published in a collection of Oppenheimer's correspondence, shows that the conferees discussed using solid and compact lithium deuteride as a hydrogen bomb fuel. Until after the 1952 American test, researchers chose to work with bulky liquid deuterium instead to simplify their experiments. Mr. Blumberg and Mr. Panos argue, to the contrary, that the idea of using lithium deuteride to fuel a hydrogen bomb was a Soviet breakthrough, and Mr. Teller claims here that he first thought of using lithium deuteride in 1950.</p>
        <p>There are many other blatant inconsistencies in ''Edward Teller.'' His biographers note that Mr. Teller complained to them that ''we actually didn't'' work on the fusion bomb at Los Alamos, and they claim that he was ''denied'' that work. But then, a few pages later, the authors acknowledge that Oppenheimer in fact ''encouraged'' Mr. Teller and his group to work on the H-bomb. In fact, a cryogenic factory to liquefy deuterium went up at Los Alamos in 1943 and the Manhattan Project dedicated some of its precious reactor time to making tritium for H-bomb research before the end of the war.</p>
        <p>The authors quote with approval Mr. Teller's assertion, at the Oppenheimer hearings, that if the original Los Alamos staff had worked on the thermonuclear problem immediately after the war ''we would have had the [H-] bomb in 1947.'' But, in 1947, in a secret review of H-bomb research, Mr. Teller himself recommended postponing, ''for approximately two years,'' the decision about which of several H-bomb designs to pursue, pending development of a digital computer powerful enough to calculate the weapon's complicated hydrodynamics.</p>
        <p>Particularly reprehensible is the authors' attempt to minimize Mr. Teller's role in the defamation of Oppenheimer. Mr. Blumberg and Mr. Panos assert that ''Teller was not involved in the years-long investigation of Oppenheimer, was never asked his opinion of Oppenheimer's loyalty until the time of the hearing, and never expressed agreement with the basic accusation against Oppenheimer.'' Thus, the authors completely overlook two secret interviews that Mr. Teller gave the F.B.I. in May 1952 (which were made public under the Freedom of Information Act in 1977 and discussed subsequently in both scholarly and popular periodicals). During those interviews Mr. Teller charged Oppenheimer with opposing and working to delay development of the H-bomb and vowed, in the F.B.I.'s paraphrase, to ''do most anything to see [Oppenheimer]  separated from [his advisory position within the Atomic Energy Commission] .'' Mr. Teller's secret accusations became the basis for the seven most devastating of the 38 charges the A.E.C. brought against Oppenheimer in 1954 when it lifted his security clearance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blumberg and Mr. Panos also uncritically accept Mr. Teller's claim that he intended to testify in Oppenheimer's favor until a last-minute revelation by the prosecutor convinced him of Oppenheimer's duplicity. In fact, Mr. Teller had already committed himself to attacking Oppenheimer. The Nobel Prize-winning physicist Hans Bethe and his wife, Rose, have reported spending hours before the hearing trying to talk Mr. Teller out of doing so, an assertion that Freeman Dyson corroborates in his book ''Disturbing the Universe.'' And six days before Mr. Teller testified, an A.E.C. public-information officer who visited him reported in a memorandum to the chairman of the A.E.C., ''Teller feels deeply that [Oppenheimer's]  'unfrocking' must be done or else - regardless of the outcome of the current hearings - scientists may lose their enthusiasm for the [nuclear weapons]  program.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Blumberg and Mr. Panos say that when Mr. Teller did testify against Oppenheimer he never explicitly called Oppenheimer a security risk. But Mr. Teller's testimony that he ''would feel personally more secure if public matters would rest in other hands'' had the same destructive effect.</p>
        <p>The authors overlook another well-known and crucial episode in the H-bomb story. To pull together wartime research on the Super (as his original design for the H-bomb was called), Mr. Teller headed a conference at Los Alamos in April 1946. Among the participants were the mathematician Stanislaw Ulam and the theoretical physicists Robert Serber, Hans Bethe and Klaus Fuchs. The following autumn Mr. Teller called together a committee to prepare a report on the conference. The draft submitted to the committee asserted that his design was ''on the whole workable'' or could be made ''feasible'' with ''simple modifications.'' Mr. Serber, and perhaps others as well, found the draft unacceptably optimistic and proposed major changes. Mr. Teller ignored the recommendations and promulgated his self-serving draft, borrowing his colleagues' authority to bolster it. His strategy worked. That document strengthened Mr. Teller's campaign, after the Soviet Union tested its first atomic bomb in the summer of 1949, to persuade the Truman Administration to push H-bomb research.</p>
        <p>The information Klaus Fuchs gleaned from the Super conference and transmitted to the Soviet Union may have been misleading and may thus have delayed its H-bomb program. But more serious from an American point of view is the certainty that Edward Teller, according to Hans Bethe, led the United States ''into an adventurous program on the basis of calculations which he himself must have known to have been very incomplete.'' Mr. Teller's classical Super was indeed a bad design. As the Columbia University physicist I. I. Rabi would later tell Mr. Blumberg and Mr. Panos with revulsion, and as they report here, Mr. Teller's efforts caused the United States to announce to the world that it was going to build a new and threatening strategic weapon which, in fact, it did not know how to build, thereby laying down ''a challenge to the Soviet Union'' that constituted ''an extreme danger to the United States.''</p>
        <p>Teller's reckless advocacy of his Super design - his trading on his reputation as a scientist to advance his personal ambitions - set a pattern he would repeat in later years. In 1983, for example, Mr. Teller assured Ronald Reagan that an antimissile defense was feasible based on his own assessment of the practicality of laser weaponry. As the authors report, Roy D. Woodruff, the physicist who directed the laser research at the Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, subsequently challenged Mr. Teller's judgment as ''overly optimistic and technically incorrect.'' However, the President believed Mr. Teller, and on that authority, proposed the Strategic Defense Initiative.</p>
        <p>Though the biography fails to examine them, two peculiar defects in Mr. Teller's character appear to have driven him to such extremes: a terror of Russia that is irrational enough to be termed clinical, and a corresponding grandiosity that makes him believe that anything is possible and nothing is unethical in the pursuit of an ever more elusive security.</p>
        <p>The new knowledge of how to release nuclear energy permanently changed the political life of the world. Indeed, the recent dramatic changes in Eastern Europe arguably followed directly from the stalemate that the fear of nuclear destruction imposed. Yet few of the scientists who figured in a major way in the development of nuclear weapons have yet received first-class, full-scale biographical treatment of their own. That delinquency will soon be addressed. Martin J. Sherwin is finishing a biography of J. Robert Oppenheimer; William Lanouette and Bela Silard have just completed one of Leo Szilard. After his extraordinary work on Albert Einstein, Abraham Pais is preparing to give us Niels Bohr. Hans Bethe, Enrico Fermi, Ernest O. Lawrence, I. I. Rabi and Andrei Sakharov, among others, still await full, objective revelation. So does Edward Teller.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
