<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All About/In-Store Promotions; Influencing Shoppers During the Moment of Decision</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="467549"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RABINOVITZ, JONATHAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D61039F93BA2575BC0A967958260" item-length="1645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All About/In-Store Promotions; Influencing Shoppers During the Moment of Decision</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN RABINOVITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RABINOVITZ, JONATHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everybody is trying to cash in on the fast-growing trend toward in-store promotions. Supermarkets are charging fees to place these sales displays in their aisles. Display companies, many of them bought by advertising agencies in recent years, are charging food manufacturers to design and produce campaigns. And venture capitalists are investing in new technologies to get in on the burst of interest in the activity. Known as supermarket point-of-purchase advertising and promotion, the technique uses high and low technology, from video terminals to hand-out coupons, to communicate sales messages and influence buying habits.</p>
        <p>Food manufacturers see these promotions, which often play on people's impulses, as a quick fix for sagging sales. And with thousands of new products introduced each year -- 1,837 in July alone, according to Gorman's New Product News, an supermarket industry magazine -- marketers are fighting for ways to keep their products from getting lost.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everybody is trying to cash in on the fast-growing trend toward in-store promotions. Supermarkets are charging fees to place these sales displays in their aisles. Display companies, many of them bought by advertising agencies in recent years, are charging food manufacturers to design and produce campaigns. And venture capitalists are investing in new technologies to get in on the burst of interest in the activity. Known as supermarket point-of-purchase advertising and promotion, the technique uses high and low technology, from video terminals to hand-out coupons, to communicate sales messages and influence buying habits.</p>
        <p>Food manufacturers see these promotions, which often play on people's impulses, as a quick fix for sagging sales. And with thousands of new products introduced each year -- 1,837 in July alone, according to Gorman's New Product News, an supermarket industry magazine -- marketers are fighting for ways to keep their products from getting lost.</p>
        <p>For the nation's supermarket chains, which charge for the displays placed on their floors, this form of advertising and promotion has been a boon. A growing share of the money that food manufacturers would have spent on other advertising media, like television, radio and newspapers, is now being spent to put displays inside stores. For example, of the millions of dollars to be spent next month by the M.&amp; M. Mars Company on its annual Halloween campaign, slightly more than half will be spent inside the stores on displays and renting space.</p>
        <p>Practitioners of the in-store arts predict solid growth for their medium. To back up their argument, they refer to the research findings of the Point of Purchase Advertising Institute, an industry association in Englewood, N.J., that says 66 percent of all buying decisions are made after the consumer enters the supermarket.  The Medium Grows  A Bigger Share of the Ad Pie</p>
        <p>It is difficult to calculate exactly how much is spent on in-store promotions, analysts say, since promotional expenditures are often lumped in with other costs in a company's marketing budget. Most analysts, however, agree that the in-store promotion and advertising business is growing much faster than traditional advertising.</p>
        <p>According to the Point of Purchase Advertising Institute, the use of in-store promotions and advertising has been growing by 10 to 15 percent annually over the last five years, compared with growth of just 4 to 6 percent for traditional advertising.</p>
        <p>But despite its growth, in-store promotions and advertising remain a small part of the nation's total advertising outlays. In-store promotional and advertising expenditures totaled $14.8 billion in 1989, according to the institute, which estimates that about one-third of that money was spent in supermarkets and smaller food stores, as opposed to other retail outlets like drug and convenience stores. Traditional advertising expenditures were about $128.6 billion that year.</p>
        <p>Traditional advertising and promotions companies are often rivals for the same dollars. They are often in conflict on the design of their campaigns. Each camp argues that its method of reaching the customer is superior. But there are signs of reconciliation. A growing number of advertising agencies, like Foote, Cone &amp; Belding and more recently Earle Palmer Brown, have established or acquired their own promotional units. For these companies, in-store displays are seen as one more media tool.</p>
        <p>"Point of purchase can't be an orphan," said David Essertier, a senior vice president at Promotional Innovations Inc. and a former advertising executive at Saatchi &amp; Saatchi. "It is at its best when used with the other forms of advertising."  Enriching Stores Manufacturers Must Pay a Commission</p>
        <p>The growth of in-store programs is largely due to the peculiarities of supermarket economics. Most supermarket chains operate on wafer-thin margins of 1 percent. As a result, in-store promotions and advertising are an important source of revenue since manufacturers pay stores a commission for the chance to display their messages.</p>
        <p>Industry experts say that about 35 percent of the money spent on a typical promotions campaign goes to the store. The stores, in return, must provide data on sales to the manufacturers, increase their stocks of the featured products and mention the product in the supermarket's regular advertising circulars and flyers. Some of the larger chains can take in as much as $430,000 from a typical two-week campaign for a single product.</p>
        <p>Paul Bernish, a spokesman for the Kroger Company, one of the country's largest supermarket chains, declined to provide the amount that chain earned from in-store advertising, though he described it as a "moderate source of revenue." But he added that in-store displays were more a matter of increasing the store's sales than providing direct revenue. "We want to increase foot traffic in the store," he said.</p>
        <p>The Money Flows  Venture Capitalists Take to the Idea</p>
        <p>The largest company in the in-store market is Actmedia, which was established 18 years ago in Norwalk, Conn., and had revenues of $156.3 million in 1990 with earnings of $23.3 million. Acquired two years ago by the Dallas-based Heritage Media Corporation, which owns television and radio stations, Actmedia's operations cover 25,800 supermarkets, drugstores and mass merchandisers.</p>
        <p>Actmedia's products range from basic signs clipped onto shelves and hung over aisles to coupon machines placed next to the discounted products. It sends teams of employees to thousands of stores to promote products and has a radio network that plays music and pitches over the stores' sound systems. With Turner Broadcasting, Actmedia is planning to test TV programming for supermarkets.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, Actmedia had no significant competition, but analysts say there is a new influx of venture capital into the field. The industry still consists largely of thousands of entrepreneurs -- many of whom work from their homes and consider themselves inventors -- as well as dozens of promotional companies hired by manufacturers to design specific campaigns. But recently, a few other companies, like Media One in New York and the Catalina Marketing Corporation in Anaheim, Calif., -- both privately owned -- have established in-store promotional networks that cover thousands of supermarkets, though they offer a more limited array of services than Actmedia.</p>
        <p>Another company, Videocart Inc., in Chicago, has generated much attention with its plans to supply stores with carts equipped with video displays. By pushing a button on the cart, a customer can automatically receive an electronic coupon that will be recorded at the cashier in front. The Videocart company is still in a fledgling state, having just completed its testing stage in supermarkets around the country  [ page 13 ] .</p>
        <p>There is some concern among marketers, manufacturers and retailers that the supermarket could become so overwhelmed with promotional gadgets that shoppers could be turned off.</p>
        <p>But others dismiss the possibility that the industry could stop growing soon. "There's still so much unused space in the supermarket," said John M. Kawula, the institute's president. THE DIFFICULTY IN DEEP FREEZES</p>
        <p>The challenge for promotional companies is to get their products noticed. But some sections of the supermarket are better than others at doing that.</p>
        <p>"The two deadliest displays are the upright freezer section of the supermarket and the open fresh-dairy case display," said Lee Weinblatt, chief executive of Pretesting Company Inc., in Englewood, N.J., which provides advertising research using hidden video cameras in stores. "Shoppers are not willing to keep opening and closing the freezer doors to compare products in different sections of the upright freezers."</p>
        <p>Attempts to put promotions in the freezer space have sometimes met with disaster. But one solution being examined by several companies is to create small, separate cold displays.</p>
        <p>James Richardson, an industrial designer and consultant in Weston, Conn., said he first began working on concepts for "secondary freezer display space" five years ago. This week, Mr. Richardson's latest project -- a small portable freezer -- will be tested at supermarkets in Montreal, its second round of tests in the last two years.</p>
        <p>The portable freezer stands about three feet tall and four feet wide, with posters on all four sides to promote the product inside. It can be assembled and taken apart for moving in less than an hour. The cooling unit is separate from the storage space.</p>
        <p>In tests last year in about 40 A.&amp; P. stores in Toronto and at Overmaitea supermarkets in Vancouver, British Columbia, the freezers produced a sales increase of as much as 100 percent for McCains Super Fries and Campbell's Le Menu frozen dinners.</p>
        <p>"Any time you feature a product in-store with a separate display, it will increase sales -- that's a given," said Mr. Richardson. "The problem is how you stock it and get it into the store."</p>
        <p>The first version of Mr. Richardson's mini-freezer was dubbed the Cold Thief because it stole cold air from nearby freezers. It was inexpensive to manufacture but met with disapproval from store managers because it had to be located near an existing freezer unit. Another version of the freezer, which could be located anywhere, proved too expensive to make and did not keep the product cold enough.</p>
        <p>The latest version of the freezer, if next week's tests prove successful, could soon appear in stores throughout North America.</p>
        <p>Then again, it could be like thousands of other products that are developed for supermarkets and fall by the wayside. "Until the tests are completed," Mr. Richardson said, "you never can tell what can be a problem and how it will affect the store."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
