<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Special Relationship</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="467551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHOENBAUM, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COCKBURN, ANDREW</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COCKBURN, LESLIE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DANGEROUS LIAISON (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DC1139F93BA2575BC0A967958260" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Special Relationship</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Schoenbaum;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHOENBAUM, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DANGEROUS LIAISON</p>
        <p>The Inside Story of the U.S.-Israeli Covert Relationship. By Andrew Cockburn and Leslie Cockburn. 416 pp. New York: HarperCollins Publishers. $25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DANGEROUS LIAISON</p>
        <p>The Inside Story of the U.S.-Israeli Covert Relationship. By Andrew Cockburn and Leslie Cockburn. 416 pp. New York: HarperCollins Publishers. $25.</p>
        <p>Faced with the opportunities of a new, more open-ended international landscape, Israel now may, imaginably, be able to pursue a different foreign policy and, as part of that, a different relationship with the United States. Had Andrew Cockburn and Leslie Cockburn started here, and then spelled out Israel's choices amid the conflicting claims of security and an open society, "Dangerous Liaison" might have been a useful study.</p>
        <p>Instead, their book, supposedly a history of the secret ties between Israel and the United States, is largely dedicated to Israel-bashing for its own sake. Its first message is that, win or lose, smart or dumb, right or wrong, suave or boorish, Israelis are a menace. The second is that the Israeli-American connection is somewhere behind just about everything that ails us.</p>
        <p>Conceived as commonwealths unto themselves and as lights unto the nations, both Israel and the United States have been forced to become countries like other countries in their quest for external security. And, as so often happens when democratic sovereignty meets the facts of international life, the results frequently have been grubby.</p>
        <p>As the Cockburns -- he is the author of "The Threat: Inside the Soviet Military Machine," she of "Out of Control: The Story of the Reagan Administration's Secret War in Central America and the Contra-Drug Connection" -- are at pains to point out, both the Israelis and the Americans have learned to live with the bad as well as the good. They have struggled with omnivorous and mendacious bureaucracies; hefty defense budgets; military-industrial and military-intellectual complexes with their own vested interests and clienteles; contentious intelligence agencies with expansive dirty-tricks departments; and allies one might think twice about inviting to dinner.</p>
        <p>The conjunction of hot war, cold war and history has led, in turn, to a relationship between the two countries that is certainly unique, if not the dangerous liaison of the title. Not for nothing, the book begins shortly before the Gulf war, with the Israeli military wowing American Jews with a well-rehearsed public-relations show. But as the rest makes clear, the links extend over decades and continents, and Americans have not had to be Jewish to like what they saw. Lieut. Col. Oliver North is a practical example. When asked during the Iran-contra hearings about Israeli involvement in the scandal, he explained to the congressional investigators: "We did not want the U.S. government's hand, or role in this activity, exposed, and thus . . . we tried to mirror the Israeli model."</p>
        <p>The byproducts of the relationship, according to the authors, include nuclear larceny and proliferation, industrial piracy, bloated weapons projects, promiscuous arms peddling, aid and comfort to thugs of almost every political stripe, even a piece of the Colombian drug trade. These, they contend, have sometimes been means to an end, sometimes their own reward. But put them all together, they spell trouble, especially for the United States.</p>
        <p>This case can certainly be argued, and the evidence presented here is intermittently original. (Ms. Cockburn's knowledge of Central America seems especially to have paid off.) But for all the former generals and retired spooks paraded through these pages, the facts of Israeli nuclear weapons, arms transfers and dirty tricks are hardly news to either Americans or Israelis who read the papers.</p>
        <p>Still less does the book's argument, with its selective documentation and unattributed interviews, support an indictment of Israel. The British, French, Chinese and Indians could be called to testify that not all reasons for nuclear proliferation are necessarily reprehensible. Impressive for their weight class, Israeli arms pushers are still not in a league with Brazil and China, let alone with the United States and the Soviet Union. Israelis have been known to keep nasty company. But who hasn't, and what are the alternatives?</p>
        <p>"Dangerous Liaison" is not without merit. Unlike other Israel-bashing volumes, this one at least acknowledges the long shadow of the Holocaust, as well as Stalinist anti-Semitism, Syrian hysteria, Egyptian and Iraqi poison gas, and Palestinian unloveliness. The Cockburns also pay tribute to the combative candor of the Israeli press -- though they typically note that the ever-slippery Israelis insist on publishing their papers in a language no one else can read.</p>
        <p>But the authors' acknowledgement of the objective realities confronting Israel hardly begins to outweigh the heavy irony, undifferentiated indignation and historical tendentiousness that otherwise pervade their text. Intent on reporting the facts of life, the Cockburns bring to mind that threshold stage when children discover where babies come from. For the aspiring student of liaisons, dangerous and otherwise, this is, of course, an important discovery. But as any grown-up can confirm, it is barely the beginning of wisdom about how things really work.</p>
        <p>David Schoenbaum, a professor of history at the University of Iowa, writes frequently on the Arab-Israeli conflict.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Schoenbaum, a professor of history at the University of Iowa, writes frequently on the Arab-Israeli conflict.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
