<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Garden Q. &amp; A.</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Pastimes Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="467720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D8153FF93BA2575BC0A967958260" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Garden Q. &amp; A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Linda Yang</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Container Climbers</p>
        <p>Q. I would like to plant something -- preferably with flowers -- that will climb a trellis and</p>
        <p>grow in a container in my</p>
        <p>home in Dutchess County. I've been told that clematis won't survive winter in a pot. Please advise. -- Ellen Markowitz, Red Hook, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Container Climbers</p>
        <p>Q. I would like to plant something -- preferably with flowers -- that will climb a trellis and</p>
        <p>grow in a container in my</p>
        <p>home in Dutchess County. I've been told that clematis won't survive winter in a pot. Please advise. -- Ellen Markowitz, Red Hook, N.Y.</p>
        <p>A. Clematis certainly will survive winter in a container. So will quite a few other hardy climbers, if the container holds enough soil for insulation from frost. In your area, a tub should be at least 24 inches high, wide and deep to insure winter survival.</p>
        <p>Moisture is crucial for winter endurance, so add a deep mulch of bark chips after the first frost, and water container plants well during thaws if there has been little snow or rain.</p>
        <p>Other hardy flowering climbers for trellis growing include honeysuckle (Lonicera species), silver lace vine (polygonum aubertii), wisteria, Oriental bittersweet (Celastrus orbiculatus), variegated kiwi (actinidia kolomikta), porcelain berry (Ampelopsis brevipedunculata) and climbing roses. A new book that sheds further light on this subject is "The Garden Wall" by Julie Harrod (Atlantic Monthly Press, $29.95). Dyes From Nature</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>I want to use natural dyes to color my knitting yarn. What plants should I use, and what colors can I expect? -- Georgina Lancaster, Hartford.</p>
        <p>A.  Plants have long been used to make colored dyes; the subject was discussed as long ago as the first century by both the Roman naturalist Pliny the Elder and the Greek physician Dioscorides. Each part of a plant -- flowers, leaves, stems, bark, seeds and roots -- can produce a hue.</p>
        <p>"Dyeing is a little like brewing a pot of tea or simmering a stew," said Rita Buchanan, the author of "A Weaver's Garden" (Interweave Press, 1987, $16.95). "Like cooks or chefs, experienced dyers develop their own recipes and techniques."</p>
        <p>Among her suggestions for yellow and orange dyes are the leaves and flowers of tansy (tanacetum vulgare); twigs of smokebush (cotinus coggygria); goldenrod, marigold and dahlia flowers, and onion skins. Red dyes can be made from roots of lady's bedstraw (Galium verum) and roots of madder (Rubia tinctorum).</p>
        <p>Black can be made from the flowers and stems of purple loosestrife (Lythrum salicaria), and rich browns from black walnut hulls. Indigo, or blue tones, can be made from the leaves of woad (Isatis tinctoria), dyers knotweed (Polygonum tinctorium) and indigo (Indigofera suffruticosa).</p>
        <p>Also useful for those new to this subject is a 1990 handbook from the Brooklyn Botanic Garden, "Dyes From Nature," available at the garden and at many nurseries for $6.95. House Plants That Bloom</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>With the end of summer approaching, I want to add to my house plant collection and would like species that flower. I have windowsill sun for about half the day. What plants do you suggest? -- Belinda McLaine, Boston.</p>
        <p>A.  Although half a day of sun is a good beginning, to keep house plants in bloom you will also have to match each species with the humidity and temperature it prefers. So some experimenting is in order.</p>
        <p>Among the plants that are relatively easy to keep in flower indoors, given your light conditions, are browalia, fuchsia, gloxinia (Sinningia speciosa), shrimp plant (Beloperone guttata), chirita, jasmine (Jasminum species), cigar plant (Cuphea ignea), cyclamen, cape primrose (streptocarpus hybrids) and many kinds of begonias and African violets (Saintpaulia hybrids). Many orchids, too, are superb as house plants, provided they are compatible with your room humidity and temperature.</p>
        <p>Address questions to Garden Q. &amp; A., The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Those of general interest will be published. Unpublished questions cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
