<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Short Visit To Playoffs By the Power</title>
    <meta content="19WUSA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1318575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Power</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Beat</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bay Area Cyberrays</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arkush, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E3DA113EF93AA2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="746" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Short Visit To Playoffs By the Power</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL ARKUSH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arkush, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>SAN JOSE, Calif., Aug. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bay Area CyberRays defeat New York Power, 3-2, to win playoff series and advance to final against Atlanta Beat; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a season of firsts for women's professional soccer, the Power picked up the first that was the last thing it wanted. The Power became the first team to lose a Women's United Soccer Association playoff game, bowing to the Bay Area CyberRays, 3-2, before a crowd of 7,756 at Spartan Stadium today.</p>
        <p>The Power fought back twice to tie the game, but was undone in the 82nd minute by forward Julie Murray, who scored her second goal of the match and 11th of the season. The CyberRays will play in Saturday's final at Foxboro Stadium against the top-seeded Atlanta Beat, a 3-2 winner in double overtime tonight over the Philadelphia Charge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a season of firsts for women's professional soccer, the Power picked up the first that was the last thing it wanted. The Power became the first team to lose a Women's United Soccer Association playoff game, bowing to the Bay Area CyberRays, 3-2, before a crowd of 7,756 at Spartan Stadium today.</p>
        <p>The Power fought back twice to tie the game, but was undone in the 82nd minute by forward Julie Murray, who scored her second goal of the match and 11th of the season. The CyberRays will play in Saturday's final at Foxboro Stadium against the top-seeded Atlanta Beat, a 3-2 winner in double overtime tonight over the Philadelphia Charge.</p>
        <p>Murray's winning goal came when she headed a cross from Megan Horvath past goalie Gao Hong to put the CyberRays (12-6-4) on top for good.</p>
        <p>''That's one of the most beautiful crosses I've seen all year,'' CyberRays defender Brandi Chastain said.</p>
        <p>The CyberRays, whose coach, Ian Sawyers, was ejected during halftime for abusive language toward an official, did not wait long to assume the lead. In the fourth minute, the Brazilian star Katia headed the ball to Murray, who headed it into the net past Gao. The Power (9-8-5), which had not scored in three previous games against the CyberRays, was suddenly in trouble.</p>
        <p>Then, just as suddenly, the Power wasn't. In the very next minute, Emily Janss, assisted by Gro Espeseth and Nel Fettig, tied the game with her second goal of the season. The drought was finally over. Goaltender LaKeysia Beene was not invincible.</p>
        <p>There was no more scoring for the next 35 minutes, though both teams certainly had their chances. Katia, in fact, had two excellent opportunities. On the first chance, Gao barely held on to prevent the ball from crossing the goal line. On the second, Katia retrieved a poor clearance by Gao and just missed the corner of the net. For the Power, it was Tiffeny Milbrett, the team's star and the league's leading scorer, who came so close to breaking the deadlock. Taking a perfect pass from Jennifer Lalor, Milbrett  moved quickly into the penalty area toward Beene. But she shot wide left.</p>
        <p>The CyberRays went back on top, 2-1, on a penalty kick in the 40th minute by Chastain after Katia had been fouled in the penalty area by Fettig. Chastain's goal brought back memories of her game-winning kick past Gao in the much-celebrated 1999 World Cup final against China at the Rose Bowl, the game whose popularity helped fuel interest in establishing the league. This time, Chastain did not take off her shirt; the game was far from over. If there had been no additional scoring, Chastain's kick would have provided a Hollywood-type script for the league's playoff debut.</p>
        <p>The Power, however, was interested in a different script. Just before the end of the first half, during injury time, the Power tied the score. Fettig seemed ready to hit a free kick, but she ran by the ball while Lalor darted in. Lalor hit it over over the arms of Beene for her first goal of the season.</p>
        <p>''We came from behind,'' Power Coach Pat Farmer said. ''We gave up a goal late. We come up one goal short. Those are all stories of our season.''</p>
        <p>It has been an up-and-down season for both teams. The Power, after emerging as the league's dominant team with only one defeat in its first 11 games, recorded only 2 victories in the final 10 games.</p>
        <p>It was not until a 2-0 triumph over the Washington Freedom last week that the Power locked up a playoff berth. The team also had to overcome the season-ending loss of the speedy defender Christie Pearce, who tore the anterior cruciate ligament in her right knee against Carolina on Aug. 2.</p>
        <p>The CyberRays took the opposite path heading into today's semifinal. After winning only once in their first six games, the CyberRays rebounded to lose only twice in their last 15.</p>
        <p>For Chastain, the game was a first for her team that she will never forget.</p>
        <p>''I love being the first,'' she said. ''The first is such a cool thing. There'll be more playoff teams in the future, but they'll never take this one away from you. It makes you feel kind of giddy.''</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
