<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Habitats/East Brunswick, N.J.; Couple Find a New Home, Only Seven Houses Away</title>
    <meta content="19HABI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/19/realestate/19HABI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1318320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Habitats"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">East Brunswick (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiffman, Abbe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schiffman, Cory</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, Trish</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">East Brunswick (New Jersey)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey (USA)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010819T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802EFDF153EF93AA2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Habitats/East Brunswick, N.J.; Couple Find a New Home, Only Seven Houses Away</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">East Brunswick, N.J.: Couple Find a New Home, Only Seven Houses Away</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRISH HALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hall, Trish</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Habitats interview with Cory and Abbe Schiffman at their new lakefront home in East Brunswick, New Jersey, just seven houses away from their old house; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CORY SCHIFFMAN and Abbe Kirsten Schiffman were looking for a weekend house, a place on a lake where he could satisfy his boundless passion for fishing. They saw homes in northern New Jersey, not too far from their house in East Brunswick, N.J., but everything seemed too expensive.</p>
        <p>''We had a rule that our second home can't be more expensive than our primary one,'' Mr. Schiffman said. And as they found nothing, they began to doubt the wisdom of getting and keeping up two houses. It seemed too complicated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A passionate fisher lands a 4-bedroom on a nearby lake</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CORY SCHIFFMAN and Abbe Kirsten Schiffman were looking for a weekend house, a place on a lake where he could satisfy his boundless passion for fishing. They saw homes in northern New Jersey, not too far from their house in East Brunswick, N.J., but everything seemed too expensive.</p>
        <p>''We had a rule that our second home can't be more expensive than our primary one,'' Mr. Schiffman said. And as they found nothing, they began to doubt the wisdom of getting and keeping up two houses. It seemed too complicated.</p>
        <p>One Sunday last year, as they were driving around just for fun looking at different neighborhoods, their daughter, Estee, then 3, needed to use a bathroom, and they stopped into a real estate office pretending to be house hunting. Since they figured they had to say something, Mr.  Schiffman said they were looking for a house in East Brunswick on a lake. They left, and figured that was that.</p>
        <p>But not long afterward, the broker called and said that he did indeed know of a house on a lake, and that it was about to go on the market. The Schiffmans were the first to see it, and oddly enough it was just seven houses away from where they lived, in the 1940's development called Lawrence Brook Manor.</p>
        <p>When they saw the house, they were smitten. Not by the house, which was older than theirs and is undistinguished from the outside, but by the land.</p>
        <p>Although only five minutes from two large highways, the New Jersey Turnpike and Route 1, and in a densely populated area just 45 minutes from New York, the land feels as if it is in the Catskills. The sloping back yard opens up to a pristine lake, with no other houses in sight.</p>
        <p>The lake is Farrington, a backup reservoir for the area's water supply. Because it's for drinking, residents aren't supposed to swim in it. But they can skate in the winter, boat in a craft that doesn't use gasoline and, most important, fish. The lake is even stocked with bass, pickerel and northern pike. Because he lived nearby, Mr. Schiffman had occasionally fished there.</p>
        <p>The couple liked the house, which was listed at $475,000, but they didn't know what a reasonable bid would be, so they hired an appraiser, who suggested offering between $415,000 and $420,000.</p>
        <p>They offered $415,000, and after a bit of time went by, they agreed with the owner on a price of $443,500.</p>
        <p>There didn't seem to be much competition for the house. ''We got lucky,'' Mr. Schiffman said. ''It was the winter.''</p>
        <p>The owner was so agreeable that he let them use the house, before they even closed, for the bris of their new baby, Sam. The house they were selling didn't have any large rooms that would accommodate 60 people or so, while the new house had a large open space and, by the time they were ready for the bris, the owner had moved out most of his furniture.</p>
        <p>Although their new house is in good condition, the Schiffmans don't like the way the space is laid out, and they plan to make some changes, probably beginning next spring. The house was renovated twice, 10 years ago and then five years ago, making it four bedrooms with a den, living room, dining room and large kitchen.</p>
        <p>BUT they feel the additions are not in keeping with the original style of the house. The previous owner also changed the location of the entry, putting it on the side, and they would like to return it to the front, so that anyone walking in immediately gets a view of the lake.</p>
        <p>They will also put in new floors because, Mr. Schiffman said, ''The floor is uneven; I could take a marble and roll it into the lake.''</p>
        <p>The Schiffmans said they were planning to spend the winter picking out the flooring, fixtures and other details of the renovation, so they have everything decided before they start. They are already working with a kitchen designer, an interior designer and an architect.</p>
        <p>But although they will combine the dining room with an adjoining storage space so they get a view of the trees from their table, and although  they will create an office for Mrs. Schiffman and a bedroom in the front of the house, they will add only 400 square feet to the 2,600-square-foot home. After consulting with several architects, who offered very different visions, they decided they didn't want a really big house, or a second story.</p>
        <p>While most people cannot imagine their futures, the couple said they would like to go through all the stages of their life in the house and have it be comfortable in each one.</p>
        <p>''When the kids move out, I don't want to feel like I'm in a house that's too big,'' Mrs. Schiffman said.</p>
        <p>They've also seen friends end up in houses so big they're hard to decorate. ''We know plenty of people in McMansions who have no window treatments because their windows are so huge,'' Mr. Schiffman said. ''We want to keep a vacation feel -- understated and elegant.''</p>
        <p>For both, New Jersey is familiar territory. Mr. Schiffman, 43, grew up in nearby Highland Park, and Mrs. Schiffman, 41, was raised in Short Hills. After living in Manhattan for 10 years, and then Atlanta and Boston, she was ready to return to New Jersey, where she met Mr. Schiffman in a hiking club in 1995, after both had left their previous marriages.</p>
        <p>They wanted to stay in East Brunswick because it is centrally located and known for good schools. She works from home as a communicators' consultant, often for Johnson &amp; Johnson, which is nearby; he is in  business with his brother, running the car dealership their father started, Sheldon Motors of East Brunswick.</p>
        <p>Being in retail can be stressful, and the lake house has been the perfect antidote. Sometimes Mr. Schiffman will come home in the middle of the afternoon, put on his hip waders, pass by the hammock in the back yard and go right into the lake to fish.</p>
        <p>''I totally relax,'' he said. ''It's my escape. It's me, the fish, and nature.''</p>
        <p>He fishes only for the sport, he said, and always throws back his catches. And although he would on principle return them to the lake, he feels especially protective of these fish.</p>
        <p>It's so private by the lake, he said, ''that it's kind of like our lake, and my fish -- I want them to grow up.''</p>
        <p>Habitats</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
