<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ultra-Marathoners Limp to An Inner Peace</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="477955"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="RUNNING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RUNNING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLUSHING MEADOWS-CORONA PARK (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARWICK, SANDY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DB1038F930A35753C1A967958260" item-length="1122" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ultra-Marathoners Limp to An Inner Peace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just like her fellow ultra-marathoners, Sandy Barwick, a New Zealand housewife whose one peculiar avocation has turned her into a world- record holder, is living out of a tent in the midst of a multinational nomad camp along the boat basin at Flushing Meadows-Corona Park.</p>
        <p>It is a place where almost everyone moves at a limp, where the tent that contains the MASH unit administers continual treatment to runners suffering ailments ranging from simple blisters to the dementia that comes from running the same one-mile circle, like a gerbil on an exercise wheel, over and over again for two weeks with only a few hours of sleep each day.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just like her fellow ultra-marathoners, Sandy Barwick, a New Zealand housewife whose one peculiar avocation has turned her into a world- record holder, is living out of a tent in the midst of a multinational nomad camp along the boat basin at Flushing Meadows-Corona Park.</p>
        <p>It is a place where almost everyone moves at a limp, where the tent that contains the MASH unit administers continual treatment to runners suffering ailments ranging from simple blisters to the dementia that comes from running the same one-mile circle, like a gerbil on an exercise wheel, over and over again for two weeks with only a few hours of sleep each day.</p>
        <p>It's a place where one of Barwick's neighbors is a bona fide guru, Sri Chinmoy, the spiritual leader who sponsors this yearly race, the world's only 1,300-miler. Sidelined by a knee injury, the guru, who wears traditional Begali robes or a tracksuit with equal serenity, has had to curtail his own ultra-running and makes do by throwing a javelin and discus and putting a put as the racers plod on around him.</p>
        <p>Some are disciples of the guru, but most, like the 42-year-old Barwick, are simply hooked on distance running. To Sri Chinmoy, such running is a metaphor for life's journey, and the Sri Chinmoy Marathon Club not only staffs this race, providing everything from a vegetarian kitchen to barracks to security guards, but underwrites its $15,000 cost, of which one-third comes from entry fees. New York City Marathon 'a Farce'</p>
        <p>To many of the runners, racing has been a passport to self-esteem, fitness, the record books and the ultimate adventure. "Most people think of the New York Marathon as the limit of human endurance, but to us that's a farce," said Emil Laharrague, a Frenchman who has lived in the Amazon jungle, among the aborigines of Papua New Guinea, carried his own supplies on a marathon through the Sahara Desert and holds his nation's record at 1,000 miles.</p>
        <p>"If you can handle this, and push your mind and body and emotions through it, you can survive just about anything in the plastic world."</p>
        <p>Regrettably, said Laharrague, this sport's rewards are motivational, not monetary. Barwick, who had worn through four pairs of sneakers by the time she reached the 1,247-mark late yesterday afternoon, is running for a trophy, several world records and two dozen red roses.</p>
        <p>"I know it looks crazy to people on the outside, living in a tent and running around in a circle for 18 or 19 days," said Barwick, who holds seven world records and is on target to become the first woman in history to complete a 1,300-mile course at about 11:30 this morning.</p>
        <p>"Ten years ago, I probably would have thought so, too," she said, talking while tracing her laps.</p>
        <p>"Why I started, I think, was that there was an empty place in me after my mother died, and I think running, which to my surprise I was good at, filled it," said Barwick, who ran 200 miles a week to train for this race.</p>
        <p>"When I'm running, and when I hit the finish line, I'm fulfilled. I call this race my stairway to heaven: I'll never do it again, but when it's over, if I never do another thing in my life, this will be enough," she said as she crossed the line for the umpteenth time. As usual, one of Sri Chinmoy's disciples, a guitarist named Sadhak, who is already in the Guinness Book of Records for longest continuous guitar-playing session and is now shooting for a new record, was doing serenade duty there. 61 Runners From 14 Nations</p>
        <p>For two or three hours daily, a tent bearing the design of her nation's flag is Barwick's home and a sleeping bag is her sanctuary. The rest of the day and night, her sneakered feet pound the macadam track that makes a one-mile loop around the site of the Sri Chinmoy Ultimate Ultra, a race whose 61 entrants run, walk, or, after two weeks of non-stop circling, virtually crawl around the course 700, 1,000, or 1,300 times depending on their tolerance for pain, their quest for spiritual transcendence and their appetite for world records.</p>
        <p>Two days short of the event's official conclusion, just 35 of the original 61 runners from 14 nations were still physically and mentally able to hit the road, and many, like Barwick, were hobbling to meet their personal deadlines and destiny.</p>
        <p>Barwick ran her first 1,000 miles with such expedience that she set a world record, 12 days 14 hours 38 minutes, for women at that distance. But she paid a price for her exuberance, a pulled hamstring that has slowed her pace to a brisk walk. Late yesterday afternoon she was just 57 miles ahead of Canada's Antana Locs, a 32-year-old secretary and student of Sri Chinmoy who was also attempting 1,300 miles, roughly the distance between New York and Miami, for the first time.</p>
        <p>"The body says she has enough world records and should call it quits," said Max Marsh, Barwick's manager, "but the mind and ego say keep going, and in this case, they're right. She's going to make it."</p>
        <p>To keep Locs at bay, Barwick, who is sponsored by the company that supplies New Zealand's most famous commercial export, Kiwi fruit, needed to spend 21 of every 24 hours on the move and log 55 to 60 miles daily.</p>
        <p>"I feel a little bit of a fraud, not being able to run it out," she said yesterday as she trudged the course, vanilla cookie in hand, for the 1,246th time. "There's pain, but not so much that I can't smile, that I can't see the end in sight. Believe me, if I couldn't smile about this, I'd quit."  You Can Run, but . . .</p>
        <p>Noise from the neighboring expressways, in triplicate, roars dully at all hours, but she has ceased to hear it. Barwick, the diminutive mother of two teen-agers, is described as "the most awesome woman I've ever met" by her male counterpart, Al Howie, the Canadian who holds the world record among the trio of men who have ever finished a 1,300-mile race.</p>
        <p>Howie, better than anyone else, knows the rigors of this unorthodox sport. Two years ago, the 46-year-old reforestation worker who replaced one addiction, cigarettes, with this one, became the first person to complete a 1,300-mile course. His time, 17 days 8 hours 25 minutes stands as the world record. This past summer, in a charity run across Canada, he covered 4,600 miles in 72 days, finished on Sept. 1, took a week off, and then rode the train from Seattle to New York for a chance to break his own record 1,300-mile record here.</p>
        <p>"I've always been a bit of an extremist, but I guess I do this to prove to me and to the world that a human being can do these things," said Howie. "And, same as Sandy, I do it because I'm good at it. I have to admit, there are days when I wish I was good at something a little easier, like darts or pool, but there's nothing like this."  RUNNING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
