<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Place And Time To Find New Ways To Move</title>
    <meta content="03HUGH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/03/arts/03HUGH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1298420"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">White Oak Dance Project</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Judson Dance Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Academy of Music</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, Allen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baryshnikov, Mikhail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hay, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Paxton, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rainer, Yvonne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Childs, Lucinda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forti, Simone</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tipton, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Trisha</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Judson Memorial Church</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Judson Dance Theater</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010603T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E6D8123CF930A35755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="2716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Place And Time To Find New Ways To Move</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLEN HUGHES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hughes, Allen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mikhail Baryshnikov and White Oak Dance Project to honor innovative Judson Dance Theater in program at Brooklyn Academy of Music; will present 15 works dating from 1960's by seven Judson choreographers, most of whom will also appear as performers; choreographers Steve Paxton, Yvonne Rainer, Deborah Hay, Lucinda Childs, David Gordon, Simone Forti and Trisha Brown and lighting designer Jennifer Tipton comment; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIRTY-NINE years ago, the sanctuary of the Judson Memorial Church on Washington Square became the site of a landmark development in the international history of dance. It housed the doings of a motley band of folks in their early 20's for whom history-making was of no concern. They were simply searching for personal paths to artistic creation through bodily movement. They became known as the Judson Dance Theater, and what they did shocked the dance establishment. Ultimately, however, the impact of their discoveries forced it to move over and make room for them.</p>
        <p>Most of the original group had classical ballet or modern-dance training or both before they got to Judson, and some had studied choreography with establishment teachers, but their skills varied widely. What they had in common was a class in choreography taught at Merce Cunningham's studio, housed at the time in a drab old building at the corner of 14th Street and Sixth Avenue. The teacher was Robert Dunn, a musician and disciple of John Cage, the avant-garde composer and music director of Cunningham's dance company. Dunn's job was to encourage the creation of dances following the far-out methods Cage had adopted for his music-making.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIRTY-NINE years ago, the sanctuary of the Judson Memorial Church on Washington Square became the site of a landmark development in the international history of dance. It housed the doings of a motley band of folks in their early 20's for whom history-making was of no concern. They were simply searching for personal paths to artistic creation through bodily movement. They became known as the Judson Dance Theater, and what they did shocked the dance establishment. Ultimately, however, the impact of their discoveries forced it to move over and make room for them.</p>
        <p>Most of the original group had classical ballet or modern-dance training or both before they got to Judson, and some had studied choreography with establishment teachers, but their skills varied widely. What they had in common was a class in choreography taught at Merce Cunningham's studio, housed at the time in a drab old building at the corner of 14th Street and Sixth Avenue. The teacher was Robert Dunn, a musician and disciple of John Cage, the avant-garde composer and music director of Cunningham's dance company. Dunn's job was to encourage the creation of dances following the far-out methods Cage had adopted for his music-making.</p>
        <p>Exactly how many choreographic aspirants had works performed at Judson during the six years of performances that began on July 6, 1962, may be something no one will ever know, given the informality that prevailed and the rate at which participants came and went. But it was the originators who set the pace and tone and ended up making the most forceful impression worldwide.</p>
        <p>Over the years, they have racked up an extraordinary record of dance works commissioned, films made, books written, operas and other theater works directed, prizes and awards received (including nine Guggenheim and two MacArthur fellowships) and myriad honors for artistic achievement here and abroad.</p>
        <p>Mikhail Baryshnikov, a dazzling classical ballet dancer when he came here from the Soviet Union in 1974, quickly became attracted to American modern dance and appeared often with various modern companies, but the Judson days had long since ended. Then, in April 1999, he saw some of the original works in revivals at a benefit for Judson Memorial Church and was intrigued. He called David Gordon, a friend and Judsonite he knew from a previous association at American Ballet Theater, and suggested their collaboration on a survey for Mr. Baryshnikov's White Oak Project. The result had its debut in Princeton last October and has since been seen in a number of cities on its way to New York.</p>
        <p>Beginning Tuesday through Saturday at the Brooklyn Academy of Music, Mr. Baryshnikov and the White Oak Project will honor seven of what are now called the postmoderns with ''PastForward,'' a celebration of 15 of their works dating from the early days as well as more recent times. On Thursday, some, perhaps all, of the choreographers will appear as performers.</p>
        <p>Following are eight recollections of the Judson Dance Theater and its beginnings, excerpted from interviews. Seven are by the choreographers included in the ''PastForward'' programs. That of the lighting designer Jennifer Tipton tells of a dancer devoted to the cause whose appearance in the very first performance at Judson remains fixed in memory.</p>
        <p>STEVE PAXTON</p>
        <p>Yvonne Rainer and I had the first meeting with Al Carmines, one of the pastors at Judson, to ask if we could perform at the church, and then we had to have a showing for him. I can't remember what was shown, but Yvonne and I were not alone. Ruth Emerson did something, and Bob Dunn was there. Whatever it was, I honestly think Carmines thought it was all so dumb, he couldn't say no. In something he wrote later, he stated that only after seeing the early performances did he begin to feel that something interesting was going on.</p>
        <p>There wasn't a big desire to shock. We were simply looking forward to having a small showing of our work in a friendly church in Greenwich Village. It wasn't a big gesture we were making. We were investigating something very seriously. Of course, art does have the ability to surprise occasionally, and that period for us was one of casually taking enormous aesthetic steps.</p>
        <p>Judson was a place not to mimic one's peers, but when something interested everyone at once, it became almost inevitable. I'm thinking particularly of our focus on pedestrian movement and our continuing fascination with it. Ideas for dance do occasionally bubble up in the culture and some people become available to explore the bubbles. That's what was happening then.</p>
        <p>YVONNE RAINER</p>
        <p>I think it was my idea to inquire at Judson because I had already been to its art gallery to see works by Allan Kaprow, I think, and perhaps Claes Oldenburg, and I had attended the Poet's Theater for Joel Oppenheimer's ''American Dream.'' So I knew that Judson was interested in the cutting edge in experimental arts. Everything was free; we paid no rent, and no tickets were sold. The program decisions were made collectively, and I remember heated discussions about them. When we started out, none of us were prepared to sustain a whole evening, but together we seemed to have an overabundance of material. Bob Dunn, acting as a sort of moderator, was reluctant to eliminate anything, and that first night turned into a three-hour marathon. My works were a solo called ''Ordinary Dance,'' in which I spoke and moved at the same time, and ''Dance for 3 People and 6 Arms,'' which I performed with two other dancers.</p>
        <p>I remember after that first concert a feeling of triumph and exhilaration that we had found a home, because it was clear, even that early, that we could show work there. Everyone was included. There was no jury that excluded people. In September we began what we called workshops, though that's not really what they were, in the Judson basement on Monday evenings. Everyone was eligible to come, and anyone who showed work there could appear in the programs. Inclusiveness, democracy and consensus were very important to me. I think the original animating energy or spirit of the Judson Dance Theater gradually weakened and wore itself out after about two years or so, when the Monday workshops ended.</p>
        <p>DEBORAH HAY</p>
        <p>I was pretty young and that was a crucial, formative period. But some part of me understood that I was in the right place at the right time. It was a hotbed of creativity because of John Cage, Merce Cunningham and Robert Rauschenberg. Bob Dunn's classes were based on Cage's approach to musical composition, so we were actually learning Cage methods of indeterminacy and chance, which were very freeing technically in making dances. We didn't have to take ourselves so seriously, though we were very serious about our work. John wasn't at those classes, but he was certainly around the Cunningham studio and, for me, his influence was parallel, if not greater, than Merce's. My aesthetic was born there, and in the work of many of us the vocabulary of movement is sort of dimensionless, not fixed in a recognizable technique. Robert Rauschenberg was a good model for us. He knew how to have a good time and gave a lot of parties in his loft. The first work I did at Judson was ''Rain Fur.'' I remember being on the floor and rolling over slowly. I started upstage and rolled downstage. Alex Hay, to whom I was married at the time, may have been in it, too, but I'm not sure. It was accompanied by Charles Rotmil playing a bamboo flute.</p>
        <p>LUCINDA CHILDS</p>
        <p>I had studied with Merce Cunningham at Sarah Lawrence and also here in New York during summer vacations, but by the time I graduated from college in 1962 I was too late for Robert Dunn's classes with the others. Later, there was a summer version of the Dunn course I did attend. But well before that, at the Cunningham studio, Yvonne Rainer invited me to the Monday workshops. In those, it was assumed, though not required, that one would appear in other choreographers' works, and I was in several by Yvonne, Steve Paxton, Robert Morris and others.</p>
        <p>Graduation could have been a traumatic experience for me, a dance major, but because of the Cunningham studio and Judson I not only had someplace to go, I knew where I wanted to go. It enabled me to begin my career, and I think it's responsible, to some extent, for the career I've had. Basically, Judson was influential in that we were all self-taught as choreographers. The last thing Robert Dunn would ever tell you was how to do something.</p>
        <p>My first Judson performance in my own work was in 1963 with a piece called ''Pastime,'' and I choreographed 12 more while active there. ''Carnation,'' which dates from 1964 and will be performed at BAM, is a solo that involves hair curlers, sponges, a colander, a sheet with two socks attached and a blue plastic bag. I've long since abandoned the use of materials as objects in that way.</p>
        <p>DAVID GORDON</p>
        <p>On July 3, 1962, my wife, Valda Setterfield, began to have labor pains near midnight, and on July 4 my son, Ain, was born. My focus instantly shifted from Judson to the fact that I was now a father. Over the next two days I spent virtually all my time at the hospital. On the night of July 6 I called to ask somebody at Judson approximately when I was supposed to go on. I took a taxi downtown, and when I got there they said, ''You're next.'' I walked out and did ''Helen's Dance.'' Everybody in the Dunn class had worked on an exercise to a Satie ''Gymnopédie,'' and that was mine. It was choreographed in a railroad flat we had lived in that was about 40 feet long, and the work consisted of me moving straight downstage from upstage for the duration of the music.</p>
        <p>My second work was ''Mannequin.'' Impending fatherhood had made me look for a job, and I had fixed on department-store display as something I might do, though I knew nothing specific about it. I applied at S. Klein, which used to be on Union Square, and was hired. I swiftly learned how to take mannequins apart and how to dress them. In the performance I sang the only two songs I knew all the words to, ''Get Married, Shirley,'' which I had learned from a recording by Nancy Walker, and ''Second Hand Rose,'' as recorded by Fanny Brice. For ''Mannequin'' I wore a bloody lab coat because I had asked a biology-major friend to design a costume, and she handed me her bloody coat.</p>
        <p>SIMONE FORTI</p>
        <p>Although I had no direct involvement with Judson Dance Theater, I'm always identified with its work. As a member of Bob Dunn's classes with the original Judsonites I, too, learned about John Cage's methods of composition. I especially remember working with Trisha Brown and Steve Paxton on pieces we called ''rule games.'' One of these entailed turning on a radio and taking cues from the first letters of words we heard. Each letter demanded a specific activity, and the collision of random cues and strict rules resulted, at times, in things that were impossible to do.</p>
        <p>In the Dunn class we showed our works for each other and visitors who might attend. La Monte Young and Jackson MacLow saw something I did and invited me to participate in a series they were curating for presentation at Yoko Ono's studio on Chambers Street in 1961. Some members of the Dunn class, including Steve, Yvonne and Robert Morris, were among the performers in the dances I presented there. ''Huddle,'' one of the pieces from that evening, is included at BAM.</p>
        <p>By the time the Judson performances began, I was participating in the work of Robert Whitman, whom I married. He was very involved in happenings (''theater pieces'' he called his) given in a Lower East Side storefront studio he shared with Claes Oldenburg, Jim Dine and others. I got caught up in that community. But when the marriage ended in 1966, I returned to dance and participated with Judson people in a couple of performances -- one, including Steve, Deborah and Alex Hay and Robert Rauschenberg, at the School of Visual Arts.</p>
        <p>JENNIFER TIPTON</p>
        <p>I was dancing with a company called the Merry-Go-Rounders that was based at the 92nd Street Y. On weekends we went out to schools to perform for children. Steve Paxton also danced with the company, and when the Judson opportunity came up he asked me to be in a work of his. I don't remember the name of it. The main thing I do remember is that I stood in a bucket of ball bearings and was turned around by others.</p>
        <p>This was early in my New York years, and for me, who grew up in Knoxville, Tenn., the whole event was very exciting. I continued to perform for a time, but I was beginning to get interested in lighting through my work as rehearsal assistant with the Merry-Go-Rounders. Those were the years in which Bob Rauschenberg was lighting for Merce, and I learned a lot from him. For most of the Judson people at that time, light illusion had no part in the theatrical experience. So, though my heart was with Judson, our career paths diverged because of my new work.</p>
        <p>TRISHA BROWN</p>
        <p>The Judson period was one of discovery for me. Bob Dunn's bringing of Cage's compositional ideas to dance really opened the door. I learned that I could make up the way I make a dance. Having gone through the Mills College dance program, which was based on Martha Graham and Louis Horst, and also three summers of Horst's tightly structured teaching of choreography at Connecticut College, I was suddenly into John Cage. Varoom! That was the most important experience, and it's been with me all my life. Had it not been for that I would probably have stopped dancing.</p>
        <p>A cluster of people came to the studio to see what Dunn class members were doing when we showed our work to each other, and that handful of people increased in size. Curiosity was high about what we were up to. In time, there wasn't room for all who wanted to come. That cadre of people was turning into an audience, and ultimately that led to Judson.</p>
        <p>My first surprise was that we were in a church. My second surprise came later when we performed in the gym downstairs, and we soon became known for the use of alternative spaces.</p>
        <p>We were a collective, a pool of unlike-minded people, totally democratic with a lot of grumbling going on back in the dressing room. We were like a pack of horses let out of the chute, running along on separate tracks with a high degree of competition that was also a kind of shared exploration. Early Judson was a free-spirited, free-wheeling, mad dash for information and discovery. As we gained confidence in what we were doing, thoughts of separate identities and separate careers inevitably began to assume increasing importance. We were outsiders, big time, when we started at Judson, but we learned courage and persistence, and here we are!</p>
        <p>DANCE Allen Hughes is a former music and dance critic of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Allen Hughes is a former music and dance critic of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
