<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yes, It's Nice to Be a Favorite, But It's Nicer to Be a Winner</title>
    <meta content="13CARD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1316944"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E4DA113FF930A2575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yes, It's Nice to Be a Favorite, But It's Nicer to Be a Winner</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott Bridge column analyzes hand from Spingold Knockout in Toronto (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The favorites in major team championships are sometimes defeated in the early rounds, and they had more trouble than usual in the Spingold Knockout in Toronto last month. Three of the top five seeds went out in the first three rounds, losing to unheralded teams.</p>
        <p>One was the fourth-seeded group headed by James Cayne, who led a star-studded group consisting of Grant Baze, Mike Passell, Michael Seamon, Bobby Levin and Steve Weinstein. On the third day they lost by just 5 imps to Mike Moss, Fred Chang, Jeff Schuett and Kerry Smith. In this foursome Moss has had many successes, including a silver medal in a world team championship, but his teammates were little known to fame until Toronto.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The favorites in major team championships are sometimes defeated in the early rounds, and they had more trouble than usual in the Spingold Knockout in Toronto last month. Three of the top five seeds went out in the first three rounds, losing to unheralded teams.</p>
        <p>One was the fourth-seeded group headed by James Cayne, who led a star-studded group consisting of Grant Baze, Mike Passell, Michael Seamon, Bobby Levin and Steve Weinstein. On the third day they lost by just 5 imps to Mike Moss, Fred Chang, Jeff Schuett and Kerry Smith. In this foursome Moss has had many successes, including a silver medal in a world team championship, but his teammates were little known to fame until Toronto.</p>
        <p>The Moss team, originally seeded 29th, went on to reach the final, losing to a team that included four Italian world champions. By that time Schuett and Smith were exhausted, for they had played nonstop for 12 days, including two earlier events.</p>
        <p>The most brilliant bidding performance of the final came on the diagramed deal, with Schuett and Smith sitting North and South. They demonstrated that they had been underrated by the commentators, who predicted that nobody would be able to reach the desirable contract of seven diamonds.</p>
        <p>After one diamond had been overcalled with one spade, the cue-bid of two spades showed a strong hand with a diamond fit. South's bidding indicated shortness in clubs, and his partner correctly interpreted the significance of the later five-heart bid. This showed interest in seven diamonds, virtually guaranteeing a strong diamond suit plus a void in clubs. North judged accurately that his losing spade would eventually be discarded on the heart ace.</p>
        <p>The club ace was led and ruffed, after which South drew trumps and claimed his grand slam. After maneuvering the discard of a spade from dummy, he could collect eight trump tricks, four heart tricks and the spade ace. The score was 2,140.</p>
        <p>In the replay Norberto Bocchi and Giorgio Duboin, two of the Italians, sat North-South and botched the bidding by landing in three no-trump from the North position. Moss, East, guessed wrong by leading the spade 10, since his partner had bid that suit. North claimed 10 tricks but would have been down 3 after a club lead. Moss was therefore lucky: his misguess on the opening lead, allowing a vulnerable game to make, cost a mere 3 imps. His team gained 17 instead of 20.</p>
        <p>The District 3 Summer Regional Championships are being played this week at Crowne Plaza Meadowlands, 2 Harmon Plaza, Secaucus, N.J. This is the schedule of major events:</p>
        <p>Today: Educational Fund Pairs, 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Bracketed Knockout Teams I, 7:30 p.m. and continues</p>
        <p>Tomorrow: Stratified Senior Pairs, 10 a.m. and 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Stratified Open Pairs, 1 p.m. and 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Wednesday: Stratified Senior Swiss Teams, 10 a.m. and 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Stratified Open Pairs, 1 p.m. and 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Bracketed Knockout Teams II, 1 p.m. and continues</p>
        <p>Thursday: Stratified Senior Pairs, 10 a.m. and 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Stratified Open Swiss Teams, 1 p.m. and 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Friday: Bracketed Compact Knockout Teams (4 people only), 9 a.m. and continues</p>
        <p>Stratified Senior Pairs, 10 a.m. and 3 p.m.</p>
        <p>Stratified Open Pairs, 1 p.m. and 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Bracketed Knockout Teams III, 7:30 p.m. and continues</p>
        <p>Saturday: Stratiflighted Open Pairs and Stratified Senior Pairs, 1 p.m. and 7:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>Sunday: Stratiflighted Swiss Teams and Stratified Senior Swiss Teams, 11 a.m. and 6 p.m.</p>
        <p>Easybridge courses Friday and Saturday at 9 a.m.; one-session open and newplicate games throughout.</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
