<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Professor in the Bleachers With a Lifelong Scorecard</title>
    <meta content="20KAKU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/05/20/books/20KAKU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1490337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gould, Stephen Jay</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Triumph and Tragedy in Mudville (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Gould, Stephen Jay</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Triumph and Tragedy in Mudville: A Lifelong Passion for Baseball (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E0DB133EF933A15756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Professor in the Bleachers With a Lifelong Scorecard</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Professor in the Bleachers With a Lifelong Scorecard</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews Stephen Jay Gould book Triumph and Tragedy in Mudville: A Lifelong Passion for Baseball; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TRIUMPH AND TRAGEDY IN MUDVILLE  A Lifelong Passion for Baseball  By Stephen Jay Gould  Illustrated. 342 pages. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $24.95.</p>
        <p>It's no surprise that the paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould, who died last May, was a lifelong baseball fan. He belonged to the third generation of a family of ardent baseball enthusiasts, and he grew up in New York in the 1940's and 50's, when the city -- home to the Yankees, the Giants and the Brooklyn Dodgers -- was the greatest baseball mecca in the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould, who died last May, demonstrates his passion for baseball and his knowledge of its history in this collection.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TRIUMPH AND TRAGEDY IN MUDVILLE  A Lifelong Passion for Baseball  By Stephen Jay Gould  Illustrated. 342 pages. W. W. Norton &amp; Company. $24.95.</p>
        <p>It's no surprise that the paleontologist Stephen Jay Gould, who died last May, was a lifelong baseball fan. He belonged to the third generation of a family of ardent baseball enthusiasts, and he grew up in New York in the 1940's and 50's, when the city -- home to the Yankees, the Giants and the Brooklyn Dodgers -- was the greatest baseball mecca in the world.</p>
        <p>He argues in ''Triumph and Tragedy in Mudville,'' this volume of collected essays, that the sport embodies the same principles of continuity and change that animate his chosen profession, evolving as the decades scrolled by, even as it continued to follow certain immutable laws: ''Baseball has changed no major rule in a century, and we can therefore look and compare, in genuine continuity, across the generations. The seasons of our lives move inexorably forward. As my father saw Ruth, I followed Maris, and my sons watch McGwire. But the game also cycles in glorious sameness, as each winter of our discontent yields to another spring of opening day.''</p>
        <p>Although this collection of a fan's notes suffers from many of the problems common to such anthologies -- repeated ideas and anecdotes, and scattershot topics dictated by the vagaries of magazine and newspaper assignments -- it attests to Mr. Gould's passion for the game and to his knowledge of its history. His writing may not be as lyrical or evocative as Roger Angell's baseball essays or as doggedly detailed as Roger Kahn's, but he demonstrates the same gifts in this volume that his many books on natural history have evinced: an ability to discuss the scientific aspects of his subject in easily accessible terms while illuminating its larger social implications.</p>
        <p>In one article, for instance, Mr. Gould argues that the disappearance of .400 hitting (no one has hit .400 since Ted Williams reached .406 in 1941) is directly related to the overall improvement in playing: ''Variation in batting averages must decrease as improving play eliminates the rough edges that great players could exploit, and as average performance moves toward the limits of human possibility.'' He then goes on to discuss how general improvement in any field, be it sports, art or science, tends to clip ''the wings of true greatness,'' as the ''right wall'' of human excellence is approached.</p>
        <p>He adds: ''One cannot avoid -- with that special sadness reserved for recognizing a wonderful thing gone forever -- the conviction that certain seminal discoveries established truths so central and so broad in import that we cannot hope to win insight in such great gulps again, for the right wall moves slowly and with limits, and we may never again open up space for jumps so big.'' And this discussion started out about batting averages and earned-run averages.</p>
        <p>Several of the essays in ''Triumph and Tragedy'' debunk popular myths, for instance that Abner Doubleday invented baseball in Cooperstown in 1839 or that Bill Buckner single-handedly blew the Red Sox' chances of winning their first World Series since 1918 when he allowed a ball to roll through his legs in Game 6 of the 1986 World Series against the Mets. Mr. Gould writes about how myth-making biographies of famous baseball players gave way, in the wake of Jim Bouton's candid 1970 book ''Ball Four,'' to more confessional works, and he discusses the relationship between what he calls H-mode (or hagiographical) and Q-mode (or quotidian) baseball books.</p>
        <p>By far the most affecting portions of this volume concern Mr. Gould's own memories as a fan, from his childhood as a die-hard Yankee fan in the golden age of baseball in New York through his adulthood in Boston, where as a longtime professor at Harvard he became that most anomalous of creatures, a Yankee fan who also rooted for the Red Sox. He relives the excruciating disappointments that Boston has suffered over the years -- a familiar litany to be sure, but engagingly recounted here -- and he recreates the excitement of that era (1947-57) in New York when a subway series was a perennial possibility, when at least one team from the city usually made it to the World Series.</p>
        <p>He writes with abiding affection for Mickey Mantle, whom he rates over Willie Mays as the greatest center fielder of recent times, but reserves his highest accolades for his boyhood hero Joe DiMaggio. Of the Yankee Clipper's 56-game hitting streak, Mr. Gould claims that a statistical analysis of all slumps and streaks shows that ''only DiMaggio's shouldn't have happened'': ''All other streaks fall within the expectations for great events that should occur once as a consequence of probabilities, just as an honest coin will come up heads 10 times in a row once in a very rare while. But no one should ever have hit in 56 straight games.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gould's hero worship of DiMaggio can lead to clichéd encomiums. (''He was the glory of a time that we will not see again.'') And baseball fans may well debate some of the other assertions in this book: that Ty Cobb ''was the greatest ballplayer in American history,'' that ''the 1954 Cleveland Indians were probably the greatest team of modern baseball.'' These, however, are the sort of questions endlessly debated by fans on talk radio and at ballparks around the country, and whether or not the reader shares all of Mr. Gould's opinions, this book makes it clear that he was as avid and knowledgeable about baseball as he was about paleontology.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
