<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pop and Jazz in Review</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCERTS AND RECITALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHOEMER, KAREN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WELCH, KEVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIS, KELLY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFDB113EF93BA15756C0A964958260" item-length="435" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pop and Jazz in Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN SCHOEMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHOEMER, KAREN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kevin Welch and Kelly Willis  Lone Star Roadhouse</p>
        <p>Country music, despite its down-home ethos, is loaded with formalities. Performers abide by a code that tells them what kind of hat to wear, which topics to cover in their songs, how many rhinestones to flaunt on a jacket or dress. Last Thursday night, Kevin Welch and Kelly Willis, two singers on country's commercial fringe, dispensed with the formalities and played a set that followed a loose, impromptu design of their own. Mr. Welch and Ms. Willis each have two solo albums to their credit, but instead of performing separately they joined in a single set, alternating lead vocals and sharing harmonies on each other's songs. They dressed casually, in jeans and comfortable shirts. There was no strict set list, no interfering egos.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kevin Welch and Kelly Willis  Lone Star Roadhouse</p>
        <p>Country music, despite its down-home ethos, is loaded with formalities. Performers abide by a code that tells them what kind of hat to wear, which topics to cover in their songs, how many rhinestones to flaunt on a jacket or dress. Last Thursday night, Kevin Welch and Kelly Willis, two singers on country's commercial fringe, dispensed with the formalities and played a set that followed a loose, impromptu design of their own. Mr. Welch and Ms. Willis each have two solo albums to their credit, but instead of performing separately they joined in a single set, alternating lead vocals and sharing harmonies on each other's songs. They dressed casually, in jeans and comfortable shirts. There was no strict set list, no interfering egos.</p>
        <p>Musically, the pair started with straight country, then departed for its outer limits. Some songs, like Mr. Welch's "Early Summer Rain," had the easy, rustic feel of a folk chestnut; others, like "Me and Billy the Kid Never Got Along," a Joe Ely song covered by Mr. Welch on his new album "Western Beat" (Reprise), kicked at the walls of rock-and-roll. Ms. Willis has a ripe, twangy voice that catches emotion in the tiniest turns of phrase, but singing alone she was occasionally overwhelmed by the band; she came off best harmonizing with Mr. Welch on a sighing, somber ballad like the 60's soul standard "The Dark End of the Street," or the jumping blues of Jimmy Reed's "Shame Shame Shame." Their duets had the unstructured grace of the Bob Dylan-Emmylou Harris collaborations on Mr. Dylan's album "Desire."</p>
        <p>The empathy between Mr. Welch and Ms. Willis was enhanced by the backing band. The guitarist Bill Dwyer added fills where they were least expected and most needed; Dennis Caplinger switched among fiddle, mandolin, dobro and banjo. By the end of the set Mr. Welch was so breathless with enjoyment that he almost forgot a song. "Oh yeah," he said, "this is my new single and video, 'Something 'Bout You.' " When the business of promotion was done with, he dove back into the real business of playing.</p>
        <p>Joe Flood, a singer and guitarist with the local band Mumbo Gumbo, opened the show with a solo acoustic set. Mr. Flood has a raspy voice that perfectly straddles the fence between country and blues, and he plays the guitar according to jagged, internal rhythms. His songs were bursting with eccentric characters, and like Mr. Welch and Ms. Willis, he adhered to a code of spontaneity. Three sailors were sitting at a front table, and he happily dedicated a song to them about being seasick.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
