<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Danielle Aiello, Guillermo Mendoza</title>
    <meta content="20AIELLO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/20/fashion/weddings/20AIELLO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1784136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Aiello, Danielle Page (Danielle Page Mendoza)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mendoza, Guillermo F.</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E2DD153EF933A1575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Danielle Aiello, Guillermo Mendoza</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Danielle Aiello and Guillermo Mendoza</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Danielle Page Aiello, the daughter of Dorrie M. Aiello and David M. Aiello of Frankfort, N.Y., was married yesterday to Guillermo F. Mendoza, the son of Rosa Garibaldi de Mendoza and Guillermo Mendoza Serrano of Lima, Peru. Mayor Jason West of New Paltz, N.Y., performed the ceremony at the French Church in New Paltz.</p>
        <p>The bride, 26, is a candidate for a master's degree in geography from Ohio University, where she has also received a grant to pursue research on coral erosion in Roatan, Honduras. She graduated magna cum laude from the State University at New Paltz.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The couple were married at the French Church in New Paltz, N.Y., on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Danielle Page Aiello, the daughter of Dorrie M. Aiello and David M. Aiello of Frankfort, N.Y., was married yesterday to Guillermo F. Mendoza, the son of Rosa Garibaldi de Mendoza and Guillermo Mendoza Serrano of Lima, Peru. Mayor Jason West of New Paltz, N.Y., performed the ceremony at the French Church in New Paltz.</p>
        <p>The bride, 26, is a candidate for a master's degree in geography from Ohio University, where she has also received a grant to pursue research on coral erosion in Roatan, Honduras. She graduated magna cum laude from the State University at New Paltz.</p>
        <p>Her father is a truck driver for CAP Scrap Metals, a steel recycling company in Frankfort. Her mother is an office manager at the Masonic Care Community of New York, a nursing home in Utica.</p>
        <p>The bridegroom, 37, is a hydrologist working for Winrock International of Little Rock, Ark., through which he is running water-resources management for the United States Agency for International Development project in Honduras. He graduated from the University of Maryland, and received a Ph.D. in bioresource engineering from Cornell.</p>
        <p>His mother, who retired as a minister of diplomatic affairs for the Peruvian Embassy in Washington, now teaches diplomatic history at the Peruvian Diplomatic Academy in Lima. His father retired as a diplomat in Lima for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs</p>
        <p>Ms. Aiello and Mr. Mendoza met in June 2002, when both were living in New Paltz and working in Kingston, N.Y., for the New York City Department of Environmental Protection, she as an intern and he as a research scientist. ''He was a very outgoing person and threw great dinner parties,'' Ms. Aiello said.</p>
        <p>They began as friends, but by the time they arrived together at a mutual friend's Halloween party, where she dressed as a vampire witch and he as the title character from the film ''Edward Scissorhands,'' they were very much an item. In January 2005, Mr. Mendoza took a job in Honduras. Two months later, Ms. Aiello followed him there, leaving a job she had taken as an urban planner for the Dutchess County Department of Planning and Development in Poughkeepsie, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''Here was this pretty girl with a great sense of humor moving to Honduras, for me,'' Mr. Mendoza said. ''It was a major sacrifice on her part, and it meant a lot.''</p>
        <p>In July last year, Mr. Mendoza proposed in a Honduran rain forest.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
