<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pop Life</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="462369"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONCERTS AND RECITALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BLACK ENTERTAINMENT TELEVISION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUKEBOX NETWORK</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOUSTON, WHITNEY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, JAMES (SINGER)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/The Pop Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D81739F937A15754C0A967958260" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pop Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Holden</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jukebox With a Difference</p>
        <p>One of the fastest-growing cable television operations in the country is the Jukebox Network, which uses no on-air personalities and whose programming is largely determined by the viewing audience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jukebox With a Difference</p>
        <p>One of the fastest-growing cable television operations in the country is the Jukebox Network, which uses no on-air personalities and whose programming is largely determined by the viewing audience.</p>
        <p>Choosing from a menu of 200 to 300 music-video selections, a list of which runs at the bottom of the screen, viewers can order their choices by dialing a 900 number and punching in a three-digit selection number. About 20 minutes later, the selection is shown.</p>
        <p>Viewers are charged $2.50 or $3 per selection on their telephone bills. About 25 percent of the charge goes to the telephone company, and another 25 percent to the cable operator. The remainder is used to cover the costs of the company, which is not yet profitable, said Andrew Orgel, Jukebox's president, in a telephone interview from the network's Miami headquarters.</p>
        <p>Like Les Garland, vice president of programming for Jukebox, Mr. Orgel is a former MTV executive. The two left that network four years ago to develop what would become Jukebox, which began broadcasting in March 1989. Since then it has grown rapidly. With 160 affiliates in 36 states, including the District of Columbia and Puerto Rico, it now reaches about 13 million of the country's 58 million cable subscribers. On July 1, homes in Manhattan were finally given access to the network (it was already available in the other four boroughs).  Manhattan is serviced by seven separate "jukeboxes," refrigerator-like devices that have their own menu of selections and serve about 30,000 subscribers each.</p>
        <p>Where most cable services beam their programming to local cable operators via satellite, the Jukebox Network's programming is determined by local operators. This permits the tailoring of menus to serve local markets and urban neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>"On the average, 25 percent of the music is freshened on a weekly basis," said Mr. Garland. "In Manhattan, we decided to go with a 100 percent current list, in which almost everything is under 15 weeks old. We may add some jukebox classics that New York has never seen before."</p>
        <p>Nationally, he said, the volume of requests has risen to more than 600,000 a month; the network recently logged its 10 millionth selection. Jukebox broadcasts 24 hours a day. A little over 65 percent of its air time is sold out; the remaining time is used by the network for self-promotion and to allow record companies to promote new music videos. Curiously, the call patterns vary little throughout the day. The network receives roughly the same number of requests at 4 A.M. as it does at 4 P.M.</p>
        <p>The Jukebox Network has already had a decisive impact on the careers of several performers, most notably Vanilla Ice. Long before his "Ice Ice Baby" video was shown on MTV, it was programmed on Jukebox, where the early public response prompted SBK Records to buy the rapper's recording contract from a small independent label. The youthful pop star Gerardo was also introduced on the Jukebox Network performing a Spanish-language music-video version of his hit "Rico Suave." Interscope Records signed him and released a bilingual version of the song that became a major pop hit.</p>
        <p>Last week, the most requested song nationally was "O.P.P.," the debut single by Naughty by Nature, a rap trio, on Tommy Boy Records. The group, from East Orange, N.J., was discovered by Queen Latifah. The music-video is so popular that it was played as often as three times an hour in Brooklyn and five times in a half-hour period in Newark. Total plays of "O.P.P." last week amounted to "several thousand," said Mr. Garland, who refused to be more specific. The most played video of all time, he said, has been Madonna's racy music-video for "Justify My Love," which was banned by MTV but which the Jukebox Network programmed in an unedited version as soon as it was released.</p>
        <p>"We play a lot of music that MTV would never touch," said Mr. Garland. "The viewers have fed back to us that they perceive us as an underground TV station and an alternative music source."  Rap on the Charts</p>
        <p>The popularity of rap music, like that of hard rock, seems to run in seasonal cycles, with both genres selling most records during the summer months. This week, three rap-oriented albums make impressive debuts on Billboard's pop album chart, while N.W.A's "Efil4zaggin" (Ruthless/Priority) remains at No. 10.</p>
        <p>D. J. Jazzy Jeff and the Fresh Prince's album "Homebase" (Jive/RCA) enters the chart at No. 15. The album has already spawned one of the year's most successful rap singles, "Summertime," which jumps to No. 5 on the pop singles chart. The movie soundtrack from "Boyz N the Hood" (Qwest/Warner Brothers) enters the chart at No. 23.  The Geto Boys arrive on the chart at No. 33 with "We Can't Be Stopped" (Rap-a-Lot/Priority).</p>
        <p>The Geto Boys' album was released by a Houston-based label, Rap-a-Lot, after Time Warner refused it because of its graphic descriptions of sex and violence. Warner's distribution company released the group's debut album, "The Geto Boys," last year, only after heated controversy. That album remained on the chart for only seven weeks and peaked at No. 171. Pay-Per-View Concert</p>
        <p>"James Brown/Living In America," the pay-per-view concert that was broadcast on June 10, was successful enough to prompt the team of Butch Lewis Productions and Black Entertainment Productions to begin planning another pay-per-view special to be aired in November. It will feature another singer, as yet unidentified, and many celebrated guests.</p>
        <p>Around 125,000 people subscribed to Mr. Brown's show, some paying $19.95 and others $24.95 to watch. That translates to about 1 percent of all possible subscribers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
