<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MILITARY PROPOSES TO END PRODUCTION OF MOST NEW ARMS</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="502735"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1038F937A15752C0A964958260" item-length="1403" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MILITARY PROPOSES TO END PRODUCTION OF MOST NEW ARMS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a shift that could save billions of dollars in future military spending, the Pentagon plans to suspend production of most new weapons after developing test models, senior Defense Department officials said today.</p>
        <p>The production phase is by far the most expensive stage in buying a new weapons, consuming 35 to 45 percent of the total cost, while the research, design and development of test models, or prototypes, usually represents 20 to 25 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a shift that could save billions of dollars in future military spending, the Pentagon plans to suspend production of most new weapons after developing test models, senior Defense Department officials said today.</p>
        <p>The production phase is by far the most expensive stage in buying a new weapons, consuming 35 to 45 percent of the total cost, while the research, design and development of test models, or prototypes, usually represents 20 to 25 percent.</p>
        <p>Congress will ultimately decide whether the new plan goes into effect through its control over the Pentagon budget. Opposition appears likely because lawmakers, while generally favoring cuts in military spending, do not like to slash weapons manufacturing that benefits their districts and states. Contractors May Suffer</p>
        <p>But if the Pentagon's proposal is approved, the move is likely to deal a severe blow to America's military contractors, who have already been forced to lay off thousands of workers because of the Pentagon budget cuts.</p>
        <p>The new system, which would mark a sharp departure from four decades of Pentagon spending practices, means that the purchase of weapons already in production, including the B-2 bomber and the Seawolf submarine, would be curtailed or canceled, saving about $50 billion that was expected to be spent over the next five years. It would mean $6 billion to $8 billion in savings in the $291 billion Pentagon budget for the fiscal year 1993 that Congress will start considering next month.</p>
        <p>The Administration is now debating whether those savings should be applied toward a tax cut, to deficit reduction or to increased spending on domestic programs, or some combination, all of which would require Congressional approval. Heading Off Congress</p>
        <p>The effect of the decision, first reported in today's Los Angeles Times, could be much greater over the longer term because there would not be an automatic move from design to production of future generations of weapons still on the drawing board, or in the imaginations of engineers.</p>
        <p>"If this comes out as advertised, it would be a revolutionary change in the Pentagon acquisition system," said Gordon Adams, director of the Defense Budget Project, a research organization here that has long advocated cutting Pentagon spending.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon plan also appears intended to head off Congressional efforts to cut deeper and faster into the military budget by showing that the Administration is acting itself. Other Pentagon initiatives disclosed in recent days, including a plan to sharply reduce or eliminate long-range missiles with more than one warhead, were partly driven by the same consideration.</p>
        <p>Suspending weapons production would have the added benefit of giving Secretary of Defense Dick Cheney a broad rationale for curtailing or ending production of a number of new weapons that he had already hoped to jettison, including the M-1 tank, the Apache helicopter and the F-14 and F-15 fighter planes. Congress has resisted many of these cuts to protect military industries in home districts.</p>
        <p>Pentagon weapons-buyers have historically been driven to engineer and build advanced weaponry as fast as possible to counter parallel advances in the Soviet military. The end of the cold war now gives weapons-designers more warning to prepare for a new threat.  Trying for Flexibility</p>
        <p>Under the Pentagon's plan, which has received tentative White House approval, the Defense Department would still contract with companies to engineer and build weapons and equipment.</p>
        <p>But instead of following the usual course of building a number of the new weapons after development and testing of the prototype, the Pentagon would suspend production until the weapon was needed and was affordable. Ideally, the weapon could then be produced on short notice to meet a crisis.</p>
        <p>"It's a strategy geared more toward keeping more flexibility, a technological edge for the future, and still maintain current fighting forces," said Jacques Gansler, a former Pentagon procurement officer and the author of a book on Defense Department spending.  How Roles Would Change</p>
        <p>Under the current acquisition system, military contractors invest their own money heavily in research in hope of winning lucrative production contracts. Under the new system, military analysts said the Pentagon would have to devote more of what is left of its $100-billion-a-year acquisition budget to research and development to maintain a healthy cadre of contractors.</p>
        <p>"This strategy means some contractors won't be around in a few years," said Phillip Giaramita, a spokesman for the Martin Marietta Corporation, a leading military contractor. "Those fewer companies remaining will be stronger."</p>
        <p>The idea of deferring production while preserving the United States' technological edge over potential foes is not new. In the last 18 months, the Defense Budget Project, the Office of Technology Assessment and Representative Les Aspin, the Wisconsin Democrat who heads the House Armed Services Committee, have all offered similar proposals.</p>
        <p>In recent months, senior Pentagon officials have signaled a willingness to embrace the concept.</p>
        <p>"We can't afford to continue to buy as we have the last 30 to 40 years," Adm. David E. Jeremiah, the vice chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, said last month. "There will be more emphasis on R&amp;D."</p>
        <p>For Mr. Cheney, the strategy marks a significant policy change on two counts. In his first two years as Defense Secretary, Mr. Cheney cautioned against cutting money for research and development, often praising the decisions his predecessors made a decade ago in explaining the military's strong performance in the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>But in the past year, both Mr. Cheney and the chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, Gen. Colin L. Powell, have balked against cutting the military forces any deeper than the 25 percent reductions by 1995 that they first outlined two years ago. Instead, the two men decided to make cuts in expensive weapons designed a to fight a cold war Soviet opponent.</p>
        <p>With more breathing room now, Mr. Cheney is giving up production of modernized weapons to spare deeper cuts in the armed forces. The military is scheduled to shrink to 1.6 million active-duty forces in 1995 from just under 2 million now.</p>
        <p>Senior Pentagon officials say Mr. Cheney's strategy now is to build essential weapons and equipment, and develop and test new technology, but not necessarily commit to the costly full production of new tanks, planes or submarines.  The Secretary on TV</p>
        <p>"Technology is clearly something we want to continue to pursue very aggressively to maintain our edge," Mr. Cheney said last Sunday on the CBS news program "Face the Nation." "But it's possible, I think, to do that in a way without buying, for example, 8,000 new tanks for the Army and fielding all of those tanks for the Army at this point."</p>
        <p>"What we're looking at now, obviously, is a situation in which our capabilities are good enough that we can have a different set of concepts in terms of how we pursue the procurement and acquisition process in the future." Outside military analysts say they will closely watch the Pentagon's budget submission next week for proof that Defense Department officials are sincere about the new strategy.</p>
        <p>Curtailing or canceling the B-2 Stealth bomber, the Seawolf attack submarine and the Army's Comanche helicopter and tank-improvement program would all be clear signals of the new direction, the analysts said.</p>
        <p>Similarly, supporting the C-17 cargo plane, V-22 aircraft, Patriot anti-missiles and the JSTARS airborne ground-monitoring plane would be indications of systems well suited to aid the military in the new arena of far-flung, regional conflicts, Mr. Adams said.</p>
        <p>The verdict is less clear on two other costly programs now in development, such as the Air Force's new F-22 fighter jet and the Navy's AX carrier-based attack plane. One option is to buy fewer F-22's, for example, than the 650 the Air Force originally wanted. Reducing the total purchase, however, drives up the cost per plane.</p>
        <p>Other military analysts criticized the idea that building successful prototypes guaranteed trouble-free full production runs.</p>
        <p>"If the proposition is that we can do a prototype, and put it on a shelf until the war when we need it is just naive," said one Senate aide who follows the issue closely.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
