<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>14 Strikes and the Big Case of a 37-Year Career Is Out</title>
    <meta content="14SNED$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/14/national/14sneddon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1680125"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="THE JACKSON VERDICT: THE PROSECUTOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Michael</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFDB1F38F937A25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>14 Strikes and the Big Case of a 37-Year Career Is Out</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">14 Strikes and the Big Case of a 37-Year Career Is Out</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER; Adam Liptak contributed reporting from New York for this article.</byline>
      <dateline>SANTA MARIA, Calif., June 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He tried to smile. He said he had no regrets. But there was little District Attorney Thomas W. Sneddon Jr. could do to cover up the bitter disappointment of the complete and utter defeat in the biggest case he has handled in his nearly four decades as a prosecutor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sneddon, who first began investigating sexual abuse allegations against Michael Jackson 12 years ago only to be thwarted when the singer reached a $20 million settlement with his accuser, acknowledged the pain of losing such an enormous case. But he refused to second-guess the jury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>SANTA MARIA, Calif., June 13 - He tried to smile. He said he had no regrets. But there was little District Attorney Thomas W. Sneddon Jr. could do to cover up the bitter disappointment of the complete and utter defeat in the biggest case he has handled in his nearly four decades as a prosecutor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He tried to smile. He said he had no regrets. But there was little District Attorney Thomas W. Sneddon Jr. could do to cover up the bitter disappointment of the complete and utter defeat in the biggest case he has handled in his nearly four decades as a prosecutor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sneddon, who first began investigating sexual abuse allegations against Michael Jackson 12 years ago only to be thwarted when the singer reached a $20 million settlement with his accuser, acknowledged the pain of losing such an enormous case. But he refused to second-guess the jury.</p>
        <p>''I've been a prosecutor for 37 years, and for 37 years I've never quarreled with a jury's verdict, and I'm not going to do so today,'' he said. He grimly replied ''no comment'' to several questions about whether he intended to continue investigating Mr. Jackson and gave the same answer to the question of whether he believed a child molester had escaped punishment.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Sneddon put on a stoic face when he met reporters, his disappointment registered in the courtroom earlier in the afternoon as the 64-year-old prosecutor slumped in his chair when it became clear that the jury was going to deliver not guilty verdicts on all 14 of the charges they considered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sneddon later suggested that Mr. Jackson's celebrity had played a role in the acquittal. ''It seems to us that that was a factor,'' he said, ''but maybe we're just looking for explanations in the wrong places.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to look back and apologize for anything we've done,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The prosecutor said there was no turning point in the case, but he seemed to acknowledge that the accuser and his family were less than ideal witnesses. ''We don't select our victims; we don't select the family of our victims,'' he said. ''We don't look at their pedigree. We look at what we think is right.''</p>
        <p>Still, the prosecution's nine-week presentation to the jury was replete with missteps and setbacks. The mother of the boy who has accused Mr. Jackson of molesting him in 2003 spent her time on the stand describing a kidnapping in a Rolls-Royce and a scheme to make her family disappear in a hot-air balloon.</p>
        <p>The accuser himself gave differing versions of how and when the molesting began.</p>
        <p>Some legal experts said Mr. Sneddon should not have been surprised that his witnesses failed him. ''When you bring a case that requires expenditure of such enormous financial and community resources and you are so wiped out by a verdict, it calls into question the prosecutor who brought it,'' said Anthony M. Glassman, a former federal prosecutor in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''It surely could not have been a mystery that the alleged victim and his family had all the baggage they had. Those just aren't the kinds of cases that prosecutors with good judgment should be bringing.''</p>
        <p>But Jean Rosenbluth, another former federal prosecutor who is now a law professor at the University of Southern California, supported Mr. Sneddon's decision to pursue the case.</p>
        <p>''He sincerely believes Michael Jackson is a serial pedophile,'' Ms. Rosenbluth said. ''He had an obligation to put his evidence before a jury and let them decide. And some of those jurors may believe in their heart of hearts that Jackson is guilty but that it wasn't proven beyond a reasonable doubt.''</p>
        <p>It is unlikely that Mr. Sneddon will again try a case that commands the global attention of the Jackson trial. Mr. Sneddon, who is serving his sixth four-year term as district attorney, has said he will retire next year.</p>
        <p>He is, say those who have worked for and against him, a tenacious and hard-nosed prosecutor. One of his nicknames is Mad Dog, because once he gets a defendant in his grip he rarely lets go. He once tried a murder defendant three times after two hung juries, finally winning a conviction that sent the killer away for life.</p>
        <p>''He's persistent when he believes the case is there,'' said Jim Thomas, a former Santa Barbara County Sheriff who has known Mr. Sneddon for more than 20 years. ''And he was sure in this case.''</p>
        <p>When he announced in December 2003 that he was bringing charges of child molesting against Mr. Jackson, many expressed the belief that he was driven by a vendetta that dated back a decade.</p>
        <p>In 1993, Mr. Sneddon and Gil Garcetti, at the time the chief prosecutor in Los Angeles County, investigated Mr. Jackson on similar charges. Their investigation turned up several reports of Mr. Jackson sleeping with and groping boys. But their case against Mr. Jackson crumbled when the family of the main accuser reached a multimillion-dollar settlement with Mr. Jackson and refused to cooperate in any prosecution.</p>
        <p>After that, Mr. Jackson wrote a song, ''D.S.,'' about his tormenter, whom he called ''Dom Sheldon,'' which sounded very much like ''Tom Sneddon'' on the track. The refrain, repeated over and over, was ''Dom Sheldon is a cold man.''</p>
        <p>Throughout the Jackson trial, it was clear that Mr. Sneddon was offended by the superstar's behavior; he tried repeatedly to impress upon the jury that his style of life was bizarre and criminal. He portrayed Mr. Jackson's Neverland Valley Ranch as a candy-coated pedophile's lair, soaked in alcohol and stocked with pornography.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sneddon and his co-counsel, Ronald J. Zonen, the chief deputy district attorney, came into the trial with an advantage over the celebrity defendant and his Los Angeles defense attorney, Thomas A. Mesereau Jr. Both residents of Santa Barbara County, they appeared to have a better feel for the jurors, most of whom came from the conservative and largely agricultural northern part of the county.</p>
        <p>The few blacks in the jury pool during the jury selection process were dismissed by the prosecution, although one young black man was kept on as an alternate. Mr. Sneddon showed a certain racial tone-deafness near the end of the trial, when the actor Chris Tucker, who is black, was on the stand as a defense witness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sneddon showed a photograph of Mr. Tucker with the accuser and his family, which Mr. Tucker said he had not seen. He asked if he could have a copy.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sneddon replied, ''It depends on whether you're a good boy or not.'' There were gasps in the courtroom, but Mr. Sneddon did not appear to comprehend what he had said.</p>
        <p>Craig A. Smith, a former prosecutor in Mr. Sneddon's office who now teaches law at the Santa Barbara College of Law, said that losing such a case would not be easy for the competitive district attorney.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure he will take this hard,'' Mr. Smith said, ''but it's not going to be the end of the world. His feeling will be, We may have lost, but at least the defendant had to work for his acquittal.''</p>
        <p>THE JACKSON VERDICT: THE PROSECUTOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
