<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parents Must Demand Better Principals</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="329659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTICUT OPINION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRINCIPALS (SCHOOL)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED9123CF936A15751C0A966958260" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parents Must Demand Better Principals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Herbert F. Pandiscio; Herbert. F. Pandiscio has been Superintendent of Schools in Avon for 22 years.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: MOST recent education reform has been a ''top down'' effort. The governors of several states and a handful of education commissioners have taken the lead in addressing problems in the schools. In Connecticut, both the Governor and the Commissioner of Education are acknowledged leaders in this area.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: MOST recent education reform has been a ''top down'' effort. The governors of several states and a handful of education commissioners have taken the lead in addressing problems in the schools. In Connecticut, both the Governor and the Commissioner of Education are acknowledged leaders in this area.</p>
        <p>MOST recent education reform has been a ''top down'' effort. The governors of several states and a handful of education commissioners have taken the lead in addressing problems in the schools. In Connecticut, both the Governor and the Commissioner of Education are acknowledged leaders in this area.</p>
        <p>Most of the reform efforts address four areas: improvement in teacher salaries, tougher certification requirements, closer adherence to existing education laws and retraining for senior teachers. All these are vitally important to school improvement. These reforms have done much to attract and keep the most qualified teachers and have helped to build public confidence in our schools.</p>
        <p>But the inner workings of the schools, like those of private industry, are often not known to the clients. While information about the schools is more readily available, experience tells me that much of what parents anf the public learn about the schools is not very accurate.</p>
        <p>For example, few parents understand the importance of the principal in the development of teachers. Most of the educational research in the 1980's indicates that the building principal has more influence in shaping reform than any other person or group in a school district. But parents usually know far less about the principal's qualifications than they do about their children's teachers.</p>
        <p>Why should parents be concerned about the quality of school administrators when many local boards and state education departments are concerned only with the teachers? It's difficult to imagine a major corporation being careless in hiring a manager for an important profit center. Yet many school boards have an inadequate system for insuring that they hire the best candidates for administrative jobs.</p>
        <p>I am not suggesting that governing boards have hired incompetent administrators. But they often hire people who are marginally competent because there are so few outstanding administrators available.</p>
        <p>Why? The recent enhancement of teachers' salaries and benefits, without a corresponding improvement for administrators, has dramatically closed the economic gap between the two groups. A teacher employed for 185 a year days generally earns more for each day than an administrator. Consequently, many teachers who once aspired to administration no longer do. Coupled with the aging administrative population, this poses a threat to our schools' success.</p>
        <p>Local boards and state officials have been remiss in not improving the relative economic status of administrators. Parents tend to believe that administrators have been given the same enhancements as teachers, when this is often not so. Unless action is taken to deal with the shrinking pool of qualified school administrators, public education will face a leadership crisis by the time the present kindergarten classes enter the upper elementary grades.</p>
        <p>Once that pool of qualified school administrators has been expanded, administrators must be trained to lead effectively in the new millennium. Teachers are beginning to be treated as professionals. Accordingly, they demand an improved administrative climate in which to work.</p>
        <p>Today's teachers want a principal who provides the opportunity for them to be part of a collaborative setting. Gone are the days of dominant, arbitrary leadership, when the principal viewed himself as the school's only visionary.</p>
        <p>Creativity, vision, leadership, and brilliance reside in all educators, teacher and administrator alike. Therefore, each person must play a role. Principals, to be effective, must master the skills of collaboration and facilitation. They must demonstrate brilliance, not at pronouncing answers to questions only they have created, but in creating a climate in which all professionals are nurtured.</p>
        <p>Where are these principals? Some manage our schools now. Most are yet to be trained, and they will be difficult to hire because the demand for their talents will far exceed the supply.</p>
        <p>Parents, particularly those with preschool children or those with youngsters in the early grades, must demand better qualified administrators for their schools. Parents must work with their school boards, urging them to establish administrators' salaries that attract only superior candidates.</p>
        <p>Whenever there is an administrative vacancy, parents must ask their board of education to define the criteria for hiring, to establish an attractive economic package, and to give assurances that assessment tools are in place to check candidates' credentials. Parents must know that funds are available to assure that the new administrator continues to receive training while working in the community. And parents should require that an effective and fair assessment process is in place to measure the principal's work.</p>
        <p>Boards must place emphasis on hiring administrators who have mastered the skills of collaboration and who demonstrate the ability to work effectively with others. And like businesses, schools must underwrite new administrators' moving expenses.</p>
        <p>Unless parents take the initiative in working for these improvements, their children will not be able to derive the maximum benefits from their teachers. Without outstanding leadership, there can be no outstanding schools.</p>
        <p>CONNECTICUT OPINION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
