<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campus Life: Brandeis;   Student Boycott Gains Staff Change At Bookstore</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="44" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="329866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOYCOTTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BARNES &amp; NOBLE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRANDEIS UNIVERSITY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DC1530F936A15751C0A966958260" item-length="449" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campus Life: Brandeis;   Student Boycott Gains Staff Change At Bookstore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WALTHAM, Mass.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Hundreds of students at Brandeis University ended a weeklong boycott of the Barnes &amp; Noble campus bookstore on Wednesday after the company agreed to replace two managers accused of discriminating against black customers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Hundreds of students at Brandeis University ended a weeklong boycott of the Barnes &amp; Noble campus bookstore on Wednesday after the company agreed to replace two managers accused of discriminating against black customers.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of students at Brandeis University ended a weeklong boycott of the Barnes &amp; Noble campus bookstore on Wednesday after the company agreed to replace two managers accused of discriminating against black customers.</p>
        <p>Barnes &amp; Noble denied that the managers had been involved in ''deliberate racial harassment or discrimination,'' as the students had asserted, but promised to move them to another store and to take other steps to show greater sensitivity to blacks.</p>
        <p>Thirty black students accused the managers of suspecting them of being shoplifters and scrutinizing their actions in the bookstore because of their race. More than 700 of the school's 3,700 undergraduate and graduate students signed a pledge saying they would not patronize the bookstore until the managers were removed. The university enrolls about 90 black undergraduate and graduate students.</p>
        <p>After investigating the charges, officials of Barnes &amp; Noble College Bookstores praised David Strati, the manager, and Thomas Fitzgerald, the assistant manager, as ''valued employees with exemplary records,'' but said they would place a new management team at the Brandeis store by March 12. The boycott began Feb. 13.</p>
        <p>Inquiry by University</p>
        <p>The company also agreed to establish a new system to handle grievances, make a ''concerted attempt'' to hire more black students and implement a racial-sensitivity and awareness-training program for all employees.</p>
        <p>The university's affirmative-action officer, Cynthia Costas-Centivany, conducted her own investigation and said her findings were consistent with the book company's review.</p>
        <p>Although pleased that the managers are being replaced, boycott organizers said that what they described as incidents of discrimination were symptoms of campuswide racism, and that they planned to continue protesting in other ways.</p>
        <p>In fliers distributed throughout the week, students said they want the school to establish a stronger policy against racial harassment; to recruit more black faculty members and students; to include in the curriculum more extensive study of African, Asian, Latin-American and Indian cultures, and to expand a one-room intercultural library into a full-fledged intercultural center. Charging that the campus police harass black men, they also opposed a proposal to give the police firearms.</p>
        <p>The university vice president for public affairs, David Rosen, denied that there was systematic racism at Brandeis and said: ''The administration continues to be ready, willing and able to meet with students to discuss concrete issues. The university is strongly committed to the recruitment of additional black faculty and the enrollment of all minorities.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
