<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getting Arafat to Sit For a TV Portrait</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="329808"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRITISH BROADCASTING CORP (BBC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PALESTINE LIBERATION ORGANIZATION (PLO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEFFEN, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARAFAT, YASIR</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FACES OF ARAFAT, THE (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D71630F936A15751C0A966958260" item-length="1468" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getting Arafat to Sit For a TV Portrait</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YOUSSEF M. IBRAHIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Putting Yasir Arafat in an hourlong documentary film is like pinning down a ball of mercury: a heroic effort requiring patience, perseverence and a great deal of money.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Putting Yasir Arafat in an hourlong documentary film is like pinning down a ball of mercury: a heroic effort requiring patience, perseverence and a great deal of money.</p>
        <p>Putting Yasir Arafat in an hourlong documentary film is like pinning down a ball of mercury: a heroic effort requiring patience, perseverence and a great deal of money.</p>
        <p>Among other things, it involves keeping a film crew on call night and day waiting for appointments that begin at 2 A.M. in places as far apart as Beijing, Tunis, Baghdad, Casablanca and Cairo, filming around nervous gun-toting Palestinian guards and losing all sense of time and place. That is why, says the film maker Anthony Geffen of the British Broadcasting Corporation, it took so long to craft his documentary on the chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization. ''I was planning on six to seven months, but it has taken well over a year,'' Mr. Geffen said during a recent interview at the BBC.</p>
        <p>The documentary, titled ''The Faces of Arafat,'' traces Mr. Arafat's career back to his early days as a student at Cairo University's Engineering Faculty and reviews with former and present associates the shaping of his career as a guerrilla fighter and politician. ''The Faces of Arafat'' will be broadcast Tuesday evening at 9 on PBS's ''Frontline'' series, with Channel 13 in the New York City area carrying it an hour later.</p>
        <p>Because the colorful 60-year-old leader, who is unmarried, has devoted so much of his career to the Palestinian cause, his personal and political lives are virtually intertwined as one, and while the film provides no startling revelations, it does set out to sketch a portrait of him in human terms. In addition to family snapshots of Mr. Arafat as a child and a young man, there are interviews with relatives, acquaintances and former professors. ''We very quickly realized that Arafat will not tell you much about Arafat,'' said the 28-year-old Mr. Geffen, whose documentary on Hirohito, the late Emperor of Japan, won broad acclaim when shown early last year.</p>
        <p>''Everyone said Arafat was going to be difficult, and in the end it was far more so than I could have imagined,'' said Mr. Geffen. ''Until three months ago, I still worried that I wasn't getting to the crux of the subject. I couldn't get the people around Arafat to start talking about him.''</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Arafat's reluctance to discuss his personal life and experiences across 40 years of working in behalf of the Palestinian cause, the principal difficulty seemed to be what Mr. Geffen calls Mr. Arafat's ''totally chaotic'' way of operating. That included scheduling interviews and then canceling them on a moment's notice and departing for trips overseas without specifying - because of security reasons - his destination until the film makers were installed on board a plane and safely out of contact with the rest of the world.</p>
        <p>At one point, Mr. Geffen's associate in the project, Marie Colvin, an American journalist who covers the Middle East for The Sunday Times of London, and a BBC film crew traveled some 20 hours all the way to Beijing where Mr. Arafat had scheduled a meeting. They arrived only to discover that the his visit had been canceled by Chinese authorities who were anticipating the events of Tiananmen Square and had asked Mr. Arafat to put off his visit, just days before they ordered a crackdown on the student demonstrators in the capital. The documentary team was told that the interview had been rescheduled for a few days later in Tunis, another 20 hours away by air.</p>
        <p>According to Mr. Geffen and Ms. Colvin, the production, a joint effort between WGBH of Boston and BBC-1 in England, is the first in-depth look at Mr. Arafat, even though the Palestinian leader is among the world's most accessible public figures. Mr. Geffen said the biggest challenge in making the film was to go beyond what is known about Mr. Arafat and to question everything that is already known about him. For this purpose he asked Ms. Colvin, who has been a Middle East correspondent for three years, to join him in the project and to serve as the on-camera interviewer, with a mission to, as he put it, ''go back to square one, wipe the book clear and get sources on everything that is known about Arafat.''</p>
        <p>''What we wanted to show,'' Ms. Colvin said, ''is the man behind the public figure.''</p>
        <p>As it happens, both Mr. Geffen and Ms. Colvin agreed that what the film accomplished was to get close to Mr. Arafat for a lengthy period of time, to verify many of the known facts about him with witnesses who have come across him over the years, and, in Mr. Geffen's words, ''in a sense pull it all together in one film.'' A few clips that were screened during the interview at the BBC suggest that the P.L.O. used its technique of flying reporters around in Mr. Arafat's private jet - a treatment that has, over the past few months, been routinely granted to favored journalists, presumably not only to gain good press for Mr. Arafat but also to impress his visitors with his role as the head of the Palestinian movement.</p>
        <p>The 33-year-old Ms. Colvin emphasized that the film ''is not a partisan endeavor to support Mr. Arafat's views or the Palestinian cause.'' The financing of roughly $450,000 came jointly from BBC and the Public Broadcasting Service, and both Ms. Colvin and Mr. Geffen insist that no other underwriters were involved.</p>
        <p>Ms. Colvin, who has developed a network of well-placed contacts within the P.L.O. and has written many articles chronicling the ups and downs of the Palestinian movement, said the moment she got involved with the Arafat project she began visiting various Palestinian officials whom she had come to know over the years so she could explain the thrust of the documentary. ''We made it very clear it is not a P.L.O.-sponsored film,'' she said, ''and that the P.L.O. would have absolutely no editorial control over any portions of it.''</p>
        <p>Among other things, Mr. Geffen said, all translations from Arabic were made by interpreters hired by the BBC. Asked if he and PBS, nevertheless, expected strong objections to the film from the pro-Israeli lobby in the United States, Mr. Geffen said, ''I tried not to take this into account, but to be very, very sensitive.''</p>
        <p>Just how sensitive the issue of financing documentaries on the Middle East can be was underscored last fall when ''Days of Rage: The Young Palestinians,'' a film about the Palestinian uprisings in Israeli-occupied territories, was shown on public television in the United States. The film, which was decidedly pro-Palestinian, was made by Jo Franklin-Trout, an independent producer.</p>
        <p>After questions about the financing of the film were raised, PBS began investigating the matter. At first, Ms. Franklin-Trout said she had financed the film with her own money. It was subsequently disclosed, however, that the Arab-American Cultural Foundation had paid her $33,000 to help finance two of her previous films. Further, the foundation had earlier promoted itself as a sponsor of ''Days of Rage,'' and Ms. Franklin-Trout had served for more than two years on its board.</p>
        <p>The Arafat project, Ms. Colvin stressed, was designed to show what the leader of the Palestinian movement was like as a person. ''You may hate him, you may love him, but you'll get to know him,'' she said. ''We are showing Arafat as a human being. If that is sympathetic in some people's view, so be it.'' The film attempts to clear up some myths surrounding Mr. Arafat's life. One of those is that Mr. Arafat was already a millionaire contractor in Kuwait before giving up a rewarding career to work in behalf of the P.L.O. ''He was a successful engineer, but no millionaire,'' Ms. Colvin said.</p>
        <p>Another interesting point about the P.L.O. leader is that he was born, and largely raised, in Egypt, not Palestine, which accounts for his heavy Egyptian accent. The most sensitive issue surrounding Mr. Arafat, which is whether he has engaged in terrorism, or indeed, whether he continues to be a terrorist, is not as clear-cut. While being questioned on the subject of terrorism, Mr. Arafat is seen in the film growing visibly irritated. As Ms. Colvin insists on an answer, Mr. Arafat loudly protests that as the chairman of the P.L.O. and the president of a yet-to-be-established Palestinian state he was not there to respond only to questions about terrorism but to talk about the larger issue of settling the 40-year-old Palestinian-Israeli conflict.</p>
        <p>Finally, as Ms. Colvin presses on with her questions, Mr. Arafat ends the interview and walks away.Ms. Colvin had to wait another two months before she could resume the interviews.</p>
        <p>''There were many moments when I thought, 'Why am I doing this?' '' Ms. Colvin said, adding, however, that with the project behind her she is pleased with the result. ''Arafat remains a very closed and difficult person to really know,'' she said, ''but I am satisfied that we got about as close to him as anyone can.''  TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
