<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reverberations of a Fading Boom</title>
    <meta content="14WED2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1053941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DC143AF937A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reverberations of a Fading Boom</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are great advantages for New York in being the financial capital of the world. But there is a downside. When financial markets are roiled, and investors grow hesitant, Wall Street inevitably cuts back. Those cuts are likely to have a larger impact on the New York region than on other areas. It would be wise for city and state officials to start planning now for reduced tax revenues.</p>
        <p>The rounds of Wall Street layoffs are just beginning, and could be larger than those that followed the 1987 stock market crash. Merrill Lynch, which yesterday announced plans to lay off 3,400 employees and 900 consultants -- about 1,500 in the metropolitan area -- believes it erred in 1987 by not reacting quickly enough.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are great advantages for New York in being the financial capital of the world. But there is a downside. When financial markets are roiled, and investors grow hesitant, Wall Street inevitably cuts back. Those cuts are likely to have a larger impact on the New York region than on other areas. It would be wise for city and state officials to start planning now for reduced tax revenues.</p>
        <p>The rounds of Wall Street layoffs are just beginning, and could be larger than those that followed the 1987 stock market crash. Merrill Lynch, which yesterday announced plans to lay off 3,400 employees and 900 consultants -- about 1,500 in the metropolitan area -- believes it erred in 1987 by not reacting quickly enough.</p>
        <p>Wall Street is being hurt by more than lower stock prices. Securities firms make much of their business underwriting new securities and selling them to investors. But the volume of such under writings has fallen sharply as investors have shunned bonds from all but the safest companies. Merrill pointed to bond markets and to emerging markets -- Asia and Latin America -- as the areas where the cuts would be steepest.</p>
        <p>By one measure, the securities industry is not a very big part of the local economy. Stephen Kagann, Gov. George Pataki's top economist, notes that just 3.3 percent of the people with jobs in the city and its New York suburbs work for Wall Street firms.</p>
        <p>But Wall Street's economic importance is far greater than that figure would indicate. Not only are there workers in related industries, such as banking and insurance, but the Wall Street jobs have been both the best-paying and the fastest-growing. The average income for those who work in the securities business in New York was $172,000 last year, or about four times the average for all downstate New York employees. That figure is inflated because many of Wall Street's lower-paying back-office jobs are now in New Jersey, but it remains impressive.</p>
        <p>That figure is likely to fall. Much of the Wall Street payments come in the form of bonuses paid early in the calendar year. Even for those who keep their jobs, next year's bonuses are likely to be sharply lower. That has negative implications for  high-end retailers and expensive home sales, as well as for state and city income-tax collections. New York politicians accustomed to the budget surpluses that have been generated in part by the Wall Street boom had better trim back their expectations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
