<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>General Motors Posts Loss of $809 Million</title>
    <meta content="Y14MOTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1053933"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY REPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DC143AF937A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>General Motors Posts Loss of $809 Million</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Oct. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The General Motors Corporation lost $809 million in the third quarter, mainly because of a nearly eight-week-long strike that ended on July 29 and crippled G.M.'s production in North America, the auto maker announced today.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s loss of $1.28 a diluted share was slightly better than analysts' expectations. The company's North American operations continued to cut costs aggressively, paying less for auto parts and making factories more efficient. But today's report also showed that the company had been discounting its vehicles heavily in North America while its foreign operations were beginning to suffer from economic troubles overseas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The General Motors Corporation lost $809 million in the third quarter, mainly because of a nearly eight-week-long strike that ended on July 29 and crippled G.M.'s production in North America, the auto maker announced today.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s loss of $1.28 a diluted share was slightly better than analysts' expectations. The company's North American operations continued to cut costs aggressively, paying less for auto parts and making factories more efficient. But today's report also showed that the company had been discounting its vehicles heavily in North America while its foreign operations were beginning to suffer from economic troubles overseas.</p>
        <p>Auto analysts said that the strike at two G.M. auto parts factories in Flint, Mich., had caused so much disruption that it was hard to draw firm conclusions from the quarter's results. ''The best thing about the third quarter is it's over,'' said Michael Ward, an analyst at Paine Webber. ''Going forward, the news should get more positive.''</p>
        <p>G.M. said the strike cost it $1.2 billion in the third quarter, the same amount it lost to the strike during the second quarter. Michael Losh, G.M.'s chief financial officer, said in a telephone interview that the $2.4 billion in after-tax losses from the strike should be pared to roughly $2 billion by the end of the year as factories continue to work overtime to make up lost production.</p>
        <p>G.M. earned $1.04 billion during the third quarter of 1997, or $1.34 a share, but those figures included aerospace operations that G.M. has since sold. Excluding the aerospace operations, the strike and a $271 million after-tax charge for the disposal of some auto parts factories, G.M.'s profits fell 28.4 percent during the third quarter, to $697 million, compared with $973 million in the quarter a year earlier.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s sales in the third quarter plunged to $34.42 billion, from $41.89 billion in the quarter a year earlier, partly because some operations were sold but mainly because of the strike.</p>
        <p>Mr. Losh said that with the third quarter behind it, G.M. was well positioned for the fourth quarter. The introductions of new pickup trucks in North America and the new Opel Astra sedan in Europe were expensive during the third quarter but should start helping the auto maker's results, he said.</p>
        <p>While G.M. spent an unusually high average of $1,732 a vehicle in discounts in the North American market during the third quarter, that figure fell to $1,400 for sales at the end of September, Mr. Losh said. Full-sized pickup trucks require virtually no discounts to sell, and G.M. had very few of them until the end of the quarter because it was changing the design.</p>
        <p>The weakening of the dollar this month may also make it harder for foreign auto makers to offer discounts, easing the pressure on G.M. to provide large discounts. ''One of the things that ought to help us is the yen is not 135 or 145'' to the dollar, Mr. Losh said. The dollar was trading at 119.15 yen late today in New York.</p>
        <p>Financial analysts generally accepted G.M.'s predictions that with the strike more than two months in the past, discounts might dwindle. ''Once you get your '98 models cleared out and your floor traffic back, then you can cut the incentives,'' said Greg L. Salchow, an auto analyst at Roney &amp; Company, a brokerage house here.</p>
        <p>Investors had little reaction today to G.M.'s results. Shares of G.M. fell 87.5 cents, to $51.0625, in a falling market.</p>
        <p>G.M. announced plans in August to sell or spin off a 20 percent stake in Delphi Automotive Systems, its huge auto parts subsidiary, early next year, and Mr. Losh reaffirmed those plans today. G.M.'s longstanding intention to wait until next year may allow enough time for financial markets to settle down, he said.</p>
        <p>The strike pushed G.M.'s cash reserves down to $11.5 billion on Sept. 30 from $14.6 billion a year earlier and $12.1 billion on June 30. Mr. Losh said that G.M. expected the reserves to rebound soon to the company's target of $13 billion. When that happens, G.M. will resume the $4 billion share buyback program that it announced in March and suspended last summer in response to the strike, he added.</p>
        <p>One of the sharpest tumbles in G.M.'s earnings occurred in the unit handling automotive operations in Latin America, Africa and the Middle East. Mainly because of the high interest rates and weak economy in Brazil, previously one of G.M.'s most profitable markets, the division reported a loss in the third quarter of $64 million after a $165 million after-tax profit a year earlier.</p>
        <p>G.M. automotive operations in Europe earned $50 million in the third quarter after losing $21 million in the quarter a year earlier. G.M.'s tiny Asian automotive division made $2 million in profits in the last three months after losing $7 million in the third quarter of last year. The General Motors Acceptance Corporation, which makes car loans and leases, earned $313 million in the third quarter, virtually unchanged from a $312 million gain in the quarter a year earlier.</p>
        <p>COMPANY REPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
