<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Museums Struggle to Recoup; With Attendance Down, Institutions Plan Special Programs to Regain Visitors</title>
    <meta content="08MUSE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/08/arts/design/08MUSE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1331958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Dinitia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Industry News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pentagon Building</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">World Trade Center</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lowry, Glenn D</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DD133CF93BA35753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1804" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Museums Struggle to Recoup; With Attendance Down, Institutions Plan Special Programs to Regain Visitors</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Museums Struggle to Recoup With Attendance Down</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DINITIA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Dinitia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Museums in New York City and elsewhere are struggling to recoup sharp losses in attendance and revenues that followed Sept 11 terrorist attacks; some museum emerged from disaster relatively unscathed, while many smaller ones in lower Manhattan near World Trade Center site were closed for several weeks and may need years to recover; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For weeks after the terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center, the Hall of Saurischian Dinosaurs at the American Museum of Natural History was eerily silent.</p>
        <p>Normally it is one of the most popular tourist destinations in New York City, echoing with the clatter and clamor of children. But until the last few days the giant dinosaurs Apatosaurus (also known as Brontosaurus) and Tyrannosaurus rex had for the most part lorded it over the hall in solitary splendor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With attendance down since the terrorist attacks, museums are planning special programs to regain their audiences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For weeks after the terrorist attacks on the World Trade Center, the Hall of Saurischian Dinosaurs at the American Museum of Natural History was eerily silent.</p>
        <p>Normally it is one of the most popular tourist destinations in New York City, echoing with the clatter and clamor of children. But until the last few days the giant dinosaurs Apatosaurus (also known as Brontosaurus) and Tyrannosaurus rex had for the most part lorded it over the hall in solitary splendor.</p>
        <p>Like most museums in the city, as well as some others around the country, the Museum of Natural History experienced a drastic drop in attendance -- in its case, a 50 percent drop since Sept. 11 -- and a major loss of revenue from admissions fees, bookshops and cafeterias.</p>
        <p>Some museums are beginning to rebound, but many smaller ones in lower Manhattan near the World Trade Center site had to close their doors for several weeks and may need years to recover, administrators say. Museums also expect that donors will divert contributions from cultural institutions to relief efforts. And as they survey the damage the museums are struggling to come up with ways to recoup.</p>
        <p>The Metropolitan Museum of Art saw a 60 percent decrease in attendance right after the attacks, said David E. McKinney, the president. Like many museums, the Met opened its doors free for several days. Altogether it lost about $2 million, or 54 percent of its usual revenues from admission fees, restaurants and shops. Mr. McKinney said those funds account for nearly 27 percent of the museum's operating costs.</p>
        <p>But visitors are coming back, he said. On Thursday, the last day for which figures were available, attendance was down by only 24 percent compared with the same day last year.</p>
        <p>The Museum of Modern Art lost about 50 percent of its visitors during the last few weeks, compared with the same period last year. ''We don't now how much revenue we've lost,'' said the museum's director, Glenn D. Lowry. ''But it's going to be into the hundreds of thousands of dollars if not substantially more.'' The Modern depends on admissions fees and store sales for about 20 percent of its operating budget.</p>
        <p>Ellen Futter, the president of the Museum of Natural History, said she also did not know how much money her institution has lost. ''But I can tell you we are assessing it,'' she added.</p>
        <p>Mr. McKinney said that the Cultural Institutions Group, whose members get the greater part of city arts financing, had met to try and assess the impact but that it had no solid figures. ''My feeling,'' he said, ''is we should be applying for relief funds, but we haven't yet.''</p>
        <p>A few museums emerged from the disaster relatively unscathed. The Whitney Museum of American Art said it had only about a 14 percent decline in attendance. ''I think part of that frankly is our mission as a museum of American art,'' said the Whitney's director, Maxwell L. Anderson. ''A lot of our audiences say how grateful they are to be able to come and admire the creative achievements of artists in this country.''</p>
        <p>Still, the Whitney has seen a 30 percent decrease in revenues from ticket sales, sales of books and the cafeteria since Sept. 11. ''At the end of the year there will be a price to pay,'' said Mr. Anderson.</p>
        <p>Downtown, Michael Govan, director of the Dia Center for the Arts, at 545 West 22nd Street in Chelsea, said the center had only a small decrease in its usual attendance, to about 1,300 visitors from 1,500 to 1,600.</p>
        <p>In Washington, where Reagan National Airport was closed until Thursday because of the attack on the Pentagon, attendance at the Smithsonian Institution was down 38 percent, said Linda St. Thomas, a spokeswoman. The Smithsonian lost 65 percent of its revenues for last month, compared with September of last year. But ''people are coming back gradually,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Art Institute of Chicago, which  expected to sell out its much anticipated exhibition ''Van Gogh and Gauguin: The Studio of the South,'' which opened on Sept. 22, still had tickets available last week, said Eileen Harakal, a spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>Even the J. Paul Getty Museum in Los Angeles, far from the disaster, has ''noticed some drop in attendance,'' said Deborah Gribbon, the director, ''but it is not the dramatic one that museums in New York and Washington are reporting.''</p>
        <p>Edward Able, the president of the American Association of Museums, attributed the losses to a decline in tourism resulting from a reluctance to fly, especially to New York. He added that ''the general population is rather reluctant to gather in large public spaces.'' But Mr. Able added,  ''I think that will wane.''</p>
        <p>By far the hardest hit have been museums in downtown New York, the locale of many younger artists. Until last week many of those museums were nearly empty.</p>
        <p>''Everyone is just reeling from the shocks of the 11th,'' said Lisa Phillips, director of the New Museum of Contemporary Art, at 583 Broadway in SoHo. ''There is a reluctance by even the most intrepid New Yorkers to come downtown, certainly for out-of-towners.''</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, Exit Art, at 548 Broadway, between Prince and Spring Streets, was completely empty. The only signs of life, besides the staff, were three large photographs of women's lips, by Sandra Bermudez, titled ''I Want You, I Miss You, I Need You.'' In one gallery a video monitor played a piece called ''Freestyle'' by Patrick Martinez, with scenes of planes taking off and nose-diving.</p>
        <p>''The first Saturday after the attack we were packed with people who came over to me with tears in their eyes and said thank you for being open,'' said Jeanette Ingberman, one of Exit Art's co-founders. ''I think right after, people wanted to show some kind of support.'' Now, she said, ''it's dropped -- a lot.''</p>
        <p>Below Canal Street, closer to the World Trade Center, the decline was especially severe. Approximately eight museums are there, some operating on small margins. There are also visitors centers at various institutions. Access to the area has been difficult, if not impossible at times. Limited subway service has resumed, and most museums are now accessible.</p>
        <p>''Volunteers and staff are fearful of coming downtown,'' said Brian Thompson, director of the Museum of Financial History at 26 Broadway, near Bowling Green. ''Now they are threatened by environmental conditions.''</p>
        <p>Most museums below Canal Street have reopened.</p>
        <p>The George Gustav Heye Center of the Smithsonian National Museum of the American Indian, at Bowling Green, where soldiers were bivouacked in the lobby until last week,  has reopened two galleries. ''The first day we had about 160 people,'' said John Haworth, the director. ''Usually we have many more --  1,000 to 2,000 is a typical day.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Haworth said he did not know when other galleries would open. ''We want to make sure the building is properly cleaned and the air filters,'' he said. ''We are looking at our security procedures to make sure the public feels safe coming to our space.''</p>
        <p>The Museum of Jewish Heritage, in Battery Park City, reopened on Friday. A spokeswoman said the museum was always conscious of security but would not comment on it.</p>
        <p>One block south of Canal Street at 79 Walker Street, the offices of Art in General, a nonprofit gallery and educational center for alternative art, closed after the attacks and reopened on Sept. 22. ''It's been a huge hardship,'' said Holly Block, the executive director of Art in General, which has a staff of 13, eight of them full time.</p>
        <p>''We have definitely lost revenues,'' Ms. Block said. ''We have a major benefit coming up in November,'' in a banquet hall in Chinatown. ''We are afraid people won't come.'' In addition, said Ms. Block, ''I anticipate a loss of 25 percent from fund-raising, from individuals. They are giving money to other places, to the relief effort.''</p>
        <p>Still, said Ms. Block, Art in General plans to go ahead with its exhibit of artists influenced by the Fluxus movement, and the first of a two-part installation of public art along Canal Street. The first part opens on Tuesday. The second is scheduled to begin in March.</p>
        <p>''If we can't raise the money we won't be able to do the program in the spring,'' she said. ''After cutting the program, we would have to cut the staff.''</p>
        <p>To try to regain their audiences, museums are planning special programs. The Met, the Modern and the Museum of Natural History are considering joint advertising campaigns, cross-promotions and package tours.</p>
        <p>The Met has been holding concerts (free with museum admission),  ''Sounds of Solace,'' daily (except Mondays) at noon in the Great Hall. There have also been poetry readings daily at 2 p.m., in the American Wing.</p>
        <p>The Modern is changing its advertising to focus on a local audience, said Mr. Lowry. In promoting its Giacometti centennial exhibition, which opens on Thursday, Mr. Lowry said, ''we've shifted our marketing initiative away from a lot of publications and ads targeted at foreign visitors.''</p>
        <p>''We are now going to shift to The Village Voice, Newsday, The Daily News and so on,'' Mr. Lowry said,  ''and community-based papers in Lower Manhattan and Queens.'' The museum will also buy more radio spots.</p>
        <p>The Museum of Natural History is planning an open house on Saturday, with cultural programming for all ages. Together with the Council on Foreign Relations it is scheduled to hold ''The World at Ground Zero: Repercussions of 9/11,'' with Tom Brokaw as host, and panelists to include Richard Holbrooke, former United States ambassador to the United Nations, on Oct. 25.</p>
        <p>Downtown, businesses and cultural institutions are banding together to seek a tax-free zone that would encourage visitors. Exit Art is planning a regular Friday night multimedia performance program, with free food, starting in about two weeks.</p>
        <p>At the Museum for African Art, at 593 Broadway in SoHo, the show ''Bamana: The Art of Existence in Mali,'' opened on Sept. 19, six days late. ''It has a strong spiritual component to it,'' said Anne Stark, deputy director of the museum. ''In Africa art and healing go together, and particularly in this show there is a strong connection between individual and community wellness.''</p>
        <p>For its first week the show was free because of the disaster. Now,  ''we are looking for a corporate sponsor to help us underwrite free admission for this exhibition till March 3,'' said Ms. Stark. ''If they were to come through the doors they would find it serene and nurturing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
