<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Case For Duckman As a Scapegoat</title>
    <meta content="14NYC.$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031831"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haberman, Clyde</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Duckman, Lorin (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Oliver, Benito</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Komar, Galina</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E0D61031F937A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="758" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Case For Duckman As a Scapegoat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Haberman, Clyde</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clyde Haberman column opposes New York State Court of Appeals decision upholding removal of Criminal Court Judge Lorin Duckman from bench; contends that Gov George E Pataki and Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani went after Duckman in 1996 after he set relatively low bail for Benito Oliver, man jailed on domestic-abuse charge, who killed former girlfriend Galina Komar and himself after he was released on bail; maintains that Duckman may not be wisest judge, but you have to ask how well anyone's reputation would hold up if put under microscope way his was once politicians decided that he must go; Duckman photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT is safe to say that Lorin Duckman, formerly Judge Lorin Duckman, is one of the more reviled public figures in New York City. The attacks against him have been so harsh, you would almost think that Mr. Duckman alone stood between New York and Periclean bliss.</p>
        <p>His critics' line of reasoning leads to one logical conclusion: Now that he has been booted off the bench, in a decision upheld last week by the State Court of Appeals, we can expect a flawless city where no one is murdered, no man beats his wife and everyone is ineffably courteous.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT is safe to say that Lorin Duckman, formerly Judge Lorin Duckman, is one of the more reviled public figures in New York City. The attacks against him have been so harsh, you would almost think that Mr. Duckman alone stood between New York and Periclean bliss.</p>
        <p>His critics' line of reasoning leads to one logical conclusion: Now that he has been booted off the bench, in a decision upheld last week by the State Court of Appeals, we can expect a flawless city where no one is murdered, no man beats his wife and everyone is ineffably courteous.</p>
        <p>Still, it did not seem an affront to democracy to visit Mr. Duckman yesterday in his house near Prospect Park in Brooklyn to hear his version of events. What he went through these last two years, he said, was nothing less than a ''lynching.'' It was an opinion that might be dismissed as mutterings of a bitter man, except that dissenting judges on the Court of Appeals came close to saying the same thing in more judicial language.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, a dissenting opinion is more of an eye-opener than a majority ruling, especially when, as in this case, the majority writes with the blandness of someone going through the motions and the minority writes with fervor. Here is what one impassioned dissenter, Judge Vito J. Titone, said in part about the Duckman affair:</p>
        <p>''The implication of the present disciplinary proceeding is that judges whose rulings displease the political powers that be may be subjected to a modern-day witch hunt.''</p>
        <p>You will remember that the state's most powerful politicians went after Mr. Duckman in 1996 after he set relatively low bail for a man jailed on domestic-abuse charges. Once released on bail, this man, Benito Oliver, killed a former girlfriend, Galina Komar, and himself.</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani lost no time screaming for Judge Duckman's scalp. Then other judges came in their cross hairs, damned as responsible for New York's crime problems. It was an all-out assault, abetted mightily by baying tabloid headlines about ''junk justice.''</p>
        <p>LOST in the noise was a critical fact: The State Commission on Judicial Conduct and other bodies that reviewed the Oliver case determined that Judge Duckman had done nothing wrong. But by then, he had become the poster child in a conservative campaign against pointy-headed, lenient judges. Officials were determined to build a case against him, and, in Mr. Duckman's view, ''it was a done deal from the very beginning.''</p>
        <p>He charged that the office of the Brooklyn District Attorney, Charles J. Hynes, had kept a dossier on him, and that it still does with other judges deemed anti-prosecution. In response, a Hynes spokesman said, ''We don't do that.'' But Judge Titone, for one, was willing to believe that anti-Duckman files were kept, and said so.</p>
        <p>In any event, the case against Mr. Duckman was built on episodes in which he used intemperate language, as well as 16 cases in which his dismissal of criminal charges was questionable or even, as he now acknowledges, flat-out wrong.</p>
        <p>But are we seriously to believe that no judge still on the bench has uttered intemperate words in the hurly-burly of the New York court system? Bear in mind, too, that no one had brought disciplinary charges against Judge Duckman until after the Oliver case.</p>
        <p>As for those 16 dismissals, all involved misdemeanors, and the District Attorney appealed not one of them. How outraged could he have been?</p>
        <p>And even if Mr. Duckman's judgment was off, they were 16 cases out of 55,000 -- repeat, 55,000 -- that he handled in five years as a Criminal Court judge. To another Court of Appeals dissenter, Judge Joseph W. Bellacosa, the ax that fell was ''disproportionate to the nature, number and gravity of the proven and acknowledged judicial misdeeds, misspeaks and mishaps.''</p>
        <p>The argument here is not that Mr. Duckman was the wisest judge since Learned Hand. He is clearly a quirky character, as evidenced by the whimsical duck themes that fill his house: wooden ducks, Donald Duck, posters for the Marx Brothers' ''Duck Soup.''</p>
        <p>But you have to ask how well anyone's reputation would hold up if put under a microscope the way his was once the politicians decided that he must go. More important is whether other judges have been intimidated by his example. Absolutely, Mr. Duckman said, ''judges are in fear.''</p>
        <p>It is a serious charge, and, the appellate dissenters agreed, no canard.</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
