<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anemic Offense Stops Yanks Short of a New Mark</title>
    <meta content="14GAME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1031834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Indians</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Cleveland Indians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFD61031F937A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anemic Offense Stops Yanks Short of a New Mark</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, July 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cleveland Indians beat New York Yankees, 4-1, and end Yankees 10-game winning streak; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul O'Neill leaned forward dejectedly on a chair in front of his locker tonight, elbows on knees, his voice barely a whisper as he discussed the Indians' 4-1 defeat of the Yankees, which ended the team's 10-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>With the defeat, the Yankees (65-21) lost the chance of establishing the best 86-game record in major league history. They are now tied for that mark, with the 1902 Pittsburgh Pirates and the 1912 New York Giants.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul O'Neill leaned forward dejectedly on a chair in front of his locker tonight, elbows on knees, his voice barely a whisper as he discussed the Indians' 4-1 defeat of the Yankees, which ended the team's 10-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>With the defeat, the Yankees (65-21) lost the chance of establishing the best 86-game record in major league history. They are now tied for that mark, with the 1902 Pittsburgh Pirates and the 1912 New York Giants.</p>
        <p>For more than a month, the Yankees' pitching staff has carried the team, and even without Bernie Williams, the team has continued to thrive. But in the rare case tonight when the Yankees' starting pitcher, Orlando Hernandez, did not pitch a shutout or something close to it, O'Neill and the other hitters failed to respond against Cleveland's Jaret Wright -- who became the first pitcher to beat the Yankees twice this season.</p>
        <p>Even as the Yankees won 10 straight, the hitters sputtered, producing an average of .266, 34 points lower than they were hitting when Williams went down with a sprained knee June 10.</p>
        <p>''We've put a lot of pressure on our pitching,'' O'Neill said. ''We've got to get in a groove here.''</p>
        <p>Williams's return is right around the corner, someone mentioned. ''I hope somebody opens the door around the corner and he comes right in here,'' O'Neill said. ''Bernie's a big part of the offense and a big part of this team.''</p>
        <p>Against Wright -- a pitcher who has probably earned permanent disrespect from the Yankees, after he broke the hand of utility infielder Luis Sojo in spring training -- the Yankees missed the few opportunities they created. They went 0 for 5 with runners in scoring position, and three times had two on and two out and could not capitalize. O'Neill struck out twice, and afterward, he mentioned how much better Wright has become, how he changes speeds now and changes the elevation of his fastball -- O'Neill chased a strike three over his head -- and how catcher Sandy Alomar has helped him.</p>
        <p>But the Yankees would not be 65-21 if they did not believe, at heart, that they can win if they just play better, and O'Neill wants to see more offense. ''We've just got to take pressure off the pitchers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Yankees' only run came in the fourth inning, when Darryl Strawberry blasted a solo home run. Even that contains an asterisk, however: Strawberry hobbled around the bases, and the Yankees are extremely concerned about the condition of his knees, which seemed to worsen on Tampa Bay's artificial surface over the weekend.</p>
        <p>Hernandez allowed nine hits, two walks and four runs in six and two-thirds innings, but generally pitched well and might have won, if not for a significant adjustment by the Cleveland hitters. He had struck out five in the first three innings, throwing fastballs and changeups away.</p>
        <p>Realizing that Hernandez was throwing outside repeatedly, Jim Thome leaned across the plate in the fourth inning, with one out, and drove the first pitch to the opposite field, instead of trying to pull it, for a home run into the left-field stands, his 24th.</p>
        <p>Hernandez turned and watched the ball carry out, hands on hips. After it landed, he twisted to face his catcher Jorge Posada and nodded, as if to say, ''Yes, I know what I did wrong.''</p>
        <p>The Indians seemed to ascertain what Thome did right, in going to the opposite field. After Manny Ramirez walked, the left-handed-hitting Brian Giles banged a first-pitch fastball to left field, off the wall, Ramirez stopping at third base. With two right-handed batters due to hit, Hernandez was still in control: right-handed batters had just 7 hits in 72 at-bats against him because they have such a difficult time hitting his sidearm slider.</p>
        <p>Hernandez threw a sidearm slider to Alomar, who stretched his arms to reach the ball out of the strike zone, barely hitting the ball, but hitting it enough. The ball fell over the head of first baseman Tino Martinez, scoring Ramirez with the run that gave Cleveland a 2-1 lead.</p>
        <p>Posada has been encouraging Hernandez to pitch inside more, to make the hitters stay honest and keep them from leaning over the plate. ''He wanted to go away,'' Posada said afterward. ''For him to do well, he's got to pitch inside. He's going to learn more every time he goes out there.''</p>
        <p>Said Mike Hargrove, Cleveland's manager: ''If you try to pull that pitch, you play right into his hands. He's a very smart pitcher; he has a good sense of what he's doing.''</p>
        <p>Thome again reached out in the sixth inning to drive a ball to the opposite field, and when it bounced against the wall and above the leaps of Yankee outfielders Tim Raines and Chad Curtis, Thome rambled into third, with a triple. He would score from there on a sacrifice fly.</p>
        <p>Kenny Lofton homered to right in the seventh, his fifth hit in eight at-bats against Hernandez. Two batters later, Torre relieved Hernandez, who stalked off the mound, self-torture evident in his grimace and in the way he snatched off his cap.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
