<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>English Pot Smokers' Pub May Prove a Model</title>
    <meta content="22POT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/22/international/europe/22POT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1345073"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Stockport (Eng)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dutch Experience (Cafe) (Stockport, Eng)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">England</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4D9173AF931A15752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1236" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>English Pot Smokers' Pub May Prove a Model</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">English Pot Smokers' Pub May Prove a Model</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>STOCKPORT, England, Nov. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dutch Experience cafe in northern English town of Stockport hosts marijuana smoking and could be thin end of wedge in Britain, where government is signaling it may ease laws on use of soft drugs in name of creating workable drug policy; photos; government says police spend inordinate amount of time dealing with minor drug offenses, with 65 percent of 120,000 drug-related arrests last year for marijuana possession; Stockport police raided cafe day it opened in September but did not act again until cafe began attracting publicity (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Until the Dutch Experience cafe opened here earlier this fall, providing marijuana by the bag instead of beer by the pint, Stockport never loomed particularly large in the greater British imagination.</p>
        <p>''I read in the newspaper that the only thing Stockport is famous for is the hat museum,'' said Darren Ince, 32, a retail manager, on his way to secure a joint or two at the cafe recently. ''I didn't know we were even famous for that.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new pub providing marijuana by the bag instead of beer by the pint has become a battleground for Britain's growing pot smokers' rights movement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Until the Dutch Experience cafe opened here earlier this fall, providing marijuana by the bag instead of beer by the pint, Stockport never loomed particularly large in the greater British imagination.</p>
        <p>''I read in the newspaper that the only thing Stockport is famous for is the hat museum,'' said Darren Ince, 32, a retail manager, on his way to secure a joint or two at the cafe recently. ''I didn't know we were even famous for that.''</p>
        <p>All that changed this fall, when the cafe opened its doors, let the distinctive smoke waft out and instantly turned this unremarkable suburb of Manchester into a battleground for Britain's growing pot smokers' rights movement.</p>
        <p>The Dutch Experience, modeled on the pot-purveying coffee shops of marijuana-friendly Amsterdam, may well prove to be the thin end of the wedge in Britain, where the government is signaling that it might relax laws on the use of soft drugs in the name of creating a workable drug policy.</p>
        <p>British drug laws are strict, and the police spend an inordinate amount of time dealing with minor drug offenses, the government says. Sixty-five percent of the 120,000 drug-related arrests in Britain last year were for possession of marijuana.</p>
        <p>Saying the police should direct their efforts at eradicating hard drugs like heroin and LSD, Home Secretary David Blunkett last month proposed downgrading marijuana to a Class C drug, from its current Class B status. That would make possession of pot no longer an arrestable offense.</p>
        <p>A pilot project in Brixton, a drug-infested neighborhood in south London where police officers spent six months focusing on hard drugs instead of marijuana, has proved effective, the police say.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Blunkett's proposals have not yet taken effect, and law enforcement officials across the country are not exactly sure what to do in this interim period.</p>
        <p>It is unclear, for instance, what the Stockport police really think of the Dutch Experience. After raiding it in September, on the day it opened, they seemed to have adopted a live-and-let-smoke policy, generously acknowledging, they said in a statement, that there is an ''ongoing debate about the medical benefits, or otherwise, of cannabis.''</p>
        <p>But it appears that the cafe has been attracting too much attention and too boldly flouting the law, no matter how mellow its activities might seem.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, as the BBC was inside filming the cafe for a program about drug policy, the police returned, threw everyone out and charged the owner, Colin Davies, and several others with various drug-related offenses, including selling marijuana.</p>
        <p>''The police in appropriate cases exercise discretion and judgment with regard to certain offenses of simple possession of cannabis, and each case is taken on merit,'' said Superintendent Richard Crawshaw of the Greater Manchester Police's Stockport division. ''However, in the face of overt and challenging behavior which amounts to intention to break the law, our stance will be one of enforcement.''</p>
        <p>It is hard to know how far such enforcement goes. Even as Mr. Davies, one of Britain's best-known campaigners for legalizing marijuana, remained in custody overnight, his cafe reopened. The patrons came back, sipping coffee, rolling joints, discussing nothing and everything.</p>
        <p>Despite the occasional police raids, the cannabis cafe, as it is generally known, has proved highly popular with its neighbors. They applaud its strict no-alcohol, no-violence policy, saying they much prefer happy, peaceful druggies to aggressive, unpleasant drunks.</p>
        <p>''They always look so pleased, and they're really friendly,'' said Becky Lees, who works at the front desk of the Outline health club, just across the walkway, speaking of the pot smokers at the Dutch Experience.</p>
        <p>She does not smoke -- ''I'm addicted to coffee, not cannabis,'' she said -- but always welcomes customers who come in from the Dutch Experience, which sells little in the way of food to vanquish the sudden appetites of its often ravenous clientele.</p>
        <p>''We get a lot of business out of it, because they get the munchies and come and eat in our cafe,'' Ms. Lees said.</p>
        <p>Eating, yes. But no weightlifting. ''We don't let people use the gym if they've been smoking weed,'' she said. ''It's not a good idea, for safety reasons, to let people who are stoned use the machines.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davies, who uses the profits from recreational patrons at the Dutch Experience to help pay for pot for medicinal users, says he started smoking marijuana to quell crippling back pains from the vertebrae he broke after a fall in 1995.</p>
        <p>Shortly afterward, he founded the Medical Marijuana Cooperative, a mail-order service that discreetly provides pot to people with a variety of illnesses, from cancer to multiple sclerosis. Mr. Davies, 44, jokingly calls the cafe the M.H.S., or the Marijuana Health Service. The National Health Service, or N.H.S., runs Britain's system of socialized medicine.</p>
        <p>It is not uncommon to see wheelchair users rolling down the path in front of the cafe, seeking drugs inside. ''People in wheelchairs shouldn't have to pay for their medicine,'' said Mr. Davies, who hopes to open a chain of cannabis cafes around Britain. ''They should get it free, and that's what we're doing.''</p>
        <p>Mark Chadwick, 39, who hurt his arm in a motorcycle accident, does not care if he can get it free or not, as long as he can get it. For the last month or so he has been regularly paying £10 (about $14) or so per bag of pot, enough to roll a half-dozen joints that help keep him off his prescribed painkillers and make it easier to sleep at night.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chadwick loves the smoky, sleepy atmosphere inside the cafe, with its green tables imported from Amsterdam and its air of festively illicit camaraderie.</p>
        <p>''It's nothing like going to a pub,'' he said. ''It's like going to the theater instead of going to a movie. In a pub you spend all your time worrying about who's looking at you, who's going to throw a bottle at you.''</p>
        <p>At the cannabis cafe, no one throws anything. Because no hard drugs are allowed, there are no dealers trying to introduce patrons to the double-edged, and far more criminal, attractions of drugs like heroin and cocaine.</p>
        <p>''If I couldn't buy here, I would have to go to a dealer, which is something I don't want to do,'' Mr. Chadwick said.</p>
        <p>At the Stockport Tourist Information center, employees say the Dutch Experience has become one of the most asked-about places in town.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman, who in keeping with tourist office policy insisted that her name not be used, declined to say whether she, or any other council employees, had patronized the cafe themselves. ''It's certainly put us on the map,'' she said, ''though whether that's a positive thing or a negative thing I couldn't say.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
