<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nightmares of Screams Haunt Rescue Workers</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="761234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="TERROR IN OKLAHOMA: THE AFTERMATH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESCUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOMBS AND BOMB PLOTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">OKLAHOMA CITY (OKLA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEVY, CLIFFORD J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oklahoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oklahoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oklahoma/Oklahoma City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rescues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6D9133CF93BA35756C0A963958260" item-length="1171" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nightmares of Screams Haunt Rescue Workers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEVY, CLIFFORD J</byline>
      <dateline>OKLAHOMA CITY, May 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Soon after Marc Bentovoja ended his stint as a rescue worker at the Federal Building here, he began having nightmares, always the same ones, always with the same grisly clarity.</p>
        <p>He dreams he is back in the wreckage of the day-care center, surrounded by bloodied chunks of concrete, a crushed tricycle, a mangled doll. He hears the screams of toddlers, but cannot locate them. He keeps frantically moving aside debris -- digging, scraping, clawing. No one is there, yet the cries will not stop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Soon after Marc Bentovoja ended his stint as a rescue worker at the Federal Building here, he began having nightmares, always the same ones, always with the same grisly clarity.</p>
        <p>He dreams he is back in the wreckage of the day-care center, surrounded by bloodied chunks of concrete, a crushed tricycle, a mangled doll. He hears the screams of toddlers, but cannot locate them. He keeps frantically moving aside debris -- digging, scraping, clawing. No one is there, yet the cries will not stop.</p>
        <p>"There aren't a couple of hours that go by without me dwelling on what happened," said Mr. Bentovoja, 34, who has returned to his job as a captain in the fire department in Sacramento, Calif. "I didn't think that it would affect me. But actually doing it isn't as difficult as reflecting on it."</p>
        <p>With operations at the Federal Building completed after 16 days of searching, many rescue workers are now being hit by psychological aftershocks as they finally let the horrors they saw sink in. Many had assumed they would have little trouble resuming their everyday lives in places around the country, yet the memories of Oklahoma City continue to well up.</p>
        <p>Even the people who have labored through the most devastating natural disasters in recent years -- the floods in the Midwest, Hurricane Andrew in Florida, the earthquake in Kobe, Japan -- say that getting over this one is different. Every time they think about the rubble and the gore and the grief, they cannot help recall that someone deliberately did this.</p>
        <p>Not everyone is facing these strains. But some rescue workers are experiencing sleepless nights, anxiety, flashbacks, short tempers and, like Mr. Bentovoja, vivid nightmares. Many say it may take them weeks to come to terms with their frustration and guilt at not being able to find survivors after the explosion, which left 164 people dead, two missing and hundreds injured.</p>
        <p>"I've dealt with most of the major emergencies that California has had, from the Northridge earthquake to the L.A. riots to the Oakland fires to the floods," said Kim Zagaris, 39, a senior official with the California Office of Emergency Services. "All those are small in comparison to Oklahoma City. I don't think any of our training ever prepared us for the magnitude of what we had to deal with emotionally out here."</p>
        <p>Many of the workers, who are mostly firefighters back home, say they have benefited from counseling that disaster-relief agencies and fire and police departments have offered in recent years to ease them through such trauma. Firefighters are now more willing to try therapy instead of relying on the traditional remedy: bottling it up and hoping it goes away.</p>
        <p>Here in Oklahoma City, the men of Station No. 1, one of the closest firehouses to the Federal Building, said they often confided to one another and to therapists about the bombing. The victims were not just anonymous. Firefighters from the station had in recent months been doing a lengthy safety inspection of the building, forming friendships with the workers there.</p>
        <p>Capt. Patrick Shaw, 39, said he had told the therapists that he could not stop replaying one scene in his mind. It was April 19, several hours after the blast, and he was struggling to extract a woman from the ruins. There was a bomb scare, and his superiors said he had to evacuate the building. He could not bear to abandon the woman.</p>
        <p>So he refused. He was ordered again. He argued. Finally, he had to give in and leave, the woman desperately shouting at him as he made his way out. Though he was able to return and the woman was saved, the scars from the incident remain.</p>
        <p>"It helps to talk about it," Captain Shaw said. "It has helped a lot."</p>
        <p>Other rescue workers also spoke of recurring images.</p>
        <p>"I have this little slide carousel in my head," said Phil Yeager, a 41-year-old paramedic and fire marshal from Phoenix. "And if I sit and think, I can click in these little pictures. Little things, little pictures. A child's shoe. That sits in my mind."</p>
        <p>Dr. Dario Gonzalez, 46, an associate medical director with the Emergency Medical Service in New York City, said he could not forget the smell of flesh and destruction in the building, and he described the shock of coming across a photo album on the fourth floor.</p>
        <p>"I picked it up, which I probably shouldn't have done," he said. "It had pictures of an office party. There was a shower announcement, a letter of promotion, family pictures of some kids. The more you saw, the more you had to look. It made the whole thing personal. They weren't just bodies. They were really people."</p>
        <p>Many were struck by how they did not seem to react strongly to the disaster until they arrived home. Now, any mention of it seems to draw forth emotion. Some said they turned off the television or radio when the bombing was discussed, seeking to block it out until they were more settled.</p>
        <p>"You are so focused when you are out there on that incident," said Jim Strickland, 46, a deputy fire chief in Fairfax County, Va. "It's kind of like holding pressure on something, and all of sudden that pressure is released when you get back. Back here, you see it on television and say, 'My goodness. I was just there dealing with that.' "</p>
        <p>Perhaps most upsetting to many of the rescue workers was their lack of success in detecting survivors. Most were used to disasters where falling materials trapped people alive. But in the Federal Building, many of the victims were killed by the force of the bomb just before the walls and ceilings collapsed. On many floors, there was no one to find.</p>
        <p>Many workers spoke of an added burden because they had grown close to the residents of Oklahoma City, who had expressed their gratitude by cooking meals for the workers, sending them letters and repeatedly thanking them.</p>
        <p>"When I was leaving, I felt extremely guilty," said Rick Martinez, 42, a division chief in the Sacramento Fire Department. "We felt that maybe we didn't work hard enough. We felt that we didn't deserve the attention that the people were giving us because we hadn't come through for them. For whatever reasons, we had failed and let them down."</p>
        <p>Others also said they were uncomfortable with the public adulation.</p>
        <p>"The heroes were the people down there that first day, who had no training or nothing, trying to save people," said Cpl. Kelsey Dillon, 31, of Station No. 1 in Oklahoma City. "Those, more or less, are the heroes. If I could have pulled one more person out alive, and no one would ever had known I had done that, I'd make that trade, no problem at all."</p>
        <p>Many rescue workers said they were now spending time by themselves, reading, horseback riding, fishing -- activities that calm them after their work has gotten to them.</p>
        <p>"I have done a lot of walking and thinking, and maybe I have a more realistic opinion of what happened," Mr. Martinez said. "That experience will be there forever, but the guilt that I carried around, I have been able to bring that in check and deal with it. Today, I feel at peace."  TERROR IN OKLAHOMA: THE AFTERMATH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
