<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disorders Follow Clash in Haitian City</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="714452"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="MISSION TO HAITI: IN HAITI"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAITI-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CAP HAITIEN (HAITI)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMITT, ERIC</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CEDRAS, RAOUL (LT GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHELTON, HENRY HUGH (LT GEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2DF133AF935A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="1361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disorders Follow Clash in Haitian City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMITT, ERIC</byline>
      <dateline>CAP-HAITIEN, Haiti, Sept. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of Haitian civilians ransacked the four police stations and the central military headquarters here today and marched through the streets with captured rifles, plunging Haiti's second-largest city into chaos for several hours.</p>
        <p>The rampage followed Saturday night's shooting of 10 Haitian security personnel by a 10-man United States Marine patrol in a 15-second gunfight outside the main police station. Marine commanders said today that the shootings were in self-defense after the Haitian security forces brandished their weapons at the patrol.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hundreds of Haitian civilians ransacked the four police stations and the central military headquarters here today and marched through the streets with captured rifles, plunging Haiti's second-largest city into chaos for several hours.</p>
        <p>The rampage followed Saturday night's shooting of 10 Haitian security personnel by a 10-man United States Marine patrol in a 15-second gunfight outside the main police station. Marine commanders said today that the shootings were in self-defense after the Haitian security forces brandished their weapons at the patrol.</p>
        <p>[ Administration officials in Washington have warned since the beginning of the Haitian operation that it was full of risks. President Clinton, after speaking Sunday at a church in Harlem, issued a statement saying, "It must be clear that U.S. forces are prepared to respond to hostile action against them and will do so." ]</p>
        <p>The only American casualty was Francis Jose, a Navy Creole-speaking interpreter who suffered a flesh wound in the leg and was evacuated to an American ship offshore for treatment.</p>
        <p>The marines did not stop the looting and pillaging of the main police headquarters and more than 45 minutes lapsed before American troops arrived at the military headquarters.</p>
        <p>At the police station, crowds crammed through the barracks, grabbing everything from electrical fuse boxes to wooden benches to tubas, and soon boys wearing the khaki caps of the military police were jauntily parading through the streets like mock soldiers.</p>
        <p>"This is only the beginning of the worse," said the owner of one of the operating bars in town. "The pulse of Haiti is Cap-Haitien."</p>
        <p>The disorder in this city of 65,000 was the most serious outbreak of violence since the United States military swept into Port-au-Prince and Cap-Haitien six days ago to establish order and to pave the way for a peaceful restoration of the exiled President, the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide.</p>
        <p>The commander of the American operation Haiti, Lieut. Gen. Henry Hugh Shelton, and the United States Ambassador, William L. Swing, flew here from Port-au-Prince this morning with the leader of the Haitian junta, Lieut. Gen. Raoul Cedras, to discuss the shootings and the growing tensions that have turned this city into a tinder box in the past 48 hours.</p>
        <p>General Cedras angrily demanded the court-martial of the Marine commander here, Col. Tom Jones, but the request was summarily dismissed by American officials.</p>
        <p>Colonel Jones later told reporters that General Cedras was seething.  "Cedras accused us of atrocities and demanded my transfer and court-martial," the colonel said.</p>
        <p>Marine officers here said that the disorder was largely a result of the lack of control by local Haitian commanders. All 400 of the Haitian security personnel stationed here seem to have fled the city, leaving a vacuum of power.</p>
        <p>But many residents questioned why the marines had failed to respond more quickly to the looting at the police barracks and the army headquarters downtown.</p>
        <p>The looting began when a throng, mostly young men, gathered at the tree-shaded two-story military compound about 9 o'clock this morning.</p>
        <p>They first routed two of the last remaining police officers in the barracks, chasing them up a dry river bed. With their courage growing, a few men in the crowd took halting steps inside the wrought iron gates of the compound and picked up rocks to hurl. Meeting little resistance, scores more coursed through the gates. Within minutes, many were triumphantly holding aloft rifles and automatic weapons.</p>
        <p>Marines said that hundreds of the weapons that the mob seized were later returned to American forces throughout the city. Haitians even made citizen arrests of people they said were paramilitary officers who had made threats against the American troops.</p>
        <p>By 10:30, the street was littered with green uniforms, sandbags and the khaki-colored hats. The shooting that set off today's rampage occurred at the police station, the headquarters of the First Military Police Company, at about 7 o'clock Saturday night.</p>
        <p>Marine commanders gave the following account:</p>
        <p>Two members of the Haitian security forces in front of the police headquarters had brandished pistols in front of a crowd of supporters of Father Aristide who were chanting anti-Cedras slogans, said Colonel Jones.</p>
        <p>As the taunts intensified, he said, one of the Haitian troops raised his Uzi machine gun in the direction of the Marine lieutenant who commanded the 10-man patrol. The lieutenant immediately opened fire.</p>
        <p>"It's hard to tell who fired first," said Colonel Jones. "I hope our lieutenant shot first. There's no doubt in my mind he made the right decision to use deadly force. He saw his life in danger and took appropriate action."</p>
        <p>The colonel did not identify the lieutenant but The Associated Press, quoting military sources, said his name is Virg Palumbo, 24, of Windber, Pa.</p>
        <p>Colonel Jones said all 10 Haitians who died belonged to either the Haitian police or to the military. Only two of the dead wore uniforms, but in recent days many members of the Haitian security forces have worn civilian clothes to prevent reprisals from angry residents.</p>
        <p>The commander of E Company, Capt. Rich Diddams, said the patrol had been stationed outside the police headquarters to prevent the police from beating the crowds. On Wednesday night, Haitian security forces had clubbed and fired into a crowd of Aristide supporters who were trailing two Marine trucks broadcasting messages in Creole.</p>
        <p>After the shooting, Colonel Jones angrily demanded that the Haitian commander here control his forces or else the Marines would. As security by the American troops tightened, the impoverished residents of Cap-Haitien took the opportunity to humiliate the police.</p>
        <p>Captain Diddams, the commander of E Company, said the Haitians had pointed guns at the Marines and thus set off the gunfight. He also said the Haitians fired Uzis, M-1 rifles and 30-caliber revolvers. The Marines fired back with M-16 rifles and belt-loading machine guns.</p>
        <p>There were some discrepancies in the details offered today by the Marine commanders. Captain Diddams said he was not sure whether the crowd's behavior had helped set off the incident. Colonel Jones said it did. Captain Diddams said the gunfight lasted only 15 seconds; Colonel Jones said it lasted about five minutes.</p>
        <p>The shooting Saturday night was the most serious of three incidents involving marines.</p>
        <p>At about 6:45 P.M. on Saturday, a Haitian-American resident who supports the military Government fired from his second-floor balcony into a crowd of Aristide supporters. The Marines detained him but he was not identified.</p>
        <p>About an hour after the shooting at the police station, an unidentified Haitian man pointed a shotgun at a marine on patrol at a basketball court. The marine fired at the man but missed, and the man fled.</p>
        <p>By this afternoon, Cap-Haitien had settled into a uneasy calm. Street lights began to return to normal but there were still signs of increased security on the part of marines.</p>
        <p>Some residents said they fear that the mobs that turned violent today might soon go after the wealthier citizens and supporters of the military.</p>
        <p>"There are a lot of people who have not been sleeping at home in their beds these past few nights" said Prosper Cadet, 54, a taxi driver. "They're all afraid of what could be next."</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>2 Held in Gonaives</p>
        <p>PORT-AU-PRINCE, Sept. 25 (Special to The New York Times) -- In the coastal city of Gonaives, a United States Special Forces team took two men into custody late Saturday when they were seen carrying M-1 rifles, the American military spokesman in Port-au-Prince said today.</p>
        <p>The men are "attaches," the armed civilians who supported the military government, the spokesman said.</p>
        <p>The men were captured during a pro-Aristide demonstration on Saturday night.</p>
        <p>One of the men, according to Haitian sources, was Jean Tatoune, a one-time opponent of the government who was widely disliked for going over to the military rulers and was presumed to have informed on his former colleagues.  MISSION TO HAITI: IN HAITI</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
