<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Headline</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="691509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FAMILIES AND FAMILY LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOTELS AND MOTELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WADE, BETSY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940605T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E6D8133BF936A35755C0A962958260" item-length="1206" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Headline</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETSY WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WADE, BETSY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A NEW YORK couple with twins under 2 years old ask what they can do for a week's summer vacation within one day's drive of New York. They do not want to pack themselves into an airplane, preferring to put kids, seats and luggage into the van and drive off. The other requirements are rather simple. The twins are happy for hours at a time if they can play in the water, the mother said, so a hotel or resort with an indoor pool is protection for rainy days. The couple, both employed, are rather informal, but they do not want to rent a cabin and cook or clean. And they do not want to spend a lot of money.</p>
        <p>There should be a hundred solutions, given the rich variety of resorts within a day's drive of New York. Calls to a few hotels with advertising directed toward families produced a peculiar result: Some resorts that cater to families advertise a calm adult dinner with children in a separate dining room. But such resorts, in high season, do not want children so young they cannot eat separately from their parents. We will love you in May or September, they told the parents, but not in summer. The couple tried several travel agents, but found their recommendations high priced and offhand. In a mountain of brochures, nothing appealed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A NEW YORK couple with twins under 2 years old ask what they can do for a week's summer vacation within one day's drive of New York. They do not want to pack themselves into an airplane, preferring to put kids, seats and luggage into the van and drive off. The other requirements are rather simple. The twins are happy for hours at a time if they can play in the water, the mother said, so a hotel or resort with an indoor pool is protection for rainy days. The couple, both employed, are rather informal, but they do not want to rent a cabin and cook or clean. And they do not want to spend a lot of money.</p>
        <p>There should be a hundred solutions, given the rich variety of resorts within a day's drive of New York. Calls to a few hotels with advertising directed toward families produced a peculiar result: Some resorts that cater to families advertise a calm adult dinner with children in a separate dining room. But such resorts, in high season, do not want children so young they cannot eat separately from their parents. We will love you in May or September, they told the parents, but not in summer. The couple tried several travel agents, but found their recommendations high priced and offhand. In a mountain of brochures, nothing appealed.</p>
        <p>Travel agents tend not to get excited about planning a family car trip: They get no commission as they would on a plane or train ticket. Further, hotels are slow about paying commissions. A result is that the quest of the family with young children does not generally get the kind of attention given to a cruise-shopper.</p>
        <p>So the question was pursued by the Practical Traveler column to see if answers were really scarce, or merely hard to extract.  Getting the Facts</p>
        <p>A first principle is to get access to local knowledge. If you call an agency in a resort area within the radius, it probably knows its turf, whereas agents at a distance may seize a quick way out by turning to a well-known chain. A few agents, not local, jumped in with the Hyatt Hotels, because of their Camp Hyatts, but the youngest age for those programs is 3. An agent in Pennsylvania, however, focused on nearby Hershey Park and the old Hershey Hotel. In Lake Placid, N.Y., a visitors' center suggested many places that filled the bill. An agent in the Wildwood-Cape May area of New Jersey had good possibilities virtually on her doorstep.</p>
        <p>A second principle is parents should try to talk to parents. A travel agency that gave informative responses on singles travel this time nominated hotels way out of the price range for a young family.</p>
        <p>A third principle applies to selecting a travel agent for any purpose: If an agent tries to sell you something other than what you have asked for, try a different agent. A couple of agents proposed Club Med and American Family Cruises, which do not meet the one-day drive requirement.  Narrowing the Choices</p>
        <p>Here are places responsive to the family's request. It illustrates that there are a lot of options but pinpointing them is not easy.</p>
        <p>Cheryl K. Bejgrowicz is a leisure-travel agent for Homestead Travel in Hummelstown, Pa., an agency that plans many trips for high school bands. Her thought was nearby Hershey, three and a half hours from New York in the area of Harrisburg. Hershey is rich in recreation, she said, with Hersheypark and Zoo America wildlife park. Lancaster, with its Dutch Country, and Gettysburg are within an hour in different directions. Ms. Bejgrowicz picked the Hershey Hotel, noting its identity as a family hotel. The comfortable 1930's hotel has indoor and outdoor pools on its 400 acres, sauna, whirlpools and an exercise area; tennis and golf.</p>
        <p>A standard double room is $174 a night for two adults, with children under 3 free in all cases. A room with breakfast adds $5 each, for a price of $184 a night. The "breakaway package" with breakfast and dinner would be $234 a night. There are other packages with admission to Hersheypark, which is otherwise $24 each.</p>
        <p>Hershey: (800) 533-3131; Hershey Hotel: (717) 533-2171; Homestead Travel: (800) 635-8749, (717) 566-9561.</p>
        <p>Recreational possibilities in Lake Placid, N.Y., five to six hours from New York City, are also strong, with a public beach on Mirror Lake as well as playgrounds, golf links, events at the Olympic Center and the Adirondack Park visitor center, which is free, open all year, stroller- and wheelchair-accessible and reachable by auto. And there is an agreeable walk around the lake.</p>
        <p>Not knowing a travel agent there, I used a chart published by the Lake Placid-Essex County Visitors Bureau with easily understandable symbols. To find places with indoor pools, look in the column for pool symbols, with an "I" for "indoor." This region has a central service with a staff that can work out packages and make reservations. The phone is (800) 447-5224 and it can be hard to get through. The mail address is Olympic Center, Lake Placid, N.Y. 12946.</p>
        <p>The Best Western Golden Arrow in the village of Lake Placid has a sandy beach on Mirror Lake, pool and spa. The public beach and park are nearby and the hotel has a restaurant. A lakefront room costs $98 to $148 a night; the Summer Sparkle package is $123.50 a night midweek and $143.50 a night weekend; that includes a room with a balcony or terrace, possibly lakefront, Champagne, cheese and fruit on arrival, and one dinner for two and one room-service breakfast for two. Golden Arrow: (800) 582-5540 or (518) 523-3353.</p>
        <p>The Holiday Inn Sunspree, back from the lake, has a refrigerator, freezer and microwave in each room. Some rooms have fireplaces and whirlpools. There is a spa and a restaurant. Lakeview rooms are $109 to $139. With breakfast included, the cost is $5 more per adult. Holiday Inn: (800) 874-1980 or (518) 523-2556.</p>
        <p>The Howard Johnson Resort Lodge is a block from downtown, on the bay of Lake Placid, with lake swimming from a lawn. The indoor pool is a favorite with children, local sources say, and the chain classifies this as one of its top 10. Rooms are $95 to $100 a night; a package with breakfast and dinner would be $120 a night for two adults. Howard Johnson's: (800) 858-4656.  Indoor Pools</p>
        <p>The Wildwood-Cape May area at the southern tip of New Jersey is well developed for tourists, with a two-mile boardwalk with rides, playgrounds, fishing, golf, tennis and bicycling. It is three to three and a half hours from New York. Ginny Posternock, owner of Away We Go Travel and Tours-Wildwood Travel, said she'd hate to try to make a living just booking hotels, but often finds herself out searching for efficiencies for clients, because she loves the area.</p>
        <p>She mentioned three hotels with indoor pools. The Admiral in Wildwood Crest has standard rooms running from $95 to $150 a night in summer: (609) 522-7704. Rates at the Grand Hotel in Wildwood Crest are $95 to $150; at the Grand in Cape May, $132 to $290, which is for a two-story town house with a full kitchen. Both hotels: (609) 729-6000. Away We Go (800) 605-4141 or (800) 605-1401 or (609) 522-4141. A few agents proposed resorts with day-care programs for toddlers, but the parents would rather not pay the high hourly rates, preferring to watch their toddlers content with waterplay.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
