<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Courage in Southampton</title>
    <meta content="LI--Hampton" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/13/opinion/nyregionopinions/LI-Hampton.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1846979"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Long Island"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Day Laborers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Immigrants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Southampton (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Epley, Mark (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/The Hamptons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E2D71731F930A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="623" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Courage in Southampton</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Courage in Southampton</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial praises Southampton, NY, Mayor Mark Epley for adding gravel and hedges to vacant lot, designated as park, to make it centralized day-labor market in Southampton, NY</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Mark Epley of Southampton Village is one of the few -- well, maybe only -- elected officials in Suffolk County to have shown real courage in confronting the difficult issue of immigrant day laborers. Others moan about or ignore it; some lawmakers have concocted mean-spirited measures to drive laborers away or make their hard lives even harder.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Epley recently did something different, something strikingly rare in the forbidding political climate of eastern Long Island. He engaged the problem in a practical and constructive way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Mark Epley of Southampton Village recently did something strikingly rare in the forbidding political climate of eastern Long Island: he engaged the difficult issue of immigrant day laborers in a practical and constructive way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Mark Epley of Southampton Village is one of the few -- well, maybe only -- elected officials in Suffolk County to have shown real courage in confronting the difficult issue of immigrant day laborers. Others moan about or ignore it; some lawmakers have concocted mean-spirited measures to drive laborers away or make their hard lives even harder.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Epley recently did something different, something strikingly rare in the forbidding political climate of eastern Long Island. He engaged the problem in a practical and constructive way.</p>
        <p>What he did wasn't much: He put some gravel on a driveway and planted some hedges on Aldrich Lane, in an empty lot where day laborers have gathered for years. He came up with a plan to make that lot -- which is designated a park, though it has no amenities -- the favored spot for workers and trucks to meet, thus centralizing the day-labor market instead of having it scattered throughout the community. He figured that if you could constrain the phenomenon you could tame it, and thus bring tangible improvement to the lives of residents who have complained for years about the many dozens of men who look for work from parking lots and street corners in his tidy village.</p>
        <p>Communities in Nassau and around the country have established informal hiring sites without fanfare or anguish. So what Mr. Epley did was nothing new. But -- and this is where the courage comes in -- it was enough to inflame hostile passions in an area where tensions about illegal immigration are an open wound, and whose County Executive, Steve Levy, is something of a national spokesman for suburban rigidity and intolerance.</p>
        <p>Minutemen now picket outside Mr. Epley's home, he has been attacked in the blogosphere and he faces a lawsuit. Residents of Aldrich Lane, shocked by his gravel-and-hedge modifications, accused him of illegally altering the lot for ''non-park'' and ''non-recreational'' purposes, violating the conditions under which the lot was bought. Southampton Town, which could have supported Mr. Epley and worked with him to solve the problem, has instead sided with the plaintiffs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Epley does not see himself as a martyr or activist. He says he is a ''fairly conservative Republican'' who is as vexed as anybody by the federal government's inability to solve the immigration riddle. He went so far as to call the White House to discuss the problem, but got nowhere.</p>
        <p>He is also well aware, as a small-town mayor, of what he cannot do. He can't deport day laborers or hassle them. He can't have the police checking people's papers. He has seen the legal mess that Mamaroneck, a village in Westchester, got into when it waged a harsh campaign to ticket, intimidate and drive off day laborers from the edges of a village park, where they had congregated for years.</p>
        <p>''I'm just trying to come up with a common-sense solution to something that's going to keep me out of federal court,'' Mr. Epley said.</p>
        <p>One hiring site in an empty lot will not end Long Island's immigration problems. It will not reduce the number of day laborers, integrate them into the community or produce a just, decent solution to the dilemma. But it does promise to bring some small, demonstrable benefit to Southampton Village, without cruelty or posturing.</p>
        <p>The Suffolk Legislature and town leaders like Supervisor Brian Foley of Brookhaven, who have been meek as mice in the long shadow of Mr. Levy, should look to Mr. Epley's example. He has received letters of praise in a local newspaper from residents who are relieved that someone was finally trying to creatively attack the problem -- to do something that the bigots, know-nothings and do-nothings who have dominated Suffolk's immigration debate could never bring themselves to try.</p>
        <p>Long Island</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
