<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Spotlight, a Bid for a Winner to Take All</title>
    <meta content="13polnjNJ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/13/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/13polnj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1847040"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Primaries and Caucuses</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Von Savage, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2DA1431F930A25756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Spotlight, a Bid for a Winner to Take All</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Spotlight, a Bid for a Winner to Take All</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ronald Smothers On Politics column on idea put forward by David Von Savage, Republican chairman for Cape May County, NJ, to change presidential primary from one that apportions delegates to candidates based on their vote totals to winner-take-all arrangement that would seem to favor Rudolph Giuliani; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH so many political players involved, it is probably not surprising that the glut of early presidential primaries slated for next Feb. 5 is already the object of schemes for gaming the system.</p>
        <p>Indications of that can be seen in an idea being circulated among Republicans in New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Republican chairman for Cape May County, N.J., wants to change the state’s primary system to favor Rudolph Giuliani, hoping for some help in return.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH so many political players involved, it is probably not surprising that the glut of early presidential primaries slated for next Feb. 5 is already the object of schemes for gaming the system.</p>
        <p>Indications of that can be seen in an idea being circulated among Republicans in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>It starts with the fact that early polling has given Rudolph W. Giuliani, the former New York City mayor, a commanding lead in the state. Other polling in the region suggests he is the one Republican who could beat the Democratic front-runners, Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton and Senator Barack Obama.</p>
        <p>David Von Savage, the Republican chairman for Cape May County, says he believes state Republicans should embrace this reality and change their primary from one that apportions delegates to candidates based on their vote totals to a winner-take-all arrangement. Such a change would seem to favor Mr. Giuliani and might chase other Republicans in the field out of the state. Mr. Von Savage said this would also relieve Mr. Giuliani of the need to raise and spend millions for a New Jersey primary.</p>
        <p>The reasoning of Mr. Von Savage and supporters of the idea takes a leap of faith from there. A grateful Giuliani campaign would then be disposed to help raise millions for the cash-needy New Jersey Republican Party. That money could be used in the 2007 state legislative races as well as the United States Senate race and presidential campaigns in 2008.</p>
        <p>''Let's face it, Republicans have very little going for themselves in New Jersey,'' Mr. Von Savage said. ''We don't have a U.S. senator. We don't have the governor's office. We don't have the Senate. We don't have the Assembly. That's what we are up against, and my motivation is the self-interest of the state party.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Von Savage is a Giuliani supporter but insists that no one will find the Giuliani campaign's fingerprints on this idea. As a conservative who has more in common on issues like abortion with some others in the race than he does with Mr. Giuliani, Mr. Von Savage put aside some of his preferences to support Mr. Giuliani for the good of the national party's goal of holding on to the White House and providing strong leadership. Mr. Von Savage's plea to his fellow Republicans is similar: think of the good of the state party.</p>
        <p>The idea demonstrated some strength Wednesday night when an advisory committee of the state party voted to recommend a winner-take-all primary to a meeting of the state committee for a June vote.</p>
        <p>But there may be a flaw in Mr. Von Savage's scenario, said Jennifer E. Duffy, senior editor of The Cook Political Report, a Washington political newsletter. Mr. Giuliani's advisers also watch the polls and may have concluded that they do not have to expend time and money in the state. She was also skeptical that any candidate faced with the Feb. 5 crush would divert money to a state party.</p>
        <p>''There are 20 states holding primaries on Feb. 5 -- so many that we are calling it the Powerball,'' Ms. Duffy said. ''And the pressure and costs are so great that if Giuliani told his finance director that he was going to take time and effort to help state parties, he would look at him like he was crazy.''</p>
        <p>ON POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
