<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For ESPN Morning Team, Opposites Attract Ratings</title>
    <meta content="23espn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/23/sports/23espn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1849363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS RADIO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">ESPN</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E5D71F31F930A15756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For ESPN Morning Team, Opposites Attract Ratings</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">ESPN’s Nice Guys May End Up Finishing First</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first time Mike Greenberg, a self-titled sportscasting metrosexual, met his ESPN Radio partner, Mike Golic, he said to himself, ''Will you look at this big, fat, disgusting slob.''</p>
        <p>Such words don't often lead to a long-term occupational commitment. Once on the air, he told Golic, ''If we stood next to each other, we would be the number 10.'' Golic, who boasts of owning two and a half suits, laughed. Later in their first on-air tryout, in November 1999, he recognized that the mocking camaraderie that began with Greenberg's unprovoked insult might create successful radio.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Greenberg and Mike Golic, hosts of the “Mike and Mike in the Morning” radio program, are consciously uncontroversial and it has paid off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first time Mike Greenberg, a self-titled sportscasting metrosexual, met his ESPN Radio partner, Mike Golic, he said to himself, ''Will you look at this big, fat, disgusting slob.''</p>
        <p>Such words don't often lead to a long-term occupational commitment. Once on the air, he told Golic, ''If we stood next to each other, we would be the number 10.'' Golic, who boasts of owning two and a half suits, laughed. Later in their first on-air tryout, in November 1999, he recognized that the mocking camaraderie that began with Greenberg's unprovoked insult might create successful radio.</p>
        <p>''We come off as regular guys,'' said Golic, a former defensive end for three N.F.L. teams. He was sitting across from the trim, well-groomed Greenberg after their show last Friday at Penn Station in Manhattan, the site of one of their regular forays away from their studio in Bristol, Conn. ''The chemistry flat-out works.''</p>
        <p>Seven and a half years after Greenberg insulted a man he had never met and took a job he did not particularly want (he preferred, at the time, to remain a ''SportsCenter'' anchor), their weekday show is carried on 336 affiliates and heard by 3.08 million listeners each week from 6 to 10 a.m.</p>
        <p>In New York, on the ESPN Radio affiliate, ''Mike and Mike in the Morning'' was heard by more men ages 25 to 54 than WFAN in the same time slot in the three months ended April 4. That was before FAN's morning man, Don Imus, was fired for his remarks about the Rutgers women's basketball team.</p>
        <p>The 3.4 share for ''Mike and Mike'' in the crucial male demographic ranked seventh in the New York market and beat the No. 11 WFAN's 2.9, in part thanks to recording an extraordinary 4.9 share in January.</p>
        <p>''Mike and Mike are perceived as good guys,'' said Tom Taylor, executive news editor of Radio-Info.com, an industry Web site. ''They're easy to listen to. They don't challenge you with a lot of heavy stuff in the morning.''</p>
        <p>Greenberg and Golic are consciously uncontroversial, unless their ''Just Shut Up Tuesday,'' a compendium of sports figures who misspeak or say too much, counts as edgy. Their language is unlikely to cross any dangerous line.</p>
        <p>There are many angry talk-show hosts, said Greenberg, who will soon milk a cow on air to settle an N.C.A.A. tournament bet with Golic. ''What are they all so angry about?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Golic is a hefty, cheerful, messy guy who cheats on his NutriSystem diet; on Friday, he ate a hunk of the ESPN baseball analyst Steve Phillips's birthday cake at Penn Station.</p>
        <p>''Not fat is not funny,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Golic's job description once included sacking quarterbacks, but he totaled only 11 1/2 over eight seasons. Golic is the handyman who instructs Greenberg in all manner of macho tasks like when best to spray a nest of bees, in daylight or dusk. Greenberg's work with his hands is more likely to feature rubbing them with Purell, lest he get strep throat, or something worse, from germs leaping off the hands he inevitably shakes. Greenberg's 2006 book about his home life was titled ''Why My Wife Thinks I'm an Idiot.''</p>
        <p>They are the beneficiaries of employment by an empire that can provide them with almost any guest and can simulcast their program each morning on ESPN2 (when one host speaks, the other is often preoccupied with what is on his laptop), cast them in the poker series ''Tilt'' and make them game announcers for the Arena Football League. ESPN unleashed them as the ringmasters of a 16-week-long promotion last year on their show that led to two fans being married on ESPN (with Bill Walton as a guest); turned them into cartoon characters, portraying themselves, on ESPN.com's ''Off Mikes'' series; and gave them a page in each issue of ESPN's magazine.</p>
        <p>Last week, they were featured in ESPN's upfront presentation to advertisers at the Nokia Theater in Manhattan. Next Thursday, they will be commentators for ESPN and ABC for the Scripps National Spelling Bee.</p>
        <p>''I can't even spell the words I can't pronounce,'' Golic said. Greenberg added, ''If they had a pronunciation bee, he'd have trouble.''</p>
        <p>Creating a successful radio pairing is most often serendipitous. Today, the uniting of Mike Francesa and Chris Russo at WFAN seems right -- like Greenberg and Golic, a meeting of opposites -- but few could be certain 18 years ago that they would become afternoon drive-time powerhouses and the dominant personalities at the station in the post-Imus era.</p>
        <p>In the month and a half without Imus, Russo and Francesa filled in during the first two weeks while continuing their afternoon show, and they returned to the morning shift early this week. WFAN has also brought in the former Jets quarterback Boomer Esiason, with Russo and with the commentator Monica Crowley; Cris Collinsworth; CNN's Lou Dobbs; Geraldo Rivera; John and Patrick McEnroe; David Gregory, NBC News's chief White House correspondent; and Leslie Gold, the Radio Chick of WXRK, an FM station that, like WFAN, is owned by CBS Radio. Jim Cramer, the host of CNBC's ''Mad Money,'' fills in today through Friday.</p>
        <p>It is proving to be very difficult to replace Imus.</p>
        <p>Golic and Greenberg, and ESPN Radio officials, offer the politic response that they compete with all local stations, not just WFAN, and declined to predict that they will gain from the vacuum caused by Imus's firing. Their audiences are somewhat different: a dedicated sports audience goes to ESPN, but a somewhat older audience that was seeking a pastiche of politics and raunchy entertainment, with a side of sports, tuned to Imus.</p>
        <p>''His absence is a factor, but it doesn't affect what we do,'' Greenberg said.</p>
        <p>WFAN and CBS Radio officials would not discuss the candidates for Imus's time slot, when they will make their decision, or whether they are leaning to a purely sports show or one with a mix like Imus's.</p>
        <p>''But there isn't another Imus out there,'' Taylor, of Radio-Info.com, said.</p>
        <p>Steve Rosner, Esiason's agent, said Esiason, an analyst for CBS Radio's ''Monday Night Football,'' initially agreed to the fill-in assignment as a ''friend of CBS Radio.'' But after CBS officials asked him whether he would consider taking a full-time position, he said he would.</p>
        <p>''Now,'' Rosner said, ''we're waiting to see if they want to talk further.''</p>
        <p>SPORTS RADIO</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
