<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fugitive From a Tour Group</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="766672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TURKEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TURKEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOLFE, LINDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E5D91E39F937A35755C0A963958260" item-length="1506" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fugitive From a Tour Group</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY LINDA WOLFE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WOLFE, LINDA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT sounded good. A 12-day tour of Turkey organized by a teacher of art history at a Westchester college. Admittedly, I'd never been on a tour before. But several people I knew had. If they'd been willing to travel that way, why not me?</p>
        <p>In a moment of madness I forgot that I am, when traveling, the quintessential dawdler, a lover of byways and detours, a philistine who thinks one can learn as much about a foreign country from a produce market as from a museum, and an ardent eater who believes that lunch should take at least an hour and dinner two, during which time the utensils used for the first course, especially if it  has been fishy or greasy, should be changed. Wanting to see Turkey and laboring  under the widely held but, as it turned out, false belief that it isn't a country in which one can wander on one's own, I allowed myself to lose sight of  my predilections, and signed on for the tour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT sounded good. A 12-day tour of Turkey organized by a teacher of art history at a Westchester college. Admittedly, I'd never been on a tour before. But several people I knew had. If they'd been willing to travel that way, why not me?</p>
        <p>In a moment of madness I forgot that I am, when traveling, the quintessential dawdler, a lover of byways and detours, a philistine who thinks one can learn as much about a foreign country from a produce market as from a museum, and an ardent eater who believes that lunch should take at least an hour and dinner two, during which time the utensils used for the first course, especially if it  has been fishy or greasy, should be changed. Wanting to see Turkey and laboring  under the widely held but, as it turned out, false belief that it isn't a country in which one can wander on one's own, I allowed myself to lose sight of  my predilections, and signed on for the tour.</p>
        <p>Mistake, I began to realize on my very first morning in Turkey. Our group -- 30 people, mostly women -- had been picked up in front of our hotel, the Sheraton in Ankara, by a sparkling new bus provided by a major Turkish tour company. The Westchester art historian, although he remained with the tour throughout, had deposited us into their presumably more experienced hands, and they had assigned us a guide, a man named aptly, I would soon discover, Attilla.</p>
        <p>"What do you think of this bus?" Attilla demanded as soon as we had taken our seats, and went on to inform us that it cost $500,000 -- "more than the homes of some of you." It was equipped, he boasted, with everything -- a refrigerator, a  heating unit for making tea and coffee and, splendor of splendors, an up-to-the-minute toilet. "But," cautioned Attilla, "please don't use the toilet, ladies and gentlemen. We will be stopping at rest stops every two hours."</p>
        <p>Why couldn't we use the toilet? Attilla had no good explanation, and after several visits to roadside facilities (Turkish roadside toilets are often primitive), several of us decided to use the one on the bus. Attilla glared at us, as did the driver. Apparently the toilet, although in fine working order, was on the bus merely for show and tell.</p>
        <p>Things quickly got worse. "You will put your bags out tomorrow at 6 A.M.," Attilla announced at the end of that first day, a rather boring four-hour drive  from Ankara to Cappadocia. "To do so, you will wake up at 5:30 A.M." I groaned.  "Five-thirty A.M.? I don't get up at 5:30 when I'm working," I said. "I'm certainly not going to do it when I'm on vacation."</p>
        <p>"You have no choice," Attilla said. And I didn't. Unless I wanted to be left  behind at the brand new walls-as-thin-as-paper Dedeman Hotel in Nevsehir and miss the underground city of Kaymakli, the painted cave churches of Goreme and the fairy chimneys of Urgup. I went to bed as early as I could, awakened as required at 5:30, and saw the wonders of Cappadocia through half-shut eyes.</p>
        <p>We had a hurried lunch that day in a roadside place packed with people from other tour buses -- American, Japanese, German. We dined, if I can use that word, on watery soup followed by a plate of beans followed by a swirl of something sinewy that was said to be chicken. It was here that I first began to  feel an uncontrollable yearning for cloth napkins, or at least paper ones larger than 3 by 3 inches.</p>
        <p>Soon we were eating in places like this twice a day. Some were prettier than  others. One was beside a spectacular lake, where Turks were eating on a sunny patio by the water -- but we were thrust inside at the usual long tables. (This  particular restaurant required our taking a long detour, and turned out to be owned by the tour company.)</p>
        <p>Seeing the sights with 30 people was no more pleasant than eating with them.  Because we were a crowd, and an assumption had been made about the average person's ability to concentrate, there was never time for absorption, reflection, ambling. We were given an hour and a half for Ephesus. Ephesus, with its vast distances, huge ancient theater, long marble-paved streets! Ephesus, where the colonnaded two-story library alone demands an hour of contemplation. But I suppose we were lucky. We had only a half-hour for the mesmerizing whirling dervish mausoleum and museum at Konya. An hour for Aphrodisias. An hour for Pergamum. Two hours -- and in the rain at that -- for Topkapi Palace and its many courtyards.</p>
        <p>Few people on the tour seemed to mind the lightning speed with which we were  whisked through famous sites. They listened avidly to brief cultural lectures given by both Attilla and the Westchester art historian and, after each stop, studiously checked off the names of the places we'd seen.</p>
        <p>How did we spend the bulk of our time?  Driving huge distances in the bus, distances that would more wisely have been flown. And shopping. We not only stopped at every trinket stall in front of every site, but we were also taken to other, more established shops -- emporiums for pottery, onyx, jewelry, wine, rugs, leather. These were relatively high-priced places but, we were told, the quality of their goods was excellent. (We were not told whether the tour company got a commission.)</p>
        <p>Pondering the fiasco, I realized that I had to bear some of the responsibility. Overworked and rushed before signing up, I hadn't taken the time to study the brochure carefully, to note the numbers of cities we were going to  visit, or the vast distances between them. Even though I usually check out an untried New York restaurant with knowledgeable friends or acquaintances before trying it, I hadn't used the same basic precautions with the tour company.</p>
        <p>I rebelled. Midway through the trip, I started doing my own thing whenever possible. One day, I persuaded three cronies to skip the scheduled hasty tour of Perge, Aspendos and Side, and to join me instead on a ramble through the narrow  streets of the charming Mediterranean town of Antalya. One of our group bought two rugs -- they were cheaper and of better quality than those in the tour-touted shop -- and we lunched at the lovely Kral Sofrasi restaurant, sitting beneath lemon trees at a table for four (an indescribable pleasure) and  eating freshly caught fish that the headwaiter not only artfully deboned but even more artfully reassembled, ornamenting the creature's toothy little mouth with a sprig of parsley. We were scolded that night by one of the tour's obsessive culture vultures. "You mean you came all this way to Turkey and didn't see Perge?" she chided. But we winked at one another. We'd had what had been missing so far: fun.</p>
        <p>ANOTHER day, I talked a woman on the tour into having dinner with me at a restaurant in Izmir, a small smoky place jammed with laughing, gossiping Turks.  We were seated at a table for six already occupied by three Turkish men, one of  whom spoke a little French, another a little English. By this time, I had learned a few words of Turkish, and soon the five of us were chatting away in three languages, and sharing our delicately fried calamari, grilled fish and a huge platter of sweets. On a third occasion, I refused to join the group at the  spot where Attilla insisted we must eat our lunch -- the rain-drenched and windswept terrace of the Konyali restaurant in Topkapi -- and fled instead to a  warm, carpeted interior room, where for $10 I sat in solitary splendor at a banquette and ate a marvelous stew of lamb and yogurt.</p>
        <p>And one afternoon, I went on my own to the intimidatingly mammoth Grand Bazaar in Istanbul, to which the group had gone en masse earlier in the day. I was fearful of getting lost, or being accosted by unshakable rug merchants. But  I found my way easily by stopping passers-by for instructions, and just as easily extricated myself from encounters with overly persistent merchants. I also ended up meeting, and eventually taking to tea, a delightful Kurdish youth, who told me the whole story of his young life and his remarkable transition from eastern Anatolian village shepherd to Istanbul English student. I treasured that talk, and knew it was something that would never have happened had I stuck to my troupe of 30.</p>
        <p>LINDA WOLFE is a journalist and novelist who lives inNew York.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">LINDA WOLFE is a journalist and novelist who lives inNew York.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
