<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Traders Have One Question: Are We There Yet?</title>
    <meta content="22PORT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/22/business/yourmoney/22PORT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1425931"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PORTFOLIOS, ETC."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Portfolios Etc</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Nasdaq Composite Index</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507EEDA1E30F931A1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Traders Have One Question: Are We There Yet?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Traders Have One Question: Are We There Yet?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jonathan Fuerbringer Portfolios, Etc column examines various barometers used to predict future of stock markets; notes lack of unaminity among gauges currently makes forecasting difficult; graph of volatility (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALL the major stock indexes tumbled last week -- one by as much as 5.4 percent -- leaving the market perilously close to the five-year low it reached in the summer.</p>
        <p>As of Friday, the Dow Jones industrial average was just 284 points away from its low of 7,702.34. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index has to fall only 48 points to reach its low of 797.70, and the Nasdaq composite is only 15 points from its low of 1,206.01.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As of Friday, the Dow Jones industrial average was just 284 points away from its low of 7,702.34. So investors may be wondering whether the bottom of the market is lower than they thought.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALL the major stock indexes tumbled last week -- one by as much as 5.4 percent -- leaving the market perilously close to the five-year low it reached in the summer.</p>
        <p>As of Friday, the Dow Jones industrial average was just 284 points away from its low of 7,702.34. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index has to fall only 48 points to reach its low of 797.70, and the Nasdaq composite is only 15 points from its low of 1,206.01.</p>
        <p>So investors may be wondering whether the bottom of the market is lower than they thought.</p>
        <p>When Wall Street analysts confront questions like this, they consult various barometers of market turns that they have used in the past, for good or ill. These include measures of market volatility, long-term moving averages of market indexes, gauges of value, volume, highs and lows, and meters of bullish or bearish sentiment.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, a glance at them does not give a clear thumbs up or down. But on the whole, a selection of these indicators doesn't say, for the moment, that things are going to become much worse.</p>
        <p>Traders use some of these market guides for short-term readings -- to get a sense of where the market is going today, this week or this month. Notably, some barometers are moving back toward their levels of July 23, when the Dow and the S.&amp; P. 500 hit their lows. The index of volatility compiled by the Chicago Board Options Exchange closed at 44.55 on Friday, not far from its close of 50.48 on July 23.</p>
        <p>There may be some comfort in the volatility numbers. Before July 23, the last time the volatility index closed above 50 was on Sept. 21, 2001. That turned out to be a bottom for the market drop that followed the terrorist attacks. When the volatility index reached highs of 39.96 in 1997 and 48.56 in 1998, the market also hit bottoms.</p>
        <p>Another measure, nicknamed Trin, takes a reading of advancing versus declining stocks and then factors in trading volume to test how meaningful the advances and declines are. Like the volatility reading, it is giving some hints of a bottom.</p>
        <p>The ratio of stocks hitting 52-week highs to those falling to lows is neutral at the moment. But it has been moving in a positive direction as the number of stocks setting highs has increased.</p>
        <p>Longer-term investment yardsticks, recommended by William E. Rhodes, chief investment strategist of Rhodes Analytics in Boston, also provide some reassurance. These measures of economic strength don't help to determine if the market will fall much below its current level. But they do hint at whether the longer-term underpinning for stocks is positive or negative.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rhodes pays close attention to a proxy for economic growth -- industrial production, adjusted for inflation by the Consumer Price Index -- because data on the gross domestic product is released only quarterly. This indicator is bullish for now. That fits with forecasts that the economy probably grew at an annual rate of 3.5 percent or more in the third quarter -- not a robust number for a traditional economic recovery, but much better than the 1.1 percent rate in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>Another measure, money supply growth, is off its peak but not worrisome, Mr. Rhodes said.</p>
        <p>BUT investor sentiment has been moving in a bullish direction in the last few weeks after dipping in late July and early August to its most bearish level since the weeks after the terrorist attacks. This contrarian measure, calculated by Investors Intelligence, has to become more bearish for a market bottom to appear closer.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rhodes adds his own bit of caution. When he runs stocks though his financial sorters, he is finding only one to buy for every 26 to sell. The market would have a better outlook, he said, if he could just find more buys than sells.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the market will not fall much further, even if it does break through the summer bottom. But if many investors are as picky as Mr. Rhodes, there may not be much of a rebound when the bottom is found.</p>
        <p>PORTFOLIOS, ETC.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
