<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some Classics In Silver: Spoons, Shovels, Subway Maps</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="697091"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="ARTS/ARTIFACTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SILVER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MUSEUM OF THE CITY OF NEW YORK</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REIF, RITA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Silver</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDD143CF930A35754C0A962958260" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some Classics In Silver: Spoons, Shovels, Subway Maps</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RITA REIF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REIF, RITA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>NEW YORKERS HAVE adapted the tribal art of silver giving to all sorts of peculiar personal and civic events: Engraved silver spoons were distributed at the 17th-century funeral of a minister upstate. Silver medals were struck in 1826 to mark the completion of the Erie Canal. And Tiffany &amp; Company produced a silver-bladed shovel in 1900 for the ground-breaking ceremony of Manhattan's first subway.</p>
        <p>The proof of the precious metal's role in the city's history is captured in "A Treasury of New York Silver," a dazzling exhibition at the Museum of the City of New York, remaining through Dec. 31. The show also reveals the evolution of the silversmith's craft, from making items in Colonial workshops for the elite to the 20th-century mass marketing of anonymous-looking silver products for all segments of society.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>NEW YORKERS HAVE adapted the tribal art of silver giving to all sorts of peculiar personal and civic events: Engraved silver spoons were distributed at the 17th-century funeral of a minister upstate. Silver medals were struck in 1826 to mark the completion of the Erie Canal. And Tiffany &amp; Company produced a silver-bladed shovel in 1900 for the ground-breaking ceremony of Manhattan's first subway.</p>
        <p>The proof of the precious metal's role in the city's history is captured in "A Treasury of New York Silver," a dazzling exhibition at the Museum of the City of New York, remaining through Dec. 31. The show also reveals the evolution of the silversmith's craft, from making items in Colonial workshops for the elite to the 20th-century mass marketing of anonymous-looking silver products for all segments of society.</p>
        <p>The museum's silver collection, one of the finest holdings in America, is rarely exhibited in such depth, says Deborah Waters, the curator of decorative arts who organized the show of 300 tankards, trays, urns, bowls and loving cups. The majority of the pieces are from the most creative periods: the late 18th and the late 19th centuries.</p>
        <p>The exhibition's labels read like a Knickerbocker Who's Who, since prominent citizens of all periods either devised or owned the pieces on view. The oldest dated object is a spoon from a 1678 memorial service, inscribed on its trefoil-shaped handle with the name and death date of Dominie Nicholas Van Rensselaer, the pastor of an Albany church, who was a member of one of the aristocratic families of Colonial New York. Among the newer pieces is a 1955 kiddush cup and cover; the wine vessel, decorated with grapevines and Hebrew lettering, is from the collection of Richard Rodgers, the composer.</p>
        <p>Another cup, this one made before 1720 for the communal sipping of brandied fruits, was a bequest to the museum by a member of the Van Cortlandt family. Known as a brandywine bowl, it is boldly embellished with stylized flowers and two delicately scrolled handles. And a hefty tankard, engraved simply with the initials of its owners, Isaac and Cornelia Roosevelt, ancestors of Theodore Roosevelt, was produced in 1752 by Nicholas Roosevelt, a cousin.</p>
        <p>New York's best-known Colonial silversmith, Myer Myers, is handsomely represented with coffeepots, tankards, salts, spoons and a tall mug -- rococo designs with strong forms and restrained decoration.</p>
        <p>In the 19th century, silver gifts became far more flamboyant, as is seen in the gilded fruit stand and dishes presented in 1866 to Cyrus W. Field, the industrialist. The pieces are part of the Gorham dinner service commissioned to celebrate the success of Field's second trans-Atlantic telegraph cable.</p>
        <p>It's not surprising that Tiffany silver outnumbers the works of all other makers in the show and includes such outlandish and nostalgic objects as a 1900 dog collar and a 1928 cocktail shaker. From the Fifth Avenue jeweler's golden age in the late 19th century comes a candelabrum, a sauce boat, a pepper shaker and several bowls awash with cast chrysanthemums, and one of the show's more spectacular objects: the Goelet trophy from 1889. The huge bowl, awash with mermaids and Neptune-like figures, was won by C. Oliver Iselin, a Manhattan banker, at Newport, R.I., racing his sloop Titania.</p>
        <p>Tiffany also conceived the shovel and tray, a yard long, for the opening ceremonies in 1904 of the Interborough Rapid Transit subway, the nation's first underground railway. Engravers labored long on the tray's surface to depict stations and a portrait of the contractor around the rim and a map of the first leg, which ran from City Hall to 145th Street and under the East River to Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>While Tiffany captured more plum commissions than other producers, the Gorham company of Providence, R.I., was as adept at conveying overstatement with flair. The best example is a loving cup in the shape of an ancient oak, its handles simulating branches, its trunk engraved with scenes from operas, including "The Meistersinger." The vessel was presented in 1897 to Anton Seidl, a conductor of the Metropolitan Opera, by his New York admirers.</p>
        <p>Many hands often became involved in the design and production of silver items made for prestigious events, including the festivities in New York Harbor that followed the completion of the Erie Canal. Five men were responsible for the medal marking the occasion, which depicts Neptune and Pan on one side, the spread-winged eagle from the crest of the State of New York on the other. The medal is displayed with its box, a work by Duncan Phyfe, Manhattan's leading cabinetmaker, who used western woods brought through the canal and down the Hudson.</p>
        <p>The most curious objects in the show are several 18th-century utensils that have become obsolete. While the sugar scissors, which were used to clip off small chunks from sugar cones, are curlicued relics now deemed eminently forgettable, today's feasts might be improved by the addition of utensils that combine tiny tines or bowls with long, slender handles. Sucket forks, made to spear brandied fruits, and marrow spoons, for scooping out the tasty contents of boiled beef bones, may be outmoded, but their spare forms are as modern as tomorrow.  ARTS/ARTIFACTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
