<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mariners Make Sure That Key Can't Stop Yankees' Slide</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="697383"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SEATTLE MARINERS</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Seattle Mariners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFDE113CF930A35754C0A962958260" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mariners Make Sure That Key Can't Stop Yankees' Slide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM MORAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The response had become so consistent that it was too easy to take for granted. Yankees lose, Key wins. They would lose a game and he would immediately respond -- effortlessly, it seemed -- and a losing streak would be averted once more. Jimmy Key's sterling season, which has already inspired memories of left-handers with the names Guidry, Ford and Gomez, included a 5-0 record following a Yankee loss.</p>
        <p>Yesterday was not one of those days, but it did serve a purpose. Seattle's 12-6 victory, the third consecutive Yankee defeat, carried the reminder that Key's craftsmanship does not come easily. He just normally makes it seem that way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The response had become so consistent that it was too easy to take for granted. Yankees lose, Key wins. They would lose a game and he would immediately respond -- effortlessly, it seemed -- and a losing streak would be averted once more. Jimmy Key's sterling season, which has already inspired memories of left-handers with the names Guidry, Ford and Gomez, included a 5-0 record following a Yankee loss.</p>
        <p>Yesterday was not one of those days, but it did serve a purpose. Seattle's 12-6 victory, the third consecutive Yankee defeat, carried the reminder that Key's craftsmanship does not come easily. He just normally makes it seem that way.</p>
        <p>Key (12-2) endured his first defeat since April 9 to end a streak of 11 victories, the longest of his career.</p>
        <p>"It makes you appreciate even more the things he has been able to do for us," said Buck Showalter, the Yankee manager.</p>
        <p>Key's earned run average, which was third best in the American League at the start of the afternoon, rose from 3.01 to 3.36 after he allowed six earned runs in four innings.</p>
        <p>"I was searching all day," Key said. "I made a good pitch here and there, but I had nothing consistently. It finally caved in in the fifth."</p>
        <p>After allowing two runs, six hits and three walks through the first four innings, Key gave up three singles and a double to the four hitters he faced in the fifth, all of whom scored. Seattle's first nine hitters reached base in the eight-run fifth, the most productive inning of the Mariners' season and the most the Yankees have allowed in an inning this year.</p>
        <p>Key's shortest outing since last Aug. 28 was a struggle from the start. He allowed two hits in the first inning. In the second, Key fell behind 3-0 before walking Bill Haselman, the No. 8 hitter with an average of .195. Key then fell behind 2-0 against Brian Turang, the No. 9 hitter with a .169 average, before escaping with an inning-ending flyout.</p>
        <p>His problems intensified in the third, when with two out, Ken Griffey lined his second hit against Key during the Seattle star's five-hit afternoon. Key then walked Edgar Martinez and gave up a line single to right by Mike Blowers that scored Griffey for a 1-0 lead.</p>
        <p>The Mariners made it 2-0 with a run in the fourth. Tino Martinez grounded a single to center field and was advanced to second by Haselman's bunt. A walk to Turang was Key's third of the game, which equaled or exceeded his total in 15 of his previous 17 starts this season. Rich Amaral then lined a single to left field to score Tino Martinez.</p>
        <p>Dave Fleming (6-10) allowed three runs in seven innings, an efficient effort that on most other days would probably not be enough to match Key. Yesterday it was more than enough to present Seattle, which won for the fourth straight time, with an opportunity to sweep the Yankees in the Bronx for the first time in the 18-year history of the Mariners' franchise. Griffey 5 for 6, All Singles</p>
        <p>Seattle succeeded by executing an approach to Key that had been tried, less successfully, by other teams.</p>
        <p>"We stayed patient," said Griffey, whose five hits -- all singles to right field -- in six at-bats came to symbolize that patience. "We laid off pitches. That made it tough."</p>
        <p>In his return to the place where he spent time as an adolescent when his father played for the Yankees a decade ago, Griffey brought 32 home runs to the batter's box where Babe Ruth produced a 60 home run season in 1927 and Roger Maris broke the record with 61 in 1961.</p>
        <p>Griffey remained stuck on 32 for a seventh game to tie his second-longest home run drought of the season. But with pitches frequently staying on the outside part of the plate, Griffey stroked five of them, four sharply with one soft line drive, to produce the second five-hit game of his career. He now has 102 hits and a batting average of .330, statistics that are obscured by the early stages of a home run chase.</p>
        <p>"Nobody wants me to break the record," Griffey said. "The fans do, but as far as the teams go, they don't want their pitchers to be on that list, and I understand that. But I'm going to go up there and swing, and I'm going to take what they give me." INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The tendinitis in DON MATTINGLY's right wrist has improved enough that he is expected to play shortly. An examination yesterday by Dr. MELVIN ROSENWASSER revealed improvement in the condition that has kept the first baseman out of the lineup since last Monday. Manager BUCK SHOWALTER said that if Mattingly's condition had not improved over the weekend, the Yankees would have considered placing the team captain on the disabled list. PAT KELLY, who has been on the disabled list since June 25 with an injured left thumb, was also examined. Kelly is expected to resume hitting in several days. . . . KEN GRIFFEY's average against JIMMY KEY is .343. . . . JAY BUHNER, the former Yankee who bruised his pelvis making a game-ending catch against the right-field wall Friday night to preserve Seattle's 4-3 victory, was not in the lineup yesterday. . . . JOHN CUMMINGS, a 25-year-old left-hander with a 1-2 record, has replaced the right-hander CHRIS BOSIO as Seattle's starter this afternoon. "I've got my reasons," said Mariners Manager LOU PINIELLA. Here's one: When New York's opponents have started left-handed pitchers, the Yankee record is 11-11. In games started by right-handers, the Yankee record is 36-19. . .  DAVE SILVESTRI, who could not prevent Griffey's hard-hit grounder from driving in the winning run Friday night, was replaced at second base yesterday by RANDY VELARDE. The appearance at second was the 31st in Velarde's major league career, but his first start at the position since May 6, 1992.  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
