<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Glitter of New York Beckons (Or Is It Tarnish Elsewhere?)</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="697337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCOTT, JANNY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E6D7103CF930A35754C0A962958260" item-length="1522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Glitter of New York Beckons (Or Is It Tarnish Elsewhere?)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANNY SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCOTT, JANNY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A city's image ebbs and flows with many tides. Prices rise, crime drops, perceptions follow. But precise turning points may slip past, slow to register on such popular barometers as housing prices and dinner-party talk.</p>
        <p>The image of New York, of course, is never simple; it has always encompassed fantastic extremes of good and bad. But in recent decades, the bad has often eclipsed the good in the views of outsiders (and more than a few insiders, too).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A city's image ebbs and flows with many tides. Prices rise, crime drops, perceptions follow. But precise turning points may slip past, slow to register on such popular barometers as housing prices and dinner-party talk.</p>
        <p>The image of New York, of course, is never simple; it has always encompassed fantastic extremes of good and bad. But in recent decades, the bad has often eclipsed the good in the views of outsiders (and more than a few insiders, too).</p>
        <p>Now some New Yorkers, at least, think the tide may be turning, and some even think this may be tied to the fortunes of other big cities turning sour. They see small signs in odd places: in what law students confide to law-firm recruiters, what executives tell headhunters, and what other Americans tell pollsters about the cities they fear most.</p>
        <p>Some of the most striking evidence is coming from Columbia University and New York University: undergraduate applications have shot up, and admissions officers believe that one reason is that more students want to be in New York.</p>
        <p>They are so sure of that point that they have overhauled their recruiting materials to try to capitalize on the city as a selling point. After years trying to ignore or explain away New York, they are now big boosters.</p>
        <p>At Columbia, the admissions office dumped its old black-and-white booklets in favor of a glossy, 52-page, full-color magazine that opens with an expansive, aerial view of midtown Manhattan at night and follows that with photographs of bagels baking, the Stock Exchange floor, jazz musicians, a perpetually sunny New York.</p>
        <p>New York University now sends out a homemade videotape about Greenwich Village, in which the university's voluble president, L. Jay Oliva, perambulates the neighborhood like a zealous tour guide, extolling its manifold virtues and chatting up local notables like Charles Kuralt.</p>
        <p>Each school can also produce a list of professors and administrators it recently lured, or kept, from competing institutions elsewhere. Many say New York was a big draw; some say the city appealed to them in ways it had not 10 years before.</p>
        <p>An image improvement, even if only among the likes of students and academics, would not be an insignificant event for New York, especially now that the region's economy depends increasingly upon highly trained professionals and less and less on its shrinking manufacturing base.</p>
        <p>But if people are, in fact, seeing New York in a better light, the reasons may have less to do with the city than with perceived problems elsewhere. If New York's image is recovering some luster, one big reason appears to be that other cities and towns are losing theirs.</p>
        <p>In the words of Dr. Herbert Pardes, Columbia's vice president for health sciences, who recently turned down a job at the University of California, Los Angeles, "You don't have the feeling that pain and drugs are the exclusive province of New York."</p>
        <p>Much of the evidence is, of course, wildly unscientific.</p>
        <p>Maria Alkiewicz, director of legal personnel for Sullivan &amp; Cromwell, the law firm, watched job applicants grow fearful for New York's future after the 1987 stock market crash. Now, she said, she has seen Seattle and California slipping down the list of favored places for young lawyers to settle. Executive Interest</p>
        <p>John P. Bassler, who runs offices in the New York region for Korn/Ferry International, the executive-search firm, finds more and more people interested in returning to New York City -- a tendency he attributes to the possibility that other cities look in many ways increasingly like New York.</p>
        <p>Even a Gallup Poll last September suggested marginal improvement (though not exactly the makings of a new advertising jingle): just 76 percent of people polled think of New York as unsafe, down from 85 percent in 1990. Miami had overtaken New York, according to the poll, and Los Angeles was closing in.</p>
        <p>Some of the conclusions being drawn amuse Californians.</p>
        <p>Robert Weisberg, Stanford University's vice provost for faculty recruitment and development, insisted that professors rarely pick their employers by geographic location, except to make sure that they can afford housing and that there is work nearby for their spouses, who are often in academia too.</p>
        <p>"To say, as a general matter, that people would strongly prefer to live and work in New York City is crazy," said Professor Weisberg, a Bronx native who left the city at age 20 and who admits to being afflicted with a "typical, complicated, love-hate relationship" with New York. 'A Refined Taste'</p>
        <p>David O. Sears, a psychology professor and former dean at the University of California, Los Angeles, conceded that the spread of urban problems "levels the playing field a little bit among the big cities." But he insisted "big-city, urban life is a fairly refined taste for academics."</p>
        <p>The idea that New York might have become a selling point came to Columbia several years ago from Jan Krukowski, a consultant hired by the university to figure out how to attract more applicants. Mr. Krukowski surveyed 800 possible applicants and found that the city was a powerful attraction.</p>
        <p>So Columbia made its recruiting materials "much more sexy in their portrayal of New York," said Drusilla Blackman, dean of undergraduate admissions and financial aid. She feels that decision helps explain this year's 16 percent increase in applications, the largest ever.</p>
        <p>Dean Blackman and others said there has been a surge of interest in big-city colleges in general. But she said the increase at Columbia was larger than that experienced by other urban schools.</p>
        <p>New York University has seen a similar leap -- from 10,837 applications in 1992 to 14,463 in 1994. Administrators credit improvements in faculty and facilities, as well as a change in the way New York is viewed. "We are convinced at this point that the city is really helping us," said David Finney, associate vice president for enrollment services. Columbia Reaching Far</p>
        <p>It is not known at whose expense the increase comes. But the percentage of New York University students from outside the New York metropolitan area is rising. Columbia has begun recruiting more aggressively in the Southwest, Southeast and Midwest. Meanwhile, out-of-state freshman applications to the University of California system have dropped by almost 50 percent since 1989, reflecting steep increases in fees and perhaps concerns about the state in the wake of recent earthquakes, riots and economic troubles.</p>
        <p>Why New York might seem more attractive is not entirely clear. Mr. Finney believes one reason is specific to students in hard economic times: with its innumerable opportunities for internships and other off-campus jobs, students see New York as a place to make contacts and get a jump on careers.</p>
        <p>Others believe city life is improving. The economy is growing, slightly, after years of recession; the crime rate and real estate prices are down.  Many symbols are offered: air conditioning on the subway trains, improved snow removal, less graffiti, the disappearance of suitcase radios.</p>
        <p>But mostly, people point to the shortcomings of other places. They say leaving New York is no longer an escape from crime, drugs, troubled schools, traffic. New York now shares those problems with many places, they say, but it still offers opportunities available nowhere else.</p>
        <p>Dean Blackman of Columbia left the city in 1987, feeling it was becoming unlivable. It seemed unsafe and in a state of collapse. "Our feeling at the time was that we were going for good," said Dean Blackman, who took a job at Harvard University. "Our plan was to eventually downsize to a small town." Liked the Intensity</p>
        <p>But she and her husband found Boston parochial and Bostonians hostile to outsiders. Over time, they began to plot their return. "We discovered that we were addicted to the level of services, activity, intensity and resources that New York provides and that we would not be happy with anything less."</p>
        <p>After six years, they came back. She insists New York feels safer and seems to be addressing much of what had driven her out. "Leaving New York didn't mean you left those problems behind," she said. New York has drawbacks, but it also has "more positives than the average city."</p>
        <p>Larry Kramer, a New York University law professor, first lived in New York in the early 1980's. He remembers it as decaying, its parks unkempt, its subway system subhuman. He moved to Chicago, then Ann Arbor, Mich. When he took a sabbatical semester in 1992, he looked for a place where he would never want to live again: "New York, for sure."</p>
        <p>To his surprise, the city struck him as cleaner and more livable than before. He began to appreciate its virtues -- and feel the limitations of the other places. So, earlier this year, he left the University of Michigan and turned down a job at the University of Chicago to move permanently to New York.</p>
        <p>"To some extent, it was my own development," Professor Kramer said. "But I found there were real differences in the city. I feel confident saying it's a better place now than when I left here in 1985."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
