<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mills' Tale, With Fact Husked of Fiction</title>
    <meta content="02WERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/02/arts/television/02WERT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1356021"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wertheimer, Ron</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mill Times (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Textiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service (PBS)</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE2D81530F931A35752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mills' Tale, With Fact Husked of Fiction</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mills' Tale, With Fact Husked of Fiction</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RON WERTHEIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wertheimer, Ron</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ron Wertheimer reviews PBS program Mill Times, introduction to New England's textile mills; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In ''Mill Times,'' on PBS tonight, David Macaulay proves an avuncular tour guide through technological history. The hour blends elements of standard documentary with animated storytelling to offer an easy-to-take introduction to New England's textile mills, which began transforming life and commerce in the region in the late 1700's.</p>
        <p>Tonight's production was suggested by Mr. Macaulay's 1983 book, ''Mill,'' part of his series of meticulously illustrated histories -- including ''Castle,'' ''Cathedral'' and ''Pyramid'' -- that are enduringly popular with older children and advanced adults. This is the fifth television adaptation of one of these books, but viewers who know Mr. Macaulay's work only from the page may be disappointed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Macaulay blends elements of standard documentary with animated storytelling to offer an easy-to-take introduction to New England's textile mills.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In ''Mill Times,'' on PBS tonight, David Macaulay proves an avuncular tour guide through technological history. The hour blends elements of standard documentary with animated storytelling to offer an easy-to-take introduction to New England's textile mills, which began transforming life and commerce in the region in the late 1700's.</p>
        <p>Tonight's production was suggested by Mr. Macaulay's 1983 book, ''Mill,'' part of his series of meticulously illustrated histories -- including ''Castle,'' ''Cathedral'' and ''Pyramid'' -- that are enduringly popular with older children and advanced adults. This is the fifth television adaptation of one of these books, but viewers who know Mr. Macaulay's work only from the page may be disappointed.</p>
        <p>It would probably be impossible for television to duplicate, at least in a mere hour, the visual and verbal detail of ''Mill,'' which follows the fortunes of three fictional Rhode Island enterprises and the people who owned them. But while the book's fiction is woven seamlessly with its careful history, the television version presents these two elements in sharp contrast.</p>
        <p>The animated passages, directed by Roger Mainwood for the Animation Partnership in London, recount the tale of a new set of fictional characters. While these sequences have a few memorable images and hints of Mr. Macaulay's lovingly rendered details of the mills' construction and operation, the cartoon scenes offer too little inventiveness and too much melodrama. They dilute the impact of the live-action sequences in which Mr. Macaulay himself shares his obvious knowledge about and enthusiasm for his subject.</p>
        <p>Some 200 years ago, he begins, water power, which was already running saw-  and gristmills, was harnessed for the manufacture of yarn and then cloth. ''Societies that once responded to the rhythm of the sun and seasons now moved to the beating of the clock,'' Mr. Macaulay says.</p>
        <p>These innovations, first developed in Britain, were soon brought to America, where ever-bigger mills were built along rivers. Mr. Macaulay visits historic restorations in New (and old) England to demonstrate the beautifully simple concepts that won this skirmish of the Industrial Revolution. To learn about it now, in this overwrought digital age, is reassuring.</p>
        <p>The goods made by that technology allowed Americans to have better clothing at lower cost. Cities grew around the mills, as workers, especially young women, were lured off farms into dangerous jobs and crowded living quarters. ''Complaints about rodents, the communal outhouse and a lack of privacy were common,'' Mr. Macaulay says. ''But most women clearly liked boardinghouse life and the excitement of the city.''</p>
        <p>Still, as with all progress, this variety had drawbacks. The mills employed children and encouraged slavery in the South, which supplied cotton for the mills' growing appetites. Competition between mills was sometimes cutthroat, as the dams for newer, bigger operations cut the vital water power from the older ones.</p>
        <p>Finally steam power rendered this revolutionary technology obsolete. In the 20th century the textile industry abandoned New England, first for the South, ''where labor was cheap, where cotton grew right outside the door,'' and later overseas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Macaulay tells a fascinating tale, although apparently not in his own words. Tonight's writing credits go to Larry Klein (also the producer and director) and Mark Olshaker. Their effort is more than educational, but it's far less inspired (and inspiring) than Mr. Macaulay's original.</p>
        <p>MILL TIMES  On some PBS stations tonight  (check local listings)</p>
        <p>Larry Klein, producer and director; Mark Olshaker and Mr. Klein, writers; animation by Animation Partnership; Roger Mainwood, animation director. David Macaulay, host. Presented by WGBH Boston.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
