<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EBay's Joy Ride: Going Once . . .</title>
    <meta content="06EBAY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/03/06/business/yourmoney/06ebay.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050313T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1654906"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ebay Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Paypal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivlin, Gary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">eBay Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitman, Meg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DD113DF935A35750C0A9639C8B63" item-length="3859" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EBay's Joy Ride: Going Once . . .</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">EBay's Joy Ride: Going Once ...</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GARY RIVLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rivlin, Gary</byline>
      <dateline>San Jose, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>People who sell on eBay protest steep fee increases announced in January, but eBay executives are not concerned, recalling protests that greeted previous increases and saying company wants to restore balance between those using auctions and those selling items for flat price in eBay stores; more worrisome for company are doubts raised by longtime sellers and Wall Street analysts about eBay's ability to keep up its torrid rate of growth; company's fortunes are thought to hinge ultimately less on growth rate of company's American site than on its foreign operations and on use of its PayPal payment system beyond eBay site; graphs; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE open revolt began almost instantly among eBay's sellers -- a hodgepodge of hobbyists, slick entrepreneurs and quirky collectors who conduct daily virtual auctions of everything from samurai swords and refrigerator magnets to an unread copy of an ''Archie and Veronica'' comic book (Volume 55). In January, eBay announced steep fee increases, which took effect two weeks ago, prompting sellers to post caustic comments on community bulletin boards both on and off the company's Web site. Petitions have been circulated, sellers have debated an eBay boycott and those unhappy with the company seem evenly split over whether ''FeeBay'' or ''GreedBay'' is the most apt epithet for it.</p>
        <p>Inside eBay, the reaction to all this is: So what else is new?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Many longtime sellers and Wall Street analysts, long bullish on eBay, now say they are uncertain about the company's ability to sustain its torrid rate of growth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE open revolt began almost instantly among eBay's sellers -- a hodgepodge of hobbyists, slick entrepreneurs and quirky collectors who conduct daily virtual auctions of everything from samurai swords and refrigerator magnets to an unread copy of an ''Archie and Veronica'' comic book (Volume 55). In January, eBay announced steep fee increases, which took effect two weeks ago, prompting sellers to post caustic comments on community bulletin boards both on and off the company's Web site. Petitions have been circulated, sellers have debated an eBay boycott and those unhappy with the company seem evenly split over whether ''FeeBay'' or ''GreedBay'' is the most apt epithet for it.</p>
        <p>Inside eBay, the reaction to all this is: So what else is new?</p>
        <p>Five times in five years, the company has raised the price of doing business on its site, and each increase -- whether a bump in the charge for listing an auction item or a jump in the commission the company collects on a completed sale -- has provoked strident outbursts. The practiced nonchalance with which eBay executives greet even these harshest of pronouncements starts with the chief executive, Meg Whitman, possibly the most powerful woman in corporate America today. Speaking at the company headquarters here last week, she sounded almost nostalgic when talking about past protests, like the ''Million Auction March,'' hatched in 2000 by those who were upset when eBay announced that it would be selling banner advertisements on its site.</p>
        <p>''The thing to know about the eBay community,'' she said, ''is that it's been vocal from Day 1.'' Ms. Whitman allowed that the dissatisfied had lately ''perhaps been a tad more vocal than in the past.'' But to her mind, that is because eBay is so much more vast today than it was only a few years ago.</p>
        <p>Despite the Million Auction March and what William C. Cobb, who oversees the company's North American operations, called the ''constant drone'' of complaints on the company's message boards, the collective worth of merchandise sold through eBay has surged since 2000, to $33.8 billion from $5.2 billion.</p>
        <p>Even so, others in the eBay universe are convinced that the company has a far bigger problem on its hands than it is willing to acknowledge. They include many longtime sellers and Wall Street analysts, long bullish on eBay, who now say they are uncertain about the company's ability to sustain its torrid rate of growth. As they see it, Newtonian physics may finally be catching up with eBay after one of the most magical rides ever for the stock of a young company.</p>
        <p>It is too early to assess the fallout from the recent furor over fees, but this much is clear: the company has never before imposed so sharp a rate climb. Hardest hit were those who operate virtual stores on the eBay worldwide mall. As of Feb. 18, store owners must pay eBay an 8 percent commission on each sale, up from 5.25 percent.</p>
        <p>''Imagine the reaction if a state raised its sales tax by nearly three percentage points,'' said Ina Steiner, the editor and publisher of AuctionBytes.com, an online newsletter that has reported on the online auction world since 1999. It is no surprise, Ms. Steiner said, that in recent weeks she has heard an outcry not only from those who tend to bark loudly whenever eBay raises a fee, but also from those who ''might have rolled their eyes over a fee increase in the past but kept selling.''</p>
        <p>SINCE the end of January, more than 24,000 people have added their names to an online petition protesting the new fees. A according to PowerSellersUnite.com, a site run by a fed-up former eBay seller, more than 7,000 eBay stores have shut down in the five weeks since the company announced the fee increase. EBay said it had 161,000 stores on its North American site at the end of 2004.</p>
        <p>''People stay on eBay because they get value from it,'' Ms. Steiner said. But Ms. Steiner, among others, worries that dishonest practices by sellers -- shipping a knock-off instead of the genuine article, for example -- are eroding the trust essential to eBay's continued health. EBay says it now has more than 1,000 employees working to eradicate fraud, but Ms. Steiner says she is convinced that the problem is getting worse.</p>
        <p>Sellers, Ms. Steiner said, ''feel there are so many problems, including fraud, including technical issues, including frustration that eBay is great at bringing on more sellers but not as good at bringing more buyers. I don't think people would seriously consider leaving eBay, or at least expanding beyond eBay, if they felt eBay was improving in the areas they care about.''</p>
        <p>In other words, the short-lived repercussions from the unpopular fee increases may be the least of eBay's problems. For months, sellers have been fulminating over a long list of complaints, from fraud to fewer bidders per auction and lower selling prices to poor service from eBay.</p>
        <p>''My complaint with eBay isn't that I'm paying more,'' said Candice Darr, who since 2000 has made her living on eBay selling software at a store she named Darrsoft. ''The way I look at it, rent goes up. That's just reality. My complaint is that my rent is going up but I'm getting less for my money.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Whitman likes to reminisce about the early days of eBay, when skeptics dismissed the company as a niche player that would have roughly the same impact on Internet commerce as a flea market on a town's economy. EBay went public in September 1998, during the madness of the dot-com bubble, but as Ms. Whitman recalls it, as many as half the prospective investors who attended the road show preceding its stock offering declined to buy shares. Back then, Amazon.com and Yahoo, not eBay, were the darlings of those interested in becoming rich from the consumer Internet.</p>
        <p>Now eBay reigns as one of the kings of Internet commerce. Amazon.com has twice eBay's revenue, but it operates warehouses around the world and carries inventory, while eBay basically sells nothing other than a spot in its worldwide bazaar. As a result, eBay is nearly three times more profitable than Amazon, and its market capitalization, at $56 billion, is nearly four times as great. And though Google's market cap is almost as large, eBay posted twice the profits last year.</p>
        <p>Yahoo is eBay's competitor for the crown. Yahoo booked slightly more revenue and profit than eBay did in 2004, but eBay's market cap is 25 percent larger than Yahoo's. EBay boasts that it is ''the most valuable e-commerce franchise in the world,'' and it may be just that.</p>
        <p>EBay has 66 million registered users in the United States and 135 million worldwide, and its revenue has grown 70 percent a year, annualized, since going public in 1998. And the company's share price has moved accordingly, increasing 21-fold since the initial public offering. The company went public at a split-adjusted $1.97 a share and now trades at $41.75.</p>
        <p>Yet eBay is again facing skeptics. Among the analysts who wonder aloud if its stock market ride has come to an end, at least temporarily, are Derek Brown at Pacific Growth Equities and Safa Rashtchy at Piper Jaffray, both based in San Francisco. Mr. Brown described eBay as ''one of the most extraordinary engines to emerge on the Internet,'' but since the fall of 2003 he has had an underweight recommendation on the company. And Mr. Rashtchy, though he used the word ''phenomenal'' to sum up eBay's business, recently downgraded eBay to market perform from buy.</p>
        <p>Both check in periodically with those who make their living through eBay, like sellers or those in the business of providing technical help and other support services for sellers. Mr. Rashtchy, for instance, had dinner last month with a group of top eBay sellers, and Mr. Brown speaks regularly with a group of 10, including several ''seller-service providers who in turn are in touch with hundreds, if not thousands, of sellers.''</p>
        <p>''They've taken on a much more negative tone in the last 12 to 18 months,'' Mr. Brown said of sellers. ''They have a variety of different complaints, but the bottom line is that our research indicates customers have grown increasingly frustrated and disenchanted with the platform. Many of them have indicated to us that they're running twice as hard to stand in place.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown also began seeing signs that people were not just complaining; they were acting on their disenchantment. He noticed that the average number of items per seller was decreasing, as was the growth rate in another important statistic: the revenue that eBay generates on everything but the commission on a sale, from the basic cost of listing an item to a long list of optional features like a ''buy it now'' button.</p>
        <p>AT the same time, he and others spotted data that suggested an abrupt slowdown in the growth of the company's North American site, such as a sharp decline in the number of new sellers joining the site.</p>
        <p>Yet in 2004, eBay's stock climbed by an extraordinary 80 percent. ''I'm watching the degradation of the metrics, and I'm hearing the grumblings by sellers get louder and louder and louder, and the stock was hitting 52-week highs,'' Mr. Brown said. ''There was a disconnect between perception and reality.''</p>
        <p>Then, on Jan. 19, eBay announced its results for the fourth quarter of 2004. Its earnings per share fell a penny short of analyst expectations, largely because of a sluggish start to the holiday buying season. The company's stock fell 19 percent the next day as a half-dozen investment banks cut their ratings. The shares are down 28 percent so far this year -- and Mr. Rashtchy is among those who doubt that eBay can continue to grow at anywhere near the pace it set in its first six years as a publicly traded company.</p>
        <p>''The market kept the valuation of eBay very high because people could be confident that the company could grow into the numbers,'' Mr. Rashtchy said. ''But with a stock like eBay, when it keeps going up and up, investors are always nervous. They always have in the back of their minds that the company will eventually hit a wall.'' When it misses the numbers, he said, it is hit hard.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Garriss is the co-founder of Gotham City Online, an online shoe store that does so robust a business on eBay that he paid the company nearly $500,000 in fees last year. Given the fee increases, he figures, he will pay an additional $75,000 in 2005, assuming the same volume in sales. By contrast, Chel Ramsey is a mother of three who until recently was paying only a few hundred dollars in fees each month to operate a children's clothing store called ScuttleBugs on eBay.</p>
        <p>Both discovered their inner retailer courtesy of eBay -- and yet both are now keenly frustrated with a service that has meant so much to their lives.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ramsey, who recently decided to move her store to its own site off of eBay, lamented that her eBay business was suffering a slow death from a thousand nicks. Eighteen months ago, she figured that she earned $800 to $1,200 a month selling children's clothes through eBay. Her profit, she said, dropped to $400 to $500 in recent months.</p>
        <p>''They get you when you list, they get you when you sell, they get you when somebody pays,'' Ms. Ramsey said. ''They even take a bite out of shipping.''</p>
        <p>First there is the monthly $15.95 that eBay charges to be a host of a store on its site -- compared with $9.95 a month until the most recent fee increase. Ms. Ramsey paid an additional $10 a month to show pictures of her inventory, largely children's clothes costing 99 cents to $3.99 an item.</p>
        <p>Listing each item for sale costs only 2 cents but that's only the start, she said. The eBay search engine typically points shoppers only to auction items, not to fixed-price items sold in its stores. So Ms. Ramsey put a dozen or more items on auction each month to drive traffic to her site, and the listing fees on those, she said, ranged from 55 cents to $1.25 an item. Often, she ended up selling those items for less than cost -- an advertising expense, as she saw it.</p>
        <p>She typically racked up several more charges on a sale, beyond the commission. Virtually all her customers used an eBay payment service called PayPal that serves as a middleman between seller and shopper and charges the seller a fee, as a credit card company would. For the typical seller, that runs 2.9 percent of the total charged, including shipping and handling. Ms. Ramsey also used eBay's shipping features, which meant paying an additional 20 cents for every label printed.</p>
        <p>The e-mail that satisfied customers sometimes sent to her was free, but she worried that the message they often conveyed might have a price. She said, ''They'll say: 'I'm so happy to have found an honest seller. I was ready to give up on eBay.'''</p>
        <p>Where Ms. Ramsey said she felt ''nickeled and dimed,'' Mr. Garriss, of Gotham City Online, who has been selling shoes on eBay since 1999, described deterioration of another important measurement inside the world of eBay: the average selling price of an item. Mr. Garriss is also the executive director of the Professional eBay Sellers Alliance, a trade group started in 2003 for eBay sellers who do at least $25,000 in business each month.</p>
        <p>EBay executives contend that the average selling price has gone up in some categories. But that does not seem to be the experience of most of the 600 or so sellers who belong to Mr. Garriss's trade organization.</p>
        <p>''For a lot of our sellers, the average selling price is getting less and less and their eBay fees continue to go up,'' he said. ''So their profitability is declining.'' As a result, he said, ''a lot of sellers have disappeared off eBay'' -- a trend that eBay's ''aggressive'' fee increases, he said, are likely to accelerate.</p>
        <p>Where will they go? Some sellers will do what he did, Mr. Garriss said: realize that it is much more economical to operate your own online store and to buy keywords from search companies like Google and Yahoo to point potential buyers to your site. He maintains a presence on eBay, he said, but outside the confines of eBay, where hard-to-believe deals are the coin of the realm, he can charge more for the same shoes.</p>
        <p>Others will do as R.J. Moore did. Mr. Moore, who started doing business on eBay in 1999, was selling $2 million to $3 million in jewelry a year. But increased competition, he said, cut into profits, and last June he left eBay altogether. He now sells his jewelry at a smaller eBay rival, Bid4Assets.</p>
        <p>''There's far less action there,'' Mr. Moore said, ''but they offer a much better deal.''</p>
        <p>More recently, Bob Lee decided to do the same. Mr. Lee had sold video games via eBay but decided to shut down his eBay store after calculating that his fees would be rising by hundreds of dollars each month. He knew that it was time to leave, he said, ''when I figured out that eBay would be making more money on each video game we sold than we were.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Whitman, eBay's chief executive, said she felt the pain of sellers who believe that eBay no longer offers the same money-making opportunities as it did in the past. When told about the plight of people working so much harder to remain in place, she nodded her head, a slightly pained expression on her face. She spends part of each day, she said, reading the company's message boards. She appreciates, she said, that a lot of people are disappointed that once-thriving eBay businesses have fallen on hard times.</p>
        <p>But her job, Ms. Whitman said, is to maintain the overall health of the wider eBay ecosystem, not to worry about individuals. To make her point, she recalled the dust storm that sellers kicked up a few years earlier, when the selling price of collectibles fell.</p>
        <p>''People asked us what we were going to do about that,'' she said. ''The answer was, we're not going to do anything.'' Since then, of course, eBay has continued to thrive and grow, and plenty of people are now making a good living in the collectibles category.</p>
        <p>That is the laissez-faire nature of life on eBay, as Ms. Whitman and others explain it. A few homesteaders staking out a new category may feel as if they have struck gold in their first months, but their good fortune is guaranteed to pique the interest of other entrepreneurs. The entry of others causes prices to fall -- but if they fall too steeply, sellers stop selling, thereby driving prices back up. In this view, eBay is a perfect manifestation of capitalism as perceived by Adam Smith, efficient and self-correcting. Ms. Whitman's job -- and the job of those who work for her -- is to help people buy and sell but otherwise to stay out of the way.</p>
        <p>Some sellers contend that there has been a decline in the percentage of auctions that end in a sale. If that were true, Ms. Whitman said, she would be worried. But she maintains that the percentage of auctions that end successfully has remained fairly constant. ''That has not swung very much since the day I walked in the door in 1998,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it was a concern for the ''balance of the marketplace,'' not a desire to bump up eBay's bottom line, that explains the most recent set of fee increases, said Mr. Cobb, who runs eBay's North American operations. The feeling inside eBay, he said, was that a kind of equilibrium needed to be restored between those using auctions and those selling items for a flat price in an eBay store. A sharp increase in the commission charged on all store sales, this reasoning went, would lead more sellers to embrace the auction model.</p>
        <p>The company also said it believed that too large a proportion of sellers were using the ''gallery'' feature -- choosing to have a picture accompany a listing -- so the company raised its fee for the feature by 40 percent to restore its premium status.</p>
        <p>DESPITE the hailstorm of criticism, Mr. Cobb sticks by the fee increases, saying only that he could have done a better job in explaining all this to what everyone inside eBay calls simply ''the community.'' As a kind of penance, the company announced last month that it would provide telephone customer service to every shop owner -- a service previously reserved for high-volume eBay vendors known as power sellers -- defined as the top 2 percent in sales -- and would not charge the $15.95 monthly rent for April. Mr. Cobb also promised to slow down the rate at which the company introduces new features on the site. The frequent addition of new bells and whistles has been blamed for the broken links and other technical difficulties that eBay sellers have been complaining about.</p>
        <p>If nothing else, the fee increase has demonstrated to eBay executives that they do not have quite the pricing power that they thought. Ultimately, however, the company's fortunes hinge less on the growth rate of the company's American site than on its foreign operations and the use of PayPal beyond the eBay site.</p>
        <p>PayPal is the default method of payment on the American site, and it is slowly gaining momentum as eBay struggles, country by country, to translate the service into a foreign language while seeking approval from local regulators to operate within their borders. Already, it accounts for one-quarter of eBay's revenue, which the company expects to reach roughly $4.3 billion this year.</p>
        <p>But the company's deepest hope for PayPal, which eBay bought for $1.5 billion in 2002, is that more and more Web sites not related to eBay will adopt it as a preferred payment method. According to data provided by eBay, only about 2 percent of the Web's small- and medium-size outposts -- which the company defines as sites doing less than $5 million in e-commerce a year -- offer buyers the PayPal option.</p>
        <p>EBay now operates independent auction sites in 32 countries. The company's footprint is especially wide in Europe, where it has had phenomenal annual growth rates, reaching triple digits in some countries.</p>
        <p>That overseas success has been largely factored into the company's stock price. The battle now is over Asia. On the upside, eBay is strong in South Korea and has first-mover advantage in China. On the downside, it has conceded e-commerce in Japan to Yahoo, which is trying to parlay its strength in Hong Kong and Taiwan to pursue the nascent Chinese e-commerce market.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, eBay announced that its international arm would spend an additional $100 million on the Chinese market, which Ms. Whitman has declared ''critical'' to eBay's continued success.</p>
        <p>For the moment, though, the company can at least take solace that people care so much about eBay that they are bothering to rant at all about the North America site. ''What we've found over time is this is like when fans of a team call in to a talk radio station,'' Mr. Cobb said. ''For the most part, while they're screaming at us they're also wearing that jersey for us on Sunday and rooting for us, with paint on their face.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 13, 2005, Sunday  An article last Sunday about business challenges facing eBay, the online auctioneer, referred incompletely to the situation of a jewelry seller, R.J. Moore, who said he left eBay last June and moved his online store to a smaller rival because it offered a better deal. EBay says it earlier suspended Mr. Moore from selling on its site. He was suspended after rival sellers accused him of bidding on their products to drive up prices and of failing to pay in auctions he won -- accusations that he denies. He says he was already intending to switch sites.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 13, 2005, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about business challenges facing eBay, the online auctioneer, referred incompletely to the situation of a jewelry seller, R.J. Moore, who said he left eBay last June and moved his online store to a smaller rival because it offered a better deal. EBay says it earlier suspended Mr. Moore from selling on its site. He was suspended after rival sellers accused him of bidding on their products to drive up prices and of failing to pay in auctions he won -- accusations that he denies. He says he was already intending to switch sites.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
