<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Israel's Bitter Culture War, Civility Is a Casualty</title>
    <meta content="21ISRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1033386"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmemann, Serge</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DE1E30F932A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="1852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Israel's Bitter Culture War, Civility Is a Casualty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmemann, Serge</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, July 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dispute between religious and secular Jews in Israel has steadily intensified in fury and emotion; passions that have simmered for decades seem hardly proportionate to realities, with every skirmish turning into angry confrontation; sides are vaguely defined--religious Jews in Israel range from fundamentalist 'haredim' to thoroughly liberal Orthodox, while 'secular' Israel runs gamut from far-right to far-left; some current conflicts between various factions discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Receiving a lifetime-achievement award at the Jerusalem Film Festival this spring, the Israeli filmmaker Assi Dayan congratulated organizers for putting on so fine a festival ''in this damned city.'' Then, turning to Mayor Ehud Olmert, he loosed another curse: Please tell your friend, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, ''that he should go to hell.''</p>
        <p>The incident was not big news. Mr. Dayan, son of the late Israeli military hero Moshe Dayan, is known for his sharp tongue and his harsh views about religious Jews and the right-wing Government.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Receiving a lifetime-achievement award at the Jerusalem Film Festival this spring, the Israeli filmmaker Assi Dayan congratulated organizers for putting on so fine a festival ''in this damned city.'' Then, turning to Mayor Ehud Olmert, he loosed another curse: Please tell your friend, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, ''that he should go to hell.''</p>
        <p>The incident was not big news. Mr. Dayan, son of the late Israeli military hero Moshe Dayan, is known for his sharp tongue and his harsh views about religious Jews and the right-wing Government.</p>
        <p>But even more than that, such language has ceased to shock as the dispute between religious and secular Jews has steadily intensified in fury and emotion. It is common now to hear references to Kulturkampf, a culture war in which the secular ''Tel Aviv'' and the religious ''Jerusalem'' are battling for the very soul of Israel. Hence Mr. Dayan's curse.</p>
        <p>The passions, which have simmered for decades, seem hardly proportionate to the realities. The sides are vaguely defined -- religious Jews in Israel range from the fundamentalist ''haredim'' to thoroughly liberal Orthodox, while ''secular'' Israelis run the political gamut from far-right to far-left.</p>
        <p>Yet every skirmish rapidly turns into angry confrontation. The most celebrated in recent months was the decision of the renowned Batsheva Dance Company to withdraw from a gala in Jerusalem in April celebrating Israel's 50th anniversary after ultra-Orthodox politicians objected to a number in which scantily dressed performers danced to a Hebrew prayer.</p>
        <p>That incident unleashed a torrent of fury among secular Israelis. Several days later, at a packed outdoor arena in Tel Aviv, the company staged a retaliatory performance in which a dancer dressed as an ultra-Orthodox Jew stripped to her underwear. The Tel Aviv audience cheered as if their team had scored a touchdown and had retaken the lead.</p>
        <p>At a tempestuous parliamentary hearing that followed, the chairman of the Israeli Artists Union, Shaikeh Levy, declared: ''There will be creative freedom. The more important question is whether there will be a country.''</p>
        <p>An enraged legislator, David Azulai, from the religious Shas party, retorted, ''The country will continue to exist, with you or without you.''</p>
        <p>Other clashes have occurred on streets the haredim want closed on the Sabbath, or in towns where the religious have tried to establish a presence. In Pardes Hanna, an old town in central Israel, arsonists set fire to a haredi trailer, and hundreds of secular Israelis have gathered for regular protests against what they see as religious encroachment.</p>
        <p>A recent announcement that Jerusalem's boundaries would be expanded drew violent protests from affluent suburbanites, many of whom had fled before the swelling religious population of the city and saw the expansion as an attempt to tap their taxes to compensate for the large and poor haredi families.</p>
        <p>Draft Exemptions And State Subsidies</p>
        <p>Politicians have been quick to seize on the battle. Mayor Roni Milo of Tel Aviv recently declared himself a candidate for Prime Minister as champion of those opposed to ''religious coercion.''</p>
        <p>''The war is not over the Batsheva dancers' clothing,'' wrote the columnist Nahum Barnea in Yediot Ahronot. ''The war is about power, about territories of control. The haredim, a rising power in Israeli politics, are testing the boundaries.''</p>
        <p>Ehud Barak, the chairman of the Labor Party, introduced a bill to draft haredi youths, seeking to cash in on what is probably the greatest source of resentment among secular Jews. Most ultra-Orthodox Jews are exempted from mandatory military service on the premise that they study the Torah at their yeshivas. What enrages other Israelis is not only that a rapidly swelling portion of the population does not take part in the defense of the Jewish state, but that this group receives state subsidies as well. About 200,000 yeshiva students currently receive a total of about $275 million -- and recently demanded a 33 percent raise.</p>
        <p>These resentments have been fanned by the fact that the haredim, because of their huge families and relative poverty, pay few taxes. And their unwillingness to take part in secular patriotic ceremonies, like the annual minute of silence for those who fell in wars, is seen as disrespectful to the nation.</p>
        <p>From the haredi side, two rabbis, Yosef Shalom Elyashiv and Aharon Leib Shteinman, published a declaration that the proposal to draft the ultra-Orthodox was a ''plot to uproot Torah from Israel.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barak's bill was defeated. But signs appeared on buses reading ''One Nation, One Draft,'' and ultra-Orthodox leaders promptly threatened to boycott buses unless they were taken down.</p>
        <p>And the haredim have other  sources of resentment. One is the Israeli Supreme Court, which they see as a threat to religious law; another is archeology, which they perceive as a threat to the sanctity of the Jewish dead.</p>
        <p>Archeology Rankles Orthodox Sensibilities</p>
        <p>The haredim have systematically tried to block archeological digs where there is any chance of coming on Jewish tombs -- which is most anywhere in Israel. In May, offices of the Antiquities Authority in Hahalal were set on fire, with the loss of extensive archeological documentation; the police said they were searching for two haredi youths.</p>
        <p>Yet when all such passions are pushed aside, it is difficult to see what the problem is. Although religious parties control the Culture Ministry, state subsidies remain intact even for art the religious would refuse to see.</p>
        <p>No program on television, stage or radio has been banned or withdrawn because of religious pressure.</p>
        <p>After months of fierce fighting along Bar-Ilan Street in Jerusalem, a quiet compromise was reached to close the street during prayer times on the Sabbath.</p>
        <p>For all the demands to draft the haredim, Army leaders admit this would create big problems because the ultra-Orthodox could not serve with women and would demand far stricter dietary controls. And the Supreme Court has usually managed to accommodate religious courts.</p>
        <p>Finally, for all their threats, neither side has succeeded in passing a law the other opposes. The attempt by the religious parties to pass a bill institutionalizing their monopoly over religious conversions was blocked, as was Mr. Barak's attempt to draft haredim.</p>
        <p>And the country is not as polarized as the language would suggest. Studies have shown that only about 14 percent of Jews in Israel define themselves as ''strictly observant'' and 20 percent as nonobservant. The rest are somewhere in between.</p>
        <p>But another survey, this one by Tel Aviv University, found that 80 percent of Israelis expect an outbreak of violence between the religious and the secular.</p>
        <p>The real reason behind the anxiety is a sense that Israeli society is undergoing profound change in which every minor conflict is a battle over the future.</p>
        <p>The journalist Yossi Klein Halevi wrote: ''What we're seeing is really an apocalyptic debate, for the religious and secular are both convinced that if the other side wins, the country will be destroyed. The secular scenario is simple: If the country becomes a theocracy, the secular middle class, which keeps Israel productive and gives it an edge in the Middle East, will leave, and this country will become a real ghetto, and Israel, as a theocracy, will be destroyed.</p>
        <p>''On the other side, which is not well understood because the religious don't make themselves understood in the media, there is the idea that we were in this land twice before, and both times we lost because we didn't follow God's law. When the religious looks at Tel Aviv culture, at Batsheva, he sees the beginning of the end of the Third Commonwealth. That's the tragedy here: the protagonists aren't always aware why they feel so passionate.''</p>
        <p>Killing of Rabin Was a Watershed</p>
        <p>Though such debates have always existed in a people defined both by blood and religion, Israel was shaped and controlled in its formative years by secular, liberal Zionists who perceived the rigorously Orthodox as a vestige of Europe's ghettoes.</p>
        <p>The assassination of Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin in 1995 by a religious nationalist stunned the left by revealing the depth of radicalization in the religious right. Then the election of Mr. Netanyahu in 1996 revealed a convergence of interests among traditional ultra-Orthodox, religious Jews from Arab countries and religious nationalists, who together gained enough muscle to make or break the coalition.</p>
        <p>''There was a debate, and suddenly the religious people brought in a gun,'' said the writer David Grossman. ''They showed that even though we had a state, they were more committed to God's laws. We're fighting now for our future.</p>
        <p>''Why now? Because everything is sharper now, because we're facing the crucial point of deciding how to live the next 50 years. Will we have peace? Will we internalize the idea of concession to neighbors? Will we create borders only or create a quality of life in those borders? Are we going to survive only, or will we seek something more than surviving from one catastrophe to another? All the crucial questions of our identity rise again. They dictate our political behavior, the way we treat each other.''</p>
        <p>Leftist Cynicism? Or Deep Anxieties?</p>
        <p>Religious politicians dismiss such talk as hyperbole and politics, arguing that the religious are not seeking or achieving anything new.</p>
        <p>''I'll tell you why I don't take this very seriously,'' said Rabbi Avraham Ravitz, of the United Torah Judaism faction in the Parliament. ''Nothing special happened in recent times in order this should cause such a tension by secular against religious. There were no religious laws passed. It was the other way around: we're lately losing a few issues that we were sure would pass through, like the Law of Conversion. So the religious parties are not in a situation of threatening the secular, in a way that we're forcing the secular to accept religious laws or religious behavior.</p>
        <p>''In a very cynical way, this is being used for the political interests of the lefties, the Labor Party, who are pushing Israeli society and making this so-called culture war.''</p>
        <p>But Moshe Halbertal, an Orthodox rabbi who is professor of Jewish thought at Hebrew University and of Talmud at the Hartman Institute in Jerusalem, insists that the struggle is symptomatic of deeper anxieties.</p>
        <p>''There is a great sense of fear because society has been transformed, and nobody knows where it's going to go,'' he said. ''What we're seeking basically is a new social contract here, a social contract that we're taking the state out of this culture war, that we're not willing to use the mechanisms of the state to decide it.</p>
        <p>''There has to be an understanding that religious legislation has caused tremendous alienation of a whole generation, besides harming the whole fabric of society. On the other hand we must respect the cultural autonomy of the hardim, in ways the state didn't respect it in the past.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
