<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.N. Rights Official, Back From China, Sees Better Attitude</title>
    <meta content="Y16CHI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980917T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1046895"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beijing (China)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robinson, Mary (Comr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE5DC1131F935A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="995" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.N. Rights Official, Back From China, Sees Better Attitude</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELISABETH ROSENTHAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rosenthal, Elisabeth</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, Sept. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations Human Rights Comr Mary Robinson, completing first visit to China, says that despite continuing abuses, Chinese leaders show new willingess to discuss nation's rights record, news conference, Beijing; lauds China's willingness to let commission work in nation; rights groups react with cautious optimism (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the end of what she called ''a successful but not always easy first visit to China,'' the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights, Mary Robinson,  said today that despite continuing human rights abuses, she had sensed among Chinese leaders a new willingness to discuss the country's  rights record.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Robinson said she had been told by Chinese officials that they were prepared to sign the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights next month. She said the Chinese Government had also signed a letter of understanding with the Human Rights Commission requesting technical assistance in resolving human rights issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the end of what she called ''a successful but not always easy first visit to China,'' the United Nations High Commissioner for Human Rights, Mary Robinson,  said today that despite continuing human rights abuses, she had sensed among Chinese leaders a new willingness to discuss the country's  rights record.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Robinson said she had been told by Chinese officials that they were prepared to sign the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights next month. She said the Chinese Government had also signed a letter of understanding with the Human Rights Commission requesting technical assistance in resolving human rights issues.</p>
        <p>''China has human rights problems, major problems,'' Mrs. Robinson said at a news conference today in Beijing. But she added, ''I was interested in the awareness of and willingness to admit human rights problems among China's leaders.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Robinson praised China's willingness to allow the United Nations Human Rights Commission to work in the country, since China has previously rejected what it regarded as outside interference in its internal affairs. ''It has to be apparent what a ground-breaking visit this is,'' she said. ''Human rights is not talked about here.''</p>
        <p>But human rights groups reacted with only cautious optimism, noting that the ultimate success of the Commissioner's visit hinges on whether China's avowed commitment to human rights leads to concrete changes in a country where people are imprisoned without trial and cannot speak out against the Government.</p>
        <p>Mike Jendrzeczyk, Washington Director of Human Rights Watch Asia, said the commitments are ''a step forward, but what remains to be seen is whether China takes specific actions as a result of the trip.'' He and others expressed disappointment that Mrs. Robinson had not met with dissidents or their relatives.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mrs. Robinson's 10-day trip was punctuated by poignant reminders of the contradictions in China's human rights policies, where scattered signs of liberalization are often offset by harsh repression.</p>
        <p>During the visit, dissidents from two provinces said they had gotten somewhat encouraging signals when they applied for permission to organize an opposition party, an act that had landed dissidents in jail just three month ago. And, at a seminar, Mrs. Robinson heard Chinese lawyers criticize the lack of protection defendants have under Chinese law.</p>
        <p>But that same week, officers of Beijing's Public Security Bureau arrested and allegedly beat an imprisoned dissident's wife, Chu Hailan, as she tried to deliver a letter to Mrs. Robinson in her hotel lobby. And a liberal journalist and editor, Shi Binhai, was taken from his home and 10 days later was still being held without explanation or charges.</p>
        <p>Such contradiction were not lost on Mrs. Robinson, who said that she had called the Foreign Ministry to demand Ms. Chu's release after she heard about the arrest. Ms. Chu was released that same evening. Mr. Shi's status is still unclear.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Robinson said that during her visit she had received a number of faxes, letters and oral messages regarding individual cases. ''I have become aware of a number of cases that I will bring up with authorities back in Geneva,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Robinson said that in meetings yesterday with President Jiang Zemin and Deputy Prime Minister  Qian Qichen she had inquired about the whereabouts of the 9-year-old boy decreed by the Dalai Lama to be the reincarnation of the Panchen Lama, the second-ranking spiritual leader of Tibetan Buddhists. China has said the boy and his parents are under its protection at an undisclosed location, and has selected its own youth as the Panchen Lama.</p>
        <p>The Commissioner also urged President Jiang to meet with the Dalai Lama and asked for a review of the sentences of those arrested in connection with the 1989 pro-democracy protests in Tiananmen Square.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Robinson traveled to Beijing and Shanghai, discussing a broad range rights issues, from dissidents to China's justice system to discrimination against women. She also made a brief visit to Tibet, which she characterized as ''very restrictive and very difficult, as many opportunities in the country are.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, she defended her work there -- which included passing out copies of the United Nations Universal Declaration on Human Rights in Tibetan at a local school -- as a step in the right direction.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Robinson repeatedly said that the main goal of her trip was merely to ''start a process of cooperation'' and did not say if she had gotten any concrete commitments for change during her lengthy meetings with Chinese leaders.</p>
        <p>Many human rights experts say they are anxious for details. While they say they are happy that China has now given a timetable for signing the covenents and has committed to further cooperation with the United Nations, they note that Beijing has not always lived up to such promises.</p>
        <p>The International Covenant on Political and Civil Rights, which China plans to sign next month, along with the International Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights, which China signed last year, are comprehensive documents protecting rights from freedom of speech to freedom to form trade unions. But China's governing bodies still have to ratify both documents and might try to attach caveats that would blunt their impact, Mr. Jendrzeczyk said.</p>
        <p>Some dissidents said that Mrs. Robinson's visit as well as a slight loosening of official policy had already helped their cause.</p>
        <p>''China is beginning to acknowledge the existence of human rights through this visit and through these covenants,'' said Wang Youcai, a dissident from Hangzhou who was arrested in July for trying to form a political party. ''I think the likelihood I'll be re-arrested now is small.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 17, 1998, Thursday  A headline yesterday about a United Nations official's comments about human rights in China misstated her whereabouts at the time. She was in Beijing, not ''back from China.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 17, 1998, Thursday</p>
        <p>A headline yesterday about a United Nations official's comments about human rights in China misstated her whereabouts at the time. She was in Beijing, not ''back from China.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
