<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Forgiving George Wallace</title>
    <meta content="16LEWI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1046867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Alabama</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, John (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallace, George C Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E6DF1131F935A2575AC0A96E958260" item-length="736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Forgiving George Wallace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, John (Repr)</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by US Repr John Lewis, leader of civil rights movement in Alabama in 1950's and 1960's, says despite his failings, former Alabama Gov George George Wallace who died recently at age 79 deserves recognition for seeking redemption for his mistakes and for his willingness to change and to set things right with those he had harmed; says rarely has country witnessed such conversion by elected official--conversion of principle that can be shaped only by courage and conviction (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Growing up in rural Alabama during the 1950's, it was hard not to know who George Wallace was. Mr. Wallace, first as a circuit judge and then as Governor, fought the civil rights movement with every fiber of his being. He was a demagogue whose words and actions created a climate that allowed for violent reprisals against those seeking to end racial discrimination.</p>
        <p>As one of the leaders of the civil rights movement, I remember that  George Wallace well. But the George Wallace who sent troops to intimidate peaceful, orderly marchers in Selma in 1965 was not the same man who died this week. With all his failings, Mr. Wallace deserves recognition for seeking redemption for his mistakes, for his willingness to change and to set things right with those he harmed and with his God.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Growing up in rural Alabama during the 1950's, it was hard not to know who George Wallace was. Mr. Wallace, first as a circuit judge and then as Governor, fought the civil rights movement with every fiber of his being. He was a demagogue whose words and actions created a climate that allowed for violent reprisals against those seeking to end racial discrimination.</p>
        <p>As one of the leaders of the civil rights movement, I remember that  George Wallace well. But the George Wallace who sent troops to intimidate peaceful, orderly marchers in Selma in 1965 was not the same man who died this week. With all his failings, Mr. Wallace deserves recognition for seeking redemption for his mistakes, for his willingness to change and to set things right with those he harmed and with his God.</p>
        <p>Rarely does our country witness such a conversion by an elected official. Such a conversion of principle can be shaped only by courage and conviction.</p>
        <p>I will never forget Mr. Wallace's inaugural address as Governor in 1963. Looking defiant, he declared, ''Segregation now, segregation tomorrow, segregation forever.'' That day, my heart sank. I knew his defense of ''states' rights'' was really a defense of the status quo in Alabama.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wallace used the language of rage and hate to rise to power and to become a force in national politics. Staring down Federal officials, he told every black American that he or she was not welcome at the University of Alabama.</p>
        <p>The Alabama of the 1950's and 1960's was a turbulent place. African-Americans were seeking to desegregate restaurants, bathrooms and buses and to secure the right to vote. Governor Wallace and his allies drew in every available resource to stem the tide of progress.</p>
        <p>A showdown was inevitable. Much of the bloodshed in Alabama occurred on Governor Wallace's watch. Although he never pulled a trigger or threw a bomb, he created the climate of fear and intimidation in which those acts were deemed acceptable.</p>
        <p>Although we had long been adversaries, I did not meet Governor Wallace until 1979. During that meeting, I could tell that he was a changed man; he was engaged in a campaign to seek forgiveness from the same African-Americans he had oppressed. He acknowledged his bigotry and assumed responsibility for the harm he had caused. He wanted to be forgiven.</p>
        <p>The very essence of the civil rights movement was its appeal to the conscience of those who beat us with batons, attacked us with dogs and stood defiantly at the schoolhouse door. We wanted our enemies to know that every blow they struck was a blow against another human being. The bloodshed that resulted was the blood of all humanity.</p>
        <p>When I met George Wallace, I had to forgive him, because to do otherwise -- to hate him -- would only perpetuate the evil system we sought to destroy.</p>
        <p>George Wallace should be remembered for his capacity to change. And we are better as a nation because of our capacity to forgive and to acknowledge that our political leaders are human and largely a reflection of the social currents in the river of history.</p>
        <p>Whether at the bridge in Selma, at a bombed church in Birmingham or on the schoolhouse steps, George Wallace and I were thrust together by fate, by our personal conviction and principle and by what I like to call the spirit of history. The civil rights movement achieved its goals in the person of Mr. Wallace, because he grew to see that we as human beings are joined by a common bond.</p>
        <p>I can never forget what George Wallace said and did as Governor, as a national leader and as a political opportunist. But our ability to forgive serves a higher moral purpose in our society. Through genuine repentance and forgiveness, the soul of our nation is redeemed. George Wallace deserves to be remembered for his effort to redeem his soul and in so doing to mend the fabric of American society.</p>
        <p>John Lewis, a Democratic member of the House of Representatives from Georgia, is the author of ''Walking With the Wind: A Memoir of the Movement.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">John Lewis, a Democratic member of the House of Representatives from Georgia, is the author of ''Walking With the Wind: A Memoir of the Movement.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
