<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Votes in Congress</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="838957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDA1439F937A15750C0A960958260" item-length="2132" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Votes in Congress</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tally Last Week in Connecticut, New Jersey and New York</p>
        <p>House</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tally Last Week in Connecticut, New Jersey and New York</p>
        <p>House</p>
        <p>1. Immigration: Vote on an amendment to an immigration bill that would allow states to deny public education to illegal immigrant children. Approved 257 to 163, March 20.</p>
        <p>2. Immigration: Vote on an amendment to an immigration bill that would delete provisions for a voluntary pilot program for employers to call a toll-free telephone line to determine the legal status of job applicants. Rejected 260 to  159, March 20.</p>
        <p>3. Immigration: Vote on an amendment to an immigration bill that deletes provisions to cut legal immigration by more than 30 percent after five years. Approved 238 to 183, March 21.</p>
        <p>4. Immigration: Vote on an amendment to an immigration bill that would have granted temporary work visas to as many as 250,000 foreign farm workers. Rejected 242 to 180, March 21.</p>
        <p>5. Immigration: Vote on passage of an immigration bill toughening enforcement provisions against illegal aliens and restricting access to federal benefits to  illegal aliens and some legal aliens. Approved 333 to 87, March 21.</p>
        <p>6. Assault Weapons: Vote to repeal the 1994 ban on manufacture and sale of many  semi-automatic weapons. Approved 239 to 173, March 22.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>6 Connecticut 1. Kennelly (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 2. Gejdenson (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 3. DeLauro (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 4. Shays (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay 5. Franks (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay  Yea  Yea 6. Johnson (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Yea  Yea  Yea  Nay</p>
        <p>New Jersey  1. Andrews (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 2. LoBiondo (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea 3. Saxton (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay 4. Smith (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Yea  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 5. Roukema (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay 6. Pallone (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 7. Franks (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 8. Martini (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay 9. Torricelli (D)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 10. Payne (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 11. Frelinghuysen (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay 12. Zimmer (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 13. Menendez (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay</p>
        <p>New York  1. Forbes (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea 2. Lazio (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Yea  Yea  Yea  Nay 3. King (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Yea  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 4. Frisa (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Yea 5. Ackerman (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 6. Flake (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 7. Manton (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 8. Nadler (D)</p>
        <p>A</p>
        <p>A  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 9. Schumer (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 10. Towns (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 11. Owens (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 12. Velazquez (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 13. Molinari (R)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay 14. Maloney (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 15. Rangel (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 16. Serrano (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 17. Engel (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 18. Lowey (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 19. Kelly (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea 20. Gilman (R)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea 21. McNulty (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 22. Solomon (R)</p>
        <p>Yea</p>
        <p>A  Nay  Yea  Yea  Yea 23. Boehlert (R)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 24. McHugh (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea 25. Walsh (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea 26. Hinchey (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay  Yea 27. Paxon (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea  Yea 28. Slaughter (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Yea  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 29. LaFalce (D)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Nay  Nay 30. Quinn (R)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Nay  Yea  Nay 31. Houghton (R)</p>
        <p>Nay  Nay  Yea  Yea  Yea  Nay</p>
        <p>Senate</p>
        <p>1. Spending: Vote on passage of a spending bill that would cover the remaining six months of the fiscal year 1996 for some of the largest departments and agencies of the Federal Government. Approved 71 to 29, March 19.</p>
        <p>2. Cloture: Vote to cut off debate and proceed to vote on a bill that would limit damages available to people who are hurt by faulty products.  Approved 60  to 40, March 20.</p>
        <p>3. Liability Damages: Vote on passage of a bill limiting damages in lawsuits involving faulty products. Approved 59 to 40, March 21.</p>
        <p>4. Grazing: Vote on passage of a bill that would loosen restrictions on hundreds of millions of acres of federally owned ranch land. Approved 51 to 46, March 21.</p>
        <p>* Senator Moynihan's office says that his "Yea" vote on grazing was recorded incorrectly and will be changed.</p>
        <p>Connecticut  Dodd (D)</p>
        <p>Yea  Yea  Yea</p>
        <p>Nay Lieberman (D)</p>
        <p>Yea  Yea  Yea</p>
        <p>Nay</p>
        <p>New Jersey  Bradley (D)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay</p>
        <p>A Lautenberg (D)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay</p>
        <p>Nay</p>
        <p>New York D'Amato (R)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay</p>
        <p>Yea Moynihan (D)</p>
        <p>Yea  Nay  Nay  Yea*</p>
        <p>Key: (A) Absent or did not vote; (P) Present.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
