<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Wives' Tales</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="838702"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALLEN, BROOKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBINSON, ROXANA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ASKING FOR LOVE: AND OTHER STORIES (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E5DC1439F937A15750C0A960958260" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Wives' Tales</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Brooke Allen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALLEN, BROOKE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ASKING FOR LOVE And Other Stories. By Roxana Robinson. 275 pp. New York: Random House. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ASKING FOR LOVE And Other Stories. By Roxana Robinson. 275 pp. New York: Random House. $23.</p>
        <p>Every time a new and promising WASP writer comes along, it is his or her inevitable misfortune to be compared with John Cheever. This is not so much because there might be some genuine points in common as because there are so few other first-rate examples to use as a measuring stick, for hardly any of the really interesting writers of this century have been upper-middle-class WASP's describing their own world.</p>
        <p>Roxana Robinson is such a writer. The author of two previous works of fiction, "Summer Light" and "A Glimpse of Scarlet," she has also produced a biography of Georgia O'Keeffe. Early in her career, she was branded as "John Cheever's heir apparent" and was even likened to Louis Auchincloss, another of the rare literary blue bloods.</p>
        <p>Aside from the fact that all three writers describe roughly the same milieu,  these comparisons are meaningless. Ms. Robinson is a much better writer than Mr. Auchincloss, who may be successful not because of his skill or depth but merely  because his subjects -- all those repressed clubmen and operagoers -- have lately become so quaint and exotic. On the other hand, she is not nearly as good as Cheever; her vision is neither as dark nor as rich, and her outlook is somewhat limited in that it is an exclusively feminine one. Ms. Robinson's sole  concern is with human relations, particularly those between family members or lovers. She gives no consideration to the themes that have traditionally been considered masculine, like the bleak and solitary battles with worldly ambition  and failure, or to speculation on the presence or absence of God. Within her chosen boundaries, however, she can be an effective artist, and occasionally a powerful one.</p>
        <p>"Asking for Love" is Ms. Robinson's second volume of short stories, and it displays her particular virtues to advantage. Her heroines tend to be middle-aged women, with one or two children, who have been through a divorce. They are either remarried or involved with men whom they see as potential husbands. These women are cautious not by nature but through experience. The hard-won perspective of Nora, the protagonist of "The Nile in Flood," is characteristic: "All her life she had relied on passion, and it had always betrayed her. This time things would be different. This marriage would be based  on sympathy, loyalty, affection."</p>
        <p>It goes without saying that sympathy, loyalty and affection prove to be no less fallible than passion as keys to domestic felicity. Men, of course, are the wild cards: they are necessary but also obscurely threatening, enemies to the domestic harmony for which these women strive. Too often the men withdraw, while the women find themselves exhausted by the fruitless task of trying to reconcile permanently hostile elements within the family.</p>
        <p>Ms. Robinson's characters are well heeled but hardly superrich. The description the narrator of the title story gives of her lover sums up the breed: "John was wearing a dark green sweater, tweed jacket, khaki pants and blue boat sneakers. These are clothes worn by all the men I know, including my father, and though I haven't known John my whole life, he looks as though I have." These folks live in New York or Boston or Philadelphia and summer in Maine or the Hamptons. All of them are confident of their place in the world; none of them suffers from social insecurity or feels the slightest need to draw  attention to wealth or status.</p>
        <p>Yet what unites Ms. Robinson's cast of characters is not so much their social standing as their miserable thralldom to the Calvinist ethics of their caste. The teen-age narrator of the first story, "Leaving Home," longs to escape the atmosphere of grim and dogged virtue exuded by her parents, and especially her father, an Episcopal minister. In a moment of adolescent daring, the girl declares that she hates her cousin Gloria, an announcement that amounts to an unthinkable challenge, for "hate" is "a word that was never used in our household." She is eventually made to apologize; even then, her father continues to look "as though I were someone he had never met. It would be hours before he approached friendship, even acquaintanceship." Her mother "gave me a brave smile, but her eyes showed damage: she had been wounded."</p>
        <p>PURITANISM does not always manifest itself in such obvious and unattractive guises. In "Breaking the Rules," perhaps the most moving story in the collection, it masquerades as enlightened liberalism. Anna, the heroine, is still grieving a year after the death of her father, an intransigent pacifist and vegetarian from whom she was estranged, after a trivial quarrel, at the time of his death. During the course of the story Anna comes to realize that her own  liberal beliefs have hardened into a crust of self-righteousness as tough as her father's. In a flash of humility, she offers the love and forgiveness she feels  for him to another bigoted, frail old man.</p>
        <p>If Ms. Robinson must be judged the heir apparent of any writer, it should probably be William Maxwell. She shares his vision of the family as a fragile unit held together by infinitely precious, infinitely delicate threads of love and trust, and she stresses the necessity of constant vigilance lest any of these threads be broken. Like him, she is adept at making the reader conscious of the potential dangers that threaten even the most peaceful family. Love, as she sees it, is the holy grail, and once attained it must never be taken for granted.</p>
        <p>Brooke Allen is a writer and critic who reviewsfrequently for The New Criterion and The Wall Street Journal.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Brooke Allen is a writer and critic who reviewsfrequently for The New Criterion and The Wall Street Journal.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
