<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawmakers Promise to Push Starrett City Rent Protection</title>
    <meta content="26housing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/26/nyregion/26housing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804EFD6113EF935A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="689" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawmakers Promise to Push Starrett City Rent Protection</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lawmakers Promise to Push Starrett City Rent Protection</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SEWELL CHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chan, Sewell</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State and city lawmakers vowed yesterday to begin a new push to persuade the State Legislature to extend rent regulation protections to certain publicly subsidized housing developments built since 1974 -- a proposal that could have a major influence on the future of Starrett City, a huge residential complex in Brooklyn that a group of investors wants to buy for $1.3 billion.</p>
        <p>Starrett City is covered by Mitchell-Lama, a state program giving tax-exempt financing to builders of low- and moderate-income housing. State law mandates rent protection for former Mitchell-Lama units, but only if they were built before 1974 -- the year Starrett opened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>State and city lawmakers vowed yesterday to begin a new push to persuade the State Legislature to extend rent regulation protections to certain publicly subsidized housing developments built since 1974  a proposal that could have a major influence on the future of Starrett City, a huge residential complex in Brooklyn that a group of investors wants to buy for $1.3 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State and city lawmakers vowed yesterday to begin a new push to persuade the State Legislature to extend rent regulation protections to certain publicly subsidized housing developments built since 1974 -- a proposal that could have a major influence on the future of Starrett City, a huge residential complex in Brooklyn that a group of investors wants to buy for $1.3 billion.</p>
        <p>Starrett City is covered by Mitchell-Lama, a state program giving tax-exempt financing to builders of low- and moderate-income housing. State law mandates rent protection for former Mitchell-Lama units, but only if they were built before 1974 -- the year Starrett opened.</p>
        <p>A bill introduced in January by Assemblyman Vito J. Lopez, a Brooklyn Democrat, would extend rent regulations to Mitchell-Lama developments built or substantially rehabilitated since Jan. 1, 1974.</p>
        <p>Sheldon Silver, a Manhattan Democrat and the speaker of the Assembly, yesterday threw his support behind the proposal. ''Working families must be able to call New York City home,'' he said in a statement. ''The 'Save Starrett City Law' is aimed at allowing tenants in that project and in other Mitchell-Lama buildings to remain in our communities.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg also supports the bill.</p>
        <p>With 5,800 units and 14,000 residents in 46 towers on 140 acres on the eastern edge of Brooklyn, facing Jamaica Bay, Starrett City, now formally known as Spring Creek Towers, is the largest federally subsidized rental complex in the country. Starrett City Associates, the longtime owners, put the complex up for auction in November, and on Feb. 8, Clipper Equity L.L.C., a partnership led by David Bistricer and Sam Levinson, won after outbidding six rivals.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bistricer has said that the new owners plan to remove Starrett City from the Mitchell-Lama program, but he maintains that the complex will remain affordable to low- and moderate-income tenants. Advocates for affordable housing are concerned that new owners will raise rents to justify the purchase price, or cut services at the development, which has its own shopping center, schools, houses of worship, power plant and security force.</p>
        <p>During the last five years, about 13,000 housing units across the city have been withdrawn from the Mitchell-Lama program.</p>
        <p>At a City Hall news conference, Bertha Lewis, executive director of New York Acorn, part of the Association of Community Organizations for Reform Now, and Dan Cantor, executive director of the Working Families Party, said their organizations would make the proposal one of their top legislative priorities this year.</p>
        <p>''Starrett City represents everything that we really think this city should be about,'' Mr. Cantor said. ''It's called the 'Save Starrett City Law,' but it really should be called the 'Save New York City Law.' ''</p>
        <p>The news conference was attended by three members of the State Senate, six members of the Assembly and eight members of the City Council. Assemblyman N. Nick Perry, a Brooklyn Democrat, said the state should make sure that ''landlords do not put profits ahead of tenants.''</p>
        <p>Gov. Eliot Spitzer, Attorney General Andrew M. Cuomo, Senator Charles E. Schumer and Alphonso R. Jackson, the secretary of the federal Department of Housing and Urban Development, have all expressed concerns about the sale, as have Mayor Bloomberg and his commissioner of housing preservation and development, Shaun Donovan.</p>
        <p>Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton echoed those concerns yesterday. At a celebration of black history at the Lower Manhattan headquarters of District Council 37, the city's largest union of public employees, Mrs. Clinton said, ''Here in the city, we are trying to save affordable housing.''</p>
        <p>Referring to Starrett City, she said to cheers and applause, ''We've got to save the housing there.'' She added, ''We are all trying to prevent what we see as likely to happen,'' saying she feared ''the end of affordable housing in this city. And that would be just yet one more example of it.''</p>
        <p>The sale is far from a certainty. The state holds the interest-free mortgage for Starrett City and could, with the Department of Housing and Urban Development, reject the new owner. And city officials would have to approve any plans by the buyers to develop buildings on the vacant land around the complex.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
