<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Versace, a Testament to Genius</title>
    <meta content="26FASHION" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/26/fashion/shows/26FASHION.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1829049"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FASHION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy/Milan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Italy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Versace, Gianni</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Lagerfeld, Karl</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Missoni, Angela</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4D6113EF935A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="922" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Versace, a Testament to Genius</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Versace, a Testament to Genius</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CATHY HORYN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Horyn, Cathy</byline>
      <dateline>MILAN, Feb. 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It will be 10 years this summer since Gianni Versace was killed in Miami Beach, and there are now more reasons than ever to wonder what fashion would be like if he had lived. Would his keen eye and sense of timing kept us better informed on the subject of sex than Dolce &amp; Gabbana and Dsquared? Would he have tempted us without losing our trust, without forgetting that we still care about fit and quality?</p>
        <p>No doubt Mr. Versace would have responded to a culture tipping toward pornography. After all, he agitated critics in the 1980s by alluding to sexual bondage. And no individual has gotten more mileage out of a safety pin than the actress Elizabeth Hurley, thanks to Mr. Versace's punk-inspired dress. (Ms. Hurley was in the front row on Friday for the show of his sister, Donatella.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reviews of the Versace, Fendi, Missoni, Moschino, Dsquared and Ferré collections.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It will be 10 years this summer since Gianni Versace was killed in Miami Beach, and there are now more reasons than ever to wonder what fashion would be like if he had lived. Would his keen eye and sense of timing kept us better informed on the subject of sex than Dolce &amp; Gabbana and Dsquared? Would he have tempted us without losing our trust, without forgetting that we still care about fit and quality?</p>
        <p>No doubt Mr. Versace would have responded to a culture tipping toward pornography. After all, he agitated critics in the 1980s by alluding to sexual bondage. And no individual has gotten more mileage out of a safety pin than the actress Elizabeth Hurley, thanks to Mr. Versace's punk-inspired dress. (Ms. Hurley was in the front row on Friday for the show of his sister, Donatella.</p>
        <p>Yet it's more than nostalgia that persuades us that Mr. Versace would have shown infallible good judgment. There is his record of work. And like only a handful of designers today -- Karl Lagerfeld, Rei Kawakubo, Azzedine Alaïa, John Galliano and, to a lesser extent, Oscar de la Renta -- he was able to embrace current waves of fashion without sacrificing technique and actuality.</p>
        <p>All this is by way of saying that Ms. Versace's collection was a real testament to her brother's genius. She and her surviving brother, Santos, have gone through some difficult times, personally as well as professionally. But she has shown three consecutive collections that no one could seriously quibble with, and the one she put up the other night was outstanding.</p>
        <p>The tailoring of exaggerated A-line coats and neat suits displayed punch, and dresses in a molded-looking white silk were a nice balance of classicism and futurism. A creamy wool coat came with an Empire band of silvery embroidery. And a parade of sleeveless black cocktail dresses put to rest the idea that this look was old hat; tight across the low back of one worn by Daria Werbowy were two or three oversize links of black chain. Three silver shifts were also low and square in the back.</p>
        <p>In the past, Ms. Versace's chiffon evening dresses have looked a bit predictable. But here, too, there was more finesse, more energy, as gowns in black, white or violet displayed skill in their construction. To the clothes, she added shoes with mirrorlike platforms and sometimes a slightly outrageous bag (and you thought bags couldn't get any bigger). The superpolished look of her models -- glossy natural lips, the hint of a cat eye, long, softly turned-under hair -- added to the confident message of the show.</p>
        <p>For the last few seasons, Mr. Lagerfeld's collections for Fendi have threaded between historic elements like Renaissance sleeves and futuristic materials, as if he were not quite sure of fashion's direction. But we are likely to see both views, and Mr. Lagerfeld has never had a problem holding seemingly opposing ideas in his mind.</p>
        <p>This collection was particularly strong for the shapes and raw textures Mr. Lagerfeld proposed. The silhouette was slightly more rounded on top, with examples like a white leather suit with yarn and fur fringe exploding from short, belled sleeves, and a black mink-lined leather jacket that looked as glossy as urban nylon and was constructed in a kind of open patchwork.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lagerfeld, who is planning to have a Fendi fashion show on the Great Wall in China in late May, has also refocused attention on furs, giving a striped chinchilla coat the look of seared wood. It was a funny, understated take on the habit of branding everything. New bags included flat, fuzzy clutches in an abstract logo pattern, wiggy looking yarn numbers and one enormous bag in matte gold sequins and turquoise dreadlocks that seemed to cry out for a rhinestone cellphone and a pink Chihuahua. A special person, indeed.</p>
        <p>Angela Missoni, despite some pleasing graphic patterns and a slimmer silhouette than the last couple seasons, seemed uncharacteristically of two minds. She opened her show with long sportswear looks cinched with a wide, latticelike contraption. The leather belts, snapped in the back, might look great for a picture, but they took something away from the actuality of the clothes.</p>
        <p>That was the real problem of the collection. Ms. Missoni seemed on the right track with patchwork jersey dresses and separates, notably a shell with soft gray trousers. But how do full, ladylike skirts of different lengths fit into the whole picture? And how do you square evening dresses harnessed with twisted silk with the natural ease of heavy silk crepe blouses?</p>
        <p>Moschino nimbly dealt with the snug jacket and the bell-shape skirt -- a trend in Milan -- and there were some lovely, loose black coats with a metallic sheen. The peace symbol appeared as a broken scattering of matte sequins on jackets and bags, so that it looked almost sprayed on, graffiti style.</p>
        <p>Another day, another homage to Mad Max and the Thunderdome. That was the scene at Dsquared, where the designers Dean and Dan Caten ran riot with sexy black leather, rough-looking fur and chain ornament. It was all fun and perfectly banal.</p>
        <p>Leaving Gianfranco Ferré's show, one felt a strange, alien sadness. Planet Ferré: there is nothing like it. The tailoring was sharp and masculine, and the new deconstructed coats, with wide cropped sleeves, hinted of sleek kimonos. Tight black pants and stripped-down furs were very cool, very boss and, in that way, closer to a night in Vegas or Dubai than an afternoon in Milan.</p>
        <p>FASHION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
