<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Saudi Clergymen Seek Tighter Islamic Rule</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="561462"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHURCH-STATE RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAUDI ARABIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAHD, KING OF SAUDI ARABIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D6163DF93BA35753C1A964958260" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Saudi Clergymen Seek Tighter Islamic Rule</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YOUSSEF M. IBRAHIM,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Oct. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the second time in two years a large group of militant fundamentalist clergymen in Saudi Arabia has submitted a petition to King Fahd criticizing virtually every aspect of domestic and foreign policy in the kingdom and demanding a more rigorous application of Islamic law in a country that already ranks as one of the world's most conservative Muslim societies.</p>
        <p>The 46-page document was delivered to the Saudi Government's senior religious leader, Sheik Abdelaziz Bin Baz, who administers the kingdom's religious affairs. It demanded revision of the nation's defense and foreign policies and the prohibition of dealings with Western financial and cultural institutions, such as banks and television and entertainment companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the second time in two years a large group of militant fundamentalist clergymen in Saudi Arabia has submitted a petition to King Fahd criticizing virtually every aspect of domestic and foreign policy in the kingdom and demanding a more rigorous application of Islamic law in a country that already ranks as one of the world's most conservative Muslim societies.</p>
        <p>The 46-page document was delivered to the Saudi Government's senior religious leader, Sheik Abdelaziz Bin Baz, who administers the kingdom's religious affairs. It demanded revision of the nation's defense and foreign policies and the prohibition of dealings with Western financial and cultural institutions, such as banks and television and entertainment companies.</p>
        <p>The document, signed by 107 religious officials from various Government-financed Muslim universities and institutions around the kingdom, denounced the Government's "containment" of religious activities and the arrests of some religious firebrands who have made inflammatory speeches at Friday prayers.</p>
        <p>It also severely criticized Saudi Arabia's payments, totaling $26 billion, to Iraq during its war against Iran from 1980 to 1988 and to other "non-Islamic governments," including Syria, Russia, Jordan, Algeria and Egypt. It asked the King to refrain from inviting foreign "atheist" troops to defend Saudi Arabia ever again, as he did in 1990 after the invasion of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>The petition, a copy of which was faxed to The New York Times by a militant Islamic organization, was bolder and more defiant than a similar document drafted in May 1991 by some of the same people, and contained more than twice as many signatures.</p>
        <p>The official press agency denounced the petition as "misguided" and "divisive," full of errors and aimed at "sowing confusion" while "overlooking the good deeds of Government."</p>
        <p>Several Saudi liberals dismissed the document as a manifestation of the insecurity of Islamic militants about the fast pace of modernization in Saudi Arabia. They said it was probably prompted by the King's decision in February to establish a 60-member consultative council.</p>
        <p>The memorandum demands that religious programming, already commanding well over 50 percent of the time and space available on radio and television and most newspapers, be increased further. It calls on the King to direct Saudi Government television to stop running programs that "glorify decadent Western life styles."</p>
        <p>The Saudi ruling establishment, the royal princes and businessmen who favor a liberal economic policy and steady modernization of political and social institutions, has run into increasing resistance from religious militants. The religious right has opposed Middle East peace talks, which the King supports, and the Saudi alliance with the United States. Religious Censorship Sought</p>
        <p>The petitioners asked that Muslim religious scholars be allowed to vastly expand their freedom of expression "on any subject they see fit" without seeking approval from elder religious leaders affiliated with the Government. It also sought permission for the fundamentalists to set up their own privately financed press and broadcast companies and a supreme consultative council of religious figures to review all written and broadcast material before it is presented to the public.</p>
        <p>The document sharply criticizes waste in military spending, saying that there is a wide discrepancy between the amounts spent on purchasing arms and expertise in the past 20 years, which exceed $150 billion, and the size and power of the Saudi Army which, it said, is too weak to defend the country against aggressors.</p>
        <p>It also criticizes the failure of the Saudi military to render assistance to fellow Muslims "or in fighting the Jews," in an allusion to Bosnia and Israel. The petition asked for the creation of an army of a half a million Saudis (in a country with a population of about 10 million), the establishment of compulsory military service and the creation of a reserve corps "as is the case with the Jewish enemy."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
