<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PRO FOOTBALL: Taylor Going, Simms Out, Hostetler In for Giants; What About Handley? He Just Not Talking</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="561567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREY, JENNIFER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMMS, PHIL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOSTETLER, JEFF</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HANDLEY, RAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D91130F93BA35753C1A964958260" item-length="1064" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PRO FOOTBALL: Taylor Going, Simms Out, Hostetler In for Giants; What About Handley? He Just Not Talking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER FREY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREY, JENNIFER</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Oct. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Phil Simms is out with an elbow injury. Jeff Hostetler is now the Giants' starting quarterback.</p>
        <p>How long will this situation last? Nobody knows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Phil Simms is out with an elbow injury. Jeff Hostetler is now the Giants' starting quarterback.</p>
        <p>How long will this situation last? Nobody knows.</p>
        <p>In fact, nobody knows much about what's going on with Giants these days, or at least that was the way it seemed today. Simms was unavailable to discuss the sudden discovery of his injury, Hostetler slipped out a side door of the locker room and eluded reporters and Coach Ray Handley found himself in an unrelated but equally wordless controversy.  Simms and Hostetler Not Talking</p>
        <p>Apparently upset by a stream of criticism in this 1-3 season, Handley today issued a statement saying he was curtailing his availability to the news media, and he declined to hold his scheduled midweek news conference. According to eyewitnesses, Handley also cleared photographers from the field, not allowing them their usual 10 minutes of access, and ended up having something of an incident with two photographers over their presence outside the practice field.</p>
        <p>Simms was not available to speak with the news media after practice. Hostetler made a point of eluding reporters, asking a locker-room attendant to drive his car to a different exit so that he could sneak out a side door.</p>
        <p>Handley paused for only a few questions after practice and did not elaborate on the extent of Simms's injury, other than to briefly explain when and how it occurred.</p>
        <p>According to Handley, Simms suffered an injury to his throwing elbow during the final series of Sunday's game against the Raiders that is more serious than anyone in the organization first thought. After undergoing a Magnetic Resonance Imaging examination on Tuesday, it was determined that Simms had suffered a strained ligament in his right elbow, and he is now taking anti-inflammatory medication to combat the problem.</p>
        <p>"We're going to evaluate it in a couple of days, see if the swelling goes down, then make a determination from there," said Handley, who did not rule out the possibility of Simms's being placed on injured reserve, which would require him to miss at least four games.</p>
        <p>Other than that, Handley wasn't saying much.  According to a member of the Giants' organization, Handley is upset because WNBC-TV aired and commented on an exchange that occurred at a news conference Monday between Handley and New York Times columnist Ira Berkow. In that exchange, Berkow tried, unsuccessfully, to get Handley to elaborate on the coach's statement that the Giants lack "killer instinct" and Handley responded by becoming angry and suggesting that Berkow would simply write anything he wanted to.</p>
        <p>Today, when he was stopped after practice, Handley explained his decision to not hold a news conference by telling members of the media: "It was too disruptive to me during the course of the week. I thought I was giving you enough time."</p>
        <p>Handley has apparently found photographers to be too disruptive as well. When Joe Gigli of The Star Ledger of Newark attempted to take a picture of Handley locking the practice gates today, Handley found it necessary to come off the practice field and confront Gigli and Keith Torrie of The Daily News.</p>
        <p>According to Gigli and the MSG producer, Anthony Fucilli, who said he was an eyewitness, Handley grabbed Gigli's arm forcefully and told Gigli: "I thought I told you practice was closed. No pictures." Handley Denies Charge</p>
        <p>Handley denied that he had touched anyone.</p>
        <p>In other words, some of the little information disseminated by Handley today may or may not be true.</p>
        <p>The reporters in Phoenix fared better when it came to getting information from Handley, if only because the National Football League requires it. The Giants play the Phoenix Cardinals on Sunday, so Handley conducted his N.F.L.-required midweek telephone conference call with the out-of-town news media.</p>
        <p>"Jeff wasn't pleased when I named Phil as the starter," Handley told the Phoenix reporters, "but I'm sure he understands why I did what I did. At the same time, I know he wanted to play. He's a professional. He kept himself ready."</p>
        <p>Simms was injured when he was hit from behind by defensive end Anthony Smith on third-and-13 from the Giants' 22-yard line late in the fourth quarter. He remained in the game and threw six passes, completing three, but felt a soreness in his elbow after the game. X-rays and the M.R.I. revealed loose bodies from a previous injury and some ligament damage.</p>
        <p>While Simms is out, rookie Dave Brown will be the Giants' backup quarterback. Offensive coordinator Jeff Fassel said today that the Giants had no immediate plans to sign a third quarterback.</p>
        <p>"I'd feel like any other coach who has an untested rookie in the game," Handley said, when asked by the Phoenix press how he felt about potentially using Brown in a game situation. "I wouldn't be overly confident, but we feel Dave Brown is a player with potential. I'm sure he'll rise to the challenge to get ready for the backup role." Players Shrug Off Change</p>
        <p>One of the only things that seemed predictable today was the players' response to the latest quarterback change. Most shrugged off the idea that a change will disrupt the Giants' offense, given that they have worked with Hostetler so much in the past.</p>
        <p>"He knows the offense," wide receiver Ed McCaffery said. "I feel confident that Jeff's going to do the job."</p>
        <p>In fact, Hostetler has started most of the Giants' games against Phoenix in the past few years and has a strong history of success against them -- a fact that did not escape Cardinals' Coach Joe Bugel.</p>
        <p>"We have utmost respect for both of them," Bugel said, "but Hostetler, he poses more of a problem because he can scramble."</p>
        <p>Hostetler is 14-5 as a starter, 4-0 in games he has started against Phoenix, and has run for five touchdowns against the Cardinals -- including a 47-yard scramble last November that marked the Giants' longest run from scrimmage that season.</p>
        <p>"It seems like every game we've played against them, Hostetler either played or starter," Handley told the Phoenix writers. "All the games have been close, but Jeff's done things with his scramble against them and made some big plays that enabled us to win."</p>
        <p>Hostetler, by the way, gave the silent treatment to the Cardinals' news media, failing to make a scheduled conference call to Phoenix, according to a reporter from The Phoenix Gazette.</p>
        <p>Anybody surprised?</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
