<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CUNY Unit For Italians Faces Turmoil</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="561503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ITALIAN-AMERICANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEACHERS AND SCHOOL EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK (CUNY)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CALANDRA, JOHN D, ITALIAN AMERICAN INSTITUTE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEISS, SAMUEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCELSA, JOSEPH V</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D8173FF93BA35753C1A964958260" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CUNY Unit For Italians Faces Turmoil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL WEISS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEISS, SAMUEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A City University of New York plan to restructure a unit largely devoted to recruiting and counseling Italian-American students has led to a bitter battle between the university's chancellor and some leading Italian-Americans.</p>
        <p>The university plans to turn the unit, the John D. Calandra Italian American Institute, into a research center specializing in Italian and Italian-American affairs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A City University of New York plan to restructure a unit largely devoted to recruiting and counseling Italian-American students has led to a bitter battle between the university's chancellor and some leading Italian-Americans.</p>
        <p>The university plans to turn the unit, the John D. Calandra Italian American Institute, into a research center specializing in Italian and Italian-American affairs.</p>
        <p>But critics say the move is a thinly disguised effort to dismantle the organization and punish its longtime director, Dr. Joseph V. Scelsa, for participating in an anti-discrimination complaint that Italian-American faculty members filed against the university. The complaint, which charges that the university is discriminating against Italian-American faculty in hiring, promotion and tenure, is pending before the United States Department of Labor.</p>
        <p>Last month Dr. Scelsa got a temporary restraining order from Federal District Court in Manhattan barring the university from carrying out its plans, and testimony on the issue of whether to make the injunction permanent is in its third week.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile Italian-American civic and political leaders have called for state legislative hearings concerning the university's treatment of minority groups, in particular Italian-American students. Involvement of Politicians</p>
        <p>"For years we've been raising the issue," said State Senator Guy J. Velella, Republican of the Bronx. "But all we've gotten is promises. There's been no constructive action to resolve the problem."</p>
        <p>Others rallying to the defense of the institute have been Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato; Rudolph W. Giuliani, the former United States Attorney and mayoral candidate; Assemblyman Frank J. Barbaro of Brooklyn, and William D. Fugazy, president of the Coalition of Italo-American Associations, an umbrella organization for more than 130 groups.</p>
        <p>But the university's plan is supported by others, including the National Sons of Italy and State Senator John J. Marchi.</p>
        <p>University officials deny any discrimination against Italian-Americans. They claim the current turmoil results from Dr. Scelsa's intensive lobbying effort to protect his current job. He has been head of the institute since the early 1980's.</p>
        <p>Under the university's restructuring plan the institute, currently located at 25 West 43rd Street in Manhattan, would be moved to the College of Staten Island. Its academic research role would be greatly strengthened.</p>
        <p>But its recruitment program would be handed over to the university's Office of Admissions Services and to various campuses. Dr. Scelsa would become director of student outreach at the Office of Admissions Services. His salary would remain the same, $70,100. Doctoral Program Planned</p>
        <p>Jay Hershenson, a spokesman for Chancellor W. Ann Reynolds, said the restructuring was intended to give the institute "academic" status by turning it into a major research center that would be used to build a new doctoral program in Italian studies.</p>
        <p>"This is a situation in which no good deed goes unpunished," Mr. Hershenson said. "The fact is that what we're trying to do is create a first-class research institute in the fields of Italian and Italian-American studies at a time when the university is being forced to reduce or eliminate other programs because of state budget cuts."</p>
        <p>The Calandra Institute, named after a former state senator, was established by the Legislature in 1978 after hearings were held in Albany on complaints of discrimination and neglect of the Italian-American community by the university. The institute performs a variety of functions, including the recruitment and counseling of Italian-American students and research on policy issues of concern to Italian-Americans.</p>
        <p>Although the university asserts that the changes will strengthen the institute, Dr. Scesla and others say the parceling out of the institute's various functions would amount to its dismantling, and the move to Staten Island would make the research center inaccessible to most students and faculty members.</p>
        <p>Dr. Scelsa said he believed he was being singled out for retribution because he was party to the labor complaint.</p>
        <p>"The fact is I'm a major irritant," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
