<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Video</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="608649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIDEO GAMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERACTIVE (TWO-WAY) TELEVISION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NICHOLS, PETER M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DA1E3EF930A25756C0A965958260" item-length="1292" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Video</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NICHOLS, PETER M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Action movies deliver thrills on screen, and as Hollywood has discovered, they also make for a star-studded breed of interactive video game. Thanks to the multi-media compact disk, called CD-ROM, the Arnold Schwarzeneggers and Sylvester Stallones can jump into the contest, too.</p>
        <p>"Real characters are better to interact with than those little green guys," said Peter Dille of Sony Imagesoft, which produces video games for the corporation that owns the Columbia Pictures and Tri-Star studios and Columbia Tri-Star Home Video.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Action movies deliver thrills on screen, and as Hollywood has discovered, they also make for a star-studded breed of interactive video game. Thanks to the multi-media compact disk, called CD-ROM, the Arnold Schwarzeneggers and Sylvester Stallones can jump into the contest, too.</p>
        <p>"Real characters are better to interact with than those little green guys," said Peter Dille of Sony Imagesoft, which produces video games for the corporation that owns the Columbia Pictures and Tri-Star studios and Columbia Tri-Star Home Video.</p>
        <p>The green characters are a reference to the video-game craze that came and went in the early 1980's. These days Mr. Dille's company and others like Sega and Electronic Arts, the world's largest interactive software producer, are developing advanced games with sound and graphics that one day might approximate the movies themselves.</p>
        <p>Last year Sony released a game based on "Hook," with players advancing from level to level on a quest with Peter Pan. In the future there will be Sony games spun off from "Bram Stoker's 'Dracula' " and two coming films from Tri-Star and Columbia, "Cliffhanger," with Mr. Stallone, and "The Last Action Hero," with Mr. Schwarzenegger.</p>
        <p>The 16-bit games, which can process more information on their wider data path, can be played on a Sega Genesis machine that has an attachment for reading the large-capacity compact disks, the CD-ROM. Like other video games, the new ones involve quests or missions that progress from one level of difficulty to the next. As with the old games, the object is to win, but CD-ROM games offer players more varied situations and options. The goal is a greater degree of reality and a higher level of entertainment.</p>
        <p>"Games are fast and have a lot of moving characters," said Ellen Beth Van Buskirk of Sega, which will issue a game this summer tied to "Jurassic Park," the Steven Spielberg film that opens June 11. For games on disk, clips from the films can be used, but the action is less than full motion. Stars might appear to offer pointers or take part in some other way.</p>
        <p>The aura of the film business has overtaken the game industry. Sega, for example, has built a $10 million studio in Redwood City, Calif., where film-trained graphics artists and technicians make all kinds of games, from sports to movie-related. For its movie games, Sega seeks ties with Hollywood. "We want to get in on the front end, see what kind of footage we can get," Ms. Van Buskirk said.</p>
        <p>At Sony and other studios' own game divisions, the game makers have the advantage of being in the studio already. "We have early access to scripts and sets," Mr. Dille said.</p>
        <p>In the planning stages are more powerful 32-bit games to be played on a new machine promised by 3DO of San Mateo, Calif. "The use of those extra 16 bits is to make the audio and video sound and look more like television than an interactive video game," said Stewart Bonn of Electronic Arts. In 32-bit games, he added, players might also be able to control the plot line.  NEW VIDEO RELEASES A River Runs Through It  1992. Columbia Tri-Star. $94.95. Laser disk, $39.95. 123 minutes. Closed captioned. PG.</p>
        <p>Robert Redford's reverent version of Norman Maclean's memoir about family and male ritual on the trout streams of Montana can follow the book only so far. With its handsome tableaux and sturdy characterizations, the film contributes a seriousness of purpose. Craig Sheffer is the scholarly and passive Maclean, with Brad Pitt as his livelier brother and Tom Skerritt as their stiff, austere father. An uncanny director of actors, Mr. Redford is able to convey the distances between men. But, Vincent Canby wrote in The New York Times, the film remains "more a homage to its source material than a work of comparable emotion or breadth." Glengarry Glen Ross  1992. LIVE. $94.98. Laser disk, $34.95. 100 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>It's crunch time in a Chicago real estate office where the most productive salesman will win a Cadillac Eldorado and the least successful will find himself on unemployment. Directed adeptly by James Foley, David Mamet's adaptation of his 1984 Broadway play ups the level of psychic desperation. With expanses of Florida scrub land to peddle in the kitchens of the unsuspecting, the smooth Ricky Roma (Al Pacino), the highest-powered of the sales crew, is off and running. The rest (Jack Lemmon, Ed Harris, Alan Arkin and Jonathan Pryce) are a sweaty bunch in a time of tight money and waffling clients. Using Mr. Mamet's gift for language. Mr. Foley delivers a "living film that preserves the claustrophobic nature of the original stage work" (Canby). Ted and Venus  1991. Columbia Tri-Star. $89.95. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>Ted (Bud Cort), a dissipated drifter, falls for Linda (Kim Adams), a pretty social worker he spies on the beach in Venice, Calif. With a courting technique that veers from dopey humor to obscene phone calls, Ted doesn't get very far. Still, Mr. Cort's film has an interesting cast (with Jim Brolin as a hard-drinking hipster and Gena Rowlands as Linda's mother) and "a vivid sense of the numerology, yoga classes and dulcimer lessons that color California beach life, circa 1974" (Janet Maslin). Zentropa  1992. Touchstone. $94.95. Laser disk, $39.99. 112 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>After the war a German-American pacifist (Jean-Marc Barr) goes to post-Nazi Germany to help out in the restoration. There he takes a job at a giant railway terminal called Zentropa and finds himself in a futuristic nightmare in which stony-faced crowds wander a bleak landscape. With this as its platform, Lars von Trier's film devotes itself to high-flown allusions to celebrated film technique, "becoming a sarcastic comic meditation about cinematic myth-making and the relationships between Hollywood, Europe and World War II" (Stephen Holden). FROM YEARS PAST The Feature Films On the Best-Seller List</p>
        <p>Of the 40 titles now on Billboard's best-seller list, 9 are feature films (the others falling into the animated, workout, music and Playboy and Penthouse categories). At No. 5 on the list, "Dances With Wolves" is the highest-ranking film. Here are the others.</p>
        <p>THE MARK OF ZORRO (No. 17). Tyrone Power, Linda Darnell and Basil Rathbone star in Rouben Mamoulian's swashbuckler. 1940. Fox. $19.98. 93 minutes. No rating.</p>
        <p>LAURA (No. 21). But she's supposed to be dead. A hard-bitten detective (Dana Andrews) looks into the murder of Laura Hunt (Gene Tierney) in the Otto Preminger's classic. 1944. Fox. $19.98. Laser disk, $39.98. 85 minutes. No rating.</p>
        <p>MCLINTOCK! (No. 22). John Wayne battles his rebellious wife (Maureen O'Hara) as his daughter (Stefanie Powers) heads for cover. 1963. Good Times. $19.98. 122 minutes. No rating.</p>
        <p>FRIED GREEN TOMATOES (No. 24). Jon Avnet's film about Southern life stars Mary Stuart Masterson, Mary Louise Parker, Kathy Bates and Jessica Tandy. 1991. MCA/ Universal. $19.98. Laser disk, $39.98. Closed captioned. PG-13.</p>
        <p>SISTER ACT (No. 27). A singer on the run (Whoopi Goldberg) hides out in a convent and teaches the nuns to harmonize. 1992. Touchstone. $19.99. 100 minutes. Closed captioned. PG.</p>
        <p>J. F. K.: DIRECTOR'S CUT (No. 31). Seventeen more minutes of evidence finds its way into Oliver Stone's film. 1991. Warner. $24.98. 205 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>BASIC INSTINCT: DIRECTOR'S CUT (No. 32). There's 47 more seconds of sex in this version of Paul Verhoeven's thriller. 1992. LIVE. $49.98. Laser disk, $69.95. 150 minutes. Closed captioned. No rating.</p>
        <p>LA FEMME NIKITA. The American remake, "Point of No Return," recalls this very good French original. 1990. Vidmark. $19.95. Laser disk, $34.95. 117 minutes. French with English subtitles. R.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
