<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Glimmer of Hope</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="143185"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="ABROAD AT HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH-WEST AFRICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONDON (ENG)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA, REPUBLIC OF</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CUBA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANGOLA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GELDENHUYS, JAN (GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSALES DEL TORO, ULISES (GEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DE173BF93BA35756C0A96E948260" item-length="727" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Glimmer of Hope</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Anthony Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Gen. Jannie Geldenhuys, Chief of Staff of the South African Defense Force, stepped aside with Gen. Ulises Rosales del Toro, Chief of Staff of the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Cuba. For an hour and a half they talked.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Gen. Jannie Geldenhuys, Chief of Staff of the South African Defense Force, stepped aside with Gen. Ulises Rosales del Toro, Chief of Staff of the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Cuba. For an hour and a half they talked.</p>
        <p>Gen. Jannie Geldenhuys, Chief of Staff of the South African Defense Force, stepped aside with Gen. Ulises Rosales del Toro, Chief of Staff of the Revolutionary Armed Forces of Cuba. For an hour and a half they talked.</p>
        <p>A scene from a far-fetched thriller? No, it actually happened last week, in a London hotel.</p>
        <p>The tete-a-tete between the Cuban and South African generals took place during an extraordinary diplomatic meeting. It was an attempt, brokered by the United States, to bring to a peaceful end the multiple wars and political disputes that have ravaged the southwest corner of Africa for years.</p>
        <p>The notion that the Reagan Administration, in its final months, could help work out a real settlement of those conflicts sounds like a pipe dream. But I think the possibility should not be dismissed. The London meeting produced reasons for guarded hope.</p>
        <p>That the meeting occurred at all was notable. For the first time, representatives of South Africa, Angola and Cuba sat down to negotiate. The U.S. Assistant Secretary of State for African Affairs, Chester A. Crocker, was there in the role of an activist mediator.</p>
        <p>Angola, South Africa and Cuba all sent their military chiefs and their top intelligence officials: a clear signal of seriousness. The negotiators talked for two days and announced that they had made progress. They decided to meet again in about two weeks.</p>
        <p>Finally, and crucially, the parties all agreed on what they were there to negotiate: a total withdrawal of the 40,000 Cuban soldiers now in Angola in return for a South African agreement to get out of Namibia, the neighboring territory that it has occupied for decades. Namibia would become independent under United Nations Resolution 435, which South Africa has accepted in principle but never agreed to implement.</p>
        <p>The issue on the table - the very hard issue - is timing. Angola has proposed that Cuban forces leave over four years: a period dismissed by South Africa as far too long. In London, the Angolans made claim that the figure was negotiable.</p>
        <p>Linkage between Namibian independence and withdrawal of the Cuban forces from Angola has been Mr. Crocker's policy for seven years. He argued that it would give South Africa an incentive to free Namibia at last.</p>
        <p>Critics, who are numerous, say the Crocker approach played into South Africa's hands. Pretoria, they say, used the asserted Communist threat as an excuse for repeated invasions of Angola. In recent months 3,000 South African troops have engaged in heavy fighting there, in support of Jonas Savimbi's rebels. The whole focus has shifted to the bloody Angolan war, making independence for Namibia ever more remote.</p>
        <p>Whatever the merits of that policy debate in the past, linked diplomacy seemingly has attractions for all parties right now. The inconclusive carnage of the recent battles in Angola has made military victory for either side unlikely. The Soviet Union, Angola's chief arms supplier, apparently supports a diplomatic resolution. It is hard to see how South Africa will get out of Namibia without a political settlement in Angola.</p>
        <p>The big question is whether the South African Government will commit itself to a settlement. It has been internally divided, with important elements in the Defense Force content to go on fighting in Angola because the military gets good training there and has acquired huge amounts of Soviet weaponry. That is why the presence of General Geldenhuys at the London meeting was so significant.</p>
        <p>The diplomatic process that is now moving confronts South Africa with a call to decide one way or the other. And President P. W. Botha knows what the friendliest American President he is ever going to have would like him to do. Mr. Reagan would not be pleased at missing a reasonable chance to see the Cubans out of Angola.</p>
        <p>The Angolan Government also faces hard decisions. Cuban withdrawal raises real risks for it. Morever, a settlement will undoubtedly require some arrangement to bring Mr. Savimbi's Unita movement into the Government.</p>
        <p>The problems are so daunting that skepticism is in order. On the other hand, reason cries out for an alternative to endless devastation in Angola and repression in Namibia. Beyond that, if peace were given a chance there, one could begin hoping for a relationship of live-and-let-live between South Africa and all its neighbors.</p>
        <p>ABROAD AT HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
