<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Key Brings the Blue Jays Just One Game Away</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="564887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="WORLD SERIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORLD SERIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TORONTO BLUE JAYS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ATLANTA BRAVES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHASS, MURRAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Atlanta Braves</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D8143DF931A15753C1A964958260" item-length="1269" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Key Brings the Blue Jays Just One Game Away</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHASS, MURRAY</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Oct. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jimmy Key, who by virtue of his nine years as a member of the Toronto Blue Jays qualifies for honorary Canadian citizenship, tonight executed the most remarkable performance by a player in a World Series game played in Canada.</p>
        <p>That this was only the second World Series game ever played in Canada makes no difference. Key was that superb.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jimmy Key, who by virtue of his nine years as a member of the Toronto Blue Jays qualifies for honorary Canadian citizenship, tonight executed the most remarkable performance by a player in a World Series game played in Canada.</p>
        <p>That this was only the second World Series game ever played in Canada makes no difference. Key was that superb.</p>
        <p>But as impressed as the Atlanta Braves were by Key, they were astounded by two specific plays in their 2-1 loss that gave the Blue Jays a commanding three-games-to-one lead. One was an eighth-inning bunt by Damon Berryhill, whose three-run home run gave them their lone victory; the other was the defensive positioning of John Olerud, the Toronto first baseman, on the last out of the same inning.</p>
        <p>The 31-year-old Key, who pitched only five innings in the previous three weeks, dazzled the Braves by allowing only three hits in the first seven innings and walking none in his seven and two-third innings of admirable work.</p>
        <p>His performance put the Blue Jays, who haven't lost two games in a row since the end of August, in position to win the World Series on Thursday night. Jack Morris, who won the seventh game of last year's World Series for the Minnesota Twins with a 10-inning shutout, will pitch for the Blue Jays against John Smoltz, who pitched seven and one-third shutout innings in that game.</p>
        <p>"We're in somewhat the situation we were in last year," Morris said. "If we win, they go home." History Favors Dome Team</p>
        <p>Morris and the Blue Jays will play the game in a domed stadium, where the home team never has lost in the World Series. This victory made the dome home record 10-0. The Braves have lost six of those games, four to the Twins last year and now two at the Skydome.</p>
        <p>Key, making his first World Series start, weakened in the eighth and gave up the Braves' only run, but Duane Ward finished that inning and Tom Henke wrapped up the victory in the ninth by easily retiring the third, fourth and fifth hitters in the Braves' woefully weak lineup, which has a .185 batting average (23 hits in four games) in the Series.</p>
        <p>The left-handed Key gave up a run but wound up allowing only five hits and striking out six. Tom Glavine, who pitched a four-hit victory in the Series opener, gave up only six hits, but one of them was a third-inning home run by Pat Borders, Key's catcher.</p>
        <p>The Blue Jays added what turned out to be the decisive run in the seventh. Kelly Gruber led off with a walk, but Glavine got the next two batters, with Gruber going to second as Manny Lee grounded out. Devon White, the defensive hero of the third game, drove Gruber home with a single to center.</p>
        <p>Gruber knocked himself out with a headfirst slide and said later that he could not remember scoring.</p>
        <p>The Braves remembered all too well not scoring much against Key.</p>
        <p>"He was changing speeds and throwing a lot of strikes," said Jeff Blauser, whose out in the eighth ended the Braves' brief rally. "He was getting ahead of everybody. It doesn't matter who you are, what type of pitcher you are. You throw strikes, you can win."</p>
        <p>Otis Nixon and Blauser, the first two batters in the game, stroked singles, but Key picked Nixon off first and got the next two batters after Blauser stole second. He also got all the batters he faced in the next four innings and extended his consecutive-out streak to 16, with nothing resembling a hit, before Nixon singled with two out in the sixth. Good Timing for Key</p>
        <p>"I was very fortunate in the first inning," said Key, whom Manager Cito Gaston skipped in the playoffs because he wanted to use all right-handers against Oakland. "I got the ball up and I was a little concerned. When I have trouble, it's usually early. They hit the ball hard but right at people. I was fortunate to pick off Otis. After that I got my feet on the ground and pitched my game the rest of the time I was out there."</p>
        <p>Key, who finished the season with a 13-13 record, was the team's most effective starter in the final five weeks of the season with a 5-1 record in seven starts.</p>
        <p>"Tonight typified the way I finished the season," he said. "Changing speeds, getting the ball over the plate. In August, I couldn't get my off-speed stuff over the plate and my pitches were up. I'm glad I got it straightened out at the right time of the year."</p>
        <p>Key's only real trouble began when, with Toronto ahead, 2-0, Ron Gant ended a 0-for-16 post-season string with a leadoff double in the eighth inning. Brian Hunter then bunted toward third base for a hit that sent Gant to third.</p>
        <p>"Normally I get that ball," Key said, "but I wasn't thinking bunt."</p>
        <p>Berryhill was the next batter. In the sixth inning of the opener, he hit a three-run homer against Morris that gave the Braves a 3-1 victory. This time he bunted the first pitch.</p>
        <p>"The whole bench was shocked," said a member of the Braves who was on the bench but didn't want to be identified. 'I Did the Worst Thing I Could'</p>
        <p>On the other bench, Dave Winfield said, "Thank you."</p>
        <p>"We appreciated that," the Blue Jays' elder statesman said. "It gave us an opportunity. We were looking for a double play, but we get a popup. It was very helpful."</p>
        <p>Yes, Berryhill popped the bunt foul to Borders for the first out, a key out for Key.</p>
        <p>"I do not know what the hell he was doing," Bobby Cox, the astonished Braves manager, said. "That was the last thing in my mind."</p>
        <p>The Braves' catcher acknowledged that Hunter's bunt influenced him.</p>
        <p>"Brian laid down a good bunt," Berryhill said, "and right there I looked at Gruber and he didn't move in for me. If I put it down third past the pitcher, I have a base hit and Ronnie scores. If I don't get a good bunt, we have runners at second and third. Unfortunately, I did the worst thing I could. I popped it up."</p>
        <p>Mark Lemke followed Berryhill, and he rapped a hard grounder off the mound and Key's arm. Gruber quickly retrieved the ball and threw out Lemke as Gant scored and Hunter went to second.</p>
        <p>"Kelly made a great play charging the mound and getting that ball," Key said. "If Kelly doesn't make that play, they have a big inning going."</p>
        <p>Gruber did not remember making the play. He had to watch a replay of it to see what he had done.</p>
        <p>At that point, Gaston replaced Key with Duane Ward, the winning pitcher in the previous two games. Ward struck out Nixon, but the third strike bounced past Borders for a wild pitch and Nixon reached first. He then stole second, giving Blauser a chance to give the Braves the lead with a single. That's where Olerud's positioning came in.</p>
        <p>Blauser hit a wicked grounder a couple of feet inside the line that the Braves were certain would go for a double. But Olerud intercepted the ball with a backhand grab, one knee on the ground, then got up quickly and beat Blauser to the bag for the third out.</p>
        <p>"I thought it was going to be down the line, especially on Astroturf," Blauser said.</p>
        <p>Blauser, Cox said, "hits a bullet down the line. It was the key to the ball game. Why is Olerud on the line with two outs and the winning run at second? I still don't understand that."</p>
        <p>Rich Hacker, the coach who is responsible for infield positioning, explained. Blauser, he pointed out, is a right-handed hitter who can't pull the hard-throwing, right-handed Ward.</p>
        <p>"He was not standing on the line and he was not way off," Hacker said. "We've had other guys who our charts show don't hit the ball the other way but do when they face Ward. He was exactly where I wanted him. John was looking in and I told him not to move."</p>
        <p>The play helped move the Blue Jays one victory away from Canada's first World Series championship.</p>
        <p>WORLD SERIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
