<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Algerians Conclude Campaigns for First Election in 12 Years</title>
    <meta content="Y06ALG$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/06/international/africa/06ALGE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040514T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1572108"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Algeria</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bouteflika, Abdelaziz (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Algeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Algeria</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bouteflika, Abdelaziz</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040406T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EEDE1F39F935A35757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1055" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Algerians Conclude Campaigns for First Election in 12 Years</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Algerians Conclude Campaigns for First Election in 12 Years</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>ALGIERS, April 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Algeria's presidential candidates conclude their campaigns for first multiparty presidential election since military coup 12 years ago prevented Islamic party from coming to power; incumbent Abdelaziz Bouteflika is widely expected to win race, although large turnout could split vote enough to require second round in order for one candidate to win majority; despite presence in country of more than 120 international observers, many people believe campaign has been manipulated by government to ensure Bouteflika a second term; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Algeria's presidential candidates concluded their campaigns on Monday evening ahead of the country's first multiparty presidential election since a military coup 12 years ago prevented an Islamic party from coming to power.</p>
        <p>The incumbent, Abdelaziz Bouteflika, is widely expected to win the race in the first round of voting on Thursday, though a large turnout could split the vote sufficiently to require a second round in order for one candidate to win a majority.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With past elections marred by allegations of fraud, more than 120 international observers have arrived in Algeria to monitor the voting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Algeria's presidential candidates concluded their campaigns on Monday evening ahead of the country's first multiparty presidential election since a military coup 12 years ago prevented an Islamic party from coming to power.</p>
        <p>The incumbent, Abdelaziz Bouteflika, is widely expected to win the race in the first round of voting on Thursday, though a large turnout could split the vote sufficiently to require a second round in order for one candidate to win a majority.</p>
        <p>With past elections marred by allegations of fraud, more than 120 international observers have arrived in the country to monitor the voting. Despite their presence, a sense of inevitability has suffused the campaign, which many people believe has been manipulated by the government to ensure Mr. Bouteflika a second term.</p>
        <p>The field of presidential contestants has been narrowed to six by disqualification of several candidates and opposition parties on technical grounds. That leaves the real race between the incumbent and his former prime minister, two men with the same military-backed political pedigree that has dominated Algerian politics since it won its war of independence from France in 1962.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bouteflika and his chief rival, Ali Benflis, are running as independents in a rupture in their party, the National Liberation Front. After Mr. Bouteflika dismissed Mr. Benflis as prime minister last year because of his presidential ambitions, Mr. Bouteflika's supporters managed to annul the results of a party convention that picked Mr. Benflis its candidate.</p>
        <p>While it could not keep him from running independently, the administration kept other opponents out of the race. Earlier this year, the interior minister refused applications that would have legalized two more opposition parties, and the ministry last month rejected three would-be candidates on technical grounds.</p>
        <p>''The existing power doesn't want a strong opposition, a credible opposition or an opposition with a large base,'' said Rashid Lerarri, in an empty room of the villa that would have served as campaign headquarters for the Wafa Party, one of those that the Interior Ministry refused to approve. ''Bouteflika wants to choose his adversaries.''</p>
        <p>The administration said it rejected the application because the party roster included former members of the Islamic Salvation Front, the Islamist party that was banned after it swept the first round of parliamentary elections in 1992, prompting the military to stop the process and take power. That caused a civil war that left well over 100,000 people dead and as many as 15,000 missing.</p>
        <p>Wafa denies that it includes former members of the banned party. There have been many reports, however, that Mr. Bouteflika has sought support from this group, which still has a significant following.</p>
        <p>On Monday, former leaders of the party's armed wing, the Islamic Salvation Army, publicly endorsed Mr. Bouteflika, who negotiated a sweeping amnesty with the group in 1999.</p>
        <p>Unresolved questions from the civil war hang over the election, among them the fate of thousands of people thought to have disappeared or been killed by government security forces in the past 12 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bouteflika came to power in 1999 after other candidates that year withdrew to protest electoral laws that allowed the military undue influence over the outcome.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bouteflika quickly proved a more difficult choice than the generals had bargained for, say many Algerian political analysts. He took eight months to form a government because of disagreements with the military over who should be appointed. Once the government was formed, he announced that he would not be a ''three-quarters president,'' which many people took to be a challenge to his military patrons.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Bouteflika in control of judicial files that could presumably pinpoint responsibility for many of the disappearances and extrajudicial killings of the past decade, he has tried to refashion himself as protector rather than protégé of the military, some analysts say.</p>
        <p>The issue has grown more pressing because an investigation was opened in Paris this year into the deaths of seven French monks who were kidnapped in Algeria and then beheaded in 1996. Many people have charged that Algeria's security forces had a hand in the killings.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Bouteflika told a French television station last month that the time wasn't right ''to tell the full truth'' about the monks' abductions, some people here saw the comment as a veiled warning to restive generals.</p>
        <p>The military declared early on that it would not back a presidential candidate this time. But Mr. Bouteflika has said during campaign speeches in recent weeks, ''I come to you in the name of the army.''</p>
        <p>A sense of defeatism about what many see as an inevitable outcome has fueled an electoral boycott in Kabylie east of Algiers. The impoverished, mountainous region is home to the ethnic Berbers, who have long complained of being left behind politically and economically.</p>
        <p>On Monday, several anti-Bouteflika newspapers charged that there had been fraud in the collection of absentee ballots in France, where a sizable expatriate Algerian population lives.</p>
        <p>The campaign is being driven largely by the personal appeal of the politicians rather than issues. At a rally for an Islamic candidate, Abdallah Djaballah, in Medea this week, he chanted with several hundred followers, ''Change, change, change!'' But after the rally, his supporters found it difficult to articulate his political program.</p>
        <p>''He's for change,'' one man said, adding when pressed, ''economic change.'' Others in the crowd were at a loss for words when asked what economic change Mr. Djaballah proposed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bouteflika and Mr. Benflis, meanwhile, find little to disagree about on the issues. One Benflis supporter conceded that the only clear difference between the two was Mr. Bouteflika's greater experience as head of state.</p>
        <p>It remains possible that if Mr. Bouteflika fails to win a majority on Thursday, Mr. Benflis could take the election in a second round. That would be an upset, not only for Algeria, but for the Arab world where no recent head of state has ever been voted out of office. Few people in this country, however, expect such a dramatic turn of events.</p>
        <p>Correction:  May 14, 2004, Friday  An article on April 10 about the presidential election in Algeria referred incorrectly to the recent history of multiparty elections there. (The error also occurred in an article on April 6.) Multiparty presidential elections were held in 1995 and 1999, and multiparty local and parliamentary elections in 1997 and 2002. The most recent voting, in which President Abdelaziz Bouteflika won a second term, was not the first multiparty presidential election since a military coup in 1992.</p>
        <p>The April 10 article also misspelled the given name of an opposition candidate from the Rally for Culture and Democracy. He is Said Sadi, not Siad Sadi.</p>
        <p>A reader's letters about the errors were initially misdirected at The Times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 14, 2004, Friday</p>
        <p>An article on April 10 about the presidential election in Algeria referred incorrectly to the recent history of multiparty elections there. (The error also occurred in an article on April 6.) Multiparty presidential elections were held in 1995 and 1999, and multiparty local and parliamentary elections in 1997 and 2002. The most recent voting, in which President Abdelaziz Bouteflika won a second term, was not the first multiparty presidential election since a military coup in 1992.</p>
        <p>The April 10 article also misspelled the given name of an opposition candidate from the Rally for Culture and Democracy. He is Said Sadi, not Siad Sadi.</p>
        <p>A reader's letters about the errors were initially misdirected at The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
