<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hectic Day for the G.O.P., Full of Hints and Speculation</title>
    <meta content="27prepare" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/27/nyregion/27prepare.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1690415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Minarik, Stephen J III</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Long, Michael</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Romney, Mitt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E6D7133FF934A15754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hectic Day for the G.O.P., Full of Hints and Speculation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Hectic Day for the G.O.P., Full of Hints and Speculation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK D. HEALY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cellphones of several New York Republican leaders were ringing nearly nonstop by late yesterday afternoon as speculation built a powerful head of steam: Was Gov. George E. Pataki on the verge of announcing he would not run for a fourth term, instead preparing to consider a presidential bid?</p>
        <p>By the hour, evidence mounted that the answer was yes. A meeting of some 25 top Republicans was arranged at the Executive Mansion in Albany, where Mr. Pataki would hold ''an important discussion about the future'' and share ''some major personal news,'' according to one person who attended the meeting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some Republican strategists believe Gov. George E. Pataki may be turning his focus from Albany to Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cellphones of several New York Republican leaders were ringing nearly nonstop by late yesterday afternoon as speculation built a powerful head of steam: Was Gov. George E. Pataki on the verge of announcing he would not run for a fourth term, instead preparing to consider a presidential bid?</p>
        <p>By the hour, evidence mounted that the answer was yes. A meeting of some 25 top Republicans was arranged at the Executive Mansion in Albany, where Mr. Pataki would hold ''an important discussion about the future'' and share ''some major personal news,'' according to one person who attended the meeting.</p>
        <p>Party chairmen like Stephen J. Minarik III, of the Republicans, and Michael R. Long, of the Conservatives, were told they had a few hours to travel hundreds of miles in time for the meeting. County Republican leaders were also notified to prepare for a relatively rare conference call today. .</p>
        <p>To some of Mr. Pataki's friends and political allies, perhaps the greatest signal that he was turning his focus from Albany to Washington was a dinner planned in a hurry with major donors and fund-raisers to be held tonight at the Water Club in Manhattan. One close Republican ally -- who like others spoke on the condition of anonymity because Mr. Pataki wanted to closely guard his intentions -- said his dinner guests were chosen because of their savvy for predicting if Mr. Pataki could raise enough money and compete as a moderate Republican in the 2008 presidential primaries, which tend to be dominated by more conservative politicians.</p>
        <p>''The Water Club dinner is a big sign, because he needs to start working with his donors immediately if he's serious about running in '08,'' said the political ally, who has been invited to tonight's dinner.</p>
        <p>One Republican strategist, who formerly worked for Mr. Pataki, read another tea leaf: The move by a potential rival of Mr. Pataki's in 2008, Gov. Mitt Romney of Massachusetts, to veto a bill that would have widened access to the morning-after pill. Mr. Romney issued the veto on Monday, pleasing some influential conservative Republican groups; similar legislation is heading toward Mr. Pataki's desk, and he is said to be leaning toward a veto as well. To the extent that Mr. Romney is receiving national media coverage this week for his veto, Mr. Pataki may be seeking to make his own splash.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romney and Mr. Pataki were both in Iowa two weeks ago, checking out the political territory, well in advance of that state's influential presidential caucuses in the winter of 2008. They were also attending a national governors' meeting, although Mr. Pataki, notably, skipped a news conference of Republican governors that Mr. Romney was leading.</p>
        <p>At the state Capitol yesterday, the governor's staff spent much of the afternoon hunkered down in their office on the second floor. Earlier, at an event in Troy, Governor Pataki said that he has a timetable for making his decision, but would not say when. ''It's in my mind, and I will let you know and the people of the state know when we're ready to do that,'' he told The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>Among the first to learn that the governor would, in fact, be ready to announce something today, were members of his cabinet, who were told to convene for an 11 a.m. meeting. One Republican, a veteran state government official, said he could not recall the last time the entire cabinet met, but emphasized that the purpose of the meeting was not laid out by the governor's office. ''This all just happened in the last 25 minutes or so,'' the official said Tuesday afternoon. ''Something is being put together, quickly.''</p>
        <p>As last night's meeting at the Albany mansion commenced, some Republicans on the outside were a little stunned by the quick turn of events. Only a few hours earlier Mr. Pataki had suggested that he would announce his intentions before the end of September, with no further detail. But the governor is a cagey politician, other associates noted, and he may have been trying to hint that he had a major decision coming.</p>
        <p>''He's excited to take this next step, where ever it will take him,'' said a Republican official who has advised Mr. Pataki over the years. ''I don't think even he knows how it will turn out, but he is ready for it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
