<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Woman Among Girls Has Her Opinions, Too</title>
    <meta content="16BUTY$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="995887"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE XVIII WINTER GAMES: FIGURE SKATING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1998)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nagano (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butyrskaya, Mariya</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipinski, Tara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kwan, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Nagano</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E3D71F3CF935A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Woman Among Girls Has Her Opinions, Too</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>NAGANO, Japan, Feb. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian figure skater Mariya Butyrskaya says she hopes to win at least a bronze medal at Olympic Games; says she believes 'childish skating,' a reference to her younger rivals Tara Lipinski and Michelle Kwan, is not what the judges want to see; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mariya Butyrskaya of Russia is an elegant performer and powerful jumper, but her confidence has not always matched her figure skating ability.</p>
        <p>She performed so poorly at the 1993 world championships that Russia did not qualify a woman for the singles competition at the 1994 Olympic Winter Games in Lillehammer, Norway. At the 1997 world championships, Butyrskaya held third place after the short program but dropped to fifth over all. Several weeks ago, she won the European championships, and she appears to have a new attitude along with a new coach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mariya Butyrskaya of Russia is an elegant performer and powerful jumper, but her confidence has not always matched her figure skating ability.</p>
        <p>She performed so poorly at the 1993 world championships that Russia did not qualify a woman for the singles competition at the 1994 Olympic Winter Games in Lillehammer, Norway. At the 1997 world championships, Butyrskaya held third place after the short program but dropped to fifth over all. Several weeks ago, she won the European championships, and she appears to have a new attitude along with a new coach.</p>
        <p>But it remains to be seen whether she can hold her composure to challenge Michelle Kwan and Tara Lipinski for a gold medal at the 1998 Winter Games. As she chewed over the question on Saturday, she also nervously chewed the polish entirely off one fingernail.</p>
        <p>''I will skate for the best place,'' Butyrskaya said, using her coach, Yelena Chaykovskaya, as an interpreter. ''I don't think about the bronze. I think about the best place.''</p>
        <p>Chaykovskaya has given her new music, a new program and a new self-assurance.</p>
        <p>''She is very strong and anchored with both legs to the ice,'' Chaykovskaya said. ''She's very talented and can do many fantastic things. But sometimes she doesn't believe in herself that she can do it. Now she is strong psychologically.''</p>
        <p>Never one for subtlety, Butyrskaya has decided that her biggest advantage over the American teen-agers is maturity. She is 25, eight years older than Kwan and a full 10 years older than Lipinski. She is a woman and she will make sure that the judges get the point. She will skate her sultry short program to ''Fever'' when the women's competition begins on Wednesday. And at the beginning of the long program, she likes to make sure the judges and the audience are paying attention.</p>
        <p>''I am like a romantic woman on the ice,'' Butyrskaya said. ''My program has style, not only jumping or something short and funny. Being a romantic woman is a good way to win.''</p>
        <p>At an Olympic preview held before Christmas in Munich, Germany, Butyrskaya snipped at Lipinski's skating, saying that her own artistry and elaborate choreography were more interesting to watch.</p>
        <p>''She does more jumps, but I think artistry makes a difference,'' Butyrskaya said. ''The judges have had enough of childish skating.''</p>
        <p>The remarks did not escape Lipinski, who went out and pummeled Butyrskaya to win the long program at the Champion Series Final.</p>
        <p>Lipinski said: ''She's elegant, but I've worked hard on my artistry. I don't feel like I'm a child out there.''</p>
        <p>Chaykovskaya conceded that Kwan ''is the best figure skater'' and ''I like her style, but Mariya is Mariya.''</p>
        <p>She can land a difficult triple lutz-triple loop jump combination, and has even done a triple axel, her coach said, but Butyrskaya will not attempt either maneuver at the Olympics. The idea is to play it safe and stay on her feet. If she cannot challenge Kwan and Lipinski for the gold and silver, perhaps she can edge out Nicole Bobek for the bronze.</p>
        <p>''The one who will win here will skate clean and artistically and musically,'' Chaykovskaya said. ''This is women's skating, not men's skating or pairs' skating.''</p>
        <p>After her own failures left Russia without any women in the 1994 Olympics, Butyrskaya said that the Russian skating federation attempted to undermine her career. But she proved resilient with a fourth-place finish at the 1996 world championships and a fifth-place finish in 1997. Then, last month, she won the European championships in Milan, Italy.</p>
        <p>''I read the American papers after their national championships and found out people think it will be between Tara and Michelle and Nicole winning the medals,'' Butyrskaya said in Milan, referring to the Olympics. ''I would make myself a contender.''</p>
        <p>While many Russian skaters and coaches have gone to the United States for better skating conditions and financial opportunities, Butyrskaya has remained in Moscow. Two years ago, she was robbed in the elevator of her apartment building as a man held a knife to her and took her earrings, rings and necklace. But she has no intention of leaving, she said. Chaykovskaya said she believed that danger in Moscow, compared with Central Park in New York City, ''is nothing.''</p>
        <p>''My home is there, my family is there,'' Butyrskaya said. ''This is my land. Skating, this is my life. I don't think it, I live inside skating.''</p>
        <p>The daughter of engineers, Butyrskaya began skating at age 5 and was formerly coached by Vladimir Kovalev, the two-time world champion. But she described their relationship as a hand smacking into a fist.</p>
        <p>''No way,'' she said. She fired him and retained Chaykovskaya after a fourth-place finish at the 1997 European championships.</p>
        <p>''She had good jumping and technique, but not enough to win,'' Chaykovskaya said.</p>
        <p>Now Butyrskaya has restored confidence. And, she hopes, a renewed chance to win an Olympic medal.  THE XVIII WINTER GAMES: FIGURE SKATING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
