<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Illness Interrupts an Athlete's Comeback</title>
    <meta content="16SKAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="995886"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE XVIII WINTER GAMES: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1998)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Germany</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nagano (Japan)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Szewczenko, Tanja</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Nagano</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E5D71F3CF935A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Illness Interrupts an Athlete's Comeback</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>NAGANO, Japan, Feb. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>German figure skating champion Tanja Szewczenko withdraws from Winter Games after flu-like symptoms prevented her from practicing for nearly a week (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the most intriguing comeback stories of the Olympics ended today when the German figure skating champion Tanja Szewczenko withdrew from the Winter Games after flu-like symptoms prevented her from practicing for nearly a week.</p>
        <p>Until last fall, Szewczenko had been out of competition for 18 months after suffering from a life-threatening viral infection. But she recovered sufficiently to finish third at the recent European championships and was expected to challenge for a medal in the women's competition, which begins Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the most intriguing comeback stories of the Olympics ended today when the German figure skating champion Tanja Szewczenko withdrew from the Winter Games after flu-like symptoms prevented her from practicing for nearly a week.</p>
        <p>Until last fall, Szewczenko had been out of competition for 18 months after suffering from a life-threatening viral infection. But she recovered sufficiently to finish third at the recent European championships and was expected to challenge for a medal in the women's competition, which begins Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Last Monday, however, Szew czenko, 20, began running a fever, her coach, Peter Jonas, said. After remaining in bed for five days, Szewczenko practiced for a short period on Saturday but had ''no power, no condition,'' Jonas said. He then recommended that she withdraw from the Olympics. After eight hours of discussion and contemplation, some of it in tears, the skater agreed, Jonas said.</p>
        <p>Numerous athletes in the Olympic Village have similar symptoms. The German figure-skating team doctor, Salim Al-Bazaz, said that Szewczenko's current illness was not related to the previous viral infection. Jonas said he hoped that Szewczenko would be able to compete next month in the world championships in Minneapolis.</p>
        <p>Today's withdrawal continued a string of bad luck at the Winter Games for Szewczenko. At the 1994 Winter Games in Lillehammer, Norway, she collided during practice with the eventual champion, Oksana Baiul of Ukraine. Szewczenko was bruised in the collision and finished sixth over all.</p>
        <p>Jonas said today that Szewczenko will return home to Dortmund, Germany, before the women's competition begins.</p>
        <p>''It would be too hurtful for her to attend,'' Jonas said. ''If she doesn't attend, there is no point in staying.''</p>
        <p>Russian Pair Nearing Repeat</p>
        <p>Pasha Grishuk and Yevgeny Platov of Russia narrowly won the original dance tonight and are on the verge of becoming the first couple to repeat as Olympic ice dancing champions. Before these Winter Games, there was much speculation about whether they would lose for the first time in four years. But that appears unlikely now.</p>
        <p>Skating to ''Jailhouse Rock,'' Grishuk and Platov demonstrated their accustomed speed, frequent change of direction and perfect unison as they narrowly won a 5-4 victory from the judges over Anjelika Krylova and Oleg Ovsyannikov of Russia. Grishuk skated with her left wrist bandaged and said she had injured it two weeks ago.</p>
        <p>''I didn't go see a doctor because I'm afraid to know the results,'' she said. ''It's in a lot of pain. If it's broken, I don't want to know.''</p>
        <p>Twice this season, Grishuk and Platov had falls during the original dance. Tonight, Platov fell during warm-ups, but their performance was flawless, even if it fizzled slightly at the end.</p>
        <p>Krylova and Ovsyannikov skated with a liquid symmetry and received a perfect score of 6 from the Russian judge for their performance to another Elvis Presley tune. They defeated Grishuk and Platov in the free dance in the recent European championships, but tonight's slim defeat means they will not likely overtake the defending champions in Monday's free dance.</p>
        <p>''I want to win gold, and then I want to win an Oscar,'' said Grishuk, an aspiring actress, who said she was familiar with the work of Sharon Stone but not Tonya Harding.</p>
        <p>She and Platov have been together since 1989, and the partnership has been stormy at times. ''Not everybody can handle me,'' Grishuk said.</p>
        <p>Perhaps that explains why she does not have a boyfriend at the moment. Interested parties should call ''1-800-PASHA,'' Platov suggested.</p>
        <p>Grishuk had a better idea.</p>
        <p>''Every cute guy please come to the Olympic Village and stand in line,'' she said. ''But only gold medalists, please.''</p>
        <p>Eldredge's Last Attempt?</p>
        <p>After finishing a disappointing fourth with a collapse in the men's free skate on Saturday, Todd Eldredge said that his Olympic career was most likely over unless rules were changed to allow professionals to compete.</p>
        <p>''I don't discount anything,'' Eldredge said.</p>
        <p>But he added: ''I am 90 percent positive this will be the the last time unless they open the rules. And I don't see that happening.''</p>
        <p>Eldredge, 26, of Chatham, Mass., said he still had no explanation for what happened in the free skate.</p>
        <p>''I wish I had skated a decent performance for myself,'' he said. ''If I had, I would have been more satisfied than I am.''</p>
        <p>Eldredge said he would compete at the world championships in March in Minneapolis.</p>
        <p>THE XVIII WINTER GAMES: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
