<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Man Who Set Off Firecrackers Is Called Hero</title>
    <meta content="16FIRE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="995903"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lunar New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fireworks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Chinese-Americans</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chinatown (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lii, Jane H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wang Jian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fireworks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E5DF163FF935A25751C0A96E958260" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Man Who Set Off Firecrackers Is Called Hero</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE H. LII</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lii, Jane H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wang Jian becomes hero in Chinatown for setting off string of firecrackers on the steps of City Hall to protest New York City Mayor Rudolph W Giuliani's fireworks ban during Chinese New Year celebrations; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With one strike of a match, Wang Jian was transformed from ordinary citizen into a community crusader.</p>
        <p>His action -- setting off a few firecrackers on the steps of City Hall to protest the Giuliani administration's fireworks ban during Chinese New Year celebrations -- has made him a hero -- if not a superhero -- to many residents of Chinatown. Restaurant owners have offered him free meals. Wealthy businessmen have pledged money for his legal defense. Civil rights organizations have rallied to his cause. Even police officers have shown deference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With one strike of a match, Wang Jian was transformed from ordinary citizen into a community crusader.</p>
        <p>His action -- setting off a few firecrackers on the steps of City Hall to protest the Giuliani administration's fireworks ban during Chinese New Year celebrations -- has made him a hero -- if not a superhero -- to many residents of Chinatown. Restaurant owners have offered him free meals. Wealthy businessmen have pledged money for his legal defense. Civil rights organizations have rallied to his cause. Even police officers have shown deference.</p>
        <p>Some people have gone so far as to declare him the Rosa Parks of Chinatown.</p>
        <p>Why? Simply because at 2:30 P.M. last Monday, Mr. Wang, 28, a former marine who was clad in military fatigues, stood in front of City Hall and ignited a string of firecrackers. Ten seconds later, he calmly descended the steps, ready to be handcuffed by the police officers who were rushing toward him. ''I did it to make a political statement,'' Mr. Wang said. ''I wanted the politicians to know that the Chinese will stand up for what we believe in.''</p>
        <p>The charges against him were minor -- four misdemeanor counts, including reckless endangerment and disorderly conduct, and one count of an administrative code violation, unreasonable noise. But when Mr. Wang emerged from Central Booking a day later, he found himself being treated with the awe and respect.</p>
        <p>''He did what many of us didn't have the courage to,'' said Thomas Lee, a businessman who waited patiently to shake Mr. Wang's hand one day last week inside a Chinatown store. ''He is not only my hero, but a hero for the whole community.''</p>
        <p>City Hall, not surprisingly, begs to differ. Brenda Perez, a spokeswoman for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, said yesterday that support for the ban was widespread in Chinatown and that Mr. Wang and another protester, Eric Lau, a 20-year-old who was arrested on Feb. 5 on a charge of aggravated harassment for sending several E-mail messages to various city agencies and to the Mayor, were no heroes.</p>
        <p>''The Mayor has been showered with praise from members of the Chinese community in New York City for enforcing the ban on firecrackers,'' Ms. Perez said, ''and he will continue to oppose those who condone a dangerous life style marked by total disregard for the safety of our citizens.''</p>
        <p>She added, ''Other than being arrested and capturing the attention of The New York Times, these two individuals have accomplished nothing for the Chinese community or for any communities in New York City.''</p>
        <p>For two years in a row, the Giuliani administration has banned the use of firecrackers during the Chinese New Year, a ritual central to many traditional celebrations. The Mayor has defended the ban on grounds of safety; on Saturday, Ms. Perez cited as evidence an Associated Press report that more than 47 people were killed in China when a firecracker storage area caught fire.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the ban say they simply want City Hall to permit them to set off firecrackers in designated areas by licensed pyrotechnists and with close city supervision, as Macy's does with its huge fireworks display on the Fourth of July.</p>
        <p>They say they have not heard of any deaths or serious injuries caused by firecrackers during Chinese New Year in New York, and that small firecrackers are often confused with more dangerous types, like M-80's. .</p>
        <p>''We're not supporting the sale of illegal fireworks or the random throwing of dangerous fireworks,'' said Jan Lee, a Chinatown civic leader and a proponent for controlled firecracker displays. ''We want City Hall to give us a chance to follow the safety regulations and do it legally.''</p>
        <p>The Police Department, which keeps statistics on such injuries, said it could not immediately supply the figures.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang's protest at City Hall was not the only act of civil disobedience: protesters set off firecrackers in front of police officers on Feb. 8, the last day of the Chinese New Year celebration. The police, however, chose to ignore the protest.</p>
        <p>Determined to make a more public statement, Mr. Wang went to City Hall, where he knew the popping sounds in close proximity to the Mayor would get him arrested. While in custody, he said, he was jokingly called a ''political prisoner'' by guards. He said police officers  bought snacks for him while he was awaiting arraignment.</p>
        <p>When he was released on $500 bail on Tuesday, Mr. Wang, who faces up to a year in prison and a $1,000 fine, found himself a local hero. During dinner one day last week at a Chinatown restaurant, the waiters and two managers took turns bowing to him and shaking his hand.</p>
        <p>But not everyone was happy with his action. Richard Hsueh, president of a Flushing-based radio subcarrier station, Chinese American Voice, said Mr. Wang went too far in making his point. ''I do not have any problems with a safe, legalized firecracker display,'' Mr. Hsueh said. ''But he should not have done what he did. It's dangerous.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Wang said he made sure the steps of City Hall were empty before he set off the foot-long strand of the small firecrackers known as ladyfingers. ''Public safety was the most important thing on my mind that moment,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But someone at City Hall took the the incident more seriously. Norman Siegel, the executive director of the New York Civil Liberties Union, which is supporting Mr. Wang, said Mr. Giuliani has taken out an order of protection against Mr. Wang. Citing concerns for Mr. Giuliani's safety, Ms. Perez declined to comment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
