<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Doing a Guitar Solo With the Web as the Teacher</title>
    <meta content="03BASI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/03/technology/03BASI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1290180"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="BASICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">lew, julie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Basics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Oxnard</location>
        <org class="online_producer">National Association for Music Education</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Heaven</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Macromedia Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Edmonds, Kenneth</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Foster, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Manilow, Barry</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E2DE1538F930A35756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Doing a Guitar Solo With the Web as the Teacher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE LEW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">lew, julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Convergence of the Internet and cutting-edge technology creates hundreds of online music instruction courses of varying difficulty and sophistication; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DURING a particularly hectic workday, Dee LaBorte likes nothing more than to take a break and pound on some drums. And she does just that, right in her home office in Coronada, Calif., where she keeps a conga. She logs onto Drumlesson.com, and with a few clicks, the room pulsates with the beats of a marcha rhythm, offering her a virtual playing partner.</p>
        <p>''It's become a habit,'' said Ms. LaBorte, a television production assistant, who has been an online student since November. ''I like to practice with people, but sometimes it just doesn't happen with people's different schedules. This way, I just click it on and it's there. It's addictive.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DURING a particularly hectic workday, Dee LaBorte likes nothing more than to take a break and pound on some drums. And she does just that, right in her home office in Coronada, Calif., where she keeps a conga. She logs onto Drumlesson.com, and with a few clicks, the room pulsates with the beats of a marcha rhythm, offering her a virtual playing partner.</p>
        <p>''It's become a habit,'' said Ms. LaBorte, a television production assistant, who has been an online student since November. ''I like to practice with people, but sometimes it just doesn't happen with people's different schedules. This way, I just click it on and it's there. It's addictive.''</p>
        <p>For frustrated musicians, the convergence of the Internet and cutting-edge technology is offering another dimension of convenience. The Web is home to hundreds of music courses, ranging from play-by-numbers piano lessons to personalized, interactive master classes.</p>
        <p>Harmonicacountry .com, for example, offers an aspiring musician almost instant gratification with its 10 simple lessons. With a harmonica and some practice with Lesson 1, a student can learn to play ''Kumbaya'' in a half-hour.</p>
        <p>''It's a new wrinkle on an old thing,'' said Michael Blakeslee, associate executive director of the National Association for Music Education, a nonprofit organization in Reston, Va., that developed the standards for music education in public schools.</p>
        <p>Just as flesh-and-blood music teachers come in different shapes and sizes, instructional Web sites have varying degrees of multimedia sophistication. Some are simple black-and-white pages, while others offer full-color streaming video. But all teach the same way: you call up the site, click on the lesson you want, manipulate the various options like tempo and sound, then begin to practice. You can practice as long and as loudly as you like without anyone telling you to ''ssshhh.'' When you are ready for evaluation, some of these sites allow you to plug into the software to get criticism and advice.</p>
        <p>Tonos.com, a musicians' network founded by the Grammy Award winners Carole Bayer Sager, Kenneth Edmonds (known as Babyface) and David Foster, offers introductory guitar and piano lessons. Taught with infinite patience by Sticky, an animated cartoon character, beginners are allowed 12 months of access to eight lessons for $15.95. The piano lessons start with an introduction to the keyboard and note reading and end with instructions on the more difficult passages in ''Für Elise.'' The guitar package is a basics course that is supposed to endow the player with enough skill to play ''Midnight Special'' eventually. Lessons do not need to be downloaded. Registered students just log in and play.</p>
        <p>Beginning and advanced guitarists will find something of interest in the treasure trove that is WholeNote. This site offers free access to more than 900 lessons, from such elementary courses as stringing your guitar to such esoteric ones as how to play ''Stairway to Heaven'' with a blues-jazz twist. The main aim of the WholeNote community is to allow guitarists to share their knowledge and techniques with other players. The archives can be searched by style, member name or skill level, and the lessons themselves include musical examples that can be manipulated by the students for tempo, the type of guitar they want to hear and the number of times they want to hear a particular section.</p>
        <p>Drummers in search of more technologically advanced lessons can find them at Drumlesson.com, one of the Web's most comprehensive sites on drumming. With high-quality video clips and MP3 streaming audio, students can delve into 50 basic drumbeats, for example, as taught on archived lessons by Kalani, a well-known performer and instructor. Eight weeks of lessons cost $9.95.</p>
        <p>With its extensive multimedia encyclopedia on drumming, audio interviews with artists, member forums and online lessons, Drumlesson.com is a labor of love for its founder, Kalani, who has performed with  artists like Kenny Loggins, Yanni, Barry Manilow and Dr. John. The site is easy to navigate, and the lessons are taught in clear, detailed, high-quality video, audio, text and graphics. The lessons range from My First Drum Set ($9.95 for eight weeks) to a starter course on topics like how to put the parts together and hold the sticks and one on complete rhythm arrangements for West African djembe and dunun drums. ($9.95 for eight weeks). Students need to download QuickTime Video, QuickTime Audio, RealAudio and MP3 Audio to get access to the lessons.</p>
        <p>Kalani, who prefers to go by a single name, has produced instructional videos and teaches workshops on drumming. He views his online lessons as good introductory and supplemental lessons to private instruction. Online lessons offer certain advantages, he said, like being able to repeat a pattern of beats easily just by clicking on a loop.</p>
        <p>Mars Music, a national chain of 46 stores selling music equipment and in-store private lessons, has entered the growing online-lessons arena with some of the most sophisticated technology available. A basic microphone feeds your performance into the computer, where the proprietary Learning2Play software on the Mars Music site translates it into a musical language called MIDI (Musical Instrument Digital Interface). The software can then tell you whether an incorrect note was played or whether the note was played too long or too short, as well as what the correct pitch or instrument fingering should be.</p>
        <p>''The software is awesome,'' said Randy Kroll, a database administrator in Santee, Calif. At 40, Mr. Kroll decided that it was time to learn how to rock 'n' roll. He had never played an instrument other than the recorder in elementary school and did not know how to read a note. Now, he said, he can play some basic chords after a week of lessons. ''I like being able to do it in the privacy of my own home and do it at my own pace,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The next-best thing to a live teacher, MarsMusic.com also takes advantage of  RealVideo and Macromedia Flash. The lessons, which so far cover guitar and flute,  will soon be available for 15 instruments,  including clarinet, saxophone, trumpet, trombone, piano and bass. Each level of lessons (there are five for each instrument)  costs $11.95 for one year. Mars Music has partnered with Warner Bros. Music, which has made its catalog of songs available available for lessons.</p>
        <p>As advanced as online lessons have become, most instructors say, they are best used in conjunction with face-to-face lessons. ''Even the best technological wizardry can never replace a human instructor,'' Mr. Blakeslee said. ''If you play the violin, for example, the finger has to be placed exactly right. It can't be just kind of right. A good teacher gives a student constant feedback, an internal sense of how it feels and how it sounds.''</p>
        <p>Site-Seeing: Music Lessons  Where Aspiring Musicians Can Get Started or Get Better</p>
        <p>HARMONICA COUNTRY: www.harmonicacountry.com -- A simple site offering 10 free lessons and harmonica-related links.</p>
        <p>MARS MUSIC: www.marsmusic.com -- This online music retailer also offers some of the most technologically advanced interactive lessons for guitar and flute and plans to add clarinet, saxophone, trumpet, trombone, piano and bass. Lessons start at $11.95 for one year's access. Requires downloading of company's software.</p>
        <p>DRUMLESSON.COM: www.drumlesson.com -- A comprehensive and well-designed site on drums and drumming. Lessons start at $9.95 for eight weeks and can be downloaded or viewed online.</p>
        <p>TONOS: www.tonos.com -- A music network founded by three Grammy Award winners. In addition to a number of tools to help connect musicians online, the site offers 12 months of access to basic piano or guitar lessons for $15.95.</p>
        <p>WHOLENOTE: www.wholenote.com -- This award-winning site offers more than 900 free guitar lessons with fingerings and an online metronome.</p>
        <p>PLAYMUSIC: www.playmusic.org -- A colorful, fun-filled introduction to the components of the orchestra created by the American Symphony Orchestra League for children.</p>
        <p>BASICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
