<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>SOCCER</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="671781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCCER</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">YANNIS, ALEX</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E0DF153AF932A35750C0A962958260" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>SOCCER</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">YANNIS, ALEX</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Name Game</p>
        <p>In an attempt to make the players more easily recognizable to the American public during the World Cup this summer, FIFA, the sport's worldwide governing body, has decided to put the names of the players on the back of their jerseys for the first time in the history of the tournament.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Name Game</p>
        <p>In an attempt to make the players more easily recognizable to the American public during the World Cup this summer, FIFA, the sport's worldwide governing body, has decided to put the names of the players on the back of their jerseys for the first time in the history of the tournament.</p>
        <p>Also for the first time, numbers will be put on the front and back of players' jerseys and the front of their shorts.</p>
        <p>"We're here on a promotional tour for soccer," Guido Tognoni, FIFA's press officer, said about the staging of the World Cup in the United States. "We have to please the crowds."</p>
        <p>During a two-day seminar last week in Manhattan, Tognoni reminded delegates and coaches from the 24 countries of their responsibility to the news media.</p>
        <p>"You're here to win games," Tognoni said, "but remember that you're in this country also on a promotional tour."</p>
        <p>News media access to the players in team dressing rooms is still forbidden in international soccer and that may never be changed. It will, however, be changed for this tournament. Instant Replays</p>
        <p>Replays of goals and other highlights of the 52 matches will be shown on a scoreboard or electronic board at all nine stadiums that will play host to games.</p>
        <p>No controversial plays will be shown and referees will not consult the video replay for questionable plays.</p>
        <p>"We're doing this to help the offensive side of the game," Sepp Blatter, FIFA's second in command behind Joao Havelange, said of the instant replay.</p>
        <p>Blatter said replays would be used for disciplinary reasons, but never for an incident that could affect the result of a game.</p>
        <p>"We're not going to show anything that questions a referee's decision," Blatter said. "Remember that the referee's decision is final." Color Them Colorful</p>
        <p>Another first for World Cup '94 will be a change in the color of the officials' uniforms from basic black to lighter colors like gray and silver.</p>
        <p>A pool of 30 referees and 25 linesmen from around the world that are on a preliminary list to officiate World Cup games will gather in Dallas March 13-18 for a seminar on tactics and strategy.</p>
        <p>Members of FIFA's Referees Committee believe that one of the reasons officials sometimes perform inadequately is because they are not up to date with tactics and strategy, especially as the rules pertain to linesmen and offside calls.</p>
        <p>"Just as the players have to know the rules of the game, the referees must know the tactics to perform more efficiently," Blatter said. "They'll get a lesson in tactics in Dallas."</p>
        <p>After the Dallas seminar, which includes one American, Arturo Angeles, a civil engineer from Temple City, Calif., 22 referees and 22 linesmen will be selected by the committee to work the tournament. World Cup Substitutes</p>
        <p>A third substitution (a notion that was unheard of a few years ago) appears to be a a certainty for this World Cup, which will be played over a month in nine American cities starting June 17 in Chicago.</p>
        <p>The International Football Association Board, which is responsible for the Laws of the Game, will meet at FIFA's headquarters in Zurich this week to adopt the change, which will allow the substitution of an injured goalkeeper.</p>
        <p>Substituting an injured goalkeeper would not count against the two regular substitutions that teams are allowed during a game. Other considerations include the replacement of a goalkeeper who has been ejected without counting it as one of the substitutions. Corner Kicks</p>
        <p>Saudi Arabia has its third coach in the last four months. Jorge Solari of Argentina was named to replace Leo Beenhakker of the Netherlands, who replaced Jose Candido of Brazil last November. . . . Bolivia, which will play defending champion Germany in the opener on June 17 in Chicago, suffered a 2-0 loss to Pumas of the Mexican League in an exhibition game Sunday. . . . Colombia and South Korea, which are in the tournament, played to a 2-2 tie in another exhibition on Saturday. ALEX YANNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
