<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3-D Oohs and Aahs, the Old-School Way</title>
    <meta content="26IMAG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/26/technology/circuits/26imag.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20021228T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1451566"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Three-Dimensional Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Stereoscopic Society</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ebay (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Lynn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Three-Dimensional Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021226T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E0DF103CF935A15751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3-D Oohs and Aahs, the Old-School Way</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">3-D Oohs and Aahs, the Old-School Way</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN HARRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Harris, Lynn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Stereoscopic Society promotes art of 3-D imaging with lectures, exhibitions and other events; equipment first appeared at 1939 New York World's Fair and is generally available on eBay; viewers and cameras described, along with process, which is fairly labor intensive in terms of finding necessary peripherals; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR Eric Drysdale, the mundane task of clearing out some clutter from his wife's grandmother's apartment opened up, almost literally, a new dimension.</p>
        <p>''I came across an old stereoscopic camera, a 3-D viewer and tons of 3-D images of her grandparents from the late 40's,'' said Mr. Drysdale, 34, a writer for ''The Daily Show'' on Comedy Central. ''My wife and I were blown away. I knew nothing about photography, but I began shooting 3-D photos immediately with the camera that had been sitting there for 50 years.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Enthusiasts using stereoscopic cameras and special viewers patch together a 3-D view of the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR Eric Drysdale, the mundane task of clearing out some clutter from his wife's grandmother's apartment opened up, almost literally, a new dimension.</p>
        <p>''I came across an old stereoscopic camera, a 3-D viewer and tons of 3-D images of her grandparents from the late 40's,'' said Mr. Drysdale, 34, a writer for ''The Daily Show'' on Comedy Central. ''My wife and I were blown away. I knew nothing about photography, but I began shooting 3-D photos immediately with the camera that had been sitting there for 50 years.''</p>
        <p>In these days of visual trickery, people may not think twice about seeing two Nicolas Cages at once in one movie frame. But Mr. Drysdale is one of thousands of aficionados worldwide who use 3-D imaging, an old-school technique that has elicited oohs and aahs since the 19th century.</p>
        <p>Stereo hobbyist clubs exist in most states and at least 10 other countries. The National Stereoscopic Association (www.stereoview.org), founded in 1974, has about 3,500 members, said its president, Mary Ann Sell. She and her husband also run the Oliver Wendell Holmes Stereoscopic Research Library in Cincinnati, which houses more than 20,000 3-D images, related books and periodicals, and 3-D equipment. And for those who cannot manage a trip to Cincinnati, Web sites focusing on stereoscopy put advice and information at hobbyists' fingertips.</p>
        <p>In a way, 3-D imaging is the opposite of special effects. Rather than tricking the eyes, 3-D pictures replicate what the eyes actually see. That is, each of the eyes projects a slightly different picture onto the retina. Merged, the two images give people a sense of their place in space.</p>
        <p>Since a standard camera has only one lens, the resulting photos are flat.</p>
        <p>But the two lenses of a stereoscopic camera, placed eye-width apart, ''see'' as people do. When the image pairs are viewed together with a 3-D viewer or special glasses doing the merging work of the brain, the illusion of depth results.</p>
        <p>''You use muscles in your eyes to view 3-D pictures that you don't use when looking at a flat image, no matter how luminous and beautiful it is,'' says Greg Dinkins, a co-founder, with Mr. Drysdale, of the New York Stereoscopic Society (www.ny3d.org), which promotes the art of 3-D imaging with lectures, exhibitions and other events.</p>
        <p>Mr. Drysdale, who makes 3-D photos of friends' weddings as gifts, added: ''Looking at a 3-D image is very much like being there. The word 'stereo' comes from the Greek 'solid.' It's as if you're in a world of solids, not somewhere flat. And you're seeing exactly what was seen through the camera at the moment the picture was taken. There's almost the sense that you're time traveling.''</p>
        <p>Acquiring the equipment needed to create most types of 3-D images also involves a trip through time, or at least to eBay or another collectors' mecca.</p>
        <p>View-Master viewers, which first appeared at the 1939 New York World's Fair, are now marketed by Fisher-Price and are available at toy stores, along with disks (known as reels) with images of cartoon characters, dinosaurs and the like. A few companies, including Vivitar, make 3-D cameras and viewers for recreational use.</p>
        <p>But 3-D hobbyists generally prefer one of two cameras produced in the 1950's: Kodak's Stereo Realist camera, which also requires a viewer of its own, or a View-Master camera. Such cameras can fetch $300 on eBay, but bargain hunters can find them for less than $100. (Some photographers do go to the trouble of mounting two current cameras two and a half inches apart.)</p>
        <p>With a View-Master camera, regular slide film is used and developed at a photo shop, but each pair of images must be cut from the film and inserted into an empty View-Master reel by using another 1950's gadget, something like a desktop hole punch, calibrated to make the images the right size and distance apart.</p>
        <p>Empty View-Master reels are no longer made, so photographers scrounge for old or used ones and then insert each tiny square by hand. ''You have to want to do it yourself,'' Mr. Dinkins said.</p>
        <p>Jim Gasperini, 50, a San Francisco resident who was creative director for the computer game SimCity 3000, described 3-D imaging as ''a curiously neglected art form with remarkable expressive possibilities.'' After years of collecting 19th-century cards, he took a Stereo Realist camera on a rafting trip.</p>
        <p>''I lost that camera in a flip halfway down the river, but the pictures I'd already taken were so much fun that I immediately found a replacement on eBay and have been a serious stereo nut ever since,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gasperini's Web site (www.well.com/user/jimg) features his work in the so-called freeview format: side-by-side photo pairs whose shared third dimension emerges only through an ungainly technique. One must first stare more closely at the screen than one's mother would like and then lean slowly back, letting the eyes relax and cross, to merge the images.</p>
        <p>The Web is thus limited as a showcase for 3-D images as such. But as a crossroads for enthusiasts, it is indispensable.</p>
        <p>When Chris Kalb, 35, of Brooklyn first tried to use his new -- well, 1952 -- 3-D slide projector, the image that appeared on his white wall was a jumbled mishmash. ''I thought the projector was broken,'' Mr. Kalb said. But instead of returning it, he turned to the Web, where a search of 3-D tricks and techniques quickly solved the problem: 3-D projection requires a silver screen.</p>
        <p>Not just a metaphor for Hollywood glitz, the silver in the screen prevents the light from depolarizing and keeps the projected image intact.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kalb, a Web designer and art director for Sci Fi magazine, has the fanciest hardware and the latest software but does not own a regular camera. Rather, he enjoys photographing retro-flavored events like the Coney Island Mermaid Parade and Fourth of July celebrations with his 1952 View-Master camera.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Kalb, 3-D photography is about being there, literally. Recently, after tracking down the proper screen, he gave a party inviting guests to ''Witness the View-Master Photography of Chris Kalb in Three Dazzling Dimensions!'' -- and turned his living room into a scene reminiscent of the famous photo of moviegoers in red-and-blue 3-D glasses.</p>
        <p>''I'm used to showing my work, often anonymously, to a large audience,'' Mr. Kalb said. ''But since 3-D images aren't really e-mailable or visible on the Web, if I want to show what I've done, there's no way to but to have people show up in person. It's much more social.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 28, 2002, Saturday  An article in Circuits on Thursday about the hobby of stereoscopic photography misidentified the maker of a camera popular in the 1950's, the Stereo Realist. It was the David White Company, not Kodak.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 28, 2002, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article in Circuits on Thursday about the hobby of stereoscopic photography misidentified the maker of a camera popular in the 1950's, the Stereo Realist. It was the David White Company, not Kodak.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
