<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sandhogs, Blind Mules and the Birth of a Subway</title>
    <meta content="25TUNN$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/25/nyregion/25TUNN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1467734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="TUNNEL VISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Tunnel Vision</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E5DB163CF936A15751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sandhogs, Blind Mules and the Birth of a Subway</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sandhogs, Blind Mules and the Birth of a Subway</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Randy Kennedy</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Randy Kennedy Tunnel Vision column focuses on news accounts of building of New York City subways century ago; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On this date a century ago, New York City was still a metropolis without a subway. But considerable evidence suggested that one was very, very near, and that it was trying hard to devour the city it was designed to help. For example:</p>
        <p>Mansions on Park Avenue between 38th and 39th Streets were sinking into the earth, and their facades threatened to collapse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If events from a century ago show anything clearly, it is that our urban forebears suffered greatly for the sake of the mass transit we have inherited.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On this date a century ago, New York City was still a metropolis without a subway. But considerable evidence suggested that one was very, very near, and that it was trying hard to devour the city it was designed to help. For example:</p>
        <p>Mansions on Park Avenue between 38th and 39th Streets were sinking into the earth, and their facades threatened to collapse.</p>
        <p>According to an account in this newspaper, inspectors tried to assure residents that the situation posed no real danger, unless, of course, they ''should chance to be standing in front of their homes at the time.''</p>
        <p>But property was not the only thing being swallowed. So were people and animals, at an alarming rate. In the fall of 1902, one Charles F. Allaire, Civil War veteran, accidentally rode his bicycle into an open subway tunnel at Amsterdam Avenue and 65th Street, breaking his right leg. Edward Morris drove a whole car in, at Broadway and 43rd Street. And several months later a runaway black gelding paid the ultimate price to the machine age: he galloped into the subway in Harlem, broke his forelegs and was put down with a police officer's pistol.</p>
        <p>With the centennial of the subway approaching -- the first passengers boarded on Oct. 27, 1904 -- it seemed a good time to begin a close reading of the news leading up to that momentous day. And if events from a century ago show anything clearly, it is that our urban forebears suffered greatly for the sake of the mass transit we have inherited.</p>
        <p>In fact, if the movie ''Gangs of New York'' tells how the city was born in the streets, stories of the subway's construction tell how the modern city was really born beneath them, with great, strange and sometimes deadly labor pains.</p>
        <p>They tell about lakes of quicksand beneath Chinatown and ''rotten rock'' under Park Avenue. They tell about the unearthing of cedar water pipes and old cannons and ancient skulls, one, according to The Times, with ''two full rows of teeth that looked as though they never knew an ache.'' They tell about a procession of lawsuits and accidents and angry strikes so great they would have doomed most major projects.</p>
        <p>But they also tell of great sacrifice. How, for example, in an era before dump trucks and bulldozers, much of the work was done by pack mules lowered into tunnels in 1900 when digging began and not brought out again until it was finished -- many of them going blind in the interim. An article in the winter of 1903 described one such valiant mule, sometimes called Jim by the workers.</p>
        <p>''For the last year,'' the article said, ''Jim has never opened his eyes, not even when a blast of dynamite was exploded in his vicinity. And although he must be as blind as a bat to all intents, his drivers say he never makes a misstep.''</p>
        <p>Some of the tunnel workers did not fare so well: one hallucinated a fire-breathing dog; another quit because he thought he saw a tiger in the tunnels.</p>
        <p>The articles tell of some very bad luck, too, personified mostly in Maj. Ira A. Shaler, who earned the nickname the ''hoodoo contractor'' after a dynamite accident and later a tunnel collapse on his watch in 1902 killed five people, wrecked the Murray Hill Hotel and began to sink several art-filled Park Avenue mansions.</p>
        <p>That same year, during a tunnel inspection with the chief subway engineer, the major stepped a few inches in the wrong direction and was crushed by a falling boulder.</p>
        <p>Most of the misfortunes of subway building were much more mundane. For example, workers had to wade through sewers and contend with man-size icicles dangling from boulders. They had to untangle such a mess of iron and clay beneath 23rd Street that one engineer surmised that more money had been spent on utility pipes there ''than under any other thoroughfare in New York, or in the United States for that matter.''</p>
        <p>Of course, none of the stories go so far as to suggest that New Yorkers, being New Yorkers even then, took ruined streets and gas leaks and collapses and blasts and fires and rat infestations with anything nearly approaching good grace.</p>
        <p>It was a city, after all, that while part Dodge City -- murderous gangs still roamed Kips Bay, commandeering businesses and attacking police officers -- was trying very hard to calm down and clean up.</p>
        <p>The offices of The Times were flooded with angry subway complaints for years, mounting as the work dragged on.</p>
        <p>One 1902 article, summarizing, said the public was finally ''beginning to ask if, in their case, patience does not cease to be a virtue.''</p>
        <p>One night, guests at the Waldorf-Astoria decided this question for themselves. Awakened by ''such a clatter and racket that it was impossible to sleep or have any peace of mind,'' they complained angrily to the manager, who complained angrily to the Board of Health, which decided to order the suspension of the work.</p>
        <p>Somehow, the subway was finished anyway. But by that point, even its workers had stopped trying to bet on when. ''Anyone who tries to say exactly when this work will be finished,'' one mining foreman said, ''is a blamed fool. There's no telling.''</p>
        <p>TUNNEL VISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
