<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Milbury Moving Up In Isles' Pecking Order</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="815698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK ISLANDERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAMOS, JASON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILBURY, MIKE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2D71639F930A25751C1A963958260" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Milbury Moving Up In Isles' Pecking Order</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAMOS, JASON</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, L.I., Dec. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It looks as if that escape clause in Mike Milbury's contract, the one that takes effect after two seasons if he wants to explore becoming a general manager, is now a moot point.</p>
        <p>Twenty-eight games into his first season as the Islanders' head coach, Milbury was named today as the third general manager in franchise history.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It looks as if that escape clause in Mike Milbury's contract, the one that takes effect after two seasons if he wants to explore becoming a general manager, is now a moot point.</p>
        <p>Twenty-eight games into his first season as the Islanders' head coach, Milbury was named today as the third general manager in franchise history.</p>
        <p>Afterward, Milbury summed up in four short words why he wants the added responsibility: "Control of player personnel."</p>
        <p>The 43-year-old Milbury, who was once being groomed to become the general manager of the Boston Bruins (with whom he spent two decades as a player, coach  and member of the front office), becomes only the third person in the National Hockey League to hold the dual roles of coach and general manager. Mike Keenan of St. Louis and Bob Gainey in Dallas are the others.</p>
        <p>Money was never an issue. Milbury has a five-year, $3.5 million contract that he has repeatedly called generous. Instead, what apparently held him up from formally declaring his candidacy for general manager was uncertainty over whether the Islanders' four-man management committee wanted him for the job.</p>
        <p>"For me, it was 'I'm available, I want it, but I don't want to be considered  if I'm not going to get it, so make up your mind,' " Milbury said.</p>
        <p>Although the Islanders' vice president of hockey operations, Al Arbour, the man heading the search since Don Maloney was relieved of his duties on Dec. 1, said he had considered about 10 candidates for the job, there were really only two. Milbury beat out the assistant general manager, Darcy Regier, who was acting as the interim general manager, and who will remain in his role with added responsibilities.</p>
        <p>"It was a horse race between him and Darcy," Ralph Palleschi, the chief operating officer of the team's four-man management committee, said.</p>
        <p>Milbury's first order of business will be to resolve the Kirk Muller situation. Muller spent his 30th day of paid exile in Southern California today. Milbury said that if Muller is not traded by Saturday, which he will very likely be, Muller will be told to report back to the team.</p>
        <p>"We need immediate help, an asset that can play," Milbury said. "If the asset isn't good enough, we won't make a deal and we'll tell Kirk to come back."</p>
        <p>Maloney, whose inability to deal Muller contributed greatly to his downfall,  was under tremendous pressure because he knew he would be judged on what he received in return for the player he traded Pierre Turgeon for.</p>
        <p>"My constraint?" said Milbury, when asked. "We want an asset."</p>
        <p>If Muller is traded before Saturday, he will probably go to one of three or four Western Conference teams that the Islanders have had discussions with. Today's news conference went off 20 minutes later than scheduled because Regier  and Milbury were on the phone with one of those teams. St. Louis, Toronto, Detroit and Dallas are apparently the leading contenders.</p>
        <p>Muller aside, Milbury is now faced with the task of reinvigorating a moribund organization from top to bottom. Once a model franchise, the Islanders are a team with a proud history -- and a 7-18-3 record heading into tonight's contest  against the surprising Florida Panthers (21-7-2, first place over all in the N.H.L.).</p>
        <p>And, at first glance, you might think it was the Islanders, not the Panthers, who were the recent expansion team.</p>
        <p>"There are a couple of teams out there, and we're playing one of them tonight, who have managed to get in a position where they are competitive," Milbury said when asked how he would combat the growing perception that most top players (like Muller) do not want to participate in the Islanders' rebuilding phase.</p>
        <p>"A couple of changes are made, you add a veteran, you spend some money in the free agent market and all of a sudden, things turn around," Milbury said.</p>
        <p>Coincidentally, the Panthers were built by Bill Torrey, the Islanders' only general manager for their first two decades -- the architect of four consecutive Stanley Cup winners from 1980 to 1983 -- who was pushed out after the new management committee took over the Islanders after the 1991-92 season.</p>
        <p>On Torrey's recommendation, an inexperienced Maloney, then the assistant general manager, was promoted to take Torrey's place.</p>
        <p>"The second time around, that not having worked out, we determined that we had a responsibility to this franchise and to our fans to conduct a search that  would be spearheaded by Al," Robert Rosenthal, the Islanders' co-chairman and co-chief executive officer, said. "We determined that the two best candidates available were within the franchise. And that was Mike and Darcy."</p>
        <p>Regier will handle most of the contractual negotiations for Milbury (who will also hire another assistant coach) as well as continue to oversee the scouting operation. Milbury added that Regier would also have the power to make trades, as Milbury did when he was the assistant general manager under Harry Sinden in Boston.</p>
        <p>"I think you're going to see an expanded role," said Regier. "It does not make up for the disappointment. But, on the other hand, it is an opportunity."</p>
        <p>There was a question if Arbour, an old-school hockey man, would recommend Milbury considering that the old school says that it is impossible for your coach to also be your general manager. In fact, Arbour did not endorse either candidate, said Palleschi, leaving the decision up to the management committee.</p>
        <p>"I would have reservations if Darcy wasn't here," said Arbour.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
