<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Players Making Debuts Give U.S. a Youth Movement</title>
    <meta content="17SOCC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1441517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="SOCCER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">El Salvador</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yannis, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/El Salvador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Soccer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/El Salvador</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Soccer</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021117T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500E6DE1030F934A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Players Making Debuts Give U.S. a Youth Movement</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY ALEX YANNIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yannis, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US national team will use 10 new players in game against El Salvador to assess talent (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With international competition months away, Coach Bruce Arena of the United States national team will assess several new players today against El Salvador in Washington.</p>
        <p>In the game at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium, Arena plans to use 10 players who have never played for the United States. Twelve American players are under the age of 25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With international competition months away, Coach Bruce Arena of the United States national team will assess several new players today against El Salvador in Washington.</p>
        <p>In the game at Robert F. Kennedy Stadium, Arena plans to use 10 players who have never played for the United States. Twelve American players are under the age of 25.</p>
        <p>The exhibition game is the first for the Americans since the World Cup in South Korea and Japan last June. Arena wants another game in January and two in February before other competition in the spring to prepare the Americans for the Confederations Cup in France and the Gold Cup in the United States in the summer.</p>
        <p>''We expect a pro-El Salvador crowd, and this will be a good experience for the players who are here for the first time,'' Arena said. ''We have a chance to see the potential of these players under pressure at the international level.''</p>
        <p>The new generation of players is expected to compete for the World Cup in 2006 in Germany and beyond.</p>
        <p>''Every one who is here belongs here,'' said Arena, who has worked with this group for the last two weeks. ''The bottom line, though, will be how these guys perform in games over the next year.''</p>
        <p>With European players in the middle of their season, a number of stars from Major League Soccer in need of rest and others past their prime for the next World Cup, Arena is calling on the M.L.S.'s top young players. Among those who may emerge are Taylor Twellman, who scored 23 goals in his rookie season with New England, and Eddie Robinson, a promising center back for San Jose.</p>
        <p>Landon Donovan, Clint Mathis, DaMarcus Beasley and Pablo Mastroeni are the only players on today's roster that reached the World Cup quarterfinals last June.</p>
        <p>Mathis played sporadically in the World Cup for what appeared to be lack of fitness. With his poor performances for the MetroStars behind him, he is determined to be an integral part of the national team.</p>
        <p>Donovan, Mathis and Mastroeni are expected to see plenty of action today. Beasley has been bothered by a sore knee and may not play.</p>
        <p>The Americans have dominated the series against El Salvador with eight victories, one loss and four ties. Their only loss came 10 years ago.</p>
        <p>The Salvadorans might be thankful for the absence of Joe-Max Moore and Brian McBride, who have six and five goals, respectively, against them.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
