<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Infiniti's G20: Luxury at the Entry Level</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="616595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT CARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NISSAN MOTOR CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INFINITI DIVISION OF NISSAN MOTOR CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHUON, MARSHALL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D91E3CF933A15755C0A965958260" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Infiniti's G20: Luxury at the Entry Level</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marshall Schuon</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHUON, MARSHALL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT must be tough to be an automotive-product planner.</p>
        <p>Sure, you have an easy day when the boss comes by and tells you to whip up a fantastic sports car. Or a utility vehicle. Or even a new station wagon. But what do you do if you work for a luxury line and you have to invent an "entry-level" car?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT must be tough to be an automotive-product planner.</p>
        <p>Sure, you have an easy day when the boss comes by and tells you to whip up a fantastic sports car. Or a utility vehicle. Or even a new station wagon. But what do you do if you work for a luxury line and you have to invent an "entry-level" car?</p>
        <p>If the company is Nissan and the line is Infiniti, you find your crayons and sketch out a four-door G20. You make it somewhat round and somewhat quiet and you borrow a four-cylinder engine from a Nissan Sentra.</p>
        <p>You outline a snub nose to create a cab-forward look that gives you a lot of passenger space in a small car. At the other end, you hide a fairly sizable trunk. You use the soft gray crayon for the leather interior.</p>
        <p>And, this being luxury land, you color the sticker light green, making it something on the order of $20,450.</p>
        <p>Later, the boss looks in to say that the creation has all the sex appeal of Ma Kettle on a down day. So you point out the things that he's missing. See here, where you've penciled in comfort? And amazing aerodynamics, with that very low .30 coefficient of drag? See?</p>
        <p>Yeah, but it's tough.</p>
        <p>The new G20 from Infiniti is a car that turns no heads. It is almost nondescript. But it certainly is comfortable and agile and civilized and easy to live with.</p>
        <p>Infiniti's designers actually cooked up their version of a front-wheel-drive baby boomer two years ago, but the car has been refined for 1993. And, with the new Q45 at the top of the line and the J30 "personal luxury sedan" in the middle, the soup seems to be simmering nicely.</p>
        <p>It is alphabet soup to be sure, and that may be another reason why the G20 initially seems so bland. The name and the image are hard to pick from the crowd, but they turn out to be well worth the picking.</p>
        <p>Outside, there are body-colored bumpers and six-spoked alloy wheels. Flush glass and narrow halogen headlights help reduce wind noise. The cab-forward design cuts down on front overhang but extends the wheelbase, allowing the car to seat five adults in reasonably uncrowded fashion.</p>
        <p>Inside, there are standard dual air bags and pre-tensioners that tighten the seat belts if there is a crash. Adjustable head restraints have also been added for safety in the rear seat.</p>
        <p>Occupants back there also have a surprising amount of leg room in a car whose overall length is only about 14.6 feet. The trunk, too, offers decent space, and it can swallow more than 14 cubic feet of cargo, all easy to load since the opening is at bumper level.</p>
        <p>Up front, the eminently adjustable buckets flank a padded console bin, and the driver is presented with a four-spoked and leather-wrapped wheel, whose tiny and hard-to-find horn buttons are one of the few complaints that one can make.</p>
        <p>Gauges, on the other hand, are easy to read, with white numerals on black dials, and a 130-mile-an-hour speedometer is complemented by a 9,000-r.p.m. tachometer.</p>
        <p>The usual power fripperies abound, and there are other neat features, too, like the standard compact-disk player below the radio. A tape cassette player is built into the tuner itself, and the system's amplifier delivers a whopping 160 watts to six speakers.</p>
        <p>The test car was painted silver, which made a nice contrast with the blackout trim. The car also had the primary option package, which included power controls for the front seats, leather, a flip-and-slide sun roof and a remote entry system that works with a push button on the key fob.</p>
        <p>That package added $2,000 to the cost, and the sticker's bottom line said $22,900, including a $450 destination charge. The only other available option is a new electronically controlled four-speed automatic transmission, which adds $950 to the price.</p>
        <p>The tester had the standard five-speed manual, a good choice both for economy and for fun-to-drive performance. Consumption with the stick shift is rated at 24 miles per gallon in the city, and 32 highway. With the automatic, the figures are 22 and 29.</p>
        <p>Either way, range is good, because the tank holds 16 gallons of regular unleaded. And either way, too, you get a very smooth and very slick little car with antilock brakes and a 140-horsepower engine that is more than sufficient in a vehicle that weighs only 2,877 pounds.</p>
        <p>What you don't get is a car that produces instant wows. But the most recent figures for the G20 show that last month's sales were up 8.3 percent. So somebody must be noticing. The Quality Is Getting Better</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, luxury cars have the fewest defects when they roll off the assembly line, but almost all of today's vehicles are improving in quality, according to the latest study by J. D. Power &amp; Associates of California.</p>
        <p>The consulting firm's 1993 initial quality survey, based on responses from more than 33,000 new owners, examined defects in 12 key problem areas. The result, measured in problems per 100 cars, showed significant improvement over all previous years.</p>
        <p>"In fact," the study said, "48 car models and 6 mini-vans and pickups joined the once-exclusive 'Under-100 Club,' meaning they had fewer than 100 problems for 100 cars. Of the cars, 22 were Japanese, 22 were domestic and 4 were European."</p>
        <p>According to the study, conducted annually since 1987, Toyota, Honda and Nissan have shown consistent initial quality, but other companies are catching up.</p>
        <p>The areas surveyed are wind noise, water leaks, squeaks and rattles, steering and handling, engine, transmission, brakes, temperature control, electrical, interior, and paint and body.</p>
        <p>In the latest study, the industry average for defects per 100 cars was 107, considerably better than last year's average of 125.</p>
        <p>These were the top 10 makes and their scores in the new survey: Lexus, 66; Toyota, 74; Infiniti, 78; Lincoln, 89; Acura, 89; Honda, 92; Nissan, 95; Buick, 95; Mercedes, 95, and Saturn, 96.</p>
        <p>ABOUT CARS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
