<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Darryl Must Keep His Eye on Ball</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="770058"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COCAINE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOL ABUSE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, CLAIRE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STRAWBERRY, DARRYL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcohol Abuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D6163AF933A15755C0A963958260" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Darryl Must Keep His Eye on Ball</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, CLAIRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YEARS after departing New York, Darryl Strawberry has chosen to describe his experiences with the Mets as baseball's version of a Roman orgy.</p>
        <p>Now Strawberry, once a Mets superstar and as of yesterday a Yankees reclamation project, is returning to the original scene of the crimes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YEARS after departing New York, Darryl Strawberry has chosen to describe his experiences with the Mets as baseball's version of a Roman orgy.</p>
        <p>Now Strawberry, once a Mets superstar and as of yesterday a Yankees reclamation project, is returning to the original scene of the crimes.</p>
        <p>After a 60-day suspension for substance abuse ends Sunday and then some time for a warm-up in the minors, he will be eligible to play baseball again for a city he claims once drew so many young Mets, Dwight Gooden and himself included, to the flame.</p>
        <p>Strawberry's history of cocaine and alcohol addiction, spousal abuse and brushes with the law is coming with him. Now it is up to the Yankees, who signed him to a one-year contract yesterday, to figure out the last Straw to stir a drink in this town.</p>
        <p>Which Darryl will show when the Yankees call him up from their Tampa, Fla., complex? The hitter whose approach to the plate assured no bathroom or refrigerator breaks by the viewing public? Or the one whose personal relapses make his life, not his baseball career, the most endangered element of his being?</p>
        <p>Darryl is back. But is his return a move of pure folly?</p>
        <p>Not necessarily, according to Dr. Allan Lans, the director of the Mets' employee assistance program who was the associate director of the Smithers Center, where Strawberry and Gooden were treated for addictions when with the Mets.</p>
        <p>According to Strawberry's onetime confidant and psychiatrist, the worst mistake the outfielder made was to leave New York in the first place.</p>
        <p>"The treatment he was getting here was working," said Lans, who is now the director of psychiatry with the Kirby Forensics Hospital Center.</p>
        <p>"The year he came out of Smithers was one of his best in baseball," he said, referring to the 1990 season, his last in New York, when Strawberry drove in 108 runs.</p>
        <p>When Strawberry joined the Dodgers as a free agent in 1991, "his head got turned around," Lans said. "He didn't keep his eye on the ball."</p>
        <p>It is not necessarily wrongheaded to wonder about Darryl's latest choice of where to work while healing, Lans said. "But Darryl has never run away from anything," he added. "He doesn't blink very much. And while New York can be a tough place, it's also a place where people have gotten healthy."</p>
        <p>And Strawberry can, Lans believes, if he does what the doctor would order: "First, attend to your family. Second, attend to your treatment. Third, play your game."</p>
        <p>It never has been in Darryl's nature to crawl before he could walk, or walk before he could strut. Strawberry isn't even eligible to play until Sunday, when his 60-day suspension for violation of baseball's substance-abuse policies ends. Still, Strawberry was being quoted before he signed as saying he wanted to come back to New York to tend to unfinished business, to prove some things to the nonbelievers.</p>
        <p>"I don't think that's the right approach," Lans said. "Your job here is to play baseball. Proving is something else. Play for your family. Play for yourself. That's proof enough. The fans, they're with you if you play. They just want to see you produce."</p>
        <p>Strawberry always had the talent to do so, but also had a laundry list of reasons why he did not. He was one of the noted members of that generation of rich ballplayer/celebrities not to initially be counseled on how to handle their millions. Instead they reveled in, then fell victim to their excesses.</p>
        <p>Lans says he and Frank Cashen, the former Mets general manager, knew that young men with millions but without proper educational support was a bad mix.</p>
        <p>"But it was a losing battle -- because of agents, management, the union -- people who always feel they know better," Lans said. "It was all avoidable, if it was taken on early enough, hard enough, seriously enough."</p>
        <p>Ten, 12 years later, baseball's dirty little secrets about alcohol, cocaine, spousal abuse etc., are out. And management and the union are working at the entry level to the majors to help kids deal with all that major league life entails. They're also obviously willing to keep working with Darryl.</p>
        <p>"Do I think it will take a miracle?" Lans said. "No. I just think it will take plain, hard work."</p>
        <p>And a Darryl Strawberry just keeping his eye on the ball this most crucial time -- not in baseball -- but in his life.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
