<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NORWAY IS PLANNING TO RESUME WHALING DESPITE WORLD BAN</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="539759"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, COMMERCIAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WHALES AND WHALING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDANGERED AND EXTINCT SPECIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NORWAY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ICELAND</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL WHALING COMMISSION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GREENPEACE (ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iceland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Iceland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Norway</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Commercial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Whales and Whaling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DD1E3EF933A05755C0A964958260" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NORWAY IS PLANNING TO RESUME WHALING DESPITE WORLD BAN</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, June 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The six-year-old international moratorium on commercial whaling began to crumble today, with both Norway and Iceland declaring that some species had been so well protected that they could be hunted again without danger of extinction.</p>
        <p>Norway announced that it would resume commercial exploitation of minke whales next year, and Iceland left the International Whaling Commission, saying that it had been taken over by a "rabid" minority against whale hunting even though scientific fact no longer supported the prohibition.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The six-year-old international moratorium on commercial whaling began to crumble today, with both Norway and Iceland declaring that some species had been so well protected that they could be hunted again without danger of extinction.</p>
        <p>Norway announced that it would resume commercial exploitation of minke whales next year, and Iceland left the International Whaling Commission, saying that it had been taken over by a "rabid" minority against whale hunting even though scientific fact no longer supported the prohibition.</p>
        <p>Japan, which has staunchly opposed the ban since it was imposed, has also sought permission to hunt minke whales, which grow to lengths of 20 to 25 feet, weigh 8 to 10 tons at maturity, and live in all the world's oceans. Japan did not say today whether it would follow Norway's lead despite the ban. Greenpeace Denounces Move</p>
        <p>The Norwegian announcement set off vigorous protests by environmental groups as well as other European governments.</p>
        <p>Greenpeace International denounced the Norwegian step as "a declaration of intent to go pirate whaling," and the British Minister for Agriculture, John Gummer, said he hoped Norway would not go through with an unsanctioned resumption.</p>
        <p>"I am sure Norway will not do it in the end because it is far too civilized," he said in Glasgow, Scotland, where a meeting of the 37-nation commission began today.  Some Caught for 'Research'</p>
        <p>The Norwegian Prime Minister, Gro Harlem Brundtland, defended the decision to resume hunting of Minke whales "on the basis of scientific knowledge on the development of stocks." Iceland's representative on the whaling commission, Gudmundur Eriksson, said in a parting statement today that the body had been structured "in such a way that a rabid minority can determine the trend of the commission as a whole."</p>
        <p>" 'Save the Whale' is an antiquated demand," he said.</p>
        <p>Minke whales are not generally considered endangered. The Norwegian Government statement said the International Whaling Commission's scientific committee had concluded unanimously a few days ago that there were 86,700 of them in the waters of the northeastern Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Other estimates are that there may be as many as 750,000 in southern oceans. The commission has been permitting limited numbers of them to be caught for "research" purposes, and is expected to decide on a new method of setting such quotas later this week that would allow them to be revised upward.</p>
        <p>As many as 70,000 whales a year may have been caught and used for meat, margarine, candles and cosmetics at the height of commercial whaling in the 1960's, and some species, like the much larger 130-ton blue whale, went into rapid decline, with perhaps fewer than 1,000 in the Southern Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>Iceland sold whales to the Japanese for $3,500 per ton in 1989, the last year for which figures were available from the Fisheries Agency in Japan.</p>
        <p>The Norwegian step was welcomed by the tiny coastal villages that used to depend on whaling for their livelihoods, but vigorously condemned by environmental groups that believe that whalers and scientists have always overestimated the numbers of whales, and by people who believe all whaling is ethically and morally objectionable.</p>
        <p>The announcement in Oslo said Norway would remain within the commission. If the international group revises its "management procedure" on setting catch limits for minkes this week, it said, Norway will use the new information to set its quota for commercial harvesting. If the commission does not act, Norway will use the commission's scientific data to set the quota, the announcement said.</p>
        <p>In advance of the meeting in Glasgow this week, European television screens have been full of grisly scenes of leviathans hunted by exploding harpoons, the sea turning red with their blood, their blubber cruelly flensed by scythelike instruments on decks glistening with gore.</p>
        <p>In Britain, Norway's decision seems bound to be unpopular. According to a survey made public by the Royal Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals survey today, 89 percent of the people questioned were more concerned about the future of whales and dolphins than of any other creatures.</p>
        <p>"We who so few years ago seemed set on destroying whole species of whales forever must realize that the world will not allow us to risk a return to the barbarity of the past," Mr. Gummer said.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the World Wildlife Fund, Cassandra Phillips, attacked the Norwegian decision on minke whales on scientific ground.</p>
        <p>"Even assuming the numbers quoted by Norway for this stock are correct, they still justify classification as a protected stock under current International Whaling Commission procedures," she said. "Given the tragic history of over-exploitation and over-estimation of whales remaining, it is essential that we err on the side of caution and the whales and maintain the protection of these whales." Emotions vs. Numbers</p>
        <p>But in a world where millions of people have come to think of whales as big, gentle relatives in the sea -- thanks to excursions to see whales, recordings of their songs, and books, films and television series by Jacques Cousteau -- emotions also play a role, despite the dry numbers purporting to show that tuna fish may be more endangered than some whales.</p>
        <p>" 'Animal rights' lobbyists, or at least their public supporters (and financiers), attach much greater 'value' to a whale or a seal than to a tuna or a cod," wrote D. S. Butterworth, a South African scientist, in the June 18 issue of Nature magazine. "The time seems overdue for scientists to speak out against the near-farcical pronouncements of some international organizations regarding endangered species."</p>
        <p>Mr. Butterworth suggested that the scientific considerations for setting catch limits for whaling might be undermined by sentimentality.</p>
        <p>Norway, which announced in December that it would catch 110 whales this year and 136 in 1993 and 1994 for research purposes, is not expected to go back to anything like the former scale.  A spokesman for the Foreign Ministry said the whaling "industry" in Norway employed only a few hundred people, though larger numbers of people depended on it indirectly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
