<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Images in fall fashion magazines take a break from daydreams for a little reality check.</title>
    <meta content="Y20ADC$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1040337"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Elle (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Marie Claire (Magazine)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Vogue (Magazine)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980820T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7DC123DF933A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="896" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Images in fall fashion magazines take a break from daydreams for a little reality check.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jennifer Steinhauer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fashion advertising in some September issues of fashion magazines shows signs that images of fantasy is shifting to images of reality; some trendlets in issues of Elle, Marie Claire and Vogue discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IS high fashion trying to speak to the masses? Flip through the September issues of fashion magazines, and there appears to be a subtle shift in the sensibility of fashion advertisers this fall season.</p>
        <p>Fashion advertising -- especially in the all-important fall season, a sort of Christmas for publishers of such magazines -- has almost exclusively used images of fantasy. But there are signs that fashion is trying to add a little realism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IS high fashion trying to speak to the masses? Flip through the September issues of fashion magazines, and there appears to be a subtle shift in the sensibility of fashion advertisers this fall season.</p>
        <p>Fashion advertising -- especially in the all-important fall season, a sort of Christmas for publishers of such magazines -- has almost exclusively used images of fantasy. But there are signs that fashion is trying to add a little realism.</p>
        <p>Here are a few trendlets noted in advertisements in the September issues of Elle, Marie Claire and Vogue:</p>
        <p>REAL PEOPLE -- The most obvious way to connect a product to its potential buyer is to show people who look as if they might actually use it. While this theory works for soap and soda, fashion has rarely bought into it. The idea instead is generally to create a world where an 87-pound woman appears to be mildly distressed by the great many men who pursue her in her high-end dress.</p>
        <p>But this season, real women populate the ads. Anne Klein's campaign features a dancer, venture capitalist, radiologist and mother among other women who do not model professionally. The fall Dockers campaign for Levi Strauss &amp; Company relies on women in film, like the actress Rosie Perez, and an advertisement for Timex watches features the faces of three sisters. Donna Karan's fall campaign uses professional models, but one of them is older than 40 and no longer works regularly. The press release for Calvin Klein's new ad for a men's fragrance boasts that the model is a father of three and hints that the fact he is drop-dead gorgeous and pitches in at home makes him, to use Mr. Klein's favorite buzzword, very ''modern.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, Mr. Klein pioneered the reality effect with his earlier advertisements that featured unscrubbed, anti-model characters.</p>
        <p>''When you put a model, a fantasy and fashion all together, it can get to be too overpowering,'' said Tom Julian, a trend analyst for Fallon McElligott's New York office. ''The fashion industry has started to realize that if you make fashion acceptable on all levels, you get more people to buy in.''</p>
        <p>BLACK AND WHITE ALL OVER -- There are so many black-and-white advertisements in the fall magazines they almost resemble newspapers. In the 568 pages of Elle, 26 fashion houses use black-and-white photography for their fall campaigns, or nearly half the fashion ads. From Calvin Klein to Halston to Gucci to Eileen Fisher, the color of newsprint is throughout.</p>
        <p>True, fall's dark palette -- grays, dark greens and beige -- lends itself to black and white. But many of these ads resemble a documentary. The photos tie together a narrative seemingly plucked from real life, as in the Ralph Lauren advertisements for the Romance fragrance line, which features four distinct images of a couple falling in love.</p>
        <p>''Black and white does seem to be the color of the moment in fashion ads,'' said Donny Deutsch, chairman and chief executive of Deutsch Inc. in New York. ''Black and white stand for reality, which is ironic because life of course is not in black and white.''</p>
        <p>BABY AS ACCESSORY -- Fashion rarely evokes family life: sippy cups, bath time and play dates are hardly the stuff of a Seventh Avenue fantasy. This season, however, it seems that babies are as important as the right handbag. Elle, Vogue and Marie Claire all feature cute babies in their fashion editorial pages, egged on, its seems, by Isaac Mizrahi, who recently featured rain slickers and evening gowns with matching baby carriers in his collection.</p>
        <p>Marin Hopper, Elle's fashion director, said her magazine's decision to run an entire photo feature titled ''Insouciant au pair'' was inspired by current fashion trends and baby adoration among her readers. ''There was a feeling this fall in fashion that was very schoolgirl-like, a fresh innocence, from pleated skirts to flat shoes,'' Ms. Hopper said.</p>
        <p>''But there is also a sort of intimacy that is very in for fall, and babies connect up with that. Baby boomers are still having babies, and fashion is sort of returning to family values, with all its hope for the future and good feelings.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Julian of Fallon McElligott said: ''In the 80's, it was the dog. In the 90's, it is the wedding ring and the children. It makes a customer think, 'Oh, this fits into my life.' There is a certain reality factor there, and it's good.''</p>
        <p>Of course, there are only so many reality factors that a reader of fashion magazines can take. A Bergdorf Goodman advertisement features a woman in a Guy Laroche dress and coat walking a llama down a Manhattan sidewalk. ''We wanted to position ourselves as a little less serious,'' said Michael Calman, senior vice president of marketing for the retailer, a unit of the Neiman Marcus Group. ''We want to show we can appeal to a younger audience, and that is generally not how we are perceived.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
