<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="14CLAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19971115T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="972814"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EED81738F937A25752C1A961958260" item-length="2363" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times or by contributors of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in New York City.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''DON GIOVANNI,'' Metropolitan Opera. Franco Zeffirelli's monumental and lumbering 1990 production of Mozart's opera may need more star power and focus than it gets here to give it any lift at all. Dwayne Croft sang handsomely in the title role on opening night without quite dominating the stage, and Maria Bayo was splendid in the lesser role of Zerlina. Perhaps the conductor, Daniel Beckwith, has at least pulled the uneven troops together by now. Tonight at 8, Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000. Tickets: $25 to $150 (James R. Oestreich).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times or by contributors of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in New York City.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''DON GIOVANNI,'' Metropolitan Opera. Franco Zeffirelli's monumental and lumbering 1990 production of Mozart's opera may need more star power and focus than it gets here to give it any lift at all. Dwayne Croft sang handsomely in the title role on opening night without quite dominating the stage, and Maria Bayo was splendid in the lesser role of Zerlina. Perhaps the conductor, Daniel Beckwith, has at least pulled the uneven troops together by now. Tonight at 8, Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000. Tickets: $25 to $150 (James R. Oestreich).</p>
        <p>HO LO TAIWANESE OPERA TROUPE. The Taipei Theater continues its splendid celebration of Chinese opera with a group well remembered from an appearance here five years ago. The company, which specializes in Taiwanese opera, a tradition less ancient than other forms of Chinese opera, presents ''Justice in Disguise,'' a satire on corruption among government officials. Tonight and tomorrow at 7:30 P.M. and Sunday at 2 P.M., Taipei Theater, 1221 Avenue of the Americas, at 49th Street, Manhattan, (212) 373-1850 or (212) 307-7171. Tickets: $15; $10, students and the elderly (Oestreich).  ''LA BOHEME,'' New York City Opera. For people who want a break from the Met's gargantuan Franco Zeffirelli production of Puccini's most popular opera, the City Opera production by Graziella Sciutti usually fits the bill. The sets are handsome and human-scale and the cast is, almost always young and eager, making the Left Bank bohemians, for once, look like they are supposed to: lean, hungry and romantic. The cast this time includes Ana Maria Martinez as Mimi, Jianyi Zhang as Rodolfo, Robert Perry as Marcello, and Abbie Furmansky as Musetta. The musicianly George Manahan conducts. Tomorrow at 8 P.M., New York State Theater, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $20 to $85 (Anthony Tommasini).  ''MARCO POLO,'' New York City Opera. The story of Marco Polo's journey from Venice to China has been fashioned into an opera of beauty and power by the Chinese composer Tan Dun and given its United States premiere by City Opera. The libretto by Paul Griffiths, a critic for The New York Times, is determinedly nonlinear and echoes the vocal techniques of Chinese opera, which make sounds and patterns of sound as important as the pronunciation of words. Mr. Tan's music is eclectic, borrowing styles from Venetian, Indian, Tibetan and Chinese music. Indian and Chinese instruments are highlighted onstage.</p>
        <p>Martha Clarke directs; the composer conducts. The cast includes Laura Tucker, Christine Abraham, Susan Botti, Adam Klein, Chen  Shi-Zheng and Stephen Bryant. Tomorrow at 8 P.M., New York State Theater, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $15 to $85 (Patrick J. Smith).</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>''IL CAFFE D'AMORE.'' When it was directed by the enterprising musicologist Paul C. Echols, the Mannes Camerata presented a string of fascinating productions that mixed period instrument performance with modern staging techniques. Often, these student presentations would use an ancient poem as a kind of plot, with medieval songs interpolated to create an operatic pageant. Since Echols's death in 1994, Grant C. Herried, a lutenist and singer who performed in many of Echols's productions, has taken up the reins of the Camerata and continued in the same spirit. His first production of the season, ''Il Caffe d'Amore,'' draws parallels between the social and sexual mores that prevailed in Milan in the early 1600's and those of the 1990's. Its centerpiece is Luigi Rossi's pastoral cantata ''Noi Siam Tre Donzellette Semplicette,'' but the score also includes bawdy (or at least suggestive) vocal works by Monteverdi, Frescobaldi, Merula and other early-17th-century Italian composers. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 8 P.M., and Sunday at 4 P.M., West Park Church, 86th Street at Amsterdam Avenue, Manhattan, (212) 580-0210, ext. 228. Tickets: $20 (Allan Kozinn)  NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC. Messiaen's ''Ascension'' is a solemn and sonorous but also exhilarating meditation on Christ's return to heaven, aptly complemented here by a piece of French program music from a century before: the wildly enhanced autobiography that Berlioz called his ''Symphonie Fantastique.'' Today at 2 P.M.; tomorrow at 8 P.M. Program repeats Tuesday at 7:30 P.M., Avery Fisher Hall, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $16 to $70. (Paul Griffiths)  NATIONAL SYMPHONY ORCHESTRA. Leonard Slatkin and the National Symphony opened their beautifully renovated home in the Kennedy Center last month, trailing accolades from a European tour. The actual performances, with the players still adjusting to new acoustics, were less grand, but perhaps the group thrives under the pressure of touring. The two evening programs here, and a family matinee that more or less combines them, share a theme of childhood and may tell more about the orchestra's condition. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 P.M., and tomorrow at 2 P.M., Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800. Tickets: $17 to $65 (tonight), $16 to $60 (tomorrow night), $5 (afternoon). (Oestreich)  NATHALIE STUTZMANN. This French contralto has built a strong American following with a series of RCA recordings that capture thoughtful interpretations couched in a dark, silken tone. Her concert performances in New York, including an impressive debut recital at the Walter Reade Theater in 1995, have shown her to be a charismatic stage presence as well, with an ear for seductive coloration. All those qualities bode well for the songs by Schubert, Brahms, Chausson and Poulenc that she has chosen for her recital with Inger Sodergren, a Swedish pianist who has been her collaborator for several years and who has also made several highly regarded solo recordings. Tonight at 8, Weill Recital Hall, (212) 247-7800. Tickets: $30. (Kozinn)  SONIC BOOM FESTIVAL: REMEMBERING CONLON NANCARROW. The late American composer devoted most of his creative life to studies for player piano, but he also set out some of his humor and rhythmic dazzlement for human musicians to perform. This program includes all these live pieces. Tomorrow at 8 P.M. Miller Theater, Columbia University, Broadway at 116th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 854-7799. Tickets: $10; $5, students and the elderly. (Griffiths)  JANOS STARKER. Perhaps ''The Indestructible Bach'' is not an ideal name for a concert series: It half implies a demolition derby, with the musicians trying to dismantle the old master. But the 92d Street Y has assembled an estimable roster for the series, and in the second of its four installments Janos Starker is offering the first three Suites for Unaccompanied Cello. Mr. Starker has recorded all six suites several times, including twice within the last dozen years. The latest of these traversals, released by RCA a few months ago, is fresh and energetic, and if it represents Mr. Starker's current thoughts on these extraordinary works, his concert should be enlightening. Tomorrow at 8 P.M., 92d Street Y, Lexington Avenue at 92d Street, (212) 996-1100. Tickets: $35. (Kozinn)  MASTERS OF INDIAN MUSIC. The World Music Institute presents just about every exotic style that musical man has devised, but Indian music has always had a special place among its offerings. This year the organization has already presented several examples of India's various ancient traditions and the current installment of its series brings together two virtuoso performers of different generations. Ali Akbar Khan, 75, is a master of the sarod, a fretless stringed instrument that is somewhat less ornate than the sitar but equally eloquent in far-ranging improvisations. Zakir Hussain, 40, has in the last decade become one of the most widely traveled performers on the tabla, an Indian drum that, in the right hands, is flexible enough to be an equal partner in a dialogue with the sitar, sarod or voice. Tomorrow at 8 P.M., Town Hall, 123 West 43d Street, Manhattan, (212) 840-2824. Tickets: $30 to $40. (Kozinn)  SARAH CHANG. Can it be that Sarah Chang is still only 16, as Carnegie Hall's publicity materials insistently point out? She already seems a seasoned veteran, and her age is the least of her selling points. It should be fascinating to see what personal maturity can add to her already compelling musical gifts, and perhaps some of that will begin to show in the varied program here, with Charles Abramovic as pianist. Sunday afternoon at 2, Carnegie Hall, (212) 247-7800. Tickets: $15 to $45. (Oestreich)  CATHERINE MALFITANO. For some years, the American soprano Catherine Malfitano, who began her career singing the lighter lyric repertory, has been taking on weighty dramatic roles like Tosca, even Salome. There has been a sacrifice in terms of vocal elegance, but she is an impassioned and intelligent singer. Her New York recital debut should reveal more intimately the current quality of her voice and artistry. The interesting program includes music by Rodrigo, Barber, Satie, Poulenc, Bolcom and Weill. Sunday at 2 P.M., Alice Tully Hall, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $35. (Tommasini)  CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY. The Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center plays two of the repertory's more famous and heavily populated ensemble pieces, both for strings and winds. Beethoven's early Septet did a lot to win his reputation across Europe. Schubert's long and heavenly Octet represents the great man at his best. The Society's familiar cast of  characters will be there to play. The musicians include David Shifrin, clarinetist; Joseph Silverstein, violinist, and Robert Rouch, horn player. Sunday at 5 P.M., Alice Tully Hall, (212) 875-5788. Tickets: $25 and $35. The program repeats on Tuesday at 7:30 P.M. (Bernard Holland)</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>AMERICAN BALLET THEATER. In the closing weekend of its New York winter season, Ballet Theater offers American dance classics by George Balanchine, Agnes de Mille and Jerome Robbins, and provocative dances by another generation of choreographers represented by Mark Morris and Clark Tippet. There will also be the chance to compare very different casts tonight and Sunday night in Balanchine's sparkling ''Theme and Variations'' (Julie Kent and Guillaume Graffin, and Amanda McKerrow and Ethan Stiefel) and tomorrow and Sunday night, in the roles of Lizzie Borden and the man she loves from afar in de Mille's ''Fall River Legend'' (Susan Jaffe and Robert Hill, and Alessandra Ferri and Victor Barbee). Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8 P.M., and Sunday at 2 and 7:30 P.M., City Center, 131 West 55th Street, Manhattan, (212) 581-1212, Tickets: $30 to $55 (Jennifer Dunning).  DANCE WOMEN/LIVING LEGENDS. The founders of five distinguished American modern dance companies will be honored at three theaters in the best way possible, with performances by their companies in a wide-ranging repertory of vivid dances. Works by Assadata Dafora, Donald McKayle, Lula Washington, Milton Myers, Elisa Monte, Gene Hill Sagan and Talley Beatty will be danced in Program A. Program B features choreography by Dwight Rhoden, Lula Washington, Ronald K. Brown, David Parsons and George Faison. The companies are Jeraldyne Blunden's Dayton Contemporary Dance Company, Joan Myers Brown's Philadanco, Cleo Parker Robinson's Dance Company, Lula Washington's Dance Theater and Ann Williams' Dallas Black Dance Company. Tonight at 8 (Program A) at 651, An Arts Center, 651 Fulton Street, Fort Greene, Brooklyn, (718-636-4181); tomorrow at 2 and 8 P.M. (Program B) at Aaron Davis Hall at City College, West 135th St. and Convent Avenue, (212) 650-6900), and Sunday at 3 P.M. (Program B) at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center, One Center St., Newark, (888) 466-5722). Tickets: $10 to $29 (Dunning).  GROUPE AFRIC AZOLOU D'ABIDJAN. A multimedia collaboration by artists from Ivory Coast, Brazil and the United States, ''Elegba Crossings: A Spiritual Journey'' tells the story of an African-born family through 400 years. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 P.M., Sunday at 2 P.M. TriBeCa Performing Arts Center, 199 Chambers St., (212) 346-8510. Tickets: $20 (Dunning).  LIMON DANCE COMPANY. ''Missa Brevis,'' Jose Limon's heroically scaled tribute to human indomitability, will be danced in Riverside Church's impressive nave accompanied by two choirs and an organ. It shares the program with ''The Winged,'' Limon's evocation of birds in flight. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 3 P.M., Riverside Church, Riverside Drive at 120th Street, Morningside Heights, (212) 870-6784. Tickets: $20 (Anderson).  RUSSELL MALIPHANT. A British dancer and choreographer makes his New York debut with ''Unspoken,'' a duet created in collaboration with James DeMaria that combines strict formal structures with opportunities for fluid improvisations. Tonight and tomorrow at 8 P.M., Dance Theater Workshop, 219 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 924-0077. Tickets: $15 (Anderson).</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 15, 1997, Saturday</p>
        <p>A listing in the Classical Music and Dance Guide in Weekend yesterday about today's performance of ''Marco Polo'' by the New York City Opera at the New York State Theater misstated the performance time. It is 1:30 P.M., not 8.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 15, 1997, Saturday</p>
        <p>A listing in the Classical Music and Dance Guide in Weekend yesterday about today's performance of ''Marco Polo'' by the New York City Opera at the New York State Theater misstated the performance time. It is 1:30 P.M., not 8.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
