<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Race Is in South Dakota But Interest Is National</title>
    <meta content="02DAKO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/02/politics/02DAKO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1347873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Dakota</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ayres, B Drummond Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Tim (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daschle, Tom (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thune, John (Rep)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Sioux Falls (SD)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Senate</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Johnson, Tim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDF113DF931A35751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Race Is in South Dakota But Interest Is National</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">South Dakota Races Could Have National Impact</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By B. DRUMMOND AYRES Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ayres, B Drummond Jr</byline>
      <dateline>SIOUX FALLS, S.D., Nov. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Senate race in South Dakota in 2002 is expected to put state in political spotlight; incumbent Democrat Tim Johnson has received pledge of strong backing from Tom Daschle, state's senior senator and majority leader, while Republican challenger Rep John Thune is receiving similarly strong support from Pres Bush; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the surface, next year's race in South Dakota for the United States Senate appears clear-cut enough -- the incumbent, Tim Johnson, a mainline Democrat, faces a strong challenge from the state's sole House member, John Thune, a solidly conservative Republican.</p>
        <p>But the contest is much more than that.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The upcoming United States Senate race between Tim Johnson and John Thune could turn out to be a battle between President Bush and Senator Tom Daschle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the surface, next year's race in South Dakota for the United States Senate appears clear-cut enough -- the incumbent, Tim Johnson, a mainline Democrat, faces a strong challenge from the state's sole House member, John Thune, a solidly conservative Republican.</p>
        <p>But the contest is much more than that.</p>
        <p>Underneath it is a battle royal -- a proxy fight, really -- between President Bush, who has pledged strong backing for Mr. Thune, and South Dakota's senior senator, Tom Daschle, who has pledged strong backing for Mr. Johnson and can deliver it, because he also happens to be the Senate majority leader.</p>
        <p>Such a standoff ensures that plenty of national political attention will be focused on South Dakota next year. But there are other reasons to watch the state, too, because besides the Senate race, there will be a House race and a governor's race.</p>
        <p>In short, next year is shaping up as one of the most important election years ever in South Dakota, with a good possibility that the votes cast here in the Senate and House contests will be especially important in the overall national struggle for control of Congress.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush recruited Mr. Thune to take on Mr. Johnson and be one of several point men in next year's all-out Republican push to regain control of the Senate by picking off two Democratic seats. The president promised Mr. Thune White House and national party help, including money and staff, and over the next few weeks several top national Republican figures are scheduled to campaign here with Mr. Thune.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daschle has made Mr. Johnson's re-election (and by extension perhaps his own survival as majority leader) what he calls ''the most important political effort for me'' in 2002. Mr. Johnson has also been promised help from Washington.</p>
        <p>Independent pollsters have not taken a look at the contest. But polls taken by both candidates show a race too close to call.</p>
        <p>Independent analysts agree.</p>
        <p>Charles E. Cook Jr., editor of The Cook Political Report, calls the race a ''nail biter'' that could end up being ''one of the nation's most competitive contests.''</p>
        <p>Stuart Rothenberg of The Rothenberg Political Report says the closeness of the Thune-Johnson contest, along with the House and governor's races, both also expected to be close, could make South Dakota ''the single most interesting state in the 2002 elections.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson narrowly won election to the Senate six years ago, beating the veteran Republican incumbent, Larry Pressler, by two percentage points. Given that slim edge, Republicans say it is not politically unrealistic to believe Mr. Thune can take Mr. Johnson. They note that South Dakota, Mr. Johnson's 1996 victory notwithstanding, has a history, year in and year out, of voting Republican more often than Democratic -- witness Mr. Bush's 22-point victory margin here last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thune also has something else going for him. Though he is a member of the House, he is as well known in the state as Senator Johnson.</p>
        <p>With about 750,000 people, South Dakota is so lightly populated that it has only one Congressional district. That means Congressional candidates always run statewide, the same as candidates for senator and governor, and Mr. Thune has run three times.</p>
        <p>Almost certainly, the Johnson-Thune race, like most other Congressional races in 2002, will turn in good part on how much progress is made in the war on terror and how much the national economy recovers. In particular, the success of the proxy efforts by President Bush and Senator Daschle will be heavily governed by economic and national security issues. Beyond that, health care will surely be a major issue in the race, as it will be in other states. Because South Dakota is a big farm and ranching state, agriculture will be a major issue, too.</p>
        <p>For the moment, however, Mr. Thune's main campaign pitch emphasizes something else. Those who ask why they should vote for him and thereby vote to break up the Daschle-Johnson team are told what Mr. Thune said when he announced his candidacy: ''Consider this: Tom Daschle leading the Democrats in the Senate and John Thune working with him and the Republican leadership in Congress and with President Bush. South Dakota would be better positioned than ever before at the federal level.''</p>
        <p>Steve Hildebrand, Mr. Johnson's campaign manager and a veteran of many Democratic election battles, contends that his man will make political mincemeat of that argument and win re-election going away. But first things first, Mr. Hildebrand says, insisting that Mr. Johnson ''really hasn't been able to focus seriously on running yet because he's spending just about all of his time in Washington working on legislation for national security and the war on terror.''</p>
        <p>''It's kind of got things on a hold,'' Mr. Hildebrand said. ''But that's where the focus should be anyway.''</p>
        <p>The South Dakota House and governor's contests are not as fully developed as the Senate contest.</p>
        <p>In the House race -- the seat opened up when Representative Thune decided to run for Senate -- Mr. Pressler has declared himself a candidate for the Republican nomination, a move that former senators usually view as a political step down. Several other Republicans have also jumped in, but Mr. Pressler is given the edge over all of them.</p>
        <p>Gov. William J. Janklow, who under state law is not permitted to run for another term, is said to be thinking about joining the field too, a political move that would also be relatively rare for a former governor. If he does, with his popularity he would immediately become the leading Republican candidate. In the judgment of most political experts in the state, he would also be the favorite to win the general election in the fall, no matter which of half a dozen or so Democratic hopefuls is nominated.</p>
        <p>The race to succeed Governor Janklow is even more wide open.</p>
        <p>Of several Republicans thinking about running, Attorney General Mark Barnett is most often given the best chance of winning the nomination. But he has yet to formally announce that he is running.</p>
        <p>Among Democrats, Jim Abbott, the president of the University of South Dakota, has expressed an interest in running and is given a good shot at winning the nomination. But he, too, has not yet made his move.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abbott was unsuccessful in three earlier tries for elective office.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
