<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boyish Wonder</title>
    <meta content="02WLN1T" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="80" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/12/02/magazine/02ANDERSON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1347573"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Wes</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sella, Marshall</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Royal Tenenbaums, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Anderson, Wes</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7DA113AF931A35751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="3631" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boyish Wonder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Wes Anderson, Boyish Wonder</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marshall Sella</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sella, Marshall</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Marshall Sella profile of Wes Anderson, director whose latest film is The Royal Tenenbaums; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a white-sky November day, Wes Anderson is lounging in a darkened studio in the Brill Building, formerly the silvery hub of Tin Pan Alley. His slight six-foot frame, all 155 pounds of it, is decked out in undersize beige corduroys and an undersize beige shirt; his auburn hair, once unruly, has settled into a subtle and rather stylish alliance of tamed cowlicks. ''We're doing a weird little recording session,'' he quietly explains. ''Yesterday, our editor was whistling along with the soundtrack, and I thought, Wait -- that's good!''</p>
        <p>Anderson immediately realized that this was a perfect touch. It matched the sound in his head that, somehow, this crucial scene lacked. So, at this late stage in the editing process of his new movie, ''The Royal Tenenbaums'' -- and despite the fact that the Brill Building is teeming with musicians -- he has enlisted a ragtag assortment of crew members to lay down a whistling track, which will then be added to the score.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wes Anderson looks like a teenager, and his films are inspired by childhood memories. But there's nothing adolescent about him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a white-sky November day, Wes Anderson is lounging in a darkened studio in the Brill Building, formerly the silvery hub of Tin Pan Alley. His slight six-foot frame, all 155 pounds of it, is decked out in undersize beige corduroys and an undersize beige shirt; his auburn hair, once unruly, has settled into a subtle and rather stylish alliance of tamed cowlicks. ''We're doing a weird little recording session,'' he quietly explains. ''Yesterday, our editor was whistling along with the soundtrack, and I thought, Wait -- that's good!''</p>
        <p>Anderson immediately realized that this was a perfect touch. It matched the sound in his head that, somehow, this crucial scene lacked. So, at this late stage in the editing process of his new movie, ''The Royal Tenenbaums'' -- and despite the fact that the Brill Building is teeming with musicians -- he has enlisted a ragtag assortment of crew members to lay down a whistling track, which will then be added to the score.</p>
        <p>Dylan Tichenor, the editor of the film, steps up to the microphone first and blows out a shockingly off-key version of the melody. No one whistles well under pressure. Tichenor jokingly calls for a mimosa to loosen him up, but Anderson is not on terms with defeatism. ''No, no, that's really good,'' he keeps saying, albeit tentatively. ''Try it again, and leave a space for a bigger breath before the dramatic part. And do that Disney sound you were doing yesterday.''</p>
        <p>Listening to the soundtrack in headphones and staring up at a screen flickering with Gene Hackman's muted image, Tichenor tries seven more times, but his shower-and-household whistling talents have abandoned him. ''Try a few more runs -- they can adjust the pitch later,'' Anderson says.</p>
        <p>''I'm nervous, man,'' Tichenor jokes. ''My lips are shaking.''</p>
        <p>Even in these tense weeks of postproduction, Anderson doesn't seem to have a care in the world. ''It's important to remember that no one expects you to be a professional whistler,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Tichenor is unconvinced. But Anderson stands in front of him, backlit by the glow of the screen, and closes his eyes to listen. Tethered like an astronaut to his own headset console four feet away, he conducts his tuneless virtuoso with crisp, happy Mitch Miller gestures, each of which concludes with a swirly little flourish.</p>
        <p>''The Royal Tenenbaums,'' opening Dec. 14, is a tale of familial dysfunction, failure and redemption. But that rough description belies its peculiar sense of joy. The three children of Royal Tenenbaum (Hackman) and his wife, Etheline (Anjelica Huston), are child prodigies: a 12-year-old playwright, a tennis champ, a boy financial whiz. But two decades later, after the separation of their parents and other mishaps, their promises of glory have turned to dust. Royal, a charming but reprehensible lawyer, hasn't seen his family in years. The movie is set in a storybook New York and chronicles Royal's comical schemes to win back his place in the Tenenbaum clan. In the scene Anderson is now tweaking, Hackman plays for sympathy by announcing that he is terminally ill.</p>
        <p>Looking on as Anderson spryly conducts Tichenor's hapless performance, I'm reminded why the press sometimes treats the 32-year-old director like a nifty kid who happens to make swell movies. Judging from appearances alone, he's an easy mark. He addresses the world through clear-framed spectacles and with the diffidence of a grad student; he carries his credit cards bundled together by a rubber band. During the ''Rushmore'' shoot, one actor recalls, ''he would always have only half of his shirt tucked into his pants -- always. Only half. The other half would be hanging out casually.''</p>
        <p>Anderson may straddle the worlds of adulthood and childhood, but he's hardly a case of arrested development. His work is not the product of emotional immaturity; quite the opposite. The appeal of movies like ''Bottle Rocket'' and ''Rushmore'' (with its reverence for stamp collecting, Swiss Army knives and BB guns) comes from the fact that Anderson has retained a boy's way of conceptualizing the world -- but he conveys it with a sophistication that a boy could never articulate. By exercising meticulous control over his films' characters and structure, he recreates the fun and cruelty of youth in a lexicon that real adults have forgotten and real children have yet to acquire.</p>
        <p>The tone of elation in Anderson's movies relies in no small measure on the careful little touches -- something as seemingly minor as 23 seconds of whistling. Which makes this odd recording session anything but frivolous, despite Anderson's sunny sense of calm.</p>
        <p>''What ever happened to those old Disney whistlers?'' he muses. ''Weren't they great? Are there whistlers like that anymore?''</p>
        <p>One of the crew suggests that they try Meryl Streep; after all, she'll be in the building Monday to loop another film. ''I bet she could whistle,'' Anderson says wistfully. ''She certainly can belt out a song.''</p>
        <p>Inside a studio, Wes Anderson moves gingerly, like a man afraid to wake a sleeping child. But outside its shadowy confines, he is nimble. He arrives at his Upper East Side address late one night after another long day of editing, clambers up the stairs two at a time and enters his apartment. He sweeps past a giant ''Alphaville'' poster into the bathroom and begins brushing his teeth.</p>
        <p>I'd been warned about Anderson's living habits. James Caan, who played a pivotal role in ''Bottle Rocket,'' recalls that after the first day of shooting, he stopped up to see Anderson in his hotel room. ''I've never seen so much stuff in my entire life,'' Caan says. ''I looked around for Wes, and there he was, looking like a pinky in clothes. If you go to his house, bring a searchlight.''</p>
        <p>Anderson's place looks like a prop-storage warehouse. Instead of mementos or family photos, the apartment is scattered with relics from his films: a Stetson hat from ''Tenenbaums,'' a Cousteau book from ''Rushmore.'' A large painting of Winston Churchill -- also from ''Rushmore'' -- smiles down on the living room from above the fireplace. One of the few traces of noncinematic life are volumes of Jules Verne and Robert Louis Stevenson that, judging from the Dewey Decimal coding taped to their spines, appear to have been cadged from a library somewhere.</p>
        <p>''Oh, those aren't real,'' Anderson says after emerging from the bathroom. ''They were made to look that way by the 'Rushmore' art department.'' On inspection, it turns out they've been cleverly disguised as library books, right down to the fake date-stamps inside the back cover, detailing when nonexistent students checked them out. They're never shown in the movie and call to mind the old story about the director Luchino Visconti, who insisted that cabinets in his scenes be filled with exquisite china, even though their contents were never going to be seen on camera.</p>
        <p>On either side of Churchill are two vast bookshelves that could easily represent the two sides of Anderson's brain. The right bank is reserved for favorite books: among them, journals and criticism written by film directors and bound screenplays of great movies. The left is for visuals, the art books: Egon Schiele, David Hockney, Lucian Freud. Both sides of the massive bookshelf brain are diffused with literature -- punished volumes of Henry James, Mann and Joyce -- mixed in with J.K. Rowling, Bjorn Borg's ''My Life and Game'' and ''America's Glorious Quilts.'' Many of the tomes have receipts tucked inside their pages. ''I use them as bookmarks,'' he says, somewhat embarrassed. ''That way, I always know when I got the book and where I came by it.''</p>
        <p>The pride of the apartment is Anderson's new gizmo: a shiny white toaster, one of the few things in the place that has never appeared in a movie. For weeks, he searched obsessively for a model that allows slices of bread to descend side-by-side with a slow, pleasing berrrjjjjh sound. Plodding into the kitchen, he gestures toward his new toy like a game-show model indicating a prize Chevrolet. ''There's only one problem,'' he says. He grabs the toaster's electrical plug and waves it aloft toward the nearest socket, which is three feet out of range. In a mixing studio, I've seen Anderson spend four hours adjusting the sound on a mere 58 seconds of footage. He knows the precise timing of where a gust of wind should be heard -- and the computer technology that will bring the sounds in his mind to life. But he is not at home with household complexity.</p>
        <p>Is he playing up his boyishness? Perhaps. It's hard not to notice, for example, that his suit is several sizes too small for him -- never mind that it's custom-made by Vahram of Mr. Ned Tailors on Fifth Avenue. ''It drives Vahram crazy,'' Anderson says, laughingly tugging at a lapel. ''I like 'em a bit snugger than most people. I guess I'd be a size 40, but this is something like a modified 36. This is a size that doesn't exist.''</p>
        <p>Despite his prep-school packaging, however, there's nothing affected about Anderson. He is blunt and, near enough, streetwise. ''I guarantee you, Wes was not an eccentric kid,'' says the actor Owen Wilson, Anderson's longtime friend and writing partner. ''He was into sci-fi movies and Maseratis and all that regular-kid stuff. It isn't as though he was obsessed with E.B. White.''</p>
        <p>That said, Anderson was a precocious child. As a schoolboy in Houston, he mounted one improbable stage production after another: an all-battle-scene re-creation of the Alamo and even an adaptation of ''Star Wars,'' which he has acknowledged was ''kind of a failure, due to the limitations of the elementary-school stage.'' (He got a second chance in ''Rushmore,'' which ends with a hilariously overblown school play about Vietnam, complete with dynamite and flamethrowers.)</p>
        <p>After attending St. John's, the same private school where ''Rushmore'' was filmed, Anderson took a degree in philosophy from the University of Texas at Austin. It was there that he fell in with Owen Wilson and, eventually, Owen's brothers Luke and Andrew -- all of whom have been major players in the blur of his personal-artistic life. ''The first time I saw Wes was in a playwriting class,'' Owen Wilson recalls. ''He walked in wearing these L.L. Bean duck-hunting boots and shorts, which I thought was kind of obnoxious. It wasn't until later that we became friends.''</p>
        <p>Anderson and the Wilson brothers, as the old expression goes, have stolen a lot of horses together in their time. ''Bottle Rocket,'' for instance -- in which Luke and Owen Wilson playfully try to rob a cold-storage facility -- isn't pure fantasy. ''Yeah, that wasn't exactly made up out of nothin','' Anderson says. ''We were living it. Only, our day-to-day crime sprees mostly involved small cans of tuna fish and school cafeterias.''</p>
        <p>Despite their seeming disparity, all three of Anderson's movies have a subtle but distinct structure. There is always the Revelation of Secrets, the Fall, the New Harmony. In ''Tenenbaums,'' Anderson fleshes out these themes in an affectionately fictionalized New York, a metropolis of gypsy cabs and posh 40's-style hotels. It's the Manhattan that Anderson conjured as a kid in his native Texas, spun from rhapsodic magazine articles and Hollywood movies. The final product is J.D. Salinger, Booth Tarkington and John Irving by way of the ''Eloise'' books. His greatest debt, though, is to Salinger, whose Glass Family stories are echoed in the Tenenbaums' air of melancholy, doomed genius.</p>
        <p>Creating an Anderson script -- even one like ''Bottle Rocket,'' which might have tumbled freely from his mind, given its off-the-cuff feel and true basis in tuna-related misdemeanors -- requires intense effort. ''The writing phase takes a surprisingly long time, he says. ''Any time I even have a script ready, I consider that a minor victory.'' He pauses. ''But really, my job is just to make sure the set is right, the clothes are right, it's the right time of day for the shot, then set up the boxes for the actors to sit on.''</p>
        <p>''You mean, after you've conceived every aspect of the movie down to the last detail?'' I counter.</p>
        <p>''Well,'' he says. ''There's that, too.''</p>
        <p>As Anderson potters around in the small office he has set up in his bedroom, simultaneously tapping out e-mail messages and talking about his past, he suddenly cocks his head toward a muffled clamor from the living room. An old friend named Stephen Dignan has stopped by, and he's been lolling around in there, unsupervised, for quite some time.</p>
        <p>''Uh-oh,'' Anderson says. ''What was that?''</p>
        <p>In the living room Dignan is on the floor hastily gathering up some miniature wooden Zulu warriors that have somehow met a grisly fate on Anderson's sisal rug. ''I hope the little spears are all right,'' Anderson says gravely, staring down into the carnage. ''They're pretty delicate.''</p>
        <p>''Does this look all right?'' Dignan asks, hopefully holding one up.</p>
        <p>''Not really,'' Anderson says. But he is accustomed to focusing on many things at once. As he talks about his own life's connections to ''Tenenbaums,'' he devotes the other 100 percent of his attention to fixing one of the damaged warriors.</p>
        <p>I ask Anderson about his habit of incorporating friends into his work. True, his latest picture is rife with major stars: not only Hackman, Huston and the Wilsons, but also Gwyneth Paltrow, Bill Murray, Ben Stiller and Danny Glover. But in all three of his movies, a legion of small but important roles are taken up by pals -- grade-school cohorts; Anderson's brother Eric; and two guys who ran a Texas coffee shop where he and Owen Wilson used to hang out. Anderson's girlfriend, Jennifer Wachtell, an executive at Miramax, has a fleeting role as Ben Stiller's wife in ''Tenenbaums.'' Dignan, a mellow man who has known Wilson since first grade, has been in all the films. Wilson's character in ''Bottle Rocket'' is even named for him, though no one remembers why.</p>
        <p>''There's also a Tenenbaum family in real life,'' Wilson says, ''but they're not like the family in the movie. Andrew went to school with one of the kids. We use names like that to make it more real for us. If we called them 'the Edwards family' or something, it would feel, I don't know, fake.''</p>
        <p>Anderson and Wilson also have a passion for portraying actual incidents from their lives in their scripts. Sometimes it's just a detail that was a running joke a few years back -- a ludicrous electric tie rack Dignan used to own, for example. Other times, it's a full-blown yarn. ''When you hear a great story from one of your friends,'' Luke Wilson says, ''certain details make it especially funny, funnier than fiction. Besides that, often when Wes directs, he'll take you aside and say: 'You know that story you were tellin' about the guy in that deli? Try it that way.'''</p>
        <p>''The stories we use aren't meant to be in-jokes,'' Anderson says, peering at the Zulu. ''We include those because if certain people are on the set, they bring a positive feeling to it. The memory of something you've lived creates a kind of electricity during the shoot, and that reality is part of what gets photographed.''</p>
        <p>To add to Anderson's youthful mien (Anjelica Huston recalls thinking he looked 17 when they first met to discuss ''Tenenbaums''), his movies constantly blur the line between childlike and grown-up behavior. Kids act like adults and adults act like kids. In one amusing sequence in ''Tenenbaums,'' Royal tries to teach his hopelessly serious grandsons how to act like boys, taking them on a crash course across Manhattan that includes jaywalking through heavy traffic and shoplifting milk. ''That childlike theme is never preconceived,'' Anderson says. ''But Owen and I are aware of it. It just keeps coming up.''</p>
        <p>One of the deepest betrayals in ''Tenenbaums'' consists of Royal shooting his son Chas in the hand with a BB gun during a game -- which is deemed unforgivable because they are playing on the same team. The film has a close-up shot of that same BB, years after the treachery has taken place. You can see it rolling around beneath the skin of the grown-up son's knuckle.</p>
        <p>''Where did you find an actor with a BB in his hand?'' I ask Anderson. ''What kind of bizarre casting call did that take?''</p>
        <p>''Oh, right,'' he says equably. ''That's Andrew Wilson's hand.'' Andrew, the alpha male of the Wilson brothers, has been a fixture in all of Anderson's pictures and has no fewer than three cameos in this one, if you count the three-second glimpse of his hand. ''That BB-gun incident is a combination of two stories,'' Anderson explains. ''Owen once shot Andrew in the hand with a BB gun when they were on the same team. Another time, he shot a guy named Max Cottrell in the back of the head with a Roman candle.''</p>
        <p>Cottrell, who fortunately recovered from the injury, clearly remembers the Wilsons' tearaway glamour. ''They were one of those families you find in every neighborhood,'' he says. ''Everything was happening in their yard. When there was a BB-gun war or a touch-football game, it was always at the Wilsons' place.''</p>
        <p>In ''Tenenbaums,'' Owen Wilson plays a neighbor who secretly yearns to be part of the famous family across the street. So it's natural to wonder whether Anderson wishes he were a Wilson -- to belong, to share their heat and perhaps even to mitigate his bookishness with some of their bad-boy charisma.</p>
        <p>''Welllll,'' he says, after an age, ''I definitely understand that impulse. There have been various families I've wanted to get adopted into along the way . . . as much as I'm connected to my own family. And the Wilsons are one of them.''</p>
        <p>Hearing this, Owen Wilson chuckles. ''You know, I kinda wanted to be adopted into Wes's family but never got the chance,'' he says. ''I never even met his parents or his brothers until we'd been friends a long time. He was always coming to our family reunions. I think it took Wes a long time to get comfortable around his own family.''</p>
        <p>Since the question of autobiography is inescapable, the issue of Anderson's own parents' divorce also looms. ''Royal is nothing like my father,'' he says. ''My mother is similar to Etheline in that she's also an archaeologist. And that she was always encouraging us to be involved in different activities. But that's about it.''</p>
        <p>In the end, of course, it's for Anderson's work to reveal whether his autobiographical touches are a callow indulgence. They certainly don't seem to be. He's every bit as adept as his elders at conceiving fully rounded, furiously detailed worlds in his movies. Though he likes to include homages to artists and other directors in his films -- a shot borrowed from Kubrick's ''Barry Lyndon,'' a composition based on an obscure photo by Jacques-Henri Lartigue -- he never relies on references to do his work for him. And if the films present a childlike worldview, it's by virtue of a tactical, and very adult, level of control.</p>
        <p>''Wes's process is as refined and evolved as it can be; he's relaxed and tremendously confident,'' says Anjelica Huston. ''He has a real voice, a real eye. It'd be an error to think that because he's young, he's not fully formed.''</p>
        <p>Back in the Brill building, the spirited hunt for a good whistle track continues. It's lost on no one that, even on a Saturday, buttonholing any musician you found strolling the halls could wrap this up in less than a minute. But Anderson prefers his troupe of amateurs, a ''Kwai'' brigade but with better shoes.</p>
        <p>After Dylan Tichenor winds up his wobbly performance, Anderson wheels around and peers into the dim studio. ''Who's the whistler here?'' he asks, as if he knows there must be one hiding in here somewhere. ''Let's gather around and do group versions!''</p>
        <p>So the groups step up: rotating trios of his pals and, because no one is too arbitrary a choice, even me. Just to mix things up, Wes himself tries a run at it -- and is precisely on key -- but decides that he lacks the stuff. ''My whistling,'' he says, mournfully shaking his head. ''It's inaudible.''</p>
        <p>As we wheeze tunelessly through take after take, seemingly bent on incorporating Arnold Schoenberg into this sprightly comedy, Anderson is all dry enthusiasm. ''That last one was special,'' he says to yet another luckless editor. ''Just make sure you hit those notes staccato. Do that thing -- what's it called? Yeah, the glissando. But that was really close.''</p>
        <p>In the midst of a discussion about who else might be worth a try, Anderson has an epiphany: ''Wasn't there a guy in 'Catcher in the Rye' who was a great whistler? A guy at Pencey Prep?''</p>
        <p>The room is stumped. For one absurd moment, it almost seems that he wants to hire a fictional character to fix the music. But Anderson has a habit of measuring the outside world against art. Sometimes the membrane between the two realms, if it exists at all, is permeable.</p>
        <p>After two hours, the recording session wraps. ''That's enough whistling for one day,'' he says brightly. ''This'll be great.''</p>
        <p>Slowly, Wes Anderson detaches himself from his headset console and drifts back from his controlled world into the formlessness of the real one. Cut free, he still carries the warmth of Salinger's adolescent fiction with him and continues to rummage through the cluttered rooms of his memory for that Pencey whistler's name.</p>
        <p>''Wow,'' he says to himself, giving up the search at last. ''That's a really great book.''</p>
        <p>Marshall Sella is a contributing writer for The New York Times Magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Marshall Sella is a contributing writer for The New York Times Magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
