<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Blasting? Don't Fret, But Geese Beware</title>
    <meta content="02GOOS$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1347712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ENVIRONMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geese</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kensico Reservoir (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Valhalla (Ny)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kilgannon, Corey</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD7143DF931A35751C1A9679C8B63" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Blasting? Don't Fret, But Geese Beware</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
      <dateline>VALHALLA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City Department of Environmental Protection resumes initiative, started in early 1990's and halted since September 11, to chase Canada geese from Kensico Reservoir in Valhalla; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST week, city enforcement officers in boats, armed with explosives, took to the Kensico Reservoir. Their target: Canada geese.</p>
        <p>In 1993, New York City's Department of Environmental Protection began Operation Goosebusters. Under the initiative, formally called a ''bird harassment program,'' officers in patrol boats and a Hovercraft tried to deter flocks of geese and gulls floating in the Kensico Reservoir by buzzing them and by firing screaming rockets and guns that make a bright flash and a boom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST week, city enforcement officers in boats, armed with explosives, took to the Kensico Reservoir. Their target: Canada geese.</p>
        <p>In 1993, New York City's Department of Environmental Protection began Operation Goosebusters. Under the initiative, formally called a ''bird harassment program,'' officers in patrol boats and a Hovercraft tried to deter flocks of geese and gulls floating in the Kensico Reservoir by buzzing them and by firing screaming rockets and guns that make a bright flash and a boom.</p>
        <p>The initiative, halted since Sept. 11, was resumed last week.</p>
        <p>D.E.P. officials said they had refrained from using the loud noisemakers since the terrorist attacks for fear that some nearby residents would mistake the blasting for an attack on the reservoir, the key holding area for most of the water to New York City and parts of Westchester.</p>
        <p>''We got a lot of calls about it,'' said Charles G. Sturcken, chief of staff for the city's D.E.P. ''Their first reaction was: 'If the reservoirs are a terrorist target, how are you going to protect me? I'm stuck with this next door to me.' ''</p>
        <p>As it happens, the D.E.P. recently allocated $30 million to improve security of the water system, increasing personnel and installing security cameras, motion sensors and better fences around sensitive areas like dams and gatehouses.</p>
        <p>And now the D.E.P. has resumed the anti-goose program it began in the early 1990's when milder winters brought sharp increases in the number of Canada geese and ring-billed gulls at thereservoir.</p>
        <p>Officials identified bird droppings as a main source of high levels of potentially harmful bacteria, enough to necessitate frequent bypassing of the Kensico reservoir on the way to city's distribution network. Faced with the possibility of having to build a multibillion-dollar water filtration plant, the agency implemented the bird deterrent program at a cost of several hundred thousand dollars a year. After a few years, bacteria levels waned.</p>
        <p>The Kensico Reservoir, a 30-billion gallon reserve just north of White Plains, is the crucial nexus in the water supply system. Usually, some 90 percent of the water consumed in New York City flows through the reservoir, the final major holding place for some 1.3 billion gallons of water a day from upstate reservoirs to nearly 9 million people in New York City and parts of Westchester.</p>
        <p>Since Sept. 11, officials have barred all fishing, hunting and hiking in and around its reservoirs, and have blocked certain access roads and bridges. Restrictions will remain for the foreseeable future, Mr. Sturcken said. Dinghies kept on watershed property should be removed or they will be impounded, he said.</p>
        <p>The department is considering other methods to deter birds. At the Hillview Reservoir in south Yonkers, clear nylon fishing line has been strung across the water to prevent birds from landing. Kensico, however, is too large for this, Mr. Sturcken said.</p>
        <p>A typical goose can graze and then dump about a half-pound of excrement a day into the water. The feces causes fecal coliform bacteria, which at high levels can endanger purity of drinking water.</p>
        <p>Geese have always plagued Westchester, where there are few predators and large expanses of freshly mown grass that offer up tender grass shoots. The county has sponsored all-day symposiums on Canada geese. In 1993, the state opened a weeklong season in September for hunters to shoot up to three Canada  geese a day in Westchester. (Hunters had difficulty getting the necessary permission of private landowners.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Sturcken said there was no significant increase in bacteria levels since Sept. 11, but, he added, geese do not congregate heavily until late November.</p>
        <p>As for the effect of the resumed noise on residents, it does not bother Jean Goeberbecker, who has lived in her home in Valhalla overlooking the reservoir for the last 32 years. She said that the booms sound like a distant muffled shotgun.</p>
        <p>''It never sounded to me like we were being attacked,'' she said, ''but some people are more skittish than others.''</p>
        <p>ENVIRONMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
