<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Huge Blackboard Thrown to the Ground</title>
    <meta content="25MEMO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1491770"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="WESLEYAN MEMO"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wesleyan University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salzman, Avi</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennet, Douglas J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7D61531F936A15756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Huge Blackboard Thrown to the Ground</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By AVI SALZMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salzman, Avi</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article by Wesleyan graduate Avi Salzman on chalking, springtime tradition of marking campus streets with sometimes dirty words and lewd drawings about mostly gay issues; practice was banned earlier this month by university president Douglas Bennet; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN spring, the Wesleyan campus became a huge blackboard thrown to the ground. Chalk was everywhere. When it was new, it was beautiful and dirty all at once. The colorful scrawlings described gay sex acts and poked fun at some of the stodgy buildings and the professorial air of the campus. Most people were amused. Some were scandalized. Later, we walked over the words without thinking. One day the rain would wash them away.</p>
        <p>Douglas J. Bennet, the president of the university who always seemed to make his most controversial decisions just before students left for the summer, banned chalking earlier this month. The issue had been hot since I left Wesleyan in 2000, and Mr. Bennet had been deciding for a while just what to do about it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN spring, the Wesleyan campus became a huge blackboard thrown to the ground. Chalk was everywhere. When it was new, it was beautiful and dirty all at once. The colorful scrawlings described gay sex acts and poked fun at some of the stodgy buildings and the professorial air of the campus. Most people were amused. Some were scandalized. Later, we walked over the words without thinking. One day the rain would wash them away.</p>
        <p>Douglas J. Bennet, the president of the university who always seemed to make his most controversial decisions just before students left for the summer, banned chalking earlier this month. The issue had been hot since I left Wesleyan in 2000, and Mr. Bennet had been deciding for a while just what to do about it.</p>
        <p>When I first saw chalkings at Wesleyan on National Coming Out Day my freshman year, they made me laugh. The dirty words and lewd drawings were a treat for an 18-year-old on his way to an anthropology lecture. For a while, chalking, which primarily dealt with gay issues, was just another political expression on a campus full of liberal rhetoric.</p>
        <p>Many of the chalkings were benign: one written at a crossroads urged people to ''go both ways.'' Others were more confrontational, even describing sex acts involving people's parents. The words, my gay friends told me, gave them ownership of the campus, as if the straight world would learn about being uncomfortable by walking down gay streets. In a world of coy heterosexual billboards, the streets of Wesleyan belonged to a different mode of sexual and political speech.</p>
        <p>At times, the chalkings achieved the desired effect. When activists pushed their verbiage and pictograms to their obscene limit, they could make me cringe.</p>
        <p>The practice first troubled me when some chalkers focused their efforts on WesFest, a weekend for high school students who have been accepted to see the campus and decide if it was right for them. One familiar chalking read, ''Your tour guide is gay.'' Others made a more determined effort to shock.</p>
        <p>When chalkers began to use the scrawlings to alienate incoming freshman, the whole situation deteriorated as far as I was concerned. It was one thing if I was reading about something pornographic, but I didn't want my parents or my classmate's parents reading about it. It became an embarrassment.</p>
        <p>The goal, I thought, was too much about making everyone uncomfortable and weeding out the freshmen who couldn't handle the political atmosphere. That didn't generate any discussion. And it alienated kids and their parents who might have brought a new viewpoint to the overwhelmingly liberal campus. The chalkings created an unfair litmus test. If people couldn't handle our particular brand of liberalism, they didn't belong at Wesleyan. For such a free-speech medium, chalking shut a lot of people up.</p>
        <p>My junior year, three students erased one of the chalkings because they said they found it offensive. One of the erasers said he didn't like the way his bisexuality was being portrayed. Later at a ''forum'' on the event, the students were berated.</p>
        <p>Chalking had given people who felt marginalized a space to express taboo acts and ideas anonymously. Their intent, often, was to push speech to its socially accepted limit -- acceptance by the university's administration and even its professors was never the point. Chalkers crossed the line of acceptable speech in order to change what was deemed acceptable. When the desired effect didn't take hold, activists pushed their verbiage to the next level. But when the words were used to bully people or to steer moderate or (perish the thought) conservative thinkers away from the campus, the practice lost its charm to me -- and its power. What the chalkings couldn't do was get people talking about their real differences.</p>
        <p>The chalking was a statement that wasn't signed and didn't really allow a reply. That's what led to the confusion and anger. It was easy to call it a cowardly or dishonest act.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, I don't think President Bennet should have ended the practice altogether. You can't place an airtight lid over a living organism. Though the chalkings weren't an adequate medium to spur debate about sex or politics, the debate about chalking itself has really just begun at Wesleyan. Twenty years from now, a ban on chalking will seem like an archaic remnant of the past, akin to anti-sodomy laws in the South. And, all political expression aside, there's something unsettling about living on a campus where no one can write on the sidewalks.</p>
        <p>Chalking is part of the experience of the most recent generation of Wesleyan students. Like most students, I neither chalked nor erased. But, at the end of the day, all of us had chalk on our shoes.</p>
        <p>WESLEYAN MEMO Avi Salzman, a reporter for the Daily News-Record in Harrisonburg, Va., graduated from Wesleyan in 2000.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Avi Salzman, a reporter for the Daily News-Record in Harrisonburg, Va., graduated from Wesleyan in 2000.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
