<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Small Brown Trout In Bright New World</title>
    <meta content="Y01OUT$13" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/01/sports/othersports/01OUTD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1445165"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="OUTDOORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Eyes and Eyesight</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clymer, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Eyes and Eyesight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E1D81138F932A35751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Small Brown Trout In Bright New World</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Small Brown Trout in a World Newly Vivid</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Adam Clymer</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clymer, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Adam Clymer Outdoors column discusses joy of dry fly fishing after cataracts surgery, which made following line possible (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five small brown trout, the biggest of them nine inches long, don't usually make for a spectacular afternoon of fishing.</p>
        <p>But they did one day last month because for the first time in a year or so, I could see them take a dry fly, a size 18 Adams.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Five small brown trout, the biggest of them nine inches long, don't usually make for a spectacular afternoon of fishing. But they did one day last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Five small brown trout, the biggest of them nine inches long, don't usually make for a spectacular afternoon of fishing.</p>
        <p>But they did one day last month because for the first time in a year or so, I could see them take a dry fly, a size 18 Adams.</p>
        <p>Until then, I had spent my time cataract fishing, which is not fishing in a waterfall but fishing with cataracts that dimmed and clouded the vision in both eyes. There had been successful days with streamers and nymphs, where the tug on the line is the signal to set the hook.</p>
        <p>But dry fly fishing had been almost hopeless. Not only had I been unable to react to the sudden disappearance of the fly from the top of the water, I couldn't even follow the drift when it didn't disappear.</p>
        <p>There had been one glorious exception. Fishing Alberta's Lower Bow River near El Paso, Wis., at sunset, Brian Larsen, a geologist-guide from Calgary, spotted a rising rainbow and provided navigational advice for my casts, with quiet directions like ''four feet out from that big rock,'' ''two more feet of line,'' ''another foot to the right,'' and finally ''STRIKE!''</p>
        <p>That 17-incher broke off after five minutes and two leaps, but it was a high point of a summer of cataract fishing.</p>
        <p>The September afternoon on the Rush River would have been a success even without the five browns. Going fishing itself had been a lucky break. At the last minute, one Minnesota congressional candidate I had expected to interview became unavailable, so there was some free time before I caught up with him and his opponent the next morning.</p>
        <p>So I called John Van Vliet, a friend in Minneapolis who wrote ''The Art of Fly Tying'' (Cy Decosse Inc., 1994), and asked if he could get off for a few hours. He could.</p>
        <p>We had fished together in July for cutthroat, brown and bull trout on the Elk River in British Columbia, my last angling expedition before surgery. It had been good below-surface fishing, and when hooked the fish jumped or dashed away on seeing the boat. And I could see them.</p>
        <p>But after two quick operations this summer, surgeries that lasted no more than 40 minutes and involved no discomfort at all, I could see again. The clouded lenses in my eyes had been replaced by plastic. Across a room, I could now recognize people who had been blurs the month before, and colors were bright. Walls that had looked gray were newly white. For the first time in 57 years (or since I was 8), I was not wearing glasses, except for reading -- and for tying small knots in 5X leaders.</p>
        <p>John met me at the Minneapolis-St. Paul airport and said we would be going about 50 miles east and south into Wisconsin for the nearest predictably decent fishing, near the hamlet of El Paso, named by returning veterans from the Mexican War.</p>
        <p>The Rush is located at the northern edge of the driftless area that was never scoured by glaciers, and it is watered throughout by limestone springs. The places we fished were shaded, with pasture on one bank and woods on the other.</p>
        <p>He had brought tackle for us, and since it was cloudy and there was no surface action, he suggested we try nymphs. Nothing doing. I wanted to cast dries, to see how softly they would land and what the float looked like.</p>
        <p>The gentle current of the Rush permitted long, smooth floats. After half an hour of satisfying casting practice, a few small trout started rising. We never knew what stirred them, but they were young enough not to know the difference between that which was natural and an Adams. The strikes were brisk, and three small browns were quickly hooked, brought in and released.</p>
        <p>We moved on to another section of the river with tall grass along the bank, and John suggested trying a small hopper pattern. More nice floats, but no strikes. So I went back to the Adams, and caught two more. Then it was time to go back to the more complicated, less edifying world of politics.</p>
        <p>OUTDOORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
