<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Happy New Year for a Cable Channel Cut by DirecTV</title>
    <meta content="10TRIO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/10/business/media/10trio.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20050113T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1640880"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DirectTV</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Trio (TV Channel)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nbc Universal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glassman, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Trio Network</org>
        <org class="online_producer">DirecTV</org>
        <org class="online_producer">National Broadcasting Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE4D71E39F933A25752C0A9639C8B63" item-length="733" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Happy New Year for a Cable Channel Cut by DirecTV</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Happy New Year for a Cable Channel Cut by DirecTV</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK GLASSMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glassman, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>DirectTV satellite television provider has dropped Trio, fringe cable channel that won acclaim for resurrecting television's flops and losers for new audience, costing it some 14 million subscribers; Trio, owned by NBC Universal, now reaches about eight million homes through cable distributors; industry executives suspect it may not survive much longer; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The cable channel Trio had quite a New Year's Day hangover. When the clock struck midnight Dec. 31, the network lost roughly 14 million subscribers.</p>
        <p>Trio, the fringe channel that won acclaim for resurrecting television's flops and losers for a new audience, was cut from the DirecTV satellite lineup on Jan. 1. The network lost about two-thirds of its subscribers and was pushed that much closer to the brink.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trio, the fringe channel that won acclaim for resurrecting television's flops and losers for a new audience, is fighting for it's future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The cable channel Trio had quite a New Year's Day hangover. When the clock struck midnight Dec. 31, the network lost roughly 14 million subscribers.</p>
        <p>Trio, the fringe channel that won acclaim for resurrecting television's flops and losers for a new audience, was cut from the DirecTV satellite lineup on Jan. 1. The network lost about two-thirds of its subscribers and was pushed that much closer to the brink.</p>
        <p>Trio now reaches about eight million homes through cable distributors, including Time Warner, Cox and Adelphia, but industry executives and analysts say the channel, which is owned by NBC Universal, may not survive much longer with its shrunken audience.</p>
        <p>Trio's travails also raise doubts about the promise of the 500-channel universe, where every taste, no matter how particular, would be represented by a network. Trio defined itself by flirting with the borders of mainstream entertainment with programs like ''Brilliant But Canceled'' and ''That's Not Funny.'' While critics have praised the network for its bold, counterintuitive choices -- Entertainment Weekly magazine called the channel ''the It network'' of 2003 -- it has had trouble keeping viewers. And whereas Comedy Central and Food Network have clearly defined genres (and advertisers), Trio's appeal is difficult to pigeonhole.</p>
        <p>''In a way, content is always king. But right behind that is distribution,'' said Andy Donchin, director for national broadcast at Carat USA in New York, a media agency that is part of the Carat division of the Aegis Group. Mr. Donchin said he could not recall ever buying commercial time on Trio and said the network's small audience was a deterrent to most advertisers.</p>
        <p>Officials at Trio declined to comment on the loss or speculate about changes in content or management. The network released a statement in November that read, ''We are committed to programming the network and the Web site for our loyal viewers and cable distribution partners. NBC Universal continues to evaluate the future of the network in relation to its overall digital strategy.''</p>
        <p>Media analysts were less optimistic about the channel's future. Bill Cella, the chairman and chief executive of Magna Global Media Research, called Trio's programming ''upscale'' and ''pretty highbrow stuff,'' but said it did not have ''the kind of brand that resonates with advertisers.'' Mr. Cella stopped short of calling the cut to Trio's audience a death knell for the network.</p>
        <p>Trio began telecasting in 1994 out of Toronto and was then run by North American TV, a joint venture between Power Broadcasting and the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation. The network was purchased by USA Networks in 2000 and moved its headquarters to New York.</p>
        <p>Two years later, the network hired Lauren Zalaznick as president. Under her guidance, Trio introduced its signature, ''Brilliant But Canceled,'' series, which showed old sitcoms like ''Bakersfield, P.D.'' and dramas like ''Cop Rock,'' which had never garnered much of an audience.</p>
        <p>''We're kind of the opposite of the TV Land network, which takes shows that were already popular and brings them back,'' Ms. Zalaznick said in a 2002 interview. ''We're like the underbelly of that. We're finding the things that everyone missed and letting viewers discover them.''</p>
        <p>In 2003, Trio was acquired by Vivendi Universal when it purchased USA Networks. The channel was rebranded and given a new slogan: pop, culture, TV.</p>
        <p>Ms. Zalaznick ''put together something original, interesting and distinctive,'' said Doug Herzog, who ran USA Networks until May and is now the president of Comedy Central. He added, ''I think she was very successful because she got herself noticed in a world of literally hundreds of channels.''</p>
        <p>Stacey Lynn Koerner, executive vice president and director of global research at Interactive, a media analysis firm, said DirecTV's decision may have been motivated by factors other than viewer interest. ''It should be about what audiences look for and want, and providing as much variety as possible,'' she said, ''but sometimes it's simply about negotiation.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Koerner added that Trio's executives might simply have cast the net too wide. ''It didn't have an easy identification with a very specific niche group,'' she said.</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
        <p>Correction:  January 13, 2005, Thursday  A picture caption in Business Day on Monday with an article about the loss of subscribers at Trio when the network was dropped from the DirecTV lineup reversed the identities of the actresses in Trio's TV series ''Kath &amp; Kim.'' Jane Turner was at the right and Gina Riley at the left.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 13, 2005, Thursday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in Business Day on Monday with an article about the loss of subscribers at Trio when the network was dropped from the DirecTV lineup reversed the identities of the actresses in Trio's TV series ''Kath &amp; Kim.'' Jane Turner was at the right and Gina Riley at the left.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
