<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mall Spa: Haven for Just-Too-Tired Shoppers</title>
    <meta content="1JOURN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="LONG ISLAND JOURNAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westbury (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Maximus Salon and Total Beauty Day Spa</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Source (Shopping Center)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ketcham, Diane</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Spas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DC1E3BF932A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mall Spa: Haven for Just-Too-Tired Shoppers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANE KETCHAM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ketcham, Diane</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on services available at new Maximus Salon and Total Beauty Day Spa at Source mall in Westbury, NY; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EXECUTIVES of Saks Fifth Avenue take note. Disposable bathing suits are now available in a retail establishment across the corridor from your outlet store at the Source mall in Westbury. Of course, there is also a Water Journey, in which the suits can be worn. Some people, however, choose to go au naturel, which may be the first time that nudity is allowed, even encouraged, in a shopping mall.</p>
        <p>Sitting under a waterfall was Penny Blank of Melville. Mrs. Blank wore a black designer bathing suit that she had brought from home. ''I'm not ready to go naked yet,'' she said. ''It's my first time.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EXECUTIVES of Saks Fifth Avenue take note. Disposable bathing suits are now available in a retail establishment across the corridor from your outlet store at the Source mall in Westbury. Of course, there is also a Water Journey, in which the suits can be worn. Some people, however, choose to go au naturel, which may be the first time that nudity is allowed, even encouraged, in a shopping mall.</p>
        <p>Sitting under a waterfall was Penny Blank of Melville. Mrs. Blank wore a black designer bathing suit that she had brought from home. ''I'm not ready to go naked yet,'' she said. ''It's my first time.''</p>
        <p>Not in a spa, she added. But certainly in a spa in a mall. Last month the Maximus Salon and Total Beauty Day Spa opened in the Source, signaling a new age in retail. The shop-till-you-drop crowd no longer has to drop. Along with its hydrotherapy Water Journey, Maximus offers full-body massages. ''Shoppers seem especially tense in the neck and shoulders,'' said a massage therapist, Francine Messina. Maybe from signing all those credit-card receipts.</p>
        <p>Maximus is not only for shoppers, its owner, Richard Calcasola, would like it known. ''We have an entrance right by the covered garage,'' he said. ''You don't have to shop to visit us.''</p>
        <p>But you do have to drive. Those commuting on Long Island roadways might consider stopping at the spa to relieve traffic-jam tensions. Male and female drivers are welcome.  This is an equal-opportunity spa.</p>
        <p>''We have separate dressing areas and relaxing rooms for men and women,'' Mr. Calcasola said. Customers take turns in water therapy. Where one starts ''depends on whether you want relaxing or stimulating,'' said Robin Kluge, the general manager. Mrs. Blank began with a high-technology bathtub that offered 150 jets. ''It gives you an underwater massage,'' Ms. Kluge said of the machine that cost $38,000 and came from France. ''It's the first in this country with this amount of jets.''</p>
        <p>The entire water-therapy operation cost $250,000 to construct. It includes a Vichy water Tingle King  shower, a rubdown with seaweed and sea salt and the waterfall, an unusual addition to Old Country Road.</p>
        <p>''I was sitting under a waterfall in Maui,'' Ms. Kluge explained, ''and it was so wonderful. I thought, 'How can I get this to New York?' '' She had the waterfall designed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Calcasola could not be happier. ''I wanted everything to be special,'' he said. All the massage rooms have elegant bed covers and soft lighting. In one was an esthetician, Gerry Lattanzi of Bellmore. ''We do deep-pore cleansing here,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The 11,000-square-foot spa-salon also offers hair styling, coloring,  makeup applications and a separate area for brides to be. Everywhere are exquisite Italian furnishings. ''You've heard of mall hair?'' Mr. Calcasola asked. ''Well we're reinventing the word.'' It is difficult to imagine hair being cut there. ''By the time the hair hits the floor,'' he said, ''it's swept off.''</p>
        <p>The coloring area has no mirrors. By design, he said. The customer doesn't need to see the process, only the result.</p>
        <p>A result of Mrs. Blank's visit was a mellow glow. ''I had to come,'' she said. ''I'm the mother of teen-age girls.'' Technically one daughter is a pre-teen-ager. But the workload is the same, the mother said. ''After this I have to take one daughter to kick-line practice and the other to Hebrew school. But they don't mind that I'm here. They always wait to ask for things until after I go to a spa.'' Her full-body massage was about to begin. ''After this,'' she said, ''I usually say yes to everything.''</p>
        <p>Drive-by Advertising</p>
        <p>A key to success in the business world is finding a niche. So says Christopher Culver, who found his. Bus shelters.</p>
        <p>His company, Culver Associates of Manhattan, won the contract in Nassau County to revolutionize the shelters. Yes, there was competition. Mr. Culver is not the only bus-shelter visionary.</p>
        <p>This month the first new shelters will be shown. Compared to the old, they will be bigger, cleaner and ''a nice hunter green.'' Some will have domed roofs, seats and telephones. It may be hard to leave. ''I want to create the best bus shelters in the country,'' Mr. Culver said. ''I was the one who made the Los Angeles bus shelters the most successful franchise.''</p>
        <p>The profit in shelters isn't from sheltering passengers. It comes from selling the advertising space that the shelters offer. In Nassau advertising space is at a premium, even on a bus shelter. ''We attract upscale clients,'' Mr. Culver said. ''Banks, automobile and movie companies.'' Fashion is big, too. Which makes one wonder about graffiti. ''Oh, we have a crack bus-shelter maintenance crew,'' he added. ''They are out every day getting rid of any graffiti and keeping the shelters clean.''</p>
        <p>So the advertising stays sparkling. But who is it for? Not the people waiting for the buses. ''It's always been for the people driving by in cars,'' Mr. Culver said. ''That's why we devised new angled panels so it's easier for the drivers to see.''</p>
        <p>Drive-by advertising can be profitable. The county will receive 55 1/2 percent of the profits, Mr. Culver said. As for Suffolk, ''we've had meetings with them,'' he said. ''They really need help.''</p>
        <p>LONG ISLAND JOURNAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
