<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Of Fairies, Free Spirits and Outright Frauds</title>
    <meta content="01GOLD$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="48" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="991973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PHOTOGRAPHY VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goldberg, Vicki</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2DC1E3BF932A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="1835" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Of Fairies, Free Spirits and Outright Frauds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Vicki Goldberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goldberg, Vicki</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Vicki Goldberg reviews photography exhibit The Cottingley Fairies and Other Apparitions at Leslie Tonkonow Gallery; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONCE UPON A TIME, IN 1917 TO be exact, two little English girls named Elsie Wright and Frances Griffiths used to play in the woods of Cottingley in the far-off region of Yorkshire. The fairy people who dwelt in these woods befriended the girls, so one day Elsie and Frances borrowed a camera and took pictures of their friends. Lo and behold, the little people were not even camera-shy, so the two girls, 10 and 16 years old, produced the first actual photographs ever taken of fairies. Needless to say, this created a sensation.</p>
        <p>And a controversy. Some who examined the pictures called them fakes, while others swore they were not. Arthur Conan Doyle believed so strongly in their authenticity that he wrote a whole book, ''The Coming of the Fairies'' (1922), about them -- and nearly lost his credibility forever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONCE UPON A TIME, IN 1917 TO be exact, two little English girls named Elsie Wright and Frances Griffiths used to play in the woods of Cottingley in the far-off region of Yorkshire. The fairy people who dwelt in these woods befriended the girls, so one day Elsie and Frances borrowed a camera and took pictures of their friends. Lo and behold, the little people were not even camera-shy, so the two girls, 10 and 16 years old, produced the first actual photographs ever taken of fairies. Needless to say, this created a sensation.</p>
        <p>And a controversy. Some who examined the pictures called them fakes, while others swore they were not. Arthur Conan Doyle believed so strongly in their authenticity that he wrote a whole book, ''The Coming of the Fairies'' (1922), about them -- and nearly lost his credibility forever.</p>
        <p>Conan Doyle admitted that the photographs might be history's greatest hoax, but having investigated them thoroughly, he thought, my dear Watson, the matter was elementary. ''It seems to me,'' he wrote, ''that with fuller knowledge and with fresh means of vision these people are destined to become just as solid and real as the Eskimos.''  And what could be more solid than that?</p>
        <p>In response, a New York newspaper published a letter saying, ''When Peter Pan called out to the audience in London at a recent performance the famous question about fairies, Conan Doyle was the first to give an affirmative.''</p>
        <p>The Leslie Tonkonow Gallery in Chelsea has had the charming idea of rounding up 4 of the girls' 5 photographs and adding some 50 images having a connection, dubious though it may be, with the spirit world, dubious though it may be. The exhibition, ''The Cottingley Fairies and Other Apparitions,'' is on view through Feb. 21. Though not every photograph is exactly a revelation, there is an air of high spirits here, as well as a clear indication that the medium most dedicated to realism and most ineluctably tied to this world has also been striving to reach another one and investing in magic along the way.</p>
        <p>Fairy folk, like in-house aliens, have infiltrated the culture in the last few months. While Mir breaks down and the Rover lands on Mars, the Cottingley fairies are flying everywhere without a hitch: in a recent movie, ''Fairy Tale: A True Story,'' and a British book, ''The Case of the Cottingley Fairies.'' Last month, the Discovery Channel ran a program called ''Arthur C. Clarke's World of Strange Powers: Fairies, Phantoms and Fantastic Photographs.'' And late last year, the Royal Academy of Art in London opened an exhibition called ''Victorian Fairy Painting.'' One of the best of the painters, Charles Doyle, went mad sometime after he had fathered the creator of Sherlock Holmes.</p>
        <p>The Cottingley photographs presented some problems in their own day. In one, in which a tiny fellow dances onto a girl's lap, ''Iris and the Gnome,'' the child's hand has grown inhumanly large. In another, with fairies dancing in the air before a girl's face, the child is not even looking at them. (The children explained that they were so used to their spritely friends, they did not always pay them any attention.)</p>
        <p>In yet another picture, a fairy wears an evening gown modeled on French fashions of that year, the only recorded instance of fairies reading Vogue. What's more, there are annoying similarities between the little people and an illustrated children's book as well as a contemporary advertisement for night lights that featured fairy creatures.</p>
        <p>One of the girls is said to have confessed in the 1980's that they had simply stuck cutouts on hatpins and then taken the pictures.</p>
        <p>Today the pictures look hopelessly fake, but the girls were so young that the public assumed that the little darlings would not know enough to doctor a photograph. Then, too, the hoax came just before the great tidal wave of photographic reproduction, and people were not yet so familiar with the medium's virtues and vices.</p>
        <p>Conan Doyle believed the pictures because he wanted to, which is the wellspring of many beliefs; he had recently become a fervent convert to spiritualism. In those days, before distrust and digitization, whoever agreed with him no doubt still trusted that photographs could not lie.</p>
        <p>It was not the first time photography had persuaded people that the unseen world could be made visible with a little assistance from light and chemicals. When Gustave Courbet said, ''Show me an angel, and I will paint one,'' some photographers tried to oblige. The mid-19th century witnessed a rash of spirit photographs of the dead. An order of monks in Prague, claiming they had closer ties to the spirit world than most, even specialized in photographing themselves mingling with ghosts who had been nicely got up in bedsheets.</p>
        <p>One anonymous photograph at Tonkonow presents a draped sleeve and a hand with its palm toward the viewer; the photographer said this appeared to him when he was quite alone on Oct. 27, 1886. Another shows a seated man in a three-piece suit, holding his spectacles. His head has become a burst of light, his torso is hidden by another, as if he had not invented the light bulb but become one.</p>
        <p>More commonly, the portrait of someone grieving revealed the shadowy existence of the dear departed. These were double exposures; the photographer would secretly photograph an accomplice first, then use the plate again for the sitter. When the picture was developed, the person in the first exposure would loom like a shadow, the flesh being weak but the spirit willing.</p>
        <p>MANY PEOPLE, struggling with the religious doubts of the time, greeted these photographs with awe, though skeptics rushed to express their doubts in print. It was something of a drawback that the ghosts in the images did not always resemble their namesakes.  An inscription on the back of one spirit photograph at the gallery notes that the gentleman it depicts failed to recognize the lady intruding on his portrait but confessed that he was old and had a wretched memory.</p>
        <p>The most successful spirit photographer, not represented here, was William H. Mumler of Boston, who took a picture of Mrs. Lincoln with an ectoplasmic Abe putting his arms about her neck as well as one of a music critic with the spirit of Beethoven hovering symphonically above. But in 1869, Mumler was sued for fraud by a client unhappy with the ghostly portrait of his father-in-law, the news of whose death, it turned out, had been greatly exaggerated.</p>
        <p>When such photographs inspired faith, that betokened a combined belief in the afterlife and the truthfulness of photography. The potential for photographic lies was realized early in the medium's history, but it was a related medium, movies, that made that potential evident to a mass audience.</p>
        <p>One critic of the Cottingley fairy photographs said that ''anyone who has studied the extraordinary effects which have from time to time been obtained by cinema operators must be aware that it is possible, given time and opportunity, to produce by means of faked photographs almost anything that can be imagined.'' In cinematography, people could float, fly to the moon, vanish into thin air. The magic of photography in motion almost overwhelmed its reality.</p>
        <p>Spirits, more blithe than deceptive, nonetheless persisted in still photography. There was the problem of slow lenses and film, which turned moving figures into ghosts. In 1899, when Eugene Atget photographed a boy beside a large statue of an Egyptian carrying urns, the boy was restless and ended up far less solid than the statue.</p>
        <p>Presumably Atget would have preferred to maintain a consistent level of reality. Once that was achieved, photographers could choose to circumvent it. Duane Michals often willfully uses blur to signify another state of being. In a 1969 series called ''Death Comes to the Old Lady,'' the indistinct figure of a man approaches an old woman whose form is quite clear. As the man comes into focus, the woman rises abruptly from her chair and is transformed into an indecipherable rush of fog.</p>
        <p>Michael Lavine's picture of the rap star Biggie Smalls (a k a the Notorious B.I.G.), looking extraordinarily wary in a cemetery a month before he was murdered last year, delineates the mammoth Mr. Smalls with absolute clarity but turns the leaning tombstones behind him into ghostly blurs. James Van Der Zee, on the other hand, kept his focus clear in his spiritual montages of funerals in the 1940's. The figure of a dead woman dwarfs her coffin, the altar and the congregation; an angel with the requisite flowers glides above another woman's corpse. Reality and unreality were not in question here. The subject was sentiment and belief, and the photographer could trust his viewers to take his fakery to heart.</p>
        <p>The camera is not much given to flights of fancy. Photographers are, but on this score they can scarcely outdo a populace in which a large majority believes in angels and an uncounted minority has spent time on spaceships. Otherworldly sightings today are generally depicted in decidedly down-to-earth ways; see Andrea Robbins and Max Becher's unassuming photographs of the area near Roswell, N.M., where space cadets believe the Government is hiding a U.F.O. that dropped by for a cup of coffee 50 years ago. Note the sign in the middle of the desert advertising the A'le'Inn Motel with a picture of an almond-eyed extraterrestrial and the reassuring comment ''Earthlings welcome.''</p>
        <p>On such subjects, however, the media that depend on imagination have an advantage. The New Yorker had a cartoon some months ago of a Martian asking the NASA Rover to send his regards to his cousin, who immigrated to Roswell in 1947.</p>
        <p>Not that artist-photographers are slouches at sendups. The irrepressible Vik Muniz, who has made copies of Corot and of famous news photographs in thread or sugar or chocolate syrup and then photographed them, is represented in this spirited show by a roundel with the head of Medusa rendered in pasta. This is a spaghetti-western version of Caravaggio's ''Head of Medusa,'' painted around 1600 on a shield, her mouth frozen open in the scream she emitted while being decapitated. Muniz replaces her virulent, snaky locks with linguine and fills the empty surround with tomato sauce.</p>
        <p>Now that's the spirit.</p>
        <p>PHOTOGRAPHY VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
