<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Australian Title Goes to Korda After He Rides Emotional Wave</title>
    <meta content="01AUSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="992315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Australian Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Korda, Petr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rios, Marcelo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Australian Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DA103AF932A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="900" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Australian Title Goes to Korda After He Rides Emotional Wave</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>MELBOURNE, Australia, Sunday, Feb. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Petr Korda, 30-year-old Czech, wins Australian Open and his first Grand Slam title with world-class pummeling of Marcelo Rios of Chile; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With a motto of better late than never, Petr Korda, the 30-year-old Czech stringbean, won his first Grand Slam title today at the Australian Open with a world-class pummeling of ninth-seeded Marcelo Rios of Chile.</p>
        <p>Korda had the 22-year-old Rios on the ropes from start to finish of this lopsided final in a 6-2, 6-2, 6-2 demonstration of willpower. Korda's domination of this all-lefty affair, the first all-left-handed final at the Australian Open since Roscoe Tanner tamed Guillermo Vilas in 1977, moved him to a career-best second in the world rankings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With a motto of better late than never, Petr Korda, the 30-year-old Czech stringbean, won his first Grand Slam title today at the Australian Open with a world-class pummeling of ninth-seeded Marcelo Rios of Chile.</p>
        <p>Korda had the 22-year-old Rios on the ropes from start to finish of this lopsided final in a 6-2, 6-2, 6-2 demonstration of willpower. Korda's domination of this all-lefty affair, the first all-left-handed final at the Australian Open since Roscoe Tanner tamed Guillermo Vilas in 1977, moved him to a career-best second in the world rankings.</p>
        <p>He also became the oldest Grand Slam champion since Andres Gomez of Ecuador won the French Open in 1990. But Korda was a decidedly less exhausted champion than Gomez had been. After dropping to his knees for a moment to allow the significance of his performance to sink in, he hurled his racquet into the stands and launched into a brief gymnastics routine.</p>
        <p>Although he had threatened to put in a call to Chicago to ask the Bulls' Michael Jordan about the secret of flying, just in case he felt like celebrating in a truly novel fashion, Korda remained earthbound as he celebrated the title it took him 35 Grand Slams to win.</p>
        <p>''I was on the waiting end of this for a long, long time; I didn't believe it could happen, it's like a dream,'' said Korda, whose only previous appearance in a Grand Slam singles final was a loss to Jim Courier at the 1992 French Open.</p>
        <p>Korda paid homage to his definitive 27-minute drubbing of Rios in the opening set with a cartwheel as off balance as Rios's baseline game had been. Then the ebullient new champion zipped through a pair of signature scissor kicks to commemorate the next two sets. Thanks to the crestfallen loser's fast fade in this 85-minute final -- the most one-sided men's championship since Ivan Lendl trounced Korda's countryman Miloslav Mecir, by an identical 6-2, 6-2, 6-2 margin -- further gymnastics were unnecessary.</p>
        <p>Korda's next celebratory act was a sprint and a climb into the friends' box at courtside, where his wife, Regina, and 4-year-old daughter, Jessica, the twin inspirations for his comeback last year after three seasons marred by injury and surgery, were awaiting his embrace. After almost quitting the game in 1995, Korda instead underwent abdominal surgery to repair a hernia, then had groin surgery and finished it all off with sinus surgery last fall two months after his rousing upset of top-seeded Pete Sampras in the United States Open. This year Korda re-entered the top 10, and he is undefeated in 1998 after kicking off the year with the title at Doha. Rios, who will be ranked a career-high fifth, suffered his first defeat of 1998 at the hands of Korda, the player he beat here in the first round in 1997.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I was nervous, but maybe I was excited; I mis-hit too many balls, lost my coordination,'' said Rios, who made 31 unforced errors against just seven winners. Rios broke Korda only once, and dropped his own serve seven times, most notably with a double-fault that cost him the opening set. Rios, who reversed a two-sets-to-none deficit at last year's French Open for the only time in his career, never came close to making a stand today. Once Korda took a 4-1 lead in the third set, Rios all but waved a white flag.</p>
        <p>Accused, sometimes by his own peers, of tanking matches in the past, Rios said he was reformed in that respect and that his no-show in the stadium this afternoon had less to do with a lack of motivation and everything to do with Korda, who came out swinging for the lines and barely missed them.</p>
        <p>''He was hitting the ball hard from the beginning, so I never got my rhythm,'' said Rios, who yielded the match by losing his serve. Though he fended off Korda's initial match point with a service winner, he was beaten on the second by a crisply angled crosscourt forehand pass, Korda's 32d winner of a contest that, thanks to his technical brilliance, turned out to be no contest.</p>
        <p>''I was so nervous yesterday, but today I enjoyed it right from the first point,'' said Korda, who warmed up with a fellow lefty, John McEnroe. ''It's been the ride of my life, and I'm happy I went to the last stop. I feel I'm on top of the world at the moment.''</p>
        <p>MATCH POINTS</p>
        <p>VENUS WILLIAMS and JUSTIN GIMELSTOB each captured a first Grand Slam title Sunday when they defeated fifth-seeded CYRIL SUK and HELENA SUKOVA of the Czech Republic, 6-2, 6-1, in the mixed doubles final. The 21-year-old Gimelstob of Morristown, N.J., said the 17-year-old Williams instigated the brand-new partnership. ''She stalked me,'' he said. ''Venus has some attributes that are really good for mixed doubles. She's a great athlete, very eager, very intelligent.'' Though the duo set no schedule, they decided that a debut like this demanded an encore. ''A partnership is formed,'' Gimelstob said.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
