<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Media Race Enters Waters Still Uncharted</title>
    <meta content="01MEDI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="992245"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE PRESIDENT UNDER FIRE: THE MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scott, Janny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EED6133AF932A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="1434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Media Race Enters Waters Still Uncharted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANNY SCOTT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scott, Janny</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Media coverage of White House sex scandal appears to many in journalism to have blurred boundaries between mainstream and tabloid news; newspapers and news shows have been dominated by story, rife with sensational elements of tabloid news, based heavily on anonymous sources and colored in many instances by what journalists themselves say is speculation and hype; many journalists feel mainstream newspapers have lowered their standards in face of information free-for-all that has resulted from rise of Internet, talk radio and 24-hour cable news (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The story that caromed off the keyboard of an Internet tipster and hurtled through the talk shows to the top of every network news broadcast and major newspaper in the country appears to many in journalism to have blurred the boundaries between mainstream and tabloid news.</p>
        <p>For 10 days now, newspapers and news shows have been dominated by the story, which centers on accusations that President Clinton had sex with a White House intern. It is a story rife with the sensational elements of tabloid news, based heavily on anonymous sources and colored in many instances by what journalists themselves say is speculation and hype.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The story that caromed off the keyboard of an Internet tipster and hurtled through the talk shows to the top of every network news broadcast and major newspaper in the country appears to many in journalism to have blurred the boundaries between mainstream and tabloid news.</p>
        <p>For 10 days now, newspapers and news shows have been dominated by the story, which centers on accusations that President Clinton had sex with a White House intern. It is a story rife with the sensational elements of tabloid news, based heavily on anonymous sources and colored in many instances by what journalists themselves say is speculation and hype.</p>
        <p>Editors have found themselves debating whether to use words like ''semen'' on the nightly news, wondering whether eight times is too often to use ''scandal'' on a single front page, scrutinizing wire stories they are about to publish to guess whether information from an unidentified source is first-, second- or third-hand.</p>
        <p>''This is in many ways the most difficult story I've seen in 25 years in journalism,'' said Sandra Mims Rowe, editor of The Oregonian in Portland and president of the American Society of Newspaper Editors. ''The advances in media, the crush of media, the greatly varying standards that media have and the 24-hour news cycle are all a piece of that.</p>
        <p>''We spout off all these high ideals and goals of journalism,'' Ms. Rowe said. ''And then you get a story where the principal characters are of questionable character, and the details have a salacious aspect, and the whole blasted thing is based on anonymous sources. That combination is troubling.''</p>
        <p>There is little disagreement about whether news organizations should be covering the story, concerning as it does accusations that Mr. Clinton encouraged the intern, Monica S. Lewinsky, to lie about their involvement under oath. Those accusations are under investigation by the independent counsel.</p>
        <p>''We're talking here about very serious allegations if they're true,'' said Peter Jennings, the ABC News anchor. ''These are not tabloid allegations. The independent counsel calls them grave and serious. This is about a power struggle, this is about a political struggle, and then it is about the way the media cover it.''</p>
        <p>How the media have covered it is the source of the discomfort. Many journalists say mainstream news organizations have lowered their standards in the face of the information free-for-all that has resulted from the rise of the Internet, talk radio and 24-hour cable news.</p>
        <p>''My view is that some of the media are out of control in covering this story,'' said James V. Risser, a two-time Pulitzer Prize winner who ran the Washington bureau of the Des Moines Register for nine years. ''Rumor and inadequately sourced information are being rushed into print and on the air.''</p>
        <p>''Much of this is due to competition,'' said Mr. Risser, now director of the Knight journalism fellowship program at Stanford University. ''But competition is not going to be an adequate excuse if elements of this story turn out to be wrong.''</p>
        <p>How the story first surfaced illustrates the problem mainstream news organizations face. When Newsweek magazine opted two weeks ago to hold off on breaking the story, the on-line gossip reporter Matt Drudge heard about it and posted a story about the story on his Drudge Report.</p>
        <p>That report, on Jan. 17, made its way to various Internet news groups, then into the conversation on the ABC News program ''This Week'' the following morning, then onto a CNBC talk show, then onto CBS Radio and finally into major newspapers and network news shows on Wednesday, Jan. 21.</p>
        <p>From there, it soared into almost round-the-clock coverage on CNN and MSNBC. Networks interrupted programs to air White House briefings. Web site use shot through the roof; newsstand sales went up. Newsweek ended up posting on line the story it had not been prepared to put into print.</p>
        <p>''Did the Web give the story additional velocity? Definitely,'' Seth Stevenson wrote in the on-line magazine Slate of the story's trajectory. ''The ethics cops who patrol newspaper and magazine newsrooms can't control the rumors and unsubstantiated stories that people post to the Web.''</p>
        <p>Reporters and editors found themselves chasing rumors that seemed to catapult into truths by simply bouncing back and forth from one medium to the next. Some news organizations published reports they had been unable to verify themselves, adding the disclaimer, ''if true.''</p>
        <p>The subject matter, too, was troublesome. The Chicago Tribune has mostly avoided using the phrase ''oral sex.'' The Christian Science Monitor is referring to semen as ''residue.'' Mr. Jennings found himself on the air trying to interview Candace Bushnell, the sex columnist, about men, sex and power.</p>
        <p>''Even if you wouldn't have covered something in your paper based on your standards, suddenly it has become part of the public policy discussion and you are forced to cover it,'' said David T. Cook, the editor of The Christian Science Monitor in Boston.</p>
        <p>There was a time when a handful of newspapers and networks acted as gatekeepers for the news. But that monopoly is long gone. Now everyone seems to compete with everyone. Some longtime journalists say they fear that the divergent standards of different media have begun to commingle.</p>
        <p>Cable television is widely believed to have changed network television news. And CNN's successful coverage of the Persian Gulf war in 1990 is seen by many as the precursor of the kind of television news coverage that characterized events like the O. J. Simpson case and the death of Diana, Princess of Wales.</p>
        <p>''It started with the gulf war -- the packaging of news, the graphics, the music, the classification of stories,'' said Danny Schechter, a former producer at ABC's ''20/20'' and CNN. ''Everybody benefited by saturation coverage. The more channels, the more a sedated public will respond to this.''</p>
        <p>''If you can get an audience hooked, breathlessly awaiting every fresh disclosure with a recognizable cast of characters they can either love or hate, with a dramatic arc and a certain coming down to a deadline, you have a winner in terms of building audience,'' said Mr. Schechter, who recently published ''The More You Watch the Less You Know'' (Seven Stories Press, 1997).</p>
        <p>Since 1993, the content of network news appears to have shifted. According to the Center for Media and Public Affairs, a nonprofit media research group, coverage of foreign news dropped while coverage of crime and popular culture rose. From 1993 through 1996, one in seven stories was about crime.</p>
        <p>''In the past, mainstream news has been pulled into crime reporting by tabloid competition,'' said Robert Lichter, the political scientist who runs the center, citing the coverage of the Simpson, Andrew Cunanan and JonBenet Ramsey cases. Now, he said, the same is true of sex.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lichter found that the evening news shows of the three major networks did more stories about the White House scandal in the first week than they did about Diana in the first week after her death, and more than the combined first week's coverage of all other scandals involving Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mainstream newspapers, too, have become more accustomed in recent years to covering politicians and sex. Some say the turning point was 1987, when Gary Hart became the first Presidential candidate to be asked by a reporter at a news briefing whether he had ever committed adultery.</p>
        <p>Since then, tabloid newspapers have drawn the mainstream papers into covering Gennifer Flowers and the sex scandal that forced Dick Morris to resign as a consultant to Mr. Clinton. They have covered other sex accusations against Mr. Clinton, too, not the least of which have been those of Paula Corbin Jones.</p>
        <p>Another increasingly common phenomenon is that of reporters being interviewed on the television talk shows that have proliferated since the advent of cable, an arrangement that some say subtly encourages reporters to speculate in ways they would not be comfortable doing in print.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the last 10 days, Ms. Rowe of The Oregonian said, ''I don't remember a time when the talking heads from Washington, many of them wonderful reporters with terrific reputations, have looked more silly and done more damage to the media in general, or when their comments are more inane.''</p>
        <p>THE PRESIDENT UNDER FIRE: THE MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
