<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shuttle Begins 10-Day Technology Flight</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="851987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENDEAVOUR (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EEDF1039F933A15756C0A960958260" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shuttle Begins 10-Day Technology Flight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., May 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The space shuttle Endeavour, beginning a 10-day mission to explore new technologies, on Monday was to deploy and test a large antenna that inflates like a balloon to tennis-court size.</p>
        <p>The experiment, a highlight of the mission, which began today with a problem-free launching, could be the prelude to constructing large, inflatable structures in space that cost significantly less than a comparable solid counterpart, say engineers of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The space shuttle Endeavour, beginning a 10-day mission to explore new technologies, on Monday was to deploy and test a large antenna that inflates like a balloon to tennis-court size.</p>
        <p>The experiment, a highlight of the mission, which began today with a problem-free launching, could be the prelude to constructing large, inflatable structures in space that cost significantly less than a comparable solid counterpart, say engineers of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</p>
        <p>The Endeavour, with six astronauts aboard, began its 11th space mission with an on-time liftoff at 6:30 A.M., when it bolted into a pink-tinged sky on a billowing stream of fire and smoke that brightened into shades of cream and white as it rose in the early sunlight.</p>
        <p>"What a ride! Boy, that was great!" said Col. John H. Casper of the Air Force, the spacecraft commander, who was making his fourth trip into space on a  shuttle. The crew, which includes four other veteran space travelers and a rookie, immediately opened the shuttle's cargo bay doors and began activating a  score of experiments that scientists want to complete before the Endeavour returns to the Kennedy Space Center on May 29.</p>
        <p>One of the experiments is scheduled to take place on Monday, when the astronauts deploy a retrievable Spartan satellite that carries the inflatable antenna experiment. Once the shuttle pulls away by about 400 feet, nitrogen gas  aboard the satellite is to fill the experimental antenna, made of thin Mylar with a reflective surface. Expanding from a container the size of a kitchen table top, the antenna is expected to swell into a disk 48 feet in diameter that is supported by three inflatable struts 92 feet long attached to the Spartan.</p>
        <p>Space agency engineers hope the experiment proves the feasibility of launching spacecraft with inflatable antennas or other major parts. Inflatable structures are much lighter, less complicated and cheaper than conventional mechanical systems, officials said, and should be more reliable because they have fewer moving parts.</p>
        <p>After an hour and a half of tests, including having the Endeavour observe the evenness of its surfaces when illuminated by bright lights, the inflatable structure is to be jettisoned from Spartan, which is to be retrieved by the shuttle the next day. Space agency researchers expect the antenna to plunge through the atmosphere and burn up within seven to eight hours after being cut free.</p>
        <p>The mission involves a record four-satellite rendezvous, including three with a small satellite called PAMS that will be launched from the space shuttle's cargo bay. The experiment will test the concept of stabilizing a satellite in orbit without using small jets. The satellite, which will be left in orbit after the shuttle makes close passes to record its brightly patterned surface, is intended to test the ability of an orbiting body to stabilize and right itself from tumbles.</p>
        <p>Much of the mission's research is to be conducted aboard the Endeavour and on a pressurized module taking up one-fourth of the shuttle's cargo bay. The module, a laboratory that is owned and operated by a commercial company, Spacehab Inc. in Vienna, Va., contains 12 major industrial experiments in such areas as drug development and materials processing. The astronauts move through  a tunnel connecting the front of the shuttle with the Spacehab module to operate the experiments.</p>
        <p>Among the duties of the Endeavour's crew, which includes a Canadian astronaut, is tending a space aquarium built by Canada that is making its first  flight into space. The multi-chambered unit, called the Aquatic Research Facility, contains 1,000 mussel larvae, 32,000 sea urchin eggs and 6,000 starfish embryos as part of an experiment to study marine feeding behavior and the development of calcified tissue.</p>
        <p>Scientists say the sea animal work could help in understanding human bone disorders, including the loss of calcium and strength in the bones of astronauts in space.</p>
        <p>Besides Colonel Casper, the Endeavour's crew consists of Lieut. Col. Curtis L. Brown Jr. of the Air Force, a veteran of two previous flights who is the mission pilot; Comdr. Daniel W. Bursch of the Navy, a mission specialist making  his third space flight; Mario Runco Jr., a mission specialist and meteorologist  who is also making his third shuttle flight; Dr. Marc Garneau, a Canadian electrical engineer making his second flight in space, and Dr. Andrew S. W. Thomas, a naturalized American citizen and mechanical engineer who was born and  educated in Australia and is the payload commander, making his first space flight.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
