<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clash With Shiites And Bomb Attack Leave 4 G.I.'s Dead</title>
    <meta content="18IRAQ$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/18/international/middleeast/18IRAQ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1528083"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: CASUALTIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Karbala (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brinkley, Joel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">al-Hassani, Mahmoud</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Al-Sadr, Moktada</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9500EFDB123EF93BA25753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1026" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clash With Shiites And Bomb Attack Leave 4 G.I.'s Dead</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Clash With Shiites and Bomb Attack Leave 4 G.I.s Dead</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL BRINKLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brinkley, Joel</byline>
      <dateline>KARBALA, Iraq, Oct. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>At least 10 people die, including three American servicemen and two Iraqi security officers, and seven more are wounded when joint United States-Iraqi military patrol is attacked by two dozen heavily armed guards of militant Shiite cleric Mahmoud al-Hassani, who is allied with Maktada al-Sadr, outside Karbala; fourth American is killed by roadside bomb in Baghdad area; total number of American casualties since Pres George W Bush declared end of hostilities is now 101; American task in Iraq appears to be growing more complicated as resistance increases from Shiite Muslim community, which had previously tolerated American presence; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a gritty street at the edge of town, a joint United States-Iraqi military patrol fell into a firefight with two dozen heavily armed guards of an ambitious and militant Shiite cleric near midnight on Thursday, leaving at least 10 people dead, including 3 American servicemen and 2 Iraqi security officers. Seven more Americans were reported wounded in the gun battle.</p>
        <p>With the death of a fourth American, a military policeman killed by a roadside bomb in the Baghdad area on Friday, the 24-hour period was the deadliest for American forces here in a month, pushing the number of American combat deaths since President Bush declared an end to major hostilities to 101.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A U.S.-Iraqi patrol fell into a firefight with guards of a Shiite cleric on Thursday, leaving at least 10 people dead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a gritty street at the edge of town, a joint United States-Iraqi military patrol fell into a firefight with two dozen heavily armed guards of an ambitious and militant Shiite cleric near midnight on Thursday, leaving at least 10 people dead, including 3 American servicemen and 2 Iraqi security officers. Seven more Americans were reported wounded in the gun battle.</p>
        <p>With the death of a fourth American, a military policeman killed by a roadside bomb in the Baghdad area on Friday, the 24-hour period was the deadliest for American forces here in a month, pushing the number of American combat deaths since President Bush declared an end to major hostilities to 101.</p>
        <p>The American task here appears to be growing ever more complicated. Until recently, the American forces had been battling Sunni Muslims, Saddam Hussein loyalists and perhaps other Islamic fundamentalists who have slipped across the border from neighboring countries.</p>
        <p>But in the past week, Americans have begun facing pockets of resistance from elements of the Shiite Muslim community, which constitutes more than 60 percent of Iraq's population and had until now accepted -- or at least tolerated -- the American presence.</p>
        <p>The guards involved in the gun battle work for Mahmoud al-Hassani, a cleric allied with Moktada al-Sadr. Americans blame Mr. Sadr for several recent disturbances and attacks, and last week he proclaimed his own government for Iraq.</p>
        <p>The firefight appeared to signal a hardening resolve on the part of the United States to face down such militant Shiite clerics.</p>
        <p>American and Iraqi forces returned to the scene here on Friday morning, searching for Sheik Hassani, witnesses said. Another brief gun battle ensued, though no one was hurt, they added. But the cleric had fled and remains in hiding, said one of his guards, Ibrahim Moussef, standing in front of his headquarters, where the gunfights occurred.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moussef said he and 23 other men armed with AK-47 assault rifles had fought the American and Iraqi officers for half an hour the night before, and that six of his own men had been killed. Another of the cleric's guards put the number at eight. To crowds of the sheik's followers on the street on Friday afternoon, Mr. Moussef shouted, ''This was an honor. We are ready to die for the sheik.''</p>
        <p>Before Thursday night, Karbala had not been the scene of any significant attacks on American forces since major combat ended. Many people interviewed here in recent months, and even today, seemed pleased by the American presence in Iraq.</p>
        <p>But followers of Sheik Hassani hold a different view. A poster on the wall adjacent to the scene of the shootout calls Iraqis who cooperate with the Americans ''traitors.''</p>
        <p>American officials in Iraq hold Sheik Hassani's reputed ally, Mr. Sadr, accountable for several recent disturbances, including an ambush last week in which two American soldiers were killed in Sadr City, the taking over of the district council office there and a gunfight in Karbala earlier this week in which at least three Iraqis were killed and several followers of a rival sheik were taken hostage.</p>
        <p>This week, a spokesman for the military said the United States intended to hold Mr. Sadr and others like him ''accountable for their actions.''</p>
        <p>In an unusually terse and serious statement on Friday afternoon, Lt. Col. George Krivo, a military spokesman, said that the firefight in Karbala ''was caused by noncompliant forces,'' adding that it ''occurred after someone came and reported that a number of men were congregating on the road in front of the mosque after curfew.'' Both the Iraqi police and American military police officers went to the scene, he said.</p>
        <p>The cleric's guards opened fire first, using rifles and rocket-propelled grenades, Colonel Krivo said. Mr. Moussef said the Americans had fired first.</p>
        <p>Colonel Krivo said American forces did not know whether Sheik Hassani ''was personally involved or not,'' but that he had made anti-American statements before. Mr. Moussef said the Americans had tried to take away the guards' weapons.</p>
        <p>The United States has said the many irregular militias and guard forces in the south must disarm, but until Friday they had made no particular effort to enforce the order.</p>
        <p>''We told them we are your friends, but we are here to protect the cleric,'' Mr. Moussef said. The Americans then returned to their Humvee vehicles and opened fire, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moussef said he was among the guards firing on the military police. Asked if he had killed anyone, he shook his head.</p>
        <p>There was no military presence apparent anywhere inside Karbala this afternoon; the sheik's surviving guards mingled in front of their headquarters without interference. But American and other foreign forces ringed the city, checking vehicles as they came and went.</p>
        <p>The sheik's headquarters are on the edge of town, about half a mile from Imam Abbas mosque at the city's center. In nearby streets, Iraqis offered a variety of opinions about the events overnight and the American presence.</p>
        <p>''Americans should not come in here; it is a holy city,'' said Hiday Ibrahim, a baker. ''We are happy to see Saddam Hussein gone,'' he added, ''but all the promises Bush and the Americans made until now have not been fulfilled.''</p>
        <p>Safa Abu Ziad, who owns a stand that sells sweet tea 100 yards from Sheik Hassani's office, chastised the sheik's men for loitering in the street, armed, when the American-Iraqi patrol came by.</p>
        <p>''To tell you the truth, we owe the Americans a lot,'' he said. ''We lived 31 years without democracy. The Americans brought us these things.''</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: CASUALTIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
