<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Insurer's Financial Weakness May Imperil Trade Center Project</title>
    <meta content="08insure" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/08/nyregion/08insure.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1824725"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Royal &amp; Sun Alliance Insurance</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bagli, Charles V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Silverstein, Larry A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom Tower (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom Tower (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E4DB113FF93BA35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Insurer's Financial Weakness May Imperil Trade Center Project</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Insurer’s Financial Weakness May Imperil Trade Center Project</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER and CHARLES V. BAGLI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bagli, Charles V; Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Financial weakness by insurer Royal &amp; SunAlliance USA may imperil rebuilding of World Trade Center site in New York City because of possible failure to pay $250 million claim by developer Larry A Silverstein and Port Authority of New York and New Jersey (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new financing gap may be about to open in the rebuilding plan for ground zero. One of the insurance companies that provided coverage for the World Trade Center is in financial trouble and may not be able to pay the $250 million claim that the developer Larry A. Silverstein and the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey say they are owed as a result of the destruction of the complex by terrorists in 2001.</p>
        <p>The money from Royal &amp; SunAlliance USA, the American subsidiary of a big British insurer, Royal Sun Alliance, represents less than 3 percent of the total cost of the massive project, now estimated at $9 billion. But with a fragile budget and rapidly escalating construction costs, every dollar counts. Mr. Silverstein's aides say he may miss construction deadlines if the insurer fails to pay up, or he could be forced to scale back the project, which includes the 1,776-foot-tall Freedom Tower and three other skyscrapers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A new financing gap may be about to open in the rebuilding plan for ground zero.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A new financing gap may be about to open in the rebuilding plan for ground zero. One of the insurance companies that provided coverage for the World Trade Center is in financial trouble and may not be able to pay the $250 million claim that the developer Larry A. Silverstein and the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey say they are owed as a result of the destruction of the complex by terrorists in 2001.</p>
        <p>The money from Royal &amp; SunAlliance USA, the American subsidiary of a big British insurer, Royal Sun Alliance, represents less than 3 percent of the total cost of the massive project, now estimated at $9 billion. But with a fragile budget and rapidly escalating construction costs, every dollar counts. Mr. Silverstein's aides say he may miss construction deadlines if the insurer fails to pay up, or he could be forced to scale back the project, which includes the 1,776-foot-tall Freedom Tower and three other skyscrapers.</p>
        <p>''This puts at risk the schedule and the budget for the rebuilding,'' said Janno Lieber, the World Trade Center project director for the Silverstein organization. ''It creates new uncertainty, which is just what downtown doesn't need.''</p>
        <p>It has always been a struggle to get enough money to rebuild ground zero.</p>
        <p>The insurance proceeds, about $4.6 billion, only covered about half the total cost. The other half had to be made up with a combination of state, federal and private financing.</p>
        <p>The insurance dispute grew out of a move by Royal Sun Alliance to sever its relationship with Royal &amp; SunAlliance USA, which provided a part of the trade center coverage.</p>
        <p>The subsidiary has been in financial trouble for several years. Now, the parent company says it no longer wants to prop up the American unit. With a final cash infusion of $287.5 million, Royal Sun Alliance hopes to turn the subsidiary over to a group of American executives and be done with it.</p>
        <p>''We are a business, not a charity,'' said George Culmer, the chief financial officer for the British insurer, at a hearing called by the Department of Insurance in Delaware, where the company has its American headquarters.</p>
        <p>The hearing officer, Lawrence A. Hamermesh, a professor at Widener University Law School, concluded that Royal &amp; SunAlliance USA, which would change its name to Arrowpoint Capital Corporation, has enough money to pay its claims to Mr. Silverstein, General Motors and other American corporations. He has recommended that the deal be approved.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Silverstein's group and other American corporate customers argue that Mr. Hamermesh is overly optimistic about the financially troubled company's ability to pay up. ''If the parent company pulls out, we don't think we'll get paid anything like what we're owed,'' said Marc Wolinsky, a lawyer for Mr. Silverstein.</p>
        <p>The Silverstein Group and other policyholders have been given until tomorrow to file objections.</p>
        <p>Last fall, state and city officials, the Port Authority and Mr. Silverstein agreed on a framework for rebuilding the 16-acre trade center site by 2012. The Port Authority, which owns the land, took financial responsibility for building the Freedom Tower, whose projected cost stands at $3 billion.</p>
        <p>The Port Authority is also building a $2.2 billion transit hub and working with government officials and private business leaders to erect a memorial and museum.</p>
        <p>Mr. Silverstein, in turn, is building three other towers along the eastern edge of the site, with a combination of insurance proceeds, tax-free Liberty Bonds and private borrowing, with the intent to lease space to the Port Authority and other agencies.</p>
        <p>The developer and others have long complained that the insurers have been slow to pay. The problem with Royal &amp; SunAlliance USA has been slowly evolving. The company encountered financial difficulty several years ago because of claims from the trade center attack and because of a wave of new claims on policies it sold years ago to General Motors and other corporations as protection against lawsuits over illnesses caused by asbestos.</p>
        <p>In 2003, the company stopped selling insurance, dismissed most of its 6,317 employees and went into what insurers call ''runoff,'' a condition in which an insurer does nothing but pay claims.</p>
        <p>A runoff is almost never good for customers. That is because with no new income from sales and with the prospect of new claims arising, managers have to ration the available money. They generate income by investing that money and they also try to persuade policyholders to settle claims for less than they expected -- in other words, take a financial haircut. If there's money left over after all claims have been resolved, it goes to the insurance company and its owners.</p>
        <p>The World Trade Center was already in danger of receiving less than the $255 million that a federal court had ruled Royal Sun's subsidiary owed as part of the $4.6 billion that the courts ordered all of the trade center's insurers to pay. Mr. Wolinsky, the lawyer for Mr. Silverstein, said the risk jumped sharply in September when the British parent first moved to abandon the subsidiary.</p>
        <p>If the British insurer continued doing business in the United States, Mr. Wolinsky acknowledged, it would have the same incentive to pay as little on claims as possible. But paying nothing, or next to nothing, would damage its standing with rating agencies and customers, Mr. Wolinsky said. In self-defense, he said, the British firm would be forced to put more money into the American unit.</p>
        <p>''There have been several runoffs in the United States in which a parent has kept the subsidiary going because of the reputational interest,'' Mr. Wolinsky said.</p>
        <p>Daniel L. Doctoroff, the deputy mayor for economic development, said that there would be serious financial problems with the rebuilding effort if Royal failed to pay the full amount. So far, he said, the insurer had paid only $5.6 million of the original $255 million claim.</p>
        <p>''It would create a major hole and there's no obvious replacement,'' he said. ''Our rebuilding plan depended on insurers living up to their obligations, which have been affirmed by the Court of Appeals.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
