<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aqueduct Jockeys Face Safety Issues in Icy Cold</title>
    <meta content="08racing" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/08/sports/othersports/08racing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1824723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Aqueduct Race Track</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jockeys, Drivers and Trainers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finley, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Barbaro (Race Horse)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4DB113FF93BA35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aqueduct Jockeys Face Safety Issues in Icy Cold</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Aqueduct Jockeys Face Safety Issues in Icy Cold</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL FINLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finley, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jockeys complain that cold weather at Aqueduct could result in injuries; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chuck Lopez knows that riding on a February afternoon at Aqueduct can be a pretty miserable experience for a jockey. He has been riding here during the last 14 winters, braving frigid temperatures, performing in front of empty grandstands and riding the type of ordinary horses that will never take him to the Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>Like most jockeys who ride at Aqueduct during the grim winter months, he has goals, but they are modest ones: He wants to make some money and he wants to avoid getting hurt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Like most jockeys who ride at Aqueduct during the grim winter months, Chuck Lopez has goals, but they are modest ones: He wants to make some money and avoid getting hurt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chuck Lopez knows that riding on a February afternoon at Aqueduct can be a pretty miserable experience for a jockey. He has been riding here during the last 14 winters, braving frigid temperatures, performing in front of empty grandstands and riding the type of ordinary horses that will never take him to the Kentucky Derby.</p>
        <p>Like most jockeys who ride at Aqueduct during the grim winter months, he has goals, but they are modest ones: He wants to make some money and he wants to avoid getting hurt.</p>
        <p>''I'm not trying to be the leading rider here or anything,'' Lopez said yesterday between races at a bitterly cold Aqueduct. ''I don't force the issue and ride every race. First and foremost, it's too cold to do that. All I want to do is come out of here in one piece and go to Monmouth Park when they open in May.''</p>
        <p>Lopez will tolerate a lot. On a day when the temperature never got above the low 20s, he rode in five races, won none, was heckled by a fan after he lost aboard the betting favorite in the third race and then headed home through rush-hour traffic to Manalapan, N.J. It was a day to be endured rather than savored, and Lopez was willing to do so. In fact, Lopez can deal with just about anything in horse racing except safety measures that he considers substandard.</p>
        <p>And so it was that Lopez was among a sizable group of jockeys who refused to ride at Aqueduct last Saturday after a spill in the fifth race injured jockey Norberto Arroyo Jr. and left two horses dead. Arroyo was immediately sent to Jamaica Hospital Medical Center, a Queens facility that some riders have said has not provided the best care.</p>
        <p>Because of the impromptu protest, New York Racing Association officials were forced to cancel the remaining four races on the Saturday card. NYRA also scrapped Sunday's entire program because of concerns about the subfreezing weather and the possibility that the jockeys would again refuse to ride.</p>
        <p>The jockeys' concerns about Jamaica Hospital first surfaced last Thursday, when jockey José Santos was sent there after sustaining serious injuries in a spill that also led to the death of a horse. Rita Santos, the jockey's wife, said that doctors at Jamaica had overlooked some of her husband's injuries and failed to provide the sort of hands-on care she believed he needed.</p>
        <p>''I never had an opportunity to ask the questions I thought needed to be asked because no doctors ever showed up,'' she said.</p>
        <p>About seven hours after he was admitted, Santos, against the advice of the doctors treating him at Jamaica, checked himself out and went to North Shore University Hospital in Manhasset. North Shore is a prestigious hospital and is where jockeys are normally sent after accidents at Belmont Park, which straddles the Queens-Nassau border. Belmont takes over from Aqueduct for racing in late spring, summer and early fall.</p>
        <p>''I understand that a lot of the jockeys have a relationship with North Shore and they are comfortable there and that's where this patient wanted to go,'' said Ole Pederson, Jamaica's vice president for emergency medicine. ''But to achieve that goal, some negative comments were made about us, and I think that was counterproductive.</p>
        <p>''No one ever expressed any concerns or issues to us while he was here,'' Pederson added in reference to Santos. ''We are very comfortable with the care that was provided in this case.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Joseph Bosco, a former doctor at Jamaica Hospital who was asked by the hospital to review Santos's complaints, said Santos was examined by doctors at Jamaica, including one specializing in spinal problems.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, a group of jockeys and NYRA officials met to discuss the hospital dispute. It was explained to the jockeys that the emergency medical technicians working at Aqueduct must abide by regulations that stipulate that any person with possible life-threatening injuries be taken to the nearest hospital that is a Level I trauma center.</p>
        <p>Jamaica Hospital is about 10 minutes from Aqueduct; North Shore is 25 minutes away. The solution reached at Tuesday's meeting stipulates that Aqueduct jockeys with less-severe injuries can be taken to North Shore; more serious cases will be sent to Jamaica. Satisfied with the agreement, the jockeys returned to work yesterday, the first day of regularly scheduled races since Sunday.</p>
        <p>The hospital dispute underscores the dangers inherent in horse racing, the only sport in which an ambulance follows the competitors around the playing field. According to the Jockeys' Guild, an average of 1.5 jockeys are killed each year while racing. Of course, far more horses die, an issue dramatized by the death last month of Barbaro.</p>
        <p>Lopez, 46, has had his share of injuries in his racing career. He has had four spills within the last three years and, early in his career, broke four vertebrae. But yesterday, his biggest problem was that he was cold.</p>
        <p>''It's awful out there,'' he said when asked about the conditions. ''You get winded because you're pushing these horses and you're trying to win and that ice-cold air gets to you. It's miserable. You're uncomfortable most of the time.''</p>
        <p>Lopez said that during a good week, he could clear as much as $15,000 from his share of the purses. That is what keeps him coming back to New York and makes him put up with the cold, one of the sport's dreariest racetracks and, ultimately, the perils that make hospital care an ongoing issue for every jockey.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
