<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Treasury Notes and Bonds Move Up</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="621630"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TREASURY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DE153CF936A25754C0A965958260" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Treasury Notes and Bonds Move Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FUERBRINGER, JONATHAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bond market got the kind of news it likes yesterday -- that inflation is low and economic growth is moderate -- and traders responded with enthusiasm, pushing prices of Treasury notes and bonds higher.</p>
        <p>The buying sent the yield on the 30-year bond down to another 16-year low and yields on Treasury notes to their lowest levels in more than two decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The bond market got the kind of news it likes yesterday -- that inflation is low and economic growth is moderate -- and traders responded with enthusiasm, pushing prices of Treasury notes and bonds higher.</p>
        <p>The buying sent the yield on the 30-year bond down to another 16-year low and yields on Treasury notes to their lowest levels in more than two decades.</p>
        <p>The question from here is how much further prices can rise and yields, which move in the oppositie direction, can fall. Traders, portfolio managers and anlaysts seem to be cautious -- aware of the possibility of a sudden reversal with the market at levels not seen in decades.</p>
        <p>But for the time being, the weakened state of the economy and inflation, and the progress in Congress of President Clinton's deficit reduction plan, seem to favor lower interest rates. No Signs of Bouncing Back</p>
        <p>"The economy is not showing signs of bouncing back and the whole political process is restrictive from the economic point of view," said John Costas, managing director of trading and sales at the First Boston Corporation. "I think that means lower yields."</p>
        <p>In trading yesterday, the price of the 30-year bond due in February 2023 rose 23/32 , and the yield fell to 6.56 percent, from 6.61 percent Tuesday. It was the fith day in a row that the yield dipped to its lowest level since the Treasury began to issue 30-year bonds regularly in May 1977.</p>
        <p>The price of the 10-year note rose 11/32 and the yield fell to 5.70 percent, its lowest since the beginning of the 1970's. Yields on other Treasury notes fell as did the discount rates on Treasury bills.</p>
        <p>The news that the Consumer Price Index for June was unchanged and that retail sales for last month rose just four-tenths of 1 percent did serve to end conclusively any thought of a rebound in inflation and a raising of interest rates by the Federal Reserve -- for now.</p>
        <p>It will be easy now to dismiss the unexpectedly high rise in consumer and producer price inflation in the first four months of the year. The Consumer Price Index through April was rising at a 4.3 percent annual rate and had prompted two sharp selloffs in the bond market that pushed the yield of the 30-year bond over 7 percent temporarily.</p>
        <p>But in the last two months, the Consumer Price Index rose just one-tenth of 1 percent in May and was unchanged in June, bringing down the annual rate of increase for the first six months of the year to 3.1 percent, just above the 2.9 percent increase for all of 1992.</p>
        <p>But the key to the inflation outlook continues to be the pace of economic growth. If the economy begins to grow faster than 3 percent in the second half of the year, then investors may begin to worry that there will be inflationary pressures building up in 1994. And that belief could stop a credit market rally.</p>
        <p>"The real issue is to what extent the economy improves," said Donald Fine, the chief market analyst at Chase Securities Inc.</p>
        <p>Even with the strong car sales reported yesterday in the first 10 days of July, the June increase in retail sales of four-tenths of 1 percent still points to modest growth for now.</p>
        <p>And it is likely that the outlook for the economy will continue to be modest because of the impact of the tax increases that are included in the President's deficit reduction plan. While problems in reaching a compromise between the House and Senate versions might spook the bond market from time to time, the bottom line is that the program will be a drag on the the economy. Buying of Treasury Securities</p>
        <p>The rally in the market yesterday, however, was not all pushed by the good news on inflation. Prices were forced higher and yields lower by trading strategies and the continued buying of Treasury securities by state and local governments refinancing older, higher-interest-rate tax-exempt bonds at lower interest rates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Costas of First Boston said that a lot of traders began yesterday thinking that prices were very high and yields low. In addition, some thought that the good news on inflation had already been factored in. So they decided to short bonds and notes, selling them in anticipation of buying them back at lower prices.</p>
        <p>Instead there was slow, steady buying that soon forced many of the short-selling traders to buy back bonds and notes to avoid losses, which pushed prices higher. Some of this steady buying was from cities and towns that put Treasury securities into escrow accounts to pay off their old high-interest-rate bonds.</p>
        <p>CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
