<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Dance; Routines That Avoid the Routine</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="621654"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DANCING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AMERICAN DANCE FESTIVAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COSTA RICA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DIQUIS TIQUIS (DANCE CO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TREJOS, SANDRA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOSATTI, ALEJANDRO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Costa Rica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Costa Rica</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">American Dance Festival (Durham, NC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D6173FF936A25754C0A965958260" item-length="806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Dance; Routines That Avoid the Routine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KISSELGOFF, ANNA</byline>
      <dateline>DURHAM, N.C., July 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Diquis Tiquis, a two-member dance troupe from Costa Rica, is typical of the foreign companies that have been both nurtured and introduced at the American Dance Festival in recent years. That is, their distinctiveness is immediately apparent but they are also part of a general international trend that, for better or for worse, plays down the very danciness of dance.</p>
        <p>Whether nearly nude as nature's children in a ritual of their own making or all dressed up with no place to go, Sandra Trejos and Alejandro Tosatti have an obvious originality.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Diquis Tiquis, a two-member dance troupe from Costa Rica, is typical of the foreign companies that have been both nurtured and introduced at the American Dance Festival in recent years. That is, their distinctiveness is immediately apparent but they are also part of a general international trend that, for better or for worse, plays down the very danciness of dance.</p>
        <p>Whether nearly nude as nature's children in a ritual of their own making or all dressed up with no place to go, Sandra Trejos and Alejandro Tosatti have an obvious originality.</p>
        <p>As the group's dancers and choreographers, they have an admirably personalized performing style. Mr. Tosatti, a modern Pierrot, is all rubber-faced grimace; Miss Trejos has an eloquent physical plasticity that stretches her lean body into elongated shapes that retract into a crumpled grotesque heap. Both performers favor a mimelike approach to detailed dramatic gesture and facial expression, but can also explore more expansive ways of moving.</p>
        <p>As Diquis Tiquis showed on Tuesday night, in four works presented here by the festival at Duke University's Reynolds Industries Theater, its choreographers are also inspired by Costa Rican material. The name of the company reportedly comes from an Indian term for a serpent, and "Los Gemelos" ("The Twins"), one of the program's works, was influenced by pre-Columbian art. Even the male-female relationships portrayed in other pieces might easily be linked to Latin American stereotypes in which the woman follows rather than leads but occasionally gets her revenge.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, for all the specifically personal and national influences in their work, Miss Trejos and Mr. Tosatti seem, like so many visiting choreographers at the festival, to be avoiding the conventional dance values. That there is movement but not a dance step in sight is not a criticism. But too often, the feeling is that the aim is chiefly to avoid established dance idioms or to make up for lack of dance training.</p>
        <p>Many of the results are not at all uninteresting, as was obvious in an informal showing over the weekend of the new Silesian Dance Theater, directed by Jacek Luminiski, from Bytom, Poland. The terrific speed, recklessness and force with which the company's men and women threw themselves around with athletic daring were astonishingly impressive. These were kinetic elements coherently channeled into a strong emotional expressiveness.</p>
        <p>If one tendency on the international circuit is to throw partners around, another is the genre loosely known as dance theater, to which Diquis Tiquis also belongs. That is, theatrical images take precedence over movement for its own sake; in this case, gesture is always used with dramatic connotations and bodies are molded into illustrative shapes.</p>
        <p>The molding is done best by Miss Trejos, who is clearly a highly trained dancer; the more mobile face of the two performers belongs to Mr. Tosatti, who is a theatrical director. Their dance theater gains from this blend of opposites, and their production values (the all-important lighting is by Mr. Tossati) are immaculate. Essentially, however, they are theatrical miniaturists.</p>
        <p>Their program's best piece was "Ladoalado" ("Side by Side/Winged Side"), to a light percussion score by Kevin Volans. Mr. Tosatti, in suit and tie, and Miss Trejos, in a see-through Victorian blouse, sit side by side on two chairs. As uncommunicative as a couple in an Antonioni film, the pair define their mutual boredom through a choreographed tilting of their chairs: each away from the other. An aura of suspicion creeps in, as the tilting is embroidered by grimaces and gestures. The chairs are rearranged, so that the woman peers from behind the man, who seems to age pathetically and lose his dominance.</p>
        <p>Adriana Castanos, a Mexican choreographer, replays the battle of the sexes in a more humorous and cleanly drawn piece, to a score by Wim Mertens. Dressed in white underwear, the man and woman hold hands but Miss Trejos suddenly looks at her other hand. She will do the same at the end, when the gesture will acquire a different meaning, simply because a relationship has since developed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tosatti, a born comic, courts his partner, miming the crooning heard on tape. Impish, Miss Trejos deflates his efforts. Cringing, he seems to shrivel up as he retreats.  She is left alone.</p>
        <p>"La Virgen del Banquito" ("The Virgin of the Stool") has Miss Trejos evoking a life cycle while she manipulates a stool as an all-purpose prop. The wild girl, stretching freely to jungle and bird sounds, is transformed cleverly, into an old figure in a rocking chair. The solo had the same acrobatic finesse as "Los Gemelos" with its two topless performers moving from masked rituals into linked sculptural shapes. The presumed deeper meaning remained elusive.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
