<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Xerox Is Set to Introduce Its First Household Product</title>
    <meta content="Y18COPY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="951404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer Printers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Xerox Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hewlett-Packard Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Deutsch, Claudia H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Color</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Printers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6DD113FF93BA2575BC0A961958260" item-length="422" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Xerox Is Set to Introduce Its First Household Product</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAUDIA H. DEUTSCH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Deutsch, Claudia H</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Xerox Corp to offer its first household product, combination color scanner, printer and copier with simplified software for people who like computers but are not computer sophisticates; is first to offer low-end multi-function document processing product with color scanner, beating out Hewlett-Packard Co (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For decades Xerox's brand name has been a household word. Now, for the first time, the Xerox Corporation has a household product.</p>
        <p>Today, the big Stamford, Conn. document company plans to introduce the Document Home Centre, a $499 combination color scanner, printer and copier with simplified software aimed at people who like technology but are not whizzes at it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For decades Xerox's brand name has been a household word. Now, for the first time, the Xerox Corporation has a household product.</p>
        <p>Today, the big Stamford, Conn. document company plans to introduce the Document Home Centre, a $499 combination color scanner, printer and copier with simplified software aimed at people who like technology but are not whizzes at it.</p>
        <p>''This is our way of proving that yes, Xerox really can create a fun product for people who like computers, but are not computer sophisticates,'' said Gerald M. Murch, vice president of Xerox's Connected Personal Products Group.</p>
        <p>The Home Centre is the first low-end multi-function document processing product that incorporates a color scanner. Practically speaking, that makes it the first all-in-one product that a 10-year-old can easily use to create and E-mail (or snail mail, of course) a color family photograph into a Christmas card for Grandma.</p>
        <p>Most industry watchers have come to expect such innovations from the Hewlett-Packard Company, which commands close to 65 percent of the lucrative small office and home office market for low-end printers and copiers. Yet most analysts say they do not expect Hewlett-Packard to incorporate color scanners into its products before next spring.</p>
        <p>''Hewlett-Packard will come back swinging, but it won't necessarily win the battle,'' said Andrew Johnson, an analyst with the market research firm Dataquest.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnson said that about $280 million of multi-function devices had been sold to small offices and homes so far this year. By 2001, he expects industry revenues to top $1 billion.</p>
        <p>While Hewlett-Packard acknowledges that Xerox has beaten it with a color scan product, it says it is way ahead of its East Coast rival in the small office market.</p>
        <p>''We thoroughly understand the customer, and we know how to follow through with subsequent products,'' said Jeremy James, a spokesman for Hewlett-Packard's consumer products group, who added that his company has been selling through mass market retailers like CompUSA and Wal-Mart Stores for more than five years.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Xerox executives have had their share of worries over their lack of consumer experience. ''We've had plenty of internal debate on whether we wouldn't be better off sticking to the office products that we know best,'' Mr. Murch said.</p>
        <p>Xerox is trying to make up for lost time. Along with the Home Centre, it also plans to introduce today a belated upgrade of the Docucenter 250, called the Document Work Centre 450c, selling for $549.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
