<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS BRIEFS</title>
    <meta content="25bizdigest" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1742216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DB1F3EF936A15751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS BRIEFS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mining Company Glamis Gold Agrees to Buy Western Silver of Canada for $1 Billion  Glamis Gold said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the Western Silver Corporation for 1.2 billion Canadian dollars ($1.04 billion). Glamis said it would pay 0.688 share for Western Silver and spin off the copper assets of the combined company. The bid is worth 24.78 Canadian dollars for each Western Silver share, a premium of 27 percent over Thursday's closing price. Acquiring Western Silver will increase Glamis's gold reserves by 85 percent, mostly from the Penasquito project in Mexico, the chief executive, C. Kevin McArthur, said on a conference call. Glamis is based in Reno, Nev., and Western Silver is based in Vancouver. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
        <p>An Apollo Management Founder Plans His Own Firm  Michael Gross, a co-founder with Leon Black of the New York buyout firm Apollo Management, has resigned to start his own company. Mr. Gross, who said he is interested in the ''convergence of private equity and hedge funds,'' declined to be more specific about his plans. ''It's time for a change, to do something on my own,'' he said in an interview. Mr. Gross has run the Apollo Investment Corporation, Apollo Management's debt-investment unit, since its founding in February 2004. Mr. Gross will continue to serve as non-executive chairman of Apollo Investment. Mr. Black declined to comment. An Apollo co-founder, John Hannan, will take over as chief executive of Apollo Investment, the company said. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
        <p>U.S. Opens Free Trade Agreement With El Salvador  A free trade agreement with El Salvador will take effect March 1, the Bush administration said yesterday, leaving behind for the moment five other Latin American nations that are supposed to be part of the Central American Free Trade Agreement. The United States trade representative, Rob Portman, praised El Salvador for the strides it has made in revising laws and regulations necessary to meet the commitments it made in the trade agreement. He said the administration would continue to work with the five other countries to ''ensure timely and full implementation'' of the agreement. (AP)</p>
        <p>Citigroup Says S.E.C. Expands Venezuelan Inquiry  Citigroup said yesterday that the Securities and Exchange Commission had expanded an accounting inquiry into the bank's activities in Argentina, and had subpoenaed materials for four additional years. In an annual report filed with the agency, Citigroup said the S.E.C. has subpoenaed witness testimony and information over its accounting and internal controls for the years 1997 to 2004. Citigroup, which is based in New York, previously said the agency's subpoenas covered only 2001 to 2004. Citigroup has said it believes the inquiry is related to investments, business activities and allowances for bad loans in Argentina in the fourth quarter of 2001 and first quarter of 2002, at the height of that country's fiscal crisis. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>Colgate-Palmolive Discloses Succession Plans for Chief  The Colgate-Palmolive Company's chief executive, Reuben Mark, said yesterday that the company planned for its president and chief operating officer, Ian M. Cook, to assume the title of chief executive in 2007. Mr. Mark said during an analyst conference yesterday that Colgate's board also asked for him to remain chairman for a brief period yet to be determined. Mr. Mark has been chief executive of Colgate since 1984 and has been with Colgate for 43 years. Mr. Cook has been operating chief since 2004 and added the title of president in July. (DOW JONES/AP)</p>
        <p>General Motors Maintains Executives' Option Grants  General Motors said yesterday it was maintaining stock option grants to senior executives at 2005 levels, according to a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. The chief executive, Rick Wagoner, left, was granted options to buy 400,000 shares of the company's common stock, according to the filing. The chief financial officer, Frederick A. Henderson, and the vice chairmen, John M. Devine and Robert A. Lutz, were granted options on 160,000 shares each. The options, which can be exercised over three years, give Mr. Wagoner and the other executives the right to buy G.M. stock at $20.90 a share. The value of the options depends on whether G.M. can recover from its recent weakness and raise its share price. At the closing price of $19.99 yesterday, the options would be worthless. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>Three Executives Leave Gap, One Temporarily  The apparel retailer Gap said yesterday that two vice presidents had left the company and a third was on leave and planned to return at a later date. Alan Barocas, the senior vice president for real estate, retired after 25 years with the company, and Jyothi Rao, vice president for merchandising for Gap's Forth &amp; Town unit, has gone on personal leave and will return at a later date. Felix Carbullido, vice president and general manager of gap.com, also left. Previous executive departures provoked investor concern that the company, struggling with declining earnings and sales, was facing an exodus of experienced people, but a Gap representative, Kris Marubio, said the most recent exits were part of the ebb and flow of business. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>Brazil's Economic Growth Falls Short of Forecasts  Brazil's economy expanded less than analysts expected in the fourth quarter as a stronger currency prompted some manufacturers to curb output and a drought in the south damaged rice and soybean crops. Gross domestic product, the broadest measure of a country's output of goods and services, grew 1.4 percent in the period from a year ago, following growth of 1 percent in the third quarter, the government said. Brazil's economy expanded 2.3 percent for all of 2005, less than half the 2004 growth rate of 4.9 percent. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mining Company Glamis Gold Agrees to Buy Western Silver of Canada for $1 Billion  Glamis Gold said yesterday that it had agreed to buy the Western Silver Corporation for 1.2 billion Canadian dollars ($1.04 billion). Glamis said it would pay 0.688 share for Western Silver and spin off the copper assets of the combined company. The bid is worth 24.78 Canadian dollars for each Western Silver share, a premium of 27 percent over Thursday's closing price. Acquiring Western Silver will increase Glamis's gold reserves by 85 percent, mostly from the Penasquito project in Mexico, the chief executive, C. Kevin McArthur, said on a conference call. Glamis is based in Reno, Nev., and Western Silver is based in Vancouver. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
        <p>An Apollo Management Founder Plans His Own Firm  Michael Gross, a co-founder with Leon Black of the New York buyout firm Apollo Management, has resigned to start his own company. Mr. Gross, who said he is interested in the ''convergence of private equity and hedge funds,'' declined to be more specific about his plans. ''It's time for a change, to do something on my own,'' he said in an interview. Mr. Gross has run the Apollo Investment Corporation, Apollo Management's debt-investment unit, since its founding in February 2004. Mr. Gross will continue to serve as non-executive chairman of Apollo Investment. Mr. Black declined to comment. An Apollo co-founder, John Hannan, will take over as chief executive of Apollo Investment, the company said. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
        <p>U.S. Opens Free Trade Agreement With El Salvador  A free trade agreement with El Salvador will take effect March 1, the Bush administration said yesterday, leaving behind for the moment five other Latin American nations that are supposed to be part of the Central American Free Trade Agreement. The United States trade representative, Rob Portman, praised El Salvador for the strides it has made in revising laws and regulations necessary to meet the commitments it made in the trade agreement. He said the administration would continue to work with the five other countries to ''ensure timely and full implementation'' of the agreement. (AP)</p>
        <p>Citigroup Says S.E.C. Expands Venezuelan Inquiry  Citigroup said yesterday that the Securities and Exchange Commission had expanded an accounting inquiry into the bank's activities in Argentina, and had subpoenaed materials for four additional years. In an annual report filed with the agency, Citigroup said the S.E.C. has subpoenaed witness testimony and information over its accounting and internal controls for the years 1997 to 2004. Citigroup, which is based in New York, previously said the agency's subpoenas covered only 2001 to 2004. Citigroup has said it believes the inquiry is related to investments, business activities and allowances for bad loans in Argentina in the fourth quarter of 2001 and first quarter of 2002, at the height of that country's fiscal crisis. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>Colgate-Palmolive Discloses Succession Plans for Chief  The Colgate-Palmolive Company's chief executive, Reuben Mark, said yesterday that the company planned for its president and chief operating officer, Ian M. Cook, to assume the title of chief executive in 2007. Mr. Mark said during an analyst conference yesterday that Colgate's board also asked for him to remain chairman for a brief period yet to be determined. Mr. Mark has been chief executive of Colgate since 1984 and has been with Colgate for 43 years. Mr. Cook has been operating chief since 2004 and added the title of president in July. (DOW JONES/AP)</p>
        <p>General Motors Maintains Executives' Option Grants  General Motors said yesterday it was maintaining stock option grants to senior executives at 2005 levels, according to a filing with the Securities and Exchange Commission. The chief executive, Rick Wagoner, left, was granted options to buy 400,000 shares of the company's common stock, according to the filing. The chief financial officer, Frederick A. Henderson, and the vice chairmen, John M. Devine and Robert A. Lutz, were granted options on 160,000 shares each. The options, which can be exercised over three years, give Mr. Wagoner and the other executives the right to buy G.M. stock at $20.90 a share. The value of the options depends on whether G.M. can recover from its recent weakness and raise its share price. At the closing price of $19.99 yesterday, the options would be worthless. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>Three Executives Leave Gap, One Temporarily  The apparel retailer Gap said yesterday that two vice presidents had left the company and a third was on leave and planned to return at a later date. Alan Barocas, the senior vice president for real estate, retired after 25 years with the company, and Jyothi Rao, vice president for merchandising for Gap's Forth &amp; Town unit, has gone on personal leave and will return at a later date. Felix Carbullido, vice president and general manager of gap.com, also left. Previous executive departures provoked investor concern that the company, struggling with declining earnings and sales, was facing an exodus of experienced people, but a Gap representative, Kris Marubio, said the most recent exits were part of the ebb and flow of business. (REUTERS)</p>
        <p>Brazil's Economic Growth Falls Short of Forecasts  Brazil's economy expanded less than analysts expected in the fourth quarter as a stronger currency prompted some manufacturers to curb output and a drought in the south damaged rice and soybean crops. Gross domestic product, the broadest measure of a country's output of goods and services, grew 1.4 percent in the period from a year ago, following growth of 1 percent in the third quarter, the government said. Brazil's economy expanded 2.3 percent for all of 2005, less than half the 2004 growth rate of 4.9 percent. (BLOOMBERG NEWS)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
