<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Richter Says He Will Play As Hasek Awaits Rangers</title>
    <meta content="25RANG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1179141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richter, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E0DB1E30F936A15751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="601" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Richter Says He Will Play As Hasek Awaits Rangers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <dateline>RYE, N.Y., Feb. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers goalie Mike Richter, who has missed six of nine games with ailing left knee, says he will be ready to play against Buffalo Sabres on Feb 25 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Richter was on the ice today and said he would be ready to play Friday night when the Rangers travel to Buffalo for a game with playoff implications. But it wasn't Richter, who has missed six of nine games with an ailing left knee, who was being tested in practice.</p>
        <p>Instead, Coach John Muckler sent waves of players at both nets, shouting for someone to shoot every time an opening presented itself. It wasn't Richter or the backup goalie Kirk McLean whom Muckler was concerned with; it was that Dominik Hasek, whom the Rangers can barely score on, will be in the net for Buffalo for the first time against the Rangers this season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Richter was on the ice today and said he would be ready to play Friday night when the Rangers travel to Buffalo for a game with playoff implications. But it wasn't Richter, who has missed six of nine games with an ailing left knee, who was being tested in practice.</p>
        <p>Instead, Coach John Muckler sent waves of players at both nets, shouting for someone to shoot every time an opening presented itself. It wasn't Richter or the backup goalie Kirk McLean whom Muckler was concerned with; it was that Dominik Hasek, whom the Rangers can barely score on, will be in the net for Buffalo for the first time against the Rangers this season.</p>
        <p>In their last 10 games against Hasek, the Rangers are 0-7-3 and have scored just 9 goals, which makes the Rangers only slightly more ineffective than the rest of the league. Since returning from a groin tear, Hasek has a 4-0-3 record, allowing just 10 goals.</p>
        <p>As Richter peeled off his equipment today, insisting he would be ready to play on Friday -- ''I feel real good,'' he said -- Richter feigned seriousness when asked about Hasek and said, ''We've gone over game films and found out he has been cheating all these years.''</p>
        <p>But joking aside, the Rangers, at 25-28-9 with 3 regulation ties, know that they need to find a solution to Hasek. They enter this game holding the eighth and final playoff berth in the Eastern Conference with 62 points, with the Sabres a point behind. So Muckler was imploring his team to shoot, and shoot some more, so that on Friday night a puck or two might find its way into the net.</p>
        <p>''Obviously, there's not too many weaknesses,'' Muckler said of Hasek. ''You've got to earn every goal you're going to get; his record indicates that.</p>
        <p>''We're definitely going to have shoot the puck. We can't get psyched out. I think that's what he does to a lot of teams -- psyches them out. They're reluctant to take shots in a good area on the ice. I don't think he's really been tested a great deal. Everybody seems to want to get in and make the perfect play; they try to hit the corners and then miss the net. I think that's the big advantage that he has right now, besides his great talent.''</p>
        <p>Petr Nedved agreed. ''I think sometimes the guys pass up the opportunity to shoot because they don't feel that they can score,'' he said. ''They think they have to make one more pass and make a better scoring opportunity instead of just shooting.''</p>
        <p>Richter said: ''I think the real key is he's a human. He's a great goalie and he's also beatable. What you don't want to do is start sparing him work on his reputation alone and not shooting the puck and not test him as you would a normal goalie. Then you get in trouble.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>ADAM GRAVES was selected to receive a $25,000 grant from the N.H.L. Foundation for his community work, which he can then apply to any of the causes he works with.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
