<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Patents; Two New Variations On Bowling</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="203518"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOWLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVENTIONS AND INVENTORS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BRUNSWICK BOWLING &amp; BILLIARD CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDREWS, EDMUND L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Inventions and Patents</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DF1F31F930A35751C1A96E948260" item-length="277" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Patents; Two New Variations On Bowling</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edmund L. Andrews</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDREWS, EDMUND L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The number of serious bowlers has been declining in recent years, so the Brunswick Bowling and Billiards Corporation, the world's largest manufacturer of pin-setting equipment, is thinking up new variations on the old game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The number of serious bowlers has been declining in recent years, so the Brunswick Bowling and Billiards Corporation, the world's largest manufacturer of pin-setting equipment, is thinking up new variations on the old game.</p>
        <p>The number of serious bowlers has been declining in recent years, so the Brunswick Bowling and Billiards Corporation, the world's largest manufacturer of pin-setting equipment, is thinking up new variations on the old game.</p>
        <p>This week, the Muskegon, Mich., company won patents for two new games, including one that would do away with strikes, spares and even the hallowed 10-pin formation. Officials say the games, designed for Brunswick's new line of advanced pin-setting machines, are meant to attract people who may have been frustrated or bored by traditional bowling.</p>
        <p>Although bowling is enjoying a resurgence in popularity, the number of league bowlers, who play every week and provide the industry's lifeblood, has declined to seven million, from nine million in 1978, the American Bowling Congress said.</p>
        <p>In one of the games patented this week, the first ball is rolled at the standard 10 pins. If the bowler does not like the look of the remaining pins, he or she pushes a button and the machine will randomly pick a new arrangement that may be easier or more difficult.</p>
        <p>A second game makes a more radical break from the traditional one. Bowlers aim at only five pins, which appear in different formations with each turn. The bowlers get a number of ''betting points,'' which they can wager on their ability to knock the pins down in two rolls. Somewhat like draw poker, the bowlers can replace as many as three pins in the arrangement before they bet.</p>
        <p>Brunswick's new bowling machines feature television monitors that show instant replays and display the speed and trajectory of each ball.</p>
        <p>Brunswick received patents 4,787,633 and 4,787,634.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
