<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jersey City Man Is Arrested In Fatal Slashing of Three</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="700190"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JERSEY CITY (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MENTER, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTS, ISABEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTS, JOANN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D81F3FF93BA25754C0A962958260" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jersey City Man Is Arrested In Fatal Slashing of Three</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD PEREZ-PENA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eighteen hours after Jersey City police officers peered through the window of a house and saw a woman lying in a pool of blood, a man was arrested yesterday and charged with murdering three members of his girlfriend's family.</p>
        <p>The suspect, William Menter, 26, went looking for his girlfriend, Latisha Roberts, on Saturday night, a day after the two had fought, the police said. Failing to find her, investigators contend, he slashed the throats of her mother, her sister, her niece and her nephew. The boy survived.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eighteen hours after Jersey City police officers peered through the window of a house and saw a woman lying in a pool of blood, a man was arrested yesterday and charged with murdering three members of his girlfriend's family.</p>
        <p>The suspect, William Menter, 26, went looking for his girlfriend, Latisha Roberts, on Saturday night, a day after the two had fought, the police said. Failing to find her, investigators contend, he slashed the throats of her mother, her sister, her niece and her nephew. The boy survived.</p>
        <p>"It was a horrible scene," said Robert Martin, the chief of investigations in the Hudson County Prosecutor's office. "Some of the veteran law-enforcement officers who were there said it was the worst scene they've ever seen."</p>
        <p>Soon after the grisly scene at 165 Wegman Parkway was discovered, an arrest warrant was issued for Mr. Menter, though officials would not say what evidence made him the prime suspect. Mr. Menter turned himself in at 5 P.M. yesterday. Investigators would not say whether he had admitted or denied responsibility for the deaths.</p>
        <p>Ms. Roberts, a woman in her 20's, had lived with Mr. Menter at 176 Lexington Avenue in Jersey City, but moved out on Friday after an argument, Mr. Martin said.</p>
        <p>The next night, he said, Mr. Menter went looking for Ms. Roberts at the duplex on Wegman Parkway, about a mile from his apartment, that was home to her mother, Isabel Roberts, and her sister, Joann Roberts. With the two women were the three children of another sister, Margaret Roberts. Latisha Roberts was not at the house at the time, and the police refused to disclose her whereabouts.</p>
        <p>Bill Murphy, 33, who lives upstairs in the duplex, said a member of the Roberts family called the home that night and Mr. Menter answered. "The guy picked up the phone and said, 'No one can come to the phone right now,' " he said. "That's when she knew something was wrong." He said the relative called 911.</p>
        <p>About 11 P.M., police officers, accompanied by Mr. Menter, looked in the kitchen window of the ground-floor unit and saw Joann Roberts lying dead in a dark puddle that had drained from a yawning wound in her neck, Mr. Martin said.</p>
        <p>"Her head was just about severed, cut from ear to ear," Mr. Murphy said. "Blood was everywhere."</p>
        <p>The officers broke down the door and found Isabel Roberts dead in the bathroom, the police said. Shayka Roberts, who the police said was 7 or 8 years old, was found dead under a bed in one of the bedrooms.</p>
        <p>"Out of another bedroom comes walking a 12-year-old boy, Omar, with his throat slashed," Mr. Martin said, and in the same room was his 4-year-old brother, whose name the police did not know, asleep and unharmed. He would not say whether Omar was able to identify his attacker. He said Omar was in critical but stable condition at a hospital he would not name.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martin said investigators were not sure what the murder weapon was.</p>
        <p>Residents of Mr. Menter's quiet, middle-class neighborhood said he and Ms. Roberts seemed to be a happy couple. "They were very quiet, no arguments or nothing," said Riza Colon. "You would never think a killer is living next door to you."</p>
        <p>Mr. Menter will be arraigned today in Hudson County Central Judicial Processing Court.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
