<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Athletics Solve Mussina And Shut Out Orioles</title>
    <meta content="29ROUN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="874184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Kansas City Royals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Oakland Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Texas Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7DF1F39F93AA1575BC0A960958260" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Athletics Solve Mussina And Shut Out Orioles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Major league baseball results</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Athletics 3, Orioles 0</p>
        <p>Don Wengert pitched a nine-hitter, his first major league complete game, and the visiting Oakland Athletics ended Mike Mussina's six-game winning streak by beating the Baltimore Orioles, 3-0, yesterday.</p>
        <p>Baltimore lost for only the 10th time in 29 games. The defeat, coupled with Chicago's 2-0 victory over Milwaukee, cut the Orioles' lead over the White Sox in the American League wild-card race to half a game. The Orioles remained four games behind the first-place Yankees, who lost at Seattle late last night, in the A.L. East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Athletics 3, Orioles 0</p>
        <p>Don Wengert pitched a nine-hitter, his first major league complete game, and the visiting Oakland Athletics ended Mike Mussina's six-game winning streak by beating the Baltimore Orioles, 3-0, yesterday.</p>
        <p>Baltimore lost for only the 10th time in 29 games. The defeat, coupled with Chicago's 2-0 victory over Milwaukee, cut the Orioles' lead over the White Sox in the American League wild-card race to half a game. The Orioles remained four games behind the first-place Yankees, who lost at Seattle late last night, in the A.L. East.</p>
        <p>Jose Herrera had three hits and two runs batted in for the A's.</p>
        <p>Baltimore's Eddie Murray went 1 for 4, a single, and remained stuck on 498 homers for his career.</p>
        <p>Red Sox 7, Angels 4</p>
        <p>Tom Gordon pitched a five-hitter and John Valentin drove in two runs as visiting Boston completed a three-game sweep of California.</p>
        <p>Boston has won 22 of its last 28 games, including 5 straight, to climb within two games of Baltimore for the A.L. wild-card spot.</p>
        <p>Blue Jays 6, Twins 1</p>
        <p>Pat Hentgen (17-7) pitched a five-hitter in his fifth straight complete game and won for the 10th time in 11 starts, leading host Toronto.</p>
        <p>Indians 9, Tigers 3</p>
        <p>Albert Belle hit a grand slam, his 43d home run this season, as Cleveland beat host Detroit, completing the first season sweep against the Tigers in the Indians' history.</p>
        <p>Jim Thome homered for the third straight game, Jeff Kent also hit a home run and Orel Hershiser (14-7) won his fourth straight decision for the Indians, who finished 12-0 against the Tigers this year.</p>
        <p>Detroit became the 12th team in history to get swept in a season series.</p>
        <p>White Sox 2, Brewers 0</p>
        <p>The rookie James Baldwin (10-4) and two relievers combined on a five-hitter to lead Chicago's shutout of visiting Milwaukee. Ray Durham tripled in the game's first run and scored on Ozzie Guillen's double.</p>
        <p>Royals 4, Rangers 3</p>
        <p>Jose Offerman singled home Johnny Damon with two outs in the 12th inning to give host Kansas City the victory, the Royals' second straight extra-inning triumph over the Rangers. The Royals beat the Rangers, 4-3, in 10 innings Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Rockies 10, Reds 9</p>
        <p>At Denver, Andres Galarraga tied a team record with his 40th homer, a two-run shot in the eighth inning that broke a tie and lifted Colorado past Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Vinny Castilla hit a three-run homer for Colorado, which won for the eighth time in 10 games and overcame five home runs by the Reds. Castilla's homer in the fourth gave him 102 r.b.i. Galarraga is tied with the Cubs' Sammy Sosa for the National League home run lead.</p>
        <p>Expos 6, Dodgers 5</p>
        <p>David Segui's two-out single in the ninth inning drove in the winning run as host Montreal rallied from a five-run deficit. A misplayed fly ball in the eighth helped the Expos stop the Dodgers' five-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>Montreal moved half a game ahead of the Dodgers in the race for the N.L. wild-card spot.</p>
        <p>Braves 9, Pirates 4</p>
        <p>Atlanta roughed up Pittsburgh's least-effective starter, scoring six runs against Esteban Loaiza to beat the host Pirates. Ryan Klesko homered twice and Terry Pendleton chased Loaiza (0-1) with a three-run double that made it 6-1 in the second inning.</p>
        <p>Loaiza lasted just one and a third innings in his fourth consecutive sub-par start.</p>
        <p>Marlins 3, Cardinals 2</p>
        <p>Reliever Cory Bailey walked the bases loaded in the 10th inning for Devon White, who hit a sacrifice fly to give Florida the victory at St. Louis.</p>
        <p>The loss dropped the second-place and slumping Cardinals two and a half games behind Houston in the N.L. Central. St. Louis has lost 7 of 9 games.</p>
        <p>Astros 5, Cubs 4</p>
        <p>Brian Hunter doubled home the winning run with two outs in the ninth inning as host Houston rallied past Chicago.</p>
        <p>Giants 7, Phillies 6</p>
        <p>Glenallen Hill had the last of four consecutive run-scoring singles as host San Francisco Giants used a five-run seventh to rally past Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
