<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>'We're Not Rethinking Our Strategy': Excerpts From Interview With Hewlett's Acting Chief</title>
    <meta content="14WAYM$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/14/technology/14wayman.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1649910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hewlett-Packard Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fiorina, Carleton S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wayman, Robert P</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivlin, Gary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hewlett-Packard Company</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502EFDD153AF937A25751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1430" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>'We're Not Rethinking Our Strategy': Excerpts From Interview With Hewlett's Acting Chief</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'We're Not Rethinking Our Strategy': Excerpts From Interview With Hewlett's Acting Chief</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF and GARY RIVLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rivlin, Gary; Markoff, John</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Feb. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from phone interview with Robert P Wayman, acting Hewlett-Packard chief executive, following ouster of chief executive Carleton S Fiorina; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert P. Wayman learned suddenly that he would be thrust into the limelight as the acting chief executive of Hewlett-Packard in a phone call early last week. The company's board had apparently just asked for, and received, Carleton S. Fiorina's resignation -- a decision that Mr. Wayman called an ''absolute'' surprise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wayman, who will retain the title of chief financial officer as the board searches for a new chief executive, is a 36-year veteran of the company. By his own acknowledgment, he would much prefer to remain in the background, and during an interview conducted by phone from his Palo Alto, Calif., office, he seemed nervous and on edge.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert P. Wayman, suddenly thrust into the limelght as the interim chief executive of Hewlett-Packard, is facing difficult questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Robert P. Wayman learned suddenly that he would be thrust into the limelight as the acting chief executive of Hewlett-Packard in a phone call early last week. The company's board had apparently just asked for, and received, Carleton S. Fiorina's resignation -- a decision that Mr. Wayman called an ''absolute'' surprise.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wayman, who will retain the title of chief financial officer as the board searches for a new chief executive, is a 36-year veteran of the company. By his own acknowledgment, he would much prefer to remain in the background, and during an interview conducted by phone from his Palo Alto, Calif., office, he seemed nervous and on edge.</p>
        <p>A partial transcript follows:</p>
        <p>Q. There's some blood in the water and competitors are circling, and they're aggressively going after your customers. From what we hear, at least one competitor is spreading the world that you're in a death spiral.</p>
        <p>A. Of course, that's what our competitors would say. It is what I'm sure our salespeople would be saying, and have said at times, when there were unplanned leadership changes at our competitors.</p>
        <p>But if I were that shallow in my purchasing decisions, I'd deserve to be sent elsewhere. I just think it's overplayed. I think it's totally overplayed.</p>
        <p>Clearly, there's a lot of distraction. Folks like you, you're in the business of making the most out of what's happening. And in this day and age, you've got thousands of publications that are publishing stories about what happened, what may have happened, etc. So there's huge distraction -- including for the customers.</p>
        <p>So what we did starting immediately, I mean literally the announcement went out at 5 in the morning on Wednesday and by 7 o'clock we had a customer contact plan in motion. Not only end-user customers but our partners. And I don't have the numbers in front of me, but just a huge number of calls went out to people providing the opportunity to discuss what went on, what it means and what it doesn't mean.</p>
        <p>That's all you can do at this point in time. And, you know, wait a bit for the distraction to get behind you and then get back to the real-value proposition that we bring to our customer base</p>
        <p>Q. This news hit one week before earnings, a stressful time for both the C.F.O. and the C.E.O. And now you're both. What are you doing now?</p>
        <p>A. It is certainly busier than usual. But I'm doing both things. And right now, they're very aligned with one another. There's no question that improving our execution is the top C.E.O. priority, and it's the top C.F.O. priority. So it's not like I have to make particularly tough choices between how I spend my time. And importantly, it's a strong team here. It's a very strong team.</p>
        <p>Q. The outside world is convinced that the answer is to spin out the printer and imaging business. What's your counter to that?</p>
        <p>A. That's been under discussion for a number of years. Frankly, even before we did the Agilent spinoff, it was brought up as a possibility. So we believe, the board believes, and they have unanimously as part of this decision readdressed that question and have told me that they are unanimous, that they think the current portfolio business is the right portfolio for the reasons that we have talked about for a good period of time -- that there are opportunities to leverage and bring capabilities in a unique way that other companies just cannot do.</p>
        <p>All of our businesses share channels of distribution. So we have customers who want it all and the opportunity to pull them together in ways that we think we are best positioned to do. I could go on and on. But that's an example of why we think it belongs together.</p>
        <p>Q. How about concerns internally, among employees?</p>
        <p>A. We've been focused on this announcement in pulling the team together, communicating with our employees in ways that calm them down as much as possible. And messages that I've been giving to people here include: Yeah, it's a change, leadership change is an important issue. But this company is way more than a C.E.O. This is 150,000 employees. It's technology, it's product, it's culture, relationships. It's a huge list of things that didn't change last Tuesday.</p>
        <p>And that's what we're focused on, making the best out of all the assets that we have.</p>
        <p>Q. It sounds like you're in crisis-management mode, dealing with employees and morale and dealing with customers. What are the next steps?</p>
        <p>A. I certainly didn't say that and I don't believe that at all. In fact, people that I talked to recently say, ''Gosh, it seems so calm.'' Yeah, we're doing a lot. But we're doing it very deliberately, very calmly. And it's just the kind of thing that happens once in a while.</p>
        <p>This is not a time of crisis. We're not rethinking our strategy. Nothing has changed in how we are doing business today.</p>
        <p>Q. What are your next steps? What are the priorities moving forward?</p>
        <p>A. One clear priority -- driven mostly by the board, but I am now a member of the board and I'm going to make sure we drive on it as hard as we can -- and that is getting on quickly and successfully with a C.E.O. search. There's no question that the sooner that we get the right person in place, the better off we'll be.</p>
        <p>From an operational point of view, we're doing a number of things. We're communicating with employees. We are talking about next quarter's goals and the critical paths between today and the end of next quarter, and what we need to do -- by the way, exactly the kind of issues we would have been talking about if Carly is at the table. So it's really not that much difference.</p>
        <p>The one thing that we are doing consciously differently now and that is putting more time on, one, communication with employees, and specifically communication about what we expect each and every person to do.</p>
        <p>Q. We've heard that there's been some dispute about whether there needs to be a further write-down, a significant write-down, related to the Compaq merger. That was certainly a big issue in a recent issue of Fortune, which said there would need to be further write-downs related to the merger.</p>
        <p>A. There's no dispute. The accounting literature is quite clear on how this decision is evaluated. We are required once a year and have been for a number of years going through the calculation that is associated with valuing the basis of the goodwill asset that is on our balance sheet -- a noncash asset by the way. You could look at our 10(k). There is commentary on the approach that we took. It's reviewed by auditors. We, like I think most other companies, use a third party to make sure that it is rigorously evaluated.</p>
        <p>What really matters is how we improve the performance of our business. That's the focus. If we don't achieve our goals, then we have an accounting event that we'll have to deal with. I don't have any reason to believe at the moment that we will. But of course, once again next year we will have to evaluate the asset -- or if some other major change in the environment causes us to relook at that sooner than once a year. I ---- That's the straightforward answer.</p>
        <p>I've been spending no time, either before this announcement or afterwards, on this matter.</p>
        <p>Q. You've consistently said that you have a strategy in place. Is it possible that you will find a C.E.O. who may reshape H.P.'s strategy? Or are you looking for someone simply to implement the board's strategy?</p>
        <p>A. We are looking for a C.E.O. based on a set of assumptions. One of those assumptions is that our current strategy is the right strategy. When a C.E.O. comes in, of course they will be re-evaluating the competitive environment, the opportunity space that we operate in, and they will have to tweak our strategy. I mean that happens all the time.</p>
        <p>But I don't ---- It is the case that the board is assuming that any C.E.O. we hire will be aligned with our strategy at this point in time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
