<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tossing Out a Chief Executive</title>
    <meta content="14HP$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/14/technology/14HP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1649909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hewlett-Packard Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rivlin, Gary</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fiorina, Carleton S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wayman, Robert P</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hewlett-Packard Company</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Fiorina, Carleton S</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Packard, David</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Hewlett, William</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03EFDD153AF937A25751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="2149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tossing Out a Chief Executive</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tossing Out a Chief Executive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GARY RIVLIN and JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rivlin, Gary; Markoff, John</byline>
      <dateline>PALO ALTO, Calif., Feb. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reasons for Carleton S Fiorina's downfall at Hewlett-Packard include both her failure to produce kind of profits she promised and collision of her management style with egalitarian corporate culture where workers were treated like family; interim chief executive Robert P Wayman denies culuture clash played role in her ouster, interview; other employees have said she was divisive force, with passionate supporters and bitter enemies; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Preserved on Hewlett-Packard's campus as a kind of museum exhibit are the spartan offices of William Hewlett and David Packard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hewlett and Mr. Packard, the founders of the fabled Silicon Valley company, did not hole themselves up like so many top executives nowadays but invited people to share ideas. A wedge of darkened linoleum can be found behind each door, evidence that the doors were open in a corporate culture created by the two engineers -- men who favored pocket protectors and short sleeves and summed up their executive style as ''management by wandering around.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Carleton S. Fiorina stood in stark contrast to a corporate culture founded years earlier.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Preserved on Hewlett-Packard's campus as a kind of museum exhibit are the spartan offices of William Hewlett and David Packard.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hewlett and Mr. Packard, the founders of the fabled Silicon Valley company, did not hole themselves up like so many top executives nowadays but invited people to share ideas. A wedge of darkened linoleum can be found behind each door, evidence that the doors were open in a corporate culture created by the two engineers -- men who favored pocket protectors and short sleeves and summed up their executive style as ''management by wandering around.''</p>
        <p>By contrast, Carleton S. Fiorina, deposed last week as Hewlett-Packard's chief executive, the first ever hired from outside, preferred to dazzle people with PowerPoint presentations and other trappings of the modern-day manager as she struggled to reinvent Hewlett, a company that gave rise to Silicon Valley and defined its culture.</p>
        <p>Where Mr. Hewlett and Mr. Packard frequently ate in the company cafeteria and stopped by people's desks to chat, Ms. Fiorina ate at her desk and was seen far less frequently by those working at company headquarters here. Indeed, an employee would typically have had to plan weeks ahead to secure an appointment with her.</p>
        <p>One way to understand why Ms. Fiorina was ousted as Hewlett-Packard's chief last week was that the company failed to produce the kind of profits she had promised.</p>
        <p>But the reasons for her downfall can also be found in her collision with the celebrated and deeply rooted ''H.P. Way'' -- a corporate culture where workers were treated not so much as employees but as family, and egalitarianism was a family watchword.</p>
        <p>''You had an antibody effect,'' said Jeffrey Christian, the executive recruiter who helped bring Ms. Fiorina from Lucent Technologies. ''Carly was a very different type of leader than H.P. had ever had before.''</p>
        <p>But Hewlett-Packard's interim chief executive, Robert P. Wayman, disagrees. Asked in an interview on Friday if he thought that a culture clash played a role in Ms. Fiorina's departure, he said: ''I have been with the company 36 years. So I think I qualify as an expert on the H.P. culture. And I categorically can't imagine that that was a reason.''</p>
        <p>Still, there was evidence that unhappiness was brewing. At the outset of Ms. Fiorina's tenure, in mid-1999, there had been great hopes, which employees say were quickly dashed.</p>
        <p>''At first it felt like Prague Spring,'' said an employee who worked in corporate headquarters through the transition six years ago.</p>
        <p>Richard Hagberg, a consultant in San Mateo, Calif., had been asked by Hewlett-Packard's board to help evaluate Ms. Fiorina before the directors made their final decision.</p>
        <p>''I told the board that I thought that her style, in many ways, was a good fit for what they said they wanted,'' said Mr. Hagberg, who served as an outside consultant to H.P. from 1997 to 2000. ''They needed a new vision to take them into the future. And she had that capability. But I also said that she needed some help on the execution side, and I also suggested they bring in a strong operations person'' as chief operating officer.</p>
        <p>Last week, in the wake of her departure, employees said Ms. Fiorina, now 50, had been a divisive force in the company -- with passionate supporters and bitter enemies.</p>
        <p>''She was brought in to drive change,'' Mr. Wayman said. ''Change is difficult, and certainly when you drive change, not everyone is happy with it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Fiorina seemed to grasp that success in her new job required a deep understanding of a workplace steeped in history.</p>
        <p>Peter Burrows, author of ''Backfire: Carly Fiorina's High-Stakes Battle for the Soul of Hewlett-Packard,'' said that she read ''The H.P. Way,'' by David Packard -- and then read it four more times.</p>
        <p>Yet from the start she seemed to trample over tradition, beginning with the compensation package she negotiated. She was given a $3 million signing bonus and a stock package worth $65 million, Mr. Burrows said, and paid at least $2.25 million a year in salary and guaranteed bonuses. (The $65 million in part offset the stock options and other benefits she would lose after 19 years at AT&amp;T and Lucent Technologies, the equipment and research arm of the Bell system that was spun off in 1996.)</p>
        <p>She even asked the board to pay the cost of shipping her 52-foot yacht from the East Coast to the San Francisco Bay Area, Mr. Burrows said.</p>
        <p>''Right away her compensation became an issue,'' said Rakesh Khurana, an associate professor at Harvard Business School and an author of a study released last year, ''Hewlett-Packard: Culture in Changing Times.''</p>
        <p>''This was a company priding itself on its egalitarianism, where everyone else more or less was considered on the same plane,'' said Professor Khurana, who is also the author of ''Searching for a Corporate Savior: The Irrational Quest of Charismatic C.E.O.'s.''</p>
        <p>''And here she had a compensation package.'' he said, ''that, by H.P.'s standards, was quite extravagant.''</p>
        <p>The H.P. Way revolved around both big ideas -- so deeply did the company believe in collaborative benefits of the open office that it can be credited, or blamed, for giving corporate America the cubicle workplace -- and the small touches that made employees feel that they are part of a caring family or team.</p>
        <p>Every employee with a new child was sent a baby blanket, and Mr. Hewlett and Mr. Packard sent a silver bowl as a wedding present to employees who got married while working there.</p>
        <p>The company's culture also effectively pushed decision-making down as far as it could into the organization.</p>
        <p>Many of the smaller touches ended with the retirement of the founders. But the essential H.P. Way endured -- and by almost all accounts, Hewlett-Packard was a company in need of an overhaul when Ms. Fiorina took the helm in July 1999. Still, some longtime employees said they thought that she failed to understand what she had set out to transform.</p>
        <p>''When you're going to change something, it's really important to know what you're changing,'' said Joe Schoendorf, a Silicon Valley venture capitalist who was a top salesman for the company in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>But others say that practices at Hewlett were so deep-set that people resisted her simply because she was an outsider seeking to make changes. ''She was a very effective exponent of what we were doing,'' a marketing executive at company headquarters said. ''She was personable and gracious,'' yet from the start, ''she was swimming upstream.''</p>
        <p>This may have been evident in the resistance that greeted her efforts to streamline the company. By the time she arrived, Hewlett-Packard had been broken into 83 business divisions, each with its own chief financial officer and management structure. The company now is broken into roughly half a dozen units, a Hewlett-Packard spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>Some old-timers also rebelled, a Hewlett employee for 25 years said, when Ms. Firorina overhauled the worker evaluation system. Where in the past there had been a ''civil service mentality'' where employees were often granted ''a 4 on a scale of 1 to 5 simply for showing up,'' he said, the new boss put into practice a far more rigorous -- and less generous -- system.</p>
        <p>''The H.P. way used to be a means toward an end,'' Professor Khurana noted, ''a way of creating innovative products. But over time, it became an end unto itself.''</p>
        <p>Hewlett-Packard also prized modesty. Early missteps, Professor Khurana and others said, included Ms. Fiorina's decision to star in a television advertisement and her campaign to alter the company's brand identification, changing its name in advertisements from Hewlett-Packard to simply H.P.</p>
        <p>''In those ads,'' Professor Khurana said, ''she stood in front of the original garage where Hewlett-Packard was founded and put herself forward as the face of innovation and change at H.P. She also decided to change the H.P. logo, dropping the founders' last names. I think people saw this as her trying to make H.P. in her own image, which didn't go over too well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schoendorf added, ''When she stood in front of the garage, she made it about her and not about the company.'' The ad was a part of a $200 million campaign that Hewlett-Packard initiated at the end of 1999.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burrows said that the company had an Web internal site for people to post comments, but ''they were forced to turn it off because people were flaming her so much.''</p>
        <p>Yet whatever animosity Ms. Fiorina engendered in her first couple of years, it was nothing compared with the firestorm that followed her decision to buy Compaq Computer in 2001. Not only did that mean a public and bruising battle with Walter B. Hewlett, the son of a founder and the largest individual shareholder, but also a planned layoff of 15,000 people.</p>
        <p>''After the merger, the walls went up and she took on a fortress mentality,'' an employee said. ''She was even booed in an annual meeting.''</p>
        <p>Where once H.P. was a company that virtually guaranteed a person a job for life, it was suddenly just another huge business, like I.B.M., General Motors, the United States Steel Corporation and a long list of others, seeking to cut costs by making widespread layoffs.</p>
        <p>''Maybe that's what she needed to do to make the merger work,'' said Don Tennant, editor of ComputerWorld, ''but, right or wrong, that really shifted the mind-set inside H.P. No longer was H.P. a company where the employees came first. It was a company where the bottom line comes first.''</p>
        <p>Hewlett-Packard had long been on Fortune magazine's annual list of the 100 best companies to work for. It has failed to make the list in the last several years.</p>
        <p>''Carly certainly had her supporters -- there was a definite Cult of Carly inside H.P. -- but she had lost the confidence of many,'' Mr. Burrows said, adding: ''She lost a lot of the engineers. She had a lot of ideas that weren't necessarily bad, but there was a question of what was doable.''</p>
        <p>For Ms. Fiorina, the beginning of the end came one day in mid-August, before 5 a.m., when the company roused West Coast analysts from bed for a surprise conference call to announce that it would miss its revenue projections in the last two quarters of the year.</p>
        <p>Around that time, she fired three top three executives in what many people in and outside the company saw as a public hanging. In particular, the loss of Peter Blackmore, a top sales executive, rankled many longtime employees.</p>
        <p>''Peter was one of most highly regarded executives inside H.P.,'' Mr. Tennant said. ''She should have at least made it clear and said, 'We're replacing these guys, but I take ultimate responsibility. Ultimately, the buck stops with me.'''</p>
        <p>But the marketing executive said it was precisely because Mr. Blackmore had been so popular that Ms. Fiorina did what she did. ''She was trying to make a statement to people,'' the executive said: no one's job is safe when they miss their numbers in a way that hurts the bottom line.</p>
        <p>Clearly the board was bothered as well, if not by the way she deposed some high-ranking employees then by the bad news that led to a 13 percent drop in the company's stock price in a single trading session.</p>
        <p>In September, according to a person close to discussions in the company, the board's concerns, the directors asked Ms. Fiorina to adopt a strategy that would help accelerate growth. She resisted, leading the directors to discuss limiting her power and forcing her to share day-to-day responsibilities.</p>
        <p>''Carly was up against people who had elevated the old culture to something that was almost sacrosanct,'' said Mr. Hagberg, the consultant, whom Ms. Fiorina's predecessor, Lewis E. Platt, hired in 1998 to diagnose ways that Hewlett-Packard's vaunted culture might be impeding it at a time of accelerated growth in Silicon Valley.</p>
        <p>''The board expressly said that the culture needed to be changed, but when she started messing with H.P.'s culture, people didn't like that.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
