<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What a Year It Was. Or Is. Or Will Be.</title>
    <meta content="02NYC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/01/02/nyregion/02NYC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1547667"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D91731F931A35752C0A9629C8B63" item-length="827" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What a Year It Was. Or Is. Or Will Be.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What a Year It Was. Or Is. Or Will Be.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you picked up a newspaper or turned on the television news during the last 10 days or so, you probably stumbled upon the ritual known as the year-end review. It was hard to avoid.</p>
        <p>This is a journalistic exercise apparently predicated on the concept that most readers suffer from severe short-term memory loss and cannot recall events as far back as American soldiers' finding Saddam Hussein in his spider hole. The custom also ignores the possibility that many people found substantial stretches of the last year to be singularly rotten, and have no desire to relive them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The year-end newspaper review is a journalistic exercise predicated on the concept that most readers suffer from severe short-term memory loss.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you picked up a newspaper or turned on the television news during the last 10 days or so, you probably stumbled upon the ritual known as the year-end review. It was hard to avoid.</p>
        <p>This is a journalistic exercise apparently predicated on the concept that most readers suffer from severe short-term memory loss and cannot recall events as far back as American soldiers' finding Saddam Hussein in his spider hole. The custom also ignores the possibility that many people found substantial stretches of the last year to be singularly rotten, and have no desire to relive them.</p>
        <p>So the last few days have been devoted to recapping 2003, its high points and its lows, its best plays and worst movies (a highly competitive category), its most laudable public figures and vilest sleazoids, and so on.</p>
        <p>Keeping up with all the retrospectives can be inordinately time-consuming. And a year later, you have to do it all over again.</p>
        <p>For the new year, why not get this chore out of the way now, especially since much of what qualifies as news is predictable? As a public service, and with a confidence unmarred by wisdom, NYC offers here a look at some of the events that shaped New York in 2004.</p>
        <p>First, in local politics -- sorry -- opponents of Mayor Michael R. Bloomberg accused him no fewer than 50 times in 2004 of being ''out of touch'' with ordinary New Yorkers. Some of the strongest attacks against Mr. Bloomberg, who rides the subway to work, came from politicians who never went anywhere except in the back seat of a city-owned car.</p>
        <p>In 2004, Senator Charles E. Schumer held more than 40 news conferences on Sunday, a traditionally slow news day, to propose federal legislation to deal with problems that just happened to have made headlines the previous Wednesday. It was unclear if any of his bills actually became laws.</p>
        <p>The mayor and the City Council argued for months over how much of your money was at their disposal to spend, but they finally settled on a figure even while calling one another names. Albany was late with the state budget for the 20th straight year, but no one except a handful of policy wonks seemed to care. The presidential campaign came to New York, notably in the form of the Republican national convention, but that wasn't enough to prod the major candidates to discuss substantively the problems of America's large cities.</p>
        <p>Terrorism fears lingered in 2004.</p>
        <p>New York remained on ''orange'' alert, and there were fresh warnings of possible attacks. Unvaryingly, news broadcasts said that intelligence agencies had picked up an unusual volume of ''chatter,'' a word that seemed oddly casual for a subject so dire. The locution made Osama bin Laden and his henchmen sound almost like schoolboys talking idly on the phone about how it would be way cool to blow up an American target.</p>
        <p>Still, New Yorkers were told to have no fear and to keep buying those Manolo Blahniks, or else the terrorists would have won. To underscore that the city would not be cowed, Mr. Bloomberg ordered the police to ticket the car of Representative Christopher Shays of Connecticut every time the congressman showed his face in town.</p>
        <p>POLITICS and terror aside, a batch of stories from last year continued to reverberate in 2004.</p>
        <p>The police pursued their investigation of the strange shooting at Rao's restaurant in East Harlem. That Rao's was a tough place to get into is an old story. But getting out of there safely was never an issue until now.</p>
        <p>Let's see, what else?</p>
        <p>Martha Stewart was treated by some news organizations as if she were the greatest female criminal since Bonnie Parker. Paris Hilton far outlasted her allotted 15 minutes. Rosie O'Donnell was busy being Rosie O'Donnell. David Letterman found ways to joke about ''downer cows,'' and George Steinbrenner found new ways to make Yankees fans unhappy.</p>
        <p>Rush Limbaugh injured a finger trying to open a vial of OxyContin and blamed the Democrats. Jayson Blair wrote a book but couldn't find anyone who believed a word. Jennifer Lopez of the Bronx married that Ben fellow. Or maybe she didn't. In the end, it didn't really matter very much, did it?</p>
        <p>Oh, and the theater scene was filled with the likes of ''Fiddler on the Roof,'' ''A Raisin in the Sun,'' ''Sweet Charity'' and ''Pal Joey'' -- each of these whiskered offerings hailed by its producers as the brightest new thing to hit the New York stage in years.</p>
        <p>Of course, some truly surprising things happened in 2004. It's just hard to remember now what they were.</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
