<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Homelessness Tests San Francisco's Ideals</title>
    <meta content="13HOME$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1061758"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vagrancy and Vagrants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">San Francisco (Calif)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Los Angeles (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Willie L Jr (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rudiger, Joshua</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nieves, Evelyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Francisco</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beggars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E2DB1531F930A25752C1A96E958260" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Homelessness Tests San Francisco's Ideals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nieves, Evelyn</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Nov. 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Recent knifing attacks on homeless people in San Francisco, including one murder, intensifies debate about huge number of highly visible street people in what has been very tolerant city; Oakland man, Joshua Rudiger, is charged with murder and attempted murder; Mayor Willie L Brown Jr enrages advocates with his policies of removing vagrants from Golden Gate Park, moving those in tourist areas to shelters and arresting those disobeying the law; vagrants and panhandlers huddle near fancy hotels of Nob Hill, sleep on benches near department stores and camp out at Civic Center; photos; city budgets $60 milloin for services, but numbers are far out of proportion: San Francisco is nation's 13th most populous city, but only New York and Los Angeles have larger numbers of the homeless (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Three weeks ago, when someone started stalking homeless people here, bending over them as they slept in alleys and doorways and slashing their throats, a grim joke began making the rounds on the streets: the killer had been hired by the city.</p>
        <p>After all, didnot the Mayor call the city's homelessness problem ''intractable'' and vow in his State of the City address last month to clear the homeless from public places?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Three weeks ago, when someone started stalking homeless people here, bending over them as they slept in alleys and doorways and slashing their throats, a grim joke began making the rounds on the streets: the killer had been hired by the city.</p>
        <p>After all, didnot the Mayor call the city's homelessness problem ''intractable'' and vow in his State of the City address last month to clear the homeless from public places?</p>
        <p>''We figured the slasher was the one way to get us off the sidewalks,'' said Donald Behr, one of two homeless men leaning against the wall of a downtown Subway delicatessen early this morning. Mr. Behr and his friend slapped their knees at the humor of it.</p>
        <p>Maybe they can afford to laugh. Early Tuesday, the police arrested a man for a knife attack on a homeless man who had been sleeping in a Chinatown alley. They have charged him with murder and attempted murder in all four recent knife attacks on homeless people in the city. The murder charge is for the killing of a longtime homeless woman named Shirley Dillahunt, whom, it is said, everyone loved.</p>
        <p>The defendant is a 21-year-old Oakland man named Joshua Rudiger, who was said to have told the police that he was a vampire who drank his victims' blood.</p>
        <p>But the arrest of Mr. Rudiger is unlikely to cool the debate that the slashings have rekindled in this live-and-let-live city over what to do about all the people with no place to call home.</p>
        <p>The gallows humor that the slashings have inspired reflects the magnitude of the problem of homelessness and how it has  emerged as a major issue for Mayor Willie L. Brown Jr., particularly as the homeless have become increasingly visible.</p>
        <p>Mayor Brown, who was considered one of the few remaining liberal mayors of a major American city when he was elected three years ago, has enraged advocates for the homeless over his policies, starting with a decision last year to have the police forcibly remove hundreds of homeless people from Golden Gate Park. The anger was refueled with the city's latest plan to move homeless people in four tourist zones to shelters and to arrest those disobeying the law.</p>
        <p>Last weekend, the Mayor was bombarded with three pies by a group calling itself the Bionic Baking Brigade, which said it wanted to call attention to the city's lack of solutions to the problem of homelessness. At the same time, members of the Coalition on Homelessness say that this city, of all cities, should know that the homeless need treatment programs, jobs and housing, not sweeps off the streets and jail time.</p>
        <p>One point on which all agree is that there are incredible numbers of homeless people on San Francisco's streets. They huddle in doorways near the fanciest hotels of Nob Hill, sleep on the benches near all the big department stores on Union Square, camp out by the hundreds in the plaza by the Civic Center and crowd the corners of the Haight-Ashbury district. Some panhandle politely, rudely, quietly, loudly. Some talk to no one, or to everyone, or to themselves.</p>
        <p>On any night, according to the Coalition on Homelessness, there may be 16,000 people on the streets here, twice as many as 10 years ago. That means San Francisco, the 13th largest city in the country, has the third highest population of the homeless, after New York and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>The common wisdom is that the city's tolerance and weather have lured them here from elsewhere. But the weather, at least, is not always great. It rains three months a year, starting now, and the rain is not soft and warm, as in Southern California, but mean and cold, the kind that sends tourists  packing and commuters straight home from work.</p>
        <p>Paul Boden, director of the Coalition on Homelessness and a board member of the National Coalition on Homelessness, said the notion that people moved to a place to be homeless was a myth.</p>
        <p>''I don't know of one city in the country that doesn't say that it's a magnet and that homeless people come from somewhere else,'' Mr. Boden said. ''Fargo, N.D., was calling itself a magnet. It's kind of sad, actually.''</p>
        <p>San Francisco's homeless people, like those everywhere, Mr. Boden said, are usually longtime residents. About a third are mentally ill, a third are drug addicts (or some mixture of the two) and the rest have been displaced from their homes through personal misfortunes like rising rents or loss of income. While the numbers of the homeless are rising all over the nation, largely because of a decrease in Federal benefits and public housing, Mr. Boden said, San Francisco's problem is exacerbated by its soaring housing prices, the highest in the country.</p>
        <p>''The problem is the worst I've ever seen it,'' he said, ''and I've been doing this 16 years. We have 62 detox beds in the city and 1,200 people on the waiting list. We have 1,800 shelter beds and 140 families on the waiting list. The city doesn't even keep waiting lists for singles.''</p>
        <p>Mayor Brown, with $60 million budgeted for services related to the homeless, has introduced job training programs and introduced an $11 million program for drug treatment on demand. But waiting lists are long for that, too.</p>
        <p>Last Friday, the city began a police crackdown on those caught drinking, urinating, defecating or sleeping on the sidewalks, a mandate that would include just about all the homeless. Those arrested for public drunkenness three times within 60 days will face 30 days in jail unless they enroll in a substance abuse program. But there is no guarantee that they will get a bed in such a program if they want one, in which case they will simply be cited and released.</p>
        <p>The city coordinator for the homeless, Terry Hill, said he was working on a variety of solutions, both short-term and long, for people in dire straits.</p>
        <p>Donald Behr, who has lived on and off the streets in Oakland and San Francisco for five years, said he was in that category. Mr. Behr said he became homeless when his wife kicked him out of their apartment in Oakland after he developed a cocaine habit and was dismissed from his job.</p>
        <p>''Half the people you step over have the same problem,'' he said. ''And there are more of us today than there used to be. That's for sure.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Behr's friend, who would not give his name, said he was a drug addict with ''mental problems.''</p>
        <p>''I need help,'' he said. ''But when I'm feeling good and go to get help, they tell me I don't need it. Then, when I go crazy, I'm too crazy to get help.''</p>
        <p>At that, he and Mr. Behr laughed and laughed.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
