<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At TriBeCa Academy, Police See Con Artistry</title>
    <meta content="29ACAD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/04/29/education/29academy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1577781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Academy of Art</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewan, Shaila K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eaton, Leslie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pivar, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Angona, Robert J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embezzlement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EEDB163DF93AA15757C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1047" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At TriBeCa Academy, Police See Con Artistry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Art Academy's Helping Hand Is Now Held as a Con Artist</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAILA K. DEWAN and LESLIE EATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dewan, Shaila K; Eaton, Leslie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert J Angona, former chief financial officer of New York Academy of Art, is charged with stealing $50,000 from school; Stuart Pivar, founder and persistent critic of academy, hired private detective who discovered that Angona was convicted twice of theft, including passing over $75,000 in bad checks under another name; calls for replacement of school's board, saying Angona case is latest of administrative problems (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two years ago, a man who said his name was Robert J. Angona answered a want ad for a bookkeeper at the New York Academy of Art in TriBeCa. Some at the school said he gained their sympathy, telling them that his business had been destroyed in the World Trade Center collapse.</p>
        <p>He went to work for an hourly wage, soon rose to be chief financial officer, and even became a benefactor, promising to donate $15,000 out of his own pocket.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Angona was arrested last week on charges of stealing more than $50,000 from the New York Academy of Art in TriBeCa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two years ago, a man who said his name was Robert J. Angona answered a want ad for a bookkeeper at the New York Academy of Art in TriBeCa. Some at the school said he gained their sympathy, telling them that his business had been destroyed in the World Trade Center collapse.</p>
        <p>He went to work for an hourly wage, soon rose to be chief financial officer, and even became a benefactor, promising to donate $15,000 out of his own pocket.</p>
        <p>The donation never materialized, but that was the least of the trouble. Mr. Angona, 64, was arrested last week on charges of stealing more than $50,000 from the academy using a company credit card, the police said. And they are investigating more of his financial transactions..</p>
        <p>The revelations have plunged the academy, created under the aegis of Andy Warhol in 1982, into turmoil. And they have reignited a long-running feud between the school and one of its founders, Stuart Pivar, an art collector and friend of Warhol.</p>
        <p>The police now say that Robert Angona is one of five or six aliases used by a man who is wanted by the federal government. The man, who is also known as John R. Blumatte and John R. Blue, has an arrest record dating to 1961 that includes assault, multiple counts of fraud, sexual assault and grand larceny.</p>
        <p>While Angona is an assumed identity, his true name remained unclear yesterday. ''I wouldn't be surprised if his wife didn't know his real name,'' one investigator said. The Manhattan district attorney's office said Mr. Angona was represented by a lawyer, but he could not be located.</p>
        <p>The academy, which offers graduate programs and lectures at its building on Franklin Street near Church Street, is known for its unusual emphasis on portraying the human figure.</p>
        <p>While it may seem odd that Warhol, the pop artist, supported such a school, he himself had been trained as a classical artist. ''Andy really felt that artists should learn all the tools of their trade, so to speak,'' said Vincent Fremont, one of the founding directors of the Warhol Foundation, which has given the academy more than $1 million.</p>
        <p>The school's board is stocked with wealthy donors, and attracts social glitter with its annual TriBeCa Ball, its fund-raising auction called Take Home a Nude, and the fact that Prince Charles is a patron.</p>
        <p>The initial financial backing for the school was provided by Mr. Pivar, and Mr. Angona might never have been caught if Mr. Pivar had not retained a proprietary air toward the academy, although he left the board on bitter terms in the mid-1990's.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pivar now says that longtime staff members considered Mr. Angona abusive and erratic, and he heard so many complaints that early this year he notified the board that something was amiss.</p>
        <p>Longtime staff members quit or were forced out. Abdelssalem Zahzam, who ran the school's cafe for many years, filed a complaint last year with the New York State Labor Department, saying that Mr. Angona drove him out by abusing him about his religion (he is Muslim). The academy's position is that Mr. Zahzam quit rather than take another position after the cafe was closed.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Pivar's early warnings went unheeded, it is little wonder. He once sued the school over some missing plaster casts he donated. He filed a petition with the New York State Board of Regents alleging mismanagement and demanding that the trustees be replaced. He became so unpopular with the school administration that in 2000 he was physically expelled from the annual benefit. He complained about the academy so much that even his friends stopped taking his allegations too seriously, said Samuel Adams Green, another former trustee.</p>
        <p>''You can cry wolf just so many times,'' he said, adding that he has tended to believe Mr. Pivar's criticisms. About a month ago, Mr. Pivar hired Bo Dietl, a well-known private investigator, to check out Mr. Angona. By early April, Mr. Dietl had decided that Mr. Angona was not who he said he was -- though it was unclear exactly who he really was.</p>
        <p>At a news conference yesterday, Mr. Dietl recounted how his investigators followed Mr. Angona to Coldwaters restaurant on Second Avenue near 53rd Street and paid a waitress to give them his glass, which was then dusted for fingerprints.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dietl said that Mr. Angona was convicted twice for theft, including passing bad checks in amounts exceeding $75,000, under the name John R. Blue. There were no records for the company he claimed to have worked for before Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>As questions were raised recently about Mr. Angona's identity, school officials requested Mr. Angona's Social Security number, but he refused to provide it, said Gerald McKelvey, a spokesman for the academy.</p>
        <p>On April 11, The Mail on Sunday in London reported that Mr. Angona was ''alleged to be a fraudster,'' and the next day a news organization gave the academy a copy of information complied by Mr. Dietl, Mr. McKelvey said. The next day, he added, the school's locks were changed, and school officials were at the district attorney's office within days.</p>
        <p>Last Friday, Mr. Angona was arrested as he walked his dog near his apartment on East 54th Street. When approached by officers, one investigator said, he pushed one aside and tried to walk away. He complained of chest pains and was taken to New York Weill Cornell Medical Center, where he remained yesterday.</p>
        <p>He is expected to be arraigned tomorrow on charges of grand larceny and resisting arrest.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Mr. Pivar called on the Regents to replace the board, saying that the Angona incident was just the latest in a series of administrative problems. A Regents spokesman said the matter was under review.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green, the other former trustee, confirmed that there had been accounting problems in the past. As at many arts institutions, he said, ''Everybody was trying to do everything on the cheap, and sometimes, you get what you pay for.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
