<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="701591"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E5DD123EF937A15754C0A962958260" item-length="683" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PLAYING IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MONIQUE P. YAZIGI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WASHINGTON HEIGHTS Synagogue's Treasures Find a Safe Harbor</p>
        <p>When an artillery shell crashed through the roof of an old synagogue in the Croatian port of Dubrovnik in the beginning of 1992, the congregation knew it was time to find a safe haven for its sacred treasures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WASHINGTON HEIGHTS Synagogue's Treasures Find a Safe Harbor</p>
        <p>When an artillery shell crashed through the roof of an old synagogue in the Croatian port of Dubrovnik in the beginning of 1992, the congregation knew it was time to find a safe haven for its sacred treasures.</p>
        <p>Its members packed up more than 80 items, including a 13th-century Torah and silver ornaments and textiles (detail above) and sent them to the Yeshiva University Museum. Fifty of those artifacts will be on display through December.</p>
        <p>The pieces came over in "two huge suitcases," recalled Randi Glickberg, associate director of the museum. "They were packed as if someone were going on vacation," she said, adding that while "it certainly wasn't museum crating, it was the easiest way to get them out of the country without any trouble."</p>
        <p>Yeshiva University Museum, 2520 Amsterdam Avenue, at 185th Street; Tuesday through Thursday, 10:30 A.M. to 5 P.M., Sunday 12 to 6 P.M.; $3 for adults, $1.50 for children 4 to 16 or those over 65; (212) 960-5390. LOWER MANHATTAN  Hockeymania Continues, But Off the Ice</p>
        <p>Hoping to capitalize on the hockeymania inspired by the Rangers' Stanley Cup victory, the National Hockey League will sponsor a street-hockey festival Saturday at the South Street Seaport. Several Rangers players, as well as members of the Islanders, and the New Jersey Devils will be on hand.</p>
        <p>Hockey can be played not only in ice skates, but in sneakers for street hockey or in-line skates for roller hockey, notes Stephen Solomon, the NHL's senior vice president.</p>
        <p>Six blocks of Water Street will be closed off for instructional clinics featuring the players; there will also be a radar gun to clock the speed of flying pucks. Roller- and street-hockey teams from around the city will compete. The Stanley Cup will be on display at the Seaport branch of Citibank, and hockey fans will be able to get players' autographs.</p>
        <p>Street Hockey at the Seaport, Water Street, between Fulton and Wall Streets; Saturday, July 30, 12 to 4 P.M.; free; (212) 789-2000. WAKEFIELD  African Culture: A Cause for Celebration</p>
        <p>Last year, Patrick Dechavennes, a real-estate-management consultant who calls himself a visionary, put together a street festival "celebrating the African culture." On Saturday, Mr. Dechavennes, who says his vision was a flesh-and-blood success, will do it again in the Agnes Hayward Playground on Barnes Avenue.</p>
        <p>"The people from this area are predominantly from an African ancestry," he said. "It's a time for us to celebrate our culture and honor ourselves."</p>
        <p>The fair will have vendors of African artifacts, clowns, art (above, a detail from a sculpture by Lavon Van Williams) and music.</p>
        <p>Heritage Street Festival, Agnes Hayward Playground, Barnes Ave. between 215th and 216th Sts., Wakefield, Bronx; Saturday, July 30, 10 A.M. to 8 P.M.; (718) 324-6938. HEARD AROUND TOWN</p>
        <p>CLEARWATER SLOOP SINGERS Sunset Picnic Concerts; folk singing; sponsored by the Rockaway Music and Arts Council and Gateway National Recreation Area; Floyd Bennett Field at Fort Tilden, Breezy Point, Queens; today, 6 P.M.; free; (718) 634-4747.</p>
        <p>GURER AYKAL CONDUCTS BEETHOVEN AND MENDELSSOHN Washington Square Festival Orchestra performs Beethoven's Violin Concerto in D Major, Suna Kan, soloist, and Mendelssohn's Symphony No. 1 in C minor, southeast quadrant of the park near the statue of Garibaldi; Tuesday, July 26, 8 P.M.; (212) 431-1088.</p>
        <p>BARBEQUE BAND WITH HAMIET BLUIETT AND DONALD HARRISON First in series of five Sunday concerts of jazz artists inspired by the soul sound of the 1960's; Frieda Schiff Warburg Memorial Sculpture Garden at the Brooklyn Museum, 200 Eastern Parkway, Brooklyn; Sunday, July 31, 3 to 4:30 P.M.; $6; (718) 638-5000.</p>
        <p>BROADWAY IN BRASS Bronx Arts Ensemble Brass Quintet; excerpts from Broadway classics; first in a series; Rockwood Drive Circle, Van Cortlandt Park (near Broadway and Mosholu Avenue), Bronx, 2 P.M.; and at McGinley Center, Fordham University, Bronx, Rose Hill campus, Sunday, July 31, 4 P.M.; free; (718) 601-7399. MONIQUE P. YAZIGI</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
