<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If Term Limits Are So Good, Who's First?</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="855268"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="NYC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERM LIMITS (POLITICAL OFFICE)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HABERMAN, CLYDE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/NYC</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960604T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DB1F39F937A35755C0A960958260" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If Term Limits Are So Good, Who's First?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE HABERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HABERMAN, CLYDE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EFFORTS are afoot to counter a form of Marxism that haunts New York: the ideology of term limits, imposed on local politicians by referendum three years  ago. We're talking about Groucho Marx, who didn't want to belong to any club that would have someone like him as a member.</p>
        <p>Under the new Marxism, the very fact that someone wants to remain in the club of elected officials means that the official shouldn't belong. Rules approved by voters in 1993 limit those elected that year to two terms, or eight  years. By Jan. 1, 2002, they must all clear out -- Mayor, Comptroller, Public Advocate, City Council members, Borough Presidents -- regardless of how good a job they may be doing or how popular they may be.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EFFORTS are afoot to counter a form of Marxism that haunts New York: the ideology of term limits, imposed on local politicians by referendum three years  ago. We're talking about Groucho Marx, who didn't want to belong to any club that would have someone like him as a member.</p>
        <p>Under the new Marxism, the very fact that someone wants to remain in the club of elected officials means that the official shouldn't belong. Rules approved by voters in 1993 limit those elected that year to two terms, or eight  years. By Jan. 1, 2002, they must all clear out -- Mayor, Comptroller, Public Advocate, City Council members, Borough Presidents -- regardless of how good a job they may be doing or how popular they may be.</p>
        <p>But with Election '96 approaching, an idea is making the rounds to put the matter before the voters again, just to make sure, the basic question for them being, Is this what you really want?</p>
        <p>True, 59 percent of the voters in 1993 endorsed term limits, the solution du jour in the prevailing "throw the bums out" climate. But that amounted to only 18 percent of all registered voters, because relatively few people actually cast ballots on this issue. And the pro-limits side had decided advantages. The referendum had been on the ballot for only two weeks, and Ronald S. Lauder, heir to the cosmetics fortune, was no powder puff in bankrolling his New Yorkers For  Term Limits.</p>
        <p>WHY not revisit the issue once more, with enough time and money invested so that all positions are well debated? That is the call from assorted good-government groups, which point out that there have always been term limits. They are called elections. The last three mayors were all voted out of office. Of the 35 people who sat on the City Council eight years ago, 15 are gone.</p>
        <p>"Let the people decide who shall serve and who shall not," said Nathan Leventhal, chairman of the Citizens Union and a former top aide to several mayors.</p>
        <p>By now the arguments are familiar.</p>
        <p>Here is the pro-limits side: Incumbents have a lock on money and media access that makes them challengeproof. Term restrictions would bring new blood and new ideas, especially to a City Council that hardly evokes the Age of Pericles. "The public is tired of business as usual," Dominick Fusco, vice chairman of the Lauder group, said. "If you can't do your job in eight years there's something wrong."</p>
        <p>But the counterarguments carry more weight with good-government types. Running New York is a complicated affair, and so, they say, tossing someone out  just when he has learned the ropes is a simplistic and foolish response.  A City Council filled with new faces would be weaker than ever against a Mayor, who, even if new himself, has a powerful bureaucracy at his beck and call. How many people of quality will be eager to run for office knowing, as Mr. Leventhal put  it, that "you get your layoff notice the same day you get elected"?</p>
        <p>And then there is the business of, ahem, democracy. You know, vox pop and all that. "We have to make people understand that term limits limit their rights," said Councilman Stanley E. Michels, Democrat of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>In reality a straightforward re-examination of the issue is unlikely. The Council is too afraid of voter retribution for that. Instead, members say they are more apt to ask voters to approve a staggered electoral system that would keep term limits but also keep virtually all present officeholders from being swept out at once. The 1993 vote, they warn, is a disaster in the making, unless modified.</p>
        <p>ONE recently floated idea would have kept some Council leaders in office until today's kindergarteners are ready for college. But it looked so much like  a job-protection plan for incumbents that it faded quickly. Now the Council is shopping for alternatives by holding hearings like one yesterday on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>The usefulness of this exercise is debatable. At a hearing in the Bronx last week Council members had a habit of asking questions that could elicit but one response, that term limits are bad. There hadn't been so much spoonfeeding of lines since Edgar Bergen held Charlie McCarthy in his lap. Still, the idea of staggered elections had support. Even Mr. Fusco said it made sense.</p>
        <p>But to get any proposal on the November ballot, the Council has to act in a  few weeks. The sooner the better, some say. Then attention can turn to a term-limits question that New Yorkers really care about. Is there nothing to be  done about this Baltimore ballplayer, this Ripken, who thinks he can go on forever?</p>
        <p>NYC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
