<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hearings Set On Examining School Crime</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="776538"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOY, VIVIAN S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CORTINES, RAMON C (CHANCELLOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DF133AF932A15754C0A963958260" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hearings Set On Examining School Crime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN S. TOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOY, VIVIAN S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's commission on school safety announced yesterday that public hearings to investigate crime in the school system would begin in late summer or early fall -- precisely when the school board will be in the middle of its search for a new schools chancellor.</p>
        <p>While school officials said they hoped the timing of the hearings would not complicate the search, school safety has long been a source of tension between the Mayor and the Board of Education. Schools Chancellor Ramon C. Cortines decided to resign the day after the Mayor created the safety commission and gave it the power to subpoena witnesses and documents from the school board.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani's commission on school safety announced yesterday that public hearings to investigate crime in the school system would begin in late summer or early fall -- precisely when the school board will be in the middle of its search for a new schools chancellor.</p>
        <p>While school officials said they hoped the timing of the hearings would not complicate the search, school safety has long been a source of tension between the Mayor and the Board of Education. Schools Chancellor Ramon C. Cortines decided to resign the day after the Mayor created the safety commission and gave it the power to subpoena witnesses and documents from the school board.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, however, John H. Beckman, a spokesman for Mr. Cortines, downplayed any connection between the hearings and the chancellor search. "They're two completely separate issues," he said.</p>
        <p>The Mayor has repeatedly said that the Police Department should take control of the school safety division, while the board and Mr. Cortines have insisted that school security is best handled by the school system.</p>
        <p>Edward N. Costikyan, chairman of the Mayor's commission, said yesterday that he did not believe the hearings would affect the selection of a new chancellor.</p>
        <p>"I would hope that one of the areas the board will look at is the role a new chancellor will play in school safety, but I don't see the two things getting tied together," he said. "I do not view the commission as putting pressure on the board to do anything except to deal with the school safety problem."</p>
        <p>Mr. Costikyan said the hearings would try to define the crime problem in city schools, examine how the division is run and consider how it should be changed.</p>
        <p>He added that he did not yet know whether specific incidents at schools would be vividly detailed.</p>
        <p>"If there are lurid things happening at schools, and they are relevant, then that might come out in the hearings," Mr. Costikyan said. "But the purpose of the hearings is not to frighten the public, it's to find out the reality."</p>
        <p>But the Manhattan Borough President, Ruth W. Messinger, said that the hearings might drive a larger wedge between the Mayor and the board.</p>
        <p>"I would hope the commission would handle the hearings in a responsible fashion," she said. "But if all kinds of decisions are made without consulting the board, then that would stir up a source of tension."</p>
        <p>The Mayor originally said the commission would make its recommendations by the end of summer, but Mr. Costikyan said commission members had found the issue to be much more complicated than they anticipated.</p>
        <p>"The data are more complex than I thought they would be," he said, noting that the school system and the teachers' union seemed to define crime in schools differently and therefore claimed different levels of school violence.</p>
        <p>"Our first job is going to be to define the problem," he said.</p>
        <p>Once that is done, the commission will look into how the 3,200-member division of security officers is deployed and request testimony from experts on how to improve the force.</p>
        <p>The Mayor has criticized the board for failing to improve recruitment and training at the school safety division and blamed the board's failure for a spate of misconduct by school safety officers.</p>
        <p>The commission has met regularly since it was formed in early June, and has spoken informally with a variety of experts on school safety.</p>
        <p>"We've been interviewing people, getting mail, reading reports -- doing all the things you do when you prepare a case," said Mr. Costikyan, an attorney at Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton &amp; Garrison who is also a fellow at the conservative Manhattan Institute.</p>
        <p>Mr. Costikyan also announced yesterday that a litigation partner at his firm, Bruce Birenboim, would serve as chief counsel for the commission and be in charge of organizing the hearings and preparing witnesses. He also named Sally Renfro as the commission's research director. Ms. Renfro is an attorney and a former public school teacher.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
