<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Benetton's unrepentant adman vows to keep pushing the envelope.</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="776681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BENETTON GROUP SPA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELLIOTT, STUART</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOSCANI, OLIVIERO</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEEDC1030F932A15754C0A963958260" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Benetton's unrepentant adman vows to keep pushing the envelope.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ELLIOTT, STUART</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OLIVIERO TOSCANI, your worldwide campaigns for Benetton featuring contentious, startling images of strife and turmoil have been ruled illegal by German judges and offensive by a French court. And they are castigated by consumers who perceive them as opportunistic exploitations of human frailties. What are you going to do next?</p>
        <p>Mr. Toscani's reply, delivered yesterday in his characteristically puckish manner: more of the same. An unrepentant, undaunted Mr. Toscani said he would not only produce additional provocative advertising for the clothing lines marketed by Benetton Group S.p.A., but would adopt the same pot-stirring tactics to sell the company's sporting goods like tennis racquets, in-line skates and ski boots.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OLIVIERO TOSCANI, your worldwide campaigns for Benetton featuring contentious, startling images of strife and turmoil have been ruled illegal by German judges and offensive by a French court. And they are castigated by consumers who perceive them as opportunistic exploitations of human frailties. What are you going to do next?</p>
        <p>Mr. Toscani's reply, delivered yesterday in his characteristically puckish manner: more of the same. An unrepentant, undaunted Mr. Toscani said he would not only produce additional provocative advertising for the clothing lines marketed by Benetton Group S.p.A., but would adopt the same pot-stirring tactics to sell the company's sporting goods like tennis racquets, in-line skates and ski boots.</p>
        <p>"Sufficient mediocrity is produced daily, particularly in the advertising world," an amiably defiant Mr. Toscani, the creative director of Benetton Group in Treviso, Italy, said in an interview. He and other top Benetton executives visited New York to introduce the first corporate image and product campaign for Benetton Sportsystem, parent of 11 brands like Prince, Rollerblade, Nordica and Killer Loop, which account for $900 million, or 15 percent, of Benetton's annual revenue of $6 billion.</p>
        <p>"Creativity is not based on security," Mr. Toscani said. "Once you're secure, you're doing something that's already been done."</p>
        <p>"Advertising agencies make millions by repeating the same old thing," he added. "They spent billions and billions and in the end there's no difference between Coke and Pepsi, Avis and Hertz, American Express and Visa. We try to go another way."</p>
        <p>The budget for the Benetton Sportsystem campaign, which carries the theme "Do you play life," is estimated at $18 million to $27 million. The print advertisements, in typical Toscani fashion, use a sperm cell as an iconic mascot; the quest to fertilize an egg is "the first human race," he said, laughing.</p>
        <p>Later, at a crowded news conference at the Benetton Sportsystem office in midtown Manhattan, Mr. Toscani elaborated: "Sport is very much linked with life. Survival is the game."</p>
        <p>Some ads mimic those for United Colors of Benetton apparel but with a Benetton Sportsystem logo. There are photographs of swimming spermatozoons, Cuban refugees sailing to the United States ("the America's Cup played between Cuba and Florida," as Mr. Toscani described it), muzzled greyhounds racing ("Wall Street yuppies," he called them) and an atomic explosion.</p>
        <p>Other ads depart from the clothing campaigns by juxtaposing prosaic product shots with shocking images, a device Mr. Toscani likened to reading a daily newspaper and finding "in the same pages war, AIDS, love, hate, sport, life, death, product."</p>
        <p>One ad depicts the Crucifixion and an Asolo climbing boot. In a second ad, a Chinese student defying a line of tanks appears opposite a Rollerblade skate. Other ads compare Ektelon eyeguards to a condom -- "Do you play safe" -- and the attributes of Prince racquets to the way Fidel Castro plays baseball. ("If you want the power, take it in your hands.")</p>
        <p>And in two ads for Kastle skis, there are German and American athletes in Nazi and black-power salutes during the 1936 and 1968 Summer Olympics. The pun-filled text reads: "Do you play race. All men are equal, not all skis. If you want to race, choose the chosen ones. Kastle Pure and Speed Machine. Only for racers (not for racists)."</p>
        <p>Benetton Sportsystem, which operates in more than 100 countries, had qualms about following the Benetton apparel model of shock-value selling, said Silvano Storer, chief executive of Benetton Sportsystem.</p>
        <p>"Of course we debated it a lot," he said. "Sometimes we even fought a lot. But we strongly believe there is the right balance between the innovation and what is needed to explain the sporting-goods products."</p>
        <p>It is, he added, "an acceptable risk."</p>
        <p>Alessandro Benetton, president of Benetton Sportsystem Communication and a member of the founding Benetton family, agreed. After a jocular reference to "the next crimes of Oliviero Toscani," he said, "For us, communication is a product itself."</p>
        <p>Before, during and after the news conference, Mr. Toscani was pressed on the issue of whether his style was counterproductive because it alienated potential customers.</p>
        <p>"You always have to consider that," he said. "But you can't exploit reality."</p>
        <p>"Traditional advertising also exploits human emotion," he asserted, by promising romance, success and happiness for buying the right brands. "That is even worse. We don't say that.</p>
        <p>"The fact they censor us is a big honor. It says we're saying something new."</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
