<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times;The Genuine Jordan Puts Family First</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="858579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHICAGO BULLS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARATON, HARVEY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JORDAN, MICHAEL MICHAEL JEFFERY JORDAN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Chicago Bulls</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DA1439F93BA25755C0A960958260" item-length="832" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times;The Genuine Jordan Puts Family First</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ARATON, HARVEY;</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE couldn't hit a jump shot, and he cried like a baby. Michael Jordan was almost an ordinary man here Sunday night, physically exhausted and emotionally spent. More human, more appealing, more like the Mike we could all very well be.</p>
        <p>He misses his murdered father, and he was not ashamed to weep for him on worldwide television, on Father's Day. He said, of the Chicago Bulls' fourth championship, "This is for Daddy." Even the kids who were watching had to know that deep within Jordan is an emptiness that all the sneaker-generating revenue  in the world can't fill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE couldn't hit a jump shot, and he cried like a baby. Michael Jordan was almost an ordinary man here Sunday night, physically exhausted and emotionally spent. More human, more appealing, more like the Mike we could all very well be.</p>
        <p>He misses his murdered father, and he was not ashamed to weep for him on worldwide television, on Father's Day. He said, of the Chicago Bulls' fourth championship, "This is for Daddy." Even the kids who were watching had to know that deep within Jordan is an emptiness that all the sneaker-generating revenue  in the world can't fill.</p>
        <p>There are societal criticisms of Jordan -- some fair, some not -- but one thing we should hope for is that he continues, in his advancing basketball age,  to be a man who misses "Daddy," as well as one who looked up in the stands the other night at the signs his three young children were holding for him.</p>
        <p>Jordan the champion. Jordan the gambler. Jordan the icon. Jordan the corporate front man. What makes up his global image creates in many minds a rather ambiguous portrait for someone as visible as him. But on the public issues of family and team, Jordan has been consistent and sure, at his best. He  ought to get credit for that.</p>
        <p>"Maybe I didn't feel as secure or as confident as I've been in the past," Jordan said after the Bulls closed out the Seattle SuperSonics and the long National Basketball Association season. "But what made the difference was my family's support, my wife and my kids. My wife pushed me every day. When I didn't feel like getting up and working with my trainer, she set the alarm and made sure I got up."</p>
        <p>He gave Juanita Jordan as much praise as he gave his father, James. And he applauded Scottie Pippen, his Tonto-like "little brother," and then read a roll  call of role players, from Jud Buechler to Steve Kerr to Randy Brown. He said he was thrilled for these basketball transients to have won their rings. His record says that he meant it, too.</p>
        <p>When Trent Tucker and Darrell Walker were veteran spares on Jordan's 1993 title team, the two former Knicks were amazed how often Jordan talked about them having the chance to join him on the finals stage, how much he wanted that for them.</p>
        <p>"Almost like a father wants to provide for his kids," is the way Tucker once  put it.</p>
        <p>It's not easy for any of them to play with Jordan, as demanding, as cruelly competitive as he can be. All season long, as the Bulls rolled on, Jordan claimed that his own artless struggles dealing with the culture of the curveball made him more tolerant of players less talented and driven than him. But as the Bulls temporarily lost their focus in the finals, Jordan could be seen barking at teammates, jumping at referees, seething in Seattle.</p>
        <p>Hypocrite? Hardly. There are no parallels between Jordan's bullying and what  has been decried, to the point of cliche now, as the trademark conduct of Generation X. If the Bulls were to win, someone had to steady the fragile Pippen, push the timid Toni Kukoc, restrain the rogue in Dennis Rodman. It can't be coincidence that with the Bulls, Rodman performed magnificently when he had to. It was partly Jordan, doing what the genteel David Robinson could not do last season in San Antonio. Get his house in order, no matter what it took.</p>
        <p>Much as he loves teeing off, Jordan is no blithe country club aristocrat, and never will be. Graying baby boom sportswriters hold professional golfers up as America's true sportsmen now, as if there are any rational comparisons to be made between the sunny, exclusionary province of the rich and a grueling sport that finds much of its talent among the urban poor.</p>
        <p>Jordan's world is somewhere between that, a working-class kid who has earned  extraordinary wealth only to be viciously robbed of the father who was his most  trusted friend. Ultimately, he is a man who brings to his work the entitlement of the chosen, but the edge and anger of the wretched. And those bottled-up emotions are unleashed in bursts of brilliance, or in heaves of sorrow on the locker room floor.</p>
        <p>On the stage, at least, there is no argument about it being honest and real.  Jordan shot woefully Sunday night, but was genuinely pleased to have had his teammates bail him out. It meant that he had done his job in other ways. He had  provided leadership for his team, for his basketball brood. For Father's Day, he got a title instead of a tie.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
