<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Group Makes the Case for Black Agencies and Media</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="395353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AFRICAN AMERICAN MARKETING &amp; MEDIA ASSN</org>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF1539F935A15753C1A966958260" item-length="633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Group Makes the Case for Black Agencies and Media</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOME of the biggest black-owned advertising agencies and media companies have formed a trade organization, the African American Marketing and Media Association, hoping to increase advertising to black audiences, alter what it sees as stereotyping and find more work for its members.</p>
        <p>The group plans to get in touch with advertisers that it thinks could use black representation on the account and creative sides.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOME of the biggest black-owned advertising agencies and media companies have formed a trade organization, the African American Marketing and Media Association, hoping to increase advertising to black audiences, alter what it sees as stereotyping and find more work for its members.</p>
        <p>The group plans to get in touch with advertisers that it thinks could use black representation on the account and creative sides.</p>
        <p>"We know instinctively what will offend our audience, because we are our audience," said Ken Smikle, president of the organization and publisher of Target Market News, a national trade publication about black marketing. "What works creatively for whites won't necessarily work for blacks. It's time to say we are the experts and will no longer be ignored."</p>
        <p>The members of the Chicago-based organization include New York and Chicago advertising and public relations firms, as well as publishing houses and black radio networks.</p>
        <p>Through its research, the organization hopes to encourage advertisers to place more advertising in media intended for black audiences.</p>
        <p>"Our media has always been underutilized," said the association's chairman, Clarence O. Smith, president and co-founder of Essence Communications. "There probably is no media more persuasive with its audience than black media."</p>
        <p>The group will soon begin substantial research about black consumers that it plans to disseminate widely. "The data on black consumers has been no more than an asterisk," Mr. Smikle said. "You cannot go to a mall and interview a thousand consumers and have the 10 percent who happen to be black reflect accurate information about the group."</p>
        <p>Black Americans spend an estimated $63 billion annually.</p>
        <p>"The need for this organization was exacerbated by the growing number of so-called experts who have no track record in this area of marketing," Mr. Smikle observed.</p>
        <p>He mentioned BBDO, which released a report last year entitled "Black Readers of Consumer Publications" that drew what he thinks were inaccurate conclusions.</p>
        <p>"The BBDO study concludes that advertisers can reach black consumers just as effectively with white publications such as Parade as they could with such publications as Ebony," Mr. Smikle said. "As in most studies of the black consumer, their methodology is inadequate. There's no psychographic data that gets to the heart of why black consumers make certain purchasing decisions."</p>
        <p>Doug Alligood, vice president of special markets for BBDO, New York, who was in charge of the analysis for the study, denied it undermined the importance of black media. "What we found was that Parade reaches as many black readers as Ebony, but that it wouldn't make economic sense to use just Parade if you want to reach black consumers exclusively," he said. "We freely acknowledge that it was an analysis of numbers only."</p>
        <p>Another goal of the new organization is to find ways to combat sterotypical portrayals of blacks in advertising or what some executives at black-owned media companies see as insidious racism in advertising.</p>
        <p>"For example, there is a Nike public service anti-drug ad that features basketball player David Robinson," Mr. Smikle said, "in which words like stupid and garbage are used to describe people in the target audience. We would never speak to ourselves like that."</p>
        <p>Liz Dolan, a spokeswoman for Nike, denied the ads were patronizing or the language even accidentally inappropriate. "We were trying to be very strong and we wanted the ad to be strong," she said. "The ad is powerful because it's clear how David Robinson personally feels about how dangerous drugs are.</p>
        <p>"The ad is addressed to anyone who watches television. None of our ads are targeted at a specific racial group. The appeal of athletes is universal."  THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
