<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Hands That Caught Ryan's Heat</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="370048"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="SPORTS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RYAN, NOLAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKOW, IRA</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900721T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED71639F932A15754C0A966958260" item-length="800" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Hands That Caught Ryan's Heat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKOW, IRA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Jeff Torborg talked about his left hand, the hand that caught most of Nolan Ryan's booming fastballs in 1973 when the two players were with the California Angels. It was the year that Ryan, with his 100-mile-per-hour heater (give or take a mile or two per hour of smoke on a given outing), established the major league record for strikeouts in a season, 383.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Jeff Torborg talked about his left hand, the hand that caught most of Nolan Ryan's booming fastballs in 1973 when the two players were with the California Angels. It was the year that Ryan, with his 100-mile-per-hour heater (give or take a mile or two per hour of smoke on a given outing), established the major league record for strikeouts in a season, 383.</p>
        <p>Jeff Torborg talked about his left hand, the hand that caught most of Nolan Ryan's booming fastballs in 1973 when the two players were with the California Angels. It was the year that Ryan, with his 100-mile-per-hour heater (give or take a mile or two per hour of smoke on a given outing), established the major league record for strikeouts in a season, 383.</p>
        <p>''The index finger of the left hand, right where the joint meets the palm, is much thicker to this day,'' Torborg said recently by telephone, 17 years after having speared Ryan's fastball for the last time. ''Of course, that wasn't just from catching Nolan. I caught Sandy Koufax at the end of his career when I was with the Dodgers. And there were other hard throwers along the way. The swelling was cumulative.</p>
        <p>''But no,'' said Torborg, ''Nolan didn't help this hand. He could certainly do damage.''</p>
        <p>Torborg, now the manager of the Chicago White Sox, was at the end of his major league career in 1973, but memories of Ryan, who last night with the Texas Rangers gained the 299th victory of his career, are indelible, just as they are with two other retired catchers, Jerry Grote, formerly of the Mets, and Alan Ashby, the ex-Astro.</p>
        <p>Those three catchers hunkered behind the plate during a good portion of the games that Ryan, now 43 and still formidable, has pitched in his 24 years in the major leagues with, first, the Mets, and then the Angels, the Astros and the Rangers.</p>
        <p>That trio of catchers also, of course, caught a large number of the record 5,000-plus strikeouts Ryan has amassed.</p>
        <p>''I caught Nolan when he first came up to the majors in 1966,'' said Grote, now a sales manager of a real estate company in San Antonio, ''and for his four years with the Mets after that. I caught him with padding, of course, and with my forefinger out of the glove, for extra cushion. So my hand was pretty well protected. But, yes, sure, the finger portion of my hand still took a bit of a beating.''</p>
        <p>Ashby, newly retired from baseball and living in Houston, recalled that Ryan sometimes hid the catcher's mitts, tossing them under the dugout bench. ''I used to like to catch with old rag gloves,'' recalled Ashby, ''and Nolan hated them. He was like most fastball pitchers. He wanted you to use new leather so that there was a louder pop to his pitches. He'd say, 'Aw, c'mon, make it at least sound right.'</p>
        <p>''That's a big part of the psychology of pitching. A bigger poom! can scare hitters. Everybody sitting in the dugout looks at each other and says, 'Jeez, he's throwin' good tonight.'''</p>
        <p>When catching Ryan, recalled Grote, he couldn't squat in the normal receiver's position. ''You had to get up a little straighter,'' he said, ''otherwise there was no way you could get to his fastballs at the letters. We had some very hard throwers on the Mets in those years: Seaver and Koosman, for example. But none threw quite as hard as Nolan. I'd say it boils down to about a two-foot difference.''</p>
        <p>In the year that Ryan broke the single-season strikeout record, 1973, one of his victims was Ashby, then a rookie with the Cleveland Indians. ''I remember I got a hit off him the first time,'' said Ashby, ''and the next time I maybe took too big a swing. I think I swung hard and spun around. It was like I was saying, 'I'm in charge.' ''On the next pitch, he cleaned off the inside of the plate a little bit. It was a fastball, high and tight, and I hit the ground. I said to myself, 'Oh, oh, I'd done something wrong.' And he was saying, 'Hey, kid, if you wanna spin, I'll be the one to spin you.' I found that he's the greatest guy off the field. But between the lines, he's the most serious player there is.''</p>
        <p>''What's made Nolan so effective is his curveball,'' said Torborg. ''It was the same with Koufax. Major league hitters can begin to time even the best fastball. And earlier this year, when Nolan pitched a one-hitter and struck out 16 of our batters, it was the curveball that was killing us. And he's improved that considerably since I last caught him.''</p>
        <p>Grote talked about Ryan's excellent pitching mechanics, his low ''drop-and-drive'' delivery; Torborg mentioned his work ethic and his superb conditioning, and Ashby marveled at his competitiveness.</p>
        <p>''I remember when Pete Rose was going for the National League all-time base-hit record and needed two hits to break it,'' recalled Ashby, ''and he had predicted that he'd do it on a certain day. And on that day he was facing Nolan. Rose got a base hit his first time up, and then Nolan struck him out the next three times. And after the last -everyone in both dugouts had been standing to see what would happen - Pete turned to Nolan and doffed his cap, and then walked on.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure that all the rest of the players felt like doffing our caps to Nolan, too.''  SPORTS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
