<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Bemoaning Their Bad Breaks</title>
    <meta content="08HOCK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="N.H.L. PLAYOFFS" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="928345"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="N.H.L. PLAYOFFS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lemaire, Jacques</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DC1639F93BA35756C0A961958260" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Bemoaning Their Bad Breaks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils Coach Jacques Lemaire complains about officiating in second-round playoff series against New York Rangers; Rangers lead series two games to one; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The term ''off day'' means different things to different teams, especially to the Rangers and the Devils and their coaches.</p>
        <p>After defeating the Devils by 3-2 on Tuesday night to take a two-games-to-one edge in their second-round Stanley Cup playoff series, the Rangers scheduled an optional practice yesterday in Rye, N.Y.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The term ''off day'' means different things to different teams, especially to the Rangers and the Devils and their coaches.</p>
        <p>After defeating the Devils by 3-2 on Tuesday night to take a two-games-to-one edge in their second-round Stanley Cup playoff series, the Rangers scheduled an optional practice yesterday in Rye, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Most players stayed home, including the Manhattan-based stars like Wayne Gretzky, Mike Richter and Brian Leetch. Mark Messier dropped by only for medical treatment. The coach, Colin Campbell, stood in a room filled with mirrors, cracking wise.</p>
        <p>Do officials favor the veteran Ranger stars who have celebrity status, as Devils Coach Jacques Lemaire, and some of his players, have suggested?</p>
        <p>''Other than the linesmen holding their canes, I don't think we get any preferential treatment,'' Campbell said. In a serious vein, Campbell called the favoritism theory ''crazy.''</p>
        <p>His players then spent last night with their families, or wherever they chose, and will report to work, business as usual, tonight for Game 4 of the Eastern Conference semifinals at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>The Devils also had an optional practice in East Rutherford, N.J., but every player had to report anyway for a meeting.</p>
        <p>After the skating, Lemaire sat behind a formal podium complaining about the officiating. Later last night, his players were due back in their suburban hotel, where they are quarantined during the tournament.</p>
        <p>''The boys, they want that, they like that, to be together,'' Lemaire said of the hotel. ''It gives them a chance to know each other more. It's the focus. Everyone thinks the same way. Everyone has the same goal.''</p>
        <p>With one cup championship and another appearance in the conference finals in his first three seasons with the Devils, Lemaire has established himself as a top National Hockey League coach. Campbell, with two second-round exits in two seasons, has much to prove.</p>
        <p>But thus far in this series, Campbell seems to have the upper hand. His mood, and Lemaire's mood, might affect and reflect those of their players. The Rangers and their coach seem loose. Their luck -- the residue of design -- is running hot, what with two tying goals by the Devils having been negated because New Jersey players were illegally in the goal crease.</p>
        <p>The Devils not only have these self-inflicted wounds, but they also admitted they were too keyed up Tuesday, throwing themselves out of position while falling behind, 2-0.</p>
        <p>Lemaire complained that Messier illegally influenced Referee Kerry Fraser to initiate a video review that nullified Doug Gilmour's tying goal. Told of Lemaire's comment, Campbell said Lemaire ''must be getting desperate.''</p>
        <p>Asked yesterday if he was desperate, Lemaire concurred, somewhat.</p>
        <p>''I am today from what I saw,'' he said, referring to what he called inconsistent officiating. ''I'm tired of seeing the same thing all the time, over and over.'' He also used the word ''depressed'' a couple of times.</p>
        <p>''I just want a fair game,'' Lemaire continued. ''I don't want to say we're getting the shaft or whatever. It's just the situation. I think they have a problem.'' But some of Lemaire's problems might be of his own making. One observer asked about his forward line rotation. Why does Lemaire use three lines instead of four when a four-line rotation used to wear down Devils opponents?</p>
        <p>Lemaire said he has used four lines less since Doug Gilmour joined the team late in the season. And he added that ''the team you play against will dictate'' some strategy.</p>
        <p>''If you feel your fourth line is not capable of playing solid against their top lines, you hold back,'' Lemaire said. What this means is that, by using Messier and Gretzky so much, Campbell has altered Lemaire's approach.</p>
        <p>Campbell also gets last choice of personnel matchups at home. But on Tuesday, he settled for the same matchups Lemaire wanted in the Meadowlands. Someone asked Campbell if he played ''mind games'' with Lemaire by giving Lemaire the matchups he wanted.</p>
        <p>Campbell chuckled and nodded.</p>
        <p>''Yeah, I did,'' Campbell said.</p>
        <p>Because Lemaire uses only three lines, ''I don't have to worry so much,'' the Ranger coach said.</p>
        <p>All this doesn't guarantee a series upset for the Rangers. Lemaire and several Devils said they felt they could gain a victory tonight to tie the series and change its momentum. Asked about Campbell's observation that Lemaire is ''desperate,'' Devils defenseman Ken Daneyko scoffed.</p>
        <p>''No, not at all,'' Daneyko said. ''Colin Campbell likes to say a lot of things. He has a lot of chirping to do in the papers. I'm not concerned what he has to say. Jacques is a pretty upbeat guy.''</p>
        <p>He also said that the hotel life is ''a small sacrifice for what you are trying to accomplish.'' And he suggested that the Devils might be better off taking fewer emotional penalties.</p>
        <p>Lemaire said that ''it's just a matter of time'' before ''it's going to turn in our favor.'' He held his finger and thumb an inch apart while saying ''we're about this much from where I would like to be'' and said the players ''are right at the doorstep of getting goals'' and that ''a team makes its own luck.''</p>
        <p>Over all, Lemaire said he still likes the matchup. He has more depth and less age. His team might still wear down the Rangers.</p>
        <p>''I'd love to go to seven games,'' Lemaire said. ''We'll have a little advantage.'' Perhaps they would, but to get there, they have to get to Game 6 first.</p>
        <p>N.H.L. PLAYOFFS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
