<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The 800-pound gorilla among advertisers, the auto industry, gained a little more weight in 1996.</title>
    <meta content="08ADCO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="928494"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Competitive Media Reporting</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chrysler Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Procter &amp; Gamble Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philip Morris Companies Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Meredith, Robyn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970508T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DA1F30F93BA35756C0A961958260" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The 800-pound gorilla among advertisers, the auto industry, gained a little more weight in 1996.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Robyn Meredith</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Meredith, Robyn</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Competitive Media Reporting says auto makers, traditionally nation's largest advertisers, nailed down industry's premier position even more securely in 1996 by raising their ad spending 9.4 percent over 1995; reports auto industry as a whole spent $11.6 billion on advertising, or more than 17 percent of $66.7 billion that nation's advertisers spent; General Motors Corp spent $1.61 bilion; Chrysler Corp, number 4, spent $1.07 billion, while Ford Motor Co, number 5, spent $843 million; sandwiched between car makers were Procter &amp; Gamble and Philip Morris, respectively number 2 and number 3; other rankings noted (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AUTO makers, traditionally the nation's largest advertisers, nailed down the industry's premier position even more securely last year by raising their ad spending 9.4 percent over 1995.</p>
        <p>Indeed, according to Competitive Media Reporting, a unit of VNU N.V. that tracks advertising expenditures, the auto industry as a whole spent $11.6 billion on advertising last year, or more than 17 percent of the $66.7 billion that the nation's advertisers spent. And the spending figures for auto companies do not include advertising paid for by local auto dealers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AUTO makers, traditionally the nation's largest advertisers, nailed down the industry's premier position even more securely last year by raising their ad spending 9.4 percent over 1995.</p>
        <p>Indeed, according to Competitive Media Reporting, a unit of VNU N.V. that tracks advertising expenditures, the auto industry as a whole spent $11.6 billion on advertising last year, or more than 17 percent of the $66.7 billion that the nation's advertisers spent. And the spending figures for auto companies do not include advertising paid for by local auto dealers.</p>
        <p>Showing just how large a shadow the industry casts on American advertising, each of Detroit's Big Three was among the nation's top five advertisers. The General Motors Corporation, the biggest advertiser, raised its advertising outlays by 13.4 percent over 1995, spending $1.61 billion last year.</p>
        <p>The Chrysler Corporation, No. 4, spent $1.07 billion on advertising, up 14.2 percent from 1995, while the Ford Motor Company, No. 5, spent $843 million, up just 1.6 percent.</p>
        <p>Sandwiched between the car makers were Procter &amp; Gamble, and Philip Morris, respectively No. 2 and No. 3. The pair of consumer products manufacturers swapped positions from 1995: P.&amp; G. raised its spending nearly 3 percent, to $1.49 billion, while Philip Morris actually cut its spending 10.8 percent, to $1.24 billion.</p>
        <p>Keeping pace with their American rivals, Japanese auto makers also increased their ad budgets last year. The Toyota Motor Corporation's ad spending rose 9.3 percent over 1995 levels to $560 million, while that of the Nissan Motor Company climbed 19.6 percent, to $439 million, and that of the Honda Motor Company rose a comparatively modest 1.2 percent, to $390 million.</p>
        <p>Each auto maker shifted money among different advertising media last year. Some bought more ads on syndicated television but fewer in local newspapers, and some companies spent more on network TV while others spent less on it.</p>
        <p>''You see different strategies,'' said Joseph C. Philport, executive vice president of Competitive Media Reporting, who when analyzing the data saw only one clear winner among advertising outlets. ''Magazines are doing fairly well in Detroit,'' he said. The top five auto advertisers all raised their spending for magazine ads last year.</p>
        <p>While G.M., the nation's biggest auto maker, has increased its overall advertising spending, it cut back its spending on network radio programs and on Sunday magazines. It sharply increased its outlays for magazines, cable television, network television, local newspapers and billboards.</p>
        <p>''We're using more paints on our palettes to do the marketing job,''  Phil Guarascio, G.M.'s general manager of marketing and advertising, said. ''Ten years ago, there was more reliance on major media.''</p>
        <p>One reason for the changes is that G.M. has shifted its marketing strategies in recent years to tailor pitches more carefully to potential buyers for each of its individual car and truck lines.</p>
        <p>Mr. Guarascio is also a fan of integrated marketing programs, such as the one in which the Buick Park Avenue teamed up with Food and Wine magazine for a special promotion.</p>
        <p>In another, the Chevrolet Venture mini-van has been linked in a 20-city shopping-mall tour to this summer's animated feature-length film by Walt Disney, ''Hercules.'' At each mall, monitors inside the mini-van show snippets of the new movie, and G.M. gives away a Venture in a contest.</p>
        <p>''More money has been moved to these integrated sorts of marketing programs,'' Mr. Guarascio said.</p>
        <p>Pursuing a different strategy, Chrysler has sharply reduced its spending on local newspapers, billboards and Sunday magazines. But it has strongly increased its advertising spending on magazines, national newspapers, network television, syndicated television and radio.</p>
        <p>Ford only raised its overall spending last year by a comparatively slight amount, but it spent much more buying ads in magazines and Sunday magazines, and on local and syndicated television. The company reduced its spending on network television and local newspapers, according to Competitive Media Reporting.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
