<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kuwaitis Press U.S. Over 12 Held at Guantánamo</title>
    <meta content="Y26KUW$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/26/international/middleeast/26KUWA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1403624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TRACES OF TERROR: DETAINEES' FAMILIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Guantanamo Bay Naval Base (Cuba)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kuwait</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macfarquhar, Neil</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Military Bases and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Kuwait</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E7D9173EF935A15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1310" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kuwaitis Press U.S. Over 12 Held at Guantánamo</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kuwaitis Sue U.S. Over 12 Held at Guantánamo</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Macfarquhar, Neil</byline>
      <dateline>KUWAIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Families of all 12 Kuwaitis known to be detainees at Guantanamo naval base file federal lawsuit seeking right to meet with prisoners and know charges against them; detainees, who mostly insist they were in Afghanistan or Pakistan doing charity work, are now sending sporadic messages home; photo; Kuwaiti government is paying costs of suit (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The notes arrive sporadically from the Kuwaiti prisoners held at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba.</p>
        <p>They contain brief messages, mostly asking whether a wife has given birth or how the children are doing in school. One included a despondent threat of suicide by hunger strike, while a few have snippets of wry humor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The families of all 12 of the Kuwaitis who are known to be detainees in Guantánamo are seeking the right to meet with the prisoners and to know the charges against them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The notes arrive sporadically from the Kuwaiti prisoners held at Guantánamo Bay, Cuba.</p>
        <p>They contain brief messages, mostly asking whether a wife has given birth or how the children are doing in school. One included a despondent threat of suicide by hunger strike, while a few have snippets of wry humor.</p>
        <p>''As for me, I am in the best of states, and I swear I am not a prisoner, but rather, in a five-star hotel, thank God,'' wrote Abdullah Kamel, 28, an assistant engineer at the Ministry of Electricity who, like most Kuwaitis captured in Afghanistan or Pakistan, insists that he was there only to do charity work.</p>
        <p>The families of all 12 of the Kuwaitis who are known to be detainees in Guantánamo want more than long postcards and have filed suit in United States District Court in Washington, D.C.</p>
        <p>They are seeking the right to meet with the prisoners and to know the charges -- if any -- against them. They want the detainees to have the right to lawyers and access to some form of court.</p>
        <p>''We can understand the war against terrorism, but there is something called human rights and the rule of law,'' said Khaled al-Odah, an American-trained, retired Kuwaiti Air Force pilot who acts as spokesman for the families.</p>
        <p>Mr. Odah has not heard from his son Fawzi, 24, who was a teacher at a Koran school, since he wrote in early January saying he was in American detention in Kandahar, Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>''We want to know the condition of our sons,'' Mr. Odah said, clicking prayer beads through his fingers as he spoke. ''Are they prisoners of war? Criminals? What are the accusations against them? We want to see them. How long are they going to be held? We want their legal rights.''</p>
        <p>Kuwaiti officials say the government is paying the legal costs, which the families say may reach $500,000 and which their law firm, Shearman &amp; Sterling, says it will donate to charity.</p>
        <p>The government's role spawned some criticism in Kuwait, with opposition politicians grumbling that the royal family is trying to curry favor with Islamic organizations and the Bedouin tribes, to which many of the detainees belong.</p>
        <p>The detainees seem to generate little attention and apparently little sympathy among the general public, though, for their claims that they devoted their vacation time last summer or fall to building mosques or helping orphans and refugees.</p>
        <p>The first hearing in the families' case, filed in May, is scheduled for June 26 before Judge Colleen Kollar-Kotelly. It is a joint hearing with another case filed earlier this year involving two Britons and an Australian.</p>
        <p>The United States government is seeking to have both lawsuits dismissed. It argues in its brief for the Kuwaiti case that the court does not have jurisdiction. It says that the detainees are foreign nationals not held on American territory and that the bench would be second-guessing decisions made by the president and the military in a time of war, matters the Constitution allots to the executive branch.</p>
        <p>But Thomas B. Wilner of Shearman &amp; Sterling's Washington office, the lead attorney for the Kuwaiti plaintiffs, contends that the government is seeking far more sweeping powers than it should.</p>
        <p>''The position the defendants are asking the court to adopt in this case -- an absolute bar to judicial review whenever aliens are detained outside the borders of a country -- would set a dangerous standard,'' Mr. Wilner said in a telephone interview.</p>
        <p>''It would seriously compromise the ability not only of foreign nationals,'' he said, ''but also of U.S. citizens to contest the conditions of their illegal detention by foreign governments.''</p>
        <p>The legal arguments include other issues, one of which is whether the base at Guantánamo can be considered United States territory. The government says no, since it is only leasing the land, while the lawyers for the Kuwaitis say it has in effect been under American control since 1903.</p>
        <p>The families' lawyers also say that the treatment of the detainees violates international law and that basic standards barring arbitrary detention should not be discarded during war no matter where the prisoners are held or why.</p>
        <p>Sheik Muhammad al-Sabah, the Kuwaiti minister of state for foreign affairs, said his country hoped to send a delegation to visit Guantánamo, something for which the United States has granted permission to other countries.</p>
        <p>''We think people are innocent until proven guilty,'' Sheik Muhammad said, comparing the men to Peace Corps volunteers. ''We are waiting to hear what sort of evidence the U.S. has on these people.''</p>
        <p>But other Kuwaitis are sure that jihad trumped charity.</p>
        <p>''Apart from the Islamists and their families, people don't believe this,'' said Abdullah Nibari, one of the stalwart liberals in Kuwait's Parliament, ''Many more were involved in the fighting than the 12; I doubt anyone knows the number. They were either convinced or misled that they were fighting an Islamic cause. Some thought it was their religious duty.''</p>
        <p>The least sympathetic suggest that the men should just stay in jail, while others note that under the guise of charity, religious Kuwaiti men often travel to places where their wealth gives them a certain cachet.</p>
        <p>''They were going there to get married,'' said Muhammad A. al-Jassem, editor in chief of the newspaper Al Watan. ''You can marry two, three, four, five women there. It is fun. Most of the people who say they're going there for charity enjoy playing around in an Islamic way.''</p>
        <p>Male relatives meet at least once weekly in Mr. Odeh's diwaniya, a room lined with couches that is a feature of every Kuwaiti home. The relatives chew over any developments and read the short notes in Arabic received through the mail or the International Committee of the Red Cross.</p>
        <p>A recent one came from Abdel Aziz al-Shimari, 38, a teacher in Kuwait's Koranic school. He wrote in late March that he was going to try to starve himself to death and asked his father and his brothers to look after his children.</p>
        <p>''I cannot tolerate this life and this place,'' he wrote in a letter that took three months to arrive.</p>
        <p>Nizar Kandari, a cousin of one detainee, said, ''Part of our confusion and fear is that the U.S. authority and public opinion do not differentiate between humanitarian aid and Arab Taliban fighters.''</p>
        <p>Munther Arabiah, the relative of another, added, ''If you are an Arab you are accused -- not just accused, guilty.''</p>
        <p>Relatives ponder whether prisoners accurately describe their treatment.</p>
        <p>''Now I am detained by the American troops and thanks be to God they are a good example of humanitarian behavior and I am in good health and condition,'' Fouad al-Rabiya, 43, an aviation engineer with Kuwait Airways, wrote from his initial detention in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kandari said: ''We don't know if he wrote his words freely. Maybe he wrote them under pressure, or just to calm down the family.''</p>
        <p>In the latest batch of three notes received in June, a month after they were written, the men finally indicated that they were getting mail from their families and knew about efforts to help them. But some exhibited a certain confusion.</p>
        <p>Saad al-Azmi, a 23-year-old detainee, said the United States Army ''transferred me many places, and I don't know where I am,'' adding, ''I asked the interrogator, and he said, 'You are in America now' and God knows.''</p>
        <p>TRACES OF TERROR: DETAINEES' FAMILIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
