<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Esiason's Status Goes From Start to Stopped</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="716579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL: JETS NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ESIASON, BOOMER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LITSKY, FRANK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEEDE103DF934A35753C1A962958260" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Esiason's Status Goes From Start to Stopped</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LITSKY, FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, L.I., Oct. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Will he or won't he? Will Boomer Esiason's sprained left ankle allow him to start on Sunday against the Indianapolis Colts or will he be sidelined again?</p>
        <p>It appeared today that Jack Trudeau would start, as he did last week against the Browns, with Esiason ready to play if needed. Esiason said he thought that would be the scenario and suspected Coach Pete Carroll had already made the decision. Carroll said he was not sure what would happen, that it depended on how Esiason felt.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Will he or won't he? Will Boomer Esiason's sprained left ankle allow him to start on Sunday against the Indianapolis Colts or will he be sidelined again?</p>
        <p>It appeared today that Jack Trudeau would start, as he did last week against the Browns, with Esiason ready to play if needed. Esiason said he thought that would be the scenario and suspected Coach Pete Carroll had already made the decision. Carroll said he was not sure what would happen, that it depended on how Esiason felt.</p>
        <p>In Wednesday's practice, Esiason took 40 percent of the snaps with the first team. But in an 11-on-11 drill today, he took only a handful and Trudeau took the rest. After practice, Esiason walked to the locker room like a man with a gimpy ankle.</p>
        <p>"It feels lousy," he said, "not much better than yesterday. I don't know if yesterday hurt me. I'll be ready to play, but I won't be 100 percent. If the decision is made that Jack starts, that's why we got him. I'm disappointed, but I'll be ready."</p>
        <p>Carroll said the decision on who will start was a day-to-day thing.</p>
        <p>"We're taking it easy on Boomer," he said. "The picture is a little fuzzier than it was yesterday. But he has a feel for what we're doing, and we haven't ruled him out."</p>
        <p>The problem is lateral mobility.</p>
        <p>"We have to make sure he can protect himself with movement," Carroll said.</p>
        <p>Esiason understood that. "It would be like Brian Leetch skating backward for the Rangers," he said. "The point is moving laterally, and I'm not able to do that the way I'd like."</p>
        <p>The Jets list Esiason as questionable, which means they give him a 50-50 chance to play.</p>
        <p>"That's probably about right," Carroll said. "It could go either way. If he's ready, he'll go. If not, if we need him, we will call on him." New Names in Lineup</p>
        <p>The Jets (2-3) have lost their last three games, and Coach Pete Carroll has promised subtle but unspecified lineup changes. Two possibilities, involving backups Ryan Yarborough and James Brown, have become apparent.</p>
        <p>When the Jets go to three wide receivers, Yarborough, a second-round draft choice, will join Rob Moore and Art Monk, the regulars. Stevie Anderson had been the third receiver, but Ray Sherman, the offensive coordinator, said Yarborough did good things in last Sunday's loss to Cleveland and merited more playing time.</p>
        <p>"Ryan has tremendous speed," Sherman said. "We've just go to get the ball downfield. Stevie fits in, but at the other receiving positions."</p>
        <p>Brown is a 6-foot-6-inch, 321-pound offensive tackle who had been Jeff Criswell's backup at left tackle. Now he is backing up Siupeli Malamala at right tackle, and in today's practice he took 40 percent of the snaps.</p>
        <p>Malamala sprained his left knee in the season opener and has not been at full strength. Larry Beightol, the Jets' offensive line coach, said there were no immediate plans to bench him.</p>
        <p>"It's an opportunity to show what I've got," Brown said. "Teams don't sub much in the offensive line, so if you're not a starter you're not going to play unless someone gets hurt. But I'm frustrated that I'm not playing. Maybe this will do me some good." A Wish Come True</p>
        <p>Nathan Smith's favorite football player is Boomer Esiason. Smith has cystic fibrosis and so does Esiason's 3-year-old son, Gunnar. Today, as part of a trip arranged by the Make-a-Wish Foundation, the 12-year-old eighth-grader from Cleveland, Tenn., met his hero at the Jets' complex here. He also wore Esiason's helmet for a few moments, relayed a play to him via helmet radio and left with game tickets, autographed footballs, photographs, posters and programs.</p>
        <p>"He's really a nice guy," Smith said. "He's fun to be around."</p>
        <p>The Make-a-Wish Foundation grants wishes to children with life-threatening and terminal illnesses. Willa Smith, Nathan's mother, said the oldest person with cystic fibrosis she knows of is a 35-year-old Florida woman. But she said Nathan, who contracted the pulmonary disease when he was 14 months old, was breathing much better because of a newly approved nasal spray. And she said gene therapy was close to realization.</p>
        <p>"He said, 'Mom, am I going to die from this?' " she said. "I don't expect him to die. He plans to go to medical school. He wants to be a doctor and be part of the cure."  PRO FOOTBALL: JETS NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
