<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Quest for Something Lasting</title>
    <meta content="19BOSS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/19/business/yourmoney/19boss.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1635922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cartier Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">De Quercize, Stanislas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tahmincioglu, Eve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/The Boss</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Careers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Human Resources</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Management</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE7DB1530F93AA25751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="816" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Quest for Something Lasting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Quest for Something Lasting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STANISLAS DE QUERCIZE; As told to Eve Tahmincioglu.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">De Quercize, Stanislas; Tahmincioglu, Eve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stanislaw de Quercize, president and chief executive of Cartier North America, comments on his background, career and philosophy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I WAS 7 years old, living in Champagne, on the same street as the Champagne company Mumm. The company paid to have a fresco done at a local chapel by the Japanese artist Tsugoharu Foujita. I remember one day I was playing in the street and I went to see what he was doing. It was fascinating. I ended up spending all my afternoons with him at the chapel for a month, watching him paint in silence.</p>
        <p>A photographer of the city took a picture of him and the chapel, but Foujita wanted me in the picture, too. I ended up being in the local newspaper.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stanislas De Quercize, president and chief executive of Carter North America, says that art has shaped his vision of the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I WAS 7 years old, living in Champagne, on the same street as the Champagne company Mumm. The company paid to have a fresco done at a local chapel by the Japanese artist Tsugoharu Foujita. I remember one day I was playing in the street and I went to see what he was doing. It was fascinating. I ended up spending all my afternoons with him at the chapel for a month, watching him paint in silence.</p>
        <p>A photographer of the city took a picture of him and the chapel, but Foujita wanted me in the picture, too. I ended up being in the local newspaper.</p>
        <p>Watching him, I became appreciative of somebody looking at the evolution of process. I realized how important it is to leave something behind, something of long-lasting value, not focused on the short term. We always long to be part of eternity. That fresco is still there today.</p>
        <p>Art has shaped my vision of the world. I am interested in contemporary art. I collect photographs. The artists live in the same world I'm living in, but see a different vision of the world. It helps to understand, everybody has a different vision.</p>
        <p>In business, there's a need for a lot of discussion to build a better vision. That's what I'm trying to do. Last year, I had an example of this. We're always trying to have the best location for our brand in stores. But one member of my team said we should have two small locations, boutiques, in a particular upscale New York store, instead of a big boutique. That's not my first impulse. My impulse is to be big and focused rather than multiple. But his idea proved to be successful. By accepting the vision of other people in the world I share, I know that enriches me.</p>
        <p>I began work with Procter &amp; Gamble in 1980 as a product manager. The packaging, the size, the formula were different all over Europe. The idea was to find how we could create one product, one packaging. So we had to figure out what makes the French, the Italians, the Swiss and the Greeks human beings. We found there is a fundamental need to be clean, to be seductive, and to seduce the other one by being clean. We all have the same DNA.</p>
        <p>I was at Procter &amp; Gamble for nine years and then I went to work for Montblanc and Dunhill in Paris. I made the career move about a year after my first son died.</p>
        <p>His name was Alban and he died of sudden infant death syndrome at one month old. When he was buried in France, the priest said something that stuck in my mind always. He said my son had a successful life. He was loved and he loved. That was a great mission in life, to love and to be loved.</p>
        <p>Procter &amp; Gamble was the rational side of me. I realized I needed to do another activity where I could use both my rational and emotional sides. The luxury end seemed to be a good fit for me. In luxury, there is a will to build something for a long term.</p>
        <p>Something else that played a role in my choice was that I come from a nice aristocratic family in Europe. One of my relatives did a good job for the king of France in the 17th century, and they gave my family a motto and a crest. Our family's motto was Quand Même, an expression loosely meaning ''We will do whatever it takes.'' It's kind of marketing for a family. If you have a motto you have to live with this motto. I found it funny; it was a mission statement before such a statement was developed by marketing.</p>
        <p>Growing up, when we would celebrate, we would celebrate a lot with Champagne. Champagne is like water over there.</p>
        <p>To make money in my early teens, I would help in harvesting of the Champagne grapes in September. It's very hard work, tiring because you know what is harvested one year will not be drunk for three years. They take the grape, press it and keep the juice for three years. Learning the value of maturation, it taught me respect for time and the influence of time.</p>
        <p>STANISLAS DE QUERCIZE  President and chief executive, Cartier North America</p>
        <p>HOMETOWN  Reims, France</p>
        <p>DATE OF BIRTH  March 13, 1957</p>
        <p>NUMBER OF WATCHES HE OWNS  25</p>
        <p>FAVORITE WATCHES  Cartier's American Tank and Roadster</p>
        <p>FAVORITE SHOPPING CITY  New York</p>
        <p>OFFICE SPACE: THE BOSS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
