<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Statehouse Journal; Term Limits Give Rise To a Comeback Kid, 65</title>
    <meta content="Y06BURT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="993275"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">John Burton</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Purdum, Todd S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burton, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D7153DF935A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="1180" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Statehouse Journal; Term Limits Give Rise To a Comeback Kid, 65</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Purdum, Todd S</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, Calif.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Burton, four-term Congressman before cocaine and alcohol caught up with him in 1982, is sworn in as President pro tem of California Senate; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Legislative term limits are supposed to produce legislative turnover, and here in the quiet old capital city of California, they certainly have. The Speakership of the State Assembly has changed hands five times in the last three years, after being wholly owned for 15 years by the irrepressible Willie L. Brown Jr.</p>
        <p>But of all the anomalies spawned by term limits, none has been more remarkable than the recent selection  of John Burton, an unrepentant 60's liberal from San Francisco, as the leader of the majority Democrats in the State Senate. Mr. Burton, the younger brother of the legendary United States Representative Philip Burton, and himself a four-term Congressman before cocaine and alcohol caught up with him in 1982, seems as surprised as everybody else.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Legislative term limits are supposed to produce legislative turnover, and here in the quiet old capital city of California, they certainly have. The Speakership of the State Assembly has changed hands five times in the last three years, after being wholly owned for 15 years by the irrepressible Willie L. Brown Jr.</p>
        <p>But of all the anomalies spawned by term limits, none has been more remarkable than the recent selection  of John Burton, an unrepentant 60's liberal from San Francisco, as the leader of the majority Democrats in the State Senate. Mr. Burton, the younger brother of the legendary United States Representative Philip Burton, and himself a four-term Congressman before cocaine and alcohol caught up with him in 1982, seems as surprised as everybody else.</p>
        <p>''It just happened,'' the new President pro tem said of his third-act triumph, in which he is replacing Senator Bill Lockyer, one of his old proteges, who must leave office because of term limits at the end of the year and has laid down his leadership duties to run for attorney general. ''It's just serendipity.''</p>
        <p>It is also a reflection of rapid change in the membership of the Legislature. California adopted term limits in 1990, in the vanguard of a national movement. All 80 current members of the Assembly have been elected since its limit of three two-year terms took effect, and most seats in the Senate, where the limit is two four-year terms, have turned over as well.</p>
        <p>Profane, ribald, his Irish eyes full of mischief above a salt-and-pepper mustache, the 65-year-old Mr. Burton is a gonzo guerrilla with a Swift ian wit who last year mocked Gov. Pete Wilson's proposals for welfare overhaul by introducing a bill making it a crime to be poor. His office wall holds a framed jockstrap embroidered, ''I am a Burton supporter.'' Old Capitol hands greeted word of his elevation with roughly the wonder that would attend the appointment of Hunter S. Thompson as dean of the Columbia journalism school.</p>
        <p>''Given the political genealogy involved in Burton's remarkable and surprising ascent, this is beyond politics,'' wrote John Jacobs, political editor of the McClatchy Newspapers in Sacramento and author of a biography of Philip Burton. ''This is opera.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burton is more modest.</p>
        <p>''They have an impression of the Senate as being stodgy,'' he said, before editing himself in midsentence, as he often does, to add: ''Not stodgy,  but -- whatever. And I'm not a stodgy guy.''</p>
        <p>The reality is that Mr. Burton is  one of the oldest hands in town and that he has always been a far more serious legislative player than his wild-eyed reputation would have it.</p>
        <p>He was first elected to the Assembly with Mr. Brown in 1964 and later became chairman of its powerful Rules Committee, where he led the only successful override of a veto by Gov. Ronald Reagan, on a bill that kept state mental hospitals open.</p>
        <p>With his brother, he formed what came to be known as the ''Burton machine,'' a powerful San Francisco Democratic organization. He was elected to Congress in 1974 but generally remained in the overpowering shadow of his older brother, a master of legislative redistricting who once  supervised the creation of a district for John that was so contorted that critics joked it was contiguous only at low tide.</p>
        <p>Then, after four terms in Washington, his marriage over, addicted to cocaine, John Burton came home to California a wreck, and his onetime district aide Barbara Boxer (now a United States Senator) took his seat.</p>
        <p>Philip Burton died the following year, 1983, and John retired from electoral politics. But in 1988, by then drug-free, he ran for his old Assembly seat and won. He became chairman of the Rules Committee once again, and a confidant of Speaker Brown. Because of the term limits law, Mr. Brown left to become Mayor of San Francisco, and Mr. Burton last year moved up to the Senate.</p>
        <p>Although the law permits him to remain in the Senate through 2004,  Mr. Burton calls term limits ''the dumbest thing that ever happened.'' One reason, he says, is that the turnover does not allow most legislators time to grow out of their youthful arrogance and zeal. He saw that growth in a Republican colleague, Assemblyman Curt Pringle, who, now that he has achieved it, is being  forced out of office by term limits at the end of this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pringle, one of three Republicans who briefly held the Speakership in the chaos that followed Mr. Brown's departure, said that as the ranking Democrat on the Rules Committee, Mr. Burton ''came into my office basically every day and said, 'What's going on, and where are we?' and he would tell me what he thought might work and what might not, and how he would retaliate and so on.''</p>
        <p>''We all know he's one of the most liberal members in the Legislature,'' Mr. Pringle added. ''We all know he has a passion for his beliefs. But we also know that he's an honest person with integrity and understanding of the system around here.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, amid the cheery clutter in Mr. Burton's office, an autographed picture of the singer Keely Smith shares wall space with a framed epigram from John Quincy Adams:  ''Always vote for a principle, though you vote alone, and you may cherish the sweet reflection that your vote is never lost.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Burton is no stranger to fights on principle, but he said: ''Why get into a fight over something you don't want to fight about? If you're sitting in a committee and it's 4 to 3 or 3 to 4 and there's no doubt, what are you going to talk about?''</p>
        <p>Senate Democrats chose him for his new post because he is an expert fund-raiser and campaigner who will bend every effort to help the party hold on to control of the Legislature.  Still, the Senator, who often refers to Mr. Wilson as ''the little marine,'' knows he will have to tone down some of his hotter oratory now that as Democratic leader, he will be called on to do face-to-face business with the Republican Governor.</p>
        <p>''I mean, Pete, you know, I mean, that was then and this is now,'' a smiling Mr. Burton said in the stop-and-start semaphoric syntax he favors. ''And if you're on the outside doing whatever, you do stuff.''</p>
        <p>But now, Mr. Burton said with satisfaction, ''he doesn't have to take shots at me, and I don't have to take shots at him, because we'll be in a room taking shots at each other.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
