<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Skater Soaks in Every Moment</title>
    <meta content="06TARA$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="993375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="OLYMPICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1998)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nagano (Japan)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Tara Lipinski</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipinski, Tara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Akebono (Sumo Wrestler)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Nagano</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CEED8123DF935A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Skater Soaks in Every Moment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>NAGANO, Japan, Feb. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tara Lipinski, at 82 pounds the smallest US Olympian, and Akebono, 516-pound sumo wrestler, pose for picture together at Nagano; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tara Lipinski and Akebono showed up at figure-skating practice today, but only one of them ventured onto the ice. At 6 feet 8 inches, 516 pounds, the grand champion sumo wrestler has not yet perfected his triple axel. ''I never skated,'' said Akebono, a native of Hawaii whose given name is Chad Rowan. ''Too dangerous.''</p>
        <p>Trailing a CBS camera crew, the sumo champion took in some of the Winter Olympic sites before he is scheduled to perform a purification ritual at Saturday's opening ceremony. Sitting in his robe and sandals at the White Ring arena, he posed for pictures and laughed with reporters, even if he wasn't quite sure who Lipinski was.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tara Lipinski and Akebono showed up at figure-skating practice today, but only one of them ventured onto the ice. At 6 feet 8 inches, 516 pounds, the grand champion sumo wrestler has not yet perfected his triple axel. ''I never skated,'' said Akebono, a native of Hawaii whose given name is Chad Rowan. ''Too dangerous.''</p>
        <p>Trailing a CBS camera crew, the sumo champion took in some of the Winter Olympic sites before he is scheduled to perform a purification ritual at Saturday's opening ceremony. Sitting in his robe and sandals at the White Ring arena, he posed for pictures and laughed with reporters, even if he wasn't quite sure who Lipinski was.</p>
        <p>''The world champion?'' he said. ''That's what they told me.'' Being from Hawaii, he said, he wasn't on a first-name basis with winter sports. Still, he clapped when Lipinski began to skate and again when she finished.</p>
        <p>Later, the skater and the sumo wrestler met to have a picture taken. At 4-10, 82 pounds, Lipinski is the smallest member of the United States Olympic team. When told her weight, Akebono said, ''That's the size of my left calf.'' Asked to pose with a man six times her size, she said, ''Oh, no,'' but gamely played along. Long gone was the devastated skater who sobbed after falling and finishing fourth in the short program a month ago at the national championships.</p>
        <p>''He's big,'' she said, cringing slightly as if she feared she might be bench-pressed.</p>
        <p>Unlike her Olympic teammates, Michelle Kwan and Nicole Bobek, who have remained home until next week to train, the 15-year-old Lipinski wants to experience as much of the Olympics as possible.</p>
        <p>She has been anticipating this moment since she stood on a Tupperware container as a 2-year-old, pretending she was a gold medalist as the national anthem played on television during the 1984 Summer Olympics in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has their own schedules,'' Lipinski said. ''The opening ceremonies are what I wanted to do.''</p>
        <p>Her parents and publicists have kept her under wraps for most of the last month, apparently not realizing that she is her own best ambassador. Today, she appeared relaxed and exhilarated, a kid having the time of her life. Not only that, but Lipinski stepped off a plane from Osaka, Japan, and rehearsed an impressive long program, landing a cleaner triple loop-triple loop combination than she had done at the national championships.</p>
        <p>''It's so great,'' Lipinski said. ''I've been dreaming of it for so long. It's once in a lifetime. I'm pumped to be here.''</p>
        <p>She appears to be buoyed by the fact that she skated a redemptive long program at nationals, pulling herself up from fourth place to second over all and earning a spot on the Olympic team instead of having to be given one by the United States Figure Skating Association.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to be one of those athletes who can't pull together after a mistake,'' Lipinski said. ''I gained a lot of confidence at nationals, being so low and having a great long program. I still have confidence.''</p>
        <p>After that devastating short program in Philadelphia, said Lipinski's coach, Richard Callaghan, ''she was very down and very annoyed with herself.''</p>
        <p>''In her mind she was going to nationals thinking it was a 1-2 situation with Michelle,'' Callaghan said. ''Then all of a sudden she ends up fourth and her whole mind-set went to making the team. Her thoughts went to something she wasn't prepared for. But she handled it well.''</p>
        <p>Three seasons ago, Lipinski finished second at the junior national championships. Two years ago, few would have given her any chance of making the 1998 Olympic team. In fact, Callaghan has said publicly that Lipinski was aiming for the 2002 Winter Games in Salt Lake City.</p>
        <p>That schedule accelerated greatly last season, when Lipinski defeated Kwan to win the national and world championships. In the disappointment of Philadelphia, it was hard for her to appreciate how much she had accomplished in such a short time. How she still has a chance to become the youngest women's Olympic figure-skating champion. ''It's hard for someone to understand how impressive it is,'' Callaghan said.</p>
        <p>The Olympic women's short program will not be skated until Feb. 18, with the free program scheduled for Feb. 20. Each Winter Games stirs a debate about whether skaters should arrive early or late. There is always a chance of arriving too early and peaking too soon, as happened to Midori Ito of Japan at the 1992 Winter Olympics in Albertville, France. She fell in the short program and knocked herself out of competition for the gold medal that went to Kristi Yamaguchi.</p>
        <p>''You can rationalize either way,'' said Todd Eldredge, the 1996 world champion who is a training partner of Lipinski's in Bloomfield Hills, Mich. ''You can say it's great she's here to experience everything. And you can say she's here too early.''</p>
        <p>Callaghan said there was never any discussion about arrival plans. Lipinski wanted to come to the opening ceremony and that was that. He said he agreed with her decision. ''I think she ought to have fun and take in the experience,'' Callaghan said. ''She's here to enjoy opening ceremonies. She's got time to get back to normal and train.''</p>
        <p>What about the possible noise and distractions in the Olympic Village? ''Let's hope it's not her being too noisy or distracting,'' he laughed.</p>
        <p>OLYMPICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
