<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Special Kind of Officemate</title>
    <meta content="14WCOL$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Workplace" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Job Market" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/14/business/14WCOL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1270645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="LIFE'S WORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Friendship</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belkin, Lisa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Friendship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DD1F31F937A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Special Kind of Officemate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LISA BELKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belkin, Lisa</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lisa Belkin column on friendships that form among co-workers and the effort needed to preserve them under strains of workplace and after career paths diverge; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY husband is about to lose his best buddy at work. Bob is leaving, off to great new adventures, and when he leaves, an important beat in the rhythm of Bruce's day will leave, too. Workplace friendships are a crossbreed of the species, sturdy yet fragile at the same time. They start out as lunch and evolve into loyalty. As Laura Senturia, an account executive with Schwartz Communications in Waltham, Mass., says about her colleague, Marybeth McLean Roberts: ''Somewhere along the way, 'Marybeth from work' became simply 'Marybeth.' ''</p>
        <p>It is a transition that comes with a lot of warning labels. There are small land mines to worry about, such as what to do when your best friend gets your promotion, and the more prosaic risk that you become one of those people who talk about nothing but shop over what is supposed to be a social dinner. ''It's like an office romance without the romance,'' jokes Karen Wright, who works in fund-raising and communications at Minnesota State University in Mankato with her close friend, Ann Rosenquist Fee. The two women sing together in a folk band after hours. On top of that, Ms. Fee's husband and Ms. Wright's significant other are professors at the same university (which is how Ms. Wright began dating him in the first place).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY husband is about to lose his best buddy at work. Bob is leaving, off to great new adventures, and when he leaves, an important beat in the rhythm of Bruce's day will leave, too. Workplace friendships are a crossbreed of the species, sturdy yet fragile at the same time. They start out as lunch and evolve into loyalty. As Laura Senturia, an account executive with Schwartz Communications in Waltham, Mass., says about her colleague, Marybeth McLean Roberts: ''Somewhere along the way, 'Marybeth from work' became simply 'Marybeth.' ''</p>
        <p>It is a transition that comes with a lot of warning labels. There are small land mines to worry about, such as what to do when your best friend gets your promotion, and the more prosaic risk that you become one of those people who talk about nothing but shop over what is supposed to be a social dinner. ''It's like an office romance without the romance,'' jokes Karen Wright, who works in fund-raising and communications at Minnesota State University in Mankato with her close friend, Ann Rosenquist Fee. The two women sing together in a folk band after hours. On top of that, Ms. Fee's husband and Ms. Wright's significant other are professors at the same university (which is how Ms. Wright began dating him in the first place).</p>
        <p>These multiple ties were tested last fall when Ms. Wright was appointed chairwoman of a search committee and Ms. Fee applied for the job. The two women dealt with the potential strain on their friendship ''by just not talking about it,'' Ms. Fee says, even though she was itching to know who else was being considered for the position and what her chances were. Ms. Wright, for her part, tried hard to prove her impartiality, even though ''I thought Ann was qualified in every way.'' Ms. Fee won the job, and now Ms. Wright is her boss.</p>
        <p>The daily stresses of an office can strain a friendship, but I think the truest test is when you take the office away. What happens, in other words, when ''Marybeth is no longer at work?'' Ms. Senturia and Ms. Roberts found out last September, when Ms. Roberts married and moved to Chicago, where she is a senior account executive with the Porter Novelli Convergence Group. She and Ms. Senturia, who used to spend 12 hours a day together, now exchange e-mail messages every morning and ''we're lucky if we talk once a week,'' Ms. Senturia says.</p>
        <p>It has been six years since I stopped my daily commute to the newsroom, and one of the most jarring changes has been the loss of bump-into-each-other-in-the-elevator contact with friends. Friendships are really life's best souvenirs; you keep a few from high school, a few from college, a handful from summer camp. My own core group of friends, the ones who shaped my sense of self and then staked a lifelong claim on it, were gathered during my first few years of work.</p>
        <p>We were all clerks at The New York Times back then, answering reporters' phones and dreaming of the day when someone else would answer ours. We spent most of our nights and weekends at the office, but during our free time we would gather in one of our tiny apartments where we'd order takeout and trade gossip over who would probably be promoted to reporter first. If we became as successful as we hoped, we knew, we wouldn't all be working in the same city again for a very long time.</p>
        <p>As we had predicted, the work that brought us together began to tease us apart. Moscow, Beijing, Tokyo, even Houston and Seattle, are very far away, and while the bonds don't break, they change with distance and with time. When I worked in the newsroom, one of the closest friends I am ever likely to have asked me to guard the door while she ducked into the office bathroom and took a pregnancy test. Fast forward a few years, when work took us to separate places, and she became pregnant again. I learned about that baby through the grapevine.</p>
        <p>The trick, then, is keeping ''simply Marybeth'' from becoming ''Marybeth who was once my friend.'' Ms. Senturia and Ms. Roberts vow to do just that, and they plan a girls' night out in Chicago, during the opening weekend of ''Bridget Jones's Diary,'' the movie version of one of their favorite books.  Bruce and Bob, in turn, will see each other often because his wife and I (who have become a whole separate category of friends) will see to it that they do. And me, I think it's time I call my own ''Marybeth'' and meet her (and her little girl) for lunch.</p>
        <p>LIFE'S WORK This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. E-mail: Belkin@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">This column about the intersection of jobs and personal lives appears every other week. E-mail: Belkin@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
