<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inquiry On A.T.M. Networks</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940305T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="670123"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTITRUST ACTIONS AND LAWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMATIC TELLER MACHINES (ATM)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">INDEPENDENT BANKERS ASSN OF AMERICA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLS, JOSHUA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RENO, JANET (ATTY GEN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED6123BF932A15751C0A962958260" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inquiry On A.T.M. Networks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSHUA MILLS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MILLS, JOSHUA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Justice Department is investigating whether any of the networks that link automated teller machines have been putting pressure on banks to buy other services from them as a condition of participating in the network.</p>
        <p>Justice Department spokesmen in Washington confirmed yesterday that an antitrust investigation was under way and said that some action would be announced soon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Justice Department is investigating whether any of the networks that link automated teller machines have been putting pressure on banks to buy other services from them as a condition of participating in the network.</p>
        <p>Justice Department spokesmen in Washington confirmed yesterday that an antitrust investigation was under way and said that some action would be announced soon.</p>
        <p>In a speech to the Independent Bankers Association of America on Saturday, Attorney General Janet Reno invited bankers to provide the Justice Department with any information they might have about the practice.</p>
        <p>"Where the evidence is clear, we will not hesitate to challenge such activity in court," Ms. Reno said to the group, which represents 6,000 community banks, precisely the types of smaller banks that would be more vulnerable to pressure from networks. The bankers were holding their annual meeting in Orlando, Fla. Access Called Essential</p>
        <p>The Attorney General noted that access to an automated network, especially for smaller banks, "has become almost as important for a bank as access to telephone or utility services." By denying access to its network, the network company would be placing the bank at a competitive disadvantage.</p>
        <p>Carl Stern, the Justice Department's chief spokesman, said yesterday that Ms. Reno had chosen the setting to disclose the investigation because "this seemed to be an opportunity to bring to their attention our concern and see if they had any matters they wanted us to know about."</p>
        <p>Mr. Stern said the antitrust investigation had been opened after the department received complaints from bankers from one region of the country. He declined to identify the region or say when the inquiry began. He said he expected the inquiry to produce "at least one significant action" soon, though not this month.</p>
        <p>When the networks were first organized a decade ago, they were simply associations of banks that agreed to share their A.T.M.'s with each other, enabling a customer with a card from one member bank to use any machine on the network. Now, most networks also market services like allowing bank customers to pay bills by telephone or from their personal computers.</p>
        <p>In the competition to sell additional services, the network industry has been undergoing consolidation. In September, for example, the Yankee 24 Network and the New York Switch Corporation, which is owned by seven banks and runs the NYCE network, agreed to combine.</p>
        <p>The result was a network of 13,000 automated teller machines from New York and New Jersey to Maine, making NYCE the second-largest network after the Star System in California. Comment From Chase</p>
        <p>Ken Mills, a spokesman for the Chase Manhattan Bank, which participates in the NYCE and Plus networks, said bank executives who dealt with automated teller operations were not aware of a Justice Department investigation. That makes it unlikely that those two networks were involved.</p>
        <p>Other banking executives could not be reached yesterday.</p>
        <p>Some other large networks include Honor, MOST and NYCE's principal competition in the East, the MAC network, owned by the Electronic Payments Corporation, which in turn is owned by four large banks: Corestates Financial of Philadelphia; Banc One of Columbus, Ohio; PNC Financial of Pittsburgh, and the Society Corporation of Cleveland.</p>
        <p>The bankers' meeting in Orlando ended yesterday, and many members left the Walt Disney World hotel where they had met.</p>
        <p>Telephone calls to association officials were not answered.</p>
        <p>The article also misidentified one of the four owners of Electronic Payment. It is the PNC Bank Corporation, not the PNC Financial Corporation.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 5, 1994, Saturday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day on Feb. 21 about a Justice Department investigation into automated teller networks misidentified the owner of the MAC network. It is Electronic Payment Services Inc., not the Electronic Payments Corporation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 5, 1994, Saturday</p>
        <p>Because of an editing error, an article in Business Day on Feb. 21 about a Justice Department investigation into automated teller networks misidentified the owner of the MAC network. It is Electronic Payment Services Inc., not the Electronic Payments Corporation.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
