<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How a Revolution Survived: A Mexican Chronicle</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="670138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIANS, AMERICAN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHIAPAS (MEX)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ZAPATISTA NATIONAL LIBERATION ARMY (MEXICO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDEN, TIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E3DF133BF932A15751C0A962958260" item-length="977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How a Revolution Survived: A Mexican Chronicle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM GOLDEN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDEN, TIM</byline>
      <dateline>SAN CRISTOBAL DE LAS CASAS, Mexico, Feb. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Soviet bloc crumbled, the Sandinista Government fell from power in Nicaragua and Marxist rebels made peace in El Salvador, the tiny guerrilla movement that would one day convulse Mexico as the Zapatista National Liberation Army braced for its own collapse.</p>
        <p>"Everything we had prepared came crashing down," recalled the military commander of the army, who calls himself Subcommander Marcos. "When we heard that all of this was happening, we said to ourselves: 'We are going to lose people. They are going to start to leave.' "</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Soviet bloc crumbled, the Sandinista Government fell from power in Nicaragua and Marxist rebels made peace in El Salvador, the tiny guerrilla movement that would one day convulse Mexico as the Zapatista National Liberation Army braced for its own collapse.</p>
        <p>"Everything we had prepared came crashing down," recalled the military commander of the army, who calls himself Subcommander Marcos. "When we heard that all of this was happening, we said to ourselves: 'We are going to lose people. They are going to start to leave.' "</p>
        <p>Instead, Marcos said, the rebels began to grow, nourished by the hard times of peasant farmers in the southern state of Chiapas and their discontent with the deep economic changes wrought by President Carlos Salinas de Gortari. And from what seems to have begun as a relatively typical movement for socialist revolution, the Zapatistas began adapting themselves to the post-cold-war world. Peace Talks Starting</p>
        <p>This account of the movement's history, detailed for the first time in an interview on Thursday at a mountain safe house, points to the complexity of the force that Government negotiators will face when they begin peace talks with the rebels here on Monday.</p>
        <p>At its roots, the insurgency appears to draw on the radicalism of both a small core of urban-born leftists who came to Chiapas to foment a revolution and the Mayan Indian peasants whom they recruited and trained in what they say was a 10-year effort.</p>
        <p>But since starting their war against the state on Jan. 1, the Zapatistas have also shown surprising political moderation for a guerrilla army, a disdain for dogma and an ability to adapt to changing political circumstances.</p>
        <p>"The difficulty," a Government official said, "is that we do not know who is really in control within the movement, what their fundamental objective is or which of the tendencies will prevail." A Show of Realism</p>
        <p>Officials including Mr. Salinas have described a hierarchy in which a handful of non-Indian, ideologically driven "professionals of violence" supposedly lead a force of impoverished, even naive peasants.</p>
        <p>In the interview, however, Marcos suggested another dichotomy that has been implicit in the rebels' statements.</p>
        <p>By turns, the rebel leader seemed to measure the military and political strength of the Zapatistas with considerable realism, and to limit the scope of their demands accordingly. But referring again and again to "the comrades" -- the Indian peasants who at least formally constitute the Zapatistas' political leadership -- he also laid out positions that were more absolutist.</p>
        <p>"Our aim is not just to make the federal Government say it is going to respect the elections," Marcos said at one point. "No, it has said that before."</p>
        <p>So will the rebels refuse to disarm before the presidential elections scheduled for Aug. 21?</p>
        <p>"We will not disarm until we have gotten housing, land, food, health care and education," he said, ticking off basic points of the Zapatista program. 'At This for 500 Years'</p>
        <p>Is that not a rather long-term plan, a reporter wondered.</p>
        <p>"The comrades say we have been at this for 500 years," he said, referring to the struggles of Mexican Indians since the Spanish conquest. "We can wait another 500."</p>
        <p>Government officials generally dismiss this notion of a radical, collective Indian leadership as merely a strategy to legitimize the Zapatistas as an indigenous force or to increase their leverage in negotiations. And though Marcos had said in the interview that the army's Central Committee might not send him to the negotiations, he arrived here today among the 19 rebel delegates escorted by officials of the Roman Catholic Church and the International Red Cross.</p>
        <p>Anthropologists who have studied the democratic traditions of Indian and peasant organizations in Chiapas lend credence to Marcos's account of a process in which as the rebel force grew he and other non-Indian leaders were forced to cede control over fundamental decisions to representatives of the communities from which the insurgency drew its support.</p>
        <p>"If we had continued with that form of organization we would still be deep in the rain forest with 15 or 20 guerrillas," Marcos said of the Zapatistas' early incarnation as a traditional guerrilla group run by a small cadre of unchallenged leaders. A Writer of Poetry</p>
        <p>In the interview, Marcos did not sound like a man who says he has spent the last decade of his life fomenting peasant rebellion. He said he occasionally wrote poems, and grew animated when asked about his tastes in literature (among many others, the poetry of the Chilean Pablo Neruda, the novels of the Mexican Carlos Fuentes, the Colombian Gabriel Garcia Marquez and the politically conservative Peruvian Mario Vargas Llosa "when you could still take him").</p>
        <p>When asked about human rights abuses by Government troops, he was quick to say that many of them "fought with honor." And had the army tried, he added, it might have destroyed the Zapatistas months before they seized San Cristobal and several other big Chiapas towns on Jan. 1.</p>
        <p>When the military reported the discovery of a small military training site in Chiapas last May, he said, what it had in fact found was a full-scale model of the center of the town of Ocosingo, built so the insurgents could practice their assault. But after a brief move against the rebels, Marcos said the army abruptly left the area.</p>
        <p>Still, the question of how far the rebels will press their advantage to try to win broad political and economic changes swirls around Marcos himself.</p>
        <p>While insisting that the rebels would not sign any peace accord that did not lead to national democratic reforms, Marcos also said that if a nonviolent political movement coalesced around the Zapatistas' political demands, that would be far preferable to more war.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
