<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yanks Clinch Tie For Division Title</title>
    <meta content="21YANK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/21/sports/baseball/21YANK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1425428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Bernie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EFD61F30F932A1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yanks Clinch Tie For Division Title</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Yanks Clinch Tie For Division Title</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Sept. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Detroit Tigers, 5-1, and clinch tie for American League East division title (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The gimpy Yankees are limping to their fifth consecutive title in the American League East. They clinched at least a tie tonight when they beat the bumbling Detroit Tigers, 5-1, on the damp lawn of Comerica Park.</p>
        <p>They won with the sore-kneed Bernie Williams back in the lineup, but only as the designated hitter; with pitcher Roger Clemens (13-6) taking a hard one-hopper off his left shin; with the slugger Jason Giambi sidelined with a sore back; and with reliever Mariano Rivera hoping to return on Saturday for the first time since a sore right shoulder idled him on August 15.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Yankees are limping to their fifth consecutive title in the A.L. East, clinching at least a tie on Friday by beating Detroit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The gimpy Yankees are limping to their fifth consecutive title in the American League East. They clinched at least a tie tonight when they beat the bumbling Detroit Tigers, 5-1, on the damp lawn of Comerica Park.</p>
        <p>They won with the sore-kneed Bernie Williams back in the lineup, but only as the designated hitter; with pitcher Roger Clemens (13-6) taking a hard one-hopper off his left shin; with the slugger Jason Giambi sidelined with a sore back; and with reliever Mariano Rivera hoping to return on Saturday for the first time since a sore right shoulder idled him on August 15.</p>
        <p>''It's all right, I got a wrap on,'' Clemens said of his injured left shin. ''There will probably be a little swelling tomorrow.''</p>
        <p>The injury occurred in the sixth inning when Clemens gave up a home run and then loaded the bases with nobody out before retiring the side with no further scoring. ''If anything, maybe that got my attention,'' Clemens said of the hard-hit ball off his body.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre came out twice to ask him if he was injured and needed to leave the game. Clemens talked Torre out of it. ''They've got to chop me down like a big tree,'' Clemens said. ''I said, 'I'm fine. I'm not favoring it.' ''</p>
        <p>The Yankees cannot clinch the division outright until at least after Saturday afternoon's game because Boston defeated Baltimore, 4-2, tonight.</p>
        <p>Derek Jeter, slumping lately, had two hits and drove in two runs for the Yankees, who took control of a close game in the seventh inning when the Tigers allowed two runs with a two-out error.</p>
        <p>Tonight's game was delayed 1 hour 57 minutes because of rain. The Yankees took a 2-0 lead on a fourth-inning single by Jeter and a fifth-inning sacrifice fly by Alfonso Soriano. It was Soriano's 100th R.B.I. of the season.</p>
        <p>The Yankees made it 4-1 with two outs in the seventh when two runs scored after left fielder Craig Monroe dropped a two-out fly ball by Juan Rivera. Jeter made the score 5-1 with a double to right, scoring Rivera. When the Tigers came to bat in the seventh, Ramiro Mendoza was pitching in place of Clemens.</p>
        <p>Clemens's leg was not the only leg that concerned the Yankees. Before the game, a big bandage held ice around the left knee of Bernie Williams to counter the effects of the inflammation that kept him from the starting lineup in the previous two games. When he took it off, Williams wore a much smaller and tighter blue wrap around the knee as he jogged gingerly down a corridor.</p>
        <p>Williams, still contending for the league batting title, entered the day in third place, his .337 batting average just six points behind Boston's Manny Ramirez and five points behind Kansas City's Mike Sweeney. Batting as a designated hitter for only the fifth time this season, Williams doubled in his second at-bat tonight.</p>
        <p>Torre had decided not to use his regular center fielder on the vast, slippery surface of one of baseball's biggest outfields. With 10 games remaining in the season before tonight, did Williams's chance for a batting title figure into Torre's decision-making?</p>
        <p>''No,'' Torre said, but he added quickly ''You want to give him an opportunity to do that, but not to the point of maybe overtaxing him for what's more important and that's what we can do as a team. And he feels that way.'' The more important agenda, of course, is the team's quest for its fifth World Series championship in the last seven seasons.</p>
        <p>The knee has bothered him for a while and it hurts more when he plays on artificial turf, as the Yankees did in Tampa earlier this week. When asked what, specifically, is wrong, Williams replied: ''It's a cyst on the back of the knee that's getting fluid and it's aggravated by playing on artificial turf and the pounding.''</p>
        <p>Williams said that during the off-season, the knee problem ''will be one of those focal points to try to get fixed.'' He also said ''The knee is obviously a concern. It's not up to the point where it's a concern to lose playing time over it'' -- at least not in important, post-season games, he added.</p>
        <p>Might Williams need surgery on the knee in the off-season? ''I don't know,'' Williams said. ''I can't really make that determination. Hopefully, it will get better and I won't have to do it. We'll see in the off-season.''</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Closer MARIANO RIVERA has not pitched since Aug. 15. JOE TORRE said again today he planned to use Rivera in Saturday's game, but his voice did not have unbridled optimism. ''He's a little tired today,'' Torre said of Rivera. ''Nothing hurt. He's been put through a pretty good range of workouts for the last week. I suspect he'll pitch tomorrow.'' RON COOMER started at first base in place of JASON GIAMBI.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
