<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Welfare Workers Rate High In Job Retention at Companies</title>
    <meta content="Y27WEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1020094"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Workfare and Employment of Welfare Recipients</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Giant Food Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Marriott Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Salomon Smith Barney</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Edelman, Peter B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pear, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEEDC1538F934A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="994" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Welfare Workers Rate High In Job Retention at Companies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pear, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Several major companies that have hired welfare recipients report these workers remain on job longer than other employees, contrary to some expectations; Giant Food reports 79 percent retention after 90 days; Marriott reports similar rate; credits training and personal counseling; Salomon Smith Barney says 92 percent of welfare recipients hired in last year are still there, in higher-paying jobs; other companies respond similarly; Peter B Edelman, who resigned from Government last year to protest welfare reform, admits more people are getting jobs than he expected (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some companies hiring welfare recipients say they have found, to their surprise, that such workers stay on the job longer, with less turnover, than other employees.</p>
        <p>The findings run counter to the expectations of many skeptics, who said that welfare recipients lacked the skills and the motivation needed to hold jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some companies hiring welfare recipients say they have found, to their surprise, that such workers stay on the job longer, with less turnover, than other employees.</p>
        <p>The findings run counter to the expectations of many skeptics, who said that welfare recipients lacked the skills and the motivation needed to hold jobs.</p>
        <p>The companies, Borg-Warner, Giant Food, Marriott International, Salomon Smith Barney, Sprint, United Airlines, owned by UAL, United Parcel Service and Xerox, said they had made systematic efforts to hire welfare recipients in the last year. And in separate interviews, executives at those companies said that they had retained a larger proportion of former welfare recipients than other entry-level employees.</p>
        <p>''It's been a real pleasant surprise for us,'' said Ricki C. Crescenzi, manager of employment at Giant Food, a regional supermarket chain based in Landover, Md.</p>
        <p>She said the company had hired more than 100 welfare recipients as cashiers, pharmacy clerks, baker's assistants and apprentice meat-cutters. After 90 days, she said, 79 percent of welfare recipients were still on the job, while the retention rate for other Giant employees in similar jobs was 50 percent.</p>
        <p>Janet M. Tully, director of community employment and training at Marriott International, said her company hired 360 welfare recipients last year and 100 so far this year, with retention rates very similar to those reported by Giant.</p>
        <p>The efforts to hire welfare recipients, to be recognized at the White House on Wednesday, come at a time of low unemployment, and those efforts have several features in common. Most of the companies work with local government agencies or nonprofit community organizations that recruit and train welfare recipients for particular jobs.</p>
        <p>Also, many of the employers use mentors, job coaches or some type of ''buddy'' system to help welfare recipients learn skills needed for their jobs and many offer welfare recipients extra help with child care and transportation to and from work.</p>
        <p>Welfare experts sounded a note of caution, saying that some of the people still on welfare might have more difficulty getting and holding jobs. They include homeless people, drug addicts, people with serious mental disorders, convicted felons, battered women and people with a limited ability to read or speak English.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tully attributed the high retention rates at Marriott to the ''training, personal attention, coaching and counseling'' given to welfare recipients.</p>
        <p>''That's a luxury that a lot of other employees don't have,'' Ms. Tully said.</p>
        <p>LaDonna A. Pavetti, a welfare expert at Mathematica Policy Research, said that welfare recipients were given access to job training, child care and transportation services that was unavailable to people ''hired off the street.''</p>
        <p>''In Massachusetts,'' Ms. Pavetti said, ''if you find a job while you're on welfare, you are guaranteed child care.''</p>
        <p>The work requirements of the 1996 welfare law may also be a factor. ''Welfare recipients have a mandate to work,'' Ms. Pavetti said. ''If they lose this job, they'll have to get another one.''</p>
        <p>Barbara A. Silvan, senior vice president of Salomon Smith Barney, said her company had retained 92 percent of the 53 welfare recipients hired in the last year. Some of the new employees took jobs paying more than $24,000 a year, and in the last few weeks, she said, ''we hired someone off welfare at $30,000.''</p>
        <p>Company executives said their main reason for hiring welfare recipients was to create a more stable work force and to improve the bottom line. Such hiring is essential to the success of the welfare bill that President Clinton signed in August 1996. But the executives said they were not hiring welfare recipients as a favor to Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Eli J. Segal, president of the Welfare to Work Partnership, said 5,000 companies had made commitments to hire and retain welfare recipients.</p>
        <p>The Welfare to Work Partnership, a nonprofit corporation formed to promote the hiring of welfare recipients, has been praised by Mr. Clinton, Speaker Newt Gingrich and Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin, a Republican.</p>
        <p>Michael E. Schlein, director of corporate development at Salomon Smith Barney, said, ''The transition from years of welfare to corporate life can be rough.'' Before being hired for full-time jobs, he said, welfare recipients must complete 16 weeks of preparation at the Wildcat Service Corporation, a job training and employment agency, and they go through a 16-week internship at Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Jablow, senior vice president of Wildcat, said his company trained 1,500 welfare recipients a year, teaching them work habits, clerical skills, computer skills and the language skills and mathematics needed for their jobs.</p>
        <p>Tony Molinaro, a spokesman for United Airlines, said the company had retained 70 percent of the 760 welfare recipients it had hired in the last year. Among other people hired for similar jobs, he said, the retention rate was 40 percent.</p>
        <p>Paula Fulford, a spokeswoman for United Parcel Service, said: ''Since January 1997, we have hired more than 10,400 welfare recipients as part-time package sorters, at an average wage of $8.50 an hour. We make no distinction between a former welfare recipient and anyone else hired for an entry-level job in terms of salary, benefits and hours.''</p>
        <p>But, she said, many of the welfare recipients receive extra ''supportive services'' from U.P.S. and community organizations.</p>
        <p>Peter B. Edelman, an Assistant Secretary of Health and Human Services, resigned in protest over the new welfare law in September 1996. In March 1997, he said that the law's work requirements were unrealistic because many welfare recipients lacked basic skills.</p>
        <p>But in an interview today, Mr. Edelman said, ''In the short run, more people are getting jobs than I would have thought.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
