<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newark Is Pushed to Build More Public Housing Units</title>
    <meta content="27NEWA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1020160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smothers, Ronald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Debevoise, Dickinson R (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E4D71538F934A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newark Is Pushed to Build More Public Housing Units</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SMOTHERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smothers, Ronald</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, May 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal District Court Judge Dickinson R Debevoise, noting that nine years ago when Newark, NJ, was beginning to demolish its high-rise public housing complexes in favor of low-rise housing a Federal court agreement directed city to make sure it quickly replaced 1,777 lost units and just as quickly renovated others, rules that Newark Housing Authority had failed to meet those goals; orders authorityto come up with revised schedule for building replacement housing; also ordersagency to hire construction expert to make sure existing units are quickly repaired so they could be rented again; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nine years ago, when Newark was beginning to demolish its high-rise public housing complexes in favor of low-rise housing, a Federal court agreement directed the city to make sure it quickly replaced 1,777 lost units and just as quickly renovated others.</p>
        <p>Late last week, a Federal judge ruled that the Newark Housing Authority had failed to meet those goals. But the judge stopped short of finding the housing agency in contempt of court as tenant advocates had asked. Instead, Judge Dickinson R. Debevoise of Federal District Court in Newark ordered the agency to come up with a revised schedule for building replacement housing. He also ordered the agency to hire a construction expert to make sure existing units were quickly repaired so they could be rented again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nine years ago, when Newark was beginning to demolish its high-rise public housing complexes in favor of low-rise housing, a Federal court agreement directed the city to make sure it quickly replaced 1,777 lost units and just as quickly renovated others.</p>
        <p>Late last week, a Federal judge ruled that the Newark Housing Authority had failed to meet those goals. But the judge stopped short of finding the housing agency in contempt of court as tenant advocates had asked. Instead, Judge Dickinson R. Debevoise of Federal District Court in Newark ordered the agency to come up with a revised schedule for building replacement housing. He also ordered the agency to hire a construction expert to make sure existing units were quickly repaired so they could be rented again.</p>
        <p>The judge said he would defer any formal finding of contempt until the housing authority had a chance to put into motion the remedial measures he was requiring.</p>
        <p>Judge Debevoise said he had some sympathy for the problems the authority was facing and cited a host of human factors and ''circumstances beyond the control'' of housing authority officials that had frustrated efforts to reach the goals set in 1989. But he also noted that only 42 percent of the replacement units had been built and that renovations and re-rentals of some existing public housing units were taking as long as 18 months rather than the 60 days set by the court. Meanwhile, there are 4,000 families on the housing authority's waiting list.</p>
        <p>In his order on Friday, the judge also directed the authority to focus on the ''physical and social realities'' of the Stella Wright Homes, the seven red brick towers that are the sole remaining high-rise public housing complex in a city which was once honeycombed with them. The housing complex currently has 300 vacant units out of 1,200 and there have been problems in re-renting vacant apartments.</p>
        <p>The ruling allowed both sides, the advocates for public housing tenants who had sought the contempt citation and officials at the housing authority, to claim victory today.</p>
        <p>Harry Robinson, the interim director of the authority, praised the judge for ''understanding the common-sense factors.'' He said the ruling came at a time when the authority had shown tremendous improvement in the Department of Housing and Urban Development's standard assessments of the nation's 3,200 public housing authorities.</p>
        <p>Mr. Robinson said that in addition to the 753 new housing units completed, 196 others were under construction. The plans for the remaining 828 units required under the court order were in various stages of planning, he said, while another 700 new units that were not part of the court settlement were also under construction.</p>
        <p>The judge's ruling came in response to a motion filed by the Newark Coalition for Low Income Housing. Harris David, a lawyer with Legal Services of New Jersey, which represents the coalition, said that the ruling vindicated the group's frequent complaints over the last four years that the authority had been lagging in compliance with the order. He said that the appointment of a construction expert and the re-examination of conditions at the Wright Homes would go a long way toward opening up desperately needed affordable housing in Newark.</p>
        <p>David Weiner, an official of Local 1081 of the Communications Workers of America and secretary of the Newark Coalition for Low Income Housing, said that more public housing was needed in a time when welfare reform was driving people off the rolls and into low-paying jobs.</p>
        <p>Newark's original decision to tear down high-rise public housing came after the buildings were falling into disfavor among urban planners as ''vertical ghettoes'' that concentrated social problems.</p>
        <p>The judge's ruling, the latest of several over the years in the complicated and emotional case, tended to echo the findings of Gustav Heningburg, the special master named by the court to monitor the agreement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heningburg refused to discuss his work, but a copy of a letter he wrote to Judge Debevoise about the tenant advocates' complaints was obtained by The New York Times. In it, he said that the city had fallen short of its goals because of difficulty in wading through competing political interests in assembling the contiguous, city-owned parcels of land necessary for the more dispersed development of town houses.</p>
        <p>In his letter, Mr. Heningburg also cited delays in getting Federal construction approvals from HUD, unanticipated problems with contractors and a period when city personnel levels were insufficient.</p>
        <p>''I am not suggesting that N.H.A. has evolved into the nation's ultimate example of efficiency,'' he wrote, ''but it is worth noting that they are presently managing almost $100 million in new housing construction activity in Newark.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, HUD has found Newark's housing agency to be growing in efficiency. The city agency has moved from being one of the nation's most troubled in the 1980's to among the top performing authorities in the department's 1997 grading, said Stan Vosper, a spokesman for HUD.</p>
        <p>That capacity will be needed if Newark hopes to meet the housing needs of low-income residents as laid out in yet another HUD survey last month about housing shortages in the region. According to the Federal agency, 9,054 families in Newark alone were on lists waiting for various forms of agency assistance, from public housing to rent-subsidy programs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
