<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bringing Financial Respectability to a Drug Maker</title>
    <meta content="Y27PLAC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1020070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: MARKET PLACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Business and Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ribavirin (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Milan Panic</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Food and Drug Administration</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Icn Pharmaceuticals Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Panic, Milan</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980527T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3DE1538F934A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="1271" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bringing Financial Respectability to a Drug Maker</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Milan Panic, former Prime Minister of Yugoslavia who heads ICN Pharmaceuticals and is credited with bringing financial respectability to beleaguered and oft-maligned drug company; Panic is subject of Securities and Exchange Commission probe into his sale of ICN stock in 1994 before company announced that ICN drug ribavirin would be not be approved by Food and Drug Administration; staff of SEC has recommended to full commission that Panic be banned from being officer or director of any publicly traded company in US; graph; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Had he engineered the reunification of Yugoslavia, where he served as Prime Minister for six months in 1992 and 1993, Milan Panic would not have produced a bigger surprise.</p>
        <p>In the last year, Mr. Panic (pronounced PAHN-ich) has done what legions of Wall Street stock analysts, investment bankers and traders who bet on stock declines long thought impossible: He has brought respectability to ICN Pharmaceuticals, a beleaguered and oft-maligned drug company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Had he engineered the reunification of Yugoslavia, where he served as Prime Minister for six months in 1992 and 1993, Milan Panic would not have produced a bigger surprise.</p>
        <p>In the last year, Mr. Panic (pronounced PAHN-ich) has done what legions of Wall Street stock analysts, investment bankers and traders who bet on stock declines long thought impossible: He has brought respectability to ICN Pharmaceuticals, a beleaguered and oft-maligned drug company.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, ICN's shares were added to the recommended list of Goldman, Sachs &amp; Company, the blue-chip Wall Street firm. In March, they were added to Standard &amp; Poor's Midcap 400 index, a barometer of up-and-coming young companies. And, most important, one day later this year, the Food and Drug Administration is expected to approve an ICN drug, ribavirin, for use in combination with Intron A, manufactured by Schering-Plough, to treat relapsed hepatitis C patients.</p>
        <p>Perhaps it is appropriate then that ICN's annual meeting of shareholders, scheduled for today, will take place at Carnegie Hall in Manhattan, where the company's fans are expected to give Mr. Panic a rousing ovation.</p>
        <p>ICN's stock, which closed yesterday at $44.875, down 37.5 cents, has more than tripled the last 12 months. Taking into account options and convertible shares outstanding, ICN's market value now tops $3.4 billion.</p>
        <p>But as today's command performance commences, some sour notes might be heard offstage. According to the company's own filings with regulators, the staff of the Securities and Exchange Commission has recommended to the full commission that Mr. Panic be banned from being an officer or director of any publicly traded company in the United States. The recommendation is based on an investigation into Mr. Panic's sale of ICN stock in 1994 before the company announced that ribavirin would not be approved by the F.D.A. A forced departure of Mr. Panic, who has many personal contacts and much influence in Eastern Europe, could seriously undermine ICN's business in the region, which last year accounted for more than half of ICN's revenue.</p>
        <p>Particularly vulnerable could be the operations of ICN Yugoslavia, in which ICN has a 75 percent stake and which contributed nearly one-third of ICN's total revenues and operating profits last year. So strapped for cash is the Yugoslavian Government -- ICN's biggest, and practically only, customer in the truncated Yugoslav republic -- that ICN has recently begun accepting portions of the Government's drug business in exchange for the money it is owed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Panic was traveling much of the last week and was unavailable for comment, said a spokesman. Arnold I. Burns, a lawyer at the New York firm of Proskauer &amp; Rose, who serves as counsel to ICN, said that the S.E.C. cannot bar Mr. Panic from the business because he has violated no law. Speculation about the effect of such a ban is therefore moot, he said.</p>
        <p>ICN investors are boldly betting on the potential of ribavirin as a treatment for hepatitis C. After several false starts, the signs now appear promising. On May 4, an F.D.A. advisory committee unanimously recommended that the agency approve the drug for use in combination with Intron A in relapsed hepatitis C patients. Two weeks later, ICN reported that new test results showed that the combination of its drug with Schering-Plough's Intron showed improved results in hepatitis C patients who had received no previous treatment for the disease, a development that could further expand the market for ribavirin.</p>
        <p>Mr. Panic himself shows few signs of restraint in discussing the company's future. Last month, he boldly predicted that revenues would climb above $1 billion this year, a 33 percent increase over 1997 revenue of $752 million. And more recently, the Dow Jones News Service reported that he planned to make an acquisition of $1 billion to $2 billion in Western Europe or the United States in the next 12 to 18 months.</p>
        <p>''It's very urgent for us,'' Mr. Panic was quoted as saying. ''We need to be somewhere between $3 billion and $5 billion in sales.''</p>
        <p>ICN has already committed vast amounts of money to expand its businesses. In February, the company announced that it would invest $300 million in Russia over five years. It has also pledged to assist the Government of Romania with the privatization of its pharmaceuticals industry, and intends to buy a stake in a major Romanian pharmaceutical company, according to company filings with the S.E.C.</p>
        <p>Then there is the roughly $20 million allotted over two years to construct a drug plant in Poland, and $24 million in cash that ICN's China subsidiary has agreed to contribute over three years to a joint venture with a Chinese state-owned drug company.</p>
        <p>But as Yugoslavia demonstrates, business can be perilous in foreign countries where the concepts of capitalism still have a a shaky foothold. In April, Yugoslavia devalued it currency, the dinar, from 6 to the United States dollar, to 10.92 to the dollar. ICN expects to recognize a $15 million loss in the second quarter because of currency fluctuations, and ''the devaluation will have an impact on future sales and gross profit margins,'' ICN said in its first-quarter report.</p>
        <p>ICN also continues to trade its accounts receivable from the Yugoslav Government for other holdings. At the end of the first quarter, those receivables totaled $177 million, or one-fifth of the company's book value. In exchange for its receivables, ICN takes stakes in businesses there -- businesses whose future ICN presumably has less influence over than its own.</p>
        <p>Last year, it acquired 42 percent of its largest customer in Yugoslavia, the pharmaceutical distributor Velefarm, and so far in 1998, it has taken a 33 percent stake in the Dr. Sima Milosevic Institute, a health care center in Montenegro, and a 15 percent interest in Komercijalna Banka, a financial institution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Panic, whose official biography says he came from Yugoslavia in 1956 with ''two suitcases and $20,'' may find such hardships common. After all, dealing with recalcitrant health care debtors could not be any more difficult than attempting to bring peace to the war-torn region of the former Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>And ICN, which Mr. Panic founded in 1960, has had plenty of failures. In the 1980's, it aggressively promoted ribavirin's potential as a treatment for patients infected with H.I.V., the virus that causes AIDS. But the effort failed, and ICN ended up the subject of lawsuits from shareholders and the Securities and Exchange Commission. The company ultimately reached settlements with both, without admitting or denying any wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>Then, in the early 1990's, it promoted the drug's potential as a stand-alone treatment for hepatitis C.  Again, the tests disappointed, and ICN recently settled more shareholder lawsuits related to those tests. The sale of stock by Mr. Panic before ICN announced the F.D.A.'s rejection of that treatment application is the subject of continuing investigations by the S.E.C. and the United States Attorney for the Central District of California.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Panic is barred from ICN's business, as the S.E.C.'s staff has recommended, much of the company's business, particularly in Eastern Europe, would be threatened. Investors seem to have overlooked or dismissed the possibility outright.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: MARKET PLACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
