<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beyond the Pale</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="853076"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="STYLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SKIN</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORRIS, BOB</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Skin</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDE1139F935A15756C0A960958260" item-length="415" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beyond the Pale</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bob Morris</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORRIS, BOB</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fashion is like the id. It makes you desire things you shouldn't. And as the  anti-conscience of mainstream culture, designers and stylists just love being naughty. Having promoted, in past seasons, blatant signifiers of transgression,  including drag, bondage and piercing, guess what some of them were glamorizing at the spring fashion shows last winter? Not pedophilia or smoking. That would be going too far. Give up? The suntan.</p>
        <p>But the funny thing is, we don't need fashion's permission to tan. We, the people, have been tanning (guiltily but regularly) right through the tanning moratorium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fashion is like the id. It makes you desire things you shouldn't. And as the  anti-conscience of mainstream culture, designers and stylists just love being naughty. Having promoted, in past seasons, blatant signifiers of transgression,  including drag, bondage and piercing, guess what some of them were glamorizing at the spring fashion shows last winter? Not pedophilia or smoking. That would be going too far. Give up? The suntan.</p>
        <p>But the funny thing is, we don't need fashion's permission to tan. We, the people, have been tanning (guiltily but regularly) right through the tanning moratorium.</p>
        <p>We tan because we have learned, the hard way, that the higher the level of S.P.F. in our sunblock, the lower the quality of our sex lives. We tan in solidarity with Bob Dole, who tans regularly on the balcony outside his Capitol  office. We tan in the spirit of the Duchess of York, whose life got more interesting after her topless tanning incident hit the tabloids a few years ago. We tan because, when you're panicking about crow's-feet, gray hair, cellulite and paunches, it's still the cheapest and fastest makeover there is.</p>
        <p>Most of all, we tan because we like ourselves better when we don't look like  ourselves. I have an olive complexion. I don't like looking like an olive. Would you?</p>
        <p>The other night, I dreamed I lived in a gated community somewhere in the sun  belt. We were in the middle of an all-day ritual, a sort of potluck tanning bacchanal in which we were throwing tubes of sunblock and self-tanning gel into  a burning lake on a golf course while chain smoking and spraying aerosol antiperspirant into the air. Although we didn't enlarge the ozone hole, develop melanomas or lung disease, the health police came to arrest us anyway. We seduced them with foil reflectors, baby oil and wine coolers, and they ended  up stripping down to their Calvins and joining the party.</p>
        <p>I don't remember much more of the dream, except for George Hamilton and Don Johnson emerging from a Coppertone calf rolled in by the cast of "Baywatch." Also, at some point, it started to acid-rain, so we put on our asbestos sarongs  and went inside to watch a horror movie. It was called "Village of the Tanned,"  I think. Or maybe it was "Wait Until You're Dark."</p>
        <p>STYLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
