<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the Top of the Heap in a Tough Game</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="853106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHESS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LOPEZ, ROBERT JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Chess</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chess</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E5DD1139F935A15756C0A960958260" item-length="1388" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the Top of the Heap in a Tough Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACKIE FITZPATRICK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Robert Lopez Jr. was about 7 years old, his father pulled out a chess board and had him play a game. "From the start I could tell he was going to be interested; he showed all the signs," Robert Lopez Sr. said.</p>
        <p>The father taught the son everything he knew about the game and when he played his son, he played him hard. "My father killed me, all the time, 20, 30,  100 times in a row," the son said. "He wanted me to learn the right way. He wouldn't go easy." But a few years later, when his father left on a trip to Puerto Rico, Mr. Lopez figured out a way to get an edge. He went to the library  and took out books on chess. He sat up late at night, after his homework was done, and thumbed through those books, taking tips from the masters, studying moves, absorbing all that he could.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Robert Lopez Jr. was about 7 years old, his father pulled out a chess board and had him play a game. "From the start I could tell he was going to be interested; he showed all the signs," Robert Lopez Sr. said.</p>
        <p>The father taught the son everything he knew about the game and when he played his son, he played him hard. "My father killed me, all the time, 20, 30,  100 times in a row," the son said. "He wanted me to learn the right way. He wouldn't go easy." But a few years later, when his father left on a trip to Puerto Rico, Mr. Lopez figured out a way to get an edge. He went to the library  and took out books on chess. He sat up late at night, after his homework was done, and thumbed through those books, taking tips from the masters, studying moves, absorbing all that he could.</p>
        <p>When his father returned, "he still beat me at chess but I was a lot better. I was also totally into the game," Mr. Lopez said.</p>
        <p>Since then, things have changed a bit at the Lopez household. At the age of 15 and a sophomore at Central High School in Bridgeport, Mr. Lopez is now the reigning champion -- in his household and in the state. Earlier this year, he won the state high school chess championship, beating students from all over Connecticut. He will go on to the United States Chess Scholastic Championship in Virginia in August where he'll face players from all 50 states.</p>
        <p>The wins he savors most are the ones against his father and when he talks about that, his lips curl up into a warm smile. He's also proud of the fact that other students at his high school "think it's cool that I won the championship."</p>
        <p>"People come up in the halls and say, 'Hey, are you the chess guy?' I like that," Mr. Lopez said.</p>
        <p>Andy Karcich, the principal of Central High School, said the whole school was wowed by the win. "We're proud because people tend to look down their noses at urban schools. We feel very strongly that our students accomplish a lot in a lot of areas, as Robert has," he said. "To have one of our kids whip kids from suburban schools shows we do have good schools in the cities."</p>
        <p>Mr. Karcich said Mr. Lopez is "in the most challenging classes for sophomores and he's a very good student. He's also a solid citizen."</p>
        <p>James MacMath, an English teacher at Central High, has been moderating the school's chess club for more than 25 years. "Robert," he said, "is a very, very  good player. He's thinking all the time when he's playing."</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez is currently ranked at 1,300 points. To be a chess master, which is one of his goals, a player has to reach 2,200 points.</p>
        <p>His father says he couldn't be prouder. "He surprises me all the time," he said. "I can't believe he's the state champion."</p>
        <p>Mr. MacMath says Mr. Lopez is representative of a surge in interest in chess  among young people in the cities. "It started in New York, in Harlem, and the interest in urban chess just grew," he said. "It's another form of competition.  You have to be in tip-top shape. It's nonviolent and yet it's has to do with strategy."</p>
        <p>Mr. MacMath said chess is also losing its egghead image. While membership in  the Central Chess Club boomed in the 1970's, he said he was hard pressed to interest students in it during the 80's but that's changing now. There are more  than 20 members of the club, with a wide range of abilities. Some had never played the game before in their lives, others have been playing with friends in  study hall or learned from a family member and want to learn more.</p>
        <p>Mr. MacMath predicts said he hopes to hold some fund-raising events so the students can switch from paper chess boards, maybe to vinyl, he said with a chuckle. Top-of-the-line chess materials aren't what matter, he's quick to point out.</p>
        <p>The chess club meets after school once a week in the library and members challenge each other. Some of the students, like Mr. Lopez, assist Mr. MacMath in teaching their peers the finer points of the game.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez says it's exciting to see when someone finally learns to play the game, when a "light bulb goes off in a person's head" and the student can see the board, can anticipate moves and create strategies. "I like to teach other kids," he said.</p>
        <p>Although he initially learned the game from his father, he also attributes his success to a chess program at the Longfellow School in Bridgeport and what he learned in a summer chess program through the Bridgeport school system's Lighthouses program. He teaches chess to younger students in the summer program  and says he has also learned a great deal from players who gather regularly at a McDonald's in Bridgeport. "They're seasoned competitors," he said.</p>
        <p>Last year, he placed sixth in a United States Junior Chess competition in Stamford. To prepare for this year's high school championship, Mr. Lopez played  for hours each day after school. He also worked out and ate "all the right foods," saying that a top chess player needs to be as well conditioned as any top athlete. He practiced with the club, with Mr. MacMath, with his father and his younger sister, Catherine, who knows a thing or two about the game herself,  having been a Bridgeport chess champion. She and her brother play game after game. Often, Mr. Lopez competes blindfolded or with his back to the board in the family matches. His sister would announce her move and then, not looking at the board, he'd try to picture the pieces and make his move.</p>
        <p>All the training, studying and practice paid off when Mr.Lopez won the state  title after several rounds and one game that lasted more than three hours.</p>
        <p>While chess figures largely in Mr. Lopez' life, it's certainly not his only interest. He plays football, basketball and volleyball. He'd like to be both a stockbroker and a chess master when he gets older. He is an honors student; but  he attributes his ability to stay focused on school to chess.</p>
        <p>"When I played football guys ragged on me for playing chess," he said. "A lot of my friends would just be hanging out on the streets and they'd ask me to come and I'd say, 'No, I'm going to go play chess.' But then I got some of them interested in playing and they liked it. People don't cut on me anymore."</p>
        <p>His father said he's grateful for his son's interest in the game. "Other kids are going out at all hours or they have nothing to do and Robert's busy with chess. So is my daughter," Mr. Lopez Sr. said. "I've been lucky."</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez' love of the game is evident when he settles in to play Mr. MacMath. He wears his game face, showing very little emotion, and the two sit and think and then move swiftly, gathering each other's pieces. Mr. Lopez's strength, Mr. MacMath said, comes in his defensive strategies.</p>
        <p>While he said he does get nervous before a big tournament, Mr. Lopez says he'll be training extremely hard as the months pass and the summer's national event approaches.</p>
        <p>His father said he isn't worried about how his son will fare. "When he sets his mind to something, he completely focuses on it. He'll do his best, I know that," he said.</p>
        <p>Always, Mr. Lopez tucks a magnetic board in his backpack, just in case there's a chance for chess, anytime, anywhere.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
