<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Welcome to the Awkward Age</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="853148"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENZWEIG, ILENE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SOLONDZ, TODD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WELCOME TO THE DOLLHOUSE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DD1139F935A15756C0A960958260" item-length="1616" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Welcome to the Awkward Age</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ILENE ROSENZWEIG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENZWEIG, ILENE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WELCOME TO the Dollhouse," Todd Solondz's bleakly comic new film that won the Grand Jury Prize at the Sundance Film Festival in January, delves into the taboos of childhood sexuality. But his creation, Dawn Wiener, the movie's 11-year-old protagonist, is no Brooke Shields pretty baby. Dawn, played by a young actress named Heather Matarazzo, is "Wiener dog," the supergeek of Benjamin Franklin Junior High. Her plodding search for love in a New Jersey suburb is handicapped by her babyish Danskin pants, her smiley-face earrings and the fact that she hasn't yet discovered contact lenses.</p>
        <p>The cheerleaders call her "lesbo," her teacher calls her a "grade grubber," and even her own mother takes away her dessert. As if making a leading lady of Dawn weren't perverse enough, Mr. Solondz sets his antiheroine in an antiplot that flouts every Hollywood formula. Dawn never gets an Alicia Silverstone makeover. Nor does she figure out a way to get the attention of Steve (played by Eric Mabius), the high school student on whom she has a life-threatening crush.  By the film's end, she aspires only to hang on through eighth grade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WELCOME TO the Dollhouse," Todd Solondz's bleakly comic new film that won the Grand Jury Prize at the Sundance Film Festival in January, delves into the taboos of childhood sexuality. But his creation, Dawn Wiener, the movie's 11-year-old protagonist, is no Brooke Shields pretty baby. Dawn, played by a young actress named Heather Matarazzo, is "Wiener dog," the supergeek of Benjamin Franklin Junior High. Her plodding search for love in a New Jersey suburb is handicapped by her babyish Danskin pants, her smiley-face earrings and the fact that she hasn't yet discovered contact lenses.</p>
        <p>The cheerleaders call her "lesbo," her teacher calls her a "grade grubber," and even her own mother takes away her dessert. As if making a leading lady of Dawn weren't perverse enough, Mr. Solondz sets his antiheroine in an antiplot that flouts every Hollywood formula. Dawn never gets an Alicia Silverstone makeover. Nor does she figure out a way to get the attention of Steve (played by Eric Mabius), the high school student on whom she has a life-threatening crush.  By the film's end, she aspires only to hang on through eighth grade.</p>
        <p>Given the emotional and visual detail that distinguishes "Welcome to the Dollhouse," which opened on Friday, it would be easy to conclude that the film is painfully autobiographical. But Mr. Solondz says it's not that simple.</p>
        <p>Mr. Solondz, who both wrote and directed "Welcome to the Dollhouse," says he  made the film to prove that "excruciating pain" not only exists in banal circumstances but can be aggravated by them. He himself is the product of an intact family in a neighborhood of split-level houses in suburban Livingston, in northern New Jersey. While at the age of 8 he wanted to be a rabbi and later wandered through a succession of religious, public and private schools, he was hardly an outcast like Dawn Wiener.</p>
        <p>"You don't have to have been sexually molested as a child to have had a hard  time as a child," he said. "You don't have to have been locked in a closet and beaten up to have experienced seventh grade as a nightmare." In his view, grappling with one's own half-formed libido while surrounded by lilac-colored shag rugs at home is enough to drive any child mad.</p>
        <p>The film maker, a small-framed man of 36 who wears enormous-framed glasses, speaks in a comically plaintive singsong that makes everything he says sound amusing, though he tends to describe most things as depressing.  He even makes his own good fortune with "Dollhouse" sound like a loss. "Now I can't really dream about success anymore," he said ruefully, sitting at a cafe near his East  Village apartment.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Solondz clings to the awkward pose of underdog, it would be wrong  to dismiss his reluctance to accept his new renown as neurotic shtick.</p>
        <p>As a seventh grader himself, he knew what it was like to be less than popular. Moreover, he is haunted by an earlier brush with Hollywood success, a success that vanished the moment his first feature film was released. At the very mention of its prophetic title -- "Fear, Anxiety and Depression" -- he slumps in his chair, drops his head in his hands and groans.</p>
        <p>Back in 1986, Mr. Solondz was a hot-shot film student at New York University  who, on the basis of a single short comic film, was given three-picture deals at both Columbia and Fox. But he wasn't enticed by the commercial projects the studios had in mind for him. "They wanted to give him like 'Revenge of the Nerds II,' " said the producer Cary Woods, who was Mr. Solondz's agent at the time. Mr. Solondz ducked out of his Hollywood deals and made his own movie.</p>
        <p>Even fans of Mr. Solondz remember that film, "Fear, Anxiety and Depression,"  as, in the words of the influential producer John Pierson, "truly horrible, one  of the more memorably bad first features, a failure on every level." The film starred Mr. Solondz as an East Village playwright who waddles around New York in a loden coat and mittens, chasing after kinky club girls and writing letters to  Samuel Beckett between failed suicide attempts.</p>
        <p>The film barely opened before it closed to dismal reviews. Mr. Solondz said he then applied to the Peace Corps ("I was thinking something African") but was  rejected. Instead, he salved his wounds by teaching English to Russian immigrants.</p>
        <p>In the days following the disastrous opening of "Fear, Anxiety and Depression," Mr. Solondz wrote the script for "Welcome to the Dollhouse" "in order to redeem myself," he said. Although he denies that "Welcome to the Dollhouse" is autobiographical in any literal sense, he concedes that his own self-loathing after his Hollywood flame-out laid the groundwork for the character of Dawn Wiener, whom he describes as "an outcast who is not a walking  innocent."</p>
        <p>"There isn't a single scene in the movie that I could say actually happened to me," he said. "But emotionally, of course, it's all very real."</p>
        <p>"Welcome to the Dollhouse" has a near-documentary feel, in large part because of Mr. Solondz's seemingly obsessive attention to visual detail. His 41-year-old sister, Lori Solondz, an artist who lives in Paris and shares his vision of suburbia ("a repulsive place that is at the same time endearing," she said), was recruited as art director to create a suburban universe that evokes their hometown. His parents, Philip and Gaby Solondz, moved from Newark to Livingston  with their four children in the 1960's. Todd Solondz's two brothers followed their father into the construction business.</p>
        <p>Todd and Lori Solondz inherited their mother's ambivalence about Livingston.  "I was never a lover of suburbia," said Todd's mother, who used to pile her babies into a carriage and take them to museums in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>She attributes what she describes as his "miserable" seventh-grade year to the fact that she didn't send her 11-year-old cello-playing and poetry-writing son to an "art school in the city" but instead planted him in a "jocky boy's prep school." Todd Solondz recalls it as a " 'Goodbye, Mr. Chips' type of place."</p>
        <p>He survived the school, but he wasn't much happier among the literary set at  Yale, where he majored in English. It wasn't until he attended film school and began his career as a director that things started to look better, even Livingston.</p>
        <p>"I always thought it was the ugliest place in the world," Mr. Solondz said. "But when I went back, looking at locations with the eyes of a film maker, it's really not so bad."</p>
        <p>Working with a budget of under $1 million, the production crew combed garage  sales and garbage cans near West Caldwell, N.J., where the film was shot, searching for tacky suburban icons: plastic bowling pins, lamps that look like DNA models, Lucite picture cubes.</p>
        <p>"It's even more depressing because it's all faded and worn, which is expressive of my feelings about the suburbs," Mr. Solondz said. "In America, there's this whole message of 'be happy,' the smiley face and all that. There's  something dictatorial about it, and it's inevitably very false."</p>
        <p>MR. SOLONDZ'S musical choices in the film mock the "idyllic" backdrop. Pounding "throb music" serves as Dawn's internal anthem, while Tchaikovsky's "Nutcracker Suite" is heard each time her contemptibly sweet little sister appears in a pink tutu.</p>
        <p>After scouting the local malls and auditioning hundreds of actors for the role of Dawn, Mr. Solondz and his casting director, Ann Goulder, settled on Heather Matarazzo, who was then 11. (The actress, who lives in East Norwich, L.  I., is now 13.) Mr. Solondz chose to write about a female character because he felt girls were more expressive of their emotions than boys.</p>
        <p>Although he eliminated a scene from an early draft of the script in which Dawn is raped in Times Square, the film, which is rated R, still has many edgy scenes. There is a threatened rape, and the children swear incessantly.</p>
        <p>"This film is an exploration of a particular time in childhood that I felt I  hadn't seen treated seriously in American movies," Mr. Solondz said. "The language, the sexuality -- that's how I understand middle-class suburban childhood. I think it's very difficult for adults to look at children as having  any degree of sexuality. It's terrifying to them." His film thus portrays children as sexual beings without presenting them as sex objects.</p>
        <p>In making a film that "legitimizes the pain of growing up," as Mr. Solondz described it, he has also redeemed himself as a film maker, a feat that is all the more gratifying after his humiliating failure six years ago. No one has been more surprised by the force of his re-entry than Mr. Solondz. At least that's how it looked at Sundance when he stepped up to the podium to accept his award.  Blanching, his glasses catching the spotlights, he looked strikingly like Dawn Wiener during a scene in which she becomes dumbstruck while addressing a school  assembly.</p>
        <p>When Dawn opened her mouth, the students jeered. When Mr. Solondz finally uttered a thank you, he heard nothing but applause.</p>
        <p>FILM Ilene Rosenzweig, a senior editor at Alluremagazine, is the author of the "I Hate Madonna Handbook."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Ilene Rosenzweig, a senior editor at Alluremagazine, is the author of the "I Hate Madonna Handbook."</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
