<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Seeks to Bar Retaliation if Haitian Is Restored</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="586234"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAITI-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAITI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLMES, STEVEN A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARISTIDE, JEAN-BERTRAND (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Haiti</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDA133BF93BA15752C0A965958260" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Seeks to Bar Retaliation if Haitian Is Restored</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN A. HOLMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLMES, STEVEN A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Clinton Administration seeks to cobble together a political settlement in Haiti, officials say that perhaps their most important task is figuring out ways to assure not only supporters of the ousted President but also members of the current military Government that they will not be subject to harassment, intimidation or even murder.</p>
        <p>While much of the public attention toward the political crisis in Haiti has been focused on the army's repression of Haitians, especially supporters of the exiled President, Administration officials said they felt that a peaceful restoration of the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide to the presidency can occur only if members of the military can be assured they will not fall victim to violent mobs seeking retribution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the Clinton Administration seeks to cobble together a political settlement in Haiti, officials say that perhaps their most important task is figuring out ways to assure not only supporters of the ousted President but also members of the current military Government that they will not be subject to harassment, intimidation or even murder.</p>
        <p>While much of the public attention toward the political crisis in Haiti has been focused on the army's repression of Haitians, especially supporters of the exiled President, Administration officials said they felt that a peaceful restoration of the Rev. Jean-Bertrand Aristide to the presidency can occur only if members of the military can be assured they will not fall victim to violent mobs seeking retribution.</p>
        <p>In recent weeks, Father Aristide has called on his supporters not to undertake "violent behavior" toward the army if he is returned to power. But the fear of retribution, based in part on Father Aristide's history of inciting mob violence, is one of the major reasons why the present military leaders cling so tightly to power, Administration officials say.</p>
        <p>As a result, the deployment by the United Nations and the Organization of American States of human rights monitors is seen by the Administration as a crucial step to protect the lives both of Haitians who support and Haitians who oppose the present Government.</p>
        <p>The Government -- nominally headed by Prime Minister Marc Bazin but, many believe, really run by Lieut. Gen. Raoul Cedras -- has agreed in principle to the deployment of monitors.</p>
        <p>While the Bush Administration had said it wanted the restoration of Father Aristide, it was never comfortable with the left-wing priest and had supported a political rival against him in the election that brought him to power.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton, by labeling Mr. Bush's order to return Haitian boat people without granting them asylum hearings "cruel" during the campaign and then adopting that policy as his own after the election, has put more pressure on himself to resolve Haiti's political crisis. He has said his adoption of the Bush policy is temporary until a political settlement is devised.</p>
        <p>The basis of that settlement, Administration officials say, is the restoration of President Aristide "when conditions permit." The feeling among Administration officials, however, is that they must allay fears that Mr. Aristide would lead a popular movement to punish members of the military.</p>
        <p>In the Haitian upheaval that toppled Jean-Claude Duvalier in 1986, mob violence killed hundreds of real and suspected members of the Tonton Macoutes, a secret police that terrorized Haitians during the Duvalier reign.</p>
        <p>In the past, the army was largely able to escape the wrath of the Haitian populace. But since the military coup that ousted Father Aristide, the country's military have been said to have engaged in a reign of terror.</p>
        <p>The soldiers, seen as an undisciplined force of about 8,000, have used their weapons to extort and intimidate. In an example of the lawlessness of the military, the Rev. Jesse Jackson, who was in Haiti on a two-day fact-finding trip, was stopped and harassed by soldiers, even though he was being escorted by American officials.</p>
        <p>Moreover, reports by the State Department and independent human rights organizations assert that at best, Father Aristide failed to condemn mob violence when he was President from January to September 1991. While he was in office, these reports say, Father Aristide or his followers were involved in killing or threatening his political rivals, intimidating judges into meting out an unconstitutional jail sentence against a coup plotter, sacking the offices of the Vatican's representative and trying to cover up the slaying of five teen-agers by his police force.</p>
        <p>Human rights advocates say the abuses during his Government pale in comparison to the repression since Father Aristide was toppled.</p>
        <p>Michael D. Barnes, a Washington lawyer and adviser to Father Aristide, said a recent opinion column in The Washington Post accusing Father Aristide of abuses was part of a campaign of "disinformation" by his opponents to forestall American action to restore him to power.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
