<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Talk of Sundance; At Sundance, a Yoking of Youth and Thrift</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="586292"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCUMENTARY FILMS AND PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUNDANCE FILM FESTIVAL (PARK CITY, UTAH)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PARK CITY (UTAH)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Sundance Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah/Park City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Utah</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED9123CF93BA15752C0A965958260" item-length="1431" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Talk of Sundance; At Sundance, a Yoking of Youth and Thrift</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</byline>
      <dateline>PARK CITY, Utah, Jan. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Zee Place" is the place to be every evening at 6.</p>
        <p>A squat building on Maine Street, it is the swarming headquarters of the Sundance Film Festival and has been known, in this ski resort's quaint version of a French accent, as zee center of town.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"Zee Place" is the place to be every evening at 6.</p>
        <p>A squat building on Maine Street, it is the swarming headquarters of the Sundance Film Festival and has been known, in this ski resort's quaint version of a French accent, as zee center of town.</p>
        <p>Inside, on a converted basketball court, everyone is in jeans, thick sweaters and, in the case of visiting Hollywood agents, parkas and boots that appear to have cost more than some of the short films that are shown here.</p>
        <p>Plenty of the 5,000 guests at the nation's major showcase for independent films have managed to slip away for several hours of skiing. But the main order of business is movies, day and night. And 6 P.M. is break time at "Zee Place," when the attendees seek out tickets for the night's movies, most of which are sold out anyway, and schmooze about what they saw in the day.</p>
        <p>If there's a consensus this year it's that the movies here, as in Hollywood, are not better than ever. Younger than ever, perhaps, but not better.</p>
        <p>What has emerged starkly at Sundance, however, is that for the first time documentaries are dominating a festival that has been known, since it started in 1981, as a haven for features.</p>
        <p>"This is the strongest group of documentaries we've had, and their range of issues and quality and esthetic have been remarkable," said Geoffrey Gilmore, the director of the festival's programming. "The documentaries have become</p>
        <p>the</p>
        <p>powerful vehicle for dealing with social and political issues. Clearly there's been an expansion of the sense of possibility for documentaries because the film industry just tries to avoid anything controversial."</p>
        <p>Certainly, the documentary films here present some highly intense personal visions. The most-discussed include "Aileen Wuornos: Portrait of a Serial Killer," about how Hollywood and book publishers cashed in on a woman accused of killing seven men; "Silverlake Life: The View from Here," a gruelling and emotional chronicle of two men infected with the AIDS virus; "Saviors of the Forest," a zany look at film makers and earth-firsters who manage to exploit the environment; "Something Within Me," about St. Augustine's School of the Arts in the South Bronx; "Nitrate Kisses," an artsy and experimental look at gay life, and "On the Bridge," about the director Frank Perry's struggle with of cancer.</p>
        <p>But the film that is perhaps attracting the most attention is "Earth and the American Dream," made by Bill Couturie, whose earlier works included "Dear America: Letters Home From Vietnam" and "Common Threads: Stories From the Quilt."</p>
        <p>Interweaving nature photography, newsreels, music and voiceovers of stars such as Dustin Hoffman, Bette Midler, Mel Gibson and Jeremy Irons depicting historical figures, the documentary, which was financed by HBO, is a ferocious indictment of the nation's environmental and moral destruction.</p>
        <p>In an interview today, Mr. Coutourie said, "People like me, people who make documentaries, are just exploring new forms. To me, the form itself is very pliable."</p>
        <p>"The stigma of making documentaries is rubbing off," he said. "They used to be like castor oil. You were supposed to take them for your own good, but it always tasted bad. People now understand: a documentary can move you, engage you, involve you just as much as a feature film." A Generation Gap</p>
        <p>If documentaries are getting the lion's share of attention, a handful of the festival's features are nonetheless proving to be popular with festivalgoers, some of them for reasons that have less to do with quality than how cheaply they were made or how young their makers are.</p>
        <p>And a question that has served as an undercurrent here is that this year's showcase somehow proves that many of the twentysomething film makers, while technically proficient, may not have the vision or life experiences that can enrich a film.</p>
        <p>"These film makers here grew up on 'Sesame Street' and video stores," said L. M. (Kit) Carson, a Texas-based screenwriter who has written such movies as "Paris, Texas," and the remake of "Breathless." "They haven't found a style yet, a grip. The features here are a struggle for coherence and an authentic expression of where these people are."</p>
        <p>Mr. Carson, who is 50, said with a smile, "We have a generation whose perceptions are unfinished because they learned it from television."</p>
        <p>In contrast, Mr. Carson and others pointed out, the young film makers and films that emerged in the 1970's, while as different as Martin Scorsese and George Lucas, or "Five Easy Pieces" and "Easy Rider," offered a coherent vision.</p>
        <p>"This was a generation that somehow felt they had a grasp on the world," said Mr. Carson, who was seated in the bustling festival headquarters. "That's what they were so upset about. They thought they knew what was right and wrong."</p>
        <p>The young feature film makers represented here may not have the life experiences Mr. Carson refers to, but they are united by an almost obsessive struggle to make their often personal films, and to do it with very little money. For that reason, they seem, at least for the moment, a decidely un-Hollywood group.</p>
        <p>They include Steven Gomer, a low-keyed 36-year-old former New Yorker, who directed "Fly by Night," a drama dealing with the struggles of New York rappers, and Victor Nunez, a Tallahassee-based film maker whose movie, "Ruby in Paradise," concerns a blue-collar woman who finds a job on the "redneck Riviera" on the Florida panhandle. (The movie has produced the festival's one unexpected star so far, Ashley Judd, a young actress who gives a complex and vulnerable performance.)</p>
        <p>There is also Michael Lessac, who ran the Colonnades Theater Lab in New York, and spent six years struggling to direct his screenplay of "House of Cards," about a woman trying to deal with her talented child who is autistic. Mr. Lessac acknowledges that he's a little luckier than many others here. The star of the film (which will be shown here this weekend) is Kathleen Turner, who knew Mr. Lessac from the theater lab. Initially, the lead character was a man, but after Ms. Turner read the script, she asked Mr. Lessac to revise it for her and agreed to have him direct.</p>
        <p>And then there's Robert Rodriguez, who is 24 and from Austin, Tex. His funny, action-adventure film, "El Mariachi," involves a mariachi musician who enters the small border town at the same time as a hit man. The two men wear black and both carry similar guitar cased.</p>
        <p>What makes "El Mariachi" remarkable is that Mr. Rodriquez made it for a microscopic $7,000, a feat that has made Mr. Rodriguez something of a star himself.</p>
        <p>After frenzied jockeying by virtually every studio in Hollywood, Mr. Rodriguez has signed a two-year contract with Columbia Pictures that calls for a low six-figure salary each year, with an extra fee if he directs a movie. Part of the reason is that Columbia made "Boyz N the Hood," by John Singleton, the young black director, which impressed Mr. Rodriguez, who is Hispanic. Another reason is that Stephanie Allain, vice president of production at the studio, flew to San Antonio to meet Mr. Rodriguez, his 10 brothers and sisters, his father, Cecilio, who sells pots and pans door to door, and his mother, Rebecca, a nurse.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rodriguez, a calm, self-assured young man who looks on his current success with plenty of humor, is a film major at the University of Texas in Austin. Hoping to make some quick money in the Spanish-language video market, he made "El Mariachi" in Spanish with his friend Carlos Gallardo, the film's star. When that attempt fell through he drove to Los Angeles from Austin.</p>
        <p>He found the name of an agent, Robert Newman of International Creative Management, on a list of people who had attended a meeting about making more films in Texas, and dropped off a copy of the tape at the agency. Mr. Newman, who is in Park City, said today that he was "amazed" by the tape. The rest, as they say, is Hollywood history.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rodriguez laughed. "I'm putting my money in the bank so I can send my younger brothers to school," he said. "We've always helped each other."</p>
        <p>Sipping coffee and sitting unshaven the other morning in his hotel, Mr. Rodriguez said he would remain in Texas. "I grew up watching the Latinos always being the bad guys," he said. "I want to make movies about Hispanics who happen to be regular guys."</p>
        <p>As for his apparent success, Mr. Rodriguez said: "Look, my stock's up now but it could change. I've saved every paycheck I've ever gotten and put it in the bank. That's what my father taught me. Pretend it's the last one."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
