<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>As Johnny Learns to Shop, Hiroko Learns to Think;   Lengthen School Year</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="371764"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D81E3BF935A15754C0A966958260" item-length="358" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>As Johnny Learns to Shop, Hiroko Learns to Think;   Lengthen School Year</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>That ''Johnny Can't Add, Hiroko Can'' (The Editorial Notebook, July 9) is hardly news to anyone following the educational debate. While Hiroko labors away in school, far too many Johnnies are, according to Anna Quindlen's column of the day before (''Latchkey Summer,'' July 8), spending their summers safely locked inside their homes with a television and an air-conditioner, casualties less of working mothers than of an outmoded school schedule that assumes most children are needed to help with the harvest for three months each summer.</p>
        <p>''A Nation at Risk,'' the landmark 1983 report, recommended that the school year be lengthened. The idea of a longer year was favored by 44 percent of those surveyed in a Gallup poll last year, with those in favor tending to be older and better educated than those opposed. Most important, however, the evidence is mounting that the more time children spend in school, the more they learn. A school district in Polk County, North Carolina, added an extra month to the academic calendar, and test scores showed improvement after only two years.</p>
        <p>If lengthening the school year works, and if significant numbers of people want to try it, isn't an experimental pilot program worth developing, to give parents a choice between the traditional 9-month program and a 12-month program (with periodic short breaks, of course)? Too expensive? Mr. Wade points out that American industry spends, it is estimated, $30 billion a year in remedial education, and that is for those who make it into the work force. People further down the social scale have problems even more acute, and Dr. Gwendolyn Baker, the new president of the New York City Board of Education, is right when she defends her goal of keeping schools open year-round by saying, ''I'd rather pay for schools than detox.''</p>
        <p>If Johnny can't add, and Hiroko can, Johnny will eventually find himself working for Hiroko. And even if Hiroko is willing to provide Johnny with the necessary remedial education, is that truly the legacy that we Americans want to pass on to our children?</p>
        <p>GENEVE S. MAROON</p>
        <p>Washington, July 9, 1990</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
