<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Tragedy to Absurdity With Finland's Prolific Upstart</title>
    <meta content="076490SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="378882"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Review</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Caryn</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Calamari Union (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Shadows in Paradise (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501EEDF153AF930A1575BC0A966958260" item-length="1337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Tragedy to Absurdity With Finland's Prolific Upstart</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, Caryn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seventeen guys in dark glasses are playing electric guitars and keyboards on the stage of a small club in Finland. All of these men are named Frank, and some of them have died earlier in the film, ''Calamari Union,'' which is not about a rock band at all, but about the Franks' meandering attempts to get to the other side of Helsinki. Yet here they are, alive and singing what could be the director Aki Kaurismaki's anthem: ''Bad boys are coming to break all your toys.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaurismaki, who has written and directed eight mischievous, society-tweaking films in the last seven years, is the highly successful bad boy of Finnish cinema. In fact, he and his older brother Mika almost are the Finnish cinema; each directs, and together they produce their own works and distribute foreign films. Now Aki Kaurismaki's films are arriving in the United States in one great wave, and they demonstrate that, at the age of 33, he is more than a prolific upstart or a local curiosity; he is an original and commanding talent among international film makers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Seventeen guys in dark glasses are playing electric guitars and keyboards on the stage of a small club in Finland. All of these men are named Frank, and some of them have died earlier in the film, ''Calamari Union,'' which is not about a rock band at all, but about the Franks' meandering attempts to get to the other side of Helsinki. Yet here they are, alive and singing what could be the director Aki Kaurismaki's anthem: ''Bad boys are coming to break all your toys.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaurismaki, who has written and directed eight mischievous, society-tweaking films in the last seven years, is the highly successful bad boy of Finnish cinema. In fact, he and his older brother Mika almost are the Finnish cinema; each directs, and together they produce their own works and distribute foreign films. Now Aki Kaurismaki's films are arriving in the United States in one great wave, and they demonstrate that, at the age of 33, he is more than a prolific upstart or a local curiosity; he is an original and commanding talent among international film makers.</p>
        <p>Beginning today, Anthology Film Archives (32-34 Second Avenue, at Second Street) will present the three earliest and most varied Kaurismaki films: a trenchant modern version of Dostoyevsky's ''Crime and Punishment'' (1983), the gleefully absurdist ''Calamari Union'' (1985) and ''Shadows in Paradise,'' (1986) the rich and droll story of a pessimistic garbage collector.</p>
        <p>''Shadows in Paradise'' is the first film in a trilogy featuring hemmed-in working-class heros. ''Ariel'' (1988), the second part, is now at the Bleecker Street Cinema and will move to Anthology on Aug. 31. And next month the New York Film Festival will present the third, ''The Match Factory Girl,'' as well as Mr. Kaurismaki's comic thriller, ''I Hired a Contract Killer,'' an English-language movie that was filmed in London. Yet another Kaurismaki film, ''Leningrad Cowboys Go America,'' will open in theaters this fall; made mostly in English, it is the comic story of no-talent Soviet rock musicians on tour in the United States. They are not named Frank. Looking at the earliest of these films, it is easy to recognize Mr. Kaurismaki's crisp, sardonic manner beneath the variety of themes and genres. The blank faces of his supermarket cashiers and factory workers suggest they are simply befuddled by life. Yet their diminished dreams erupt in flashes of anger or action, often involving fake passports and escape from Finland.</p>
        <p>Their dingy apartments, the bright urban lights and the ocean that promises freedom are captured in sharp yet luminous photography that heightens reality without adding glamour. And their stories are told with great conciseness. When a woman reaches for a phone to call the police, there is a quick cut to the police car's lights flashing outside the house. Throughout all this, Mr. Kaurismaki skillfully controls the flow between humor and tragedy. Few film makers have shown such authority so early in their careers.</p>
        <p>''Shadows in Paradise'' is the most characteristic of the three early works, with its nearly plotless story, garbage-collector hero and desolate atmosphere. With his greased-back hair, sad yet bitter eyes and laconic manner, the hero is the perfect hapless Kaurismaki character. ''I'm Nikander,'' he explains to a potential girlfriend, with a glimmer of anger at his own condition. ''Bad teeth, bad stomach, liver hanging on. That's more than I can say for my head.''</p>
        <p>When he romances this equally downtrodden supermarket cashier - they sit on the back of his garbage truck and chat - he is both affecting and exasperating. He puts on a suit and buys her flowers, and before she knows what hit her they are at a bingo game. She returns the flowers, saying she just doesn't think this will work.</p>
        <p>It would be easy to feel cheap pathos for such characters, except that they never feel sorry for themselves. They bounce back to life as Mr. Kaurismaki keeps sight of the absurd comedy that creeps into odd corners of their stories. The cashier returns to Nikander after she is fired and steals the store's cash box. ''I wanted to go to Florida, but I missed the plane,'' she tells him, adding in the casual, deadpan manner all these characters share, ''My aunt's been to Florida. All she saw was some Finns and Donald Duck.'' America is no dreamland to these people, but American pop culture is a constant presence in Mr. Kaurismaki's films. Old rock-and-roll songs, often sung in English, are standard backdrops, suggesting escape to another world rather than cultural oppression. But Mr. Kaurismaki knows even better than his characters that Florida has its own Nikanders and Helskinki has its own Robert De Niros.</p>
        <p>To American audiences, the funniest Frank in ''Calamari Union'' is likely to be the one who speaks English and who is fond of quoting Mr. De Niro's lines from ''Taxi Driver.'' In the slow, deliberate voice of someone reciting an English-language lesson (something Kaurismaki characters often do), this Frank drawls, ''You talk-in' to me?''</p>
        <p>''Calamari Union'' is itself a chaotic mix of ''Mean Streets'' and the Marx Brothers. In appropriately seedy black and white, Mr. Kaurismaki takes over the American gangster film and flavors it with his improbable humor. The Franks, who desperately want to be tough guys, commandeer a subway train and sleep in trees. Two of them steal a motor scooter, ride it inside a bar, stride up to the bartender and, in a tone as tough as Bogart's, demand two ice waters. Next to such freneticism, ''Crime and Punishment'' seems classical in its spareness and its serious tone. But it too reveals Mr. Kaurismaki's touch. He has referred to this film as a ''homage to those golden years when one murder was enough for one crime film,'' and beneath that glibness is some truth about an affecting modern story that intelligently echoes Dostoyevsky's questions about guilt, responsibility and the psychology of crime.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaurismaki's counterpart to Raskolnikov is a slaughterhouse worker called Rahikainen (played with beautiful restraint by Markku Toikka, the De Niro-quoting Frank). He murders a rich businessman for vengeful reasons that he chooses to deny. By giving his character a personal motive, Mr. Kaurismaki undermines the murderer's insistence that he wanted to kill an idea, not a man.</p>
        <p>But his haunted, mournful look suits the typical Dostoyevsky hero as well as the typical Kaurismaki character. And in scenes of searing eye-to-eye-contact between characters, Mr. Kaurismaki makes Rahikainen's ruthlessness and mental anguish visible on screen. ''I came to kill you,'' he tells his victim. ''Why?'' the man asks, and Rahikainen replies, ''You'll never know that.''</p>
        <p>As Rahikainen wavers between freedom and imprisonment, he sets the pattern for future Kaurismaki heroes - all those bads boys about to make their big cinematic escapes from Finland and onto American movie screens.</p>
        <p>Shadows in Paradise  SHADOWS IN PARADISE, written and directed by Aki Kaurismaki; director of photography, Timo Salminen; edited by Raija Talvio; released by Aki Kaurismaki/Villealfa Film Productions. Running time: 76 minutes. This film has no rating.</p>
        <p>Nikander . . . . . Matti Pellonpaa  Ilona . . . . . Kati Outinen  Melartin . . . . . Saku Kuosmanen</p>
        <p>Calamari Union  CALAMARI UNION, Directed by Aki Kaurismaki; screenplay by Mr. Kaurismaki; director of photography, Timo Salminen; edited by Aki Kaurismaki and Raija Talvio; released by Aki Kaurismaki/Villealfa Film Productions. Running time: 80 minutes. This film has no rating.</p>
        <p>WITH: Matti Pellonpaa, Sakke Jarvenpaa, Pirkka-Pekka Petelius and Puntti Valtonen.</p>
        <p>Crime And Punishment  CRIME AND PUNISHMENT, directed by Aki Kaurismaki; screenplay by Mr. Kaurismaki and Pauli Pentti; director of photography, Timo Salminen; edited by Veikko Aaltonen; music by Shostakovich and Schubert; released by Aki Kaurismaki/Villealfa Film Productions. Running time: 93 minutes. This film has no rating.</p>
        <p>Antti Rahikainen . . . . . Markku Toikka  Eeva Laakso . . . . . Aino Seppo  Inspector Pennanen . . . . . Esko Nikkari</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
