<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Plane and Patriotism Take Flight in Gaza</title>
    <meta content="07PALE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1067911"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gaza International Airport</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza Strip</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Palestinian Airlines</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Gaza Strip</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5D8163AF934A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Plane and Patriotism Take Flight in Gaza</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL GREENBERG</byline>
      <dateline>RAFAH, Gaza Strip, Dec. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Palestinians inaugurate regular air service from Gaza International Airport, which opened in October; Palestinian Airlines 48-seat Fokker 50 propeller plane makes first flight to Amman, Jordan; detours 300 miles to avoid Israeli airspace; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cruising at 19,000 feet on Saturday in the cockpit of the first Palestinian Airlines flight to depart from Gaza's new international airport, Captain Jamal Al-How from the Jabaliya refugee camp could not restrain himself.</p>
        <p>''At this historic moment, taking off for the first time in history from a Palestinian airport, all the languages of the world cannot express my pride and joy,'' he declared. ''I thank the heroic Palestinian people, which sacrificed everything it had so that we could reach this moment.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cruising at 19,000 feet on Saturday in the cockpit of the first Palestinian Airlines flight to depart from Gaza's new international airport, Captain Jamal Al-How from the Jabaliya refugee camp could not restrain himself.</p>
        <p>''At this historic moment, taking off for the first time in history from a Palestinian airport, all the languages of the world cannot express my pride and joy,'' he declared. ''I thank the heroic Palestinian people, which sacrificed everything it had so that we could reach this moment.''</p>
        <p>Earlier, applause rang through the cabin as the 48-seat Fokker 50 propeller plane, painted with the Palestinian national colors of red, green, black and white, took to the air. Mohammad Abdel Salam from Bethlehem, the steward, greeted the passengers of Flight 152, inaugurating regular service from Gaza International Airport, which was ceremonially opened last month.</p>
        <p>''Welcome aboard the first flight from Gaza Yasir Arafat International Airport, bound for Amman,'' Mr. Abdel Salam said over the loudspeaker. ''Thank you for choosing Palestinian Airlines, and we wish you all a pleasant flight.''</p>
        <p>Times have changed. In the not-too-distant past, the combination of the words ''Palestinian'' and ''airplane'' evoked images of gun-waving hijackers from the P.L.O. Now the Palestinians are running their own airline from Gaza, with planes flown by former P.L.O. pilots and with Palestinian guards checking bags and passengers for would-be terrorists.</p>
        <p>Established in 1996, the tiny Palestinian airline was an outgrowth of the accords with Israel on Palestinian self-rule. It has two Fokker 50's donated by the Netherlands, and a Boeing 727 given by Prince Walled bin Talal of Saudi Arabia, which is still being prepared for service.</p>
        <p>Starting operations in 1997 without a home airport, the airline's first flights left from Port Said in Egypt, ferrying Muslim pilgrims to Saudi Arabia. Regular service began a few months later from the Egyptian town of El Arish to Amman and to the Saudi Arabian city of Jidda. Departing passengers had to make a night-long trek by bus from Gaza to El Arish, moving slowly through Palestinian, Israeli and Egyptian checkpoints to board flights that took far less time than the ground journey.</p>
        <p>Flying from Gaza for the first time on Saturday, passengers remarked on the convenience of going directly from home to their local airport, avoiding Israeli interrogations and security checks at border crossings and at Ben-Gurion airport near Tel Aviv. It enhanced their sense that, while there was no Palestinian state yet, something like one is emerging from negotiations with Israel.</p>
        <p>''I drove here with my family, like anyone else in the world,'' said Ahmad al-Ghandour, a department head in the Palestinian Authority. ''I'm leaving like people do everywhere else, on your own plane, with your own passport.''</p>
        <p>Mahfouz Othman, a psychiatrist from Rafah, said that he was relieved of the anxiety that often plagued his departures in the past, when he was worried that he might be turned back or detained. ''I feel that I'm keeping my dignity; these are Palestinians like us,'' he said as he handed his passport to a Palestinian police officer. ''At a personal, human level, this is a changing point in our lives.''</p>
        <p>Not entirely. Shortly after Mr. Othman spoke, Palestinian security officers and their Israeli counterparts at the airport got into a dispute about departure procedures, delaying takeoff for three-and-a-half hours.</p>
        <p>Fayez Zaidan, the airline chairman, came to the passenger lounge to encourage his customers. ''We are with you facing the Israelis,'' he told them. ''This is your airport.''</p>
        <p>In the end, the passengers were bused to the adjacent Rafah border terminal to undergo passport control under Israeli supervision before returning to the plane.</p>
        <p>But the first-day hitches did not mar the patriotic spirit on the first flight from Gaza, and its passengers were greeted with roses in Amman. Flights to Jidda and Cairo are scheduled to start in a few days. The airline expects to carry thousands of passengers to the annual Muslim pilgrimage to Saudi Arabia in March, and there are plans to expand service to Cyprus, Turkey and Greece.</p>
        <p>''I always imagined that it would come,'' said Mr. Zaidan, who is also head of the Palestinian Civil Aviation Authority. ''There were many obstacles and difficulties. I'm very happy that I could achieve this goal of establishing a civil aviation authority from zero, an airport from zero, an airline from zero.''</p>
        <p>The company has sent some of its 400 employees to train in Morocco and Jordan, but the core of its crews and staff served in what was once the air wing of the Palestine Liberation Organization, or worked in airlines in the Arab world.</p>
        <p>''Like any revolution struggling for freedom, we were fighting for the liberation of Palestine,'' said Yassin al-Hawamdi, a pilot. ''Now we're building up a state.''</p>
        <p>For now, however, Palestinians do not control their skies. Takeoffs and landings must be reported to the Israelis. Flights from Gaza are barred from crossing Israel's southern airspace because there are military installations en route, compelling flights to Amman to detour over the Sinai peninsula, nearly doubling the flight time to about 90 minutes. Sophisticated landing equipment is still being held in an Israeli port, and planes can only land and take off at the Gaza airport in daylight.</p>
        <p>Yet for the Palestinian Airlines staff, operating their national carrier is a source of great satisfaction.</p>
        <p>''I have traveled everywhere, to 70 countries,'' said Mr. Abdel Salam, who worked 15 years for Kuwait Airways. ''Now I feel different. I'm taking care of my own people. We waited a long time to realize our dream.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
