<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Neediest Cases; Newborns A Blessing And a Trial For a Family</title>
    <meta content="07NEED" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1067890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York Times Neediest Cases Fund</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gershenson, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Utti, Rosalyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E1DA163AF934A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="886" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Neediest Cases; Newborns A Blessing And a Trial For a Family</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM GERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gershenson, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rosalyn Utti, Nigerian immigrant faced with huge costs after giving birth to triplets, one of whom died, is aided by Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, one of seven New York charities supported by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rosalyn Utti was ecstatic in the spring of 1997 when she found out she was pregnant. But when the sonogram showed she was carrying triplets, she feared that maybe it was too much of a good thing.</p>
        <p>She remembered how difficult and expensive it had been for her mother to raise two sets of twin boys in her village in Nigeria.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rosalyn Utti was ecstatic in the spring of 1997 when she found out she was pregnant. But when the sonogram showed she was carrying triplets, she feared that maybe it was too much of a good thing.</p>
        <p>She remembered how difficult and expensive it had been for her mother to raise two sets of twin boys in her village in Nigeria.</p>
        <p>At 34, living in Brooklyn with few relatives nearby, Mrs. Utti could not imagine how she would afford to care for her own children. Although she was college-educated and had been a nurse in Nigeria, Mrs. Utti was still waiting for her working papers four years after she had moved to the United States.</p>
        <p>Her husband, Luke, had been here since 1979, and worked full time as a case manager for mentally ill patients at the Institute for Community Living. But his salary barely covered the costs of feeding their young son, Obi, and the rent on their apartment.</p>
        <p>After carrying the children for 21 weeks, Mrs. Utti suffered from premature contractions and had to spend six weeks at Kings County Hospital.</p>
        <p>On Nov. 8, 1997, doctors performed a Caesarean section, and Rosalyn, Shirley and Vivian entered the world. Together, the triplets weighed almost as much as one healthy baby.</p>
        <p>Shirley and Vivian gradually gained weight and went home after six weeks, but Rosalyn never did. She died at the age of two months without ever having left the incubator.</p>
        <p>While they coped with Rosalyn's death, the Uttis had to find ways to support their living children.</p>
        <p>So, like other new parents, the Uttis gathered their resources to provide for their expanded family. But the Uttis had to buy twice as many supplies as typical parents. The challenge was formidable, but they were not discouraged.</p>
        <p>''I knew that with hard work, we'd find a way,'' Mr. Utti said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Utti shopped carefully and Mr. Utti took on an extra shift at work, adding the midnight to 8 A.M. shift on Sundays to his regular hours.</p>
        <p>Still, the family did not have enough money.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Utti's co-workers saw the strain on his face, and gave him the phone number for the Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, one of the seven New York charities supported by The New York Times</p>
        <p>Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>The federation, which coordinates the charitable efforts of 260 agencies in New York City, helps people work through emergency situations so that they can support themselves once more.</p>
        <p>Once the Uttis documented their problems and demonstrated that they would be able to provide for their family in the future, the federation used $800 from the Neediest Cases Fund to buy two crib sets and a double stroller, said Judy Milone, director of client services.</p>
        <p>''That young family was psychologically overwhelmed by the loss of a child,'' Ms. Milone said, ''and financially overwhelmed by a multiple birth, and we were glad to be able to help.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Utti said: ''I was so grateful. I had no idea how we were going to survive.'' Not only did the family survive, it thrived. Shirley and Vivian developed at a steady rate, crawling at six months and trying to stand before their first birthday.</p>
        <p>And though the Uttis are still struggling financially, they say they feel encouraged.</p>
        <p>''I am confident,'' said Mr. Utti, ''that one day we will be helping others.''</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to P.O. Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087, or any of these  organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE  285 Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK  1011 First Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS  191 Joralemon Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK  105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES  281 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK  Church Street Station, P.O. Box 4100, New York, N.Y. 10261-4100</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on Federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded $1,624,957.75  Recorded last week $92,978.00</p>
        <p>Total $1,717,935.75</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
