<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Profits From Risky Customers</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="507273"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MAIL ORDER COMPANIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FINGERHUT COMPANIES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAPIRO, EBEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mail Order Companies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DC1338F930A25751C0A964958260" item-length="1061" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Profits From Risky Customers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EBEN SHAPIRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHAPIRO, EBEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mail-order shopping is largely a pursuit of the affluent, with companies like J. Peterman offering a $33 leather-brimmed baseball hat described as a "treasure."</p>
        <p>But the Fingerhut Companies is making large profits pursuing customers that most cataloguers would not waste postage on. In fact, Fingerhut has grown into the nation's fourth-largest mail-order company by serving customers who on average have a household income of $24,000, about $5,000 less than the national average.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mail-order shopping is largely a pursuit of the affluent, with companies like J. Peterman offering a $33 leather-brimmed baseball hat described as a "treasure."</p>
        <p>But the Fingerhut Companies is making large profits pursuing customers that most cataloguers would not waste postage on. In fact, Fingerhut has grown into the nation's fourth-largest mail-order company by serving customers who on average have a household income of $24,000, about $5,000 less than the national average.</p>
        <p>Selling goods on monthly installment plans, the company last year shipped enough $100 leather skirts, $150 gold rings in the shape of dolphins and $9.99 porcelain unicorn night lights to take in $1.4 billion in revenues.</p>
        <p>Analysts said Fingerhut was one of the few cataloguers to show an increase in profits in 1991, a dismal year for most retailers. Last year, earnings climbed 12 percent, to $53.6 million; the year before, earnings rose 21 percent.</p>
        <p>The stock of the Minneapolis-based company hit a 52-week high of $34.375 yesterday, up 50 cents from the previous day, on the New York Stock Exchange. Its 52-week low is $20.25, posted in February of last year.</p>
        <p>"We can maneuver through recessionary times," said Theodore Deikel, the chairman and chief executive.</p>
        <p>Fingerhut's success is built on selling merchandise on credit to shoppers who cannot get credit anywhere else. A few years ago, an issuer of Visa credit cards mailed applications to a sampling of Fingerhut's 13 million customers; 97 percent of the applicants were rejected as bad credit risks.</p>
        <p>So, Fingerhut sells more than 99 percent of its products on the installment plan. Its catalogues show a department-store range of products from black lingerie ($5.09 a month) to brass crucifixes ($4.69 a month) to air pumps for inflating tires ($7.79 a month).</p>
        <p>Maria L. Fernandez, a 53-year-old resident of Astoria, Queens, is still using the 127-piece flatware set she bought from Fingerhut nearly 20 years ago for $30. "They make it so easy with the payments," she said. Analyzing the Risk</p>
        <p>After 44 years in business, Fingerhut has developed a sophisticated system to filter out bad credit risks. To glean clues, Fingerhut painstakingly analyzes the order form filled out by first-time customers. If a customer uses a pencil rather than a pen to order a color television, a red flag goes up. Failure to include a middle initial is another strike. Deadbeats often print, rather than sign, their names on the signature line, Fingerhut has learned over the years. Not having a home phone is another bad sign.</p>
        <p>The company also uses traditional credit reports in making a final judgment about a customer.</p>
        <p>Another way Fingerhut covers its risk is with monthly installment prices that translate into an effective annual interest rate of 24 percent, estimates Carol M. Clark, an analyst with John G. Kinnard &amp; Company in Minneapolis.</p>
        <p>But analysts say the company does not make money as a financing operation. The high interest rate is needed to cover an equally high number of bad debts. Last year, the company set aside about 13.6 percent of its sales to cover bills it could not collect. In contrast, Mastercard International said 4.86 percent of its charges went bad in the third quarter of 1991; for all of 1990, Mastercard's bad-debt experience was 3.61 percent, a rate typical of the credit card industry.</p>
        <p>Wall Street has been concerned that Fingerhut's customer base makes the company vulnerable to increased bad debts in hard economic times. To allay those fears, Fingerhut deliberately ratcheted down its bad-debt level to 13.6 percent of sales in 1991, compared with 15 percent the year before. The company raised its credit standards and rejected more potential customers.</p>
        <p>"We manage our bad debt, the economy doesn't," said Michael E. Qualen, the chief financial officer. "We wanted to prove that this year." An Uncrowded Market</p>
        <p>Fingerhut does not have a lot of competition in the mailbox. "The vast majority of catalogue retailers chase the upscale market," said Ms. Clark, the analyst. She said the typical Sears, J. C. Penney or Spiegel mail-order customer earns considerably more than a Fingerhut customer.</p>
        <p>"The higher the income, the greater the propensity to shop by mail or phone," said Chester Dalzell, a spokesman for the Direct Marketing Association, a trade group in New York. Mr. Dalzell said time-pressed two-income couples like the convenience of shopping while lounging in bed or watching television.</p>
        <p>Despite its strong perfomance, Fingerhut's shares have a far lower price-earnings ratio than other mail-order retailers. The ratio, the price of a stock divided by its earnings per share, is a good measure of how investors view a stock's growth potential.</p>
        <p>"This company is calling on a client base that is difficult for a lot of us to identify with," Ms. Clark said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Deikel, the company's chairman, said : "You get the feeling that some people are elitist. Typically, our customer base does not get a lot of respect."</p>
        <p>That may begin to change as Fingerhut sets its sights on a slightly more affluent customer base through a joint venture with Montgomery Ward &amp; Company. Last year, the two companies formed Montgomery Ward Direct to mail catalogues to Ward's 10 million credit card customers. Ward's chairman, Bernard F. Brennan, has said he expects the venture to be a $500 million business by 1995.</p>
        <p>Fingerhut is working to improve the quality of its merchandise, some of which has been somewhat shoddy in the past. Fingerhut recently appeared near the bottom of a Consumer Report customer satisfication survey on mail-order companies. Ms. Clark, the analyst, said the towels carried by Fingerhut several years ago let through more light than a window.</p>
        <p>About 72 percent of its merchandise is name-brand products like Sony Walkmans or Kitchen Aid mixers, up from 65 percent name-brand goods two years ago.</p>
        <p>Toasters, blenders and other housewares account for nearly 20 percent of Fingerhut sales. Electronics, including Pioneer car stereos and Yamaha electronic drum pads, make up 17 percent of sales.</p>
        <p>Fingerhut first offered shares, with an initial price of $16.50 each, in 1990, when it was spun off from the Primerica Corporation, a financial-services company. Primerica still owns about 40 percent of Fingerhut, but is gradually reducing its stake.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
