<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tax-Exempt Yields Decline in a Reversal</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="507267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="CONSUMER RATES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MONEY MARKET FUNDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOWLER, ELIZABETH M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920213T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DC1438F930A25751C0A964958260" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tax-Exempt Yields Decline in a Reversal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH M. FOWLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FOWLER, ELIZABETH M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The yields on tax-exempt funds reversed and moved down a little for the week ended Monday, according to IBC/Donoghue's Money Fund Report. Taxable funds continued their decline for the period ended Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Walter Frank, economist for Donoghue's, said: "There was some movement by investors in the latest week into tax-exempt funds as indicated by a sharp increase in their asset value to a record level. But as these yields decline, we will probably see demand for the tax frees slacken unless the Federal Reserve eases."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The yields on tax-exempt funds reversed and moved down a little for the week ended Monday, according to IBC/Donoghue's Money Fund Report. Taxable funds continued their decline for the period ended Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Walter Frank, economist for Donoghue's, said: "There was some movement by investors in the latest week into tax-exempt funds as indicated by a sharp increase in their asset value to a record level. But as these yields decline, we will probably see demand for the tax frees slacken unless the Federal Reserve eases."</p>
        <p>As for the taxable yields, Mr. Frank said their decline had continued longer than expected, adding that most of the decline in taxable yields was in anticipation of further Federal Reserve easing. "We think the odds favor the easing, but it is not a sure bet," he said.</p>
        <p>The seven-day compound average yield for the tax-exempt funds dropped to 2.81 percent from 2.95 percent, a decline of 14 basis points, while the seven-day simple yield dropped to 2.77 percent from 2.91, also 14 basis points. A basis point is a hundredth of a percentage point.</p>
        <p>In the same period, the 30-day compound yield dropped 10 basis points, to 2.82, and the 30-day simple yield dropped to 2.78, also a decline of 10 basis points. Top Performers</p>
        <p>The top Connecticut fund again was Fidelity Spartan Connecticut Municipal Money Market Portfolio, which reported a seven-day compound yield of 3.35 percent, the same as the previous week.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, the top fund again was Fidelity Spartan N.J. Municipal Money Market Portfolio, with a yield that held steady at 3.46 percent.</p>
        <p>In New York, the top fund again was Salomon Brothers N.Y. Municipal Money Market fund. It had a seven-day compounded yield of 3.74 percent, down slightly from 3.77 percent a week earlier.</p>
        <p>Assets of the tax-exempt funds, which have been declining, reversed course and rose sharply by $1.8 billion, to record of $98.9 billion.</p>
        <p>Donoghue's said the average number of days to maturity of securities held in the tax-free portfolios dropped to 50 days from 51.</p>
        <p>Of the funds monitored by Donoghue's with assets larger than $100 million, the Strong Municipal Money Market Fund, Milwaukee, continued to lead the way, with a seven-day compounded yield of 3.73 percent, down from 3.84 percent a week ago.  Taxable Funds</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, assets of the taxable funds rose sharply by $5.4 billion, to $509.7 billion, a record, and Mr. Frank noted that the average days to maturity of holdings in the taxable funds rose by a day, to 57 days.</p>
        <p>The average seven-day compounded taxable yield was down 8 basis points, to 3.92 percent, while the seven-day simple yield fell 7 basis points, to 3.85 percent, down from 3.92 percent.</p>
        <p>The 30-day compounded yield declined to 4.05 percent, down 9 basis points, and the 30-day simple yield dropped to 3.97 percent, also a decline of 9 basis points.</p>
        <p>The taxable fund with the best seven-day compound return for the week was again the Fidelity Spartan Money Market fund, with a yield of of 4.65 percent, compared with 4.83 percent a week ago.</p>
        <p>By comparison, the average bank money market account, a prime competitor of money funds, was at 3.78 percent, according to The Bank Rate Monitor's national index.</p>
        <p>CONSUMER RATES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
