<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>House Speaker Offers Words of Hope for New Orleans</title>
    <meta content="04tour" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/04/politics/04tour.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1744044"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Saulny, Susan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hastert, J Dennis (Speaker)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dams and Dikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Orleans (La)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Hastert, J Dennis</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DA1431F937A35750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="533" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>House Speaker Offers Words of Hope for New Orleans</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">House Speaker Offers Hope for New Orleans</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN SAULNY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Saulny, Susan</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, March 3</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>House Speaker J Dennis Hastert, six months after he said it did not make sense to rebuild parts of New Orleans, visits city and says we want to make sure that levees are safe and that system is foolproof (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six months after he said it did not make sense to rebuild parts of New Orleans, Speaker J. Dennis Hastert stood amid the rubble of the Lower Ninth Ward on Friday and, in a reversal, spoke words of comfort.</p>
        <p>''I think you have to be here firsthand on the ground to see the impact,'' Mr. Hastert, an Illinois Republican, said while standing on the banks of a breached levee that allowed a surge of water to wipe away a swath of the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Six months after he said it did not make sense to rebuild parts of New Orleans, J. Dennis Hastert, the speaker of the House, reversed his stance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Six months after he said it did not make sense to rebuild parts of New Orleans, Speaker J. Dennis Hastert stood amid the rubble of the Lower Ninth Ward on Friday and, in a reversal, spoke words of comfort.</p>
        <p>''I think you have to be here firsthand on the ground to see the impact,'' Mr. Hastert, an Illinois Republican, said while standing on the banks of a breached levee that allowed a surge of water to wipe away a swath of the city.</p>
        <p>''We want to make sure these edifices are safe and that the system is foolproof,'' he said, so that New Orleans does not have to ''relive this nightmare over again.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hastert and Representative Nancy Pelosi of California, the House Democratic leader, arrived in New Orleans on Thursday with a 34-member Congressional delegation on a fact-finding tour of the section of the Gulf Coast devastated by Hurricane Katrina. Louisiana officials took advantage of the opportunity to urge support for President Bush's proposed aid package.</p>
        <p>''We are extremely dependent on your good graces and understanding,'' Gov. Kathleen Babineaux Blanco said.''We ask for your mercy and plead for your help.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hastert made no commitments, but said that he was most interested in making sure taxpayers' money would be well spent and that people would not be in harm's way again.</p>
        <p>Ms. Pelosi was blunter, saying, ''I'm not absolutely certain that our federal agencies on the ground here are meeting that challenge.''</p>
        <p>In the Ninth Ward, the delegation was greeted on Friday by about three dozen protesters who were angry about what they called Mr. Hastert's slow pace in getting to New Orleans. The speaker's visit came after tours of the city by the Prince of Wales and the king of Jordan.</p>
        <p>When the Congressional leaders said they were shocked by the extent of the flood devastation, the protesters said they should have expressed that feeling earlier.</p>
        <p>''You wouldn't be shocked if you had come sooner than six months,'' one protester, the Rev. Will McCadney, shouted toward the delegation.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCadney's congregation had been based in the Ninth Ward but is now scattered around the country. He said he had hoped to get answers from the delegation. But the protesters were kept about 100 yards from the officials.</p>
        <p>Later, Governor Blanco, Lt. Gov. Mitch Landrieu and others talked with the protesters.''Why did it take six months for them to come see us?'' Mr. McCadney asked. ''That's too long. I feel bewildered, left. Forgotten.''</p>
        <p>Asked about his earlier comments about not rebuilding New Orleans, Mr. Hastert said, ''I think that was a misrepresentation of what I said. I said, Before you rebuild New Orleans, you have to make sure the people are not in harm's way.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
