<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>METRO DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="781350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDA163EF93AA3575BC0A963958260" item-length="534" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>METRO DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WELFARE RULES ALSO AFFECT RURAL POOR</p>
        <p>In Friendship, N.Y., where oil barons lived in splendor 100 years ago, today an estimated 1 in 6 households is on welfare and 1 in 4 is poor, about the same percentages as in Brooklyn. Yet amid this year's vigorous push in Albany to change the state's welfare rules, there was little discussion of the problems that afflict the rural poor.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WELFARE RULES ALSO AFFECT RURAL POOR</p>
        <p>In Friendship, N.Y., where oil barons lived in splendor 100 years ago, today an estimated 1 in 6 households is on welfare and 1 in 4 is poor, about the same percentages as in Brooklyn. Yet amid this year's vigorous push in Albany to change the state's welfare rules, there was little discussion of the problems that afflict the rural poor.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>DOCTOR CONVICTED IN ABORTION DEATH</p>
        <p>A Queens obstetrician was convicted of killing a woman who went to him for an abortion, making him the first doctor in New York State found guilty of murder stemming from the medical mistreatment of a patient.  [ A1. ] NEW YORK CITY  A DRIVING RANGE FOR CHELSEA</p>
        <p>The golf driving range that Shinya Muto built just outside Kobe, Japan, was still standing after an earthquake leveled the city. So there's no reason to be concerned, Mr. Muto said through an interpreter, about the one being erected on Pier 59, jutting out into the Hudson River at 17th Street.  [ B3. ] INTERNATIONAL PLOT SEEN IN ABDUCTION</p>
        <p>Two Chinese immigrants held captive for 13 days in a Brooklyn basement were freed and their abductors were captured, the police said, after an around-the-clock investigation of an international kidnapping-for-ransom plot.  [ B3. ] FEWER CHILDREN IN TROUBLED HOMES DIE</p>
        <p>Twenty-five children whose troubled families were known to New York City child protection officials died in 1994, the lowest number of such deaths since 1985, according to a report.  [ B3. ] VINDICATION SEEN IN SUIT AGAINST UNION</p>
        <p>For four years, Carlos Guzman fought a lonely battle against one of the biggest unions in New York City. Last week, Mr. Guzman won a measure of vindication when a Federal jury awarded him $100,000 in compensatory damages for emotional distress.  [ B2. ] REGION  TRAVELING WITH A PAROLE OFFICER</p>
        <p>The ex-convict shifted uneasily in a chair, pulled on a cigarette and exhaled a soft blanket of smoke, as though to cushion the hardness of the words Richard Novack was hurling his way. The stop was just one in a long day that took Mr. Novack, a longtime parole officer, across Middlesex County in New Jersey to check on parolees.  [ B5. ] LETTING PARAMEDICS PRACTICE ON CATS</p>
        <p>Governor Pataki announced that he had signed legislation that allows paramedics to practice inserting breathing tubes into the throats and lungs of live cats. The statute is intended to provide paramedics more realistic training in a treatment for children.  [ B5. ] BAR OWNER WANTS TO SUE A DRINKER</p>
        <p>An underage customer bought a drink in a bar in Middletown, Conn., and got off with a lecture from the police. The bar was forced to shut down for three days, losing an estimated $20,000. The bar's owner wants to sue the customer for damages.  [ B5. ]</p>
        <p>Federal regulators began an investigation into an incident at the Hope Creek nuclear power plant in which cooling water was misdirected for 19 hours before anyone noticed.  [ B5. ]</p>
        <p>Del Laboratories agreed to pay $1.185 million to settle a complaint that its chief executive had sexually harassed female employees, but many lawyers see nothing to cheer about.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Chronicle B4</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
