<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Next Step for Congress: Impeachment Decision</title>
    <meta content="Y22IMP$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1048479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE INQUIRY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Kenneth W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DE1130F931A1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1002" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Next Step for Congress: Impeachment Decision</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis of mood in Congress as nation watchs Pres Clinton's videotaped grand jury testimony; many Republican and Democratic members of Congress have already decided that Clinton lied under oath and are now debating whether that is grounds for impeachment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even as the nation watched President Clinton on videotape today, many members of Congress on both sides of the aisle had already decided that he lied under oath. Now the question, which Congress is already starting to debate, is whether that is grounds for impeachment. Kenneth W. Starr, the Whitewater independent counsel, certainly seemed to think so. In his report to Congress, he held that perjury and obstruction of justice by any citizen ''are profoundly serious matters'' and that ''when such acts are committed by the President of the United States, we believe these acts 'may constitute grounds for an impeachment.' ''</p>
        <p>But the Constitution's description of an impeachable offense as treason, bribery and other ''high crimes and misdemeanors'' is subject to continual reinterpretation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even as the nation watched President Clinton on videotape today, many members of Congress on both sides of the aisle had already decided that he lied under oath. Now the question, which Congress is already starting to debate, is whether that is grounds for impeachment. Kenneth W. Starr, the Whitewater independent counsel, certainly seemed to think so. In his report to Congress, he held that perjury and obstruction of justice by any citizen ''are profoundly serious matters'' and that ''when such acts are committed by the President of the United States, we believe these acts 'may constitute grounds for an impeachment.' ''</p>
        <p>But the Constitution's description of an impeachable offense as treason, bribery and other ''high crimes and misdemeanors'' is subject to continual reinterpretation.</p>
        <p>That constitutional ambiguity has sent Congress looking through precedent, law, public opinion polls and Mr. Clinton's parsings to decide whether his attempt to cover up his affair with Monica S. Lewinsky should bring his removal from office.</p>
        <p>Representative Charles T. Canady, a Florida Republican, said today: ''The President cannot go before a grand jury and say things that are not true. What will happen to the rule of law if he did that?''</p>
        <p>But he is only one member of the House Judiciary Committee, which is in the vanguard of impeachment deliberations. And while many members of the committee now say they are certain to recommend that the House open an impeachment inquiry, the spectrum among its 37 members shows that the ultimate decision on whether to impeach Mr. Clinton is not likely to be clear or easy.</p>
        <p>It may be the preponderant view in Congress that Mr. Clinton lied. But is that perjury? Not every committee member agrees. Nor do all members of the Judiciary Committee put the same weight on the President's deposition in the sexual harassment case brought by Paula Corbin Jones as on the four hours of grand jury testimony, which was broadcast today. In fact, some members of Congress are asking whether a perjury case based on Mr. Clinton's Jones deposition is one that most prosecutors would bring to court.</p>
        <p>Representative Lindsey O. Graham, a South Carolina Republican, draws a distinction, for example, between Mr. Clinton's testimony before the grand jury and his earlier deposition in the Jones case. The Jones civil case was ultimately dismissed.</p>
        <p>''That's always bothered me,'' said Mr. Graham, a Judiciary Committee member who was once an Air Force prosecutor. ''Would I as a prosecutor spend time and money to prosecute a guy who lies in a deposition in a case that was dismissed?</p>
        <p>''My goal is to set the standard that if the average citizen engaged in like conduct they would have severe legal consequences.''</p>
        <p>Representative Bill McCollum of Florida, one of Mr. Graham's Republican colleagues, does not share his qualms about the Jones deposition. ''I have no doubt in my mind, based on other cases,'' Mr. McCollum said, ''that it doesn't make any difference if the case was thrown out.''</p>
        <p>Yet on the other side, Representative Jerrold Nadler, Democrat of New York, is not even certain that a prosecutor would bring a perjury case against Mr. Clinton based on the grand jury testimony.</p>
        <p>''It's, 'he said, she said,' '' Mr. Nadler said. He noted that Mr. Starr had presumed that Ms. Lewinsky had been the one telling the truth when her testimony deviated from the President's. ''It's all based on Monica Lewinsky's testimony,'' he said. While Mr. Starr found that Ms. Lewinsky's testimony matched contemporaneous accounts she gave to 11 friends of her affair, Mr. Nadler said that she may have been exaggerating to all her friends.</p>
        <p>To sort through precedent and the Framers' intent, the Republican and Democratic staffs of the Judiciary Committee have independently given their members extensive legal research. The panel's members say they are studying the writings of legal scholars, the report on impeachment drawn up by the Judiciary Committee staff in the Watergate proceedings and other documents.  But impeachment proceedings have been so infrequent that even these materials can lead to different interpretations.</p>
        <p>Representative Zoe Lofgren, Democrat of California, who was an aide to the House Judiciary Committee in 1974, has posted on her Web site the 1974 report on Constitutional Grounds for Presidential Impeachment. In a sign of her own thinking, she pointed her constituents toward its observations and its conclusion as ''pretty relevant today.''</p>
        <p>''Not all Presidential misconduct is sufficient to constitute grounds for an impeachment,'' that 1974 report concluded. ''Because impeachment of a President is a grave step for the nation, it is predicated only upon conduct seriously incompatible with either the constitutional form and principles of our government or the proper performance of constitutional duties of Presidential office.''</p>
        <p>That might seem to suggest that evasions about illicit sex would not rise to the level of impeachment. But Mr. Canady looks elsewhere for a model: the precedent set by Congress in the impeachment and conviction of Judge Walter L. Nixon of Federal District Court in Mississippi in 1989 for perjury.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nixon had been criminally convicted of lying to a grand jury about his talks with a prosecutor in a marijuana-smuggling case. He had been accused of concealing his attempt to help the son of a business partner. ''He was impeached and removed from office because he committed perjury,'' Mr. Canady said, ''and the interesting thing is he committed perjury before a grand jury on matters where if he simply told the truth there would have been no legal responsibility.''</p>
        <p>Should a judicial impeachment be considered relevant to a President? Federal judges are not elected but under the Constitution have lifetime tenure subject to ''good behavior'' in office. ''It's certainly the case that impeaching a judge and impeaching a President has two different standards,'' said Representative Barney Frank, Democrat of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>THE TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE INQUIRY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
