<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Yanks Are Seeing The Magic Reappear</title>
    <meta content="15NYNY$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="877604"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toronto Blue Jays</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Claire</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDB123AF936A2575AC0A960958260" item-length="1007" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Yanks Are Seeing The Magic Reappear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Claire</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Sept. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Toronto Blue Jay, 3-1; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The luck is back.</p>
        <p>That was the feeling that radiated throughout a chipper Yankees clubhouse after the team not only defeated the Toronto Blue Jays, 3-1, today but won other victories, both tangible and intangible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The luck is back.</p>
        <p>That was the feeling that radiated throughout a chipper Yankees clubhouse after the team not only defeated the Toronto Blue Jays, 3-1, today but won other victories, both tangible and intangible.</p>
        <p>Not only did the Yankees defeat the tough Pat Hentgen to maintain their three-and-a-half game lead over second-place Baltimore, which came from behind to beat Detroit, 7-6. The Yankees also won on an afternoon when they lost another starting pitcher -- Kenny Rogers -- because of niggling injuries.</p>
        <p>The show of heart found was found not only in Rogers, who is obviously ailing more than many thought, but also in a relief corps that has added yet another important cog in Brian Boehringer; and a lineup that suddenly remembers how to snatch victory from what looks to be certain defeat.</p>
        <p>These discoveries couldn't have come at a better time. For the Yankees used the inspirational performances to win their fifth straight, tying a season high last achieved July 1-6.</p>
        <p>It all left the Yankees buoyed, even though they now know that yet another starter is hurting. Manager Joe Torre labeled Rogers's left shoulder inflamed. But Torre said he still expected to start him Thursday at Yankee Stadium, against those pesky Orioles.</p>
        <p>''Kenny's fine,'' Torre said. There is still some waiting to be done, the manager acknowledged, but ''if he's O.K., he'll start.'' It was a vote of confidence Rogers had not received since Sept. 1, when a 10-8 record, a 5.00 earned run average and a streak without a victory dating to Aug. 12 led Torre to unceremoniously bounce him from the rotation.</p>
        <p>And if Rogers can't go? ''With 15 games to go, I'm not going to be concerned about how many starters we have,'' said Torre, who earlier this weekend scratched an ailing Dwight Gooden from a start Sunday. We'll have enough people to play every game.''</p>
        <p>People like Boehringer, the onetime struggling starter turned surprisingly stingy reliever. Called on in the fifth inning when Rogers was lifted, Boehringer pitched three scoreless innings of relief, striking out five. It was good enough to give the Yankees time to fathom Hentgen, who had allowed but two runners to get into scoring position in the first seven innings.</p>
        <p>Hentgen struck out the first two batters in the eighth, then watched consecutive doubles by Bernie Williams and Paul O'Neill tie the game at 1-1.</p>
        <p>Cecil Fielder, the designated hitter whose infrequent heroics had helped drop the Yankees into doldrums last month and had no hits in three previous at-bats against Hentgen, stepped in. And to the Yankees' relief, Fielder delivered a run-scoring hit, his fifth run batted in on the Yankees' five-game-old road trip.</p>
        <p>With the lead, the Yankees turned the game over to Mariano Rivera, who worked his magic on the high wire in the eighth. After allowing a leadoff single to Tomas Perez, then a sacrifice, Rivera got Jacob Brumfield to look at a third strike, then Juan Samuel to ground to second. The play was turned superbly by Mariano Duncan.</p>
        <p>Duncan later contributed a double to a one-run ninth against Hentgen. Borrowing from a formula that initially made winning streaks seem routine, Rivera turned the game over to John Wetteland in the ninth and the Yankees' top reliever put an exclamation point on save No. 41 by striking out Joe Carter, Ed Sprague and John Olerud.</p>
        <p>Torre was not only satisfied with Boehringer and the rally, but with what he got out of Rogers. The left-hander had allowed but four hits and one run, on an r.b.i. double by Sprague in the fourth in Rogers's first start in 13 days.</p>
        <p>But then Torre said he noticed that the pitcher began to drag his arm in an at-bat against Carter in the fourth. Rogers went back out in the fifth and had the count at 1-2 against Alex Gonzalez. But when Torre saw the arm continue to drag, he yanked the pitcher, saying, ''I just didn't like what I saw.''</p>
        <p>That the Yankees were discussing Rogers's well-being at this point in the season underscores the intrigue that has surrounded the pitcher and his relationship with the manager all season.</p>
        <p>Before the game, when asked whether Rogers was healthy, Torre said flatly: ''Right from spring training we haven't been . . . I hate to use the word 'honest,' but it's 'I can pitch, I can pitch,' which leaves some questions unanswered.''</p>
        <p>After the four-inning outing, when asked whether Rogers has a bad shoulder, Torre said, ''He won't own up to anything.'' Neither will Torre, apparently. When he was asked if Rogers had received any cortisone injections in that shoulder of late, Torre smiled and said, ''I have no comment -- in lieu of lying.''</p>
        <p>Rogers? Now he'll admit that the shoulder has been uncomfortable since early in the season -- a revelation in itself. But in his mind, this shouldn't cost him starts. ''I've pitched with tired stuff before. Today was better than most.''</p>
        <p>What treatments Rogers has had other than ultrasound and anti-inflammatory medications he won't say. ''It's just a bunch of stuff, too much for my taste,'' Rogers said cryptically. ''I don't like to go into the trainer's room.''</p>
        <p>Especially now, with the Yankees so enticingly close to the playoffs, a place Rogers has yet to visit. Even if it means risk of further injury.  ''What's your career if you don't ever get into the playoffs?'' Rogers asked. ''If there was something I couldn't deal with, I would tell them.''</p>
        <p>That attitude has at last won the admiration of Torre. ''He's a tough kid,'' Torre said. ''I appreciate what he gave me.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
