<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kitchens of Doom</title>
    <meta content="15OWENLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CD-ROM's" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="877258"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="CD-ROM's"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cd-Rom (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Muppet CD-ROM, The</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">CD-ROM (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DA1E3BF936A2575AC0A960958260" item-length="766" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kitchens of Doom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Owen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Owen reviews The Muppet CD-ROM; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE MUPPET CD-ROM  Muppets Inside.  (Windows.)  Bellevue, Wash.:  Starwave Corporation and Jim Henson Interactive. $19.95.</p>
        <p>When ''The Muppet CD-ROM'' arrived at my house, I handed the unopened box to my 8-year-old son and asked him to take it for a test drive. He disappeared into his subterranean computer complex and remained there for most of the rest of the day. Shortly before dinner, he emerged to pronounce the program ''awesome.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE MUPPET CD-ROM  Muppets Inside.  (Windows.)  Bellevue, Wash.:  Starwave Corporation and Jim Henson Interactive. $19.95.</p>
        <p>When ''The Muppet CD-ROM'' arrived at my house, I handed the unopened box to my 8-year-old son and asked him to take it for a test drive. He disappeared into his subterranean computer complex and remained there for most of the rest of the day. Shortly before dinner, he emerged to pronounce the program ''awesome.''</p>
        <p>When I tried it myself, a few weeks later, I was quickly transformed into one of those comic-strip dads who can't handle any piece of technology more modern than a pencil sharpener. The CD-ROM's setup program didn't like the graphics accelerator on my computer, and it disagreed with my decision not to install a couple of seemingly extraneous multimedia drivers when I upgraded to Windows 95. But I eventually got everything straightened out. Best of all, I didn't have to ask my son for help.</p>
        <p>Adults should be warned that the first act of the successfully installed ''Muppet CD-ROM'' is to simulate a computer crash. The picture disappears and a menacing electronic tone blares from the speakers, leaving the frightened grown-up to assume that he's just incinerated his silicon chips. But then Fozzie Bear pries open the frozen image on the screen as if it were a balky curtain, and Kermit says, ''I thought computers were supposed to make life better, not worse.'' The Muppets thus cleverly introduce their program's theme, which is that they themselves are trapped inside your computer, and it's up to you -- or, more likely, your children -- to get them out.</p>
        <p>To free the Muppets, a player must travel (on a ''data bus'') through the computer's supposedly garbled circuitry, reassembling fragmented files and programs by playing and winning various games. My favorite game is the Swedish Chef's Kitchens of Doom, a parody of an immensely popular and bloodthirsty computer game called Doom. In the Muppet version (an accompanying brochure explains), ''the Swedish Chef confronts a cornucopia of angry groceries out to avenge his abusive food-preparation techniques.''</p>
        <p>The chef's arsenal consists not of submachine guns, grenade launchers and plasma rays -- weapons of choice in the original Doom -- but eggbeaters, rolling pins, whisks and similar utensils. The game appeals to youthful bloodlust without seeming to be the work of the Devil. The only danger, I suppose, is that the vegetable version may arouse an uninitiated child's curiosity about the original.</p>
        <p>Among the other Muppet games, I also got a kick out of one called Beaker's Brain. In it, the player is shown a series of images lifted from the befuddled Muppet's scrambled cerebrum and asked to arrange them in the proper sequence. Once reassembled, the images turn into a film clip. As with the other games on ''The Muppet CD-ROM,'' you can skip over the introduction and the filler by clicking the left mouse button -- a useful feature for anyone whose patience with Muppet humor is finite.</p>
        <p>''The Muppet CD-ROM'' is, among other things, an anthology of brief Muppet bits, including one of Milton Berle being slammed in the face with a pillow-sized powder puff. A player can replay favorite clips from completed games by visiting the Memory Bank and making selections on the Cache Machine. True Kermit fans can also use a feature called the Muppetizer to equip their computers with Muppet-based cursors, sounds and desktop backgrounds. (Oddly, there is no Muppet screen saver.)</p>
        <p>My only complaint about this disk is that the parts don't live up to the package. Strip away the puns and the 10-second film clips and you're left with a handful of simplistic games that wouldn't attract many customers if they were sold separately. The clever thing about Kitchens of Doom is the joke, not the execution. The Swedish Chef is harder to maneuver than the protagonist of a real shoot-'em-up game, and the great big carrots are too easy to kill. I chuckled the first time, but I have no overpowering urge to play it again.</p>
        <p>Still, ''The Muppet CD-ROM'' has enough features to keep a child occupied on a rainy afternoon. That is more than can be said for most of the stuff at our house.</p>
        <p>CD-ROM's  David Owen's most recent book is ''My Usual Game: Adventures in Golf.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">David Owen's most recent book is ''My Usual Game: Adventures in Golf.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
