<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Career in Advertising, but Still With a Wicked Streak</title>
    <meta content="24HEFF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/24/arts/television/24heff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1674912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heffernan, Virginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccarthy, Jenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Larice, Marcelle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moore, Christina</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bad Girl's Guide, The (Tv Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Upn</org>
        <org class="online_producer">MTV Networks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Playboy</org>
        <person class="online_producer">McCarthy, Jenny</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Phair, Liz</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Diaz, Cameron</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DC1239F937A15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Career in Advertising, but Still With a Wicked Streak</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A New Career in Advertising, but Still With a Wicked Streak</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Virginia Heffernan reviews sitcom The Bad Girl's Guide starring Jenny McCarthy, Marcelle Larice and Christina Moore; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was something ace about Jenny McCarthy in the 1990's. On ''Singled Out'' she was so brash, so crass, so great-looking, so expertly just-shy-of-annoying. Or maybe she was annoying sometimes. But she was good at comedic saves, too; if you were annoyed, she made you think it was your problem and why didn't you know how to have fun? With her Playmate of the Year looks and her flooring-it party-girl persona, she came off like a low-cal Liz Phair, and she was by far the best thing on MTV's squealy dating show.</p>
        <p>But since the days Ms. McCarthy spent as a high-flying television personality, which followed the days she spent as a high-flying Playboy Playmate of the Year, her career has been a series of good-natured misfires. She had some small movie roles, as well as a variety show on MTV and a sitcom on NBC, although neither lasted long. And though it seemed at times as if she should have been a full-on comic blond sensation -- did Cameron Diaz steal her career? -- she faltered, married, had a baby, disappeared.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jenny McCarthy is back, playing a boy-crazy advertising executive on a new sitcom airing on UPN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was something ace about Jenny McCarthy in the 1990's. On ''Singled Out'' she was so brash, so crass, so great-looking, so expertly just-shy-of-annoying. Or maybe she was annoying sometimes. But she was good at comedic saves, too; if you were annoyed, she made you think it was your problem and why didn't you know how to have fun? With her Playmate of the Year looks and her flooring-it party-girl persona, she came off like a low-cal Liz Phair, and she was by far the best thing on MTV's squealy dating show.</p>
        <p>But since the days Ms. McCarthy spent as a high-flying television personality, which followed the days she spent as a high-flying Playboy Playmate of the Year, her career has been a series of good-natured misfires. She had some small movie roles, as well as a variety show on MTV and a sitcom on NBC, although neither lasted long. And though it seemed at times as if she should have been a full-on comic blond sensation -- did Cameron Diaz steal her career? -- she faltered, married, had a baby, disappeared.</p>
        <p>But now she's back. She's filling the role of host on live shows, making appearances. Her book, ''Baby Laughs,'' about the first year of motherhood, is on the best-seller list, just above a memoir by Bob Dole. And her latest sitcom, ''The Bad Girl's Guide,'' starts tonight on UPN.</p>
        <p>There's no pleasure in reporting that it's another misfire, though typically good-natured. Tonight's episode is madcap but ultimately strident and not entertaining. As JJ, a boy-crazy advertising executive, Ms. McCarthy smiles wide, cavorts and cracks up with two friends, Holly (Marcelle Larice) and Sarah (Christina Moore), as she pushes deadlines, fantasizes about guys and gets high while working for a huffy boss.</p>
        <p>That's cool, that's bad. But the kooky dialogue, delivered in shrieks, falls flat. And JJ and her friends are far too pleased with themselves; they amplify the grating laugh track with so much deranged gaiety of their own that they seem to be crying for help.</p>
        <p>The advertising firm, at which JJ and Holly share an office tricked out with dot-com kindergarten décor (exercise balls, beanbags, cheery Macs), provides plenty of opportunities for the bad girls to blow off their work but keep their salaries and their reputations as geniuses by pulling something out at the last minute (in the case of tonight's episode, a detergent campaign they come up with while stoned).</p>
        <p>After hours, JJ and Holly coach softie Sarah on how to stand up to her thieving ex-boyfriend, while juggling prospective boyfriends of their own. Sweetly, each episode purports to offer a little moral, mostly about love. On tonight's, JJ proposes that ''the real deal is worth waiting for,'' only to be told, by Sarah, that sometimes a girl needs support from her friends even when she's dating the wrong guy. The story concludes with a plug for ''America's Next Top Model,'' another UPN show; the bad girls, it turns out, are big fans.</p>
        <p>Next week's episode is a little better, though it relies on gags about vibrators and cheap booze. What's nice about it comes at the end again. This time JJ learns a lesson about letting down her guard with a man. She trips, falls and locks her keys in her car after a wacky night, only to come across the obnoxious trend-forecaster who has been menacing her with talk of what-women-want for the entire episode. There's something genuine in the way she lets him call AAA for her. It's as though this act, Jenny McCarthy's decade-long act -- beautiful, raunchy, and above all loud -- might actually be difficult to maintain.</p>
        <p>The Bad Girl's Guide  UPN, tonight at 9:30, Eastern and Pacific times; 8:30, Central time.</p>
        <p>Robin Schiff, executive producer and show runner; Tony Krantz, executive producer; Cameron Tuttle, co-executive producer. Produced by Palm Tree Productions and Flame Television in association with Paramount Network Television.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jenny McCarthy (JJ), Marcelle Larice (Holly), Christina Moore (Sarah), Stephanie Childers (Irene), Johnathan McClain (Patric), Cedric Yarbrough (Kip), Christopher Gartin (Doug), Oscar Nunez (Melicio), John Balma (caterer), Matthew Garel (Rick).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
