<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Roll Over, Tchaikovsky: Roiling That Famed Lake</title>
    <meta content="24SWAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/24/arts/dance/24swan.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1674893"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BALLET REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carolina Ballet</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rockwell, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">North Carolina</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Carolina Ballet</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Weiss, Robert</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Tchaikovsky, Peter Ilyich</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E7DC1239F937A15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Roll Over, Tchaikovsky: Roiling That Famed Lake</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Roll Over, Tchaikovsky: Roiling That Famed Lake</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN ROCKWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rockwell, John</byline>
      <dateline>RALEIGH, N.C., May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Rockwell reviews Carolina Ballet performance of Robert Weiss version of Swan Lake; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Radical reinterpretations of ballet classics have not gone so far in this country as have operatic rethinkings in Europe. Yes, there was Matthew Bourne's male ''Swan Lake.'' But by and large, American ballet audiences want to take their classics straight. Even dowdy.</p>
        <p>Enter Robert Weiss. A former New York City Ballet dancer and director of the Pennsylvania Ballet, Mr. Weiss founded the Carolina Ballet seven years ago. It began modestly, with an annual budget of $2 million, and even with steady growth is now at only $4.3 million. It's a midsized regional company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Robert Weiss' "Swan Lake" may look conventional on the surface but is actually downright radical and bold.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Radical reinterpretations of ballet classics have not gone so far in this country as have operatic rethinkings in Europe. Yes, there was Matthew Bourne's male ''Swan Lake.'' But by and large, American ballet audiences want to take their classics straight. Even dowdy.</p>
        <p>Enter Robert Weiss. A former New York City Ballet dancer and director of the Pennsylvania Ballet, Mr. Weiss founded the Carolina Ballet seven years ago. It began modestly, with an annual budget of $2 million, and even with steady growth is now at only $4.3 million. It's a midsized regional company.</p>
        <p>Yet Mr. Weiss finally took it upon himself over the weekend -- the last of five sold-out performances at the 2,200-seat Raleigh Memorial Auditorium was Sunday afternoon -- to create a new ''Swan Lake.'' It looked conventional, on the surface: dreamy, attractive set designs and costumes; Tchaikovsky's music; classic ballet choreography; a swan maiden who seems to go over to the dark side; a handsome prince; an evil sorcerer; a white-clad lady swan corps; happy happy courtiers and peasants. Many in the audience seemed content that they were seeing a familiar ''Swan Lake,'' and in some ways rightly so.</p>
        <p>But right underneath the surface this was a downright radical undertaking. For better and for worse, it amounted to a bolder rethinking of this classic than ones with Petipa's choreography stuck onto some shocking modern setting.</p>
        <p>In his comments both in the program and in conversation, Mr. Weiss placed emphasis on his need to scale down the traditional staging to something manageable for a small company like his own -- and, he hopes, others of a similar size. Odette had eight swan girlfriends, not 24 or more. The orchestra of 34 (which played well under Alfred E. Sturgis's baton) was amplified more loudly than a full band twice its size would sound on its own. Jeff A.R. Jones's sets were handsome but painted on two-dimensional flats. The ballet was some 45 minutes shorter than usual.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weiss said he began to believe he could do ''Swan Lake'' when he came upon a children's-book version by an Austrian writer and illustrator, Lisbeth Zwerger. Mr. Jones's sets don't replicate Ms. Zwerger's designs, but they echo their feeling of wistful intimacy, with a nice use of blue silk to evoke the flood at the end and lovely, soft lighting by Ross Kolman throughout. David Heuvel's costumes suggest Romantic ballet, not the later short tutus seen in most productions today.</p>
        <p>So far, so unradical. But Mr. Weiss had more ideas than just rescaling the story. He builds up Rothbart's part into a real antithesis to the prince. The national dances in the ballroom scene are redistributed to the crowd. Music -- a lot of the music -- is shuffled from act to act. Petipa reshaped Tchaikovsky's score himself, but not to this extreme. It was like ''Swan Lake'' on random play.</p>
        <p>More crucial still, some 90 percent of the choreography, by Mr. Weiss's estimate, is by Mr. Weiss himself. Most ''Swan Lake'' choreographers build on Petipa and Ashton and Balanchine and everyone else who has contributed to ''Swan Lake'' tradition in sedimentary layers over the last 125 years. However much those influences have seeped into Mr. Weiss's subconscious, he struggles perhaps excessively to make this his ''Swan Lake.'' Even going so far as to jettison some particularly beloved bits, like the four cygnets and Odile's 32 fouettés. Along with their accompanying music, including what Tchaikovsky wrote for the famous pas de deux.</p>
        <p>Sometimes Mr. Weiss's musical cuts and reshufflings sound bizarre, familiar passages unaccountably missing in action or stuck into the sequence in odd places, the key sequences rattled and expectations flustered. Sometimes the music he uses instead does not quite fit, as in the sweeping swan waltz for the evil Rothbart or the Russian dance for the prince-Odile pas de deux.</p>
        <p>The choreography, on its own terms, is sometimes bland but often striking and rarely anachronistic, a couple of twisty, contemporary-European-looking interactions (which I liked) in the ballroom pas de deux being about the outer limit of experimentation. Mostly it's classic and appropriate, even when the accompanying music isn't.</p>
        <p>And the dancing was very good, blossoming in the choreography Mr. Weiss has tailored to his company's strengths. Lilyan Vigo was lovely and scary as Odette/Odile (here, the Swan Princess and the Sorcerer's Daughter). Timour Bourtasenkov preened a little but looked like a plausible, stalwart prince. Cyrille de la Barre made the most of his expanded opportunities as Rothbart.</p>
        <p>In the end, one was left impressed with the effectiveness of Mr. Weiss's vision if disoriented by the aggressiveness of his revisions. It might seem plausible to retain the intimacy and focus of this version while still sticking more humbly to the conventional sequence and not deliberately rejecting time-tested dances. Mr. Weiss would be an even more commanding auteur if, instead of fearing competition from the master choreographers of the past, he welcomed them into his own, overarching vision of this classic.</p>
        <p>BALLET REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
