<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MEMO PAD</title>
    <meta content="24MEMO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/24/business/24memo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1674946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Memo Pad"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Homeland Security Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE7D91239F937A15756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MEMO PAD</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Keeping Watch on the Watch Lists</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SHARKEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>KEEPING WATCH ON THE WATCH LISTS -- The government's bid to exempt from the Privacy Act portions of a vast new data bank, which includes information on blacklisted fliers, is coming under fire from corporate travel managers. The Association of Corporate Travel Managers began sounding out its members yesterday, and said that opposition is running 90 percent against the Homeland Security Department's plan to exclude from the protections of the privacy law its new compilation of data, including watch lists of suspect travelers kept by airlines and government agencies, as well as information about them drawn from both classified and public sources. The association says the change could make it even more difficult for travelers who share names with people on the lists to find out what the files say about them or to petition to correct errors. ''Exempting this new database from the Privacy Act will make an unwieldy resolution process virtually impossible,'' said Greeley Koch, the president of the trade group. The government says the data base needs to be confidential to protect national security and encourage information sharing among myriad agencies.</p>
        <p>WORK VS. PLAY -- Plan ahead, business travelers. ''Planes will be full this summer as Americans return to the skies,'' according to Suzanne Cook, vice president for research at the Travel Industry Association of America. The group predicts a 4 percent increase in air traffic over last year, and record spending of $633.5 billion on business and leisure travel in the United States for all of 2005, up from $600 billion. Hotels will be humming, too; PricewaterhouseCoopers forecasts that summer occupancy will be 71.4 percent, the highest since 2000, when the rate was 72.1 percent, and that room prices will rise an average of 4.5 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>KEEPING WATCH ON THE WATCH LISTS The government's bid to exempt from the Privacy Act portions of a vast new data bank, which includes information on blacklisted fliers, is coming under fire from corporate travel managers. The Association of Corporate Travel Managers began sounding out its members yesterday, and said that opposition is running 90 percent against the Homeland Security Department's plan to exclude from the protections of the privacy law its new compilation of data, including watch lists of suspect travelers kept by airlines and government agencies, as well as information about them drawn from both classified and public sources. The association says the change could make it even more difficult for travelers who share names with people on the lists to find out what the files say about them or to petition to correct errors. "Exempting this new database from the Privacy Act will make an unwieldy resolution process virtually impossible," said Greeley Koch, the president of the trade group. The government says the data base needs to be confidential to protect national security and encourage information sharing among myriad agencies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>KEEPING WATCH ON THE WATCH LISTS -- The government's bid to exempt from the Privacy Act portions of a vast new data bank, which includes information on blacklisted fliers, is coming under fire from corporate travel managers. The Association of Corporate Travel Managers began sounding out its members yesterday, and said that opposition is running 90 percent against the Homeland Security Department's plan to exclude from the protections of the privacy law its new compilation of data, including watch lists of suspect travelers kept by airlines and government agencies, as well as information about them drawn from both classified and public sources. The association says the change could make it even more difficult for travelers who share names with people on the lists to find out what the files say about them or to petition to correct errors. ''Exempting this new database from the Privacy Act will make an unwieldy resolution process virtually impossible,'' said Greeley Koch, the president of the trade group. The government says the data base needs to be confidential to protect national security and encourage information sharing among myriad agencies.</p>
        <p>WORK VS. PLAY -- Plan ahead, business travelers. ''Planes will be full this summer as Americans return to the skies,'' according to Suzanne Cook, vice president for research at the Travel Industry Association of America. The group predicts a 4 percent increase in air traffic over last year, and record spending of $633.5 billion on business and leisure travel in the United States for all of 2005, up from $600 billion. Hotels will be humming, too; PricewaterhouseCoopers forecasts that summer occupancy will be 71.4 percent, the highest since 2000, when the rate was 72.1 percent, and that room prices will rise an average of 4.5 percent.</p>
        <p>MORE FRILLS, PLEASE -- That is what owners of small businesses say about their preferences in air travel, according to the American Small Business Travelers Alliance. ''While no-frills airlines and smaller airports may attract leisure travelers, business travelers still want the higher level of service available to them at the major international airports,'' the group said.</p>
        <p>FREQUENT-FLIER THREAT -- With unions at United Airlines considering a strike over lost benefits, IdeaWorks, the research company, took a detailed look at how a work stoppage might affect United's huge frequent-flier program, Mileage Plus. Drastically curtailed service would immediately ''send ripples through the categories most aligned with frequent-flier programs, such as hotel and car rental companies'' with promotional tie-ins to Mileage Plus, it said, and would erode the loyalty of the program's 45 million members. IdeaWorks said that the Loyalty Services unit of United, which operates Mileage Plus and has partnerships with 145 national brands that buy United miles for their own promotions, is the only reporting segment within United that has posted earnings since 2001. United is a unit of the UAL Corporation.</p>
        <p>COMFORT ON CATHAY -- The British aviation research company Skytrax just put out its annual survey on the world's most luxurious airport lounges, and Cathay Pacific in Hong Kong took the top spot in both the first-class and business-class categories. For first-class passengers, the runners-up were Thai Airways at Bangkok, South African Airways at Johannesburg, Asiana Airlines at Inchon, South Korea, and Malaysia Airlines at Kuala Lumpur. For business class they were Virgin Atlantic at Heathrow, Gulf Air at Bahrain, Asiana Airlines at Inchon and Swiss Air at Zurich. The study was based on hundreds of thousands of online responses as well as on-site evaluations.</p>
        <p>MAKING TRACKS IN DALLAS -- Skylink, considered the world's largest airport train, was to open Saturday at Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport. The system has 64 cars, with trains running at two-minute intervals on elevated tracks at the sprawling airport.</p>
        <p>JOE SHARKEY</p>
        <p>Memo Pad</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
