<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Colgate to Cut Plants and Jobs</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="473278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAYOFFS (LABOR)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COLGATE-PALMOLIVE CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KERR, PETER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D81339F930A2575AC0A967958260" item-length="729" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Colgate to Cut Plants and Jobs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER KERR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KERR, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Saying it must consolidate its far-flung international operations to keep profits strong, the Colgate-Palmolive Company announced yesterday that it would shrink operations or close nearly a third of its factories. The moves will eliminate 2,000 jobs in its worldwide work force of 24,800.</p>
        <p>The company, which makes such familiar brands as Colgate toothpaste, Ajax cleanser, Fab detergent and Irish Spring soap, said the closings would help the work of its 91 factories be more efficient. Colgate-Palmolive also said it anticipated taking advantage of falling trade barriers in Europe and North America, which would permit fewer plants to produce more goods for entire trade regions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Saying it must consolidate its far-flung international operations to keep profits strong, the Colgate-Palmolive Company announced yesterday that it would shrink operations or close nearly a third of its factories. The moves will eliminate 2,000 jobs in its worldwide work force of 24,800.</p>
        <p>The company, which makes such familiar brands as Colgate toothpaste, Ajax cleanser, Fab detergent and Irish Spring soap, said the closings would help the work of its 91 factories be more efficient. Colgate-Palmolive also said it anticipated taking advantage of falling trade barriers in Europe and North America, which would permit fewer plants to produce more goods for entire trade regions.</p>
        <p>To cover the cost of the changes, the company will take a third-quarter after-tax charge of $243 million, or $1.81 a share. But Colgate-Palmolive executives stressed that the changes did not belie long-term troubles for the $5.7 billion consumer products company. Positive Outlook for '91</p>
        <p>"Our success in recent years has given Colgate an extraordinarily strong marketing and financial foundation upon which to build an even stronger, faster-growing company," said Reuben Mark, Colgate's chairman and chief operating officer. "Our outlook for the rest of 1991 is positive as well."</p>
        <p>But some Wall Street analysts cautioned that the decision to cut so many jobs -- 8 percent of the company's force -- and eliminate work at 25 factories indicated that Colgate might still have far to go to reduce overhead. . Among the plants to be closed are factories in Canada, Portugal, Belgium and Australia.</p>
        <p>"They may still have to rationalize further," said Jay H. Freedman, an analyst with Kidder, Peabody.</p>
        <p>Colgate-Palmolive stock fell 62.5 cents a share yesterday to close at $39.625 on the New York Stock Exchange. The market, however, did not appear to be overly concerned by Colgate's move.</p>
        <p>The company, which together with Procter &amp; Gamble and Unilever is one of the largest manufacturers of household care and personal care products in the United States, was considered a success story of the late 1980's, as Mr. Mark breathed a bit of entrepreneurial fire into what had long been a sleepy, low-profit international conglomerate.</p>
        <p>The company's sales rose to $5.6 billion in 1990 from $3.4 billion in 1984, while the work force was sliced to 24,800 last year from 42,800 over the same period.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mark also achieved one goal of his five-year plan with an average 17 percent growth in earnings per share annually over the last six years.</p>
        <p>Analysts said yesterday's move underscored the seriousness of Mr. Mark's commitment to his new five-year plan, which pledges to increase earnings by 15 percent a year through 1995.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the company, Anne Crawford, said that expected increase in the flow of goods between the United States and Canada and inside the European Community after 1992 would permit Colgate-Palmolive to combine production into fewer plants and ship more products across international boundaries. Sixty-five percent of the company's sales are outside the United States.</p>
        <p>In addition, the increasing demand for detergents and fabric softeners in concentrated form, particularly in Europe, has reduced the bulk of many products and reduced the number of people needed to manufacture and transport them. The company, she said, also found that it had considerable overcapacity after acquiring more than 35 new plants since 1987.</p>
        <p>As part of the strategy, the company will move Canadian production of powder detergents, liquid cleaners and bar soaps to the United States. Colgate's manufacturing complex in Liege, Belgium, will also be closed.</p>
        <p>Ms. Crawford refused to say how many, if any, jobs would be eliminated in the United States.</p>
        <p>Gregory S. Sigmund, an analyst with the investment firm of A. G. Edwards, said the new five-year plan had placed the company under a great deal of pressure to keep earnings up. Mr. Sigmund said increasing competition in Europe from Procter &amp; Gamble and other companies and the company's low profit margins in the United States meant the company must squeeze overhead as much as possible.</p>
        <p>"In order to achieve their goals, they are going to have to position themselves a little better to compete," Mr. Sigmund said. "It is not as if they have stubbed their toe. It's just they must become leaner and meaner."  COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
