<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Film; Hippiedom to Lawyerdom</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="473253"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MASLIN, JANET</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JASON, JACK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">POSTER, RANDALL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORGAN, W T</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MATTER OF DEGREES, A (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910913T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DF1539F930A2575AC0A967958260" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Film; Hippiedom to Lawyerdom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MASLIN, JANET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Providence, R.I., that is celebrated in "A Matter of Degrees" is a geographical location, but it's mostly a state of mind. It's the undergraduate limbo enjoyed by Maxwell Glass (Arye Gross), who has just been accepted at law school but will not easily make the transition from late-1980's campus hippiedom to the corporate world. An opening montage, replete with public figures ranging from Abbie Hoffman to Ronald Reagan, reflects the confusing array of influences that have shaped Max's consciousness and left him just barely able to get out of bed in the morning. The idea of a grown-up law career seems remote at best.</p>
        <p>"A Matter of Degrees," co-written by two Brown University alumni, Jack Mason and Randall Poster, with W. T. Morgan (who is the film's director), is extremely sympathetic to Max's predicament. So the film adopts an attitude of anti-professionalism very like its hero's, to the point where any of the normal plot contrivances that might shape Max's story become suspect. This means that "A Matter of Degrees" doesn't try very hard to tell a story. Instead, it drifts with Max from classroom to junkyard to corporate party, touching all the bases of a counterculture on the verge of extinction but still clinging to a distinctive world view. "Remember," someone remarks earnestly, "women and animals hold up two-thirds of the sky."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Providence, R.I., that is celebrated in "A Matter of Degrees" is a geographical location, but it's mostly a state of mind. It's the undergraduate limbo enjoyed by Maxwell Glass (Arye Gross), who has just been accepted at law school but will not easily make the transition from late-1980's campus hippiedom to the corporate world. An opening montage, replete with public figures ranging from Abbie Hoffman to Ronald Reagan, reflects the confusing array of influences that have shaped Max's consciousness and left him just barely able to get out of bed in the morning. The idea of a grown-up law career seems remote at best.</p>
        <p>"A Matter of Degrees," co-written by two Brown University alumni, Jack Mason and Randall Poster, with W. T. Morgan (who is the film's director), is extremely sympathetic to Max's predicament. So the film adopts an attitude of anti-professionalism very like its hero's, to the point where any of the normal plot contrivances that might shape Max's story become suspect. This means that "A Matter of Degrees" doesn't try very hard to tell a story. Instead, it drifts with Max from classroom to junkyard to corporate party, touching all the bases of a counterculture on the verge of extinction but still clinging to a distinctive world view. "Remember," someone remarks earnestly, "women and animals hold up two-thirds of the sky."</p>
        <p>A remark like that transcends the limitations of campus life, but a lot of the film is more narrowly nostalgic. You may have had to be there, or at least to have spent time in a similar setting, to appreciate the film's very nonchalant approach to drama. The fact that Mr. Gross has been more at home in lovable-sidekick roles than he is as a leading man contributes further to the film's aimless feeling. The best of "A Matter of Degrees" is merely atmospheric and anecdotal. And a lot of it has the drifting feel of a good-natured anecdote without an ending.</p>
        <p>"A Matter of Degrees," which opens today at Village East, does achieve a level of journalistic interest at times, in documenting the fact that there are courses in subjects like "Interdisciplinary Approaches to Ethnicity" and that "Ivan Boesky" can be used as a verb. Of a greedy friend who implements the corporate takeover of a once-independent college radio station, it is said, "He Ivan Boeskied it for them." The film also demonstrates, for anyone who's interested, that it's possible to make sandwiches out of white bread and undiluted canned soup.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Gross, who is amiable if not magnetic, the cast includes Tom Sizemore as Max's closest crony, Judith Hoag as his pert, feisty roommate and Christina Haag as a college temptress whose motives remain a bit more mysterious than they have to be. Also seen briefly are Joseph R. Paolino Jr., the former Mayor of the film's beloved Providence, and John F. Kennedy Jr., who neither sings nor acts very well but can have a career in movies any time he cares to. As they used to say in Hollywood, the camera loves him.  A Matter of Degrees</p>
        <p>Directed by W. T. Morgan; written by Randall Poster, Mr. Morgan and Jack Jason; music by various composers; produced by Roy Kissen; released by Fox/Lorber. At Village East, 11th Street at Third Avenue, Manhattan. Running time: 88 minutes. This film has no rating. Maxwell Glass . . . Arye Gross Kate Blum . . . Judith Hoag Zeno . . . Tom Sizemore Isabella Allen . . . Christina Haag WITH: Joseph R. Paolino Jr. and John F. Kennedy Jr.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
