<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Republican Moderates Say Questions Remain Unanswered</title>
    <meta content="Y09REPU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068338"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE SWING VOTES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EED7153AF93AA35751C1A96E958260" item-length="1155" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Republican Moderates Say Questions Remain Unanswered</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Republican moderates, largest bloc of undecided votes on impeachment in House, say Pres Clinton's first day of defense might have slowed what has seemed to be growing momentum behind vote to impeach him; say testimony left unanswered some of their most pressing questions about Clinton's behavior and his fitness to govern; urge Clinton or his allies to provide less evasive explanation of his actions in Monica Lewinsky affair; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Republican moderates, the largest bloc of undecided votes on impeachment in the House, said President Clinton's first day of defense today might have slowed what had seemed to be growing momentum behind a vote to impeach him.</p>
        <p>But many of those moderates said that today's testimony left unanswered some of their most pressing questions about the President's behavior and his fitness to govern, and they urged Mr. Clinton or his allies to provide a sharper, less evasive explanation of his actions in the Monica Lewinsky affair.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Republican moderates, the largest bloc of undecided votes on impeachment in the House, said President Clinton's first day of defense today might have slowed what had seemed to be growing momentum behind a vote to impeach him.</p>
        <p>But many of those moderates said that today's testimony left unanswered some of their most pressing questions about the President's behavior and his fitness to govern, and they urged Mr. Clinton or his allies to provide a sharper, less evasive explanation of his actions in the Monica Lewinsky affair.</p>
        <p>''Has he eroded his credibility to the point where he can't govern?'' asked Representative Rick A. Lazio, a Long Island Republican. ''There is nothing that addressed that today. For the core issues that are at the heart of this for me, today's hearing wasn't on point.''</p>
        <p>Despite such concerns, a leading moderate Republican, Representative Amo Houghton of upstate New York, decided that he would vote against impeachment on the House floor. Mr. Houghton is the sixth House Republican to say publicly that he opposes impeachment.</p>
        <p>Three Democrats have said they will vote for impeachment. That means the President's allies need to swing eight more Republican votes to block impeachment.</p>
        <p>''The main issue is how to heal, rather than further divide, the nation,'' Mr. Houghton said in an Op-Ed page article to be published in The New York Times on Wednesday. ''Of course, morals and decency and the laws we live by are all important. But can anyone argue that these threads are made stronger if we dismiss someone from office instead of issuing a strong rebuke?''</p>
        <p>A centrist Democrat who had voted in favor of opening an impeachment inquiry into the President's behavior said today that he was leaning against impeachment. The Democrat, Representative Jim Maloney of Connecticut, said Republicans who have been demanding that Mr. Clinton admit that he lied before a grand jury were asking for the impossible: that the President admit to a crime.</p>
        <p>''It's in effect a trick question,'' Mr. Maloney said. ''They want him to admit to something on the basis that that will solve all of our little problems. But they are asking him to step into a criminal prosecution two years hence. That's the kind of partisan posturing that is counterproductive.''</p>
        <p>In many ways, the White House's two-day presentation before the House Judiciary Committee is aimed mainly at winning over the three dozen or so moderate Republicans who remain undecided about impeachment. Many of those moderates come from districts where Mr. Clinton did well in the 1996 election and where sentiment for impeaching him is weak.</p>
        <p>Many of them have said that they consider the President's behavior abhorrent but that they prefer a less severe punishment than impeachment. So they have been waiting for the President's team to present a vigorous defense before the committee that could provide arguments, facts or new evidence that could justify bucking their leadership and voting against impeachment.</p>
        <p>It is not clear they got what they were looking for today.</p>
        <p>''I am desperately looking for a reason that it can be explained away,'' said Representative Brian P. Bilbray, a California Republican, referring to Mr. Clinton's statements about the Lewinsky affair. ''I just wish the President had gone before the committee. No one speaks better for Bill Clinton than himself. I just wish he'd spent more time explaining himself than having his attack dogs go after these issues.''</p>
        <p>Many of the undecideds watched today's hearing at home or in their Capitol Hill offices, and several said they planned to read a 184-page legal brief presented by the White House to the Judiciary Committee today.</p>
        <p>But despite the historic nature of the impending vote, many undecided members of Congress were scattered across the globe, unable to pay attention to today's testimony because of vacations or other pressing Congressional business.</p>
        <p>Representative Nancy L. Johnson, a Connecticut Republican, and other members of the Ways and Means Committee were in New Zealand to discuss trade issues. Representative W. J. (Billy) Tauzin, a Louisiana Republican, spent the day deer hunting in Maryland. And Representative Wayne T. Gilchrest, a Maryland Republican, was in London at a meeting of the International Maritime Organization.</p>
        <p>Some said they did not bother to watch today's hearing because they were already familiar with the facts of the case and did not expect to be enlightened by new testimony on behalf of the President.</p>
        <p>''Hearings don't make much difference,'' said Representative Scott L. Klug, Republican of Wisconsin, who added that he was still undecided. ''Most of the hearings at this point sound like a bunch of lawyers fighting a personal injury case. Lots of legalistic polka dancing on the head of a pin.''</p>
        <p>Several undecided Republicans said that they were pleased that the witnesses presented by the White House today did not criticize Kenneth W. Starr, the independent counsel, and that Gregory B. Craig, the White House special counsel for impeachment matters, had adopted a more conciliatory tone with the committee's Republicans.</p>
        <p>But one undecided Republican, Representative Bob Ney of Ohio, said Mr. Craig had not helped the President's case when he said Mr. Clinton had not necessarily lied about the Lewinsky affair.</p>
        <p>''Come on, everyone in the country knows the President didn't tell the truth,'' Mr. Ney said. ''Ask my children. Everyone knows it. The President said he misled the country. For him to play coy is absurd.'' But Mr. Ney, who watched several hours of the hearing before flying back to his district in eastern Ohio, said he would not vote for impeachment just because of a poor performance by the President's lawyer.</p>
        <p>A few moderate Republicans said privately that they had been contacted either by White House officials or Democratic colleagues in Congress. But most said they had not been lobbied strenuously by either side.</p>
        <p>Representative Christopher Shays, a Connecticut Republican who opposes impeachment, said lobbying by the White House and its allies at this late date could only hurt the President.</p>
        <p>''If I were thinking of voting for impeachment and the White House generated calls urging me to vote against it, I think I might be less inclined to accommodate them,'' Mr. Shays said. ''Because the thought that I would vote based on political pressure would be an insult to me. Contrition won't do it; honesty will. That's their best hope.''  TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE SWING VOTES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
