<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unfazed by Excess, the Pundits Chatter On . . . and On</title>
    <meta content="09NOTE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068267"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Walter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Cokie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Donaldson, Sam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kristol, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Will, George F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stephanopoulos, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">This Week (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E1D6143AF93AA35751C1A96E958260" item-length="901" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unfazed by Excess, the Pundits Chatter On . . . and On</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Walter Goodman</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Goodman Critic's Notebook column on television's talking heads, and foolish, pointless, peculiar things they spout; notes that while politicians can be kicked out of office, corporate executives can lose their perks and athletes can be fined, the privileged cadre of chattering class goes on forever; holds programs that started out as discussions have slid down slopes of entertainment to sheer blather; comments on remarkably wrong predictions of regular panelists on ABC's This Week; photo of Sam Donaldson, Cokie Roberts, Bill Kristol, George Will and George Stephanopoulos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The beauty part of the television blowhard's calling is that you never have to say you're sorry. When you are obliged to talk as incessantly as demanded by that line of work, especially on nonstop cable, you are bound to utter foolish, pointless, peculiar things, and the louder, the more authoritative. But neither excess nor error nor eccentricity can stay these spouters from their anointed rounds.</p>
        <p>Politicians can be kicked out of office, corporation executives can lose their perks, athletes can be fined. But the privileged cadre nicely named the chattering class goes on forever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The beauty part of the television blowhard's calling is that you never have to say you're sorry. When you are obliged to talk as incessantly as demanded by that line of work, especially on nonstop cable, you are bound to utter foolish, pointless, peculiar things, and the louder, the more authoritative. But neither excess nor error nor eccentricity can stay these spouters from their anointed rounds.</p>
        <p>Politicians can be kicked out of office, corporation executives can lose their perks, athletes can be fined. But the privileged cadre nicely named the chattering class goes on forever.</p>
        <p>Programs that started out as discussions have slid down the slopes of entertainment into sheer blather. One might have thought that NBC News worthies would by now have slinked away in chagrin at the Monica merchandising that has been MSNBC's stock in trade for months. But no, respectables like Tim Russert are still lending themselves to that dubious enterprise.</p>
        <p>The grapplings on CNBC, the Fox Network and elsewhere as debaters vie in the ferocity stakes are about as reasoned as wrestling matches. For viewers, the saving grace of a McLaughlin gang or one of its clones is that half the time you can't make out what any of them is saying.</p>
        <p>Over in more sedate precincts, one might assume that the remarkably wrong predictions of the regulars on ABC's ''This Week,'' who announced President Clinton's forced departure from office a year or so ago, would have earned them a vacation. But there's Sam Donaldson still delivering bombast and Bill Kristol indulging in wishful analysis. George Will, who one assumes was hired to bring a touch of class to the gab, is descending into vituperation.</p>
        <p>Thus do the imperatives of show business impinge on the discipline of journalism. Call it all talk, rarely listen television. It's in the nature of a medium that never stops running; any sound is preferable to the sound of silence.</p>
        <p>The spirit blossoms in all its glory on talk shows and call-ins, but it infiltrates what used to be known as hard-news programs, too. From the wackiest to the relatively conventional, the people we are hearing often don't seem to be hearing themselves. Does anybody care? Polls tell us that the nation doesn't particularly like or trust journalists, but there's no escape. Nonstop news abhors a vacuum; the model has become the mayhem of the Internet or of upchuck radio.</p>
        <p>It's head-to-talking-head competition, not over anything as rarefied as depth or analysis but simply over attention grabbers. On the networks as well as on cable, Monica Lewinsky guaranteed ratings; and what was actually heard amid the din was mostly filler.</p>
        <p>The hawkers of those commodities tend to come on loud and fast and are never caught in the dead air of reflection. Assertions abound; reservations are risky. A pause for breath may send millions of viewers to the remote control. So you repeat what you or somebody said yesterday. If you're really stumped, take a call from Freddy in Philadelphia. Does anyone notice that the callers are given to parroting what they have just heard? That would be like criticizing elevator music on esthetic grounds.</p>
        <p>To be sure, words of sense do emerge, but they are quickly drowned in the commotion. It may be imagination, but I think I've detected more than once a look of alarm as some stunned sobersides who actually has something original or interesting to say suddenly realizes that he has accepted an invitation to bedlam.</p>
        <p>The conflict here is between freedom, or the illusion of freedom, and responsibility, which brings with it some sort of control. When communication is reduced to noise and populism runs rampant, not only is everyone entitled to be heard, but courtesy requires that all opinions be treated as of like worth. Expertise becomes window dressing; the experts, too, after all, are competing for who will be called back; stutterers need not apply. Credentials, education, knowledge become a form of discrimination. Standards become stuffy, elitist. Larry King is the great leveler.</p>
        <p>The loose-talk formula has appeal; it can be infectious. The intelligent Mr. Will cannot fail to notice that in this contest anybody can get away with anything; no one is called to account, so why strain for some rigor of discourse when rival performers are mouthing off on all sides without nice distinctions that might slow down the hustle to be first to nowhere? If network news has been getting soft at the edges, with graphic fripperies and an endless supply of revelations of medical wonders, that's in part an effort to keep up with or down with the cable crowd.</p>
        <p>In this universe of deafening interactive nonstop hot air, journalists find themselves in competition not just with their peers but with everybody. The lately liberated audience members turn out to have a lot to say and is increasingly insistent on saying it, and their hosts are in no position to tell them to stuff it.</p>
        <p>A dedication to ratings is democratic, all right, but not a sure route to information. Becoming informed sometimes requires that one shut up and listen.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
