<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Making the Case For Instant Replay</title>
    <meta content="09VECS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Football League</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vecsey, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Officiating (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFDA153AF93AA35751C1A96E958260" item-length="803" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Making the Case For Instant Replay</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vecsey, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Vecsey Sports of The Times column discusses recent embarrassing and crucial mistakes by officials in National Football League games; holds league should bring back instant replay (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>EMBARRASSING mistakes by officials in the National Football League did not merely affect something as simple as ''a ball game.'' Each error influenced one-sixteenth of a season, which is a compelling reason for getting it right.</p>
        <p>The word from league headquarters is that there is a possibility the owners can return instant replay in time for the playoffs in January. It's not as if they would be inventing the wheel in double time. The league operated with instant replay from 1986 through 1991, and has held experiments recently with better technology and tighter application.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>EMBARRASSING mistakes by officials in the National Football League did not merely affect something as simple as ''a ball game.'' Each error influenced one-sixteenth of a season, which is a compelling reason for getting it right.</p>
        <p>The word from league headquarters is that there is a possibility the owners can return instant replay in time for the playoffs in January. It's not as if they would be inventing the wheel in double time. The league operated with instant replay from 1986 through 1991, and has held experiments recently with better technology and tighter application.</p>
        <p>Anything is better than the sight of Vinny Testaverde of the Jets failing to get the ball over the goal line Sunday only to be given credit for a touchdown. The officials did not operate out of arrogance or dishonesty; they merely blew the call. However, in pro football, human imperfection can cost 6 percent of a season.</p>
        <p>You want human imperfection? Take Richie Garcia's missing a kid sticking his hands over the wall and turning Derek Jeter's fly ball into a home run in the 1996 American League playoffs. Garcia blew the call, but even then, who told the Baltimore Orioles to lose that game in extra innings, and then lose three more games in the next four?</p>
        <p>During the 1969 World Series, Gil Hodges mesmerized the umpire by plodding deliberately to home plate, and methodically waving a baseball with a smudge, persuading the entranced ump that Cleon Jones had been hit on the foot with a pitched ball. The Mets clinched the Series almost immediately.</p>
        <p>Don Denkinger blew a call at first base in the ninth inning of the sixth game of the 1985 World Series. Who told St. Louis to lose that game, and the next one, too?</p>
        <p>Instant replay might have solved all three of those disputes, but at least baseball plays a 162-game season and now has three tiers of post-season series. Hockey actually employs instant replay for all 82 games and four tiers of Stanley Cup playoffs. The National Basketball Association normally has the same structure, but trapped in a lockout, it canceled its All-Star Game yesterday, heading toward oblivion. And none of those sports plays a one-game championship, like football.</p>
        <p>''Everyone's greatest fear is what happened yesterday happening in the Super Bowl,'' Greg Aiello, a league spokesman, said on Monday.</p>
        <p>The Super Bowl is a lumbering rush to judgment, with the whole world watching, but, then again, so is every football game, with no time for schmoozing or common sense.</p>
        <p>Back when there used to be such a thing as pro basketball, I would sometimes see three referees put their little heads together, with the two coaches eavesdropping, and sometimes the refs would make a common-sense reversal of themselves.</p>
        <p>In the N.F.L. there are petty regulations about the length of socks, and the Emotion Police penalize whacked-out monsters for celebrating what they were born to do, create a touchdown.</p>
        <p>This is not the fault of the officials. It is the cumbersome charm of pro football. The industry takes itself seriously, and so should we. There is already a climate of obedience and regimentation. I mean, this is not exactly telling Earl Weaver he can't toss his cap, or John Calipari he can't bounce up and down like a 3-year-old.</p>
        <p>The way the story goes, pro football scuttled instant replay because it ate up too much time. Ha! In this sport, the ball is in play for something like 12 minutes out of three hours. They want faster games, they can cut down on substitutions and calling plays from the bench and they could keep the clock running like in a real sport, soccer.</p>
        <p>They could also cut down on commercials. Right.</p>
        <p>Some people say instant replay was right only 80 percent of the time. I'd settle. Eighty is a higher percentage than most elected public officials tell the truth.</p>
        <p>The physical quality of football allows only one game a week, with a finite number of plays. It would be great if the N.F.L. could eliminate some of the travesties of recent weeks. The officials did not mean to make a mistake, and would not surrender their credibility to the replay camera.</p>
        <p>The league is on the right path in limiting the number of challenges to two per game at the cost of a timeout, with added discretion for the officials to review their own call in the final two minutes.</p>
        <p>With so much of a season decided by one honest mistake, the players and coaches and fans deserve instant replay.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
