<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Immobilizing Lies</title>
    <meta content="09WED1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1068324"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0D8153AF93AA35751C1A96E958260" item-length="586" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Immobilizing Lies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial contends that Pres Clinton must free himself and his defenders from paralyzing fiction that he did not lie under oath if he wants to avoid impeachment showdown in Congress</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If President Clinton wants an impeachment vote in the House of Representatives and a possible trial in the Senate, he has got the House Judiciary Committee exactly where he wants it. If, however, Mr. Clinton would like to be less passive about his future, he has to change the direction and content of the committee's deliberations. In practical terms, that means the President must free himself and his defenders from the paralyzing fiction that he did not lie under oath.</p>
        <p>It is unclear, of course, whether Mr. Clinton wants to avoid an impeachment showdown in Congress. He may be so addicted to chaos that he can only feel comfortable in a storm. Or he may simply be imprisoned by lawyers who tell him he can cling to office and defeat any criminal indictment if he will just stick to his story. But if the White House and Congress should want to respond to the public desire for a censure deal, the hearings yesterday were not a total washout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If President Clinton wants an impeachment vote in the House of Representatives and a possible trial in the Senate, he has got the House Judiciary Committee exactly where he wants it. If, however, Mr. Clinton would like to be less passive about his future, he has to change the direction and content of the committee's deliberations. In practical terms, that means the President must free himself and his defenders from the paralyzing fiction that he did not lie under oath.</p>
        <p>It is unclear, of course, whether Mr. Clinton wants to avoid an impeachment showdown in Congress. He may be so addicted to chaos that he can only feel comfortable in a storm. Or he may simply be imprisoned by lawyers who tell him he can cling to office and defeat any criminal indictment if he will just stick to his story. But if the White House and Congress should want to respond to the public desire for a censure deal, the hearings yesterday were not a total washout.</p>
        <p>For the most part, the Democratic case was well presented. Only a gratuitously patronizing presentation by Sean Wilentz, a Princeton historian, marred the Democratic experts' argument that Mr. Clinton's misconduct did not meet the constitutional tests for impeachment. The White House lawyer, Gregory Craig, adopted the conciliatory tone demanded by House Republicans. He said the President had ''personally instructed'' him to avoid legalisms and admit that Mr. Clinton was blameworthy, evasive and immoral, and had ''misled his wife and family, his friends and colleagues and our nation.'' But Mr. Craig could only squirm and backpedal when Republicans pressed him to explain his insistence that the President had not violated his sworn oath to tell the truth, the whole truth and nothing but the truth.</p>
        <p>Mr. Craig's presentation showed why the White House has to resort to lawyering when its President is not leading. Many Republicans are motivated by political blood lust. A smaller but potentially decisive number is looking for a way to let Mr. Clinton off the perjury hook if he will admit that he lied under oath. Neither faction is willing to accept Presidential assertions that defy reason and the factual record. Representative Charles Schumer, the New York Democrat, is wrong, on politics and principle, to ridicule Republican demands for fuller statements of contrition. He and the White House should listen to Representative Lindsey Graham's somber statement that ''because this is not Watergate,'' impeachment could be avoided if Mr. Clinton would ''reconcile himself to the law'' with an admission of lying.</p>
        <p>What Mr. Graham, a Republican, is saying is simply that Mr. Clinton needs to find a way out of the box he has built for himself. But the Republicans who demand a statement of culpability as well as one of remorse have to be ready to respond if the President moves. Any deal on censure has to protect him from prosecution in the courts on the evidence known at this time.</p>
        <p>Not much progress was made yesterday toward such a settlement. The White House's new 184-page report is designed to continue the stalemate. Yet the Judiciary debate was dignified and productive, and although both sides remain in fixed positions, nothing happened that would preclude a settlement if, against all present indications, a leader should step forward.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
