<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When the Attack Fallout Moves the Office to the Suburbs</title>
    <meta content="30COMM$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/30/nyregion/30COMM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1338445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: THE COMMUTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City Metropolitan Area</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kennedy, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Commuting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Relocation of Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stations and Terminals (Passenger)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">World Financial Center</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EED91430F933A05753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When the Attack Fallout Moves the Office to the Suburbs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">When the Attack Fallout Moves the Office to the Suburbs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDY KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kennedy, Randy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article looks at people who are commuting to New Jersey because offices were destroyed in Sept 11 attack on World Trade Center; some relocations are temporary, others are permanent, and in many cases, employees receive commuting assistance from their companies; many displaced workers face hard decisions about possibility of moving closer to where their companies are relocating; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kristian Areche grew up in Washington Heights. He loves his neighborhood. But it does not make much sense for him to live there anymore.</p>
        <p>Before Sept. 11, it did. To get to work, he took the No. 1 train to the World Financial Center. The trip was about 10 miles. It took about half an hour and cost less than $20 a week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Officials have estimated that 100,000 jobs were displaced by the attacks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kristian Areche grew up in Washington Heights. He loves his neighborhood. But it does not make much sense for him to live there anymore.</p>
        <p>Before Sept. 11, it did. To get to work, he took the No. 1 train to the World Financial Center. The trip was about 10 miles. It took about half an hour and cost less than $20 a week.</p>
        <p>Now, this is the way to work: a used Honda Civic. A 60-mile drive to his new office in South Brunswick, N.J. An hour and a half on the road, with luck. And $1,650 a year for insurance. He calls his car the beast, and he hates it. But what he and his wife hate more is the thought of moving.</p>
        <p>''We don't have anything against New Jersey,'' he said. ''We just don't want to live there. We're New York City people.''</p>
        <p>In an overcrowded metropolitan region -- where people have often chosen their homes because of where their jobs are or their jobs because of where their homes are -- Kristian Areche and his wife are among those people now facing a set of tough choices about both life and work.</p>
        <p>Mr. Areche, a page designer for The Wall Street Journal, is one of the workers displaced from the World Trade Center area who will not be coming back to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>There may soon be many more like him. Former Manhattan employees of Citigroup and Deloitte &amp; Touche might wind up in Connecticut. Corporate campuses from Jersey City to Princeton to Parsippany, N.J., might take workers from Merrill Lynch and American Express.</p>
        <p>Officials have estimated that 100,000 jobs were displaced by the attacks. Many companies have not made final decisions on which employees will remain in satellite offices, and there are no statistics yet on how many have moved to the suburbs so far. But people involved in the financial services industry predict there could be tens of thousands who arranged their lives around commuting to Lower Manhattan who will never return there. Because many financial companies already had cheaper office space in the suburbs, it became easier for them after the twin towers attack to transfer some of their operations to those offices.</p>
        <p>Many companies that have moved some of their employees from Manhattan would not let their workers discuss the relocation publicly, partly because the companies were afraid of being seen as abandoning Manhattan.</p>
        <p>But many of the displaced workers now think of themselves as urban exiles, piecing together tough new trips from bus, ferry and train schedules. Some are doing the reverse commute, from city to suburb. Others are trying to make their way from suburb to suburb, along transit lines not intended to move people efficiently that way.</p>
        <p>They are confronting questions they never imagined.</p>
        <p>Some are wrenching: Do we pull up stakes and move to be closer to the new office? Do we pull our kids out of the school we worked so hard to get them into? Or do we try to rearrange our lives around a two-hour-plus trip to work?</p>
        <p>Other questions seem trivial, in light of what has happened. But as people who made their careers in Manhattan try to write new formulas for enjoying their lives again, those questions are important, too. Such as: Do I really want to work in the suburbs?</p>
        <p>Mr. Areche, 28, and his wife, Harriba, a bartender in NoHo, used to go out in the city on Fridays, the only work night she got off early. Now he spends Friday nights on the road.</p>
        <p>He used to buy a paper on the way to the subway and read it on the train. But he can't read the paper and steer at the same time. He used to get a sandwich at his favorite deli near the World Financial Center. Now when he wants a bite, he usually drives to a strip-mall restaurant like T.G.I. Friday on Route 1.</p>
        <p>''To go anywhere around here you have to drive,'' he said last week, in his car. ''It's too far to walk. Where are you going to walk? Into the woods? To see a deer?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Areche, one of about 250 workers at The Journal whose jobs have been transferred permanently to South Brunswick, takes pains to stress that his problems are paltry compared with those of people who lost loved ones or jobs as a result of the attacks.</p>
        <p>Dow Jones, The Journal's corporate parent, has provided hotel rooms and other commuting assistance to soften the blow as he and other workers decide how they will deal with the transfers.</p>
        <p>But many have already had enough of a glimpse of their new commuting trip and new office to know what it will mean for their lives.</p>
        <p>One Dow Jones employee now working in South Brunswick had bought a house in Westchester just before the attack. Another lives on the Upper East Side and her new trip usually clocks in at more than two hours, door to door.</p>
        <p>Paul Bernard, who runs an executive coaching and career management firm in Manhattan, said he had  had many clients since the terror attacks who found themselves grappling with the rearranged geography of their lives. They were asking him whether they could find another job, back in the city or closer to home. Or they were thinking about moving closer to the new office.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Bernard cautions them to be careful, because they may uproot themselves only to find that their company shrinks, they lose their job and they have moved for nothing.</p>
        <p>The other option, finding a new job, and in the right location, is not so easy anymore.</p>
        <p>''For a long time around here, with the economy so good, people have worked on the assumption that they can have everything,'' he said. ''And that is not the case anymore. For many people, if they want their job, they may have to face the commuting problems that people face in London and in Los Angeles, where a two-hour drive is not uncommon.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernard described one Manhattan couple, who did not want to be identified, in which the husband is now working in New Jersey, with a long trip, and does not know if his financial-services job will return him to Manhattan. The wife is a successful lawyer. They just had their second child. Their lives -- already built on ''thin margins of comfort'' in being able to handle everything -- have become a scramble.</p>
        <p>''They're both questioning how long they're going to be able to handle this,'' he said. He added that they had considered moving to Chicago, where they thought it would be easier to find a downtown job and afford a downtown lifestyle.</p>
        <p>Glenda Williams, an associate senior director at the Consortium for Worker Education, a nonprofit organization that is helping train and place lower-income workers affected by the attacks, said she had also been hearing from workers with severe new commuting problems.</p>
        <p>''They call in on our hot line,'' Ms. Williams said, ''and they say, 'My company has moved to Jersey, way out there somewhere, and I don't have a car. What am I going to do? Or, 'They've moved to Long Island, and I told them I can't go out there and so they just laid me off.' It's a very hard time for a lot of people right now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Areche thinks he can make it all work.</p>
        <p>But he lasted only three days on New Jersey Transit trains before giving up in exasperation.</p>
        <p>''It just took too long,'' he said. ''You have to arrange your whole day around the train schedule.'' He rented a car. Then he finally ''broke the piggy bank'' and bought the first car he had owned since 1989.</p>
        <p>His inexperience as a suburban commuter showed. The first car he bought, on eBay, turned out to be a lemon, and he had to tow it back to the seller using his rental car. His next purchase was the 1989 powder-blue Civic, with rusted-through fenders and 168,795 miles. It cost $600, plus $200 for a tuneup. The windows whistle when it gets past 50 miles per hour.</p>
        <p>He considers himself lucky because his shift begins at 3 p.m. and ends at 10, so he misses the rush-hour traffic both ways. But his luck usually runs out when he gets back to the city. Last Wednesday, he spent 45 minutes looking for a parking place near his apartment.</p>
        <p>''Everybody else is already home and parked by the time I'm looking for a spot,'' he said. ''It wears you out.''</p>
        <p>He has considered renting an apartment near South Brunswick, where he could bunk some nights of the week. But his wife, who moved to the city six years ago from France, has said she might as well go back to France if she is never going to see her husband. Mr. Areche adds that if they have children, he does not know how they will be able to deal with his trip to work.</p>
        <p>''We're just not sure what we're going to do,'' he said. ''I love my job, I really do. And I love where I live. It's where I know everybody. We're really going to try to make it work.''</p>
        <p>Others are not quite so sure.</p>
        <p>Ben Craft, who works on the copy desk at The Wall Street Journal, has an even more difficult trip, from Port Chester, N.Y., to South Brunswick. Most nights he stays in a New Jersey hotel because it is just too difficult to go back and forth: The trip, about 80 miles, using Metro-North, New Jersey Transit and a Dow Jones shuttle from the train station, usually takes more than three hours.</p>
        <p>''I have a job, I didn't lose anybody, I'm not hurt, so I can't really complain,'' said Mr. Craft, 27, sitting at his new desk the other day. ''But this is not the kind of experience I want to be having at this point in my life.''</p>
        <p>''It's just not the same getting out of a shuttle bus on a corporate campus in New Jersey as it was stepping out of the subway and walking past Wall Street,'' he added. ''You felt like you were right in the middle of things. Now, you have this feeling that you've been, well, back-officed.''</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: THE COMMUTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
