<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Even His Freeze-Frame Moments Seem Spastic</title>
    <meta content="30PROF$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/30/nyregion/30PROF.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1338415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PUBLIC LIVES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Sandi Simcha DuBowski</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wadler, Joyce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dubowski, Sandi Simcha</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Halloween</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Halloween</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Lower East Side (NY)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Film Forum</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE7D91430F933A05753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Even His Freeze-Frame Moments Seem Spastic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Even His Freeze-Frame Moments Seem Spastic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE WADLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wadler, Joyce</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column profiles career of film director Sandi Simcha Dubowski; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE voice that responds to the ringing of a Lower East Side doorbell reflects the hysteria of a host running way behind schedule. It's so intense that the visitor briefly fears having rung the wrong buzzer, and violated the lair of a New York crazy. But it is merely an artist.</p>
        <p>''Oh, noooo, you're early,'' filmmaker Sandi Simcha DuBowski, 31, is wailing. ''I haven't even showered, all these people were calling, I couldn't get them off the phone. Do you want to sit on the porch on the back? I wish the sukkah was still up, we just tore it down!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE voice that responds to the ringing of a Lower East Side doorbell reflects the hysteria of a host running way behind schedule. It's so intense that the visitor briefly fears having rung the wrong buzzer, and violated the lair of a New York crazy. But it is merely an artist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE voice that responds to the ringing of a Lower East Side doorbell reflects the hysteria of a host running way behind schedule. It's so intense that the visitor briefly fears having rung the wrong buzzer, and violated the lair of a New York crazy. But it is merely an artist.</p>
        <p>''Oh, noooo, you're early,'' filmmaker Sandi Simcha DuBowski, 31, is wailing. ''I haven't even showered, all these people were calling, I couldn't get them off the phone. Do you want to sit on the porch on the back? I wish the sukkah was still up, we just tore it down!''</p>
        <p>The porch, which one enters by climbing through a window, looks like its mother was a fire escape. The apartment, on Bleecker Street, is a former fur factory in which  worn wooden steps slant sideways, the décor is thrift shop, even the futon seems to sag.</p>
        <p>''Piazza del Bleecker,'' sings the filmmaker, returned from the shower. ''Well actually, the stairs in front of the building -- that is Piazza del Bleecker.''</p>
        <p>Documentary filmmakers are rarely wealthy and Mr. DuBowski, 31, is no exception. A Harvard graduate with no training in filmmaking, he spent six grant-filled years making ''Trembling Before G-d,'' a documentary about Orthodox Jews who are homosexual and wish to remain observant. It is, for most, an impossible matter. Homosexuality is forbidden by Jewish law. Mr. DuBowski, making the film, was often forced to visit his subjects with his film equipment hidden, so the neighbors would not know. It has since been voted best documentary at several film festivals and will resume playing on Thursday at the Film Forum in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. DuBowski, his speech is peppered with Yiddish and Hebrew, although he knows his visitor understands very little. This is perhaps the sign of the newly converted, which in a sense is what Mr. DuBowski is, a Jewish man who became more religious as he worked on his film.</p>
        <p>He also seems to lack a pause button for the moments between thought and speech. He mentions, in passing, that his cellphone has not worked since he put it on a ledge while he was taking a shower and it fell in the toilet. He took the phone into the bathroom? That must have been some important call he was waiting for.</p>
        <p>''No, it's just a whirlwind of calls these days, dealing with people with needs.''</p>
        <p>Mr. DuBowski, you're a director now, people are supposed to be worrying about your needs.</p>
        <p>But the filmmaker on the sagging couch is suddenly serious.</p>
        <p>''I'm the director slash support group slash matchmaker. I'm -- look, when I started the film I don't think I anticipated what would be required, the desperate situations people are in. I'm meeting people who have been kicked out of yeshiva, abandoned by Orthodox families. It became clear that this was much more than being director of a film. There was a whole voice of people who had never had a voice.''</p>
        <p>MR. DUBOWSKI did not come from an Orthodox home. He grew up in what he calls ''deep coastal Brooklyn,'' Manhattan Beach, and his family went to the synagogue only on holidays. Mr. DuBowski attended public schools, graduated Harvard magna cum laude. He was always attracted to men, although he did not have the click of realization until college, when he saw two men, holding hands, heading into a gay dance. He recalled how, moments later, a group of young men in the vicinity yelled, ''faggot,'' and attacked him. He told his mother he was homosexual the same year.</p>
        <p>''There was about 45 minutes first of making sure she loved me.  My room looked like a lunar landscape with all these little rolled up Kleenex of tears on the floor.''</p>
        <p>What about Mr. DuBowski's father?</p>
        <p>''I didn't tell him. Then when my mother didn't eat or sleep for three days he said, 'Rima, what's wrong?' It wasn't easy for them at first.'' Mr. DuBowski made a film about his grandmother using the family camcorder and supported himself as a researcher at Planned Parenthood. Later, at an international conference of lesbian and gay Jews, he met a young man who had been thrown out of his yeshiva because he was gay. Over the years, he interviewed hundreds of homosexual men and women who were or had been Orthodox. He also sought out rabbis. Often, he was rebuffed. In Israel, he approached a leading rabbi to say he was there with the pain of Jews who felt abandoned by their religion. He asked what the rabbi could say to help them. The rabbi offered two words: ''animalistic'' and ''abomination.''</p>
        <p>Now Mr. DuBowski has been showing his film, still often in secret, in the homes of Orthodox Jews. Often, there are discussion groups. He is particularly proud of a Sabbath dinner he hosted with Rabbi Steven Greenberg, a gay Orthodox rabbi, at the Berlin Film Festival.</p>
        <p>''There were German gay Christians and gay Jews, all kinds of people,'' Mr. DuBowski says. ''And this old guy with a heavy accent, a Holocaust survivor, got up and told a story. He said when he was a boy, at Yom Kippur, there would be men, standing alone, at the back of the synagogue, praying and crying. He asked his father who they were and his father said they were the rashas, the evil ones. He said, 'Now, seeing this film, I understand what they were. And I want to tell you, you are all welcome.' And Steven cried.''</p>
        <p>PUBLIC LIVES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
