<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Richter's Play Overshadows Teammates' Career Marks</title>
    <meta content="30RANG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/30/sports/hockey/30RANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1338457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Dallas Stars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Dallas Stars</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Richter, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D81430F933A05753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="855" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Richter's Play Overshadows Teammates' Career Marks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Richter's Play Overshadows Teammates' Career Marks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers defeat Dallas Stars, 4-2, at Madison Square Garden; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The milestones just kept on coming at Madison Square Garden last night as the Rangers, behind another sterling effort from goaltender Mike Richter, moved above .500 with a 4-2 victory over the Dallas Stars.</p>
        <p>With two assists, Theo Fleury reached 1,000 points in his career. Mark Messier picked up his 1,135th career assist to tie his former Edmonton Oilers teammate Paul Coffey for fourth on the N.H.L. list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The milestones just kept on coming on Monday night as the Rangers, behind another sterling effort from goaltender Mike Richter, moved above .500 with a win over the Dallas Stars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The milestones just kept on coming at Madison Square Garden last night as the Rangers, behind another sterling effort from goaltender Mike Richter, moved above .500 with a 4-2 victory over the Dallas Stars.</p>
        <p>With two assists, Theo Fleury reached 1,000 points in his career. Mark Messier picked up his 1,135th career assist to tie his former Edmonton Oilers teammate Paul Coffey for fourth on the N.H.L. list.</p>
        <p>The Rangers even scored a power-play goal, their first in six games after an 0-for-25 span.</p>
        <p>All of this, plus two goals from Mike York and 36 stops by Richter, enabled the Rangers to overcome a pair of one-goal deficits, not to mention another glaring disparity in shots on goal: the Rangers (6-5-1-0) were outshot by 38-23 but won their second straight game.</p>
        <p>They were able to do so mainly because of Richter, who was again stingy in goal two nights after stopping 45 shots in a 2-1 overtime victory against Boston.</p>
        <p>''The last two games it's been just vintage Richter,'' Messier said.</p>
        <p>Coach Ron Low agreed. ''Ricky out and out stole that game for us the other night in Boston,'' he said. ''And tonight, he was as good as he had to be. Him being on both legs and healthy is huge for our hockey club.''</p>
        <p>The 35-year-old Richter, who is coming off reconstructive knee surgery, found himself under fire from the start of last night's game. The Stars outshot the Rangers by 15-4 in the first period, but the Rangers somehow managed to take a 1-1 tie into the first intermission.</p>
        <p>They allowed the first goal of the game for the 10th time in 12 games. Brenden Morrow scored it, his fourth of the season, 7 minutes 41 seconds into the game, off the rebound of a Richard Matvichuk shot. York's first goal, at 13:37 of the first, tied the score at 1-1. The goal came at the end of a long shift, in which York, Fleury and Eric Lindros had been pinned in their own end. Lindros was finally able to clear the puck, chipping it out along the boards.</p>
        <p>What had started out as a clearing attempt, however, turned into a two-on-one rush for the Rangers. As Lindros headed to the bench for a line change behind the play, Fleury scooped the puck onto his stick behind the Dallas defense, kept himself onside into the offensive zone, then found York sprinting up the middle.</p>
        <p>In a moment of improvisation, York slammed on the brakes in front of Dallas goaltender Ed Belfour. As Belfour committed himself to the ice, and as defenseman Brad Lukowich skated helplessly past York, York pirouetted clockwise at the top of the crease, then swept a backhander past the prone Belfour.</p>
        <p>Dallas (4-4-2-2) went up by 2-1 at 3:15 of the second on the power play when Pierre Turgeon stuffed in a loose puck for his fourth goal of the season. By the midway point of the period, the Rangers had been outshot by 25-5. But York, who was teamed with Fleury on the penalty-killing unit for the first time this season, tied the score at 2-2 at 12:49, seconds after a Dallas power play had expired. Fleury made the play happen by forcing Derian Hatcher to turn the puck over at the Dallas blue line. Belfour made the initial stop on a rising shot by Fleury. But York chipped the rebound home to give Fleury his 1,000th point in his 960th N.H.L. game.</p>
        <p>''For a guy who wasn't even supposed to play in the N.H.L.,'' said the 33-year-old Fleury, referring to his 5-foot-6-inch frame, ''I don't know if I'm just old or what. But the way this whole thing came about means more to me than anything. I think it just makes it extra special.''</p>
        <p>The last reference was to Fleury's treatment last season for alcohol and substance abuse.</p>
        <p>Messier's milestone came with his assist on Sandy McCarthy's first goal of the season at 15:19 of the second. The goal gave the Rangers the lead for good.</p>
        <p>''I haven't really thought about those kind of stats personally,'' said Messier, who will turn 41 in January. ''I never really considered myself a natural goal scorer or point getter. I guess with the longevity I've had and the amount of games I've played, those sort of statistics go hand in hand. But I'm not looking back and reminiscing right now.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers definitely did not look back from there.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>The Dallas Stars donated $130,000 to firefighter relief efforts arising from the Sept. 11 attack.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
