<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Transactions</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="754294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DA1F38F933A25757C0A963958260" item-length="524" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Transactions</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Baseball  American League</p>
        <p>BALTIMORE ORIOLES -- Agreed to terms with and Kevin Brown, Joe Borowski, Russell Brock, Jimmy Haynes, Doug Jones, Scott Klingenbeck, Rick Krivda, Jesse Orosco, Billy Percibal, Brian Sackinsky, pitchers; Paul Carey, first baseman; Alex Ochoa, Jim Wawruck, outfielder; and Gregg Zaun, catcher, on one-year contracts. Placed Mark Eichhorn, pitcher, on the 15-day disabled list. Shifted Eichhorn from the 15- to the 60-day disabled list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Baseball  American League</p>
        <p>BALTIMORE ORIOLES -- Agreed to terms with and Kevin Brown, Joe Borowski, Russell Brock, Jimmy Haynes, Doug Jones, Scott Klingenbeck, Rick Krivda, Jesse Orosco, Billy Percibal, Brian Sackinsky, pitchers; Paul Carey, first baseman; Alex Ochoa, Jim Wawruck, outfielder; and Gregg Zaun, catcher, on one-year contracts. Placed Mark Eichhorn, pitcher, on the 15-day disabled list. Shifted Eichhorn from the 15- to the 60-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>BOSTON RED SOX -- Agreed to terms with Mike Macfarlane, catcher; Reggie Jefferson, first baseman; and Stan Belinda, pitcher, on one-year contracts, and Mike Hartley, pitcher, on a minor-league contract. Traded Scott Cooper, third baseman; Cory Bailey, pitcher; and a player to be named to St. Louis for Rheal Cormier, pitcher, and Mark Whiten, outfielder.</p>
        <p>CALIFORNIA ANGELS -- Agreed to terms with Bob Patterson, pitcher; Rene Gonzales, infielder, and Rob Deer, outfielder, on minor-league contracts.</p>
        <p>CHICAGO WHITE SOX -- Agreed to terms with Jim Abbott, pitcher, and Mike Devereaux, outfielder, on one-year contracts.</p>
        <p>CLEVELAND INDIANS -- Agreed to terms with Orel Hershiser, pitcher, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>DETROIT TIGERS -- Agreed to terms with Alan Trammell, shortstop, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>KANSAS CITY ROYALS -- Agreed to terms with Tom Browning, pitcher, and Chris James, outfielder, on one-year contracts and Jose DeJesus, pitcher, on a minor-league contract.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK YANKEES -- Agreed to terms with Dion James, outfielder, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>OAKLAND ATHLETICS -- Agreed to terms with Dave Stewart, pitcher, on a one-year contract, and Rick Honeycutt, pitcher, on a minor-league contract.</p>
        <p>SEATTLE MARINERS -- Agreed to terms with Rich Amaral and Greg Pirkl, infielders, and Bob Wells, pitcher, on one-year contracts. Designated Chris Howard, catcher, for assignment.</p>
        <p>TEXAS RANGERS -- Agreed to terms with Bob Tewksbury, pitcher, on a one-year contract. National League</p>
        <p>CHICAGO CUBS -- Agreed to terms with Jaime Navarro, pitcher, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI REDS -- Agreed to terms with Mike Jackson, pitcher, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>COLORADO ROCKIES -- Agreed to terms with Larry Walker, outfielder, on a four-year contract; Bill Swift, pitcher, on a three-year contract and Omar Olivares, pitcher, on a one-year contract. Designated Marcus Moore, pitcher, for assignment.</p>
        <p>FLORIDA MARLINS -- Agreed to terms with John Burkett, pitcher, on a two-year contract and Bobby Witt, pitcher, and Andre Dawson, outfielder, on one-year contracts.</p>
        <p>NEW YORK METS -- Agreed to terms Robert Person and Hector Ramirez, pitchers, and Omar Garcia, first baseman, on one-year contracts.</p>
        <p>PHILADELPHIA PHILLIES -- Agreed to terms with Dave Gallagher, outfielder, and Jose Melendez, pitcher, on minor-league contracts.</p>
        <p>PITTSBURGH PIRATES -- Designated Roberto Ramirez, pitcher, for assignment.</p>
        <p>ST. LOUIS CARDINALS -- Agreed to terms with Bernard Gilkey, outfielder, on a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS -- Agreed to terms with Mark Leiter and Terry Mulholland, pitchers, and Glenallen Hill, infielder, on a one-year contract.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
