<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fujimori Is Well Ahead in an Election Exit Poll in Peru</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="754315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRAUDS AND SWINDLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PERU</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SIMS, CALVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUJIMORI, ALBERTO K (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEREZ DE CUELLAR, JAVIER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DB113BF933A25757C0A963958260" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fujimori Is Well Ahead in an Election Exit Poll in Peru</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CALVIN SIMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SIMS, CALVIN</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, April 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Alberto K. Fujimori appeared poised to win a second term in Peru's elections today, according to an early and unofficial survey of voters leaving polling places, but rival candidates continued to charge that the voting had been compromised by fraud.</p>
        <p>A national exit poll by the Apoyo group, Peru's leading polling organization, indicated that Mr. Fujimori had won 61 percent of all votes, thus avoiding a second round of balloting. Final results will not be known until Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Alberto K. Fujimori appeared poised to win a second term in Peru's elections today, according to an early and unofficial survey of voters leaving polling places, but rival candidates continued to charge that the voting had been compromised by fraud.</p>
        <p>A national exit poll by the Apoyo group, Peru's leading polling organization, indicated that Mr. Fujimori had won 61 percent of all votes, thus avoiding a second round of balloting. Final results will not be known until Monday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fujimori's closest rival, Javier Perez de Cuellar, a former Secretary General of the United Nations, had less than half as many votes, with 26 percent, the exit survey indicated. Twelve other candidates split the remainder of the votes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perez de Cuellar and five other candidates said Saturday night in a letter delivered to an observer team of the Organization of American States that they believed the election had been tainted by a ballot fraud scheme uncovered on Thursday in the city of Huanuco, about 150 miles northeast of Lima. Fifteen people were arrested for trying to alter more than 3,000 voting tally sheets in advance of the election,</p>
        <p>Mr. Perez de Cuellar said that he had received information that the fraud extended to other cities across the country and that he believed Mr. Fujimori was directly involved because the tally sheets were discovered at the home of a top organizer of Mr. Fujimori's party, Change 90 -- New Majority.</p>
        <p>But Peru's National Election Board said Saturday night that the Huanuco fraud was an isolated case and the work of common criminals trying to earn extra money.</p>
        <p>"Inexplicably, the National Elections Board has reduced the fraud to a criminal act supposedly meant to favor congressional candidates, exempting the principal beneficiary of the fraud, President Alberto Fujimori, from any responsibility," the rival candidates said in the letter.</p>
        <p>Carlos Chipoco, Mr. Perez de Cuellar's campaign manager, said in a television interview this afternoon that the exit polls were just that: "exit polls that have been shown to be wrong before."</p>
        <p>Local and international observers said that voting at polling places across Peru was orderly today and that there was no immediate evidence of fraud, although many polling centers opened an hour later than the scheduled 8 A.M.</p>
        <p>"Today, we had a quiet process," said Santiago Murray, head of the O.A.S.'s observer team. "All the reports I am getting from the field are normal irregularities that happen on every voting day."</p>
        <p>Mr. Murray said the O.A.S. was "very concerned" about the voter fraud case in Huanuco but that the group was convinced the Government had acted quickly and responsibly in investigating it.</p>
        <p>More than 100,000 army troops and national police officers were posted at polling places in Lima and other major cities and rural areas to guard against possible fraud and terrorist attacks, but no major incidents were reported.</p>
        <p>"At this time, we can say that this has been more or less a clean election with a few minor irregularities in the opening of voting centers, but this we don't feel will affect the outcome," said Orlando Moro, a spokesman for Transparencia, a local good government group.</p>
        <p>Opinion polls taken days before the vote showed Mr. Fujimori well ahead, and political analysts attributed his seeming victory to his success in revitalizing Peru's economy and crushing the Shining Path guerrilla insurgency.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perez de Cuellar campaigned on a theme of creating new jobs and social programs for the poor but his crusade was eclipsed by Peru's border war with Ecuador in February and tactical mistakes, like starting his campaign too late and failing to establish himself as a viable alternative to Mr. Fujimori.</p>
        <p>In San Juan de Lugrigancho, a large shantytown where residents waited in long lines to vote, Juan Rudas, 32, a ceramics worker, said he voted for Mr. Fujimori because of the "peace and economic opportunity he has brought to Peru." Asked if he was concerned about the allegations of voter fraud, Mr. Rudas said: "I don't think Fujimori was involved. It's a local situation that the other candidates are exaggerating to try and win."</p>
        <p>In the middle-class Lima neighborhood of Jesus Maria, Maria Rojas, 21, said, "Perez de Cuellar is an excellent man and a great diplomat, but I voted for Fujimori, principally because of the peace he has brought to Peru."</p>
        <p>Voting is mandatory in Peru, and failure to do so can lead to a $17 fine, a large sum for a worker who earns the minimum wage of $45 a month.</p>
        <p>In the legislative race, the Apoyo exit poll indicated that Mr. Fujimori's Change 90 party had won 46 percent of the 120 congressional seats and Mr. Perez de Cuellar's party, Union for Peru, 16 percent. The remainder went to other parties.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
