<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Confusion Over Tax Law, Don't Overlook Some Changes</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="832405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR TAXES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOULD, CAROLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EFD71039F936A15751C0A960958260" item-length="1262" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Confusion Over Tax Law, Don't Overlook Some Changes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE GOULD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOULD, CAROLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WITH the nation's tax rules in seemingly constant flux, even tax professionals are occasionally tripped up. Ask Nadine Gordon Lee, a partner with Ernst &amp; Young, the Big Six accounting firm in New York.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lee, a mother of two boys, prepared the paperwork and paid the Federal unemployment tax for her baby sitter in January, when she received the forms in the mail from the Internal Revenue Service. She had grown accustomed to the quarterly blizzard of paperwork needed to pay Social Security and unemployment taxes for baby sitters and other domestic employees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WITH the nation's tax rules in seemingly constant flux, even tax professionals are occasionally tripped up. Ask Nadine Gordon Lee, a partner with Ernst &amp; Young, the Big Six accounting firm in New York.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lee, a mother of two boys, prepared the paperwork and paid the Federal unemployment tax for her baby sitter in January, when she received the forms in the mail from the Internal Revenue Service. She had grown accustomed to the quarterly blizzard of paperwork needed to pay Social Security and unemployment taxes for baby sitters and other domestic employees.</p>
        <p>So it completely slipped her mind that there is a new, simpler way to do it: complete the new Schedule H as part of your tax return and make those payments along with your income tax.</p>
        <p>But having filed the old way, Ms. Lee said that it would not be simple for her, at least not this year. "I'm expecting to get into a long letter-writing campaign with the I.R.S. to get the tax I already paid offset against what I owe," she said.</p>
        <p>Here are some other recently changed areas that tax professionals say many people may stumble over, as well as perennial snares. Being alert to them can help you pay as little as possible on April 15 and avoid trouble with the I.R.S.</p>
        <p>If you are self-employed and not covered by your spouse's health insurance, do not overlook or understate the deduction for your health insurance premium. That would be easy to do, because after letting the insurance deduction for the  self-employed lapse at the end of 1993, Congress reinstated it retroactively, and increased the size of the deduction to 30 percent of the premium amount for  1995, from 25 percent previously.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, eligible people who did not claim the deduction for 1994 may do  so by filing an amended 1994 return, 1040X, using the 25 percent figure.</p>
        <p>Be sure to get a Social Security number for your baby. Seeking to reduce fraud, the I.R.S. has whittled away the age at which Social Security numbers are required for dependent children, and the number of children claimed as dependents has dropped in tandem. Now Social Security numbers are needed for children two months or older to claim them as dependents on returns, compared with two years previously.</p>
        <p>Take any business deductions for travel, meals and entertainment to which you are entitled, even if some of the small receipts have been lost. In an audit the I.R.S. could demand to see receipts for business expenses of $25 or more until last Oct. 1. After that, receipts are required only for expenses of $75 or more. You still need a business diary to back up the expense by stating reasons, location, date and who was entertained.</p>
        <p>The maximum earned income tax credit has increased for families of all sizes  -- although only by $8 for the childless -- and the amount you can earn and still qualify for the credit has increased. More military personnel will qualify, but many nonresident aliens are cut off. Beginning with 1996, you cannot claim the earned income credit if you have investment income of more than $2,350.</p>
        <p>Be careful not to overpay taxes on mutual fund dividends reported on Form 1099. Ordinary dividends are indeed taxable at your marginal rate -- up to 39.6  percent -- but the gross dividends figure sometimes includes capital gains generated by a fund's sale of securities, said Jeff J. Saccacio, the West Coast  partner in charge of personal financial planning services for Coopers &amp; Lybrand, a Big Six accounting firm, in Los Angeles. And capital gains are taxed at a top  rate of 28 percent.</p>
        <p>Furthermore, you owe no tax on any "return of capital" dividends. So it pays  to read all the details on the 1099 to sort out exactly what kind of dividends are being reported.</p>
        <p>Don't ignore incorrect 1099 statements. The I.R.S. cross-checks nearly every  dividend and interest payment reported by taxpayers against the amounts reported by the banks and financial institutions that paid them. When they do not match, the I.R.S. computer kicks out a return for a closer look, and the examiner might find something else to question.</p>
        <p>What is the best solution? Write the bank or other payer and have it issue a  corrected 1099. When there is not enough time to do that, Ms. Lee advised, write the correct figure on your return and then attach an explanatory schedule to the return.</p>
        <p>Even if you do not have the money to pay the taxes you owe, be sure to file your return, or a request for an automatic extension, by April 15. Failing to file could cost you a bundle unnecessarily, Ms. Lee said. If you do not file on  time, you will owe an I.R.S. penalty of 5 percent of the unpaid taxes a month up to a maximum of 25 percent, plus taxes and interest. If you file without paying  what you owe, the penalty is just a half-percent a month plus taxes and interest on whatever is owed.</p>
        <p>If you pay or receive alimony, remember that it is taxable income to the recipient and an above-the-line deduction for the payer. The I.R.S. cross-checks nearly all alimony payments because Social Security numbers are required. People who fail to report income are likely to be audited and owe not only taxes but also penalties and interest.</p>
        <p>If you own or rent a pied-a-terre in town or a vacation home elsewhere, bone  up on the legalities of residency and keep careful records to avoid being taxed  as a resident unexpectedly. It is possible legally to be a resident of two or more cities or states.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lee had clients who lived in Westchester County, N.Y., but also bought a  small apartment in Manhattan, where they worked. They used the apartment only 8  to 15 days a year, but had to pay resident income taxes in New York City, which  considers anyone a resident who has a home in town and is present more than 183  days a year; part of a day counts.</p>
        <p>Do not automatically file joint tax returns if you are married. True, married filing jointly will generally result in a lower total tax bill, but if one spouse has a lot of medical or itemized expenses, filing separate returns might  lower the liability. That is because medical expenses are permitted only to the  extent that they exceed 7.5 percent of adjusted gross income; miscellaneous itemized deductions like unreimbursed business expenses and union dues are allowed only to the extent they exceed 2 percent of adjusted gross income. The only way to be sure is calculate both ways.</p>
        <p>Finally, if filing at the last minute, do not send your return to the I.R.S.  by Federal Express or a similar overnight delivery service. By law, tax returns  are considered filed when mailed, even if the I.R.S. receives them several days  after April 15. If the United States Postal Service is not used, a return is not legally filed until it is delivered to the I.R.S.</p>
        <p>YOUR TAXES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
