<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teaching Musicians How to Keep Their Bodies in Tune</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="832660"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HACKLEY SCHOOL (TARRYTOWN, NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHENSON, ROBERTA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAIRBANKS, VICTORIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3DE1139F936A15751C0A960958260" item-length="573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teaching Musicians How to Keep Their Bodies in Tune</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHENSON, ROBERTA</byline>
      <dateline>TARRYTOWN</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEARNING to play an instrument can be a struggle not only with notes and rhythms but also with aching arms, necks and backs. The pain may be caused by poor posture or unconscious tension. Some musicians have found relief -- and a path to better playing -- with the Alexander Technique, which stresses awareness of the body as a key to well being.</p>
        <p>Victoria Fairbanks, a private practitioner of the method who lives in Tappan, teaches students at the Hackley Music Institute here that creative energy is best released by a body in harmony with itself. Clad in flowing velvets, the native of London arrived recently at the institute, a division of the Hackley School, with a bag full of styrofoam pillows and cotton sheets. Then she assembled a group of high school musicians on stage and began a session.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEARNING to play an instrument can be a struggle not only with notes and rhythms but also with aching arms, necks and backs. The pain may be caused by poor posture or unconscious tension. Some musicians have found relief -- and a path to better playing -- with the Alexander Technique, which stresses awareness of the body as a key to well being.</p>
        <p>Victoria Fairbanks, a private practitioner of the method who lives in Tappan, teaches students at the Hackley Music Institute here that creative energy is best released by a body in harmony with itself. Clad in flowing velvets, the native of London arrived recently at the institute, a division of the Hackley School, with a bag full of styrofoam pillows and cotton sheets. Then she assembled a group of high school musicians on stage and began a session.</p>
        <p>The students all attended Hackley, although the institute, which offers private instruction by an adjunct faculty of 16, is also open to the community.  The faculty will give its first concert March 16 at 3 P.M. at the school to raise for a trip to Europe for the students.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fairbanks began by asking the students to remove their shoes. Then, as they played scale patterns on their string and wind instruments, she moved from  one to the other, whispering in their ears and touching tense necks, backs and calves. The touches were a reminder of her suggestions, she said, explaining later: "You want the body to remember, not just the head. The body is learning,  too."</p>
        <p>Her voice barely rose above a whisper, even when addressing the group. "Let your feet feel free on the floor," she said. "Your toes need to be completely relaxed. Don't sink down when the sound goes down."</p>
        <p>Lifting a flutist's arm, she said: "Let's let our elbows float. Do any of you sense any tension in your elbows? If you free your elbows up, you'll see your diaphragms are freer."</p>
        <p>Then the students lay down daisy fashion, with their heads nearly meeting. In hushed tones, Ms. Fairbanks spoke of "coming into the stillness" and feeling "the architecture of the body." Knowing that the students were in the middle of  exams, she said, "This isn't really for your music -- this is for your life."</p>
        <p>After that exercise, the students found it easier to play their scales. "There is a difference," David Erickson, a violinist, said. "My legs don't buckle."</p>
        <p>Adam Rosen, an oboist, sounded astonished. "My entire body feels open and relaxed," he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Fairbanks talked later about some common bad habits. "A lot of kids lock  their knees and lock their pelvis," she said. "I want them to come up off their  pelvis. I want more openness."</p>
        <p>Susannah Smith, a flutist, said she was appalled at a picture she had seen of herself playing. "My neck was out like this," she said, pushing her head forward. Her knees hurt sometimes, she added. Ms. Fairbanks gave her a private lesson, full of whispers and gentle touches.</p>
        <p>"Think open," Ms. Fairbanks said. "Say 'ahhh' and feel the vibration in your  diaphragm."</p>
        <p>Text and photographs</p>
        <p>By ROBERTA HERSHENSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
