<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Watches as Palestinians Drop Call for Israel's Destruction</title>
    <meta content="15MIDE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1069970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="CLINTON IN THE MIDEAST: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Palestine Liberation Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Netanyahu, Benjamin (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sontag, Deborah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EFDE153DF936A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="1286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Watches as Palestinians Drop Call for Israel's Destruction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBORAH SONTAG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sontag, Deborah</byline>
      <dateline>GAZA, Dec. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hundreds of former Palestinian guerrilla fighters, with Pres Clinton in midst in Gaza, vote to rid Palestinian charter of all clauses calling for destruction of Israel, removing critical roadblock to peace; are congratulated by Clinton, who expresses honor to be first American President to address Palestinians in city governed by Palestinians; Clinton says vote is challenge to Israel; is warmly welcomed by Palestinians, who turn visit into celebration of imminent statehood and US endorsement of it; Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat revels in moment; both he and Clinton stage ribbon-cutting inauguration of passenger terminal at new Gaza international airport; Israel's Prime Min Benjamin Netanyahu hails vote; describes it as real and very positive change, but says he will not agree to meet December 18 deadline to return more land to Palestinians, who must comply with more Israeli demands for change; will meet with Clinton and Arafat on December 15 at Erez checkpoint between Israel and Gaza; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With President  Clinton as their witness, hundreds of former Palestinian guerrilla fighters voted here today to rid their organization's charter of any clauses calling for the destruction of Israel, knocking down a critical roadblock on the rutted path to peace.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel said he accepted the vote, a show of hands before a worldwide television audience, as ''a real change, a very positive change.'' But he added that he would not agree to meet the Friday deadline to return more land to the Palestinians until they complied with more Israeli demands for change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With President  Clinton as their witness, hundreds of former Palestinian guerrilla fighters voted here today to rid their organization's charter of any clauses calling for the destruction of Israel, knocking down a critical roadblock on the rutted path to peace.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel said he accepted the vote, a show of hands before a worldwide television audience, as ''a real change, a very positive change.'' But he added that he would not agree to meet the Friday deadline to return more land to the Palestinians until they complied with more Israeli demands for change.</p>
        <p>In the interest of breaking stalemates on such other sensitive issues as the Israeli release of Palestinian prisoners, a three-way meeting between Mr. Clinton, Mr. Netanyahu and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, was scheduled for Tuesday morning at the Erez checkpoint between Israel and Gaza.</p>
        <p>With a flurry of fingers, some barely held aloft, some thrust into the air with exhilaration, the vote here today signaled a watershed moment for the Palestinians -- partly because it represented a new political pragmatism and partly because it was overseen by Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Playing preacher and healer, the American President presided over what amounted to a large reunion of the Palestine Liberation Organization at the moment of its public transformation from outlaw group to a nearly sovereign entity and a diplomatic partner of the United States.</p>
        <p>''I am profoundly honored to be the first American President to address the Palestinian people in a city governed by Palestinians,'' Mr. Clinton said, bringing hundreds to their feet, as he congratulated them on the vote.</p>
        <p>''By turning this page on the past, you are taking the lead in writing a new story for the future,'' he said. ''And you have issued a challenge to the Government and the leaders of Israel to walk down that path with you.''</p>
        <p>In the isolated, hardscrabble Gaza Strip, the Palestinians pulled out all the stops today to make Mr. Clinton's visit a celebration of imminent statehood and endorsement by the United States. ''We have a dream same as you,'' read posters pinned to trees, lampposts and donkeys' saddlebags.</p>
        <p>American and Palestinian flags fluttered side by side on every available pole -- from the huge hand-sewn flags that draped the control towers at the new Palestinian airport, where Mr. Clinton landed in his Marine One helicopter, to the paper flags in the hands of schoolchildren along the route of the motorcade.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arafat reveled in the moment, which both he and the Americans called historic many times. The flowery language flowed. ''This ancient city that receives you today has not seen many happy days during its  history,'' Mr. Arafat said. ''But your presence here made us relive the golden days of Palestine.''</p>
        <p>At a ceremony to inaugurate the passenger terminal at the new airport, he prolonged the ribbon-cutting so that mementos could be produced.</p>
        <p>In a somewhat comic interplay that lasted several minutes, before viewing stands packed with dignitaries, Mr. Arafat held the red ribbon steady while Mr. Clinton cut off strip after strip for posterity.</p>
        <p>Not everyone was impressed by the pomp, though. One of those was Mamoun Tamimi, who traveled from Jordan to vote against the change in the covenant. ''We should not give a freebie to Israel,'' he said. ''We should link it with a deal that Israel should recognize our state and we will recognize theirs.''</p>
        <p>Still, the events of the day in Gaza were preprogrammed, and there was no surprise when the Palestine National Council, together with other Palestinian leaders, raised their hands in support of Mr. Arafat's decision to amend the charter.</p>
        <p>It was nonetheless a delicate day of diplomacy for the Americans, since Mr. Netanyahu's acceptance could not be guaranteed. Mr. Clinton risked a failed trip, which would have been an untimely defeat for him. But, given the unrest in the West Bank for the last few weeks, the larger cost of such a failure would have been a collapse of the peace effort itself.</p>
        <p>Nahum Barnea, an Israeli newspaper columnist, said the looming challenge for the Americans was ''how to conclude their visit without leaving the country in flames.''</p>
        <p>Pronouncing the visit to Gaza a success, Secretary of State Madeleine K. Albright made it clear that the Americans believe that the Palestinians, in voting, met a crucial demand of the Israelis, and that the Israelis would be called upon to comply with their own promises, too.</p>
        <p>''The important thing is the Israelis wanted this P.N.C. action to take place,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Netanyahu said he did feel vindicated by today's vote. ''They told us it was impossible, and if you insist on it, you're jamming the process,'' he said. But, he said, that proved that he could hold firm on the other demands, ''and in the same way try to achieve the other changes.''</p>
        <p>Six days before he faces potential doom in a no-confidence vote by the  Parliament, Mr. Netanyahu is considered loath to make sudden moves forward on the peace agreement that cost him his right-wing support.</p>
        <p>The Palestine National Council was the Palestine Liberation Organization's leadership in exile. This marked only its third meeting on its home ground in the last 25 years. The first took place in Jerusalem in 1964, before Israel annexed the eastern part of the city.</p>
        <p>The second occurred in Gaza just two years ago, and it was convened to do just what the leaders did today: annul the offending clauses in the P.L.O. charter. Although the Americans and the previous Israeli administration accepted those results, the Israelis pointed to the continued inclusion of the clauses in copies of the charter. They also said the vote should be loud and public to send a message to the Palestinian people.</p>
        <p>For the Palestinians, today's vote, attended by about 500 of an estimated 650 members of the Palestine National Council, did not represent a newly felt renunciation of hostile feelings. It was a pragmatic move, most said, to appease Mr. Clinton by satisfying Mr. Netanyahu.</p>
        <p>''Three years ago, I voted in favor, but today it's time to put an end to Mr. Netanyahu's excuses,'' said Hani al-Hassan, a member of Mr. Arafat's Fatah party. ''We have to call his bluff. So I voted for.''</p>
        <p>A student from the Islamic University, Mohammed Salah, 22, said the vote itself, even if it produces a breakthrough in the stalemated peace efforts, was not terribly significant. ''The charter is not a substantial issue for us,'' Mr. Salah said. ''Most people knew nothing about this charter until the Israelis brought it to our attention. What was substantial was President Clinton's visit because it sends many signs. It is a recognition. Clearly, we are not considered anymore a people whom nobody wants to recognize.''</p>
        <p>With his special blend of empathy and stern counsel, Mr. Clinton endorsed the Palestinian struggle, saying he felt the pain of their ''dispossession'' from their land. But he advised the Palestinians to feel empathy for the Israelis' point of view as well, and suggested that Palestinian children not be taught to glorify suicide bombers.</p>
        <p>''Our great American prophet, Martin Luther King, once said, 'The old law of an eye for an eye leaves everyone blind.' '' he said. It was one remark that went unapplauded by the Palestinians gathered in Gaza.</p>
        <p>CLINTON IN THE MIDEAST: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
