<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Bonds Trade Lower On Fresh Data</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="787245"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURTADO, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDA133FF93BA3575AC0A963958260" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Bonds Trade Lower On Fresh Data</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HURTADO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HURTADO, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bonds traded lower yesterday, as investors reacted to both fresh economic data and comments by a Federal Reserve official.</p>
        <p>"The market is in a sideways drift that seems destined to hold into next week," said James Hales, a fixed-income analyst with MMS International in San Francisco. "Day traders see the risk-reward of trading this market as unappealing right now. To them, the bull market is tired and not worth chasing." He said people trying to short it lately had been burned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bonds traded lower yesterday, as investors reacted to both fresh economic data and comments by a Federal Reserve official.</p>
        <p>"The market is in a sideways drift that seems destined to hold into next week," said James Hales, a fixed-income analyst with MMS International in San Francisco. "Day traders see the risk-reward of trading this market as unappealing right now. To them, the bull market is tired and not worth chasing." He said people trying to short it lately had been burned.</p>
        <p>Initial unemployment claims shrank last week for the first time in a month, signaling to some in the market that economic growth was stronger than expected. That could entail a possible risk of accelerating inflation, which would leave the Fed little reason to cut interest rates again.</p>
        <p>That sent the benchmark Treasury bond down, but it rebounded as some market participants concluded that the economy was not growing at a fast enough pace to press the inflation-alert button just yet.</p>
        <p>Analysts said another economic report showing that nonfarm productivity shot up 4.8 percent at a seasonally adjusted annual rate from April through June indicated a lack of underlying inflation pressures; rather, it showed businesses were producing more goods and services with fewer workers.</p>
        <p>Still, the 30-year bond fell 6/32 of a percentage point, to 103 19/32 ; its yield, which moves in the opposite direction from its price, rose to 6.60 percent, from 6.58 percent on Wednesday. Intermediate-term and short-term issues were off as well.</p>
        <p>Jobless claims for the week ended Sept. 2 fell by 10,000, to 339,000. Traders had expected claims to slip by only 1,000. The four-week moving average, which takes the volatility out of the weekly data, rose to 343,500 from a revised 341,750.</p>
        <p>Kathleen Stephensen, senior economist at Donaldson, Lufkin &amp; Jenrette, noted that since the jobless data for the week ended Sept. 2 were collected during a shortened business week, because of the coming Labor Day holiday, the drop of 10,000 claimants for the weekly survey might be subject to a substantial revision with next week's report.</p>
        <p>James Hale, at MMS International, said, "There continues to be talk of flows out of mortgages and into Treasury securities supporting the long end of the market, as prepayment adjustments cause duration of mortgage portfolios to shorten." A large West Coast institutional money manager bought between $500 million and $1 billion of 30-year Treasuries early in the session, and that may have been the motivation.</p>
        <p>Some of the market's selling yesterday was attributed to comments by Robert T. Parry, president of the San Francisco Fed. Speaking in Boise, Idaho, before directors of the Salt Lake City, Seattle and Portland, Ore., branches of the Federal Reserve System, he said the economy would soon recover from its recent slow growth. He added that the second-quarter gross domestic product figures were not so weak as they appeared on the surface.</p>
        <p>Mr. Parry also said that the current unemployment rate, 5.6 percent in August, was below the lowest level that could be sustained for long without raising the risk of accelerating inflation. The so-called natural rate of unemployment is "closer to 6 percent," he said.</p>
        <p>Traders said the comments suggested to some in the market that the central bank would not be compelled to cut rates further in order to stimulate the economy, which appears to be gathering strength on its own.</p>
        <p>Traders and investors should get more insight into the pace of inflation next week, when the Government releases data on last month's producer and consumer prices.  CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
