<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Owners Aiming to Keep Raiders in L.A.</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="764475"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL FOOTBALL LEAGUE (NFL)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES RAIDERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEORGE, THOMAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Oakland Raiders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DD113EF930A15756C0A963958260" item-length="552" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Owners Aiming to Keep Raiders in L.A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GEORGE, THOMAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Few rivalries in the National Football League compare with the Raiders and Chiefs, a colorful affair full of big games and big plays and Hall of Fame players.</p>
        <p>When it comes to the Raiders' shaky stadium situation, however, the Chiefs join the rest of the league in wanting one thing for the Raiders: to stay in Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Few rivalries in the National Football League compare with the Raiders and Chiefs, a colorful affair full of big games and big plays and Hall of Fame players.</p>
        <p>When it comes to the Raiders' shaky stadium situation, however, the Chiefs join the rest of the league in wanting one thing for the Raiders: to stay in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>"The Raiders have been very successful in a big part of the National Football League and it is true that our rivalry has been special over the years," the Chiefs' owner, Lamar Hunt, said. "But here it is May and they haven't started season-ticket sales. Their lease is up in the Coliseum. We've already lost the Rams in L.A. We cannot lose the Raiders in that market. It is just too important to the health of the league."</p>
        <p>Thus, Hunt and the other N.F.L. owners will meet in Jacksonville, Fla., today and tomorrow in an attempt to solidify the Raiders' home in Los Angeles. The owners have discussed building a stadium that the Raiders could lease, or helping the Raiders build a stadium of their own in Hollywood Park. Either idea, said Hunt, is acceptable.</p>
        <p>The owners also hope to decide on other controversial ideas that Hunt has proposed. One of the most striking is to award the conference championship games each year to cities through bidding, much like cities do for the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>"Remember that Cincinnati-San Diego A.F.C. championship game played in minus-59-degree wind chill?" Hunt asked. "We've seen a few A.F.C. championship games played in Buffalo in extreme cold. And last year the N.F.C. championship game was played on a field of mud in San Francisco. I think we should be about equitable and fair competition, especially when you get one game away from the Super Bowl.</p>
        <p>"I'd like to see us pick 16 or 17 locations that are either warm-weather sites or cities that have dome stadiums. Rotate the conference championship games there. And in order to eliminate a home-field advantage, play the N.F.C. championship game in an A.F.C. city and the A.F.C. championship game in an N.F.C. city. It makes for fair competition and it gives us a chance to promote and market our game in a new way."</p>
        <p>Hunt has also ruffled feathers in Detroit and in Dallas. Hunt wants the two annual Thanksgiving Day games, which are hosted each year by the Lions and Cowboys, to be shared by the league on a rotating basis.</p>
        <p>"It is grossly unfair to have two teams have that game every year," Hunt said. "It is extremely prejudicial to the other teams in the league. First of all, the visiting team in those games often plays the Sunday before. Then they have two days of practice. Then they have to travel and play on a Thursday in a very short week. Dallas and Detroit, they don't have to travel for the game. They have done it for so many years that they are used to the schedule. And they have the extra rest the following week, which is like having an extra bye week."</p>
        <p>Other issues on the owners' agenda includes:</p>
        <p>*A proposal by the Washington Redskins to bring back instant replay and limit it to scoring plays, change of possession and out-of-bounds plays and require replay officials to make quicker decisions.</p>
        <p>*A look at creating even more ways for all 30 teams to participate in revenue sharing.</p>
        <p>*A proposal to increase the number of playoffs teams from 12 to 16.  PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
