<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Answering Arabs, Israel Says It Rejects Conditions on Talks</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="859978"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PALESTINIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISRAELI SETTLEMENTS (OCCUPIED TERRITORIES)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NETANYAHU, BENJAMIN (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENBERG, JOEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00EFD61539F937A15755C0A960958260" item-length="589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Answering Arabs, Israel Says It Rejects Conditions on Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOEL GREENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENBERG, JOEL</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, June 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu accused Arab leaders today of dictating the terms of Middle East peace efforts in their statement concluding a summit meeting in Cairo.</p>
        <p>The statement warned that Arab countries would reconsider their relations with Israel if the new Israeli Government strayed from the "land for peace" formula that serves as the basis for talks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu accused Arab leaders today of dictating the terms of Middle East peace efforts in their statement concluding a summit meeting in Cairo.</p>
        <p>The statement warned that Arab countries would reconsider their relations with Israel if the new Israeli Government strayed from the "land for peace" formula that serves as the basis for talks.</p>
        <p>The policy guidelines of Mr. Netanyahu's Government insist on Israeli sovereignty over the Golan Heights in any agreement with Syria and reject a Palestinian state. They assert that Jerusalem will remain Israel's undivided capital and call for strengthening Jewish settlement in the West Bank and Gaza Strip.</p>
        <p>Commenting on the Arab statement tonight, Mr. Netanyahu said that peace must  be achieved "without preconditions."</p>
        <p>"We won't dictate to them, and they won't dictate to us," Mr. Netanyahu told  reporters in the southern Israeli town of Qiryat Gat. "The attempt to make assertions and dictate prior conditions that undermine the security of Israel is not compatible with a real peace process. Therefore, such prior conditions should be removed so that Israel and the Arab states can advance toward the peace we all hope and pray for.</p>
        <p>"I view the attempt to create prior demands as something that does not benefit the peace process."</p>
        <p>In an earlier written statement issued by his office, Mr. Netannyahu said tersely: "One-sided demands that harm security are not reconcilable with peace talks. In order for the process to continue successfully and fruitfully, such demands must stop."</p>
        <p>Foreign Minister David Levy, who suggested on Friday that Syria and Israel might reach a compromise over the Golan Heights, said the Arab leaders' statement contained "things which are serious, contradictory to the atmosphere necessary for continuing to achieve peace."</p>
        <p>The Arab statement had made "the result of negotiations a condition," Mr. Levy added. "Peace is not achieved through dictates and certainly not by a style that can be perceived as a threat."</p>
        <p>But Israeli officials who studied the summit meeting communique said that it  had some positive elements. It was more muted than a statement issued after a recent meeting of Saudi, Egyptian and Syrian leaders in Damascus, and it defined peace as a strategic Arab objective, they said.</p>
        <p>But the officials expressed disappointment at what they described as a linking of maximum Arab demands with warnings that if Israel does not comply there will be no peace and the region will slide into renewed tension.</p>
        <p>"There's a fundamental difference between the rules of negotiation and the positions of the parties," said Dore Gold, a leading foreign policy adviser to Mr. Netanyahu. "Our proposal for the rules of negotiation is that there are no prior conditions. If everyone wants to bring their dreams to the negotiating table, let them bring their dreams."</p>
        <p>Even as Mr. Netanyahu and the Arab states exchanged verbal jabs, the first Israeli commercial flight landed at Amman, Jordan, marking another step in carrying out the peace treaty the countries signed in 1994.</p>
        <p>Transport Minister Yitzhak Levy led a delegation of officials on board the 25-minute flight of Israel's national airline, El Al, which will fly to Amman five times a week. Jordan began flights to Israel in April, and bus service between the countries started this month.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
