<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Can Xerox Auction Off Hot Air?</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="860007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTER SOFTWARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUCTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR CONDITIONING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">XEROX CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARKOFF, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Software</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Conditioning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Heating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DF1239F937A15755C0A960958260" item-length="1034" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Can Xerox Auction Off Hot Air?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARKOFF, JOHN</byline>
      <dateline>PALO ALTO, Calif., June 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A software-based system that holds digital mini-auctions to distribute hot and cold air throughout a laboratory has been developed by scientists at the Xerox Corporation, marrying the laws of markets with those of electronics.</p>
        <p>The system, which has lowered energy costs in the building by more than 10 percent, is based on software "agents" that represent individual room temperature controllers that bid to buy or sell cool or warm air. An agent that  loses an auction might suffer a brief reduction in heating, which would encourage it to increase its bid in the next auction to be more certain of winning. The system holds about 1,500 auctions a day, more than one a minute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A software-based system that holds digital mini-auctions to distribute hot and cold air throughout a laboratory has been developed by scientists at the Xerox Corporation, marrying the laws of markets with those of electronics.</p>
        <p>The system, which has lowered energy costs in the building by more than 10 percent, is based on software "agents" that represent individual room temperature controllers that bid to buy or sell cool or warm air. An agent that  loses an auction might suffer a brief reduction in heating, which would encourage it to increase its bid in the next auction to be more certain of winning. The system holds about 1,500 auctions a day, more than one a minute.</p>
        <p>The system uses a powerful computer that acquires sensor data and distributes control information over a network throughout the building.</p>
        <p>The researchers believe the auction system has wide application wherever scarce resources need to be allocated efficiently, and is an example of growing  interest in using market mechanisms for managing and selling network resources.</p>
        <p>A recent project by researchers at Sun Microsystems Inc. and Agorics Inc. explored the use of software auctions to manage digital traffic jams in a computer network designed to carry video data.</p>
        <p>The idea of building automated market-based systems for control purposes is not new. But only in the last two years have scientists been able to build systems based on modern computer networks.</p>
        <p>"Originally people thought this was science fiction," said Bernardo Huberman, a Xerox physicist and a pioneer in the emerging field of computational ecology.  "However, it has turned out that using the market mechanism for controlling systems is a wonderful tool."</p>
        <p>The auction-based approach is a useful tool for controlling large systems because it can operate without a hierarchical authority.</p>
        <p>"Centralized approaches toward managing networks are doomed to failure," said Michael Rothschild, president of the Bionomics Institute, an economics research  organization in San Francisco.</p>
        <p>The Xerox researchers believe that decentralization becomes increasingly attractive as systems that require the interaction of large networks of computers grow in size.</p>
        <p>"Systems that are based on market mechanisms scale up very gracefully," Mr. Huberman said. "Their real advantage comes as they increase in size."</p>
        <p>During the 1970's the Xerox laboratory created the first practical office networks and scientists as the laboratory began experimenting with ways to harness the power of multiple computers in a network. In the late 1980's Mr. Huberman began research on using auction systems to share more efficiently a network's computer time. The research project, known as Spawn, was an early attempt to organize a computer network without a centralized control facility.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huberman developed the thermal auction system with Scott Clearwater and several other researchers at Xerox's Palo Alto Research Center. During the day,  as the sun shines on various sides of the building, the double-blind auctions take place electronically, a system in which neither buyer nor seller knows the  amount of any bid except its own. As software buyers purchase warm and cool air, air control vents in each office in the system are adjusted accordingly.</p>
        <p>The researchers designed the system with several notable differences from conventional auction systems. For example, they dealt with the tendency of the network to permit a single agent to accumulate large sums of "money" -- if, say, one office was on a shady side of the building and needed less air conditioning  -- by simply erasing excess amounts from the agent's accounts.</p>
        <p>While the auction-based thermal cooling system does not use real money, the researchers believe the technology can provide significant energy savings. They  are holding discussions with companies including Honeywell about licensing the system for commercial use.</p>
        <p>Many executives predict that the Internet will become an ideal media for automating commercial transactions. A number of entrepreneurs and industry researchers share the vision of creating software agents that will "shop" on behalf of computer users, keeping an eye out for particular items or bargains in Internet shopping malls.</p>
        <p>"Markets like this are likely," said Hal Varian, an economist who is dean of  the School of Information Management and Systems at the University of California at Berkeley. "The barrier is consumer acceptance."</p>
        <p>Indeed, Xerox executives believe that the auction technology may have a commercial application that falls much closer to the heart of Xerox's business:  printing services.</p>
        <p>Mr. Huberman has designed a system called Docubid that would permit companies to choose a printing company by placing the job up for bid on a national network that Xerox would run. Once a buyer and seller were matched, the job would be submitted electronically and then shipped to the customer upon completion.</p>
        <p>Yet the system could present Xerox with some problems, its executives acknowledge: some of its best customers for printing equipment are not interested in seeing more open markets.</p>
        <p>And there are other barriers.</p>
        <p>"The main thing that has been slowing up the larger-scale electronic commerce is the emergence of electronic money or a simple credit card scheme," said Mark  Manasse, a researcher at the Digital Equipment Corporation. "There are a lot of  regulatory and social issues that still need to be solved."</p>
        <p>Another significant problem is the absence of workable systems that permit small-scale financial transactions -- as small as a nickel or a dime, or even a  fraction of a penny in the future.</p>
        <p>Mr. Manasse has designed an electronic money system known as Millicent to support financial systems that require large numbers of small transactions. Such a system might conceivably work well with an auction-based system, or one in which writers might desire to sell their work at a lower cost than is required by the current paper-based publishing economy in order to do multiple transactions quickly and benefit from the volume.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
