<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic of Gingrich Is Warmly Praised at Home</title>
    <meta content="31FORB$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="898652"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gingrich, Newt (Speaker)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Forbes, Michael P (Repr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0DF1130F932A05751C1A960958260" item-length="1184" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic of Gingrich Is Warmly Praised at Home</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>EAST QUOGUE, L.I., Dec. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Long Island Republicans express support for their Representative Michael P Forbes for his becoming first Republican in House not to back Newt Gingrich for another term as Speaker (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jo Ann Doyle, 42, has known Representative Michael P. Forbes since junior high school and, while she is a Republican like him, she is quick to say they do not always see eye to eye.</p>
        <p>But today, on a busy pre-New Year's afternoon in her liquor store here, she said she was completely behind the stand he took that could remake his political life: to be the first Republican in the House to say he would not back Newt Gingrich for another term as Speaker.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jo Ann Doyle, 42, has known Representative Michael P. Forbes since junior high school and, while she is a Republican like him, she is quick to say they do not always see eye to eye.</p>
        <p>But today, on a busy pre-New Year's afternoon in her liquor store here, she said she was completely behind the stand he took that could remake his political life: to be the first Republican in the House to say he would not back Newt Gingrich for another term as Speaker.</p>
        <p>''I think it was very brave,'' Ms. Doyle said of Mr. Forbes, a fellow member of the class of 1971 at West Hampton Beach High School. ''A lot of people in his district aren't that happy with Gingrich.'' Mr. Forbes, she said, is following their mandate, adding, ''This won't hurt him at all in the district.''</p>
        <p>Along the tiny main strip of this working-class Republican village just east of Mr. Forbes's hometown of Quogue on the East End of Long Island, it was hard to find anyone today -- in either party -- who had a good word to say about Mr. Gingrich or a nasty word about Mr. Forbes's decision.</p>
        <p>The question now, as the House moves toward its vote on Mr. Gingrich's reappointment Jan. 7, is: How widespread is this distaste for the Speaker if the first defector is Mr. Forbes, a painfully earnest career politician who went to Washington in 1994 feeling so confident of his constituents' desires that he called himself one of Mr. Gingrich's ''loyal lieutenants''?</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Forbes announced his intentions on Sunday, saying the Speaker's explanations of his ethical lapses did not ring true, no other Republicans in the House have joined him. But in interviews in his district, there were many echoes of closed-door worries among Republicans in Washington: that Mr. Gingrich is too wounded to carry out his plans to reform the Government or find a moral high ground against a President who is facing his own allegations of improprieties in raising funds for the election this year.</p>
        <p>Cynthia Barna, a 49-year-old secretary and bookkeeper, worked out on her fingers that she had been a Republican for 31 years, and pronounced that Mr. Gingrich's time as the party's leader in the House should come to a close.</p>
        <p>''I think we've had enough clowns,'' she said. ''We had Bozo. We had Clarabell. I just think that people should take more responsibility for the positions they are in.''</p>
        <p>Of Mr. Forbes, whom she voted for after his office looked into a problem she had been having, she said: ''You don't usually see that kind of honesty in a politician's part, to come out and say what he thinks. So I had more respect for him.''</p>
        <p>The applause for Mr. Forbes, who won a rough race in November with 55 percent of the vote, was not unanimous, of course. Perhaps explaining his decision in part, Mr. Forbes had faced much criticism in his district for being too close with Mr. Gingrich.  And some people said Mr. Forbes should not rush so quickly to the other extreme.</p>
        <p>''While I think Newt Gingrich made some mistakes, he readily admitted them,'' said Harry Gunther, 72, of Kings Park, a Republican who said Mr. Forbes should back the Speaker. ''I can't say the same for the Clintons. We've got a President who has made some tremendous mistakes and won't admit that he ever made a mistake.''</p>
        <p>What was striking about conversations with voters, mostly Republicans, was that few said they cared particularly about the specific ethical lapses that have thrust Mr. Gingrich into round after round of explanation. Few said they were aware of the specifics about Gopac, the political action committee that Mr. Gingrich headed until 1994. A House ethics subcommittee said this month that Gopac had promoted and raised money for a course he taught at two small colleges in Georgia; that the Speaker had brought discredit to the House by using tax-exempt money for political purposes, and that he had provided the committee with inaccurate and incomplete information about Gopac's role in the course he taught.</p>
        <p>And it was not even Mr. Gingrich's policies that rankled so much, though in this district, as in many Northeastern states, there seemed to be a sharp distaste for cutting the Federal Government too deeply. Rather, voters said it was mostly the Speaker's manner, which many termed both highhanded and undignified.</p>
        <p>''I don't like him,'' said Brian Misiewicz, 38, a Republican and a golf pro who had just played a round. ''I think he's very pompous.''</p>
        <p>''When he got into the thing with Clinton over who shut down the Government,'' Mr. Misiewicz said, ''he was like a little boy who didn't get his way.'' His golfing partner, John Linguiti, 60, also a Republican, shook his head. ''He's his own worst enemy,'' he said of Mr. Gingrich. Mr. Linguiti added: ''We both agree.''</p>
        <p>''And that's scary,'' Mr. Misiewicz said.</p>
        <p>Bob Ankerson, 63, a consultant who is a Republican, said of Mr. Forbes's decision, ''From the point of view of electoral politics, it seems to me he did the right thing by his party and by himself.''</p>
        <p>''If you are a Republican and you don't want to lose the opportunity to discredit the Democrats, wouldn't it be a shame to uphold an icon of the past here?'' he said. ''I mean, Gingrich doesn't even seem influential in the things he was talking about in the revolution of '94.''</p>
        <p>William Moore, a Democrat who is retired from a business selling marine equipment, said he had known the Forbes family all his life and was surprised when he heard about the announcement from Mr. Forbes, who he always took as a loyal party man.</p>
        <p>''He would be the last person I would expect to have come out with a statement like that,'' said Mr. Moore, 63, who did not vote for Mr. Forbes. ''He's almost acting like a maverick.'' Still, he said the announcement inspired admiration as well as a bafflement he said Mr. Forbes's other constituents might share.</p>
        <p>''They are probably very curious about what he's got in the back of his mind,'' Mr. Moore said. ''I don't know. I wonder if he does.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
