<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sublime Sadness of the Portuguese</title>
    <meta content="25EVOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="967633"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="POP REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Portugal</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Performing Arts Center (Newark)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evora, Cesaria</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Portugal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E1DD1E3EF936A15753C1A961958260" item-length="498" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sublime Sadness of the Portuguese</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Oct. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Program of Portuguese music is presented at New Jersey Performing Arts Center, Newark; photo of singer Cesaria Evora; Jon Pareles review (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Across their former empire, the Portuguese carried the idea of saudade, a wistful, nostalgic sadness and longing that imbue poetry and songs. Portuguese fado, Brazilian bossa nova and Cape Verdean morna are all permeated by saudade. And that mood, as much as the Portuguese language, linked the double bill of Cesaria Evora, from Cape Verde, and Madredeus, from Portugal, at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>The concert inaugurated a series of events with Portuguese connections -- from Portugal to Angola to Brazil -- that are a wise move on the part of the new performance center, in a city with a sizable Portuguese community.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Across their former empire, the Portuguese carried the idea of saudade, a wistful, nostalgic sadness and longing that imbue poetry and songs. Portuguese fado, Brazilian bossa nova and Cape Verdean morna are all permeated by saudade. And that mood, as much as the Portuguese language, linked the double bill of Cesaria Evora, from Cape Verde, and Madredeus, from Portugal, at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center on Thursday night.</p>
        <p>The concert inaugurated a series of events with Portuguese connections -- from Portugal to Angola to Brazil -- that are a wise move on the part of the new performance center, in a city with a sizable Portuguese community.</p>
        <p>It was a double bill of earth and air. Ms. Evora was the earthy half: barefoot and low-voiced, with morna songs that sauntered easily through their tidings of loneliness and perseverance. Her contralto is filled with forbearance and comfort, as if she has seen the worst but can still offer consolation; it is made for slow songs where she can linger over notes that seem to share a wordless sympathy.</p>
        <p>In the songs she chooses, the melodies often climb to a high note that Ms. Evora accents with a sighing slide; then they fall back to earth with a graceful, resigned arpeggio.</p>
        <p>Her group blends guitars with the strumming of a cavaquinho, the small guitar also used in samba, with the ornate piano parts of tango, and with occasional perky saxophone lines. Drawing on her new album, ''Cabo Verde'' (Nonesuch), she sang more up-tempo songs than in previous New York concerts, varying the pace of her set but sometimes limiting the expressiveness of her vocals. Although she could bring a sly, knowing tone to her faster tunes, the most telling songs were still the slower ones, where her voice could float and ache and melt. Ms. Evora is to perform on Nov. 1 at Town Hall in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Madredeus does to fado what Enya does to Irish traditional music: wrapping folk-rooted melodies in gauzy, portentous new age trappings. Teresa Salgueiro's voice, a richly doleful soprano, is at the center of the music, carrying clear melodies with distant ancestors in fado songs. Around her, four guitarists pluck glimmering traceries of notes, while a synthesizer does the job of a movie-soundtrack orchestra, mimicking string sections, church bells, even a jew's-harp. In many ways, Madredeus is closer to an international movement of ethereal pop, akin to the Cocteau Twins and Kate Bush, than it is to fado.</p>
        <p>At times, the delicacy of the guitars and the tenderness of Ms. Salgueiro's voice created music of haunting beauty. But over the course of a 90-minute set, the unvarying prettiness and the relentlessly pompous and symmetrical instrumental passages grew ever more cloying. In the end, saudade and bombast don't mix.</p>
        <p>POP REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
