<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE -- Houses on Lakes; Summer Camp Redux</title>
    <meta content="23live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060630T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1771146"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE5DF1630F930A15755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="941" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE -- Houses on Lakes; Summer Camp Redux</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Amy Gunderson</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO -- Tom Cucciniello, 48, from Paterson, N.J., owner of a linen service, shown with his wife, Margaret, 48, a stay-at-home mother  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  WHERE -- Ferrisburg, Vt.</p>
        <p>My wife and I vacationed for many years in Westport, N.Y., on Lake Champlain. We grew to love the area but we never thought frontage on the Vermont side was in our price range. One day, a few years ago, we rode by this place. I could barely see the house, the property was so overgrown, but I did see the 400 feet of frontage on the lake. My wife told me I was crazy and to go sleep it off. I contacted the owner and it turns out he was ready to sell. I thought, ''When am I ever going to find this kind of frontage again?''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO -- Tom Cucciniello, 48, from Paterson, N.J., owner of a linen service, shown with his wife, Margaret, 48, a stay-at-home mother  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  WHERE -- Ferrisburg, Vt.</p>
        <p>My wife and I vacationed for many years in Westport, N.Y., on Lake Champlain. We grew to love the area but we never thought frontage on the Vermont side was in our price range. One day, a few years ago, we rode by this place. I could barely see the house, the property was so overgrown, but I did see the 400 feet of frontage on the lake. My wife told me I was crazy and to go sleep it off. I contacted the owner and it turns out he was ready to sell. I thought, ''When am I ever going to find this kind of frontage again?''</p>
        <p>You couldn't walk inside the house, it had so much junk. And the yard was filled with vintage typewriters, old bicycles and 12 lawn mowers. The most unusual thing was the contents of an old wallpaper factory in the barn. The cleanup took two years -- a massive project since there were six buildings on the property. This is an old camp; I was buying the property for the land and had no idea how nice the house was. But as I gutted the place I found 12-foot ceilings, hardwood floors, chestnut trim and views of the lake from every room.</p>
        <p>We have a large concrete dock, and it's a 20-minute boat ride to Burlington. I keep canoes and kayaks in the boathouse, and the lake gets up to the perfect swimming temperature of 70 degrees in July and August. My family uses this as a summer place from Memorial Day right through the foliage season. It's gorgeous with the Adirondacks to one side, the Green Mountains on the other and an expanse of lake on three sides of the property. My kids have made me promise to never sell it.</p>
        <p>As told to Amy Gunderson</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the owners or the listing agents.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Sebago, Me.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $749,000</p>
        <p>This century-old cottage has 157 feet of frontage on the 47-square-mile Sebago Lake. It has two bathrooms, a sunroom that overlooks the lake, several decks, a stone fireplace and a loft. There are a heated garage with a workshop that has a finished second level, as well as another detached two-car garage. The house has been winterized for year-round use. The property is 6.1 acres. Sebago is two and a half hours north of Boston. Agent: Steve Titcomb, Agency 1 Real Estate -- Jordan Rentals, 800-942-5547; www.sebagolakeproperties.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Cohasset, Minn.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $745,000</p>
        <p>Built in 1996, this 3,900-square-foot house has 202 feet of frontage on the 15,000-acre Lake Pokegama. It has a fireplace, vaulted ceilings, oak floors, four bathrooms, a walkout lower level, a two-car attached garage, a shed for kayaks or canoes and a deck off the master bedroom. The property is 3.9 acres a few minutes from Grand Rapids. Agent: Jane O'Leary, Prudential Lakes Realty, 800-795-9404; www.aplaceatthelake.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Zephyr Cove, Nev.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $4,889,000</p>
        <p>This half-acre property includes 80 feet of sandy beach on the southeastern shore of Lake Tahoe, a 90-foot pier and a boat lift. The house, which was built in 1991, is 3,274 square feet and has vaulted pine ceilings, three and a half bathrooms, a mudroom, a breakfast bar, a stone fireplace and a two-car attached garage. The master suite has a whirlpool tub, two walk-in closets and a private deck with views of Mount Tallac. Zephyr Cove is 55 miles southwest of Reno. Agent: Ryan Forvilly, Dickson Realty, 866-413-0985; www.realtahoe.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Lake George, N.Y.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house with guesthouse  HOW MUCH -- $2,498,000</p>
        <p>This one-acre property has 171 feet of frontage with a sandy swimming area on the southern basin of Lake George. It has an E-shaped covered dock with two boat slips. The main house was built in 1920 and has been winterized. It has cedar siding, a screened porch, four and a half bathrooms and a fireplace. The one-bedroom guesthouse has two levels of living space and a three-car garage. There is also a separate two-car garage. Brokers: Sharon and Daniel Davies, Davies-Davies &amp; Associates, 518-656-9068; www.davies-davies.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Swanton, Vt.  WHAT -- 5-bedroom house  HOW MUCH -- $700,000</p>
        <p>This early 1800's brick house, known as the Captain Brown house, has 147 feet of frontage on Lake Champlain in the Maquam Shore area of northern Vermont. It is 2,632 square feet and has plank floors, a wood-burning stove, an above-ground swimming pool, a hot tub, two bathrooms and a screened porch that overlooks the lake. The property is 15 acres and includes a shed. It is six miles from the Canadian border. Agent: Judy Desorcie, Coldwell Banker Choice Properties, 802-524-9526; www.vermontchoiceproperties.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Jacksonport, Wis.  WHAT -- 4-bedroom house with guesthouse  HOW MUCH -- $750,000</p>
        <p>The 3,200-square-foot main house (not pictured) is across a road from both the guesthouse and from Lake Michigan. It was built in 1996 and has two fireplaces, a two-car attached garage and two and a half bathrooms. The guesthouse (shown above) is 975 square feet. It has 100 feet of rocky frontage on the lake, a fireplace, two bedrooms and knotty pine walls. Jacksonport, 170 miles north of Milwaukee, is in Door County, a popular vacation area. Agent: Tricia Cramer, Premier Properties of Door County, 920-854-9799; www.premierdoorcounty.com.</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 30, 2006, Friday  The Living Here column on Friday, about houses on lakes, misstated the size of one property on Sebago Lake, Maine, with a three-bedroom house. It is 0.61 acres, not 6.1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 30, 2006, Friday</p>
        <p>The Living Here column on Friday, about houses on lakes, misstated the size of one property on Sebago Lake, Maine, with a three-bedroom house. It is 0.61 acres, not 6.1.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
