<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Video Releases</title>
    <meta content="22VIDB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1513997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bowling For Columbine (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Good Thief, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">All the Real Girls (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3D61F30F931A1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Video Releases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Films Bowling for Columbine, The Good Thief and All the Real Girls are released on video; brief excerpts from original reviews; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bowling for Columbine</p>
        <p>In the good-natured confrontational style of his 1989 documentary ''Roger and Me,'' Michael Moore, left, tracks gun violence far and wide, beginning with the massacre at Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo. Larger questions include why Americans shoot one another much more frequently than people in other developed countries do and why they are so inclined when other societies are as inundated with violent entertainment and as affected by unemployment and other strains. But though Mr. Moore seems to be digging for specific historical causes, he indulges in glib generalizations and oversimplifications. When he goes against his prejudices, his appraisal is riveting and scary, but ''the slippery logic, tendentious grandstanding and outright demagoguery on display in 'Bowling for Columbine' should give pause to its most ardent partisans,'' A. O. Scott wrote in The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bowling for Columbine</p>
        <p>In the good-natured confrontational style of his 1989 documentary ''Roger and Me,'' Michael Moore, left, tracks gun violence far and wide, beginning with the massacre at Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo. Larger questions include why Americans shoot one another much more frequently than people in other developed countries do and why they are so inclined when other societies are as inundated with violent entertainment and as affected by unemployment and other strains. But though Mr. Moore seems to be digging for specific historical causes, he indulges in glib generalizations and oversimplifications. When he goes against his prejudices, his appraisal is riveting and scary, but ''the slippery logic, tendentious grandstanding and outright demagoguery on display in 'Bowling for Columbine' should give pause to its most ardent partisans,'' A. O. Scott wrote in The New York Times.</p>
        <p>2002. MGM. VHS, $49.99; DVD, $26.90. 119 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>The Good Thief</p>
        <p>Neil Jordan's remake of Jean-Pierre Melville's atmospheric, poetic film noir ''Bob le Flambeur'' heightens the combustion by a few cylinders. As played by Nick Nolte, Bob is an old trickster with his cards close to his vest. A gambler and heroin addict, he kicks the habit long enough to become involved in a casino heist. A towering figure of the Nice demimonde, Bob seems able to get away with just about anything and finds an advantage even when he doesn't. That kind of cool and sense of irony puts Bob beyond torment. It also attracts a beautiful 18-year-old Russian émigrée (Nutsa Kukhianidze). ''Mr. Jordan has the right actor for the task. Mr. Nolte uses 'The Good Thief' as a haven for a majestic ruin he has worked at for years'' (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
        <p>2003. Fox. VHS, $110.99; DVD, $27.90. 109 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>All the Real Girls</p>
        <p>A self-assured 18-year-old named Noel (Zooey Deschanel) returns from a girls' boarding school and tells her would-be boyfriend, Paul (Paul Schneider), that she's passing up college because she doesn't see much point in spending four years writing bad-girl poetry. Paul tells her she'll find plenty of bad poetry around her North Carolina hometown, but the pair's sweet, inconclusive romance has lyricism in the second film by David Gordon Green (''George Washington''). With unabashed sincerity and tenderness, Mr. Green ''captures both the world-stopping intensity and the delicate absurdity of youthful longing, and Paul and Noel themselves are at once gawkily real and luminously peculiar'' (Scott).</p>
        <p>2003. Columbia TriStar. VHS, $54.99; DVD, $24.95. 108 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a theater release, appeared on television or been on videocassette or DVD in earlier editions.</p>
        <p>I'M GOING HOME. In Manoel de Oliveira's film, the 75-year-old Michel Piccoli is Gilbert Valence, a distinguished French actor performing scenes as a dying monarch in Ionesco's ''Exit the King,'' as Prospero in ''The Tempest'' and as Buck Mulligan in a screen adaptation of Joyce's ''Ulysses.'' Mr. Piccoli is the alter ego of the Portuguese-born Mr. de Oliveira, who was 92 when this film was made. Old age doesn't automatically confer wisdom and artistic profundity, but when it does, as in the case of Mr. de Oliveira, ''what can emerge is a remarkable mixture of appreciation and sadness, colored with an implacable, clear-eyed awareness of looming extinction,'' Stephen Holden wrote in The New York Times. The DVD has a commentary by Richard Peña, program director of the Film Society of Lincoln Center. 2001. Milestone. VHS, $29.95; DVD, $29.99. 90 minutes. French with English subtitles. Information: (800) 603-1104.</p>
        <p>MARYAM. In 1979, with American hostages being held in Iran, a 16-year-old Iranian-American girl (Mariam Parris) tries to fit into her suburban New Jersey world. Ramin Serry's film falters when he reaches for drama, but he works well with a gifted cast that has a feel for emotional details. ''Ms. Parris, a quicksilver young talent who projects common sense, is a real find,'' Elvis Mitchell wrote in The Times. 2000. Wellspring. VHS, $49.98. DVD, $24.90. 90 minutes. No rating.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
