<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pro-Beijing Party Wants Hong Kong Security Legislation Delayed</title>
    <meta content="Y22HON$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/22/international/asia/22HONG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1513847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hong Kong</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tung Chee-Hwa</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hong Kong</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E3D91639F931A1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="521" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pro-Beijing Party Wants Hong Kong Security Legislation Delayed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pro-Beijing Party Wants Hong Kong Security Legislation Delayed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>HONG KONG, Aug. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leaders of main pro-Beijing political party in Hong Kong call for government to delay internal security legislation by more than year, fearing setback in coming elections; step is surprising because Beijing-controlled newspaper has called for quick enactment of legislation; huge street demonstrations last month and defection of key political allies has already forced Tung Chee-hwa, Hong Kong's chief executive, to retreat from his original insistence that bill be passed before lawmakers' summer recess (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fearing a setback in elections next year, the leaders of the main pro-Beijing political party here called today for the government to delay internal security legislation by more than a year.</p>
        <p>The step was especially surprising because the Beijing-controlled China Daily newspaper declared in a column this week that the legislation must be enacted ''as soon as possible.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fearing a setback in elections, party leaders called for the government to delay internal security legislation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fearing a setback in elections next year, the leaders of the main pro-Beijing political party here called today for the government to delay internal security legislation by more than a year.</p>
        <p>The step was especially surprising because the Beijing-controlled China Daily newspaper declared in a column this week that the legislation must be enacted ''as soon as possible.''</p>
        <p>Huge street demonstrations last month and the defection of key political allies had already forced Tung Chee-hwa, Hong Kong's chief executive, to retreat from his original insistence that the bill be passed before the lawmakers' summer recess.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tung's administration is now preparing to issue a so-called consultation document next month, seeking the public's views on how to make the proposed laws against sedition, subversion, secession and treason more acceptable.</p>
        <p>Today two top officials of the Democratic Alliance for the Betterment of Hong Kong, a pro-Beijing group better known as the D.A.B., called for postponement of consideration of the bill until after next year's Legislative Council elections, which are to be held in late August or early September. Members elected then will take office on Oct. 1, 2004.</p>
        <p>Ma Lik, the party's secretary general, said in a telephone interview that his party still believed the legislation should eventually be passed and that it would not deprive residents of any civil liberties, as democracy advocates have contended.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ma said that the bill, known as Article 23 legislation, was still an emotional subject, and acknowledged that it could hurt his party in the next election if it remains at the center of public attention.</p>
        <p>''If Article 23 legislation is still an issue, it will not benefit D.A.B., because it is very, very politicized,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ma said that he and Tsang Yok-sing, the party's chairman, had informed Mr. Tung and leaders in Beijing of their worries. ''Both Mr. Tung and Beijing, they're evaluating and will decide later'' when the issue should be brought to a vote, although the consultation document may be issued regardless, Mr. Ma said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tsang called for a delay in a column in today's edition of the Ming Pao newspaper, asserting that too little time was left in the current session of the Legislative Council to permit a full review.</p>
        <p>A government spokeswoman repeated today previous statements by Ambrose Lee, the new secretary of security, that no timetable had been set yet for passage of the bill. Mr. Lee took office after Regina Ip, his predecessor, stepped down last month following widespread criticism of her championing of the bill.</p>
        <p>The D.A.B. is one of two pro-Beijing parties, and is the more vulnerable in the next election. Six of its 10 members in the 60-member legislature represent geographic constituencies open to voting by the general public, which has turned out huge demonstrations against the bill.</p>
        <p>The other party, the Liberal Party, had its eight members elected by industries and professions, following rules that benefit pro-government parties.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
