<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOME VIDEO/NEW RELEASES</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="199899"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (VIDEO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CASSETTES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">KELLERMAN, STEWART</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ANNA (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GRAND HIGHWAY, THE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ABOVE THE LAW (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">VERNON, FLORIDA (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LITTLE NIKITA (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MY BEST FRIEND IS A VAMPIRE (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DA173CF933A15752C1A96E948260" item-length="1450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOME VIDEO/NEW RELEASES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEWART KELLERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KELLERMAN, STEWART</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  Anna  Starring Sally Kirkland, Robert Fields, Paulina Porizkova. Directed by Yurek Bogayevicz. 1987.  Vestron Video.  100 minutes. $79.98. Closed captioned. Not rated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  Anna  Starring Sally Kirkland, Robert Fields, Paulina Porizkova. Directed by Yurek Bogayevicz. 1987.  Vestron Video.  100 minutes. $79.98. Closed captioned. Not rated.</p>
        <p>Anna  Starring Sally Kirkland, Robert Fields, Paulina Porizkova. Directed by Yurek Bogayevicz. 1987.  Vestron Video.  100 minutes. $79.98. Closed captioned. Not rated.</p>
        <p>Anna, a once-celebrated Czechoslovak actress played by Sally Kirkland, is living in gloomy exile in the United States.</p>
        <p>Krystyna (Paulina Porizkova), a devoted young fan just off the plane from Czechoslovakia, tracks Anna down and then faints from hunger.</p>
        <p>Anna takes Krystyna to live with her and encourages her to seek stardom.</p>
        <p>''The whole thing turns out to be an 'All About Eve' variation in which Eve is just too nice for words,'' Janet Maslin said in The Times. The film is annoying, Ms. Maslin said, despite ''Miss Kirkland's immensely dignified presence and the obvious glamour'' of Miss Porizkova, a star fashion model.</p>
        <p>''Miss Porizkova is gorgeous, and she also has a spry, unpredictable manner that works well on the screen, but the film seems too determined to turn her into Audrey Hepburn, making her do things not even Miss Hepburn, at her most elfin, could get away with,'' Ms. Maslin said.  The Grand Highway  Starring Anemone, Richard Bohringer, Antoine Hubert, Vanessa Guedj, Christine Pascal, Raoul Billerey, Pascale Roberts, Marie Matheron. Directed by Jean-Loup Hubert. 1987.  Pacific Arts Video.  107 minutes. $89.95. Not rated.  In French, with English subtitles.</p>
        <p>Nine-year-old Louis is sent from Paris to the country for three weeks while his mother has a baby. Jean-Loup Hubert's film is about how the ingenuous youngster encounters the enchanting landscape and the cold reality of a pretty peasant village in France in 1958.</p>
        <p>Though the film has ''the makings of a nostalgic glance backward, full of easy charm and sentimentality,'' Caryn James wrote in The Times, ''it is unexpectedly rich in warmth, wit and intelligence.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Hubert's son, Antoine, plays Louis, captured in the last stages of boyhood, before a hint of puberty has appeared,'' Ms. James said. ''With his wide eyes, pathetically narrow shoulders and skinny legs, Louis is the picture of heart-wrenching sweetness.''</p>
        <p>He arrives to find Marcelle, the old friend of his mother with whom he is to stay, skinning a rabbit and scooping out its eyes.</p>
        <p>''Marcelle sees a treat for Louis's first supper,'' Ms. James said. ''Louis sees a dead bunny.'' Marcelle's husband, Pelo, is ''coarse when he's sober and vicious when he's drunk.'' '' 'The Grand Highway' sometimes seems like a French version of 'My Life as a Dog,' '' Ms. James said. ''But the hero of the Swedish film always had a mischievous gleam in his eye; Louis is more conventional, always guileless and baffled. Antoine Hubert is so natural that at first it seems he is not acting at all.''</p>
        <p>The story isn't what really matters, the reviewer said, adding, ''It is the atmosphere of Mr. Hubert's film that makes us feel we have entered his village, that the mismatched details of life there make sense.''</p>
        <p>The film was the top French-made film at the box office in 1987.  Above the Law  Starring Steven Seagal, Pam Grier, Henry Silva. Directed by Andrew Davis. 1988.  Warner Home Video.  99 minutes. $89.95. Rated R.</p>
        <p>A bunch of whackos in the Central Intelligence Agency are trafficking in drugs to finance their covert operations. Enter Nico Toscani, a Chicago detective who quit the C.I.A. during the Vietnam War but isn't quite through with it yet.</p>
        <p>''Above the Law,'' Vincent Canby said in The Times, is a ''left-wing right-wing movie.''</p>
        <p>''It's an action melodrama that expresses the sentiments of the lunatic fringe at the political center,'' Mr. Canby said.</p>
        <p>Nico, a martial-arts expert played by Steven Seagal, tries to save the life of a United States senator who's about to blow the whistle on the C.I.A. crazies. The crazies, of course, want to blow him away first.</p>
        <p>''Stripped of his authority as a cop, Nico proceeds to lay waste his enemies, and a large part of Chicago, in his defense of the Constitution,'' Mr. Canby said.  Vernon, Florida  With Claude Register, Albert Bitterling, Henry Shipes, Snake Reynolds, Roscoe Collins, Coy Brock, Joe Payne, George Harris, Ray Cotton and Mr. and Mrs. J. W. Martin.</p>
        <p>Directed by Errol Morris. 1981.  RCA/Columbia Pictures Home Video.  60 minutes. $79.95. Not rated.</p>
        <p>Errol Morris's film is about the oddest eccentrics in a very odd town. One man is obsessed with turkey hunting, another with eating turtle meat. A husband and wife ''raise'' sand in a jar. And a police officer remarks that nothing ever happens in Vernon, Fla.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morris's second film, Janet Maslin said in The Times, ''cuts back and forth among these different parties, establishing a rhythm for Vernon and marveling at the breadth of the townspeople and their whimsy.''</p>
        <p>The director, whose first movie, ''Gates of Heaven,'' was about pet cemeteries, ''lets it all go on a bit too long, but his film is humorous, idiosyncratic and fond,'' Ms. Maslin said.</p>
        <p>At a New York Film Festival news conference, she continued, he ''came under fire for making fun of his subjects, but that seems not to have been his idea at all.</p>
        <p>''The fancifulness of his subjects is something he appears to appreciate and enjoy.''  Little Nikita  Starring Sidney Poitier, River Phoenix, Richard Jenkins, Caroline Kava, Richard Bradford, Richard Lynch. Directed by Richard Benjamin. 1988.  RCA/Columbia Pictures Home Video.  96 minutes. $89.95. Closed Captioned. Rated PG, thanks to several killings and possibly the suggestion that one's parents might be Soviet moles.</p>
        <p>Sydney Poitier is an F.B.I. agent who discovers a couple of K.G.B. sleepers, Richard and Elizabeth Grant, in Southern California. The Grants' teen-age son, born Nikita but now known as Jeff, is disturbed to learn from Mr. Poitier that his parents are spies.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Poitier's company is always agreeable, only in this case he is the most conspicuous undercover agent in the annals of the F.B.I.,'' Walter Goodman commented in The Times. ''He practically forces people to catch on to him.''</p>
        <p>There's also a former Soviet agent who's out gunning down his old comrades and a Soviet hit man out to get him.</p>
        <p>''The script sends Mr. Poitier out on an assignment that only his immediate boss knows about and puts him in bed with a plump guidance counselor mainly so that Jeff can burst in on them, for a laugh,'' Mr. Goodman said. ''In a burst of inventiveness, the final car chase is between a pickup truck and a trolley.''  My Best Friend Is a Vampire  Starring Robert Sean Leonard, David Warner, Rene Auberjonois.  Directed by Jimmy Huston. 1988.  HBO Video.  89 minutes. $79.99. Closed captioned. Rated PG. Some sexual innuendo, none of it shocking.</p>
        <p>Jeremy, a brawny high-school boy, is seduced by a beautiful vampire. He's a wholesome, All-American boy, and he makes a wholesome, All-American vampire.</p>
        <p>''There could be advantages to having a best friend who's a vampire - all-night parties, great black clothes, contact with the afterlife,'' Caryn James said in The Times. ''There's something to be said for the trendy night scene.'' Though he has to dress better to fit his new image, Ms. James said, Jeremy makes the transition ''with just a few adjustments.'' ''In fact, Jeremy comes to sound like a vampire-rights advocate, lecturing the bad guys that vampires are just people, too,'' she said. In one of the film's witty scenes, Ms. James said, Jeremy and his vampire mentor ''pop open a couple of cans of pig's blood and toast, 'This blood's for you!' ''  SHORT TAKES  Heart of the Champion  Fox Hills Video. 45 minutes. $19.95. Not rated.</p>
        <p>National Football League athletes who have overcome adversity.  Raffi in Concert  With the Rise and Shine Band  A&amp;M Video. 50 minutes. $19.98. Not rated.</p>
        <p>Raffi's second concert video, with contemporary songs for children, including ''Baby Beluga'' and ''Shake My Sillies Out.''  Tommy Tricker And the Stamp Traveller  Family Home Entertainment. 101 minutes. $39.95. Not rated.</p>
        <p>A mischievous child makes off with a stamp and ends up in the middle of an international intrigue. For children, with Lucas Evans, Anthony Rogers and Jill Stanley.  Animal Olympians  Vestron Video. 60 minutes. $29.98. Not rated.</p>
        <p>Athletes of the animal world, from the award-winning Nova science series.  The Unholy  Vestron Video. 105 minutes. $89.98. Rated R.</p>
        <p>Ben Cross is a priest who tries to prevent Satan from luring troubled clerics to their deaths, with Hal Holbrook and Trevor Howard.  N.F.L. Quarterback  Fox Hills Video. 45 minutes. $19.95. Not rated.</p>
        <p>How do you get to be a quarterback in the National Football League? A look at what it takes.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
