<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>South Lebanon Towns Reclaim Their Dead and Hold Funerals</title>
    <meta content="17burial" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/17/world/middleeast/17burial.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1783418"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Lebanon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Funerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cemeteries</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Lebanon</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Hezbollah</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E7DB143EF934A2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>South Lebanon Towns Reclaim Their Dead and Hold Funerals</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">South Lebanon Towns Reclaim Their Dead and Hold Funerals</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HASSAN M. FATTAH</byline>
      <dateline>HALUSIEH, Lebanon, Aug. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For weeks the bodies were symbols of the helplessness many felt in the face of Israel's bombs.</p>
        <p>But on Wednesday, Lebanon's dead became symbols of closure as towns and villages throughout the south began burying their loved ones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On Wednesday, Lebanons dead became symbols of closure as towns and villages throughout the south began burying their loved ones.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For weeks the bodies were symbols of the helplessness many felt in the face of Israel's bombs.</p>
        <p>But on Wednesday, Lebanon's dead became symbols of closure as towns and villages throughout the south began burying their loved ones.</p>
        <p>Families mourned for relatives and towns honored the bodies of Hezbollah fighters in ceremonies in the rubble-strewn villages of the south, vowing never to forget the price they paid in the fight against Israel.</p>
        <p>In Halusieh, about a 30-minute drive east of Tyre, residents carried the coffins of 11 men, women and children through town before holding an emotional ceremony led by a prominent sheik whose relatives were among the dead.</p>
        <p>In Shabiye, hundreds marched behind the coffin of Mostafa Rakin, 16, a Hezbollah fighter who died in a firefight with Israeli soldiers on Sunday. In other towns and villages, bodies uncovered in the rubble were buried in solemn ceremonies.</p>
        <p>Health officials on Wednesday began releasing bodies from the main morgue in Tyre, calling on families to begin burying their loved ones in their home villages instead of a mass grave near the morgue, where more than 200 others have been buried until families can claim them.</p>
        <p>The bodies, some in pine coffins and others wrapped in blankets, were given their last respects and buried in open fields and cemeteries on Wednesday afternoon, some beside the graves of fighters from wars past, others beside relatives.</p>
        <p>The largest funeral was in Halusieh, where the bodies of five members of the Mouanes family and six members of the Hamed family were cleansed and wrapped for burial in a makeshift mortuary on Wednesday evening.</p>
        <p>All 11 were killed on July 24, when Israeli warplanes bombed two houses in which more than 40 people had taken refuge. When one of the houses was bombed, the families inside escaped into the one next door, residents said. But minutes later, bombs struck that home too, killing most of those who had run inside.</p>
        <p>Three generations of the Mouanes family were among the dead, including Kalthoum al-Haj Ali, 85, her daughter Nahya Mouanes, 65, and a granddaughter, Ibtisssam Khamees, 43, as well as Mrs. Khamees's nephew and niece. The wife of Sheik Muhammad Hamed, a village leader, was also buried in the rubble, as well as two of his sons and three of his daughters.</p>
        <p>''We couldn't save our children and we couldn't feed our families,'' cried Wansa Mouanes, 40, as she marched in a funeral procession. When the bombs went off she scrambled to try to save her sister and relatives, but she was no match for the weight of the rubble in which they were buried. ''If the Israelis thought they could force us to flee this way, they failed,'' she said defiantly.</p>
        <p>The bodies lay there for three weeks before they could be recovered, Ms. Mouanes said, serving as a constant reminder of the tragedy here. Five were removed Tuesday and taken to the morgue, she said, and another six were dug out Wednesday. All 11 were buried together on Wednesday in a grave that had 11 compartments, one for each body, fashioned out of cinder blocks.</p>
        <p>''Mama, listen to me!'' Fatima Mouanes cried as several young men lowered her mother's body before her in the mortuary. ''We are thinking of you. We will never forget you. Your death will not be in vain.''</p>
        <p>The crowd lifted the bodies on stretchers and in coffins and marched through the town's back streets as people looked on. A group of women who had gathered in a community center nearby threw rice at the bodies as they were carried past and soon fell into a loud wail.</p>
        <p>Minutes later Sheik Hamed, a portly man in his 50's, stood stoically before the bodies of his wife and children and called on the men in the crowd to open their hearts and pray for the souls of the dead, speaking in a matter-of-fact tone, as if praying for any other member of the community.</p>
        <p>Then, one by one, the bodies were carried to the grave site yards away and lowered into each compartment, as Sheik Hamed guided the young men carrying the bodies and led further prayers.</p>
        <p>''Bring me Abbas!'' he said, speaking of the body of his 7-year-old son, which was lowered in.</p>
        <p>''Now Khadija!'' he shouted, as the body of his 6-year-old daughter was lowered in, the crowd breaking out in calls of ''God is Great!''</p>
        <p>''Now Zeinab here!'' he exclaimed, speaking of his 22-year-old daughter.</p>
        <p>When all the bodies were in place, the crowd broke into a final wail as the sheik dipped down to each body to read a prayer. When he reached his wife's body, he kissed the shroud wrapping her and stopped briefly, grimacing, then composing himself.</p>
        <p>A tractor began scraping mounds of dirt into the grave, and within minutes the burial was over. As Sheik Hamed greeted well-wishers, he blessed them.</p>
        <p>''The history of this town is built on resistance,'' said Adil Mahmoud, Halusieh's mayor. ''Today we offered 11 martyrs, but we know we will continue to give more.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
