<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shares Rally, Then Sputter, After the Fed Trims Rates</title>
    <meta content="Y18STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1063102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Russell 2000 Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE3D61F31F93BA25752C1A96E958260" item-length="1041" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shares Rally, Then Sputter, After the Fed Trims Rates</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Widely anticipated cuts in interest rates by the Federal Reserve Board fail to invigorate stock market, which closes mixed in moderate trading; Dow Jones industrial average declines 24.97 to 8,986.28; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index gains 3.45 to 1,139.32; Nasdaq composite index gains 16.84 to 1,878.52; Russell 2000 declines 0.99 point to 389.43; graph; chart on stocks with large price percentage gains and losses (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Widely anticipated cuts in interest rates by the Federal Reserve Board did not invigorate the stock market yesterday. Prices, which have rallied sharply the last six weeks, closed mixed in moderate trading.</p>
        <p>Stocks moved lower early in the session, then jumped abruptly in midafternoon after the Fed announced its third cut in the overnight Federal funds rate and second reduction in its discount rate in the last seven weeks. But sellers emerged in the last hour of trading, particularly in big, blue-chip issues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Widely anticipated cuts in interest rates by the Federal Reserve Board did not invigorate the stock market yesterday. Prices, which have rallied sharply the last six weeks, closed mixed in moderate trading.</p>
        <p>Stocks moved lower early in the session, then jumped abruptly in midafternoon after the Fed announced its third cut in the overnight Federal funds rate and second reduction in its discount rate in the last seven weeks. But sellers emerged in the last hour of trading, particularly in big, blue-chip issues.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average, which fell as much as 82 points in the morning and was up as much as 91 after the Fed's announcement, closed down 24.97, or nearly three-tenths of 1 percent, at 8,986.28. Nearly all the average's decline resulted from a sharp slide in Hewlett-Packard, which closed at 60 1/16, down 6 1/16. Hewlett-Packard warned that first-quarter earnings might fall and that sales in its 1999 fiscal year were not likely to meet forecasts because of increased competition and weakness in Asia and Latin America.</p>
        <p>Most broader market indexes did better than the Dow. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index rose 3.45, or three-tenths of 1 percent, to 1,139.32. And the Nasdaq composite index gained 16.84, or nine-tenths of 1 percent, to 1,878.52. But the Russell 2000 index of mostly small-capitalization  stocks dipped 0.99 point, or a quarter of 1 percent, closing at 389.43.</p>
        <p>''We have come a very long way in a very short time,'' said Al Goldman, chief market strategist at A. G. Edwards, noting that since Oct. 8 the Dow rose 21 percent; the S.&amp; P. 500, 24 percent, and the Nasdaq composite, 39 percent.</p>
        <p>''The market was doing some consolidating last week and is likely to be doing some more of that,'' he said. ''But I don't see a lot of downside risk below 8,600 on the Dow. If there had been a 1-in-3 risk of a recession next year before the Fed started to cut rates, it has been reduced to a risk of 1 in 10.''</p>
        <p>The cuts in the Federal funds rate and the discount rate pushed those two rates to their lowest levels in four years and helped lift prices of financial service and bank stocks, which have been on the rise since the Fed began to cut rates in late September.</p>
        <p>J. P. Morgan and American Express, two Dow stocks, rose for the second consecutive day. Morgan gained 3 3/8, to 106 7/8. American Express rose 2 7/16, to 99 3/8. BankAmerica rose 1, to 60 3/4, and Chase Manhattan climbed 3 3/8, to 61 1/4.</p>
        <p>Brokerage stocks also gained. Merrill Lynch rose 2 13/16, to 66 5/16, and Morgan Stanley Dean Witter closed at 66 5/8, up 2 9/16.</p>
        <p>But not everyone was sanguine. Richard Bernstein, chief quantitative strategist at Merrill Lynch, said Hewlett-Packard was not likely to be the last company to issue a somber message on earnings for the coming year.</p>
        <p>''Most people think that if you get Fed easing, you will get earnings growth,'' he said. ''But we are in a period where earnings growth is negative. That is something people have pretty much ignored over the last six to seven weeks.''</p>
        <p>With interest rates at current levels, Mr. Bernstein said stocks were  between 10 and 20 percent above what he considered fair valuation.</p>
        <p>Slumping crude oil prices, which fell to a 10-year low in London and a 4-year low in New York, pushed down oil stocks.</p>
        <p>Chevron fell 2 1/2, to 80 3/4. Exxon dropped  7/8, to 70 9/16. And Mobil lost 11/16, to 71 15/16.</p>
        <p>With much fanfare, DaimlerChrysler, formed by the merger of Daimler-Benz and Chrysler, introduced its shares on the New York Stock Exchange yesterday. But the stock ended lower, closing at 83 7/8, down 7/16.</p>
        <p>The stars of Nasdaq included Amazon.com. Shares in the on-line bookseller soared 22 1/4, to 148 1/2, after it said it had opened an on-line video store to compete with Hollywood Entertainment's Reel.com Web site.</p>
        <p>Bigger high-technology companies that trade on the Nasdaq system also moved higher. Microsoft gained 3 1/16, to 111 7/8. Cisco Systems rose 1 13/16, to 68 3/4. And Intel closed at 108 1/2, up 1 5/8.</p>
        <p>K-Tel International was one of the session's biggest losers. The seller of music, videos and other entertainment was notified by Nasdaq that it had failed to meet the minimum tangible net asset requirement for trading, and faced delisting. The stock tumbled 5 5/8, to 12.</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Treasuries Are Mixed</p>
        <p>By Reuters</p>
        <p>Treasury bond prices ended mixed yesterday after the Federal Reserve cut interest rates as investors booked profits on the view the Fed would keep rates steady for the near future.</p>
        <p>The price of the 30-year Treasury bond fell 5/32, to 99 10/32. The bond's yield, which moves in the opposite direction, rose to 5.30 percent, from 5.29 percent on Monday.</p>
        <p>''It was buy the rumor, sell the fact,'' said Charles Parkhurst, the head bond trader at Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>Treasuries rose early in the session and held those gains until the Fed announced late in the session that it had lowered its Federal funds rate by a quarter of a point, to 4.75 percent, and cut the discount rate also by a quarter of a point, to 4.5 percent.</p>
        <p>The early gains were extended after the Fed's announcement, but the rally quickly faded as a wave of retail selling emerged.</p>
        <p>''People were ready to sell when the market went up,'' said John Spinello, fixed-income strategist at Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
