<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taking Turkey's Temperature</title>
    <meta content="18KITC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1063067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TEST KITCHEN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Thermometers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hesser, Amanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Temperature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05EEDC1F31F93BA25752C1A96E958260" item-length="880" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taking Turkey's Temperature</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Amanda Hesser</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hesser, Amanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Amanda Hesser tests meat thermometers in Test Kitchen column; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN roasting turkey, some people prefer to wing it, relying on a ballpark feeling for doneness. Others -- especially on major holidays -- want precision. They want to know exactly what they're getting and when they're getting it. And beyond the big day, they want to keep track of subtle differences, so they can modify temperatures a few degrees each time until they achieve perfection.</p>
        <p>For this, of course, they need a meat thermometer.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN roasting turkey, some people prefer to wing it, relying on a ballpark feeling for doneness. Others -- especially on major holidays -- want precision. They want to know exactly what they're getting and when they're getting it. And beyond the big day, they want to keep track of subtle differences, so they can modify temperatures a few degrees each time until they achieve perfection.</p>
        <p>For this, of course, they need a meat thermometer.</p>
        <p>Most meat thermometers are fairly accurate and vary only by two or three degrees. Their ease of use, though, varies widely. I tried instant read thermometers, which cannot remain in the oven, and oven thermometers, which are inserted in the thickest part of the meat at the beginning of cooking. And in the spirit of Thanksgiving, I tried them out on a plain roasted turkey.</p>
        <p>The Hoffritz meat and poultry thermometer, $9.99 at Zabar's, 2245 Broadway (80th Street), (212) 787-2000, and the Taylor basic meat dial thermometer, $5.98 at Zabar's, both oven thermometers, were clunky and difficult to read. They have thick shafts that left holes so large the turkey looked like it had been shot, and the thermometers were so top heavy I had to push them far down in the meat just so they wouldn't fall out.</p>
        <p>The other oven thermometer, made by Polder, is a digital unit that sits on a counter top or, with its magnet back, sticks on the oven door. It has a thin metal wire that stretches to a long, thin metal probe, which is inserted into the meat in the oven. It has nifty features, beyond giving continuous temperature readings without the cook having to open the oven door, like a timer and an alarm that will sound when the desired temperature is reached. It worked well and was very easy to read, but I found the wire cumbersome, especially when it came time for basting. One wrong move and the digital unit could topple to the floor, a pricey loss -- it's $21.99 at the Vinegar Factory, 431 East 91st Street (York Avenue), (212) 987-0885.</p>
        <p>Instant read thermometers can be troublesome, too. The Taylor classic one-inch dial model, $6.98 at Zabar's, is the thermometer that many chefs use. It is small and accurate and usually comes with a clip to attach to a shirt -- you can be armed and at the ready on Thanksgiving Day. And the shaft is thin, so you can test the meat in several places without making it look like Swiss cheese. But it takes about 45 seconds to give a reading -- so you have either to take the roasting pan out of the oven entirely or to stand there with the oven door open while the oven loses heat.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, the least professional-looking thermometer -- Maverick's Redi-Chek electronic food probe -- proved to be the easiest to use. Though it has a long shaft, which can be inserted in the meat, it is only the quarter-inch metal tip that measures the temperature. This allows you to pinpoint the center of the meat and know that exactly that point will be measured.</p>
        <p>It also works the most quickly of the instant read thermometers. You open the oven door, insert the thermometer, wait five seconds, press a button, wait another two or three seconds and, when it beeps, the temperature pops up on the digital display. The thermometer can then be removed and the oven door shut, and the reading will remain on the thermometer. Its only useless feature is a bar at the bottom of the digital display, which reads ''medium,'' ''medium-well'' and so on. (I'll avoid the temperature debate here, but whatever point you deem correct, remember that turkey continues to cook once it's out of the oven, so take it out when the thermometer reads a few degrees below that.) The Redi-Chek is $19.95 at Broadway Panhandler, 477 Broome Street (Wooster Street), (212) 966-3434.</p>
        <p>Testing these thermometers in a deep pan of 180-degree water revealed another characteristic worth considering. First, I dipped them just a half-inch into the water, then three inches. The two instant read thermometers were not sensitive enough at the tip -- they gave a reading 20 degrees below what it was, which means that when you insert them into a turkey, they may read the internal temperature as lower than it is. This explained why, when I tested them on a roasted pork tenderloin, which is only about an inch and a half thick, they had such low readings, while the Redi-Chek digital indicated the pork was done. And it was done.</p>
        <p>I put the thermometers to one last test: the drop. Thermometers so often roll off counter tops, it seemed worth testing their durability. I dropped each from counter-top height onto a tile floor. The glass in the Hoffritz dial cracked straight down the middle and a piece of plastic broke off the Polder. The others survived unscathed. Again, the Redi-Chek has an edge. It lies flat on your counter, so it can't roll off.</p>
        <p>TEST KITCHEN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
