<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shanahan Wants to Be the Perfect Coach</title>
    <meta content="18NFLL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1063107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Mike Shanahan</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denver Broncos</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shanahan, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Denver Broncos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EED61F31F93BA25752C1A96E958260" item-length="1256" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shanahan Wants to Be the Perfect Coach</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., Nov. 17</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mike Shanahan, vice president and head coach of Denver Broncos, discusses team's chances of going undefeated for whole season; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mike Shanahan is vice president and head coach of the Denver Broncos. It's the vice president title that's the thing. Shanahan picks his coaches, his players, his practice schedule, his offensive plays, the game plan and the Broncos' overall direction.</p>
        <p>And what a path the Broncos are blazing. With their dominating 30-7 victory over Kansas City here on Monday night, the Broncos are 47-16 in four seasons (including the post-season) under Shanahan, have won at least 9 of their first 10 games in each of the last three seasons, are the defending Super Bowl champions and, this season, have won 10 games and lost none. It is official now. With six regular-season games left, Shanahan and Denver are chasing history: an unbeaten and untied 16-game regular season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mike Shanahan is vice president and head coach of the Denver Broncos. It's the vice president title that's the thing. Shanahan picks his coaches, his players, his practice schedule, his offensive plays, the game plan and the Broncos' overall direction.</p>
        <p>And what a path the Broncos are blazing. With their dominating 30-7 victory over Kansas City here on Monday night, the Broncos are 47-16 in four seasons (including the post-season) under Shanahan, have won at least 9 of their first 10 games in each of the last three seasons, are the defending Super Bowl champions and, this season, have won 10 games and lost none. It is official now. With six regular-season games left, Shanahan and Denver are chasing history: an unbeaten and untied 16-game regular season.</p>
        <p>Who would have thought it possible 10 years ago when Shanahan was head coach of the Raiders in a miserable situation where control was not his. Shanahan refuses to offer details about his brief Raider tenure and continues to keep the depth of his frustration there inside. But he has said this: ''I thought I was going to the Raiders to be the head coach. That is not what I was.''</p>
        <p>A puppet? Maybe. But make no mistake, Al Davis, the Raiders' managing general partner, was in control. Here is how much:</p>
        <p>After the Raiders' initial 7-9 season under Shanahan in 1988, Nick Nicolau, then the Raiders' receivers coach, and Art Shell, the offensive line coach, got into an argument. Nicolau was a coach Shanahan had hired. Davis had forced Shanahan -- against Shanahan's wishes -- to keep several of the Raiders' assistant coaches, including Shell. Several of those coaches did not like it that Shanahan had been hired from outside the organization. Several of them wanted the job.</p>
        <p>Shanahan was 35 then, young and fresh and full of innovative ideas. Several coaches from the Raiders staff bucked against him. They wanted him to fail. Shanahan wanted big changes: For example, he wanted to run 80 plays in rapid-fire practices and games, rather than the 50 or so plays in the slow-paced style the Raiders had long featured. Some coaches and veteran players resisted; this was not the Raiders way at all, they insisted.</p>
        <p>After the Nicolau-Shell argument, Shanahan dismissed Shell and a few other coaches. A few days later, Davis hired them all back. And then Davis dismissed Nicolau. And then hired Fred Biletnikoff as Nicolau's replacement. Power play to Davis.</p>
        <p>Four games into the next season, after a 1-3 start, Davis dismissed Shanahan.</p>
        <p>''Getting fired is tough on anybody,'' Shanahan said here after Denver beat the Chiefs, making the Broncos only the eighth team since the merger of the old National and American Football Leagues in 1970 to reach 10-0. ''Not succeeding with the Raiders hurt. I think some of the edge is taken off that when you win the Super Bowl. But we didn't succeed here two seasons ago when we got off to a 12-1 start and lost at home in the playoffs to Jacksonville. That was an opportunity wasted. That still sticks in my craw.''</p>
        <p>In essence, this is Mike Shanahan.</p>
        <p>The failures nearly match the victories. The ones who doubted him he remembers nearly as much as the ones who applaud him. Winning the last Super Bowl is not enough. He wants another. And if it wasn't for that Jacksonville playoff debacle, Shanahan believes, he might be shooting for three consecutive rings.</p>
        <p>Driven. He wakes up thinking about winning. He goes to bed thinking about winning. And he is willing to pay the price for it -- with tireless work and attention to detail. He wants his place in history. Winning the Super Bowl again is, indeed, the priority. But 16-0? Believe it, he smells it. You want to leave a mark? That would be one for the ages. It is a vision dancing in his head.</p>
        <p>His team's, too.</p>
        <p>''If we go 16-0, it would not be finished,'' Denver safety Tyrone Braxton said. ''We want the Super Bowl again. But Mike is already being called the best coach in today's game. We do that, we go 16-0, and he goes down in history as one of the best ever. He would never say that, though. He is committed. As a defensive player, I always try to get into the opposing offensive coordinator's head. It is very difficult to get into Mike Shanahan's head.''</p>
        <p>Ask Kansas City. Shanahan, besides his superior talent in assembling and orchestrating an offense, has a knack for blending players' skills with his schemes. Take quarterback Bubby Brister, the backup to  John Elway. Brister is now 4-0 as a starter this season, including Monday night's game when Elway watched with bruised ribs. Brister runs better than Elway. First drive versus the Chiefs, Shanahan calls for a sell-out on the run and a bootleg keeper by Brister. Thirty-eight yards later, Brister was in the end zone and had achieved the longest scoring run by a quarterback in Denver history.</p>
        <p>If Elway were in the game, that play at that time would likely not have been called. Rather than wring his hands over not having Elway, Shanahan cooked up something that would milk what he did have in Brister. The Raiders can expect more when they visit Denver on Sunday as the Broncos continue their quest. And it is Shanahan who has lately had the last laugh on the Raiders: He is 6-1 against the Raiders as Denver's head coach.</p>
        <p>Bill Romanowski, the Denver linebacker who spit on the 49ers' J. J. Stokes last season, causing an uproar, appreciates Shanahan. ''That next afternoon, things were getting wild, and I walked up to Mike's office for advice; I wanted to hear what he had to say,'' Romanowski said.</p>
        <p>He wanted to get into Shanahan's head. ''Mike said I messed up,'' Romanowski said. '' He said I had already apologized and that I should keep apologizing. He told me to hold myself accountable for my actions.''</p>
        <p>Blunt and effective. Romanowski did what Shanahan advised. The incident could have lingered. It is now barely an afterthought.</p>
        <p>The Broncos have been good for four quarters in nearly every game, but their early play has been incredible. They are crushing opponents, 100-13, in the first quarter and by 42-3 on both teams' opening drives. This indicates two things: Shanahan's scripted plays that start each Denver game, that are practiced meticulously, work. It also says that he is winning the cat-and-mouse coaching game.</p>
        <p>Shanahan does the little things for his players. Each one has his own hotel room on the road. He serves them breakfast and lunch daily at the team's complex. Practice on Fridays is less physical because the Broncos don't wear pads. Mondays are a day when players arrive for work when they want, as long as the work is done. He rewards them financially, too. Produce, and you are treated fairly at contract time.</p>
        <p>''In my career I have played for Bill Walsh, George Seifert, Rich Kotite, Ray Rhodes and Mike Shanahan,'' said Romanowski, an 11-year veteran. ''Mike Shanahan is the best coach I have played for. When you win a Super Bowl, you get that hungry feeling to win another. It starts at the top and by understanding what Mike wants.''</p>
        <p>By getting into his head.</p>
        <p>ON PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
