<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Other 'Cradle of Aviation' Unveils a Museum</title>
    <meta content="02ISLA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="926946"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">History</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nassau County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Long Island (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cradle of Aviation Museum (East Garden City, NY) (Proposed)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gulotta, Thomas S (County Exec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindbergh, Charles A (1902-74)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lambert, Bruce</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E4D81F31F931A35756C0A961958260" item-length="655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Other 'Cradle of Aviation' Unveils a Museum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE LAMBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lambert, Bruce</byline>
      <dateline>EAST GARDEN CITY, N.Y., May 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Nassau County Exec Thomas S Gulotta breaks ground for $30-million Cradle of Aviation Museum that will open in East Garden City, New York, in 1999; Long Island has been major center of aviation development and aerospace industry; Charles Lindbergh took off from Long Island on flight to Paris in 1927 (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>No offense intended to the Wright Brothers and Kitty Hawk, N.C., but Long Island is staking its own claim as ''the cradle of aviation.''</p>
        <p>Today the Nassau County Executive, Thomas S. Gulotta, broke ground for a $30 million Cradle of Aviation Museum that is to open in 1999. Antique biplanes and monoplanes flew over, and Mr. Gulotta's ceremonial shovel was a long-handled scoop originally made for a mission to the moon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>No offense intended to the Wright Brothers and Kitty Hawk, N.C., but Long Island is staking its own claim as ''the cradle of aviation.''</p>
        <p>Today the Nassau County Executive, Thomas S. Gulotta, broke ground for a $30 million Cradle of Aviation Museum that is to open in 1999. Antique biplanes and monoplanes flew over, and Mr. Gulotta's ceremonial shovel was a long-handled scoop originally made for a mission to the moon.</p>
        <p>The event evoked nostalgia for the days of daredevil fliers on the 80 airfields that once operated on the Island, for Charles Lindbergh's electrifying solo trip across the Atlantic to Paris in 1927 -- which started with a bumpy takeoff just a mile from here -- and for the factories that built planes for World War II, Korea and Vietnam as well as the lunar module that took the first people to the moon.</p>
        <p>But the most visible legacy of Long Island's aviation history will be the museum itself. Unfortunately for the local economy, much of its aerospace industry has gone, devastated by Government cutbacks and eclipsed by West Coast competitors. The last plane made on the Island flew over Grumman's fence in Bethpage two years ago.</p>
        <p>''It's a little sad,'' lamented an industry old-timer who did not give his name as he walked around some of the aircraft on display in a hangar at what used to be Mitchel Field, an Air Force base. The base has been converted for use by two colleges, the Coliseum, office towers and a park.</p>
        <p>For now, Nassau officials are counting on the museum to infuse $40 million a year into the economy, drawing a predicted 400,000 visitors annually plus 120,000 children on school trips. The museum will house a 330-seat giant Imax dome theater and a fantasy 23d century space station theme restaurant called the Red Planet Cafe.</p>
        <p>In the future, to help develop a central Nassau hub, officials plan an entire museum row to include a children's museum, a firefighters museum, a science and technology museum and a carousel pavilion.</p>
        <p>Historians agree that the first sustained, powered flight was made by Orville and Wilbur Wright on Dec. 17, 1903. Their best effort that day lasted 59 seconds and covered 852 feet.</p>
        <p>But if Kitty Hawk was aviation's birthplace, Long Island makes a case that it soon became a major center of aviation development.</p>
        <p>''I would not argue with the name cradle -- it's perfectly justifiable -- but you just have to be careful to recognize that Long Island was not the only cradle,'' said Dr. Tom D. Crouch, chairman of aeronautics at the National Air and Space Museum in Washington, D.C. Other major centers were in southern California, Florida and Dayton, Ohio, where the Wrights were based, he said.</p>
        <p>The nation's first major aviation meet, with pioneering exhibitions and races, was held at Belmont Park in 1910.</p>
        <p>The rakish F-14 Tomcat fighter that Tom Cruise piloted in the hit movie ''Top Gun'' and the Hellcat and Wildcat that helped win World War II were all built by Grumman. Automatic-pilot systems and other innovative instruments that improved safety and made possible flying at night and in bad weather were created by Sperry in Lake Success. Other major companies included Fairchild and Republic in Farmingdale.</p>
        <p>The museum will have 65 exhibits. Its curator, Joshua J. Spoff, said that although it will not be the biggest aerospace museum, its interactive exhibits and other features will make it the world's most advanced. It will also be more diverse than many aviation museums, he said, with both civilian and military aircraft and a range in eras from pioneering aviation to modern space missions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
