<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Awaiting 'Santa Claus' At Labor Headquarters</title>
    <meta content="02LOND$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="926954"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyall, Sarah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E7D71F31F931A35756C0A961958260" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Awaiting 'Santa Claus' At Labor Headquarters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyall, Sarah</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Friday, May 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mood is festive at Labor Party's headquarters in London following election of Tony Blair as Prime Mininister and party's landslide victory in Parliament (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mood was festive and the scent of victory already in the air when crowds of Labor supporters -- party organizers, campaign volunteers and general hangers-on -- began arriving at the party's election-night headquarters by subway, by taxi and on foot late last night.</p>
        <p>Young and not so young, ebullient and serious, alone or in large, boisterous groups, many of the party loyalists who turned up for Labor's  all-night would-be celebration, at the Royal Festival Hall on the South Bank, said they could hardly believe their luck was about to change. A Labor victory, they seemed to agree, signified nothing less than a turning point in their lives and in the life of Britain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The mood was festive and the scent of victory already in the air when crowds of Labor supporters -- party organizers, campaign volunteers and general hangers-on -- began arriving at the party's election-night headquarters by subway, by taxi and on foot late last night.</p>
        <p>Young and not so young, ebullient and serious, alone or in large, boisterous groups, many of the party loyalists who turned up for Labor's  all-night would-be celebration, at the Royal Festival Hall on the South Bank, said they could hardly believe their luck was about to change. A Labor victory, they seemed to agree, signified nothing less than a turning point in their lives and in the life of Britain.</p>
        <p>''This is definitely the most important day in British politics in my lifetime,'' said Alex Bromley, 31, who works with the handicapped and who was 12 when Labor was last in power. ''All my adult life has been dictated by the Tories. We've waited and waited, and it's finally time.''</p>
        <p>Fortified by several large bottles of beer, Mr. Bromley and his friend Paddy Tipping, also 31 and a former coal miner who lost his job when Margaret Thatcher was Prime Minister and who now works as a health and safety adviser in London, prepared to wait out the night outside the hall. They were joined by a growing number of Laborites increasingly dazed with joy.</p>
        <p>''This feels absolutely wonderful,'' said Mr. Tipping, as early results -- first one constituency, and then another -- began to come in, with Labor winning each time. ''Margaret Thatcher once said that there's no such thing as a society. But now society has kicked out the Government.''</p>
        <p>John Casey, a 42-year-old teacher who has taken odd jobs on construction sites since losing his job, also found himself drawn to the Labor gathering. ''I was sitting at home and I thought I'd like to be closer to a bit of history,'' he said. ''Without being too dramatic, I believe we've been in the dark for too long.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Casey had no ticket for the gathering, and neither did Stefan Demetriou, a television technician who was 11 during the last Labor Government and who was hoping the celebratory mood inside the hall would rub off on the crowd outside. He said he felt the country was on the verge of something stupendous.</p>
        <p>''It's a bit like Christmas and New Year's Eve and the 1917 revolution all rolled up in one,'' said Mr. Demetriou, who had been drawn to the campaign headquarters when he began believing Labor would win. ''I feel like we're waiting for Santa Claus.'' He warmed to his theme. ''Most right-minded people would say they were fed up with the Tories' hypocrisy and profiteering. We've had it for 18 years, and we don't know anything else.''</p>
        <p>As excited as they were, many old-time Laborites recalled with horror the sad night (for them) of the 1992 general election, when a victory that seemed well within reach slipped away at the last minute. As a result, they were loath to take anything for granted.</p>
        <p>''It was devastating and highly depressing,'' said Alan Hutchings, 53, a graphic artist who lost his job several years ago and has been working as a Labor fund-raiser. ''All I can say tonight is that I'm hopeful.''</p>
        <p>Gail Pike, 18, a hotel waitress from Liverpool who has never known a Labor Government, said she had come to the party because she was a friend of the members of the pop group Dream, who sing Labor's theme song.</p>
        <p>She said she hoped Tony Blair would make good on his vow to establish a minimum wage. She said she now made about $3.75 an hour, before taxes, hardly enough to do more than scrape by. ''At home it'll be mad tonight,'' she said, speaking of Liverpool. ''Nobody likes the Tories.''</p>
        <p>But many Labor supporters stopped short when trying to describe exactly what they expected of a Government run by Mr. Blair.</p>
        <p>''I'm really excited,'' said Ray Ankrah, an accountant and one of a small number of black Laborites making their way to the party.</p>
        <p>''I'm looking forward to more social justice, a fairer society, a more active, listening government,'' he said. ''Of course, you never know what will really happen. All I'm saying is that after 18 years, we've had enough. It's time.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
