<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hussein's Refuge Offer: Risky Strategy</title>
    <meta content="02JORD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="927005"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Jordan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jehl, Douglas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein I (King of Hashemite Jordan)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abu Marzook, Mousa Mohammed</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Jordan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Jordan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asylum (Political)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E1DF1630F931A35756C0A961958260" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hussein's Refuge Offer: Risky Strategy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS JEHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jehl, Douglas</byline>
      <dateline>AMMAN, Jordan, May 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Douglas Jehl analysis contends that King Hussein's offer of refuge to Islamic militant leader Mousa Mohammed Abu Marzook has brought relief to US and Israel, whose misgivings about putting Abu Marzook on trial have left him in limbo after 22 months in New York jail; maintains that it is open question whether granting refuge to Abu Marzook will solve or contribute to Jordan's problems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>King Hussein of Jordan has long shown a liking for sailing close to the wind, with sharp and frequent tacks, so there is more wonder than puzzlement here about his latest innovation: offering refuge to a jailed Islamic militant leader radically opposed to the King's peace policies.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the invitation to Mousa Mohammed Abu Marzook, the political leader of the Islamic movement Hamas, has brought relief to both the United States and Israel, whose misgivings about putting Mr. Abu Marzook on trial have left him in limbo after 22 months in a New York jail.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>King Hussein of Jordan has long shown a liking for sailing close to the wind, with sharp and frequent tacks, so there is more wonder than puzzlement here about his latest innovation: offering refuge to a jailed Islamic militant leader radically opposed to the King's peace policies.</p>
        <p>Clearly, the invitation to Mousa Mohammed Abu Marzook, the political leader of the Islamic movement Hamas, has brought relief to both the United States and Israel, whose misgivings about putting Mr. Abu Marzook on trial have left him in limbo after 22 months in a New York jail.</p>
        <p>But it is an open question whether granting refuge to Mr. Abu Marzook will solve or contribute to problems for Jordan, already buffeted by more anti-Israeli sentiment than at any time since the two countries reached an accord almost three years ago.  ''It's very difficult to predict what role he might try to assume'' when he returns to Jordan, a senior Jordanian official conceded today of Mr. Abu Marzook.</p>
        <p>Jordan agreed to expel Mr. Abu Marzook at the request of the Americans in 1995 because of his links to terrorists. It was also in response to an American request that the King ''made the call'' to invite the Hamas leader to return and defuse a crisis over his fate, the Jordanian official said today.</p>
        <p>For nearly all of the time that Mr. Abu Marzook was jailed in Manhattan, the Israelis had requested that he be extradited to stand trial in Israel on allegations of complicity in a series of attacks. But Israel abandoned that request earlier this year in the face of Hamas threats to wage a new campaign of violence, and American officials had been quietly trying to find him a suitable home.</p>
        <p>Among all available options, Hamas officials had made plain that Jordan was at the top of their list, and they have said that Mr. Abu Marzook will play ''a leading role'' in the organization if he is permitted to return home.</p>
        <p>In announcing the King's decision on Wednesday, Jordan's Information Minister, Samir Mutawae, said that the invitation was being extended to Mr. Abu Marzook unconditionally, and that no restrictions apart from Jordanian law would govern his conduct in the country.</p>
        <p>There were few people today who expressed surprise at what was only the latest tactical shift for King Hussein. In the last six months the King has personally freed from prison an outspoken Islamic critic two years ahead of his term, summarily dismissed a Prime Minister he had until then fulsomely praised, dispatched a harsh letter to Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu over Israel's decision to build Jewish housing in predominantly Arab East Jerusalem and followed that up with a conciliatory visit to Israel after the shooting of Israeli schoolgirls by a Jordanian soldier.</p>
        <p>Such maneuvers, a hallmark of the King's nearly 45 years in power, have appeared part of his efforts to accommodate the sensibilities of a population whose majority is Palestinian while pushing an agenda that is often at odds with public sentiment.</p>
        <p>One Jordanian official said the decision had been based on the calculation that the longer Mr. Abu Marzook remained behind bars, the greater the danger that hostility toward the peace effort would spread within Jordan itself. But the official and several other analysts said they recognized that the strategy carried potential risk, particularly if Mr. Abu Marzook began to emerge as a prominent spokesman for the hard-line Hamas views. That would force the King to choose again whether to muffle the Hamas leader or continue to permit him to rile anti-Israeli sentiment.</p>
        <p>''The well-established ground rules here have been that you can't use Jordan as a platform for vocal threats toward Israel,'' said Rami G. Khouri, a Jordanian columnist. ''The new breed, including Hamas, has been inclined to push and prod, and some of them have found themselves in jail. I think that Abu Marzook will try to do his thing, but if he wants to stay here, he'll have to stick by the unwritten rules of the game.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
