<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Guards and Fans Swarming, Tyson Blames His Accusers</title>
    <meta content="25TYSO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/25/nyregion/25TYSO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20030726T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1507055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Von Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tyson, Mike</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Velez, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alvarez-Ramos, Nestor</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Threats and Threatening Messages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Tyson, Mike</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EFDF133FF936A15754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Guards and Fans Swarming, Tyson Blames His Accusers</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Armed Guards and Admirers Swarming, Tyson Blames Accusers</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL von ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Von Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Crowds swarm outside courthouse as Mike Tyson arrives to plead not guilty to charges of beating Samuel Velez and Nestor Alvarez-Ramos in hotel lobby in Brooklyn on June 21; Tyson's lawyer says men threatened Tyson; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Past his prime or not, Mike Tyson, the aging Brownsville brawler and former heavyweight champion of the world, seemed no less a star yesterday in Brooklyn Criminal Court than he has been in the boxing ring over the past two decades.</p>
        <p>Small armies of television cameramen and photographers lined up three deep to catch him strolling with an entourage out of court, where he had just pleaded not guilty to state charges in the beating of two men in a Brooklyn hotel lobby last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Boxer Mike Tyson appeared in court to plead not guilty to state charges of beating two men in a Brooklyn hotel lobby last month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Past his prime or not, Mike Tyson, the aging Brownsville brawler and former heavyweight champion of the world, seemed no less a star yesterday in Brooklyn Criminal Court than he has been in the boxing ring over the past two decades.</p>
        <p>Small armies of television cameramen and photographers lined up three deep to catch him strolling with an entourage out of court, where he had just pleaded not guilty to state charges in the beating of two men in a Brooklyn hotel lobby last month.</p>
        <p>Armed and nervous, state court officers escorted the famous prize fighter out of the building. Reporters surrounded Mr. Tyson, walking in baby steps as a single organic mass, jamming microphones and tape recorders in his face, some asking for a comment, others keeping oddly quiet, as if cowed by Mr. Tyson's reputation for violently losing his cool.</p>
        <p>From the balcony of the court building's sweaty lobby, a crowd of employees and passers-by waved and shouted, ''Mike Tyson!'' as the boxer, the court officers and the media mob passed underneath. Mr. Tyson, calm and silent during his 20 minutes in the spotlight yesterday, looked up, smiled and waved to his fans, who cheered even louder.</p>
        <p>''He's friendly and engaging with members of the public,'' said Mel A. Sachs, one of Mr. Tyson's lawyers.</p>
        <p>That may not be evident to Samuel Velez and Nestor Alvarez-Ramos, whose beating at the hands of Mr. Tyson on June 21 led Brooklyn prosecutors to charge him with seven misdemeanor counts that include assault, harassment and disorderly conduct. The two men said they approached Mr. Tyson in a Marriott hotel in Brooklyn around 5:30 a.m., after spending most of the previous night out on the town.</p>
        <p>Mr. Velez and Mr. Alvarez-Ramos told the police they had only asked Mr. Tyson, 37, for an autograph, and that Mr. Tyson reacted by pounding Mr. Velez about the head and body and knocking Mr. Alvarez-Ramos into a reception stand.</p>
        <p>Yesterday in court, Mr. Sachs told Judge John Carter that Mr. Tyson had been provoked and, considering the circumstances, had been justified. ''They told him, 'You got fists. We got guns,' '' Mr. Sachs said, with his client beside him and nine state court and city police officers hovering nearby. Later, outside the court building, Mr. Sachs told reporters: ''Mike Tyson exercised restraint. This a bad, weak case.''</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday afternoon, Mr. Sachs, who also represented Yankees pitcher David Wells after a Yonkers man punched him in a Manhattan diner last September, said Mr. Velez had reached toward his waist after threatening Mr. Tyson.</p>
        <p>''Mike Tyson had every reason to believe that he had a gun,'' Mr. Sachs said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Velez and Mr. Alvarez-Ramos deny having made threats. In fact, five days after the brawl, Mr. Velez, 31, of Reading, Pa., told The Daily News in an interview from a Rikers Island jail that he had approached Mr. Tyson ''out of love, out of respect.''</p>
        <p>Both men were charged with menacing and harassment and are scheduled to make their own appearance in Brooklyn Criminal Court next week, officials said.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, Judge Carter ordered the Brooklyn assistant district attorney prosecuting Mr. Tyson, John O'Hara, to hand over hospital records detailing injuries to Mr. Velez and Mr. Alvarez-Ramos, as well as a hotel security tape documenting the melee.</p>
        <p>The videotape shows Mr. Tyson assaulting the two men, pausing to remove his jacket, then resuming the attack, the authorities said. At one point, he chased one of the men around the check-in desk. The tape also shows one of the men picking up a stanchion and thrusting it toward Mr. Tyson.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tyson is due back in court for a preliminary hearing on Sept. 30. Mr. Tyson, who was knocked out in the eighth round by Lennox Lewis in his most recent bid for the heavyweight title, would face up to a year in prison if convicted.</p>
        <p>He has already gone to prison twice in the last 11 years: for three years after a 1992 conviction for raping a woman in an Indianapolis hotel room, and briefly in 1999 for assaulting two people in a car that had rear-ended his vehicle.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tyson's most notorious act inside a boxing ring was biting off a portion of Evander Holyfield's ear during a 1997 title fight that, by most expert accounts, he was losing.</p>
        <p>Correction:  July 26, 2003, Saturday  An article yesterday about a hearing in Brooklyn Criminal Court at which Mike Tyson pleaded not guilty in the beating of two men in a hotel lobby last month misstated the surname of the prosecutor. He is John O'Mara, not O'Hara.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 26, 2003, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article yesterday about a hearing in Brooklyn Criminal Court at which Mike Tyson pleaded not guilty in the beating of two men in a hotel lobby last month misstated the surname of the prosecutor. He is John O'Mara, not O'Hara.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
