<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Child-Abuse Case, in the Eyes of the Accused</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="762593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILD ABUSE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOME BOX OFFICE (HBO)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MCMARTIN, VIRGINIA, PRESCHOOL (MANHATTAN BEACH, CALIF)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MYDANS, SETH</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">INDICTMENT: THE MCMARTIN TRIAL (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950514T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DA1531F937A25756C0A963958260" item-length="1075" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Child-Abuse Case, in the Eyes of the Accused</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH MYDANS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MYDANS, SETH</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT WAS THE LONGEST AND MOST expensive criminal case in the nation's history. It set a baseline for the legal exploration of child abuse and its treatment by the courts, the police and the press. And it left a legacy of bitterness and ruined reputations.</p>
        <p>The McMartin Preschool child molestation case, which ended with a hung jury in 1990 after seven years and two trials, was the courtroom sensation of its day. A total of 124 witnesses, 800 exhibits and more than 60,000 pages of court records accumulated as hundreds of charges of child molestation were brought against seven workers at the Virginia McMartin Preschool in suburban Manhattan Beach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT WAS THE LONGEST AND MOST expensive criminal case in the nation's history. It set a baseline for the legal exploration of child abuse and its treatment by the courts, the police and the press. And it left a legacy of bitterness and ruined reputations.</p>
        <p>The McMartin Preschool child molestation case, which ended with a hung jury in 1990 after seven years and two trials, was the courtroom sensation of its day. A total of 124 witnesses, 800 exhibits and more than 60,000 pages of court records accumulated as hundreds of charges of child molestation were brought against seven workers at the Virginia McMartin Preschool in suburban Manhattan Beach.</p>
        <p>In the years since, the impact of the case has been overshadowed by ever-more-sensational "trials of the century" in Los Angeles -- Rodney King, Reginald Denny, the Menendez brothers, O. J. Simpson. But on Saturday, starting at 8 P.M., an HBO film that forcefully presents the point of view of the defense in the case is to reopen old wounds and old controversies.</p>
        <p>What are parents, doctors and the police to do when a child reports sexual abuse at a day-care center; when more than 300 children report the abuse; when their reports grow ever more extraordinary, to include accounts of satanic rituals, mutilated corpses, the killing of a horse and the sacrifice of a live baby in a church? How can one assess hundreds of hours of videotaped interviews in which one child after another at first denies to a social worker that he or she was abused, then, under continued questioning, apparently begins to remember?</p>
        <p>For the makers of "Indictment: The McMartin Trial," questions like these are not hard ones. The film makes no pretense at objectivity: There are good guys in the McMartin saga, and there are very, very bad guys, ambitious prosecutors, misguided social workers, angry or deluded parents and, most of all, a voracious press corps gone wild.</p>
        <p>Nor does the film try to examine difficult issues. It is a drama not so much about the painful process of assessing children's stories of abuse or about the fear and guilt their parents feel but about the destructiveness of a system run amok. As advertisements for the film declare, "The charges were so shocking, the truth didn't matter."</p>
        <p>They were the sort of charges that tar a defendant forever, no matter what the trial's outcome. Five of the defendants were dropped from the case midway because the evidence against them was so insubstantial. The sixth, Peggy McMartin Buckey, was acquitted in the first trial. Charges against her son, Raymond Buckey, were finally dropped after two juries could not reach verdicts against him. At the time, he had already spent five years in jail.</p>
        <p>But the film's closing portrayal of a gratuitous taunt is a reminder that the Buckeys, though never convicted, will forever be child molesters in the eyes of many people.</p>
        <p>THE LEADING PLAYERS HERE, as in real-life legal dramas, are the lawyers. The story is told from the point of view of Mr. Buckey's lawyer, Danny Davis, who is portrayed by James Woods as a small-time opportunist who becomes a crusader. His foil is the prosecutor, Assistant District Attorney Lael Rubin, played by Mercedes Ruehl as driven and relentless -- one of the easy-to-dislike villains in this film.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rubin said she could not comment on the film because its makers had not let her see it before it is broadcast. "I'm in a very difficult position because I would like very much to comment," she said, "and I can't because they have not given me the opportunity to see the film."</p>
        <p>Robert Cooper, senior vice president of HBO Pictures, said the film could be compared with others that have addressed serious subjects, like "And the Band Played On," about the early years of the AIDS plague, and "Murderers Among Us: The Simon Wiesenthal story," about the Holocaust and the postwar hunt for Nazis.</p>
        <p>"To me what was most intriguing was that the media had become crazy, insane, irresponsible," Mr. Cooper said. "The villains would have been much smaller had they hot been magnified by the media. The media takes a magnifying glass and distorts, as well as exaggerates, what's going on."</p>
        <p>This is an assessment the press itself has made -- in somewhat more muted terms -- in post-mortems on the McMartin coverage, particularly in a four-part analysis by David Shaw of The Los Angeles Times. Mr. Shaw said that the media had played "a pivotal and sometimes distorting role" in the case, and that news organizations, particularly in the early stages, had failed to maintain their objectivity.</p>
        <p>The HBO production seems to be something of a crusade for some of those involved with it.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Woods, the film seemed not only an artistic project but a personal mission. In an interview, he referred to some people in the case as real villains and talked with reverence about "the power of the truth" and the "soul-enhancing experience" of Mr. Davis's transformation from cynic to believer.</p>
        <p>The film was written by Abby Mann, whose credits include "Judgment at Nuremberg." He is also writing a book about the McMartin case, he said. His wife, Myra, sat through years of slow-going testimony in the case and served as a sort of encyclopedia for the film makers.</p>
        <p>In a case with few neutral players, the couple became identified with the defense. Mr. Mann said he had been accused of bias by parents who believe that Mr. Buckey was guilty and who remain as dedicated to the case as he is. He said his house had burned down under suspicious circumstances on the first day of filming.</p>
        <p>"There's still a group out there, still coming out of the woodwork," Mr. Mann said. His wife added, "The McMartin case was never brought to a conclusion."</p>
        <p>Should a television film about real events and real, living people try to be balanced? Mr. Cooper of HBO Pictures said that while a docu-drama was clearly a drama and not a documentary, this project had hewed faithfully to the record of the case while exploring the emotions and motivations of its characters.</p>
        <p>"If you don't have a point of view, then you have nothing; it just meanders," he said. "So one tries to be accurate and get all the facts, but the facts of a person's life have a point of view.</p>
        <p>"I think every single drama does that," he added. "I don't know how you can tell a story without taking a point of view. When we did Simon Wiesenthal, we did his point of view. We didn't do the point of view of the Nazis."  TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
