<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Capri: Convertible From Down Under</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="382867"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT CARS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DA1430F93AA3575AC0A966958260" item-length="1659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Capri: Convertible From Down Under</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARSHALL SCHUON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Like Mazda's Miata, America's newest doff-top car attracts a tremendous amount of attention. Drive it and you'd better be ready with some answers, or at least some chitchat for the curious.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Like Mazda's Miata, America's newest doff-top car attracts a tremendous amount of attention. Drive it and you'd better be ready with some answers, or at least some chitchat for the curious.</p>
        <p>It arrives in the States in two flavors, plain Capri and Turbo XR2, both with four-cylinder engines, both with manual tops and both with air bags in the hubs of their leather-wrapped steering wheels.</p>
        <p>It is also this country's first car from Australia, assembled at Ford's Broadmeadows plant near Melbourne, which produces Down-Under Falcons and Fairlanes (and how are those for names from the past?). The ragtops make their 12,000-mile sea journey at a cost that is said to be only $355 per copy, and the fee is incorporated into stickers that range from $12,943 to $15,877.</p>
        <p>That makes the price very right, and the sticker ought to help Mercury sell a ton of these cars, if the dealers can resist the trend toward premiums.</p>
        <p>Unlike the Mazda two-seater, Capri has a rudimentary back seat and a reasonable amount of storage room. And the base price, in part made possible by tax concessions from the Australian Government, is about $1,000 less than the Miata's.</p>
        <p>Comparisons with Mazda's gem of a convertible are impossible to avoid. While the rear-wheel-drive Miata harks to the heyday of the British sports car, the front-drive Capri is more Italian - maybe more Italian-American - and the cars exhibit quite different personalities.</p>
        <p>Both have 1.6-liter engines that use four valves per cylinder. But the Miata's 116 horsepower falls right between the 100 horses of the bottom-of-the-line Capri and the 132 of the turbocharged XR2. At 2,182 pounds, the Miata also is 200 pounds lighter, and its performance almost matches that of the XR2 while outstripping the base Merc.</p>
        <p>The Miata's roof is easier to put down, although the Capri also is something of a snap. The difference is that the Miata can be unlatched and flipped open while you sit at the wheel; the Capri requires that you get out and do some fiddling around.</p>
        <p>The Capri's top disappears under plastic tonneau, however, while the Miata has a canvas cover that is more trouble and less sleek. For colder climes, Capri offers a 75-pound steel roof, while Mazda has a plastic hardtop.</p>
        <p>The tester was an appropriately white plain-vanilla Capri with blackout trim, body-colored bumpers and a black and red vinyl strip around the midsection. There were hooded headlights, power windows and electrically operated mirrors, and all Capris have a ''walk-in'' release that allows the front seats to slide forward for easier entry.</p>
        <p>In addition to red, white and blue, the car can be had in black or silver, and the upholstery is cloth. The front buckets, gray-and-red tweed in the test car, are comfortable and have surprisingly long seat cushions, but the rear consists of a folding bench that even Ford admits is for people you don't like.</p>
        <p>With the back seat folded, however, there is the sort of cargo room that Capri's buyers probably will appreciate, and a pass-through from the trunk actually allows for skis, foils or other such dangerous silliness.</p>
        <p>The car is tight, a result of engineering and construction that aimed at creating an exceptionally stiff and safe convertible. There are no rattles and few shakes, and the car's all-strut suspension handles remarkably well, with stopping accomplished by four-wheel disk brakes.</p>
        <p>The cloth and vinyl interior makes no pretense to luxury, but it is nicely done, well put together and functional. Instrumentation includes a 140-m.p.h. speedometer whose top digits will never wear out, an 8,000-r.p.m. tachometer and the usual gauges.</p>
        <p>Under the glove box, there is a knee bolster for passenger protection, and the car has an assortment of niceties to make it easy to live with. Unfortunately, the test car also had the 100-horsepower engine coupled to the Capri's optional four-speed automatic transmission, and that is a less-than-optimum way to go.</p>
        <p>While the combination made the Capri fine at highway speeds, acceleration was leisurely, and there was a surprising sluggishness when the fuel-injected engine was cold. The standard five-speed stick, all that is available in the more powerful XR2, is a better choice.</p>
        <p>But the question remains? Miata or Capri. For my money, the Miata has the edge - but you can buy Australian for less. And either way, you are likely to be just a bit happier than you are right now.</p>
        <p>LIKE Mazda's Miata, America's newest doff-top car attracts a tremendous amount of attention. Drive it and you'd better be ready with some answers, or at least some chitchat for the curious.</p>
        <p>The car is Ford Motor Company's 1991 Mercury Capri, which began life as a concept vehicle at the Frankfurt auto show in 1983. At the time, it was called the Barchetta, more apt perhaps than Capri, although there is something to be said for using a name from the past, at least from a marketing standpoint.</p>
        <p>The car at the German show was designed by the Ghia studio in Turin, Italy, based on the European Ford Fiesta but with Japanese underpinnings. Barchetta is Italian for ''little boat,'' and that is just what the convertible Capri has come to be.</p>
        <p>It arrives in the States in two flavors, plain Capri and Turbo XR2, both with four-cylinder engines, both with manual tops and both with air bags in the hubs of their leather-wrapped steering wheels.</p>
        <p>It is also this country's first car from Australia, assembled at Ford's Broadmeadows plant near Melbourne, which produces Down-Under Falcons and Fairlanes (and how are those for names from the past?). The ragtops make their 12,000-mile sea journey at a cost that is said to be only $355 per copy, and the fee is incorporated into stickers that range from $12,943 to $15,877.</p>
        <p>That makes the price very right, and the sticker ought to help Mercury sell a ton of these cars, if the dealers can resist the trend toward premiums.</p>
        <p>Unlike the Mazda two-seater, Capri has a rudimentary back seat and a reasonable amount of storage room. And the base price, in part made possible by tax concessions from the Australian Government, is about $1,000 less than the Miata's.</p>
        <p>Comparisons with Mazda's gem of a convertible are impossible to avoid. While the rear-wheel-drive Miata harks to the heyday of the British sports car, the front-drive Capri is more Italian - maybe more Italian-American - and the cars exhibit quite different personalities.</p>
        <p>Both have 1.6-liter engines that use four valves per cylinder. But the Miata's 116 horsepower falls right between the 100 horses of the bottom-of-the-line Capri and the 132 of the turbocharged XR2. At 2,182 pounds, the Miata also is 200 pounds lighter, and its performance almost matches that of the XR2 while outstripping the base Merc.</p>
        <p>The Miata's roof is easier to put down, although the Capri also is something of a snap. The difference is that the Miata can be unlatched and flipped open while you sit at the wheel; the Capri requires that you get out and do some fiddling around.</p>
        <p>The Capri's top disappears under plastic tonneau, however, while the Miata has a canvas cover that is more trouble and less sleek. For colder climes, Capri offers a 75-pound steel roof, while Mazda has a plastic hardtop.</p>
        <p>The tester was an appropriately white plain-vanilla Capri with blackout trim, body-colored bumpers and a black and red vinyl strip around the midsection. There were hooded headlights, power windows and electrically operated mirrors, and all Capris have a ''walk-in'' release that allows the front seats to slide forward for easier entry.</p>
        <p>In addition to red, white and blue, the car can be had in black or silver, and the upholstery is cloth. The front buckets, gray-and-red tweed in the test car, are comfortable and have surprisingly long seat cushions, but the rear consists of a folding bench that even Ford admits is for people you don't like.</p>
        <p>With the back seat folded, however, there is the sort of cargo room that Capri's buyers probably will appreciate, and a pass-through from the trunk actually allows for skis, foils or other such dangerous silliness.</p>
        <p>The car is tight, a result of engineering and construction that aimed at creating an exceptionally stiff and safe convertible. There are no rattles and few shakes, and the car's all-strut suspension handles remarkably well, with stopping accomplished by four-wheel disk brakes.</p>
        <p>The cloth and vinyl interior makes no pretense to luxury, but it is nicely done, well put together and functional. Instrumentation includes a 140-m.p.h. speedometer whose top digits will never wear out, an 8,000-r.p.m. tachometer and the usual gauges.</p>
        <p>Under the glove box, there is a knee bolster for passenger protection, and the car has an assortment of niceties to make it easy to live with. Unfortunately, the test car also had the 100-horsepower engine coupled to the Capri's optional four-speed automatic transmission, and that is a less-than-optimum way to go.</p>
        <p>While the combination made the Capri fine at highway speeds, acceleration was leisurely, and there was a surprising sluggishness when the fuel-injected engine was cold. The standard five-speed stick, all that is available in the more powerful XR2, is a better choice.</p>
        <p>But the question remains? Miata or Capri. For my money, the Miata has the edge - but you can buy Australian for less. And either way, you are likely to be just a bit happier than you are right now.</p>
        <p>ABOUT CARS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
