<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Trashing of CUNY</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STANDARDS AND STANDARDIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CITY UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK (CUNY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COOK, BLANCHE WIESEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">COOPER, SANDI E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E0DE1E38F93BA3575AC0A962958260" item-length="1000" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Trashing of CUNY</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Blanche Wiesen Cook and Sandi E. Cooper;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COOPER, SANDI E; COOK, BLANCHE WIESEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The decline or demise of the City University of New York has been forecast at least as far back as 1969, when enrollment was opened to anyone with a high school diploma. But this summer, the critics have been especially busy, and mean-spirited, too.</p>
        <p>First, a long, contemptuous article by Heather Mac Donald appeared in the summer issue of City Journal, the quarterly of the Manhattan Institute, a conservative group that aspires to serve as the Giuliani administration's think tank. That attack found a much wider audience when John Leo cited it approvingly in U.S. News &amp; World Report; Mr. Leo's column was then reprinted in newspapers around the country, and readers as far away as Seattle learned that "CUNY is at the cutting edge of a nationwide movement to do away with the very distinction between academic proficiency and deficiency and replace it with the concept of competence in one's own culture."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The decline or demise of the City University of New York has been forecast at least as far back as 1969, when enrollment was opened to anyone with a high school diploma. But this summer, the critics have been especially busy, and mean-spirited, too.</p>
        <p>First, a long, contemptuous article by Heather Mac Donald appeared in the summer issue of City Journal, the quarterly of the Manhattan Institute, a conservative group that aspires to serve as the Giuliani administration's think tank. That attack found a much wider audience when John Leo cited it approvingly in U.S. News &amp; World Report; Mr. Leo's column was then reprinted in newspapers around the country, and readers as far away as Seattle learned that "CUNY is at the cutting edge of a nationwide movement to do away with the very distinction between academic proficiency and deficiency and replace it with the concept of competence in one's own culture."</p>
        <p>These latest attacks reflect the national hand-wringing about the collapse of educational standards and local hostility to spending money for public education. They also reflect a social vision, disguised in the language of fiscal accountability, that follows these lines:</p>
        <p>Not all students are educable; governments and universities are not equipped to repair the legacy of familial and societal decay; well-intended public efforts to eliminate inequality and abolish racism are expensive failures. Competition is the only way that the fittest and finest emerge as leaders. Higher education can benefit only a talented minority; it cannot address racial injustice or repair past discrimination; and, finally, what's good for the goose is good for the gander (that disposes of feminist or multicultural arguments). In short, social Darwinism is the anthem for the late 20th century.</p>
        <p>To us, both graduates of city colleges in an era when tuition was free, these attacks are disgraceful. At a time when complex skills are needed for entry-level jobs, we see no wisdom in calls to curtail opportunity.</p>
        <p>Those who lament the loss of 1950's standards, 1950's students and 1950's culture, the loss of some imagined Harvard on the Hudson, ignore the failures of the past, the achievements of the present and the realities of New York City.</p>
        <p>There are in fact many similarities between the graduates of the old days and the graduates of today. CUNY's critics, however, tend to compare the top of the old with the bottom of the new. They ignore that the university has grown from 4 colleges to 20, including 10 senior colleges, 7 community colleges, a graduate center, a law school and an affiliated medical school. It serves more than 210,000 students, representing every segment of New York City.</p>
        <p>These students include people from every ethnic group, from homeless families and families on welfare, and the newly arrived from every continent. At a time when less than 4 percent of students from the bottom quarter of the economic ladder now finish college, according to a recent report in Business Week, CUNY remains an exceptional avenue of opportunity. The first Rhodes Scholar from Brooklyn College is a Puerto Rican woman. CUNY graduates more African-American and Latino engineers, science majors and master's candidates than any other university in the United States.</p>
        <p>But CUNY's critics invoke only those statistics designed to demonstrate that students burn money, fail excessively and earn worthless degrees. Ms. Mac Donald cites a 1989 survey finding that only 22 percent of the 1980 freshmen had graduated within five years. But studies by CUNY statisticians suggest that 40 percent graduate within eight years, and there is a good reason it might take so long: a typical CUNY student is a working adult, often with family responsibilities and often attending part time.</p>
        <p>Open enrollment, the favored target of conservative critics, does not really exist anymore at the four-year colleges -- City, Hunter, Brooklyn, Queens, Staten Island, New York City Technical, York, Baruch, Lehman and Medgar Evers. It was basically undone as a result of New York City's fiscal crisis in 1974-75. That year, classes and graduations were suspended, faculty and staff members lost salary, tenure was broken and tuition was imposed. Eventually the four-year colleges reinstated admission requirements close to the national norms.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the system has been starved of the resources it needs to do its job. The full-time faculty has been reduced by a third since 1975. Class size has doubled, and classes are increasingly taught by young adjuncts or graduate students. Last year there was a furor over Chancellor W. Ann Reynolds's reorganization plan, which appeared to restrict liberal-arts education and redirect resources to practical, career-oriented training. Though this plan has been formally abandoned, faculty members remain suspicious that its objectives may yet be achieved by the back door, through budget allocations.</p>
        <p>These difficult circumstances don't upset CUNY's critics, including a few professors who continue to accept salaries for work they now seem to detest. They represent a tiny minority of the faculty who have declared war not on the shrinking of the public purse but on the students.</p>
        <p>The critics are correct to this extent: the allocated budgets cannot support CUNY's needs. But the critics' prescriptions for triage of the weak -- curtailing admissions, remedial services, counseling support and the SEEK program for disadvantaged students -- are wrong.</p>
        <p>We must relearn some lessons and treat this generation as generously as we did the veterans of World War II. The public funds that they got helped create the biggest boom in American history. Only a handful of far-right cranks, in those days, complained about the G.I. Bill, or housing loans or pensions for the disabled. Is that because the beneficiaries were largely white males? Amid the difficulties of the present, the past always has a rosy glow that wasn't there when we lived in it.  Blanche Wiesen Cook, professor of history at John Jay College, is author of "Eleanor Roosevelt." Sandi E. Cooper is professor of history at the College of Staten Island and head of CUNY's Faculty Senate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Blanche Wiesen Cook, professor of history at John Jay College, is author of "Eleanor Roosevelt." Sandi E. Cooper is professor of history at the College of Staten Island and head of CUNY's Faculty Senate.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
