<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If It's Early September, It's Time for a Haircut; With School Starting, Barbers Find Wedges, Buzzes and Bowls in Big Demand</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Out and About -- A periodic look at rites of summer in the New York area." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY METROPOLITAN AREA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KLEINFIELD, N R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hair</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940908T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E1D91138F93BA3575AC0A962958260" item-length="1312" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If It's Early September, It's Time for a Haircut; With School Starting, Barbers Find Wedges, Buzzes and Bowls in Big Demand</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By N. R. KLEINFIELD,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KLEINFIELD, N R</byline>
      <dateline>MIDLAND PARK, N.J., Sept. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If there is one thing that Larry Giglio has learned in 56 years cutting hair, it is that a barber who can survive the day before school can survive anything.</p>
        <p>"Give me a wedge," said 11-year-old Steve Fiedeldey. "Cut it a little higher and less hair than usual. I'm playing football. The helmet has to fit on."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If there is one thing that Larry Giglio has learned in 56 years cutting hair, it is that a barber who can survive the day before school can survive anything.</p>
        <p>"Give me a wedge," said 11-year-old Steve Fiedeldey. "Cut it a little higher and less hair than usual. I'm playing football. The helmet has to fit on."</p>
        <p>Eight-year-old Michael Mattera had a different preference. "I want a bowl," he said, explaining with gestures of his hands. "I would like a buzz. But my mother says no buzz. So it's a bowl."</p>
        <p>"This is going to be a madhouse today," said Mr. Giglio, an easy-talking, beetle-browed man who is the Larry in Larry &amp; Phil's barber shop on Godwin Avenue here. "The hair's going to be flying."</p>
        <p>As the sedate rhythms of summer wind down, school preparation arrives as one of the ceremonial conclusions to the season. Thus the trips to buy pencils, notebooks and lunch boxes, not to mention rubber bands to propel at the teacher. Thus the acquisition of new clothes that you dread being seen in. And thus, inevitably, the obligatory haircut.</p>
        <p>The days preceding major holidays are plainly welcome to barbers, since that is when their scissors are most in demand. The week before Christmas and the week before Easter are widely felt to be the two most congested hair-cutting periods, followed by the week before New Year's. After those come the swarm of back-to-school haircuts.</p>
        <p>With school opening tomorrow in this northern New Jersey community and on Thursday in some encircling towns, Larry &amp; Phil's has been frenetic for the last week, building to a pitch today. Capering youngsters with excess hair were elbowing one another for a place to wait.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giglio was alertly attentive. About to turn 80, he has witnessed up close more ways to wear hair than he can vividly remember. He has an invulnerability to surprise. The latest styles do not amaze him, but neither do they particularly delight him.</p>
        <p>"Kids used to come in and say, 'Give me a haircut,' " Mr. Giglio said somewhat ruefully. "Now they come in and say, 'Give me a buzz.' 'Give me a wedge.' You tell me what a buzz is?"</p>
        <p>A buzz is a crew cut, which is back in vogue. It's also called a clipper. A wedge, even more popular, is cut very short around the sides, and left longer on top, with the hair converging to a wedge shape in the back.</p>
        <p>This is where the line between a completed and uncompleted haircut begins to blur. The wedge looks like half a haircut. An early version was worn by Dorothy Hamill, the Olympic figure skater. It is of the same family as another commonly requested style, the mushroom or surfer cut, where the shorter portion climbs higher on the head. Then there is the bowl, where the hair is even all around. There are modified bowls, as when the hair is cut very short beneath lengthier overlapping hair.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giglio sent his eyes through the head beneath him, halfway to a bowl. "It's a circus today," he said, never less than candid. "Sometimes, you're ashamed to say you're a professional barber. They want you to do this bowl cut. That used to be for when you couldn't afford a barber and your parents did it for you in the kitchen. It's not good art barbering. I like the nice conventional haircut.</p>
        <p>"But who am I to judge? They pay the freight."  Awards for First Haircuts</p>
        <p>At least he and Phil Veli, the Phil of Larry &amp; Phil's, are relieved that the days have pretty much passed when youths wished small ponytails in the back or initials, football numbers and lightning bolts sculptured into their heads. For the lettering work, the barbers kept a supply of cardboard stencils that they held against the head. They threw away the last of the stencils more than a year ago.</p>
        <p>The barber shop is decorated in beiges and browns. It is well kept. There are three barber chairs. Besides Mr. Giglio and Mr. Veli, who is 50, a third barber, Sal Cammalleri, 71, also cuts hair. A row of seats is available for waiting, and a small rack is heaped with the customary wad of out-of-date magazines.</p>
        <p>A haircut is $11, which sometimes rises a few dollars for anything really taxing. Children get two lollipops apiece once their head is finished. Any toddler receiving his first haircut earns a First Haircut Award, a certificate and a lock of hair encased in plastic.</p>
        <p>Bobby Bulmer, 12, took a seat and requested a wedge.</p>
        <p>"I like the look of it," he said. "It's a good look. That's what most of the kids get. Some kids get crew cuts, usually the snobby kind of kids who think they're the greatest. The rest of us get the wedge." 'All My Friends Went Bowl'</p>
        <p>Jeff Van Dyke, 15 and heading into 10th grade, scuffed into Mr. Velio's chair.</p>
        <p>"Shave it all around the sides," he declared.</p>
        <p>"A wedge?" Mr. Velio asked.</p>
        <p>"No, a bowl."</p>
        <p>As Mr. Veli went to work, Jeff reflected on his hair. "I've had my bowl about a year," he said. "Before that, I had it long. Then all my friends went bowl, so I went bowl."</p>
        <p>How important is hair, he was asked.</p>
        <p>He stroked his chin and reflected for a moment. "I don't think it's so important, because I wear a hat all the time," he said. "But a lot of kids think it is. If you wear your hair wrong, they'll get after you.</p>
        <p>"The way it works, you get one warning. If your hair is wrong, they'll ask you why you're wearing it that way. Then if you don't fix it, they'll tease you. And I mean a lot."</p>
        <p>Matthew Cohen, 8, opted for a "spike," apparently short everywhere but in the front, which gets pushed up.</p>
        <p>"It's cool," he said. "That's what my friends want." A Cut of His Own</p>
        <p>Keith Valley, 17, got comfortable in Mr. Giglio's chair. He was a challenge. "I want it as short as you can get it on the sides and the back and don't touch the top," he said. "I want it long so I can jell it and style it." The hair on the top dangled over his left eye, making it invisible.</p>
        <p>"This is my own style," he said. "I just thought it up one day."</p>
        <p>Mr. Giglio said, "Call it the long-short style."</p>
        <p>The barber had the electric clippers going furiously.</p>
        <p>Keith examined his hair in the mirror. His conclusions were soft and brief. "A little shorter," he declared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giglio went back at it. "More?" he asked.</p>
        <p>"Yeah, smoother."</p>
        <p>"Now?"</p>
        <p>"A little more."</p>
        <p>Mr. Giglio looked like something he had eaten had begun to disagree with him. "This is like six haircuts in one."</p>
        <p>In the next chair, Andrew Patrizio, 11, was getting, of all things, a conventional haircut.</p>
        <p>"A lot of my friends get a buzz," Andrew explained. "But my hair is thin and you can see the skull. My dad gave me a buzz once and I didn't like it at all. That was my first and last buzz."  The Fickleness of Style</p>
        <p>Teachers needed haircuts, too. In came Dick Bennett, a physical education teacher at nearby Ridgewood High School.</p>
        <p>Asked if Ridgewood students were wearing wedges and mushrooms, he said right back: "What? Is that what they call them? Did you say a turnip?"</p>
        <p>The barbers' eyes were glazing.</p>
        <p>Peter Rogers, 8, took a chair. His sister, Emma, 6, hopped into the adjacent one, and they plunged into their instructions. Emma, with long, straight blond hair, wanted a very mild trim that she hoped nobody would notice she had gotten. Her mother referred to it as a pretend haircut.</p>
        <p>Peter was going pretty traditional. "I used to like it to cover half my ears," he said. "But I wanted to change it because I got sick of it. All my friends are different. They don't like each others' haircuts, and so everyone wears it different. Then you look like yourself."</p>
        <p>The buzzing of the clippers had a lulling effect. Mr. Giglio stared at the jostling sea of waiting heads and sighed. He believed the mushrooms and wedges won't persist much longer. Hairstyles are fickle, subject to unmappable whims.</p>
        <p>What will succeed the wedge? The buzz? The bowl?</p>
        <p>"It could be anything," Mr. Giglio said. "It could be crazy. But what can you do? We'll cut it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
