<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Army Liaison Who Lobbied Congress for Weapon Resigns</title>
    <meta content="Y11PENT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/05/11/politics/11PENT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1391287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dao, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steadman, Kenneth A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rumsfeld, Donald H (Sec)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ackerman, Michael W (Lt Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Taylor, Joe G (Maj Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Thomas E (Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E4DB1F30F932A25756C0A9649C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Army Liaison Who Lobbied Congress for Weapon Resigns</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Army Liaison Who Lobbied Congress for Weapon Resigns</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES DAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dao, James</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Army accepts resignation of Kenneth A Steadman, midlevel official who aggressively lobbied Congress to back $11 billion artillery system Sec Donald H Rumsfeld had vowed to cancel; Army inspector general Lt Gen Michael Ackerman says Steadman used inappropriate, inaccurate and offensive language in 'talking points' distributed to Congress to defend Crusader system; his report exonerates Steadman's boss, Maj Gen Joe G Taylor, and Army Sec Thomas E White; Rumsfeld leaves door open to shakeup in Army's legislative liaison office; Congressional aides from both parties call Steadman scapegoat; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Army said today that it had accepted the resignation of a midlevel official who aggressively lobbied Congress to support an $11 billion artillery system that Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld had vowed to cancel.</p>
        <p>The official, Kenneth A. Steadman, distributed a two-page set of ''talking points'' on Capitol Hill last week that used ''inappropriate, inaccurate and offensive language'' to defend the artillery system, known as the Crusader, the Army's inspector general said in a report released today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Army accepted the resignation of a midlevel official who aggressively lobbied Congress to support an $11 billion artillery system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Army said today that it had accepted the resignation of a midlevel official who aggressively lobbied Congress to support an $11 billion artillery system that Secretary of Defense Donald H. Rumsfeld had vowed to cancel.</p>
        <p>The official, Kenneth A. Steadman, distributed a two-page set of ''talking points'' on Capitol Hill last week that used ''inappropriate, inaccurate and offensive language'' to defend the artillery system, known as the Crusader, the Army's inspector general said in a report released today.</p>
        <p>A weeklong inquiry by the inspector general, Lt. Gen. Michael Ackerman, found that Mr. Steadman, the principal deputy in the Army's office of legislative liaison, was the highest-ranking Army official to see the talking points.</p>
        <p>As a result, the report exonerated Mr. Steadman's boss, Maj. Gen. Joe G. Taylor, the chief of the legislative liaison office, and the Army secretary, Thomas E. White, whose job had briefly seemed in jeopardy because of the imbroglio.</p>
        <p>''He was without knowledge of what took place, and in my view, he has addressed the subject,'' Mr. Rumsfeld said today of Mr. White. Earlier this week, Mr. Rumsfeld said he did not intend to ask for Mr. White's resignation.</p>
        <p>Though Mr. Rumsfeld said the resignation of Mr. Steadman -- which he said was voluntary -- would be the final disciplinary action relating to the case, he left the door open to a shakeup in the Army's legislative liaison office.</p>
        <p>''This would complete whatever might be done from a disciplinary standpoint, although I would not say it's necessarily all that will be done,'' Mr. Rumsfeld said.</p>
        <p>Senior Pentagon officials said Mr. Rumsfeld was contemplating cutting the size of the liaison office, which has about 90 employees. They also said General Taylor was likely to be transferred within the year. He will probably be replaced by a one-star general to reduce the office's influence, the officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rumsfeld has raised questions about why each of the four armed services needs its own legislative lobbyists, and has suggested he might try to shrink the offices or even combine them, Pentagon officials said.</p>
        <p>The talking points infuriated Mr. Rumsfeld by asserting that the Pentagon would endanger soldiers on the battlefield by canceling the mobile, rapid-firing Crusader system, all for the sake of saving money.</p>
        <p>''A decision to kill Crusader puts soldiers at risk,'' the document said. ''Degrading land power capabilities and putting ground formations at risk for the sake of cost cutting is to call into question the relevance of land power.''</p>
        <p>Mr. White today called the talking points ''offensive and insulting,'' adding, ''I have made clear within the Army that this action was repugnant and contrary to the interests of our troops and country.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Steadman did not return calls for comment today.</p>
        <p>Military and Congressional officials said Mr. Steadman was a political appointee who had served on George W. Bush's transition team after the 2000 election. He is a former Army colonel and a Vietnam veteran who worked as executive director of the Veterans of Foreign Wars before taking the $118,300-per-year job in the legislative liaison office last August.</p>
        <p>On Capitol Hill, Congressional aides from both parties described Mr. Steadman as a scapegoat.</p>
        <p>The aides said Mr. Steadman was a victim of poor timing who had simply been doing his job -- advocating for the Crusader, the Army's top budget priority before Mr. Rumsfeld decided to cancel it. The talking points were internal Army documents that Mr. Steadman naïvely gave to a few lawmakers, not realizing they would be widely distributed, the aides said.</p>
        <p>Critics of the Crusader contend it is too heavy, even after being slimmed down to 40 tons, to be moved swiftly to distant battlefields, and that precision-guided bombs have reduced the need for conventional artillery. Mr. Rumsfeld has said he would prefer to spend money from the Crusader on new kinds of fire support systems that link manned and unmanned, airborne and ground-based weapons through high-tech communications.</p>
        <p>But the Crusader's supporters, including the Army until last week, argued that fighter jets were often not available to protect ground troops and that artillery could outperform laser-guided bombs in bad weather. ''We have been outgunned since WWII and still are by any credible adversary, esp. the 'axis of evil' nations,'' the Army's talking points said, referring to Iran, Iraq and North Korea.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Rumsfeld's vow to cancel the program, the House approved a $383 billion defense authorization bill for 2003 early this morning that included $475 million for the Crusader. The Senate Armed Services Committee also included $475 million for the program in its version of the authorizing legislation, which passed the committee on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The full Senate is expected to take up the legislation after the Armed Services Committee holds hearings next week in which Mr. Rumsfeld will be asked to explain his decision to cancel the program.</p>
        <p>In its version of the authorizing bill, the Senate Armed Services Committee also cut $812 million from missile defense programs, transferring much of the money to shipbuilding programs. The move places many Republicans in the difficult position of having to choose between missile defense, which is among President Bush's highest military priorities, and shipbuilding, which is a major industry in many states, including Mississippi, home to the Republican minority leader, Senator Trent Lott.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
