<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trans Fats to Safe Sex: How Health Advice Has Changed</title>
    <meta content="11BROD$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/11/science/11BROD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1534398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Personal Health (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/AIDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weight</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Viruses</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031111T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1D61139F932A25752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1328" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trans Fats to Safe Sex: How Health Advice Has Changed</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Trans Fats to Safe Sex: How Health Advice Has Changed</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANE E. BRODY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jane E Brody Personal Health column explores how health advice has changed in 25 years Science Times has been published; way in which health is discussed, content of health information and emergence of obesity as major health threat are some differences identified and discussed; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The times (and The Times) sure have changed. On April 18, 1966, Dr. William H. Masters and Virginia E. Johnson released the findings of an 11-year study of the physiology of sex in their groundbreaking book, ''Human Sexual Response.''</p>
        <p>I was in my first year at The Times and my beat included birth control, abortion and venereal disease, among other sex-related subjects. Even so, my editors were reluctant to have a young woman even read the book, let alone have her byline on the article. (It was written instead by a male reporter on cultural affairs.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>AIDS changed the way health was discussed. It was not possible to address prevention and disease transmission unless you could talk about sexual activities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The times (and The Times) sure have changed. On April 18, 1966, Dr. William H. Masters and Virginia E. Johnson released the findings of an 11-year study of the physiology of sex in their groundbreaking book, ''Human Sexual Response.''</p>
        <p>I was in my first year at The Times and my beat included birth control, abortion and venereal disease, among other sex-related subjects. Even so, my editors were reluctant to have a young woman even read the book, let alone have her byline on the article. (It was written instead by a male reporter on cultural affairs.)</p>
        <p>When the article ran, it unabashedly referred to a woman's genitalia as a ''vagina,'' but described the penis as a ''genital organ in a male.''</p>
        <p>The Times and other newspapers and magazines, as well as television and radio, have changed in the way health and sex are talked about and written about. And although the change may seem superficial, it is not. Without straight talk, you simply cannot deliver useful information about health and sexuality.</p>
        <p>I have no particular devotion to seeing previously forbidden words in print. But because I wrote about sexuality as part of health, and did not wish to mince words, I became the first Times reporter to use terms like ''penile thrusting'' in print, in this case in a 1976 article about the ''Hite Report'' and women and sex.</p>
        <p>When I inaugurated the Personal Health column that same year, I chose impotence as one of my first four topics. The column ran as written, as did others on sexual subjects, including one that told readers exactly how to put on a condom. There were, however, some lines drawn. A column on masturbation took four years and many rewrites to get into the paper.</p>
        <p>In the end, AIDS changed the way health was discussed. It was not possible to address prevention and disease transmission unless you could talk about sexual activities without prudishness or embarrassment. Nowadays, infertility, impotence and menopause are the subjects of many reports in print and on television. Today, a health writer can describe virtually any disease, no matter how it is transmitted or what part of the body it affects.</p>
        <p>Dissecting Major Killers</p>
        <p>It is not just the way health is discussed that has changed. The content of health advice has also changed drastically. Looking back, for example, on what were thought to be the most important predictors of coronary heart disease a quarter-century ago, our naïveté is all too apparent. A diet rich in saturated fat and cholesterol, high blood pressure and smoking once dominated public health concerns for American hearts.</p>
        <p>These remain important, but we now see other factors rising in relevance: levels of homocysteine and C-reactive protein (a marker of inflammation) in the blood, abdominal fat and obesity, and diabetes, as well as levels of blood pressure and cholesterol that were once considered ''normal.''</p>
        <p>We now know that total blood cholesterol levels tell only a fragmentary story. Blood cholesterol can be broken down into good (protective) and bad (damaging) kinds, depending upon the protein that carries it in the circulation. Even the size of the protein-cholesterol molecules may matter, a recent genetics study suggests. The bigger they are, the longer you are likely to live, and live free of heart disease.</p>
        <p>We have also learned more about how to keep this leading killer of the industrialized world at bay. Polyunsaturated fats are now overshadowed by monounsaturates like olive oil and canola oil, walnuts and fatty fish as protective against heart disease, along with moderate drinking (especially red wine) and antioxidant-rich fruits and vegetables.</p>
        <p>Trans fats, often formed when polyunsaturated vegetable oils are hardened to form margarine, cooking fats and partially hydrogenated vegetable oils, are now recognized as major contributors to clogged arteries, possibly more harmful than the saturated fats in red meat and butter.</p>
        <p>And the protection afforded by regular physical activity, which continues to be a hard sell for a majority of Americans, has been repeatedly and convincingly demonstrated, not just against heart disease but cancer, as well. Now a sedentary life is on a par with high cholesterol and blood pressure as a predictor of coronary risk.</p>
        <p>Cancer, too, has seen major advances in treatment, detection and prevention. Though the final words are far from in, you can expect many changes in advice as medical science reveals new protective and lifesaving measures.</p>
        <p>A quarter-century ago, with few exceptions, only those found at initial diagnosis to have cancer that spread beyond the site of origin were given further treatment with chemotherapy or radiation. Now such therapy is routine for most cancers.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, radical mastectomy reigned as the established treatment for all breast cancers. Through a combination of improved detection and studies demonstrating equal value for lesser surgery, most women now have breast-sparing lumpectomies or, at most, simple mastectomies. In addition to now-standard postoperative therapy, breast cancer survivors can be further protected against a recurrence or a new breast cancer by one or more estrogen-blocking drugs.</p>
        <p>Some previously incurable cancers are now being stopped cold by monoclonal antibodies designed to attack a particular cancer, and cures for some advanced cancers can sometimes be rendered with the aid of bone marrow transplants.</p>
        <p>There is also now a blood test to screen for prostate cancer, which is highly curable when detected early. But this advance has created a new quandary: how to decide which men are likely to die of their cancer and thus warrant immediate treatment and which may die of another cause with a slow-growing cancer that never became a threat.</p>
        <p>Still, with cancer as with most other diseases, prevention holds the greatest promise. Stop-smoking efforts have finally halted what for decades was an unstoppable rise in lung cancer deaths. Now many preventive discoveries are focused on nutrition, specifically the protective role of antioxidant-rich fruits and vegetables -- and not just against cancer, also to delay damage to the eyes, brain and other organs.</p>
        <p>Toward a Healthier Old Age</p>
        <p>Which brings me to what has been the most striking shift in emphasis in medical science in the last quarter-century: the current concern with age-related ailments like Alzheimer's disease, osteoporosis, macular degeneration and congestive heart failure. With more and more people living into their 90's and beyond, disorders associated with advanced age threaten to bankrupt the health care system as well as the families of affected individuals unless better ways are found to prevent or treat them.</p>
        <p>Americans of all ages have also backtracked in one important area that increases their risk of developing many serious diseases, including heart disease and cancer. That area, as you may have guessed, is body weight. The seemingly unrelenting rise in the number of overweight and obese people, and the resulting rise in Type 2 diabetes, now threatens to undermine much of the progress that has been made in preventing heart disease and certain cancers, including breast cancer.</p>
        <p>We seem incapable of learning the secret of lasting weight control. It is not a diet that one goes on to go off. It is an eating and exercise management plan that you stay on for life -- no gimmicks, drugs or deprivation that sooner or later result in backsliding.</p>
        <p>Many more of us could enjoy a healthier old age if we all took an old joke more seriously: ''If I had known I'd live so long, I would have taken better care of myself!'' There's no better time to start than now.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
