<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite the Despair of Depression, Few Men Seek Treatment</title>
    <meta content="30DEPR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <meta content="First of two columns on depression in men." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="984007"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL HEALTH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Manic-Depressive Illness</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brody, Jane E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Styron, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wallace, Mike</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Personal Health (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Bipolar Disorder</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E5DE1531F933A05751C1A961958260" item-length="1174" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite the Despair of Depression, Few Men Seek Treatment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brody, Jane E</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>First of two Jane E Brody columns on depression in men; cites cases of Mike Wallace, news correspondent and co-editor of television program 60 Minutes, and author William Styron, both of whom suffered bouts of severe depression and who discuss their experiences for documentary that will be shown on HBO; says frank confessions of these two famous men on national television may help to break 'conspiracy of silence' that has long surrounded depression in men; although recent surveys indicate that there are at least half as many depressed men as depressed women, a far smaller proportion of men seek treatment for their condition; photos; charts show differences between men and women in incidences of depression and bipolar disorder (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOW can a man who has ''got it all'' -- a top job, financial security, a loving wife and children -- become depressed? Mike Wallace, the news correspondent who is co-editor of ''60 Minutes,'' addresses that question as he discusses his own depression in a documentary, vividly describing the ''endless darkness,'' the paralyzing, crushing weight of the three episodes of depression he experienced before he sought professional help.</p>
        <p>''The sunshine means nothing to you at all,'' Mr. Wallace says. ''The seasons, friends, good food mean nothing. All you focus on is yourself and how bad you feel.'' The candid documentary will be broadcast next week on HBO.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOW can a man who has ''got it all'' -- a top job, financial security, a loving wife and children -- become depressed? Mike Wallace, the news correspondent who is co-editor of ''60 Minutes,'' addresses that question as he discusses his own depression in a documentary, vividly describing the ''endless darkness,'' the paralyzing, crushing weight of the three episodes of depression he experienced before he sought professional help.</p>
        <p>''The sunshine means nothing to you at all,'' Mr. Wallace says. ''The seasons, friends, good food mean nothing. All you focus on is yourself and how bad you feel.'' The candid documentary will be broadcast next week on HBO.</p>
        <p>William Styron, the Pulitzer Prize-winning author, joins Mr. Wallace on camera in recounting the oppressiveness of depression. He says he thought of himself as being ''condemned'' to life. ''In severe depression, the entire body and spirit of a person is in a state of shipwreck, of desolate lostness,'' Mr. Styron says. ''Nothing animates the body or spirit. It's a total wipeout.''</p>
        <p>The frank confessions of these two famous men on national television may help to break the conspiracy of silence that has long surrounded depression in men. Although recent surveys indicate that there are at least half as many depressed men as depressed women, a far smaller proportion of men seek treatment for their condition.</p>
        <p>Even health professionals are loathe to diagnose depression in men. At the very nadir of Mr. Wallace's depression, his doctor told him there was nothing wrong with him. Complicating the matter is the widespread but mistaken impression that depression is a woman's disease that only rarely afflicts men. In a widely distributed 32-page booklet on men's health published this year in cooperation with the American Academy of Family Physicians, there is a discussion of stress but nothing about depression, which afflicts one of every eight men at some time in their lives.</p>
        <p>As Terrence Real, a psychotherapist in Cambridge, Mass., put it:  ''There's been a cultural collusion about hiding men's depression. Men are reluctant to acknowledge it, those around men are reluctant to acknowledge it -- like Mike Wallace's doctor, boss and co-workers -- because there's a stricture that says depression is unmanly.''</p>
        <p>Recognizing the Problem</p>
        <p>Mr. Real, author of a groundbreaking book about depression in men, ''I Don't Want to Talk About It: Overcoming the Secret Legacy of Male Depression'' (1997, Scribner, $24), said the participation of two prominent men in the HBO film indicated that ''it is now less unmanly to admit to depression when it is severe and biological, an acute disease-like condition.'' However, he emphasized that speaking about other less severe but more prevalent forms of depression was still considered ''wimpy.''</p>
        <p>''Yet,'' he added, ''for every one man like Mike Wallace and William Styron with a severe clinical depression, there are four others with milder forms that are poisoning their marriages, harming their kids and destroying their lives.''</p>
        <p>Rather than showing classic signs of acute depression, like severe lethargy, loss of appetite and inability to concentrate, the great majority of depressed men express their distress in covert ways, for example, by being angry or irritable, self-medicating, withdrawing from loved ones or acting irresponsibly. Mr. Real said: ''Depressed women have pain; depressed men have troubles. They're not in pain but the people around them are in pain.''</p>
        <p>The psychotherapist, who is now co-director of the Harvard University Gender Research Project and a senior faculty member of the Family Institute of Cambridge, described what he calls the ''unholy triad of covert depression'' in men. It consists, he said, of ''1) self-medication to enliven dead feelings by drinking, drugging, womanizing, burying themselves in work, overeating or overspending; 2) radical isolation, a pulling away from relationships, intimacy, from life itself, and 3) lashing out, which runs the gamut from increased irritability to domestic abuse and violence.''</p>
        <p>Lifting the Cloud</p>
        <p>More than 80 percent of people who are treated for depression -- men as well as women -- get substantial relief. The two primary treatments, which often work best when used together, are psychotherapy and antidepressant medication. A number of different psychotherapeutic approaches and a host of drugs have proved effective.</p>
        <p>In fact, the enormous publicity given to the newer antidepressants -- the selective serotonin re-uptake inhibitors, like Prozac, Paxil and Zoloft -- has helped to make a diagnosis of depression less stigmatizing. Unlike most older antidepressants, the newer drugs are highly effective, not only for acute episodes of major depression but also for so-called minor depression, or dysthymia, which tends to be chronic.</p>
        <p>It is true that antidepressants have side effects that may include gastrointestinal disturbances and, for most, a diminished sex drive. But Mr. Wallace says: ''You are willing to do it, nay, happy to do it because it begins to lift that cloud. You begin to eat, smile, appreciate your family.''</p>
        <p>In psychotherapy, Mr. Real stated, the first step is to stop masking the depression with addictive or aggressive behaviors and ''allow the pain that is driving the behavior to surface.'' Only then can a more constructive approach to life and loved ones be formulated.</p>
        <p>Psychotherapy may involve a series (usually weekly) of one-on-one conversations with a therapist -- psychiatrist, psychologist, social worker or pastoral counselor -- or marital or family counseling. The style of psychotherapy can range from highly passive, in which the patient gradually recalls old psychic traumas and arrives at a healthier understanding of their meaning and impact, to highly directive, in which the therapist challenges the patient to confront old hurts and current behaviors and prescribes new interpretations and alternative actions for the patient to practice.</p>
        <p>''Often the best approach to treating depression in men is to do the behavior first and let the feelings follow -- fake it until you make it,'' Mr. Real said. He added that chronic depression in men was often alleviated if they ''force themselves to be as relational as they can be rather than isolating themselves. Do the dishes, help the kids with their homework.''</p>
        <p>The HBO documentary, ''Dead Blue: Surviving Depression,'' will be broadcast next Tuesday at 10 P.M. and on Jan. 10 at 1:30 P.M., Jan. 14 at 10 P.M., Jan. 19 at 11:35 P.M. and Jan. 25 at 3:15 P.M.</p>
        <p>Next: Impact on the family.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL HEALTH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
