<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Official Under Fire: Graft or 'a Dry Hole'?</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="441868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIBERY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">QUEENS (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOARD OF ELECTIONS (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEWSDAY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SADOWSKI, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">REALE, SALVATORE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOYLE, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARBER, M A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910429T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DD123AF93AA15757C0A967958260" item-length="1629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Official Under Fire: Graft or 'a Dry Hole'?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By M. A. FARBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARBER, M A</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This, a story about three friends from Queens, has its beginning in the dusty southwestern Texas town of Sierra Blanca, near the Mexican border.</p>
        <p>The first of the three is Salvatore Reale. On Feb. 6, 1990, Mr. Reale was pulled off the road in Sierra Blanca (pop. 800) by Federal agents. In the trunk of the Lincoln Continental Mr. Reale drove was $3.8 million in United States currency and about $96,000 in Swiss francs. The car itself had been rented in New York by the second of the Queens men, Michael Doyle. Mr. Reale told the agents he was "relocating" to Florida and the money was his "nest egg."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This, a story about three friends from Queens, has its beginning in the dusty southwestern Texas town of Sierra Blanca, near the Mexican border.</p>
        <p>The first of the three is Salvatore Reale. On Feb. 6, 1990, Mr. Reale was pulled off the road in Sierra Blanca (pop. 800) by Federal agents. In the trunk of the Lincoln Continental Mr. Reale drove was $3.8 million in United States currency and about $96,000 in Swiss francs. The car itself had been rented in New York by the second of the Queens men, Michael Doyle. Mr. Reale told the agents he was "relocating" to Florida and the money was his "nest egg."</p>
        <p>Mr. Reale wasn't convincing. And his arrest set in motion events that led to big headlines in New York Newsday last week about the third of the Queens men, Anthony Sadowski.</p>
        <p>The headlines seemed to portend a corruption scandal that, as in 1986, would rock the Queens Democratic Party and the city. Newsday reported that Federal agents had gathered many hours of tape recordings in which Mr. Sadowski, a 78-year-old Democratic district leader in Queens and a member of the New York City Board of Elections, tried to bribe a city detective and boasted that he could corrupt prosecutors and judges.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadowski had never been near Sierra Blanca. But, owing in part to his two friends, he was under fire. That is because the taping of his conversations was made possible by Mr. Doyle, who may have been trying to help his friend Mr. Reale out of the trouble he had encountered in Texas.  Demand for Resignation</p>
        <p>The Queens Democratic organization -- in a "wish you and Catherine the best" letter to him and his wife -- demanded Mr. Sadowski's resignation from party and public posts. District Attorney John J. Santucci of Queens, whose office was said to be a subject of the Federal investigation, railed against what he called press attacks on Italians and defended himself once again about an hours-long lunch he had attended with Mr. Sadowski and his two friends eight years ago.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadowski -- who has been under a separate investigation for more than a year over his role on the elections board -- deflected telephone callers from his home in Boca Raton, Fla.</p>
        <p>At one of the meetings the F.B.I. listened in on, Mr. Sadowski supposedly offered $5,000 to have Detective Louis Hammer drop charges against a gangster accused of assaulting the detective after a traffic incident in 1989.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadowski's lawyer, Marvyn Kornberg, denied the charge, while describing his client as "not the smartest guy in the world." Although the "bribe" was never tendered to Detective Hammer, Federal authorities said it had been planned.  Declined to Cooperate</p>
        <p>When F.B.I. agents confronted Mr. Sadowski with the bribery allegation last month -- hoping to use him to build a major corruption case tying the Mafia to the Queens criminal-justice system -- they were disappointed. Mr. Sadowski declined to cooperate, and Federal prosecutors concluded that, while there might be a state charge of attempted bribery or obstruction of justice against Mr. Sadowski with regard to the detective, nothing on the tapes constituted a Federal crime or pointed to corrupted cases.</p>
        <p>"It was a dry hole," said a prosecutor familiar with the matter.</p>
        <p>And it was the long and lately severed friendship among the three men from Queens that led prosecutors to that hole in the first place.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadowski was convicted of bookmaking "about 30 or 40 years ago," Mr. Kornberg said, but has no criminal record today. He was in the real-estate business in Queens for years and apparently owned a few bars.</p>
        <p>Becoming active in Queens politics in the 1960's, he briefly challenged Matthew Troy for the post of county Democratic leader in 1971. In 1973, Mr. Troy proposed him as the party's representative on the patronage-filled Board of Elections, a post he has since held in addition to being the party's district leader for Ozone Park-Woodhaven.</p>
        <p>Perpetually tanned, Mr. Sadowski became best known among Queens politicians for his avid interest in golf and gossiping. Far from being the political "powerhouse" with "golden connections" portrayed by Newsday, he seems never to have enjoyed much influence in party circles.</p>
        <p>"Listen to him and you would think he was the county leader," said a senior Queens Democratic official who asked not to be identified. "But he had no influence on the party leadership. No one ever knew what he did. I don't think he delivered 4 votes for a Democratic candidate in the last 20 years. Most of the time he lives in Florida." A Celebrated Luncheon</p>
        <p>The official, like several other Queens politicians, could not recall any major issues on which Mr. Sadowski was consulted. He said Mr. Sadowski kept his posts in his heavily Republican district and on the elections board largely through Democratic Party inertia. "He wasn't bothering anybody, so why remove him?" the official said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sadowski was in the news in late 1986, when reports surfaced of a now-celebrated luncheon that went through dinner in March 1983 at the Altadonna Restaurant in Queens.</p>
        <p>Those attending, besides Mr. Sadowski, included Mr. Santucci; Peter J. Prezioso, a deputy chief who was being promoted to head the Police Department's intelligence division; Mr. Doyle, a police lieutenant in Ozone Park, Queens, where Chief Prezioso had once worked with him, and Mr. Reale, a businessman and private detective who was arrested on loan-sharking charges in Florida five months after the luncheon and was identified by the F.B.I. as a Gambino crime family associate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Doyle retired from the police force in October 1983 after a departmental investigation into his possible ties with underworld figures. Chief Prezioso was cleared in 1986 after a departmental inquiry into the luncheon and he retired in January 1987. In 1988, Mr. Santucci was cleared by the state's anti-corruption prosecutor of knowing that Mr. Reale had connections with organized crime, but he has never fully shaken the perception that he should not have been at the luncheon.</p>
        <p>In 1987, Mr. Sadowski was the host for a dinner dance in honor of James Golia, the Queens borough engineer. An advertisement in the souvenir program for the event was placed by the Bergin Hunt and Fish Club in Ozone Park, the social club used by John Gotti, reputed head of the Gambino crime family. Rumors have long circulated in Queens that Mr. Sadowski had a business relationship with Mr. Gotti at a Long Island gambling parlor. The rumors have never been substantiated.</p>
        <p>Court-approved wiretaps on Mr. Gotti over the years have not picked up a reference to Mr. Sadowski, law-enforcement officials say.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kornberg, the lawyer, said last week that he did not "have the faintest idea" whether Mr. Sadowski knew Mr. Gotti. "It's no crime to know John Gotti," Mr. Kornberg said. "If a man is living in your district, is it improper?"</p>
        <p>In January 1990, Mr. Golia, who is also a lawyer, was hired by Mr. Santucci as an administrative and budget assistant, not handling cases. Without further detail, Newsday reported last week that Mr. Golia was "one of the featured players" on the Sadowski tapes. Mr. Golia, who declined to comment during the week, was traveling yesterday and could not be reached.</p>
        <p>Mr. Santucci said Federal authorities had told him that neither his nor Mr. Golia's name was on the tapes and "there are no aspersions on my office." And, he said, people honored at political dinners normally do not know in advance who is taking program ads.</p>
        <p>In 1988, Judge Jack B. Weinstein of Federal District Court in Brooklyn gave Mr. Reale a 15-year suspended sentence for labor racketeering. The judge said Mr. Reale, with a history of psychiatric problems, would almost certainly kill himself or be killed if imprisoned. "He just knows too much," the judge said, ordering him to stay out of the New York area for five years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reale moved to Scottsdale, Ariz., where the Internal Revenue Service closely watched his financial dealings. But he was not arrested until February 1990 in Sierra Blanca. With him was a convicted felon who was not publicly identified but who Federal authorities say was not Mr. Doyle.</p>
        <p>In May 1990, Judge Weinstein resentenced Mr. Reale to 10 years in prison for violating his parole conditions.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Reale's friend, Mr. Doyle, reappeared, agreeing as early as March 1990 to tape conversations with Mr. Sadowski for the F.B.I.</p>
        <p>A representative of Mr. Reale, who asked to remain anonymous, said last week that he thought that a "confluence of factors" led to Mr. Doyle's decision, including possibly a long-buried grudge against Mr. Sadowski.</p>
        <p>But two prosecutors and Mr. Kornberg, Mr. Sadowski's lawyer, said Mr. Doyle undertook the taping only to help out Mr. Reale by gathering information that might result in major corruption cases. The only problem was that Federal prosecutors concluded that the Sadowski tapes produced little more than vague "name dropping." And when Mr. Sadowski declined to cooperate with the F.B.I., the prosecutors told Mr. Reale that Mr. Doyle's efforts would not translate into a break for him. A hearing on Mr. Reale's request for a reduced sentence is scheduled for tomorrow.</p>
        <p>It is not clear whether Mr. Sadowski will be further investigated with regard to the supposed bribe of the detective. The Manhattan District Attorney's office is still investigating an allegation by a lawyer for a voting machine company that Mr. Sadowski solicited a bribe from him. Mr. Sadowski was also taped clandestinely in that case, then confronted by the authorities. He declined to cooperate.</p>
        <p>"Ninety percent of what they say about me is untrue," Mr. Sadowski said in a brief telephone interview last week. "I know that."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
