<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whitewater Prosecutor Drops Files Issue</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="858810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS ANDEXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION (FBI) FEDERAL BUREAU OFINVESTIGATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSTON, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STARR, KENNETH W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RENO, JANET(ATTY GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LIVINGSTONE, CRAIG</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARCECA, ANTHONY JANET RENO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506EFD81439F93AA25755C0A960958260" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whitewater Prosecutor Drops Files Issue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSTON, DAVID;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kenneth W. Starr, the Whitewater prosecutor, withdrew today from the investigation into how the White House improperly obtained hundreds of confidential background files on Republicans, and Attorney General Janet Reno then ordered the Federal Bureau of Investigation to complete the inquiry.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department said that after Mr. Starr's weeklong preliminary inquiry, officials in his office had advised Ms. Reno's aides that they did not  have adequate authority to continue the investigation into the files search, which was conducted by Clinton aides in 1993 and early 1994.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kenneth W. Starr, the Whitewater prosecutor, withdrew today from the investigation into how the White House improperly obtained hundreds of confidential background files on Republicans, and Attorney General Janet Reno then ordered the Federal Bureau of Investigation to complete the inquiry.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department said that after Mr. Starr's weeklong preliminary inquiry, officials in his office had advised Ms. Reno's aides that they did not  have adequate authority to continue the investigation into the files search, which was conducted by Clinton aides in 1993 and early 1994.</p>
        <p>The Justice Department said officials in Mr. Starr's office had said that they would not object if another "appropriate investigative or prosecutorial office were now to investigate." Ms. Reno referred the matter to the F.B.I., which will expand its initial inquiry to include the questioning of employees who took part in the files search at the White House.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reno said she had asked the F.B.I. to conduct a "complete and thorough investigation." Law-enforcement officials said tonight that the investigation would be considered a preliminary criminal investigation and that it would be supervised by the F.B.I. general counsel, Howard M. Shapiro.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr's abrupt withdrawal seemed unlikely to dampen the issue, which flared up a week ago when Congressional investigators examining the dismissals of White House travel office employees discovered that White House aides had obtained in late 1993 the file of the director of the travel office, who had been dismissed seven months earlier. That led to subsequent disclosures that the White House had improperly obtained more than 400 files of former White House employees, many of them prominent Republicans.</p>
        <p>White House officials said they would cooperate with the inquiry. "We look forward to providing the Department of Justice and the Federal Bureau of Investigation with whatever information is necessary to answer conclusively all  outstanding questions," said Mark D. Fabiani, a White House spokesman.</p>
        <p>But Republicans expressed misgivings about the new approach. Representative William F. Clinger, the Pennsylvania Republican who heads the committee that has investigated the White House travel office dismissals, said he had doubts, "given the Clinton Administration's proven inability to investigate itself in previous instances, including the travel office." He said, "The onus is on the F.B.I. to prove they can resist political pressure from the White House and the  Justice Department and conduct a thorough and comprehensive investigation of this matter."</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr's legal authority to investigate the use of the files appeared to stem from his jurisdiction over the dismissals at the White House travel office, including the question of whether a Clinton official had been truthful about the travel-office issue in his comments to Congressional investigators.</p>
        <p>One person involved in the investigation that Mr. Starr's office had informed the Justice Department that after its preliminary examination of the matter, the independent counsel's office did not have the jurisdiction to go further because the inquiry was much broader than the simple mandate of examining the White House travel office issue.</p>
        <p>Today, President Clinton's aides sought to calm the political furor by preparing to name a successor to Craig Livingstone, the head of the personnel security office, which directed the file search. Mr. Livingstone was placed on administrative leave on Monday. Officials said that, subject to final review, they had settled on Charles C. Easley, a White House security officer in the executive office of the President who has worked at the White House since the Reagan Administration.</p>
        <p>Ms. Reno's decision raised potentially thorny questions about the impartiality of the F.B.I. and its ability to investigate an incident in which it was directly involved, particularly since the agency's Director, Louis J. Freeh, in announcing the results of the F.B.I.'s initial review last Friday, seemed to have concluded that the White House was responsible for what he called an egregious violation of privacy.</p>
        <p>At the time, Mr. Freeh said he felt "victimized" by the requests for the files, an unusual expression that seemed to indicate that he felt the White House was responsible. Mr. Freeh sought to clarify his remarks later, saying he  had in effect victimized himself because he had failed to supervise the process  diligently.</p>
        <p>In other developments today, Congressional inquiries into the files issue moved ahead, in preparation for hearings in both houses. Mr. Clinger's staff questioned Anthony Marceca, the investigator at the White House who actually asked for the files, and William Kennedy 3d, the former deputy White House counsel who supervised the personnel security officer, in preparation for the hearings, which begin on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>In another private session, Secret Service officials told several Republican  lawmakers and aides that their computer system could not generate the kind of information that the White House used to obtain the files. That suggested, people who attended the meeting said, that White House aides might have created  a list that showed some Republican officials were cleared for access to the White House long after their passes had been revoked.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
