<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Astros Pack Balls, Bats . . . Baedekers</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="545761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="AROUND THE MAJORS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Houston Astros</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920727T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D9153EF934A15754C0A964958260" item-length="556" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Astros Pack Balls, Bats . . . Baedekers</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Their bags are packed, and unpacked, and packed, and unpacked.</p>
        <p>John McMullen is gone as the owner of the Houston Astros. His legacy remains: the 26-game, 28-day road trip he agreed to, which begins today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Their bags are packed, and unpacked, and packed, and unpacked.</p>
        <p>John McMullen is gone as the owner of the Houston Astros. His legacy remains: the 26-game, 28-day road trip he agreed to, which begins today.</p>
        <p>The Astros flew to Atlanta last night after losing to the Cubs, beginning a 9,186-mile odyssey that will take them to eight National League cities, a trip that was forced on them because McMullen, who announced the sale of the team on Friday, allowed the Republican Party to hold its convention in the Astrodome on Aug. 17-20.</p>
        <p>The traveling secretary, Barry Waters, has worked out all the logistics of hotels, buses to and from the hotels, and prepared for extra laundry money. It's all explained to the players in a seven-page travel itinerary, five pages longer than normal.</p>
        <p>"We've restricted the players to two bags and relaxed the dress code," Waters said. "We're encouraging them to pack light and we've given them a one-time laundry allowance." Detroit's Pizza Connection</p>
        <p>The Detroit Tigers' owner, Tom Monaghan, has moved $23 million of the team's profits during the last four years into his other businesses, including Domino's Pizza, The Oakland (Miss.) Press reported yesterday.</p>
        <p>Monaghan is attempting to sell the Tigers and other assets not directly related to Domino's. Mike Ilitch, who owns the Detroit Red Wings of the National Hockey League and Little Caesar's pizza, is believed to be the leading candidate to buy the Tigers. The newspaper said two ranking Tigers officials confirmed the figure on the condition of anonymity. Quick Pitches . . . and Hits</p>
        <p>Giants reliever Bryan Hickerson has been perfect against Philadelphia this season. He has faced 11 batters and recorded 12 outs (one double play), including six strikeouts. . . . Chicago's Lance Johnson extended his hitting streak to 11 games with a hit against the Brewers yesterday. . . . The Brewers improved to 53-44, the first time the club has been nine games over .500 since the end of the 1988 season. . . . Cleveland has won 41 games so far this season. It took them exactly one month longer to win that many games last year. . . . Saturday's game was the 2,500th of George Brett's career. Yesterday Brett had two hits, increasing his total to 2,931 and tying him with Jake Beckley for 22d on the career list. . . . With two more hits, California's Luis Polonia extended his streak as the Angels designated hitter to 16 for 32. . . . Oakland's Carney Lansford is 12 for 31 (.387) since the All-Star break. . . . Tom Brunansky extended his hitting streak to 12 games with a seventh-inning single. . . . Minnesota's Rick Aguilera, who has 29 saves in 33 opportunities, is 4 for 4 in save opportunities against Boston this season. . . . Cincinnati's Barry Larkin is hitting .413 (33 for 80) in July. . . . Rob Dibble of the Reds has 63 strikeouts in his last 45 innings. . . . Felix Jose of the Cardinals was batting .390 (41 for 105) right-handed and .250 (46 for 184) left-handed before yesterday's game, in which he did not play. . . . After going 2 for 2 in steals Friday, Eric Davis of the Dodgers boasts the best stolen-base percentage of any player in the history of the game, based on at least 300 attempts. He has 263 steals in 301 attempts for an 87.5 percent success rate. He's 16 for 17 (94 percent) this season.</p>
        <p>AROUND THE MAJORS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
