<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wine and Women in Tuscany: Bertolucci Lightens Up</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="785152"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERTOLUCCI, BERNARDO</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYLER, LIV</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">IRONS, JEREMY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">STEALING BEAUTY (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DB123EF934A1575BC0A963958260" item-length="1165" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wine and Women in Tuscany: Bertolucci Lightens Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BOHLEN, CELESTINE</byline>
      <dateline>SIENA, Italy</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER A SUDDEN SUMMER rainstorm, the garden at the Villa di Geggiano takes on a soft, damp glow, just right for the outdoor party scene in Bernardo Bertolucci's new movie, "Stealing Beauty." Wasps buzz around soggy slices of watermelon, elegant extras drift about with wine glasses and Liv Tyler, the film's 18-year-old star, resumes her search for love and identity, against the bewitching backdrop of a Tuscan landscape.</p>
        <p>After an absence of more than a decade during which he traveled through China, North Africa and India to film "The Last Emperor," "Sheltering Sky" and "Little Buddha," which was a spectacular flop, Mr. Bertolucci, at 55, has come home to Italy to make what he himself calls a "light" movie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER A SUDDEN SUMMER rainstorm, the garden at the Villa di Geggiano takes on a soft, damp glow, just right for the outdoor party scene in Bernardo Bertolucci's new movie, "Stealing Beauty." Wasps buzz around soggy slices of watermelon, elegant extras drift about with wine glasses and Liv Tyler, the film's 18-year-old star, resumes her search for love and identity, against the bewitching backdrop of a Tuscan landscape.</p>
        <p>After an absence of more than a decade during which he traveled through China, North Africa and India to film "The Last Emperor," "Sheltering Sky" and "Little Buddha," which was a spectacular flop, Mr. Bertolucci, at 55, has come home to Italy to make what he himself calls a "light" movie.</p>
        <p>But this, too, turns out to be a voyage of discovery. "For me, coming to Tuscany is like going to Bhutan," he said, admitting to some discomfort at the thought of a movie that promises to be as serene as the surrounding countryside. "This is a search for lightness, whereas my last three films were heavy."</p>
        <p>"There are not many conflicts in this film," he went on as evening fell and another rainstorm drove the crew inside the 18th century villa, "and yet I like melodrama, I consider myself an Italian melodramatist. Here, there is no melodrama, and for me, this is a challenge. "</p>
        <p>For this movie, Mr. Bertolucci has replaced his long-time director of photography -- Vittorio Storaro -- with the Iranian-born Darius Khondji, whose credits include "Before the Rain," "The City of Lost Children" and "Delicatessen." But the vivid sense of color promises to remain. "Because I have some nervousness about the lightness of the story, I wanted strong colors," Mr. Bertolucci said. His artistic inspiration for the film came not from the late-medieval masterpieces of nearby Siena, he said, but from the bolder works of the Fauvists.</p>
        <p>For Jeremy Thomas, an independent producer who has worked with Mr. Bertolucci since 1986, the lightness of "Stealing Beauty" -- with its budget of $10 million, one quarter the cost of the last film -- is something of a relief. "The last three films were colossal undertakings," Mr. Thomas said. "All stories are difficult to translate into film, but this is a lighter burden."</p>
        <p>The idea for "Stealing Beauty" -- a Jamesian tale of a young American girl who comes to Europe seeking answers -- was Mr. Bertolucci's. But the script was written by Susan Minot, a 38-year-old American writer who has spent the last year and a half in close collaboration with him.  The two learned to mesh their contrasting styles -- his Mediterranean love of drama with her New England economy of manner and emotion.  "His inclination is to be more expansive, mine is to make the connections between the characters," said Ms. Minot, whose 1986 book, "Monkeys," was acclaimed for its finely tuned account of a large family growing up outside of Boston. "He makes cracks about there not being enough going on."</p>
        <p>Ms. Minot has been on the set throughout the three months of filming, remaining at Mr. Bertolucci's side as he guides the camera on the long, lingering shots that have been characteristic of all his movies.  When the script hits a snag, they fix it together. But for Ms. Minot, who has never worked on a movie before, the outcome is still uncertain. "The script is a skeleton, a blue print, a slight reference of what the movie will be," she said. "You want to make sure all the raw material is there so you can choose. In that sense, it is like writing: you flush out a lot of material and work with it."</p>
        <p>The story centers on 19-year-old Lucy (Ms. Tyler), who spends a week with a family of English expatriates, friends of her mother's who live in Tuscany (or Chiantishire as the British call this region in central Italy) surrounded by children of several generations and friends of several nationalities, all of whom contribute to Lucy's brief but intense sentimental education.</p>
        <p>There is also a dash of mystery, as Lucy explores the meaning of her mother's suicide four years before, after an earlier visit with the same family. But mostly there is romance -- a lot of it, judging from the complex relationships that link a long list of characters, who include a dying playwright (Jeremy Irons), a crusty art collector (Jean Marais), an Italian lonely-hearts columnist (Stefania Sandrelli who starred in Mr. Bertolucci's "The Conformist" and "1900") and a cynical Italian journalist (Carlo Cecchi, a prominent Italian actor), not to mention the inhabitants of the Villa di Geggiano across the valley, whose members include two sons who succeed each other in Lucy's affections.</p>
        <p>But for all its many threads, the story, its authors say, remains simple and familiar, a kind of 1990's film version of a Henry James novel. Like a Jamesian heroine, Lucy is semi-orphaned, and like James's novels, "Stealing Beauty" circles the question of which man Lucy will end up with. Mr. Bertolucci calls her an "Isabel Archer in Tuscany, a young American woman who is both very strong and very vulnerable."</p>
        <p>He chose Ms. Tyler to play Lucy when Ms. Tyler was only 17 years old and still in high school. Ms. Tyler, the daughter of Steve Tyler, the lead singer in the rock band Aerosmith, had already made a name for herself in three films, but she still remembers how her ears turned red during her interview with the director. "I was terrified," she said. "Being in a Bertolucci film just seemed like a huge big deal."</p>
        <p>Since then, Ms. Tyler -- like Lucy -- has grown up some. "At this age, you blossom into your own person," she said. "I have learned a lot, mainly about how to go about being with people."</p>
        <p>But her unaffected adolescent innocence remains. Mr. Bertolucci says that he is in awe of her natural sense of the camera, and that Ms. Tyler is like a filly. On the set, she walks in bare feet, her head slightly tilted to the side.</p>
        <p>Jeremy Irons concurred. "It is wonderful to see someone that age who still has a little awkwardness," he said, "and such a relief when you see all those 12-year-old Californians going on 32."</p>
        <p>Mr. Irons, who finished filming last month, was back in Tuscany recently to join his wife, Sinead Cusack, who plays Lucy's hostess. He accepted the role of the dying writer for several reasons. The script was "charming," he said, he found the opportunity of working with Mr. Bertolucci exciting, and "it gave me a chance to work with my wife in Tuscany, which is a very nice thing to do."</p>
        <p>If the film is light, then so is the atmosphere on the set. "It is very relaxed," Ms. Cusack said as she sat with her two sons watching the fifth take of a party scene. "Bertolucci is a very social animal, and it all comes from him." Relatives of actors wander by with their dogs, children dart in and out of the camera's way and, as mealtime approaches, the crew moves en masse toward the tent where Mr. Bertolucci's Italian chefs, who have followed him to the Himalayas and the Sahara, are home again at last, cooking pasta.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
