<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Half a Century, Still Writing, Still Questing</title>
    <meta content="07MAIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1015157"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Books and Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Norman Mailer</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mailer, Norman</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyman, Rick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Naked and the Dead, The (Book)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Time of Our Time, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0DA1431F934A35756C0A96E958260" item-length="1760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Half a Century, Still Writing, Still Questing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK LYMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyman, Rick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Norman Mailer, who is celebrating 50th anniversary of his novel The Naked and the Dead with publication of The Time of Our Time--compilation of lengthy excerpts from his works over the years; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>He is a courtly old gent, limping precariously on a bad knee across his top-floor apartment in Brooklyn Heights, a flat gray light sweeping in from the harbor. ''Oh, I have been using too many big words,'' he says, a little sheepishly, a shy smile breaking across his furrowed face.</p>
        <p>''I really don't rely on talismans as a writer,'' he says. ''But I do have this growing sense as the years go along that the one thing you should never do is take yourself too seriously. Because you are not in this alone.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>He is a courtly old gent, limping precariously on a bad knee across his top-floor apartment in Brooklyn Heights, a flat gray light sweeping in from the harbor. ''Oh, I have been using too many big words,'' he says, a little sheepishly, a shy smile breaking across his furrowed face.</p>
        <p>''I really don't rely on talismans as a writer,'' he says. ''But I do have this growing sense as the years go along that the one thing you should never do is take yourself too seriously. Because you are not in this alone.''</p>
        <p>Here is Norman Mailer at the age of 75, a half-century after the publication of ''The Naked and the Dead,'' his career-making debut about soldiers in the South Pacific during World War II. To mark the moment, he is publishing a compilation of lengthy excerpts from his work over the years, fiction and nonfiction, essays and journalism.</p>
        <p>It is called ''The Time of Our Time.'' Those tempted to think of it as the Portable Mailer might first try to pick it up. At 1,286 pages, it stands taller than the Manhattan white pages, which it outweighs.</p>
        <p>''What people don't understand is that religion has been a major theme of all of my work,'' Mr. Mailer says. ''For the last 50 years, my preoccupation has been religion. What might God be? I am searching for a notion of God that is alive for me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mailer rests on a wooden chair at the breakfast table near his tiny kitchen, a loft and skylight spilling light from above and the towers of lower Manhattan hanging over his shoulder in the distance. He wears an argyle sweater-vest over a blue-striped Oxford cloth shirt. The eyes are gentle beneath shaggy brows, the smiles unforced, a halo of wispy white hair framing everything.</p>
        <p>The boxer, the braggart, the king of all authors, the radical with a prankster's love of debate: where has he gone? He's still here, and the flashes of anger still erupt. He is still barrel-chested and looks as though he could still do some damage if he got hold of you. But the white heat has cooled.</p>
        <p>''As one gets older, the anger softens,'' Mr. Mailer says. ''To use Bob Dole's favorite word: Whatever.''</p>
        <p>He lives most of the year with his wife, Norris Church, in a house he loves in Provincetown, Mass.. They are both writing books now, in separate rooms (''Oh, I could never work in the same room with someone'') and once the publicity tour for this new book ends, he hopes to dive head first into the long-awaited second volume of ''Harlot's Ghost.'' They have been married for 18 years. She is his sixth wife, and he has nine children; sometimes they come to visit him in Cape Cod, but more often he sees them during his forays into New York.</p>
        <p>''The joke in our family is that New York is our Miami Beach,'' he said. ''I guess I spend about two months a year here, in bits and pieces. We have a good time, we see friends.''</p>
        <p>But he needs to go back to Provincetown to work. ''In winter, it's wonderful to wake up and you don't feel sorry for yourself that you're missing anything, because nothing is happening,'' he says.</p>
        <p>He spends much of his time reading (he has been on Jung lately, and is planning a summer of Don DeLillo and Cormac McCarthy) and watching movies. He recently watched a video of Warren Beatty's new political comedy, ''Bulworth,'' and is very high on it. ''I really think it's a great movie,'' he says. ''Warren Beatty is onto something.''</p>
        <p>His wife loved it, too, which convinces him that it is a great film, because they often disagree about movies. ''She can find a reason to enjoy a movie that amuses her or entertains her,'' he says. ''She doesn't get all in high dudgeon if people are not engaging their full esthetic potential, like I do.''</p>
        <p>He drifts back to the subject that most occupies him these days.</p>
        <p>''Religion to me is now the last frontier,'' he says. ''Christianity was being abused and exploited during the cold war. But now I think Christianity might be the last bulwark against a global capitalism that leeches out all of our humanity. You know, Christ and Marx touch fingers at some point.''</p>
        <p>His new ideal for the future is  some kind of ''Judeo-Christian socialism,'' he says. The only danger is that Judeo-Christian religious values will be abused by big money interests, he says.</p>
        <p>''What was it Mencken said? That politics is the last refuge of a scoundrel?'' he says. ''Well, now I think Christianity is becoming the last refuge of a scoundrel. There. Let me be the hat on Mencken's head.''</p>
        <p>He says he was startled by a recent question after a speaking engagement in which he argued that there are no philosophical questions left. What about abortion, he was asked? It set him back. He thought about it for a long time and then finally came up with an answer that satisfied him.</p>
        <p>''At present, I believe, it's not a philosophical debate because no debate is possible,'' he says. ''There is a huge gap between entrenched groups. There is a terroristic camp and a police force, if you will, people who are willing to go to extremes for their point of view and those who want to use the power of the state for theirs. No debate is possible.''</p>
        <p>Which is not to say that the question does not need to be addressed, that it is not potentially capable of debate. ''My God is an existential God,'' Mr. Mailer says. ''A God who is doing the best that He or She can do. And the question of abortion is of very lively interest to this God. Certain abortions are wise, certain abortions are wrong. But God does not necessarily have direct control over how people behave.''</p>
        <p>Fifty years after ''The Naked and the Dead,'' Mr. Mailer is still seeking out the big questions.</p>
        <p>The new anthology, which was published yesterday by Random House, on the exact 50th anniversary of his first novel, has created an inevitable occasion for the author to ponder and try to find the connective tissue.</p>
        <p>''I'd say the most surprising thing for me that emerged from working on the anthology was how little difference there is between my fiction and my nonfiction,'' he said. ''The piece on Marilyn Monroe and Arthur Miller could be a chapter in a novel. When you have good nonfiction, you have fiction. Really, you do. And when you have bad nonfiction, you have bad journalism.''</p>
        <p>He smiles again, sheepishly. ''Sorry, I didn't mean to put the onus on you,'' he says.</p>
        <p>The figures who were important to him over those decades -- from Eisenhower to Muhammad Ali to the Kennedys -- still tower in his memory, Mr. Mailer says. The decades have not diminished them. ''Jack Kennedy is as vivid to me as Bill Clinton, and he's been gone all these years,'' he says.</p>
        <p>The anthology is organized in an unusual way. It is chronological, not in the order in which it was written, but in the order of the periods Mr. Mailer was writing about.</p>
        <p>So sections from some of his earlier work rest next to snippets written 40 years later that address the same moment in time. It helps make the book both a compilation of one writer's sensibility and a social history of the half-century, Mr. Mailer says.</p>
        <p>''I was living with all the possibilities for organizing it,'' he says. ''You could do it in sections; one with all the pieces about writing, one about boxing, and so on. Then I thought, no one is going to read it. Another idea was to do it in the order that I wrote it. That might work with some writers, where development can be followed like the curve of an arc. But there is a tendency in my work for certain themes to repeat themselves five years apart.''</p>
        <p>Besides, he says, it gave a ''subtle flavor'' to the work to have pieces on the same time period written so far apart placed in proximity. ''What I had written in white heat in the 50's or 60's, let's say about Fidel Castro, is 30 years later put in more perspective,'' he says.</p>
        <p>It's all in there: Pieces of the novels from the 50's and 60's like ''The Deer Park'' and ''An American Dream,'' the groundbreaking nonfiction of ''Armies of the Night'' and ''Of a Fire on the Moon,'' the breathtaking leaps of ''The Executioner's Song'' and ''Harlot's Ghost.''</p>
        <p>He spent about half a year going over his old work, reading through about 5,000 pages of it to come up with what is now in the anthology.</p>
        <p>''I think people tend to dip into anthologies,'' he says. ''They tend to use them, really, as a box of chocolates. If one person in a hundred reads this volume through, from front to back, that's great. If 10 or 20 will read 200 or 300 pages at a time, that's great, too.''</p>
        <p>What he most wants now is to begin work on that second volume of ''Harlot's Ghost.''</p>
        <p>''I never sit down to begin a book without thinking, I've lost it, it's not there anymore,'' he says. ''And then, the feeling comes back. I've been waiting seven years to be visited by the muse for this second volume. She's been silent. I've been waiting. But now she's come back. What happened is that I got a major idea. So now, we'll see. Either it's going to happen or it's not.''</p>
        <p>But first, there will be a round of television interviews, then a book tour to Chicago, San Francisco and Los Angeles (''It's the basic tour,'' he says).</p>
        <p>It's difficult during all of this, Mr. Mailer says, not to think of this moment -- 50 years of writing, 75 years of living -- as something of a summation, an ending, an epitaph. But he is resisting it.</p>
        <p>''It's either my living memorial or else it's a chance to take a large part of my life and look at it before getting on with all that I have left to do,'' he says. ''For certain, I'll opt for the second option, but that doesn't mean it's accurate. We'll find out.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
