<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="07PUBL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1015228"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoban, Phoebe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980507T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E3DB1531F934A35756C0A96E958260" item-length="693" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON and Phoebe Hoban</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoban, Phoebe; Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public Lives column discusses several celebrity events; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Chinese Dissident Reaches Library</p>
        <p>''If he can get out of China, he can get to the New York Public Library,'' someone in the crowd said before WEI JINGSHENG, the Chinese dissident in exile, arrived last night.</p>
        <p>The journey to the library was not easy. Mr. Wei was hospitalized in Montreal on Tuesday for tests on his heart and had canceled a speech there. Officials at the library had been assured early yesterday that Mr. Wei had been released from the hospital and had resumed his breakneck schedule, which called for him to spend the day in Boston, then fly to New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Chinese Dissident Reaches Library</p>
        <p>''If he can get out of China, he can get to the New York Public Library,'' someone in the crowd said before WEI JINGSHENG, the Chinese dissident in exile, arrived last night.</p>
        <p>The journey to the library was not easy. Mr. Wei was hospitalized in Montreal on Tuesday for tests on his heart and had canceled a speech there. Officials at the library had been assured early yesterday that Mr. Wei had been released from the hospital and had resumed his breakneck schedule, which called for him to spend the day in Boston, then fly to New York.</p>
        <p>But foggy, rainy weather delayed his plane. Mr. Wei missed an early-evening reception but arrived for a question-and-answer session. He stepped to the microphone after a long, serious introduction by the television personality CHARLIE ROSE.</p>
        <p>''At the time there was an announcement that it was raining so hard in New York we would not be able to land,'' Mr. Wei said. ''And just when I thought I'd have to apologize to the 400 people expected, they told us it would be O.K. to fly. So I think this parallels the situation in China. You may think you're not going to take off, but suddenly there is a chance, and you have the opportunity to take off.''</p>
        <p>Poet's Film Debut</p>
        <p>WARREN BEATTY'S new film, ''Bulworth,'' features the acting debut of the black nationalist, poet and playwright AMIRI BARAKA. Mr. Baraka plays a homeless poet who offers advice to Bulworth (Mr. Beatty), a senator whose midlife meltdown involves an extended rant against America's political system.</p>
        <p>''Warren called me and asked me to do it,'' Mr. Baraka said. ''I liked the movie 'Reds,' '' he added, referring to the 1981 movie in which Mr. Beatty starred and directed, ''so I said sure, if I can write my own words. Basically, I try to consciously react to Warren's character. I think it's a very funny movie and it says some things that definitely need to be said.''</p>
        <p>Next week will be a busy one for Mr. Baraka and his family: ''Bulworth'' opens on May 15, three days after the election in Newark in which his son, Ras, 28, is running for councilman at large.</p>
        <p>Style Matriarch Sues Landscaper</p>
        <p>MARTHA STEWART, the matriarch of style, is suing the landscaper who maintains that she came this close to running him down with her sport-utility vehicle last year in East Hampton, N.Y. She accused the landscaper, MATTHEW MUNNICH, and his lawyers of extortion, coercion and defamation and seeks $825,000 in damages.</p>
        <p>Ms. Stewart and the landscaper tangled outside her 2,600-square foot pavilion of glass, marble and concrete, where she accused Mr. Munnich of building a fence between her property and that of her neighbor, the real-estate developer HARRY MACKLOWE. They have been feuding for several years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Munnich maintained last fall that he ducked into the bushes to escape being hit by Ms. Stewart's Chevrolet Suburban. He also said publicly that Ms. Stewart had used language a good deal more colorful than her signature phrase, ''It's a good thing.'' In her lawsuit, Ms. Stewart says the police report he filed was false.</p>
        <p>Mr. Munnich's lawyer, LEONARD AUSTIN, called the lawsuit frivolous and mean-spirited. He said that it was a pre-emptive move against a $6 million lawsuit that he had been preparing to file against Ms. Stewart and resulted from a call he had placed to a lawyer who represents her.</p>
        <p>''He asked me to hold off,'' Mr. Austin said of the lawyer, whom he would not name. ''He said, 'I need to reach her.' The day before yesterday, he said, 'I'm having trouble reaching her, could you give me a little more time?'</p>
        <p>''This is the result of my courtesy.''</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON and Phoebe Hoban</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
