<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Words to Spare, Schenkel Strikes a Chord</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="601856"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="TV SPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOWLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN BROADCASTING COS INC (ABC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANDOMIR, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago White Sox</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bowling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DE173AF930A25757C0A965958260" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Words to Spare, Schenkel Strikes a Chord</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Richard Sandomir</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SANDOMIR, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Confession: during my Wonder Years, more hours than I care to remember (because I clearly did not have a life out of doors) were spent watching and listening to ABC's Chris Schenkel and Billy Welu chronicle the bowling exploits of Don Carter, Dick Weber and Ray Bluth.</p>
        <p>In the 32d season of the Pro Bowlers Tour on ABC, Schenkel remains the gentle baritone of bowling who is still capable of excitement about the exploits of Del Ballard Jr. and Walter Ray Williams, still adept at setting up his partner (now Nelson Burton) and proud of the success of Pete Weber, Dick's son, whom he recalls holding in his arms.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Confession: during my Wonder Years, more hours than I care to remember (because I clearly did not have a life out of doors) were spent watching and listening to ABC's Chris Schenkel and Billy Welu chronicle the bowling exploits of Don Carter, Dick Weber and Ray Bluth.</p>
        <p>In the 32d season of the Pro Bowlers Tour on ABC, Schenkel remains the gentle baritone of bowling who is still capable of excitement about the exploits of Del Ballard Jr. and Walter Ray Williams, still adept at setting up his partner (now Nelson Burton) and proud of the success of Pete Weber, Dick's son, whom he recalls holding in his arms.</p>
        <p>"I grew up with bowling," he said a day before ABC's telecast of a recent tournament in Sayville, L.I. "I never looked down on it. I've enjoyed it as much as anything except the Olympics."</p>
        <p>Schenkel embraces the ordinary-guy appeal of bowling that keeps viewers coming back. Although the producer, Carol Lehti, and the director, Larry Kamm, have modernized the bowlcasts with the use of miniaturized cameras and a glitzy weekly opener, Schenkel's job has changed little. "I've learned about the scarcity of words," he said. "It's a sin to talk when the ball is rolling."</p>
        <p>Schenkel is the enduring star of the ABC series. Fans venture from the bleachers to press him for autographs. Bowlers greet him like an old friend. "Howya doing, Hooz," he said recently to a fellow Indianan, bowler Mike Aulby.</p>
        <p>Nearing his 70th birthday, the gray-haired Schenkel now works for ABC solely on bowling, which once vied for his network time with the Olympic events, pro basketball, golf and football. For 13 years, he was the voice of the New York Giants; in 1958, he called the seminal National Football League championship game between the Giants and the Baltimore Colts.</p>
        <p>For a sports broadcasting career that began in 1942 on a Muncie, Ind., radio station, Schenkel will receive a Sports Emmy tonight for lifetime achievement.</p>
        <p>Schenkel is a prized artifact from an earlier era, showing the versatility an announcer needed to survive and make a living in the 1950's -- his low-key personality and the cool medium of television were well matched.</p>
        <p>Sports broadcasting in the 50's leaned on the play-by-play announcer, but that burden shifted in earnest during the 60's, when former athletes and coaches flooded the television booths.</p>
        <p>"After better technology came in, I championed the role of the analyst," he said. "When the replay came in, I saw the need for someone with greater depth than I did. I got criticized that I was coddling these guys, but I had confidence in my own ability. They've added a hell of a dimension."</p>
        <p>Schenkel's partners have included Jack Twyman and Bill Russell (basketball), Red Grange and Paul Christman (college football), Johnny Lujack and Pat Summerall (pro football) and Peggy Fleming and Dick Button (figure skating).</p>
        <p>He said that he no longer feels melancholy about being absent from the big events he used to personify. "I only felt it for the first year after I didn't do golf," he said. "But I'd done so much football, college and pro. It wasn't as much fun. I really hit my goals from Day One."</p>
        <p>But don't expect a tell-all memoir from him. Only feel-good words flow from Schenkel. He is torn about whom to thank tonight. He worries that his wife, Fran, a former June Taylor dancer, will join him despite a recent foot injury. Schenkel even says nice things about another former partner, Howard Cosell.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the single best thing one needs to know about Schenkel is that he collects Indian peace medals.</p>
        <p>How much bowling remains in Schenkel's future is difficult to gauge. A one-year contract settled yesterday means ABC will air 14 tournaments in 1994, down from 24. The prospect, for now, pleases Schenkel.</p>
        <p>"At my age, 24 tournaments is a lot," he said, then added with a chuckle: "But how could ABC give us up entirely? What would 'Wide World of Sports' do without us? They'd die." When Green Is Boring</p>
        <p>You can't blame CBS for the dullness of Sunday's final round of the Masters. The only reason it was worth watching was the work of the wordsmith from England, reporter Ben Wright.</p>
        <p>On Chip Beck's lame layup shot on the 15th: "When you lay up and don't hit the 15th green, you really look foolish."</p>
        <p>On a shot by Seve Ballesteros into a pond: "The hole has dealt scurvily with him."</p>
        <p>On Beck's weak putt on the 16th: "That's a very tentative prod. I think Chip Beck's been looking at too many leader boards."</p>
        <p>On winner Bernhard Langer: "The imperturbable, phlegmatic one."</p>
        <p>On a man in the crowd shouting "You're the man!" on Langer's 16th tee shot: "Well, there's an idiot in every crowd."</p>
        <p>On Langer walking to the 16th green: "Once again, the green jacket is for export." AIRWAVES</p>
        <p>It's becoming an epidemic on sports broadcasts: WPIX/Channel 11 was in commercial when it missed the first pitch to LANCE JOHNSON in the bottom of the first inning of the Yankees-White Sox game on Sunday. . . .  What? WPIX's TOM SEAVER said twice of White Sox's STEVE SAX : "This is his first time up for the White Sox." Guess last year didn't count. . . . Really? NBC's STEVE JONES said Sunday, "Seattle has national respect because NBC is here." How about those 50 victories, Snapper? . . . Huh? NBC's DAN HICKS said the Lakers' JAMES WORTHY has "missed a step or two." Hope he didn't fall down and hurt himself. . . .  AL MICHAELS and JOHN DAVIDSON of the MSG Network are expected to be in Los Angeles on Sunday to call one of ABC's three regional National Hockey League playoff games. The other announcing teams are GARY THORNE and MIKE EMRICK and JIM SCHOENFELD  TV SPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
