<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Man, a Van, a Plan For Scrappy Baseball</title>
    <meta content="25jetblue" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cars" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/25/automobiles/autospecial/25jetblue.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1799755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="TRANSPORTATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Uniforms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061025T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EED81130F936A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1935" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Man, a Van, a Plan For Scrappy Baseball</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Man, a Van, a Plan for Scrappy Baseball</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARA RIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rimer, Sara</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN Washington Heights, up in northern Manhattan, there are two JetBlues, each indispensable, in its way, to its passengers from the neighborhood's Dominican immigrant enclave.</p>
        <p>There is the airline, of course, which makes it possible to travel between New York and the Dominican Republic. And there is the other JetBlue, a beat-up, secondhand Chevy van with a powder-blue paint job. JetBlue the van belongs to Tony Trinidad, the community affairs officer for the neighborhood's 34th Precinct, and his scrappy sandlot baseball team, the New York Bulldogz.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Washington Heights, there are two JetBlues, each indispensable, in its way, to its passengers from the neighborhood’s Dominican immigrant enclave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN Washington Heights, up in northern Manhattan, there are two JetBlues, each indispensable, in its way, to its passengers from the neighborhood's Dominican immigrant enclave.</p>
        <p>There is the airline, of course, which makes it possible to travel between New York and the Dominican Republic. And there is the other JetBlue, a beat-up, secondhand Chevy van with a powder-blue paint job. JetBlue the van belongs to Tony Trinidad, the community affairs officer for the neighborhood's 34th Precinct, and his scrappy sandlot baseball team, the New York Bulldogz.</p>
        <p>With his players from immigrant families struggling to cover the rent in Washington Heights and the Bronx, Officer Trinidad uses his own money to keep the team in uniforms, equipment and food. Except for the 2003 season, when Officer Trinidad hit the Lotto for $28,000 -- as his assistant manager, Xavier Medina, tells it, ''Trin wasted most of the money on the Bulldogz'' -- the team is generally strapped for cash. But that doesn't stop their wanting to get out of the city, to travel to New Jersey, upstate New York and even to Florida, like other, more affluent sandlot teams.</p>
        <p>Enter JetBlue. ''The team,'' said Mr. Medina, known as X by the Bulldogz and all his other friends in Washington Heights, ''is nothing without the van.''</p>
        <p>The players tend to get emotional when they talk about JetBlue. ''We love that van,'' said Deyvi Martinez, 19. ''It's like an airplane. We went to Florida, Canada, Pennsylvania, Connecticut in that van. Trin'' -- everyone calls Officer Trinidad Trin -- ''even lends it to us to go to the beach. It's blessed, that van. It brings us everywhere.''</p>
        <p>To be a young Dominican-American ballplayer in Washington Heights is to dream of making it to the major leagues, like Manny Ramirez, the Boston Red Sox star who hit his way out of George Washington High School. A major part of the fantasy involves a flashy vehicle, a Cadillac Escalade, say, Bentley or Range Rover, like the ones the rap stars drive in the videos.</p>
        <p>In real life in Washington Heights, the Bulldogz, 30 players age 14 to 19, take the subway -- and, for the last three years, JetBlue.</p>
        <p>''JetBlue keeps the players grounded,'' Mr. Medina said.</p>
        <p>Staying grounded -- that is pretty much the idea behind the Bulldogz. Officer Trinidad, who is 44 and was a champion wrestler back in high school, is not much of a baseball fan. But the game is the neighborhood passion. So in 2001, when Officer Trinidad was looking for a way to keep young men off the streets, he started a baseball team.</p>
        <p>From the beginning, the players were desperate to travel. Officer Trinidad, who is married and the father of two teenage girls, knew how they felt. He grew up in a family of six children. His father was a building porter.</p>
        <p>''I never left the city,'' recalled Officer Trinidad, who is Puerto Rican. ''My father was always working. We never had the money to go anywhere.''</p>
        <p>Officer Trinidad packed the Bulldogz into his seven-passenger minivan and a borrowed second van, and began taking them to games in New Jersey. In the summer of 2002, thanks to a local sponsor, the Bulldogz made a weeklong trip to Orlando, Fla., to compete in a tournament. They went on JetBlue -- the real JetBlue, the airline. The airline treated the players like V.I.P.'s, with the pilot welcoming the team over the loudspeaker.</p>
        <p>Four years later, the players remember it as one of the best weeks of their lives. They had pillow fights at the Travelodge motel. They swam in the pool. They went to Disney World.</p>
        <p>''We had a great time,'' Officer Trinidad said. He laughed. ''Maybe that's why we lost all the games.''</p>
        <p>The next season, naturally, everyone was dying to go back to Florida. But there was no sponsor. Meanwhile, someone's uncle had just bought a 12-passenger van at an auction in Morris County, N.J. The van had been a county vehicle, which is why it said Morris County in big letters on the side. Officer Trinidad bought it for $2,000. He removed the name, but kept the powder-blue paint.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Medina at the wheel, the team headed for Orlando -- 24 hours on the road. The players sang, told jokes and argued about baseball, girls, the air-conditioning -- ''turn it down, it's too cold;'' ''turn it up, it's too hot'' -- and when they should stop again to eat. The miles flew by.</p>
        <p>No official christening was necessary. The players had started calling the van JetBlue from the moment they climbed aboard. The ride home was somewhat bumpier -- JetBlue broke down in New Jersey, about an hour outside of New York, when the transmission went, at 4 a.m. Everyone had to pile into the second van to get home, and JetBlue was towed back to Washington Heights.</p>
        <p>Like the Bulldogz, who generally win at baseball -- except in Florida -- the JetBlue van has some impressive numbers: vintage, 1991; mileage, 113,000; baseball games, hundreds.</p>
        <p>The famous blue paint -- people all over the neighborhood have become accustomed to the sight of the powder-blue van -- is peeling. The windshield is cracked. Mysteriously, the driver's door leaks water. Mr. Medina, 23, spends more time behind the wheel than anyone else. He was cataloging the van's idiosyncrasies one Sunday morning in early September as the Bulldogz were preparing for a doubleheader in Newark, loading up JetBlue and another van borrowed from a bike shop nearby.</p>
        <p>Mr. Medina pointed out the dent on the back door on the passenger's side where someone had broken in. ''They stole a pack of Trin's Diet Cokes,'' he said. The van runs on gas ($85 for a fill-up). Officer Trinidad runs on Diet Coke.</p>
        <p>Recently, the van has been making troubling noises. Mr. Medina says it could be coming from the rims. On the other hand, it could be the engine. ''Trin just spent $1,000 on a new transmission,'' Mr. Medina said. (It was the second transmission Officer Trinidad paid for). ''Hopefully it's not going to break down any day soon.''</p>
        <p>Inside, the carpeting is ripped. The three passenger seats are stuck permanently in recline. As for the area under the seats, ''you could probably find a burger under there,'' Mr. Medina said with a slow grin. (One of Officer Trinidad's strict rules is that no one on his team goes hungry, not even for 10 minutes.)</p>
        <p>To the casual observer, the best possibility may be a trip to the junk heap for JetBlue, followed by a new van. But with the Bulldogz -- in other words, Officer Trinidad -- already in debt this season for more than $4,000 worth of baseball equipment, a new van is out of the question.</p>
        <p>Besides, said Mr. Medina, ''That van is still good.''</p>
        <p>To anyone who knows its history, JetBlue is as irreplaceable as Officer Trinidad, or Mr. Medina, or the individual players. ''It's not only a team, it's a family,'' one player, Mr. Martinez, said. ''Everything is fun, even when we lose.''</p>
        <p>They eat together (El Malecón, where $6 buys a chicken dinner with rice and beans, is the team restaurant). They do their homework together (sometimes Officer Trinidad has to force them). Their parents may be working, or in the Dominican Republic or unavailable for other reasons. But JetBlue -- meaning Officer Trinidad and Mr. Medina -- is there for every baseball game at George Washington High School, and for every graduation.</p>
        <p>The Bulldogz tend to stay attached, even after they move on from high school and start working. Once a Bulldogz, always a Bulldogz. ''Like the Marines,'' said Officer Trinidad, who is himself a former marine.</p>
        <p>No prima donna baseball stars need apply. ''I look for the kids with the best attitudes,'' Officer Trinidad said. Loyalty to the team, as well as what people in Washington Heights describe as ''heart,'' trumps talent. His scouting method has been successful: this summer, the Bulldogz won the Hudson Valley summer league championship, among many victories over the years.</p>
        <p>If the Bulldogz are a family, then JetBlue is the family station wagon. ''A lot of stories in there, a lot of memories,'' Mr. Medina said. ''It's hard to let go of a van like that.''</p>
        <p>JetBlue is available, with either Mr. Medina or Officer Trinidad driving, to take the Bulldogz and their friends and families wherever they need to go: the airport, the hospital (when Mr. Martinez had an excruciating toothache at 2 one morning, Officer Trinidad dispatched Mr. Medina, in JetBlue, to take him to New York-Presbyterian/Columbia hospital), the batting cages in Yonkers, a new apartment. JetBlue has hauled more than a few living-room sofas in its day.</p>
        <p>In the spring of 2004, seven veteran Bulldogz -- Hector Fernandez, Angel Salome, Deyvi Martinez, Pedro Pena, Bobby Alvarez, Willie Gomez and Anthony Collado -- needed transportation to George Washington High School's senior prom. A limo would have been nice, but who could afford it? Mr. Martinez did not even have the money for a tuxedo.</p>
        <p>Officer Trinidad bought him a tux. He let it be known that JetBlue was available.</p>
        <p>The Bulldogz jumped at the offer. ''We wanted to go in JetBlue,'' Mr. Martinez said. ''We felt comfortable in JetBlue.'' There was only one problem. ''The girls didn't want to go in JetBlue,'' Mr. Martinez said. ''They wanted to look fancy.''</p>
        <p>In the end, Rick Huerta, who had coached the players when they were with the neighborhood's Michael Buczek Little League, took them to the prom in his new black Ford Expedition.</p>
        <p>About a month later, Mr. Salome, George Washington's star catcher and the Milwaukee Brewers' fifth-round draft pick, was about to leave for spring training in Phoenix. He had an early morning flight out of La Guardia.</p>
        <p>''Trin left us the van about 11 p.m.,'' Mr. Medina recalled.</p>
        <p>With Mr. Medina at the wheel, Mr. Salome spent his last night in Washington Heights riding around in JetBlue with the Bulldogz. The sun was just coming up when Mr. Medina collected Mr. Salome's mother and other family members and headed for the airport.</p>
        <p>Mr. Medina takes enormous pride in his role as JetBlue's No. 1 driver. ''That van is me,'' he said. ''I have my own keys.''</p>
        <p>Still, he said he understood why some young women might not want to be seen in an old Chevy van with the paint peeling off.</p>
        <p>Mr. Medina recalled the time a young woman he knew called him for a ride home from a club downtown. Figuring that she might want to slip unnoticed into JetBlue, Mr. Medina called her on his cellphone as he approached the club.</p>
        <p>''I told her, 'I'll meet you around the block,' '' Mr. Medina said. ''She's a model. She's used to being in a Bentley. JetBlue was a big, big step down for her.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Medina, however, JetBlue is all about stepping up in life. It starts with his connection to Officer Trinidad. Mr. Medina, along with several of the players, looks to Officer Trinidad as his surrogate father.</p>
        <p>''I started cutting school at 14, 15,'' Mr. Medina said. ''Trin pulled me in. He put me under his wing. I say he's more my father than my real one. He's done everything for me for the past couple years. He forced me to get my G.E.D. Now I'm trying to get to college. Anything to make him happy.</p>
        <p>''My dream for Trin and the Bulldogz?'' Mr. Medina said. ''It's a big dream, I doubt we'll get it. But my dream is to get an RV so we can travel in one van. It's always good to have everyone together. Hopefully, Trin will hit the Lotto again soon.''</p>
        <p>TRANSPORTATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
