<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Different Sort of Scion</title>
    <meta content="20FORD$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1047900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="FIVE QUESTIONS/WILLIAM CLAY FORD JR."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ford, William Clay Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DF1430F933A1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Different Sort of Scion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with William Clay Ford Jr, set to become Ford Motor Co chairman; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WILLIAM CLAY FORD JR., soon to be chairman of the Ford Motor Company, is not exactly a car man from central casting.</p>
        <p>The auto industry has been feuding with environmentalists ever since air quality became an issue in the 1960's, but Mr. Ford has long been active in environmental groups. He is a great-grandson of a famously autocratic industrial titan and leads an extended family that still controls 40 percent of Ford's voting stock, but he is happy to share power and the spotlight with Jacques A. Nasser, who will become Ford's president and chief executive.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WILLIAM CLAY FORD JR., soon to be chairman of the Ford Motor Company, is not exactly a car man from central casting.</p>
        <p>The auto industry has been feuding with environmentalists ever since air quality became an issue in the 1960's, but Mr. Ford has long been active in environmental groups. He is a great-grandson of a famously autocratic industrial titan and leads an extended family that still controls 40 percent of Ford's voting stock, but he is happy to share power and the spotlight with Jacques A. Nasser, who will become Ford's president and chief executive.</p>
        <p>After the company announced on Sept. 11 that Mr. Ford, 41, and Mr. Nasser, 50, would succeed Alexander Trotman, 65, at the end of the year, Mr. Ford talked about driving down roads less traveled.</p>
        <p>KEITH BRADSHER</p>
        <p>Q.  You've said Ford will seek environmental leadership in your tenure. Is there a tension between that and maximizing profits?</p>
        <p>A.  In the short term, there probably is a tension. But I think in the long term, if we are the leading corporate citizen, it will do several things for us. It will create an image for Ford in the marketplace that is different from others, and in a cluttered and crowded marketplace in which differentiation is hard to obtain, particularly in image. If we achieve this, we will attract better employees and the highest caliber of people out of universities. They're going to want to come work for a company like Ford.</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Is it true that when you joined the Ford board, you were asked to distance yourself from the environmental movement?</p>
        <p>A.  Somebody close to the board thought it would be a good idea if I stopped associating with crazies, and I assured them that not only was I not doing so, but that the group I was involved with, which was very benign -- the Nature Conservancy -- was made up of a cross-section of our customers. At the time, I was in Switzerland, where business and environmentalists actually had a dialogue. In this country, all they did was snipe at each other. I felt that somebody needed to start building bridges, so I really chose to stay involved.</p>
        <p>Q.  Are you going to have formal meetings with Mr. Nasser to coordinate your division of responsibilities?</p>
        <p>A.  We're going to have to set aside some formal time so that we can both make sure we actually do it. And then there's going to be a lot of just wandering into each other's offices and picking up the phone. The less formal that we can make this, and the more of a true partnership in making it easy, I think, the better it's going to be for the company. That's something that both he and I want to do. We really have a running start on this because we've known each other a long time. We get on very well; we think the same way.</p>
        <p>Q.  Splitting the jobs of chairman and chief executive is unusual. You're busy now with running the Detroit Lions football team and other activities. Might you someday want to add the job of chief executive at Ford?</p>
        <p>A.  I don't believe so. I really believe this is a great setup. One of the nice things about this arrangement is that it does use the strength of two capable people. Having watched how large this company has become, and how tough it is to manage, I think separating these jobs makes a lot of sense. And internationally, as you know, that is quite common -- less so in this country. Jac and I both concluded this is the way to go. We're both relatively young, and I think we'll hopefully be at this a long time together. By the time Jac is ready to go, I really have no idea what my mindset will be.</p>
        <p>Q.  After Princeton, why did you choose to study management at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology rather than at the more famous Harvard Business School?</p>
        <p>A.  As a liberal arts major as an undergrad, I felt I would be best served by going to the most quantitative program that I could find. I felt that would give me the best rounding-out experience, and, in fact, I think that was true. I was one of only two non-engineers in my class at M.I.T., and it was a great experience.</p>
        <p>FIVE QUESTIONS/WILLIAM CLAY FORD JR.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
