<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From/Rye; It's Back to School and the Basic Values Beyond the Three R's</title>
    <meta content="20VIEW$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1047794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Rye (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE6D61F31F933A1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1229" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From/Rye; It's Back to School and the Basic Values Beyond the Three R's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>RYE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scene at Midland Elementary School in Rye, NY, described as school year begins; describes traditions that continue even into computer age; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE banner in the lobby says it  all  ''Welcome back to school.'' Brightly colored cardboard letters form the words, which surround a big, three-dimensional paper apple. Also in the display case: a lacrosse stick, a globe, a football and copies of ''Heidi,'' ''Tom Sawyer'' and ''Frankenstein.''</p>
        <p>The 550 students at Midland Elementary School here may be in a different era from the schoolchildren who first read books like ''Heidi'' -- there are four computers in every classroom, including kindergarten -- but in many ways their yearly return to class seems timeless. Boys and girls toting backpacks stuffed with notebooks, rulers, pencils and, yes, an occasional lunchtime apple, streamed through the hallways; teachers set out poster paint for art, plants for science lessons and multiplication table charts for arithmetic; mothers looked relieved and happy when their children emerged from the building smiling. By the third day of school last week there was a sense that the more things change, the more they stay the same.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE banner in the lobby says it  all  ''Welcome back to school.'' Brightly colored cardboard letters form the words, which surround a big, three-dimensional paper apple. Also in the display case: a lacrosse stick, a globe, a football and copies of ''Heidi,'' ''Tom Sawyer'' and ''Frankenstein.''</p>
        <p>The 550 students at Midland Elementary School here may be in a different era from the schoolchildren who first read books like ''Heidi'' -- there are four computers in every classroom, including kindergarten -- but in many ways their yearly return to class seems timeless. Boys and girls toting backpacks stuffed with notebooks, rulers, pencils and, yes, an occasional lunchtime apple, streamed through the hallways; teachers set out poster paint for art, plants for science lessons and multiplication table charts for arithmetic; mothers looked relieved and happy when their children emerged from the building smiling. By the third day of school last week there was a sense that the more things change, the more they stay the same.</p>
        <p>In Vicki Sitner's first-grade classroom, for example, pupils were using chalkboards. That's right, little individual squares of slate, and writing on them with old-fashioned chalk, and using felt erasers to wipe them clean. ''They love them,'' Ms. Sitner said.  ''It's a little different from paper.'' To the youngsters, grouped in a semicircle around her feet, she said, ''O.K., everyone, write the letter that comes after V.'' When all 23 put ''W'' on their boards, she oohed and aahed and said: ''Oh my, you are good. Are you sure you're not in second grade?''</p>
        <p>Tradition also appeared in a most unexpected form at recess, with a game of jump-rope. By the time they reach the fifth grade, the highest in the school, 10-year-olds have already had lectures warning of the dangers of drugs (D.A.R.E., a national antidrug school program, is implemented in Midland by the Rye Police Department) and learned about their anatomies in something called ''The Body Shop.'' Some of the oldest students already look more like little teen-agers than little children. Yet here were a dozen girls, giggling and shouting, jumping rope to chants that sounded like quaint, turn-of-the-century nursery rhymes:</p>
        <p>''Teddy bear, teddy bear, turn around,'' they sang rhythmically. ''Teddy bear, teddy bear, touch the ground. Teddy bear, teddy bear, turn out the light, teddy bear, teddy bear, say good night.''</p>
        <p>The Rye School District prides itself on high test scores and good grades. The Midland principal, Dr. Joseph Soury, and Dr. Edward J. Shine, Superintendent of the Rye schools, point to the objectives listed in a recent newsletter: students should excel in ''critical thinking and communications skills'' and should ''set and achieve personally challenging educational goals.'' Beyond the academic, however, are the social goals, the desires to impart what one teacher called ''good old-fashioned values.''</p>
        <p>''I want to teach them to be kind to everyone, to be a positive influence on society,'' Heidi Lohrfink, a 31-year-old teacher, said. Ms. Lohrfink, who looked anything but old-fashioned with her deep suntan and chic, sporty clothes, said she believes in ''teaching children to share, to treat each other with respect, to have empathy -- it doesn't help just to say, 'That's not nice' if someone is teasing someone; you have to make them see what it would feel like if it was being done to them.''</p>
        <p>These lessons seem to have made an impression on at least some of the students. Even the older pupils, at an age when cliques form faster than real friendships, said anyone was free to join their playground games. ''Groups will usually let you come in and play if you have no one else to play with,'' said one fifth grader, Julia Partington. ''Whatever the activity is, you just join it.'' Eileen Clancy, also a fifth grader, added, ''They have to, because you can't not include anyone.''</p>
        <p>Concern about basic social interactions permeated the conversations of several mothers who were at the school to pick up their children. The group of attractive thirty-something mothers who, with their blond hair, casually stylish outfits and cool poise, seemed the antithesis of insecurity, confided that they worried about whether their children would strike a balance between fitting in and remaining true to themselves.</p>
        <p>''This is the age when peer pressure begins,'' said Suzanne O'Connell, mother of a kindergartner, Douglas, and a second grader, Philip. ''They have to fit in socially, but they also have to try to keep intact the things you've taught them.''</p>
        <p>Another mother, Ann Borer, recalled: ''Last year, I wrote little hello notes on the napkins that my son, then in first grade, took with his lunch. He told me to stop it: kids were teasing him. But this year, so far, it seems O.K. with him. We'll see if he is swayed by his peers again.''</p>
        <p>Kathy Gelghegan said: ''The most important thing is for them to feel that they are worth something as individuals, to feel happy. We were all insecure once about going back to school, missing our families, worrying about making friends. I'll be pleased if my children simply feel happy with themselves.'' At that moment, as if on cue, Mrs. Gelghegan's daughter, Katie, appeared. Katie, a little blonde who has just begun kindergarten, was wearing denim overalls with flower appliques, purple clogs and a little rope bracelet like those of the older girls. She looked very stylish and relaxed for a kindergartner. Mrs. Gelghegan said that her daughter is basically shy, however -- ''I am just happy to see her smiling.'' As for Katie, asked what she did that day, she said: ''I had fun. I made friends.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, each classroom is perhaps a microcosm, with its little tables and tiny chairs, with every inch of space taken up with everything from live fish in glass bowls to state-of-the-art computers and with each teacher still teaching virtually everything (departmentalization starts in later grades). Children have an opportunity to learn much more than the three R's. Harold Voge, a fifth grader with big brown eyes and a mischievous manner, said:</p>
        <p>''When you first go to school, you think another year of torment. But then it gets to be fun. You get to be with your friends and do a lot of things. Well, maybe I should say, recess is fun, doing work is torment. But not really. Because in school, there's much more than just work.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
