<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>OIL RICH, OIL POOR: A special report.; High Claims in Spill Betray Depth of Nigerian Poverty</title>
    <meta content="20NIGE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1048118"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Nigeria</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mobil Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cohen, Roger</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abubakar, Abdulsalam (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Special Report</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Nigeria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DB1230F933A1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="2973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>OIL RICH, OIL POOR: A special report.; High Claims in Spill Betray Depth of Nigerian Poverty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cohen, Roger</byline>
      <dateline>EKET, Nigeria</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Special report on Mobil oil spill off Nigerian coast in January, which has become subject of vehement dispute and catalyst for pent-up claims fed by poverty and state neglect; as Nigeria approaches delicate transition from military rule to democracy, delta region's long-festering problems pose threat of widespread violence; sabotage against pipelines is becoming routine, and poverty-stricken villagers are making huge financial demands on Mobil; since oil was discovered in delta region 42 years ago, enormous wealth has been taken by Western companies and by country's military rulers; now Mobil is facing billions of dollars in claims from population that feels it has been long ignored and Government of Gen Abdulsalam Abubakar is making conciliatory gestures but initiating little real reform; maps; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Denny Sansom of Mobil Oil has the ocean behind him, seven million restive Nigerians of the Niger River Delta in front of him, huge reserves of oil beneath him and hundreds of thousands of angry complaints against his corporation threatening to sink him.</p>
        <p>The trouble began on Jan. 12, he recalled. Mr. Sansom, a Texan who is Mobil's operations manager, walked into his 6:45 A.M. staff meeting and was told that despite full production at Mobil's 57 offshore wells, oil was not reaching shore. ''Shut it down!'' he hollered. ''Shut everything!''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Denny Sansom of Mobil Oil has the ocean behind him, seven million restive Nigerians of the Niger River Delta in front of him, huge reserves of oil beneath him and hundreds of thousands of angry complaints against his corporation threatening to sink him.</p>
        <p>The trouble began on Jan. 12, he recalled. Mr. Sansom, a Texan who is Mobil's operations manager, walked into his 6:45 A.M. staff meeting and was told that despite full production at Mobil's 57 offshore wells, oil was not reaching shore. ''Shut it down!'' he hollered. ''Shut everything!''</p>
        <p>The order came too late. A 24-inch underwater pipeline from Mobil's Idaho production platform three and a half miles offshore had snapped. Flying 26 miles out over the Atlantic in a helicopter that afternoon, Mr. Sansom saw 26 miles of oil. ''The slick was moving like a giant ship,'' he said. ''That thing about killed me.''</p>
        <p>Along the Nigerian coast, the spilled oil has now become a subject of vehement dispute, a catalyst for pent-up claims fed by poverty and state neglect. In few places on earth do the West's richest corporations and millions of the world's poorest people rub shoulders with such intensity or such potentially explosive consequences as in the Niger Delta, the fifth-largest source of America's imported fuel.</p>
        <p>''Things are very turbulent,'' said Ernest Ukocho, a community leader in the villages surrounding Mobil's operations at Eket. ''We are trying to maintain calm, but there has been some rioting. The fact is, everyone wants a piece of the Mobil cake.''</p>
        <p>The oil -- 40,000 barrels of it, or roughly one-sixth of the giant Exxon Valdez spill in Alaska -- drifted west, thus avoiding nearby Cameroonian waters to the east and an international fiasco. The fiercely secretive former Nigerian regime of Gen. Sani Abacha, who died in June, also helped keep the Mobil spill largely out of the news.</p>
        <p>But in the Niger Delta everyone quickly knew of it. Mr. Sansom has been held hostage, repeatedly rebuked and now spends 70 percent of his time on ''community issues'' -- essentially trying to stop resentment turning to rioting.</p>
        <p>As Nigeria approaches a delicate transition from military rule to democracy, which is supposed to take place next year, the delta's long-festering problems pose the threat of widespread violence. In the wetlands, the world's largest mangrove swamp, unrest now seems close to boiling over, with sabotage against pipelines becoming routine and intermittent acts of violence.</p>
        <p>The spill -- dwarfing those caused by sabotage -- made Mr. Sansom's position doubly difficult. Scientific evidence shows that environmental damage was ultimately slight. But for people long subjected to the stunted development apparently willed on the delta by Nigerian military governments, that spilled oil was a bonanza beckoning.</p>
        <p>The Claimants  Thinking Very Big, Poor Seek Redress</p>
        <p>''I understand these people,'' Mr. Sansom said. ''They're poor. So they think we're all Howard Hughes. One Saturday morning alone, I had $4.5 billion in claims -- that's 45 percent of the total oil revenue of the country.''</p>
        <p>Since oil was discovered here 42 years ago by Royal Dutch/Shell, enormous wealth has been taken from the area by Mobil, Chevron, Shell, Texaco and other Western companies, and by Nigeria's generals, who have ruled for 28 of the last 32 years. But, as a result of apparently gross neglect by the military Government that takes the bulk of the country's oil revenue, life for the people living in the wetlands has scarcely improved.</p>
        <p>When the Nigerian writer Ken Saro-Wiwa had the temerity to point this out, demanding compensation on the grounds that the entire region, and his Ogoni people, remained poor, Nigeria's generals hanged him in 1995.</p>
        <p>The pretext was a flimsy charge of involvement in a murder, upheld by a kangaroo court of military officers. The real issue was -- and remains -- where and how the more than $10 billion Nigeria takes in annually from oil is invested.</p>
        <p>Even a senior official at the Nigerian National Petroleum Company conceded, albeit on condition of anonymity, that years of taking oil from the delta and plowing the profits into northern Nigeria -- the base of the ruling generals -- is a policy increasingly fraught with risk.</p>
        <p>''You are going to see an escalation,'' the official said. ''We're taking oil from one part of the country and investing it in the north. I do not think you can go on taking money from a place without enhancing life there.''</p>
        <p>Gen. Abdulsalami Abubakar, General Abacha's successor, has indicated that he wants reform. He made a conciliatory gesture this month in releasing several Ogoni prisoners. But the problems are so deep-rooted that such gestures are unlikely to have immediate effect.</p>
        <p>President Clinton and other Western leaders expressed indignation at Mr. Saro-Wiwa's execution -- although not enough to impose oil sanctions on Nigeria, where American investment totals $7 billion. Three years later, the seven million delta people still appear mired in a paralyzing web. Among them are Ibo and several large minority ethnic groups; the Ogoni form a small minority of about 500,000.</p>
        <p>To Western oil interests, generally synonymous with Western political interests, stability has been of paramount importance in Nigeria: the country's oil is ecologically desirable to America because it is unusually sulfur-free and strategically desirable because it represents diversification from Middle Eastern sources.</p>
        <p>That stability has been preserved at gunpoint.</p>
        <p>As a result of interethnic tensions, and memories of Biafra's secession in 1967, the northern generals who have governed Nigeria have mainly sought to keep the delta area poor and backward on the basis that a region with oil and development might be tempted to go it alone again. The then-Republic of Biafra comprised much of the oil-producing region; its independence was quashed in a three-year war that cost a million lives.</p>
        <p>The oil companies, meanwhile, have long taken the view that their obligations are met by paying taxes and royalties to the authorities. Oil production, not regional development, has been their role. Although this approach is now changing, the delta still bears heavy scars.</p>
        <p>Potholed roads, rundown schools and isolated villages without running water dot an area that produces over 90 percent of Nigeria's hard-currency earnings.</p>
        <p>Only the widely resented flares of the oil companies that light the night sky betray the fact that this land is rich. Because the oil companies are far more visible in the area than the military Government, they are the main focus of ire.</p>
        <p>In one sense they are unfairly criticized: the Government takes over 70 percent of Nigeria's oil revenue and could clearly have invested more of it in the delta. But Western companies effectively acquiesced in the region's impoverishment so long as they could pump oil and get their money out: their push for ''community development'' in recent years, and especially since the death of Mr. Saro-Wiwa, may have come too late.</p>
        <p>''If I were from the delta, I would long ago have joined an armed struggle,'' said Bola Ige, a prominent Lagos lawyer and former governor of the southern Oyo state. ''What else can you reasonably be down there but a guerrilla leader?''</p>
        <p>And what else could Mobil's oil spill reasonably provoke, in such an environment, but dreams of sudden wealth?</p>
        <p>The Fairfax, Va.-based company, which produces about one-third of Nigeria's total oil output in a joint venture with the state-owned Nigerian National Petroleum Corporation, moved fast as the oil seeped into the ocean.</p>
        <p>Enormous interests were at stake: Mobil has more than $2.5 billion invested in Nigeria; the Ubit offshore platform, pumping 250,000 barrels a day, is the company's largest single production unit.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sansom took over an emergency command center that he manned almost uninterruptedly for over a month. (At one point during that time, as he was meeting with community leaders, a mob rushed into the Eket site and held him captive. It took him about 10 hours to talk his way out of the crisis.) Helicopters and boats were deployed to apply dispersants to the oil slick; containment booms and oil skimmers were used; scientists and environmentalists were rushed in from Lagos University and the United States to test the degree of pollution; Mobil announced that it would compensate anyone suffering injury.</p>
        <p>The Spill  A Quick Response, And Lots of Luck</p>
        <p>But with disaster looming, weather and currents smiled on Mobil. For a long time the bulk of the oil remained offshore, where warm winds and the light nature of Nigerian crude favored evaporation.</p>
        <p>''Between Mother Nature and Mobil's highly effective and targeted response,'' said David Page, an American oil spill expert, ''the shoreline was spared what could have been a very serious environmental event. The amount of oil that got ashore was minimal, perhaps 1 percent of the spill, or 400 barrels, certainly no more than 1,000 barrels.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Page, a chemistry professor at Bowdoin College in Maine who has visited Nigeria three times since the spill, says hardly any oil entered the sensitive mangrove creeks that lace the delta. Certainly none is visible today. ''I'm not an attorney,'' he added, ''but it's fair to say that because so little oil got ashore, I'd be very surprised if fishermen's livelihoods were cut off.''</p>
        <p>That, however, is emphatically not the view of hundreds of thousands of poor Nigerians along the coast. Claims have been pouring in to the American company from Akwa Ibom state, home to Mobil, from Delta state, from Cross River, from Bajelsa, from Lagos -- ''the entire damn coast,'' in the words of Isong I Akpabio, a Mobil spokesman.</p>
        <p>At Mobil headquarters in Lagos recently, Celia Onitiri, head of the legal staff, was unavailable for comment. She was at home and was said to be suffering from stress.</p>
        <p>''Look, we wanted to be fair,'' said Paul L. Caldwell Jr., chairman of Mobil Producing Nigeria Unlimited, as the company's Nigerian venture is named. ''But this has turned into a major undertaking and a big headache. The fact is, the communities look to us to provide support that they are not getting from the Nigerian Government.''</p>
        <p>Effiong Ikot, a fisherman and owner of a small business, is among those who have made claims. He has demanded 490,000 naira of Mobil -- about $5,700 -- for the loss of fishing nets clogged with oil. He regards Mobil's offer of about $250 as insulting.</p>
        <p>Like other claimants, Mr. Ikot brought his bundles of nets to be inspected by Mobil officials and insurance agents. Once the inspection was completed, the nets were burned. ''How can I be happy,'' Mr. Ikot said, ''when somebody burns my nets?''</p>
        <p>Throughout the area, the chorus of indignation at the burning of nets is overwhelming, driven by a sense that, as one local leader, Chief Daniel Utong, put it, ''this act added injury to injury.''</p>
        <p>Mercy Akpakip, a mother of six, said her business had been ruined. A single shark net, she said, cost at least $600, and ''how can I live when my nets have been burned and I've yet to receive anything?''</p>
        <p>But Grace Nwawo, a community affairs official for Mobil in Eket, insisted that there had been no alternative but to burn the nets.</p>
        <p>''If they were usable,'' she asked, ''why were they brought in? Where could we have stored them? How could we have found uncorrupt guards to protect them? How would we have prevented them being sold to the next village?''</p>
        <p>The dilemma of the nets illustrates Mobil's situation. In strictly rational terms, the decision to burn them seems sound. But in the world of poverty and vague fears that surrounds Mobil, Shell, Texaco, Chevron and other oil companies in the delta, symbols and fantasy tend to hold sway. And what could be a more overwhelming symbol of a rich company trampling on poor fishermen than the burning of their nets?</p>
        <p>In the absence of state investment -- authorities have built no schools for several years -- Mobil has effectively become the local government: the object of all claims, all hope of jobs, money or investment, all aspirations for electricity, or hospitals or running water -- and all resentments.</p>
        <p>To travel the Eket region -- an area of about 100 square miles that might reasonably be renamed Mobiland -- is to encounter a fantastic array of complaints leveled at the American company: gutters not deep enough, roads and clinics promised but not built, oil-polluted sea waters now allegedly emptied of fish all the way to Cameroon, zinc roofs rusting because of the flares, even doors and walls vibrating from earth tremors allegedly caused by Mobil's activities.</p>
        <p>''They come to me asking for Mobil to build a water supply system'' Mr. Sansom said, ''and I say, why don't you go to the water board and ask the same question? And they say, because the water board would shoot us!''</p>
        <p>He laughed. ''You know, the naira these local governors get from the military Government would not buy you a piece of chewing gum.'' Yet more than 60 percent of the revenue from Mobil's joint venture goes to the Government.</p>
        <p>The Caretaker  Its Blessings Flow, But Not Fast Enough</p>
        <p>The tranquil village of Itafre, a collection of mud-and-thatch houses, lies in the midst of the mangrove swamp about 10 miles from Mobil's Eket base. Like many settlements, it is inaccessible other than by boat or helicopter. Mobil has built a school here and tried to develop a cashew-nut farm.</p>
        <p>But resentment is strong, especially since the spill. Thomas Ebitu, the village chief, acknowledged that Mobil had built his house and the school and started the farm. But what about a road? And why was the village without electricity? And where was the running water that Mobil should provide?</p>
        <p>The assembled villagers nodded. They were asked if the Government might provide some of these services. Mobil, it was pointed out, is an oil company, not a civil engineering company. It spends over $8 million a year on improving village conditions.</p>
        <p>''But there is no government here,'' said Mike Maru, a fisherman. ''Mobil is the only visible entity. They are making a lot of money here, and we've been left like monkeys out here in the swamp.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Maru added that he had lost 350 bundles of nets as a result of the spill and was claiming 300 million naira, or $3.4 million. The figure, in the context of the village, appeared utterly fantastic. Another fisherman, Monday Smith, said he would settle for $11,500. Both said their nets had been burned and asked how they were expected to live in the absence of compensation.</p>
        <p>In another village, Okuro Utip, a resident named James Nyoh stood up and made a half-hour speech. He listed everything that Mobil should provide: spill compensation, an education endowment, a health center, a road network, clean water, jobs. The company, he concluded, owes the village just under $100 million for the spill alone.</p>
        <p>These claims are a very long way from Mobil's estimates. With oil prices at a low ebb, the company is cutting costs. Of nine exploration rigs that were operating in Nigerian waters, eight have been shut down.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nwawo said the company believed that a little over $100 was fair compensation for each lost net. Although some payments will be higher, Mobil believes most validated claims should be settled by payments not exceeding $600.</p>
        <p>In all, the spill of about $600,000 worth of oil may cost the company about $40 million -- $10 million in cleanup and $30 million to settle the claims. Payments have started but are being disputed, and the process seems likely to continue for a very long time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sansom says he is determined to see it through. He is a practical man, conveying a passionate sense of mission. In 21 months in Eket, he has been struck by the poverty, the lack of family planning, the absence of state investment, the desperation. ''I want to do more than hold the line,'' he said.</p>
        <p>He spends hours with community leaders seeking middle ground. He is determined to maintain or increase the money that Mobil spends annually on community projects.</p>
        <p>''Planned parenthood is one key,'' he said. ''I had two women in my office the other day with 28 children. Another key is diversification.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sansom's dreams of a better delta appear to have found an echo. Despite the flood of claims, chiefs in the surrounding villages described him as popular.</p>
        <p>''Denny is admired,'' Mr. Ikot, the fisherman, said, ''because he likes to engage in dialogue and he has some good ideas to produce electricity and bring in investors and use the model that made Texas rich. Even if he's not on our side, we feel he is.''</p>
        <p>The other factor that helps maintain a tenuous peace is clearly the precedent of the Ogoni, whose region has been hard hit.</p>
        <p>''That was a warning to us,'' said Mr. Ukocho, the community leader, who like most people around Eket is a member of the Ibibio ethnic group. ''The military almost wiped them out. So now we think twice about taking the law into our own hands.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
