<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Television;   New Host and New Technology, But a Familiar Oscar Show</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="338490"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACADEMY AWARDS (OSCARS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN BROADCASTING COS INC (ABC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MASLIN, JANET</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Academy Awards (Oscars)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DF1F39F93BA15750C0A966958260" item-length="1094" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Television;   New Host and New Technology, But a Familiar Oscar Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MASLIN, JANET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Advice to Oscar the Diplomat: stay home. The effort to make this year's Academy Awards show an international media miracle led to nothing but headaches. Beyond opening up whole new worlds of triple feedback (from a malfunctioning microphone in Moscow) and global indiscretion (''Don't Cry for Me, Argentina'' was not the ideal musical lead-in for the show's Buenos Aires segment), the scheme to connect Hollywood with these and other capitals fell flat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Advice to Oscar the Diplomat: stay home. The effort to make this year's Academy Awards show an international media miracle led to nothing but headaches. Beyond opening up whole new worlds of triple feedback (from a malfunctioning microphone in Moscow) and global indiscretion (''Don't Cry for Me, Argentina'' was not the ideal musical lead-in for the show's Buenos Aires segment), the scheme to connect Hollywood with these and other capitals fell flat.</p>
        <p>Advice to Oscar the Diplomat: stay home. The effort to make this year's Academy Awards show an international media miracle led to nothing but headaches. Beyond opening up whole new worlds of triple feedback (from a malfunctioning microphone in Moscow) and global indiscretion (''Don't Cry for Me, Argentina'' was not the ideal musical lead-in for the show's Buenos Aires segment), the scheme to connect Hollywood with these and other capitals fell flat. The Oscar show's special commercials said it better, from Coca-Cola's ''I'd Like to Teach the World to Sing'' to an ode to ''food, folks and fun'' in honor of McGlasnost.</p>
        <p>This new arrangement created a few firsts, as when Natalya Negoda, with Jack Lemmon in Moscow, became the first Soviet actress to squeal delightedly as she opened an envelope and read the winner's name. And it did take a terrible human toll: an unidentified, weary-looking group of revelers had been assembled at 3:30 A.M., London time, for the sole purpose of watching Glenn Close and Mel Gibson spend a minute or two on camera. Otherwise, the globe-circling strategy contributed very little to a generally well-managed evening, though it did serve as fodder for some of the show's more wickedly funny presenters. ''We were going to go live from Malaysia,'' Steve Martin said, ''but the TV crew was hanged at the airport.''</p>
        <p>Billy Crystal, who made a graceful, quick-witted host and deserves tenure in the job, set the evening's comic tone with his opening monologue. Eager to err on the side of nastiness for the sake of a good laugh, Mr. Crystal trampled toes with various ethnic wisecracks but still managed to be thoroughly entertaining. Jack Nicholson ''is so rich Morgan Freeman drove him here tonight,'' he said. ''Jack is so rich Jon Peters still cuts his hair.'' Later in the evening, Mr. Crystal insisted that the nonexistent ''lovely young lady who presents me with these Oscars is, of course, Mr. Salman Rushdie.''</p>
        <p>It appeared, at first, as if the evening would never rise even to this comic pitch. In the wake of last year's debacle a more sedate approach was clearly to be expected, but the opening shots of ''the beautiful Isabelle Adjani,'' ''the very funny Chevy Chase'' and ''the ever-popular Tom Selleck'' warned ominously that the much-too-gracious Oscar might be up to his same old tricks. A commencement-style greeting from Karl Malden, president of the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences, complete with joking reference to his American Express ads and two exclamations of ''What a world,'' was equally worrisome. And the five-minute compilation of 330 film clips, juxtaposing ''The 400 Blows'' with ''Mary Poppins'' and a dance from ''Zorba the Greek'' with the one in ''Big,'' seemed a dizzying homage not to the movies but to MTV.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crystal saved the day by asking, ''Where's that big, terrible number that usually opens the Oscars?'' and then delivering a one-man parody (''Gee, but it's great in a segregated state, driving Miss Daisy back home,'' he crooned). This was by far the best musical number of the evening, since the raucous ''Little Mermaid'' sequence choreographed by Paula Abdul (complete with dancing frogmen in flippers) was wildly out of touch with the spirit of that film, and since the best-costume extravaganza featured a break-dancing chauffeur and twisting old lady in its ''Driving Miss Daisy'' segment. This alone was enough to bring back a flood of awful Oscar memories, and to foster an appreciation of the restraint imposed by this year's producer, Gilbert Cates.</p>
        <p>Luckily, the show was not without its verbal gaffes and weird fashion statements. Kim Basinger managed to provide one of each. Championing Spike Lee's overlooked ''Do the Right Thing,'' she declared, ''Ironically, it might tell the biggest truth of all''; no one applauded. Ms. Basinger reflected the influence of her friend Prince by wearing a white satin dress that was shirt-collared on one side, strapless on the other and Good Witch Glinda from the waist down. Mr. Lee sat calmly in the audience and was the evening's best sport, simply by virtue of having shown up.</p>
        <p>One of the evening's greatest and most gratifying novelties was its large number of well-chosen winners. The academy, having made a record number of inexcusable omissions in the nominating process, seemed to have come inexplicably to its senses. Only the best original screenplay award to ''Dead Poets Society'' (over screenplays by Mr. Lee, Steven Soderbergh and Woody Allen), recalled Oscar voting at its most irrational. Morgan Freeman, who appeared likely to win the best-actor Oscar that went instead to Daniel Day-Lewis, was an especially worthy and gracious nonwinning nominee.</p>
        <p>The evening included a tribute to Akira Kurosawa, marked by birthday greetings from Tokyo, an incoherent film montage and the director's humble declaration that ''I really feel that I haven't yet grasped the essence of cinema.'' The Jean Hersholt Humanitarian Award went to the producer Howard Koch, who thanked a record number of grandchildren. Among the more distinguished presenters were Martin Scorsese and Robert De Niro, introduced by a lovely cinematic tribute to their longtime collaboration, and Jack Nicholson and Warren Beatty, who presented the award for best picture. On the other end of the spectrum was Arnold Schwarzenegger, who looked phenomenally uncomfortable.</p>
        <p>The evening's best acceptance speech came from the cinematographer Freddie Francis (''God bless you, we love you all and we're available from September''). Geena Davis, in drop-dead red, had the evening's best dress (though Melanie Griffith and Michelle Pfeiffer, both in black, looked particularly chic). Jodie Foster, last year's best-actress winner, had a becoming new haircut and color, Jane Fonda had a becoming new shape. The evening's most beautiful presence was easily its 80-year-old best-actress winner, Jessica Tandy.</p>
        <p>The night's most gratuitious moment: Diana Ross's 12:25 A.M. rendition of ''Somewhere Over the Rainbow'' (''Sing with me, Los Angeles!''). Its most reassuring one: when Charlton Heston tried to pronounce a word and couldn't. Mr. Heston's purpose, on a night like this, was to represent Hollywood at its most traditional. He shouldn't have had to say ''lambada,'' anyhow.</p>
        <p>AROUND THE WORLD IN 3 1/2 HOURS - THE 62D ANNUAL ACADEMY AWARDS PRESENTATION, directed by Jeff Margolis; Paula Abdul, choreographer; produced by Gilbert Cates for the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences; Billy Crystal, host. On ABC Monday at 9 P.M.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
