<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Children</title>
    <meta content="30KIDS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="For Children" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="874191"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="For Children"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor Day</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leimbach, Dulcie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entertainment and Amusements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960830T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E0DD1F39F933A0575BC0A960958260" item-length="1290" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dulcie Leimbach</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leimbach, Dulcie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some cultural events for children in New York City area over Labor Day weekend noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'Bats'  'Masters of the Night'  Liberty Science Center  251 Phillip Street  Jersey City, N.J.  (201) 451-0006  Recommended ages: 2 and up  Through Sept. 8</p>
        <p>Bats are neither vampires nor blind, and they don't get caught in your hair. So throw away those myths. Bats do, however, hang upside down, which makes them all the more bizarre. Do they hang that way, 7-year-old Dylan Warren asked recently, because it's cool or something?</p>
        <p>He found out at the end of this exhibition, in a recreated bat cave. Bats' curling toes lock them in precarious places, and they are counterbalanced by their upside-down weight. You also see two real Egyptian-fruit bats, zooming back and forth in a display case in which a special lighting system has reversed day and night. You'll learn an awful lot about these mammals by the time you leave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'Bats'  'Masters of the Night'  Liberty Science Center  251 Phillip Street  Jersey City, N.J.  (201) 451-0006  Recommended ages: 2 and up  Through Sept. 8</p>
        <p>Bats are neither vampires nor blind, and they don't get caught in your hair. So throw away those myths. Bats do, however, hang upside down, which makes them all the more bizarre. Do they hang that way, 7-year-old Dylan Warren asked recently, because it's cool or something?</p>
        <p>He found out at the end of this exhibition, in a recreated bat cave. Bats' curling toes lock them in precarious places, and they are counterbalanced by their upside-down weight. You also see two real Egyptian-fruit bats, zooming back and forth in a display case in which a special lighting system has reversed day and night. You'll learn an awful lot about these mammals by the time you leave.</p>
        <p>The tour begins at a Gothic-style portal that depicts bats in folklore and dispels those silly myths. The next gallery is peppered with photographs of the many different types of bats, like the wrinkled-face bat, the vampire bat, the sword-nose bat and the hammer-headed fruit bat, none of which would win a beauty contest.</p>
        <p>To learn about echolocation, or how bats navigate and locate objects by emitting sound waves, you can try on a pair of oversize bat ears. A puzzle challenges you to match the bat face with the description. A video shows bats swooshing down on their prey. A hollowed-out, fake silk-cotton tree gives you an idea of where bats go when caves aren't around. If you want to pretend you're a bat, you can stand in a display mount and flex your arms bat-style.</p>
        <p>But before you go home packed with bat knowledge, be sure to ride the glass elevator to the science center's second floor and peruse the exhibition on health. You can test your physical endurance (which you will need for an afternoon here with children) by hanging on a bar. Then again, you might not want to know how little endurance you have left.  Children, of course, always have plenty.</p>
        <p>The museum's hours are 9:30 A.M. to 5:30 P.M., Tuesdays through Sundays. Admission to the exhibition  halls is $9.50 for adults and $6.50 for  ages 2 to 12; there is an additional charge for the Omni and 3-D theaters. From Manhattan, you can take a ferry from the World Financial Center ($4 round trip for anyone over 6) that connects with a free shuttle bus in the Colgate Clock terminal parking lot in Jersey City. Not a bad way to get around, even for a bat.</p>
        <p>'You're an Animated Classic, Charlie Brown'  'The Artistry of Charles M. Schulz'  Museum of Television and Radio  25 West 52d Street  Manhattan  (212) 621-6800  Recommended ages: 4 and up  Through Jan. 12</p>
        <p>Charlie Brown was a real person, but he didn't have an overbearing psychological adviser named Lucy.  When Charles M. Schulz, the creator of the Charlie Brown character and the cartoon strip ''Peanuts,'' was teaching at Art Instruction Inc., a correspondence school for commercial artists in Minneapolis, he ''borrowed'' a colleague's name, and the character Charlie Brown was born.</p>
        <p>This happened in the late 1940's.</p>
        <p>The real Charlie Brown ''liked a good time, going to parties,'' Mr. Schulz said in a telephone interview from Santa Rosa, Calif., where he lives.</p>
        <p>He says the invented character does not have the real man's personality. ''He and I were very close,'' he said. ''I would never do that.'' But he conceded that his onetime colleague, like the pretend Charlie Brown, had a round, plain face.</p>
        <p>In this exhibition, that chubby, hairless face stares benignly from  the walls, and you never get tired of it. Mr. Schulz recalled worrying that United Features Syndicate, which introduced ''Peanuts'' in 1950, would think the name Charlie Brown was dumb; in hindsight, it seems that no other name could ever fit.</p>
        <p>Tracing the leap from black-and-white cartoon strips to animation cels and, eventually, to television, with examples of all three, this exhibition links you closely to Mr. Schulz's work and characters. The process of how the seemingly simple drawings, with their daft humor and air of noble eccentricity, evolved into  animated characters is not the point of this exhibition. It's more about Mr. Schulz's art (even if he does calls it ''lowly.'')</p>
        <p>Here is the ''Peanuts'' crew in scenes from ''It's the Great Pumpkin, Charlie Brown,'' the animation cels from 1966 bringing these lives into full color and letting you see the difference from the black-and-white version. There are also cels and cartoon strips from other shows, with  three television sets running the same video simultaneously.</p>
        <p>During one visit, snatches of a program were a reminder of the  grammatical value of Charlie Brown, especially when he asks Lucy, ''From whom are you expecting a call?'' The exhibition is small, and afterward you can watch a full ''Peanuts'' program in a viewing room. The museum's hours are Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Saturdays and Sundays, noon to 6 P.M.; Thursdays, noon to 8 P.M., and Fridays, noon to 9 P.M. Admission is $6 for adults and $3 for children under 13.</p>
        <p>World's Fair Marina  126th Street and Northern Boulevard  Flushing, Queens  (718) 478-0480  Recommended for all ages</p>
        <p>There is no problem sighting big, blue Shea Stadium from Northern Boulevard in Queens, but if you're heading west and glance in the other direction, you may be surprised to see a sign for ''sunset boat rides'' and a tiny marina that from a distance looks as if it's entangled in highways. It's actually in water -- Flushing Bay -- and if you get off Northern Boulevard at the World's Fair Marina (westbound), you will get there. Like Emerald City, it only appears out of reach.</p>
        <p>The marina has a long pier with party cruise boats the size of mansions. These are mostly dinner cruises for grown-ups. The fees on the Marco Polo cruises are $39 a person on Fridays and Saturdays (the other nights are for singles and moonlight cruises), so you might just want to stick with gawking at the boats and not going aboard. There is a snack bar where you can grab a hot dog and soda. But what you're really here to see is in the sky: airplanes taking off from La Guardia Airport, right behind the pier. (You don't need to walk on the pier to see the aerial spectacle.)</p>
        <p>At sunset, the planes' ascent resembles a theatrical production. During the day it's just as exciting, as planes ritually swoop down the tarmac and bolt into the sky. In a matter of a half-hour or so, we watched US Air, Continental, Delta and American Airlines send planes into the clear blue sky, taking our breath away. Farther beyond, planes are landing, but their descents can't compete with the planes bound for far-off places.</p>
        <p>There are two parking lots, but on a recent Sunday we were stopped by a man at one entrance who told us we couldn't park unless we were going on a boat. So we pretended we were partygoers. Later, a call was made to Vincent Coccoli, the manager of the marina, who said anyone was permitted to park in these lots.</p>
        <p>The marina is part of the New York Department of Parks and Recreation and is bordered by a crescent-shaped park where families encamp with picnics and appreciate the view. This is a little-known spot in a well-trod city. Try to find it and sit for a while.</p>
        <p>For Children</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
