<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Evidence of Explosive So Far in Crash Inquiry</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="866957"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIRLINES AND AIRPLANES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOMBS AND BOMB PLOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SABOTAGE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONG ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRANS WORLD AIRLINES (TWA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURDY, MATTHEW</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PATAKI, GEORGE E (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sabotage</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E4D61639F937A15754C0A960958260" item-length="1813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Evidence of Explosive So Far in Crash Inquiry</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATTHEW PURDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURDY, MATTHEW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Investigators examining the small amount of wreckage recovered so far from the crash of Trans World Airlines Flight 800 said yesterday that they had not yet found any concrete evidence that the plane was destroyed by an explosive device.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Investigators examining the small amount of wreckage recovered so far from the crash of Trans World Airlines Flight 800 said yesterday that they had not yet found any concrete evidence that the plane was destroyed by an explosive device.</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters yesterday evening, President Clinton said investigators were making progress, but he added: "We must not draw conclusions until we're sure the conclusion is supported by the facts. And I cannot say that I've learned anything today which enables me to give you a definite conclusion about  the cause of the accident."</p>
        <p>Law enforcement officials on Long Island continued to maintain that circumstantial evidence suggested that the 747 jetliner crashed because of an act of either political terrorism or sabotage. And they said they expected to have a clearer sense of what caused the plane to explode last Wednesday night when they begin recovering large sections of the wreckage, possibly as early as  today.</p>
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki said the first priority was to recover the "dozens and  dozens" of bodies that divers had found trapped in large sections of the fuselage resting on the bottom of the ocean. He estimated that the divers had found 60 to 100 bodies, which could account for most of the 122 bodies that have not been recovered.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Pataki's announcement, there were conflicting statements from other officials last night.</p>
        <p>Robert Francis, the vice chairman of the National Transportation Safety Board, said there were no bodies in the wreckage that had not been recovered.</p>
        <p>But a Federal official in East Moriches, L.I., who spoke on the condition of  anonymity, confirmed that there were dozens of bodies still on the ocean floor.</p>
        <p>And early today, James K. Kallstrom, assistant F.B.I. director for the New York office, said: "Given the fact that a portion of the fuselage has been discovered, and that the search team has apparently located a large debris field in the same area, we have every hope and expectation of finding and recovering a significant number of victims soon."</p>
        <p>The accounts angered family members staying at the Ramada Plaza Hotel at Kennedy International Airport, who told reporters late last night that they were frustrated by the contradictions.</p>
        <p>So far, the remains of 108 of the 230 people on board the New York to Paris flight have been recovered, and 77 bodies have been identified.</p>
        <p>At the crash site off the coast of Suffolk County on Long Island, recovery workers brought up three more bodies yesterday and continued sonar mapping of the ocean floor in preparation for the enormous task of disentangling bodies from the wreckage, bringing them to the surface and then raising the pieces of the airplane.</p>
        <p>"Raising the remains, identifying the bodies is a top priority," the Governor said. "We believe there will be dozens and dozens of bodies that will be identified and returned."</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki said the second task would be to recover the large pieces of the plane, which he said would help solve the mystery of what made the airplane explode at an altitude of 13,700 feet shortly after it took off for Paris.</p>
        <p>Law enforcement officials, who from the beginning suspected that the plane had been destroyed by an explosive device, said yesterday that further tests for traces of explosives from a piece of the airplane's wing had not yet produced any evidence of such traces. On Monday, when law enforcement agents on Long Island tested a residue found on the underside of the wing segment, they first found traces of an explosive, but in a later test with different equipment, no traces were detected.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, when the residue was tested with more sophisticated equipment at the Federal Bureau of Investigation laboratory in Quantico, Va., once again no explosive traces were found on this or any other piece of wreckage that had been retrieved.</p>
        <p>"Right now," a senior law enforcement official said, "we just don't have enough pieces of metal to make a judgment about the cause of the crash. Not today and maybe not tomorrow."</p>
        <p>Even as the crash inquiry remains classified as an accident investigation, the F.B.I. is investigating various criminal theories. And Zachary W. Carter, the United States Attorney for the Eastern District of New York, has assigned prosecutors and investigators, led by Valerie Caproni, head of the criminal division, to monitor the case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kallstrom, said yesterday that the F.B.I. had already conducted 1,300 interviews on the crash. "We're looking at everybody that touched that aircraft," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kallstrom said that two working criminal theories were that the plane was destroyed by a bomb or a missile and that "there's circumstantial evidence pointing in those directions."</p>
        <p>Kenneth Bacon, the Defense Department's chief spokesman, cast some doubt on the possibility of a missile. He said that satellite photographs and radar data  offered no evidence of a missile strike on the plane. He said that apart from the accounts of eyewitnesses who described a streak of light near the 747 before the explosion, there was "precious else" to suggest that a missile had hit the plane.</p>
        <p>But he told reporters that the Defense Department and other Federal agencies  had left open the possibility of a missile, possibly fired from a boat. "Could it have been fired from the water?" he said. "That is the question that they're  looking into."</p>
        <p>Investigators, however, say they are waiting to examine the airplane before ruling in or out any theories -- mechanical or criminal. And even though little  physical evidence has been recovered so far, the F.B.I. is scouring it for potential leads. Yesterday, investigators flew a 30-foot section of one wing to  Washington for laboratory analysis by the F.B.I. and the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms. And other pieces of the plane have been sent to Washington for testing.</p>
        <p>Recovering the bodies and the airplane wreckage from more than 100 feet below the surface of the ocean requires synchronizing the activities of dozens of boats and hundreds of recovery workers.</p>
        <p>The large fields of debris -- one measuring a mile and a half by a half mile  -- have been found by boats towing sonar equipment back and forth across a 500-square-mile area over the last six days. So far, the debris has been examined by scuba divers using hand-held video camera. The divers, wearing tanks and mask, can stay at the bottom for only five minutes, although using a portable decompression unit, they can stay under water up to 90 minutes.</p>
        <p>Once the pieces of the airplane are recovered, they will be taken to a former Grumman plant in Calverton, L.I, where investigators will try to roughly reassemble the plane and conduct chemical and metallurgical tests on the pieces  to try to determine the cause of the explosion.</p>
        <p>As one indication of how difficult it is to make precise determinations from  the wreckage, investigators noted that some of the bodies were covered with a metallic substance they could not immediately identify, which turned out to be theatrical glitter that was being shipped to Paris aboard the plane.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the slivers of evidence that have emerged continue to alternate between pointing toward and away from the theory that the plane was destroyed by an explosive device -- either a bomb or a missile launched from below.</p>
        <p>Investigators said they had fully examined the list of passengers aboard the  plane and had found nothing to indicate that any were using fake names or otherwise raised suspicions that they might be involved in a bombing.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey H. Erickson, the chief executive of T.W.A., said that according to information he received from people who reviewed satellite images and radar tapes from the time of the crash, "it appeared that the plane broke in two and one of the wings came off."</p>
        <p>Mr. Erickson said while some problem with the maintenance of the plane "has yet to be excluded as the cause," it was "less likely."</p>
        <p>The major work of recovering the dozens of bodies found in the debris will be performed by so-called hard-hat divers, who wear hard helmets and are supported  by oxygen flowing through tubes from a boat above. Those divers, officials said, can work for hours below the surface, unlike the more lightly equipped divers at work yesterday.</p>
        <p>But the equipment used by the hard-hat divers interferes with the operation of the sonar mechanisms. Therefore, those divers cannot begin working until recovery workers finish mapping the floor of the ocean, which is expected to be  completed by this morning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki said he could not say when the bodies would be recovered because "it depends on everything from the weather to the ability to finish the mapping."</p>
        <p>When the workers begin the recovery efforts, the main vessel to be used will  be a Navy combat salvage ship called the Grasp, which travels with 23 hard-hat divers and is outfitted with a crane that can hoist objects weighing up to 40 tons.</p>
        <p>In addition, a 609-foot Navy amphibious support ship, the Oak Hill, left Norfolk yesterday for the 24-hour voyage to the crash site, where it will act as a floating base of operations for the recovery effort. That ship, by far the largest of the more than two dozen vessels involved in the search and recovery mission, is big enough to be used as a landing pad for helicopters, which will be used to ferry workers and bodies to the shore.</p>
        <p>"It gives us a logistical platform out there," said Lieut. Comdr. Gordon Hume, a Navy spokesman.</p>
        <p>The tension between drawing a conclusion about an explosive device and withholding judgment was evident at the highest reaches of the Government yesterday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton made his remarks cautioning against drawing conclusions without solid evidence just hours after after his chief of staff, Leon Panetta, told reporters traveling on Air Force One that terrorism was the explanation for the  crash that investigators were "looking at most closely." And he said "chemical leftovers" were recovered from the crash site that the F.B.I. wanted to examine  further. But the White House quickly backed away from Mr. Panetta's remarks.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
