<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taiwan Keeps a Step Ahead of China in U.S. Lobbying</title>
    <meta content="14LOBB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="915431"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taiwan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lilley, James R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kissinger, Henry A (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Haig, Alexander</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eagleburger, Lawrence S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zuckerman, Laurence</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Taiwan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Year</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1D91E39F937A25750C0A961958260" item-length="1222" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taiwan Keeps a Step Ahead of China in U.S. Lobbying</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURENCE ZUCKERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zuckerman, Laurence</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Taiwan has developed one of most effective lobbies in Washington, to exasperation of China; appearance by Pres Clinton and Vice Pres Gore and their wives at Taiwan's New Year party noted; China's efforts to match intricate network is central to controversy over illegal contributions to Democrats in last election; former Amb James Lilley notes China has long history of interfering in other countries, although one lobbyist puts down efforts; China does have network of former officials like Henry Kissinger, Alexander Haig and Lawrence Eagleburger, who act as unofficial lobbyists and then parlay China connections into work as consultants (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last month, President Clinton, Vice President Al Gore and their wives dropped in on a party at a restaurant in Chinatown here to help usher in the Chinese Year of the Ox. Among the cheering crowd that greeted them was Jason Hu, Taiwan's unofficial ambassador to the United States.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Hu did not talk to the President or the Vice President that night, and the White House said this week that Mr. Clinton was not aware that Mr. Hu was at the restaurant, the fact that the three of them were briefly in the same room was a diplomatic coup for Taiwan, which is not officially recognized by Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Last month, President Clinton, Vice President Al Gore and their wives dropped in on a party at a restaurant in Chinatown here to help usher in the Chinese Year of the Ox. Among the cheering crowd that greeted them was Jason Hu, Taiwan's unofficial ambassador to the United States.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Hu did not talk to the President or the Vice President that night, and the White House said this week that Mr. Clinton was not aware that Mr. Hu was at the restaurant, the fact that the three of them were briefly in the same room was a diplomatic coup for Taiwan, which is not officially recognized by Washington.</p>
        <p>The symbolism was not lost on China, which considers Taiwan to be a wayward province and has long viewed it as its chief rival for influence in Washington.</p>
        <p>''Why didn't the President come to our party?'' asked an exasperated Chinese Embassy official who spoke on the condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>China's efforts to match the intricate network of supporters that has made Taiwan one of the most effective lobbies in Washington is central to the expanding controversy surrounding illegal campaign donations to Democrats in the last election.</p>
        <p>Federal officials said they began investigating whether China was making covert efforts to influence American politicians early last year after the National Security Agency overheard Chinese officials expressing their desire to counter Taiwan's influence. Earlier this week, several Democrats in Congress said the Federal Bureau of Investigation warned them in June that the Chinese Government might try to funnel illegal donations to their campaigns.</p>
        <p>Chinese officials have strongly disputed the accusations that they made illegal contributions, calling them ''groundless.'' But there is no doubt that the Chinese Embassy here has increased its lobbying efforts in recent years.</p>
        <p>The need for a more aggressive effort was driven home in June 1995, when Taiwan's President, Lee Teng-Hui, was allowed to attend his class reunion at Cornell University, the first time a Taiwanese President had visited the United States since the latter broke off relations with Taiwan in 1979 and recognized China. Although the White House had assured China that Mr. Lee would not be issued a visa, it was forced to change course after Congress overwhelmingly passed a resolution urging Mr. Clinton to allow the visit.</p>
        <p>The Chinese Embassy has since increased the number of people who lobby Congress and appointed Shao Wenguang, an urbane graduate of both Oxford University and the Fletcher School of Diplomacy at Tufts University, as its new head of Congressional liaison.</p>
        <p>James Lilley, a former American Ambassador in Beijing and a veteran of 27 years at the Central Intelligence Agency, said China had a long record of interfering in the affairs of other countries.</p>
        <p>''They've been kicked out of more countries in Africa than we have,'' Mr. Lilley said. ''They've been at it all the time, influencing people with guns, politics and money.''</p>
        <p>But many China watchers find the current focus on Beijing's activities curious, given Taiwan's long history of aggressive and sometimes questionable lobbying activities. Some suggest that Federal agencies may look the other way at Taiwan's efforts to influence American policy.</p>
        <p>Taiwan regards American domestic politics as a question of national security and has done so for years. It studies the United States intensively  and has brought hundreds of American politicians, journalists, academics and other opinion leaders to Taiwan on free visits. As an indication of the broad sweep of Taiwan's effort, a young Arkansas Governor, Bill Clinton, visited Taiwan four times but never once went to China.</p>
        <p>''The Chinese are the weakest embassy in Washington,'' said one industry representative who requested anonymity. ''That is why it is so laughable that they are orchestrating some elaborate campaign.''</p>
        <p>Even before the Taiwan President's visit, China's supporters here and abroad had been urging Beijing to beef up its lobbying. Unlike Taiwan and many other countries, China has been reluctant to hire professional lobbyists to promote its interests. But as a nuclear power, home to one-fifth of the world's people, and the world's fastest-growing economy, China has won many friends in Washington in recent years.</p>
        <p>On major economic issues, like China's trading privileges with the United States, there has been little need for Chinese officials to lobby because their cause has been championed by a broad network of large corporations, including Boeing, International Business Machines and Motorola, that do business in China. In addition, Hong Kong Chinese tycoons and even Hong Kong's colonial government, have lobbied on behalf of China because much of Hong Kong's wealth is derived from China's rapidly expanding exports.</p>
        <p>China also has a network of former high-ranking American officials, including former Secretaries of State Henry A. Kissinger, Alexander M. Haig Jr. and Lawrence S. Eagleburger, who act as unofficial lobbyists and then parlay their China connections as private consultants to businesses and foreign governments.</p>
        <p>But despite its rising influence in Washington, China has been irritated by the fact that Taiwan's influence in the capital has not diminished in equal measure.</p>
        <p>Taiwan has been adroit at making its voice heard, despite being hobbled by its lack of official recognition. The report about allegations of Chinese influence buying, which first appeared in The Washington Post, put the total amount at about $2 million. That is less than half what the Taiwan Research Institute, a private organization closely allied with Taiwan's governing party, is paying Cassidy &amp; Associates, a Washington lobbying firm that has been widely credited with getting Mr. Lee his visa.</p>
        <p>Taiwan also employs numerous other lobbyists and knows the legal ways to curry favor with influential members of Congress. In 1993, for example, Taiwan donated $225,000 to a foundation that supports a museum dedicated to the career of Senator Jesse Helms, the North Carolina Republican who heads the Senate Foreign Relations Committee.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, an official in Taiwan told The Los Angeles Times that the island's unofficial embassy in Washington helped its friends in Congress by supplying them with lists of Taiwanese-Americans in their districts whom they could target for fund-raising. The Taiwan Economic and Cultural Representative Office denied that it was engaged in such activities, which in any case would be legal if the contributors were legal United States residents.</p>
        <p>The only overseas fund-raising trip made by John Huang, the former Commerce Department and Democratic National Committee official now at the center of the campaign fund-raising furor, was to Taiwan last May.</p>
        <p>Because of Washington's long history of support for the Chinese Nationalist Party during World War II and the cold war, the F.B.I and American counterintelligence agencies do not scrutinize Taiwan's activities here, said Roger Sullivan, who was a China specialist on the National Security Council in the Carter Administration.</p>
        <p>''There are all sorts of guys in the military and at the bureau who think they are the good guys,'' Mr. Sullivan said, referring to Taiwan. ''In my time it was very difficult to get anyone to focus on what they were doing. How much is anyone watching them even now? Probably not that much.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
