<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cooking</title>
    <meta content="08COOKINT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/08/books/review/08COOKINT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1446663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Holiday Books"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garner, Dwight</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0DF1338F93BA35751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="3982" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cooking</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cooking</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dwight Garner</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Garner, Dwight</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dwight Garner reviews selection of cookbooks; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a strange phenomenon but a true one: sometimes there's nothing like reading a pile of gleaming new cookbooks to put you off your feed. It's not that most cookbooks are badly written and killingly earnest, though they are. It's not that you can usually find better versions of most of the ''new'' recipes in older cookbooks (probably ones you already own), though you can. The real problem is one that I couldn't put my finger on until I stumbled across my copy of Phillip Lopate's 1989 book ''Against Joie de Vivre.''</p>
        <p>Lopate, of course, is not opposed to the ''hearty enjoyment of life.'' What bugs him is ''the stylization of this private condition into a bullying social ritual'' -- a kind of bullying that cookbook writers have turned into an art form. Lopate tends to blame the French for a lot of the ''professional joie de vivrism'' going on out there. But, he adds, ''the whole Mediterranean'' seems to be full of it: ''The Italians export dolce far niente as aggressively as tomato paste. For the Greeks, a Zorba dance to life has supplanted classical antiquities as their main touristic lure.'' (Fortunately, Lopate adds, Greece still ''has its share of thin, nervous, bitter types.'')</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There's a problem with a lot of food books: the recipes steer clear of canned ingredients, but the "atmosphere" is ladled right out of a 10-gallon jar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a strange phenomenon but a true one: sometimes there's nothing like reading a pile of gleaming new cookbooks to put you off your feed. It's not that most cookbooks are badly written and killingly earnest, though they are. It's not that you can usually find better versions of most of the ''new'' recipes in older cookbooks (probably ones you already own), though you can. The real problem is one that I couldn't put my finger on until I stumbled across my copy of Phillip Lopate's 1989 book ''Against Joie de Vivre.''</p>
        <p>Lopate, of course, is not opposed to the ''hearty enjoyment of life.'' What bugs him is ''the stylization of this private condition into a bullying social ritual'' -- a kind of bullying that cookbook writers have turned into an art form. Lopate tends to blame the French for a lot of the ''professional joie de vivrism'' going on out there. But, he adds, ''the whole Mediterranean'' seems to be full of it: ''The Italians export dolce far niente as aggressively as tomato paste. For the Greeks, a Zorba dance to life has supplanted classical antiquities as their main touristic lure.'' (Fortunately, Lopate adds, Greece still ''has its share of thin, nervous, bitter types.'')</p>
        <p>Lopate isn't a food writer, but he's tapped into a problem with a lot of food books: the recipes steer clear of canned ingredients, but the ''atmosphere'' is ladled right out of a 10-gallon jar. The worst offenders these days tend to be those writers who dive deeply into rustic foreign cuisines. For one thing, they crank out travel-brochure copy by the yard. ''We drive past Alberobello, with its conical homes, through towns where women huddle, making pasta by hand, red cherry tomatoes hanging over door frames,'' Micol Negrin writes in RUSTICO (Clarkson Potter, $35), her otherwise perfectly decent new regional Italian cookbook. ''The kaleidoscope of colors, the unmistakable sounds of families feasting and arguing, even the brilliant light are unabashedly Mediterranean. We have entered southern Italy.'' We have also entered a hazardous kitsch zone. ''A Marseillais may consume an outstanding piece of fish without a single herb, spice or grain of salt,'' Daniel Young says in MADE IN MARSEILLE (HarperCollins, $32.50). ''But a good fish tale never passes between his lips without savory embellishment.'' Young's book happens to be full of first-rate bouillabaisse recipes; it's his prose that makes you want to hit the nearest K.F.C. drive-in for a bucket of greasy wings.</p>
        <p>Negrin and Young's books stand in here for dozens of others. You can love hearty peasant food and agree that tradition is a good thing and yet still cringe at the way so many food writers cheerfully condescend to the small-time cheese, sausage and bread makers they ''discover'' in out-of-the-way villages. (Is there one of these locals, male or female, who isn't a big-hearted sage with twinkly eyes?) Happily, the cookbook writers who focus on American food producers have a harder time whipping themselves into folknik frenzies. Over here, that artisanal cheese maker probably has a trust fund and an art history degree from Yale.</p>
        <p>The best advice this season for anyone who wants to avoid the professional joie de vivrists can be boiled down into an unlikely sound bite: buy British. In particular, look for a copy of Nigel Slater's APPETITE: So What Do You Want to Eat Today? (Clarkson Potter, $35). Slater contributes a terrific column to The Observer in London, and his writing could not be more palate-cleansing -- his acidic riffs put you in mind of Nick Hornby, Martin Amis and Philip Larkin all at the same time. Part of the fun of ''Appetite'' is just scanning it for the throwaway lines: ''Ignore anyone who tells you that you shouldn't drink alone''; ''Two cannot live as cheaply as one. It is a myth put about by people trying to justify a decision they have just made''; ''There is no such thing as a nice pasta salad, despite what women's magazines would have us believe.''</p>
        <p>Slater's recipes are serious and thoughtful -- his braised oxtail is a dark, sticky knockout, and his fish soup with saffron and hot pepper cured me of an oncoming cold -- but he's always on the side of the harried home cook. People who come to your house for dinner, Slater writes, are not after ''little piles of food and twee puddles of sauce''; they're after genuine home cooking. You should make a strenuous effort, he advises, but beware of crossing that invisible line: ''When some overachieving wannabe presents show-off food at home I always find there is an awkward feeling around the table -- what are we supposed to say as Julian presents us with his copy of some visual masterpiece he found in a chef's (ghostwritten) cookery book? What is he trying to prove?''</p>
        <p>Slater won me over for good with his ode to the occasional joys of take-out food. Here he is on McDonald's and Burger King: ''Your teeth sink into that soft, comforting bun and the piquant-sweet sauce squidges up, though there is never quite enough of it. The gherkin smarts on your tongue. A moment of absolute bliss. The doughy bun becomes your best friend. You chase the last bit of sauce around the polystyrene container with a stalk of warm lettuce or a cold French fry and lick the last sweet-salty blob from the corner of your mouth.'' Slater gets bonus points for admitting he even loves the ''whingeing Muzak'' in burger joints. Three cheers for a crusty but careful cookbook that doesn't sound like it was written by the combined editorial boards of The Nation, Mother Jones and N.P.R.</p>
        <p>The impression that the Brits are having more fun than everyone else is confirmed by three other new books: TEA &amp; SYMPATHY: The Life of an English Teashop in New York (Putnam, $27.50), by Anita Naughton, with 60 recipes and an introduction by Nicola Perry; NIGELLA BITES (Hyperion, $35), by Nigella Lawson; and HAPPY DAYS WITH THE NAKED CHEF (Hyperion, $34.95), by Jamie Oliver.</p>
        <p>Tea &amp; Sympathy is a West Village hole in the wall that functions, as Naughton puts it, as Manhattan's ''unofficial British embassy.'' The place is always packed with homesick Londoners who line up for antiquated and odd-sounding dishes like spotted dick, treacle pudding and bubble and squeak, as well as shepherd's pie and homey chicken soup. My wife and I lived practically across the street from Tea &amp; Sympathy for four years, but we could hardly ever elbow our way in; thank God for their often spookily deserted take-out counter. The recipes are all here, and they're all toothsome and fine. The book reads like a brisk mini-primer on old-school British cookery, one that never gets its knickers in a twist about formality.</p>
        <p>What's really winning about this book, though, is Naughton's snarky and unassuming prose style. The waiters, almost all women, tend to call one another ''selfish cow'' and issue complaints like ''No doubt she spent most of the night sitting on the customers' laps.'' My favorite moment in ''Tea &amp; Sympathy'' is when the Dalai Lama is spotted at a corner table. As word spreads, chaos ensues, and half the employees need to be reminded who he is. (''The Holy Leader of Tibet. The . . . the . . . Richard Gere's friend.'') When he finally gets up to leave, Naughton does the only sane thing a person can do: she runs over and plops down in his chair. ''It was still warm,'' she reports dreamily.</p>
        <p>Nigella Lawson and Jamie Oliver are, of course, familiar from their popular, populist television shows. (Lawson also writes a column for The Times's Dining section.) There's almost zero food theory in their books. Now that the Two Fat Ladies are gone, Lawson and Oliver have assumed their roles as cable's most appealing culinary cheerleaders. ''Nigella Bites'' is more padded than Lawson's previous books -- there's a lot of big type, big photos and even blank pages for note-taking -- but her enthusiasm is infectious and her recipes are artful spins on traditional comfort food. The only bad news is that she admits here to dabbling with low-carb diets. Say it ain't so, Nigella!</p>
        <p>Oliver's ''Happy Days With the Naked Chef'' -- imagine the sales if Nigella wrote a book with that title -- is the perfect cookbook to give the Maxim magazine reader in your life. And I don't mean that as a put-down. Oliver is committed to fresh ingredients, and his recipes work (he's particularly good with simple but surprising fish dishes), but you do have to fight upstream against all the ''lad'' chatter. Here's his take, for example, on herbs: ''They're cool -- not just cool, but very cool.'' Oliver may look like Ewan McGregor's younger brother, but he writes as if he's taking dictation from Keanu Reeves.</p>
        <p>There are few worse sins in journalism than ''burying the lede,'' and here I'm going to have to plead no contest. This year's best cookbook -- the one people are still likely to be talking about, and cooking from, 20 years down the line -- is THE ZUNI CAFE COOKBOOK (Norton, $35), by Judy Rodgers. Just opening this book up is like plunking down the needle on one of those old LP's that tells you, on first listen, that you've made a friend you're going to keep for the rest of your life.</p>
        <p>The Zuni Cafe is a lovely, unassuming triangular wedge of a restaurant that sits on the corner of Rose Alley and Market Street in San Francisco. Zuni's food is lovely and unassuming, too. (The oysters are so good that it can be hard to get past them even to look at the rest of the menu. But you must persevere.) Rodgers, the restaurant's co-owner and chef, explains in her calm, lucid introduction that she fell into the world of serious cooking by accident. When she was a high school student in St. Louis, with no particular interest in food, a neighbor arranged for her to spend a year in France. But she wouldn't be staying with just any French family, she'd be staying with the family of Jean Troisgros, one of the owners of Les Frères Troisgros, arguably the best restaurant in the country. This smart girl began taking so many notes that Troisgros nicknamed her Mata Hari.</p>
        <p>The note-taking paid off. So did the time she would later spend cooking at Alice Waters's Chez Panisse. Rodgers does so many things right that it's hard to catalog them all. Her opening essay, ''What to Think About Before You Start, and While You Are Cooking,'' is a classic of the genre -- smart and disarmingly direct. (Among her best bits of advice: ''Making even a simple dish three times in two weeks can teach you more about cooking than trying three different dishes in the same period of time.'') She is unafraid of championing novel methods -- salting proteins a day or more in advance, for example, or declining to skim the fat from stocks while they are reducing. Her recipes, thoughtfully, provide measurements in both weight and volume. (This should become standard practice in all cookbooks.)</p>
        <p>I won't lie to you: for the home cook, some of Rodgers's recipes can be headache makers. Among her mottos, she says at one point, is ''Stop, think, there must be a harder way.'' But you can work up to these. Start by making Zuni's trademark roast chicken, its devastating Caesar salad and its simple but elegant take on Argentine chimichurri sauce. (Be sure to fry some eggs in this sauce the next morning.) You'll also want to zero in on Page 322, where you'll find a recipe for sea bass with leeks, potatoes and thyme. It sounds straightforward, and it pretty much is. My wife -- a far better and more dedicated cook than I am -- made this on a whim one night, and after taking one bite we simply dropped our forks and stared at each other. This was the best thing that had ever come out of our kitchen. Our highest level of approbation, on trying a new recipe, is usually, ''I'd definitely serve this at a dinner party.'' Zuni's sea bass is something we'd serve at our last meal.</p>
        <p>Two other books by young female chefs are worth knowing about: THE ANATOMY OF A DISH (Artisan, $35), by Diane Forley with Catherine Young, and COOKING FROM A to Z (St. Martin's, $35), by Patricia Yeo and Julia Moskin. Forley is the chef and owner of Verbena, a restaurant that's an oasis of Zen calm in downtown Manhattan, and her elegant book wins this year's award for the cookbook with the best feng shui. Forley pays particularly close attention to fruits and vegetables; it is her contention, and it is a hard one to argue with, that it is the use of fruits and vegetables, along with grains and legumes, that defines ''sensibility in cooking.'' Forley's recipes are models of clarity, as well as being quite tasty. At times, though, ''The Anatomy of a Dish'' can read like a dissertation. Forley is an amateur botanist who wants to bridge ''the gap between the culinary and botanical languages,'' and her book is studded with complicated graphs and charts. Happily, you can skip these, though it is interesting to discover the link between, say, potatoes, belladonna and tobacco. (They're all part of the Solanaceae family.) Forley's tone can be as forbidding as her recitations of Latin plant names: ''Cooking is not a matter of common sense,'' she writes. ''It is a matter of understanding chemistry . . . and knowing how to plan and control outcomes.'' Yikes. This is comfort food with a Ph. D.</p>
        <p>Patricia Yeo is the executive chef at Manhattan's AZ, a temple of lively pan-Asian fusion cuisine, and she shares an academic interest with Diane Forley. (Yeo studied biochemistry at Princeton.) But Yeo, who was raised in Malaysia and attended boarding school in England, also spent many years working in Bobby Flay's restaurants, and she's been influenced by Flay's fondness for big, knock-you-sideways flavors. (I gather that she too can be forbidding: Flay tells us in an introduction that Yeo was known as ''Patricia the Enforcer'' when she worked for him.) ''Cooking From A to Z'' will be a lot of fun for those who can track down all of the sometimes mildly arcane ingredients. Yeo's dishes run the gamut from gingered hash browns to terrific curries and soups to lapsang-souchong-marinated chicken to a very fine orange mu shu duck. I made a beeline for her short ribs with a green-peppercorn-apple glaze, and was glad I did. As she skims along, Yeo tosses out a lot of nice small ideas too, like adding toasted sesame seeds to a bowl of sliced cucumbers. Yeo's British boarding school influence tends to pop out when you least expect it: she knows what to do with a chunk of Stilton.</p>
        <p>Three of New York's most celebrated male chefs -- Alain Ducasse, Daniel Boulud and Eric Ripert -- also have new cookbooks this season, and each of their books is a low-key surprise. These aren't big, formal, career-spanning summas; instead, they come at you from unexpected and sometimes welcome angles. The effect is like picking up new albums by Eddie Van Halen, Keith Richards and Slash and finding that, this time out, they're all playing acoustic guitar.</p>
        <p>THE GOOD CUISINE: 208 Recipes Easy and Inspired</p>
        <p>(Ici La Press, $30) features a tag-team assortment of recipes by both Alain Ducasse and the popular French cookbook writer Françoise Bernard, a sort of no-fuss French Julia Child. They're an odd couple, but an engaging one. In this book, they single out 52 of the most frequently eaten foods in France, and then each cook supplies two recipes for each food. Part of the fun here is reading the comments -- sometimes amusingly tetchy -- that one posts after the other's recipe. ''I never cook this type of dish, in which the taste of the main ingredient disappears beneath a strong sauce,'' Ducasse sniffs at the bottom of Bernard's recipe for salmon loaf with shrimp sauce. Even if ''The Good Cuisine'' can read like a foodie version of ''Crossfire,'' these two cooks seem genuinely to like and respect each other. My only complaint is the book's hideously small type.</p>
        <p>The cover of CHEF DANIEL BOULUD: Cooking in New York City (Assouline, $34.95) gives us a photo of Boulud on a Manhattan street preparing to chomp into a hot dog, and his book is a mostly winning attempt to humanize both the chef and his three New York restaurants. I could have done without Peter Kaminsky's sometimes wackily overwrought text, which can sound like movie-trailer writing: ''In the city that never sleeps there is a chef who barely sleeps: a bespectacled dynamo who speaks rock-and-roll slang with a thick Lyonnaise accent and who serves forth exquisite renditions of French country fare alongside modern fantasies of global culture.'' Look, up in the sky! It's Chefman!</p>
        <p>Boulud's recipes are brilliant, though -- from the marinated pork shoulder with an herb spice crust that was developed by one his sous-chefs (Boulud aptly calls it ''Burgundy meets Memphis'') to more classic pâtés and dishes like rosemary braised veal shank. One puzzling thing, though, is the way Boulud praises various dishes and then doesn't tell us how to make them. We get mouth-watering photos of two ''staff meal'' dishes -- a beet-cured salmon and a ''steakhouse'' pizza -- but only very general descriptions of how they are prepared. And Boulud devotes two pages to a glistening photo and a description of his famous</p>
        <p>''DB burger,'' the hamburger stuffed with foie gras and truffles that's the signature dish at his DB Bistro Moderne. You guessed it: no recipe. This bespectacled superhero is as secretive as he is dynamic.</p>
        <p>Eric Ripert, chef and partner at Le Bernardin in Manhattan, is a sublime cook, and his new book, A RETURN TO COOKING (Artisan, $50), with a text by Michael Ruhlman, paintings by Valentino Cortazar and photographs by Shimon Rothstein and Tammar Rothstein, is a hefty art object that is, for the most part, worth the whopping price tag. The book chronicles an interesting experiment: Ripert, who seems to have been experiencing some burnout, agrees to go on an extended road trip with a writer, an artist and two photographers in order to ''let the cooking fill me again.'' These five make extended visits to Sag Harbor, Puerto Rico, Napa and Vermont, where Ripert cooks impromptu dishes using mostly local, seasonal ingredients.</p>
        <p>The recipes, which cover a wide spectrum, are first-rate. My advice, though, is to stay as far away as humanly possible from the excruciatingly earnest text, which make the participants sound like world-class simps and sensitivos. We hear an awful lot about how this is a ''spiritual journey'' and how ''every recipe is a poem.'' Ruhlman has a knack for making poor Ripert sound like a second-rate Gary Snyder. ''I touch an onion, and something happens inside me,'' Ripert is quoted as saying. ''I understand the nature of that onion.'' In Ruhlman's portrait of him, Ripert can't even light a candle without intoning something like ''Flame breaks through the darkness, helps to connect you with the spirits.'' Maybe Ripert really talks this way, as if his dental fillings were made from turquoise. Either way, I'm happy to report that there's nothing sanctimonious or feather-headed about the way he cooks.</p>
        <p>A few other favorites:</p>
        <p>SOUP OF THE DAY (HarperCollins, $25.95; available in January), by Lydie Marshall. Marshall is the author of the now-classic ''Passion for Potatoes,'' and here she gives us -- after a foreword by Calvin Trillin -- a host of very fine recipes, including everything from lobster bisque to Mexican chicken soup with tortilla chips to her spa-worthy recipe for a ''day after'' soup when you've overdone it the night before.</p>
        <p>THE PLEASURES OF SLOW FOOD: Celebrating Authentic Traditions, Flavors, and Recipes (Chronicle, $40), by Corby Kummer. This is a big, handsome, well-written book with straightforward recipes from chefs ranging from Paul Bertolli and Rick Bayless to Alice Waters and Deborah Madison. It also functions as a welcome primer on the slow-food movement, which is the culinary world's version of filmmaking's back-to-basics Dogma 95 manifesto. Slow Foodies protest the evils of fast food in favor of cooking locally grown products using time-honored methods.</p>
        <p>NANCY SILVERTON'S SANDWICH BOOK: The Best Sandwiches Ever -- From Thursday Nights at Campanile (Knopf, $24.95), by Nancy Silverton with Teri Gelber. Silverton, along with her husband, owns and operates both Campanile and the La Brea Bakery in Los Angeles. This book is based on her restaurant's popular ''sandwich nights,'' and these are not your mother's tuna melts and PB&amp;J's. Her rare-seared tuna sandwich with braised leeks, hard-cooked egg and tapenade takes two full pages to explain. Don't look at her recipes as ''complicated sandwiches,'' Silverton explains, ''but as satisfying entrées on bread.'' For the really hard core, she even provides a recipe for making your own hot-dog buns.</p>
        <p>THE WISEGUY COOKBOOK: My Favorite Recipes From My Life as a Goodfella to Cooking on the Run (New American Library, paper, $17), by Henry Hill and Priscilla Davis, with a foreword by Nicholas Pileggi. Forget that faux ''Sopranos'' cookbook. Here's the real deal. Hill's story about his life in the mob was the basis for Martin Scorsese's film ''Goodfellas,'' and when he talks about ''cooking on the run,'' he isn't kidding. Hill has spent the last two decades moving around the country in the federal witness protection program. He has always been an obsessive eater -- When's the last time you saw a thin mobster?'' -- and has spent most of his life, both pre- and postmob, owning or working in restaurants. It's hard to resist dishes like his rolled veal cutlet canapés and ziti with a sauce made with pork butt and veal shanks, particularly after Hill tells us that he made these as a ''last supper'' when he knew he was about to be busted for ''the big Lufthansa heist.'' This book is good-natured, well written and frequently hilarious. Whenever Hill arrives in a new location, he drives his security detail nuts. A typical line here is, ''So we dumped our things at the hotel, and I made the Feds take us shopping.''</p>
        <p>X-TREME CUISINE: An Adrenaline-Charged Cookbook for the Young at Heart (HarperEntertainment, $24.95), by Robert Earl. This is a collection of formidably off-putting recipes from skateboarders, surfers and motorbike racers, many of them along the lines of a ''white trash casserole'' (use your imagination) and Hostess Ding Dongs with ice cream and peanut butter. Earl's etiquette tips tend to be x-tremely memorable, though, from how to deal with a grease fire (''do not urinate on flames'') to his tip for remembering which fork to use: ''Did you know that animals on the outside of a herd always get eaten first? If not, now you know, and the same goes for eating utensils. Always start with the outside fork/spoon and work your way in.''</p>
        <p>EVERYTHING TASTES BETTER WITH BACON: 70 Fabulous Recipes for Every Meal of the Day (Chronicle, paper, $18.95), by Sara Perry. Perry's dessert recipes aside (peanut butter cookies with bacon brittle, anyone?), I have the sneaking feeling that both the professional and nonprofessional joie de vivrists out there can agree on Perry's thesis -- she's onto something.</p>
        <p>Holiday Books Dwight Garner is an editor at the Book Review.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dwight Garner is an editor at the Book Review.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
