<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Santa's Shop Wishes It Checked Buyer Twice</title>
    <meta content="08SANT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/12/08/nyregion/08SANT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1446993"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Santa's Workshop (NYS Amusement Park)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reiss, Bob</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cunningham, Gregory P Sr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waterbury, Doug</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Adirondacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Amusement Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christmas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amusement and Theme Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Adirondack Mountains</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4DD1E3BF93BA35751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1761" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Santa's Shop Wishes It Checked Buyer Twice</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Santa's Shop Wishes It Checked Buyer Twice</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <dateline>NORTH POLE, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Santa's Workshop, venerable Christmas theme park in Adirondack Mountains, survives brush with disaster that followed agreement by its owner, Bob Reiss, to sell park to Gregory P Cunningham Sr, who turns out to have been convicted felon with reputation as con man; Reiss decided to block sale and not open park for 2001 season, but people of Wilmington, NY, whose economy relies on park, worked to keep it open; Reiss has found a buyer more to his liking in Doug Waterbury; Cunningham is suing Reiss and insists his involvement with park was completely honest; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bob Reiss knows the business of Christmas make-believe. For several decades he has supervised every ho, ho and ho that has echoed through Santa's Workshop, his quaint theme park here in the Adirondack Mountains. He is also in his 30th year of playing Jack Jingle, a kind of advance man for Santa who wears a bell-jangling hat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reiss knows about prima donna Santas. He knows that a viewing window in Santa's house can reduce children's fears and speed up lines. He knows to hire a new Santa when the old Santa starts believing his press clippings. Over the years a couple of white-bearded employees have legally changed their surnames to Claus, which Mr. Reiss considers an unsettling form of Method acting.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bob Reiss's attempt to sell Santa's Workshop, a theme park in the Adirondack Mountains, went awry when the would-be buyer turned out to be a convicted felon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bob Reiss knows the business of Christmas make-believe. For several decades he has supervised every ho, ho and ho that has echoed through Santa's Workshop, his quaint theme park here in the Adirondack Mountains. He is also in his 30th year of playing Jack Jingle, a kind of advance man for Santa who wears a bell-jangling hat.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reiss knows about prima donna Santas. He knows that a viewing window in Santa's house can reduce children's fears and speed up lines. He knows to hire a new Santa when the old Santa starts believing his press clippings. Over the years a couple of white-bearded employees have legally changed their surnames to Claus, which Mr. Reiss considers an unsettling form of Method acting.</p>
        <p>But for all his savvy in make-believe, Mr. Reiss said he still does not know how he, of all people -- 76 years old and as sharp as a holly leaf -- came to believe that his own fantasy had come true: that he had finally found a buyer who would preserve the theme park's integrity and allow him to keep playing Jack Jingle every Christmas season.</p>
        <p>Well, Merry Christmas.</p>
        <p>The would-be buyer, Gregory P. Cunningham Sr., turned out to be a convicted felon with a bit of a reputation. A ''con man,'' an upstate prosecutor calls him. An itinerant ''pitchman,'' says an upstate judge, who described Mr. Cunningham's modus operandi as ginning up a sure-fire project and then leaving the area, ''his promises virtually always unfulfilled.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cunningham, 49, admits to both his criminal record and a decade-old tax lien of roughly $280,000 in Binghamton. But he said that he had worked with Mr. Reiss for months to develop a business plan for Santa's Workshop, and that his family's trust invested $50,000 in the deal. ''I don't know how that's a pitchman,'' he said.</p>
        <p>By the time Mr. Reiss determined that a convicted felon was not quite the right fit for Santa's Workshop, the damage had been done: to his reputation, to his business, and to Wilmington, a town whose economic sleigh is hitched to the park. The workshop even closed for a few months, for the first time in its half-century existence; the fallout was measured in the sport utility vehicles filled with crying children that pulled away from the locked gates and into the Hungry Trout and North Pole motor inns.</p>
        <p>''Personally, I'd be better off if four years ago I'd said, 'We're done, knock the buildings down and call it a day,' '' Mr. Reiss said. ''But I wouldn't have felt too good.''</p>
        <p>Today, Santa's Workshop is open again, thanks to an investor from Oswego and a determined band of local good-deed doers. But things are still as messy as slush, with lawsuits and angry words and hurt feelings -- all revolving around a place where, the ads say, ''Christmas dreams come true for kids from 1 to 92.''</p>
        <p>One day last week, Mr. Reiss put on his noisy hat and wandered through the snow-covered park that sprung from the imagination of his father, Julian Reiss; a park that in this age of frenetic, high-tech amusement seems so earnest and retro. Here was the St. Nicholas Chapel with its Nativity scene and small pews. Here was the stable with real-live reindeer. Here was Tannenbaum the Talking Christmas Tree to compliment you on your scarf, thanks to a hidden elf with a microphone.</p>
        <p>The theme park, the first of its kind, made national news when it opened in 1949. Every day from late June until Columbus Day, thousands of people came to the side of Whiteface Mountain to see Santa in his off-season, or to send a letter with a North Pole postmark. Mr. Reiss watched its success from afar while serving in the Navy; anyway, he planned to be an industrial engineer.</p>
        <p>But by the 1960's, the would-be engineer was honoring his dead father by running Santa's Workshop. And by the 1970's, the former Navy lieutenant was performing as Jack Jingle in the park's new Christmas preview show, which was luring hundreds of families to spend late-autumn weekends in the post-fishing, pre-skiing Adirondacks.</p>
        <p>''It bothered me at first; I thought I was out of costume,'' Mr. Reiss said. ''I had to mature into it.''</p>
        <p>As Jack Jingle was maturing, so was the park, which over the years became tired-looking. Its popularity melted gradually, like Frosty in the sun. Mr. Reiss looked up one day to find that he was in his 70's, with a wife saying it was time to retire and three children with no interest in placating Santas in summer.</p>
        <p>On Thanksgiving Day 1999, Mr. Reiss appeared on the QVC home-shopping network to say that he would be willing to sell his theme park, as long as the buyer shared his values -- his father's values. ''We've tried to conduct this business to be a force of good in other people's lives,'' he said the other day.</p>
        <p>After wading through the offers, Mr. Reiss thought he had found his heir apparent by springtime in Mr. Cunningham, who talked of preserving the park's charms while also bringing in virtual-reality attractions. Finally, 12-year-old Buddy would have something to do while Santa mesmerized 5-year-old Sis.</p>
        <p>The newcomer's words enchanted Mr. Reiss. ''I wanted to believe,'' he now says. Before long Mr. Cunningham was living with his wife, Joan, at the Reiss family's Holiday Lodge, helping with the 2000 Christmas preview and learning about the business his family was poised to buy.</p>
        <p>About that time a copy of a newspaper article from a faraway town mysteriously arrived in Wilmington; soon its words were crackling like kindling in the foothills of Whiteface Mountain. Not only had Mr. Cunningham been convicted of an embezzlement-related charge in Broome County in 1997, but he had also been recently arraigned on similar charges in Montgomery County, 200 miles away.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Reiss inquired, Mr. Cunningham explained that he had settled for a plea bargain in Broome County, and that the new matter was merely a business misunderstanding. ''Before he took our deposits, Mr. Reiss was aware of my background,'' Mr. Cunningham said, although he did not recall mentioning that outstanding $280,000 tax lien.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reiss admitted that he knew of these matters when he signed a sales contract in early 2001, one that came with the agreement that he could continue to play Jack Jingle.</p>
        <p>''Here was the white knight I'd been waiting for,'' he said. ''Now that I was locked in, I wanted to believe he was telling me straight.''</p>
        <p>With Mr. Reiss's approval, the Cunninghams set about to make Santa's Workshop more hip. They fixed some of the rides, gutted the kitchen in the Mother Hubbard's Cupboard restaurant and moved things around in the Jack Jingle Theater.</p>
        <p>But doubts mounted through the spring of 2001, as The Lake Placid News peeled back the layers of Mr. Cunningham's past, and the state police took him away in handcuffs for his indictment on grand larceny and forgery charges in Montgomery County. Finally, Mr. Reiss made two startling, humbling decisions: he would try to block the sale to the Cunninghams, and he would not open Santa's Workshop for the 2001 season. The place was in physical and karmic shambles.</p>
        <p>This was big news in Wilmington, where just about every one of the 1,036 residents seems to have worked at Santa's Workshop, from Jeanne Ashworth, the town supervisor, to Roy Holzer, the owner of the Little Super Market. More important, it was bad news to tourists, who were now annoyed and somewhat deaf, thanks to the back-seat wails of traumatized children. ''Oh, it was very painful, both economically and emotionally, with carloads of crying children at the doorstep of the visitors bureau,'' Ms. Ashworth recalled. ''That is not an overstatement.''</p>
        <p>It may sound like a movie script, but it is true. Jim Carmelitano from the North Pole Motor Inn, Jerry Bottcher from the Hungry Trout and some other local residents worked to put Santa's Workshop back together again in time for the 2001 Christmas preview. They may have shaken their heads at Bob Reiss's stubborn naïveté, but if it were not for him, they say, the jingles of the season would not be emanating from their cash registers.</p>
        <p>Everyone wound up having a nice Christmas last year -- except, perhaps, Mr. Cunningham, who was convicted of those charges in Montgomery County and sentenced to up to six years in prison. He is still in town, though, managing a local motor inn while awaiting some legal rulings: on a lawsuit against Mr. Reiss, on the appeal of his conviction, and on his challenge of a new, related indictment, this one in Oneida County.</p>
        <p>He and his wife say that they may not be the most loved people in Wilmington, but they work hard and expect to be running Santa's Workshop soon. Perceptions in Wilmington have been skewed by the dominance of Bob Reiss, Mrs. Cunningham said, adding, ''He owns Santa Claus and Jesus.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Reiss said he doubted that the Cunninghams would ever step foot again on workshop soil. He has learned his lesson, he said. ''My main problem probably was that I am altogether too trusting, and I was eager -- very eager -- to find the right person to pass the mantle on.''</p>
        <p>Although some wonder whether Mr. Reiss will ever let go, he has chosen another successor: Doug Waterbury, an Oswego businessman who has bought a majority share in the park with an agreement to buy out Mr. Reiss within five years. He has already made changes, and has coaxed Mr. Reiss into raising the modest prices for things like hot dogs and letters from Santa.</p>
        <p>The two also have an understanding about when a certain old man can put on a hat of bells and walk around his father's Christmas fantasy: any time he wants.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
