<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Japanese Presence Shrinks</title>
    <meta content="08JAPA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1446776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="IN BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zhao, Yilu</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFD9143BF93BA35751C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1193" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Japanese Presence Shrinks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YILU ZHAO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zhao, Yilu</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on sharp decline in number of Japanese expatriates living in Westchester County, NY, over past decade and adverse impact it is having on local businesses; decade-long stagnation of Japanese economy has prompted Japanese companies to trim New York-based staffs, cut benefits or eliminate American branches; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A DECADE ago, the Scarsdale office of Furumoto Realty was buying mansions in Westchester for Japanese corporations to house their expatriate staff. Now, it is selling those properties for the same clients.</p>
        <p>Four years ago, Meidiya, a supermarket popular among the local Japanese, closed its Yonkers store, the bigger of the two it operated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A DECADE ago, the Scarsdale office of Furumoto Realty was buying mansions in Westchester for Japanese corporations to house their expatriate staff. Now, it is selling those properties for the same clients.</p>
        <p>Four years ago, Meidiya, a supermarket popular among the local Japanese, closed its Yonkers store, the bigger of the two it operated.</p>
        <p>At the Greenwich Japanese School in Connecticut, which draws three-quarters of its students from Japanese families living in Westchester, enrollment has slid from 417 in 1992, to 314 before the World Trade Center attack, to 253 today.</p>
        <p>The Banbanka, the late summer festival with traditional dances and fragrant teas, put on in Eastchester by the local Japanese, is no longer held.</p>
        <p>The ripples of the decade-long stagnation of the Japanese economy have unraveled the once-thriving Japanese enclaves in Westchester. The number of Japanese living in Westchester has dwindled, as cost-conscious Japanese companies trim their New York-based staff or eliminate their American branches.</p>
        <p>In 1992, before the bubble economy burst in Japan, a total of 357 Japanese companies employed 6,048 Japanese citizens in the New York metropolitan area, according to the Japanese Chamber of Commerce and Industry of New York. Between one-quarter to one-third of the expatriates lived in Westchester with their families, and the Japanese population in the county was around 16,000, according to the Japanese consulate in New York.</p>
        <p>Currently, 273 companies employ 2,528 Japanese citizens in New York, New Jersey and Connecticut, a 58 percent decrease from 1992. Westchester's loss in Japanese population has declined accordingly.</p>
        <p>While many Japanese men -- the expatriate employees are almost entirely male, proud and reserved -- are unwilling to discuss their feelings about the shrinking Japanese community in the county, their wives are more open.</p>
        <p>Keiko Onoda, whose family will return to Japan next month, would prefer to live in Scarsdale a little longer. Mrs. Onoda, 52, the wife of a Japanese executive with a publishing company, has lived in Westchester for six years.</p>
        <p>Their son, Hayato, a 24-year-old psychology major at the City University of New York, loves the freedom that the American education system offers. He can pick his major when he is ready and change it if he wants to. He can transfer to another school if he chooses to. Mrs. Onoda would have liked to live near her son until he finishes college.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Onoda loves the trees, the grass and the chirping birds in Westchester. She can also store as many gadgets, books and clothes as she would like to in her roomy, airy house on a quiet street in Scarsdale.</p>
        <p>''There are so many people in Japan,'' she said recently, as she sorted through the family's belongings. ''Every place is like Manhattan. We'll never get this much space again.''</p>
        <p>Because the family will live in a Tokyo apartment much smaller than their Scarsdale house, Mrs. Onoda has been choosing which household items to keep.</p>
        <p>''And I like to play golf,'' Mrs. Onoda said, a little sad. ''It's really cheap to play golf here. You can play as much as you want. Back in Japan, you cannot.''</p>
        <p>Most Japanese companies were generous with their expatriate employees until a few years ago, often covering housing expenses, children's tuition, memberships of golf clubs, subscriptions to magazines, and for senior staff members, cars with full-time chauffeurs. It could cost more than $50,000 a year beyond the basic salary to support even a mid-level employee in the United States.</p>
        <p>Now, most companies have shrunk the benefits, and many are planning to shed more of their overseas staff. The Mizuho Corporate Bank, one of the largest in Japan, has already sold all of its properties in the New York area as well as its golf club memberships, said Osomu Ogura, its spokesman. The company is planning to cut half of its 300 Japanese employees in the United States.</p>
        <p>Takuya Honjo, the president and chief executive of Mizuho Corporate Bank's American operations, is the one who decides which employees must return home. Also a Scarsdale resident, Mr. Honjo leaves home for his office in Midtown Manhattan at 6 a.m. and doesn't get home until 10 or 11 p.m. Trimming staff, he said, is necessary to revive the companies.</p>
        <p>''It doesn't make a difference to me whether we have a big or small community,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But the size of Westchester's Japanese community matters a lot to Ozao Shizue, the owner of Meidiya, the Japanese grocery -- now one store instead of two.</p>
        <p>''The families go back to Japan and they don't come back,'' Mrs. Shizue said, drawing in the air the shape of a plummeting roller coaster. ''The companies are not sending replacements.''</p>
        <p>At her store on Central Park Avenue in Hartsdale, where packages of ramen noodles are neatly stacked on shelves and freshly cut fish are buried in ice, business is slower, Mrs. Shizue said.</p>
        <p>The exodus of Japanese families from Westchester has also reduced enrollment at the Greenwich Japanese School, set up 27 years ago for the children of Japanese citizens. The school teaches subjects in Japanese, except for English, American social studies and art.</p>
        <p>''I used to have 30 kids in my class,'' said Kay Nitta, who has taught English as a second language there for more than 10 years. ''Now I have 13.''</p>
        <p>Administrators are worried about balancing the books. The school, though heavily subsidized by the Japanese government, needs tuition and fees ($7,000 a year per child) to pay the bills. When the school had between 400 and 500 students, paying the bills had been easy. This year, the school will run a big deficit, said Tomiko Okajima, the school's longtime office manager. When a new principal, Koji Yoshida, was brought in 18 months ago, one of his main missions was to attract more students. He reasons that if a larger percentage of Japanese expatriates send their children to his school instead of American schools, it can survive.</p>
        <p>And for Tak Furumoto, the owner of Furumoto Realty, which has offices in Scarsdale, Fort Lee and Manhattan, to survive means to diversify its clientele. A decade ago, its Westchester clients were exclusively Japanese expatriates, and now, they are one-quarter local American families, Mr. Furumoto said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Furumoto's agents know how to sell properties for departing families and corporations eager to get rid of them. Mike Mikuni, the head agent in its Scarsdale office, just advised a Japanese family who left the country in July to price their house on a quiet road at $659,000, lower than the asking prices of many similar houses.</p>
        <p>''It'll be an easy sell,'' Mr. Mikuni said.</p>
        <p>IN BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
