<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big East Tries to Keep Tradition in Two-Division Format</title>
    <meta content="05EAST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1173983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Big East Conference</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Syracuse University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Georgetown University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drape, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tranghese, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000205T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E5DC1E3FF936A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big East Tries to Keep Tradition in Two-Division Format</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drape, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comr Mike Tranghese of Big East basketball conference comments on considerations he and conference athletic directors weighed when it became clear that Big East was heading into territory of two divisions; first rule of division was that New York was Big East's most important market in terms of recruiting, fan base and news media; second was that certain rivalries had to be kept intact, like the oldest: Syracuse versus Georgetown; table shows new Big East (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Once the decision was made to add Virginia Tech to Big East basketball for next season, Commissioner Mike Tranghese and the conference athletic directors knew they were heading into the territory of two divisions. To divide them, the commissioner kept tradition in mind.</p>
        <p>The first rule of division was that New York was the Big East's most important market in terms of recruiting, fan base and news media. The second was that certain rivalries had to be kept intact.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Once the decision was made to add Virginia Tech to Big East basketball for next season, Commissioner Mike Tranghese and the conference athletic directors knew they were heading into the territory of two divisions. To divide them, the commissioner kept tradition in mind.</p>
        <p>The first rule of division was that New York was the Big East's most important market in terms of recruiting, fan base and news media. The second was that certain rivalries had to be kept intact.</p>
        <p>Like the oldest: Syracuse versus Georgetown. One of the most exciting: St. John's-Connecticut. And the regional: the New England round robin of UConn, Boston College and Providence, as well as the battle of New Jersey, Rutgers and Seton Hall. So St. John's was assigned to the New England-centric division and separated from the Pirates and the Scarlet Knights.</p>
        <p>''This way every team is coming to the New York metropolitan area at least once a year,'' Tranghese said. ''It's a huge recruiting issue.''</p>
        <p>In addition to having teams play each division opponent twice, the new configuration allows four crossover games. And in an unusual arrangement, Tranghese will become the nation's first conference commissioner to assume the responsibility of matchmaker. He will schedule the crossover games and will be conscious of the fact that a team like St. John's likes to play its neighbors in New Jersey, as well as Syracuse.</p>
        <p>''We thought about a computer, but there are too many issues,'' he said. ''It will be my responsibility. It's either that or chaos. I'm the only one who can factor in fairness, rivalries and business. We want the big games.''</p>
        <p>Coaches in the conference accept the two divisions and Tranghese's role in determining the crossover games. St. John's Coach Mike Jarvis said it would be ideal if the Red Storm played Rutgers, Seton Hall and Syracuse each year, but he knew that would probably not happen.</p>
        <p>''They are close,'' Jarvis said. ''It makes travel easier and it's less time away from the classroom and campus. We have a very capable commissioner, but any plan that involves as many schools will not make everybody happy.''</p>
        <p>More problematic is the decision to allow just 12 teams to compete in the conference tournament. Coaches from Jarvis to Providence's Tim Welsh anticipate the day that a colleague is fired for not making the Big East tournament.</p>
        <p>Tranghese acknowledged that locking two teams out of Madison Square Garden for the tournament was not popular with athletic directors either, though they approved the plan, 13-0. But logistics and logic left the conference no choice. Six first-round games beginning at 9:30 a.m. was not practical.</p>
        <p>''If you can't play yourself into a position of being one of the top 12 of 14 spots, you've got bigger problems in your program than not going to New York City,'' Tranghese said. ''We're not asking teams to do something insurmountable. If a coach misses it a couple of years, there's more problems with the program than missing New York.''</p>
        <p>Seniors' Farewell</p>
        <p>There's nothing like a celebration in the cozy confines of home against a struggling opponent to bust St. John's out of a slump. The Red Storm (13-6) has lost four of five games and plays host to Boston College (9-11) today for senior day at Alumni Hall.</p>
        <p>The sixth man Chudney Gray might join his fellow seniors Lavor Postell and Bootsy Thornton in the starting lineup in place of Reggie Jessie for their last home game in Queens.</p>
        <p>Jarvis would not say for sure, but he cautioned: ''If he's starting, it's because of senior day. I'm not benching anybody.''</p>
        <p>Mouring's Turn</p>
        <p>Connecticut Coach Jim Calhoun has been waiting all season for one of his Huskies to assert himself as the score-from-anywhere player the way Richard Hamilton did on last year's national championship team. Albert Mouring says he is that player. He is shooting 46 percent from the field and 51 percent from 3-point range.</p>
        <p>The junior guard was impressed enough with himself after scoring 22 points on 8-of-9 shooting in a victory over Villanova on Wednesday that he proclaimed, ''I feel like I'm one of the best shooters in the country, and I have to play that way.''</p>
        <p>He will get a chance today as No. 7-ranked UConn (16-4) takes on No. 8- ranked Michigan State (16-5) in East Lansing, Mich.</p>
        <p>Both teams have a chance to return to the Final Four behind their point guards, Khalid El-Amin of UConn and Mateen Cleaves of Michigan State. With El-Amin nursing a deep thigh bruise, Mouring needs to supplement the Huskies' offense -- today and all the way through the tournament.</p>
        <p>Last-Second Replay</p>
        <p>Last week, the National Collegiate Athletic Association adopted the use of instant replay on last-second shots, partly because of what happened in Villanova's 67-66 loss to Miami on Jan. 17. The Hurricanes' Johnny Hemsley hit a 3-pointer that came after the final horn.</p>
        <p>The N.C.A.A. did not overturn the call, but Coach Steve Lappas is already lobbying for his Wildcats (11-8) to the tournament selection committee. ''If we're on the N.C.A.A. bubble, I have to think they'll look at that game differently,'' he said. ''We've got to get to the bubble first. But even though we won't get credit for a full game, I have to think we'd get something for it.''</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL: NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
