<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AHEAD | Destination Marathons; Visiting on the Run</title>
    <meta content="23ahead" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1828116"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tsui, Bonnie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EED7133EF930A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AHEAD | Destination Marathons; Visiting on the Run</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BONNIE TSUI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tsui, Bonnie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on marathon running events scheduled around country; list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT'S often said that the best way to get to know a place is to walk through it -- hike in the hills, say, or ramble through a city's downtown streets. But what about running?</p>
        <p>For many runners, a marathon can be a distinctive way to see and experience a new location as most people do not -- especially when that place is a major travel destination itself. And for the most part, it's not even necessary to be a marathoner to join in and walk or run along for a few miles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT'S often said that the best way to get to know a place is to walk through it -- hike in the hills, say, or ramble through a city's downtown streets. But what about running?</p>
        <p>For many runners, a marathon can be a distinctive way to see and experience a new location as most people do not -- especially when that place is a major travel destination itself. And for the most part, it's not even necessary to be a marathoner to join in and walk or run along for a few miles.</p>
        <p>''Winding 26.2 miles through sunny San Diego was a great way to understand the city's relaxed vibe,'' said Brynn Harrington, a manager for the nonprofit Taproot Foundation in San Francisco, who has run five marathons. Last June, she flew to San Diego with her husband, Sean, for the Rock 'n' Roll Marathon, and met up with two friends from Calgary to enjoy the beach before and after the race. ''It was still about the time -- for most runners, at least,'' she said. ''But it was also a great reason to visit and an awesome way to get to know some locals.''</p>
        <p>Marathons go on all year from Paris to Puerto Rico. In the next couple of months, several will be in places at the top of many travelers' to-visit lists.</p>
        <p>The Los Angeles Marathon absorbs some of the sprawling city's vibe. ''The L.A. event is enormous,'' said Stephen Goldmann, a dedicated race enthusiast who competes in trail running, marathon and ultra-marathon events. ''Every mile they'll have a band or a dancing troupe or a religious evangelist -- it's totally what you expect from L.A.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldmann, a partner at the Culinary Edge, a restaurant consulting business in San Francisco, said he always looks forward to running in a new place. ''You're out when everyone who lives there is out, and you get to see what the community is like at different times of the day,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the big Los Angeles event, the Big Island Marathon is a small-scale race that is rich in natural scenery. The course takes participants along Hawaii Island's lush eastern coast, with stunning views of the Pacific Ocean, tropical rain forests, waterfalls and lava-formed beaches. It's known as a friendly -- and often rainy -- event that lets visitors experience the ''Old Hawaii'' feeling around the city of Hilo, a center of Hawaiian history.</p>
        <p>The Charlottesville Marathon in Virginia follows a distinctive route around the foothills of the Blue Ridge Mountains and several historic sites. Runners buzz past buildings that Thomas Jefferson designed at the University of Virginia and breeze by horse farms out in the pretty, forested country. But they should also beware the humidity and the area's unrelentingly hilly terrain, which has helped gain the event a reputation for putting even experienced runners through some seriously challenging paces.</p>
        <p>Though the Big Sur International Marathon doesn't run until late April, places fill up quickly. (This week, online registration for the marathon was almost all booked.) And no wonder. The course is a spectacular run up the Pacific Coast Highway in California, a wild, winding route through ranchlands and redwood forests. Heartbreaking sprints up steep, curving hills are rewarded by glimpses of whales surfacing just offshore and barking sea lions sunning themselves on rocky beaches.</p>
        <p>Taking place on the same weekend, the Country Music Marathon in Nashville provides an all-day soundtrack for runners, with 50 bands on 28 stages around the city. And if a lineup of jazz, swing and country isn't enough to keep morale up, hundreds of high school cheerleaders also lead ''cheer stations'' at every mile. The marathon culminates in a post-race concert in downtown Nashville; this year's scheduled headliner is the country music star Sara Evans.</p>
        <p>These marathons have half- or short-distance options, including five-kilometer ''fun runs'' and walking events, so even noncompetitive participants can get the high of a race experience.</p>
        <p>Not being a serious marathoner doesn't diminish the joys of running through a beautiful new place, Mr. Goldmann said. ''When I was in Paris,'' he said, ''I wasn't even a runner then. But we just jumped in during the marathon -- it was just fun to run around Paris.''</p>
        <p>DETAILS</p>
        <p>LOS ANGELES</p>
        <p>What: Los Angeles Marathon, www.lamarathon.com</p>
        <p>When: March 4</p>
        <p>HILO, HAWAII</p>
        <p>When: Big Island Marathon, www.hilomarathon.org</p>
        <p>When: March 18</p>
        <p>CHARLOTTESVILLE, VA.</p>
        <p>What: Charlottesville Marathon, www.charlottesvillemarathon.com</p>
        <p>When: April 21</p>
        <p>CARMEL, CALIF.</p>
        <p>What: Big Sur International Marathon, www.bsim.org</p>
        <p>When: April 29</p>
        <p>NASHVILLE</p>
        <p>What: Country Music Marathon, www.cmmarathon.com</p>
        <p>When: April 28</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
