<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Witty Modern Women, and the Men Who Loathe Them</title>
    <meta content="23spoo" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/23/arts/television/23spoo.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1828142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">BBC America</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D6133EF930A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="459" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Witty Modern Women, and the Men Who Loathe Them</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Witty Modern Woman, and the Men Who Loathe Them</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GINIA BELLAFANTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bellafante, Ginia</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you have read Helen Fielding, then you know that the millennial young British woman, of even just moderately good breeding, is a clever creature: witty, insouciant, unrestrained in matters of consumption, alluring to men no matter how actively her insecurities have conspired to make her believe otherwise.</p>
        <p>You know this because you have experienced Ms. Fielding's Bridget Jones in book, movie and newspaper column form. But Ms. Fielding's view of her Anglo sisters, is, in her homeland, not universally held. In other pockets of British popular culture disagreement has mounted, with the faint hint of misogyny even, the grim view that young women, single and married, are a drag on the male psyche, and thus presumably the kingdom and future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>BBC America’s sketch comedy show devotes itself exclusively to capturing the moments  awkward, destructive and banal  of young dating and married life.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you have read Helen Fielding, then you know that the millennial young British woman, of even just moderately good breeding, is a clever creature: witty, insouciant, unrestrained in matters of consumption, alluring to men no matter how actively her insecurities have conspired to make her believe otherwise.</p>
        <p>You know this because you have experienced Ms. Fielding's Bridget Jones in book, movie and newspaper column form. But Ms. Fielding's view of her Anglo sisters, is, in her homeland, not universally held. In other pockets of British popular culture disagreement has mounted, with the faint hint of misogyny even, the grim view that young women, single and married, are a drag on the male psyche, and thus presumably the kingdom and future.</p>
        <p>The most recent evidence at hand is ''Spoons,'' a sketch comedy show that makes its debut tonight on BBC America. It is unusual for a sketch show to keep such a tight thematic focus, but the eight-member troupe devotes itself exclusively to capturing the moments -- awkward, destructive and banal -- of young dating and married life.</p>
        <p>The men are always louts; there is no doubt. But they are driven, as they are in the British comedy ''Coupling,'' by the grand demands and manipulative ways of the female contemporaries they bed and aim to bed. Men try to escape from their girlfriends as if they were prisoners. In one repeating bit, a woman who looks every bit the harridan screams at her husband -- in restaurants and stores, prompted by nothing, profanities and all -- that she wants ''a baby!''</p>
        <p>A typical moment in ''Spoons'' has a guy delivering a toast at his friend's wedding. He speaks of his own marriage, the difficulties and rewards of it, the perseverance it requires. ''I still love you, Jackie,'' he says to his wife, during the toast. ''Despite your affair.''</p>
        <p>Simon Farnaby is the show's primary draw. Of all the actors he seems to wear his disdain for the whole business of women and partnering the least insidiously. He carries himself like a slacker, aware of his own ineptness. One of the show's funniest moments has him going back to an old girlfriend, presumably to ask her to reconsider. But when he talks to her on a park bench, he makes this announcement instead: ''I didn't think it through. I would like my rowing machine back after all.''</p>
        <p>Bridget Jones could fall for such a character, but eventually wisdom would get the best of her.</p>
        <p>Spoons  BBC America, tonight at 11 Eastern time; 8, Pacific time; 10, Central time.</p>
        <p>Written by Charlie Brooker, Ben Caudell, Peter Holmes and Neil Webster.</p>
        <p>WITH: Rob Rouse, Kevin Bishop, Josie D'Arby, Tom Goodman Hill, Rosie Cavaliero, Simon Farnaby, Elizabeth Bower and Kerry Godliman.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
