<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Concerned Coaches Are Wondering, Why So Few Blacks?</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="360455"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">RHODEN, WILLIAM C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDB123DF932A25755C0A966958260" item-length="1516" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Concerned Coaches Are Wondering, Why So Few Blacks?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM C. RHODEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RHODEN, WILLIAM C</byline>
      <dateline>OMAHA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AS college baseball continues to make major strides toward more widespread popularity, the virtual invisibility of black players at the sport's college level has raised a concern about its future growth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AS college baseball continues to make major strides toward more widespread popularity, the virtual invisibility of black players at the sport's college level has raised a concern about its future growth.</p>
        <p>AS college baseball continues to make major strides toward more widespread popularity, the virtual invisibility of black players at the sport's college level has raised a concern about its future growth.</p>
        <p>In this year's College World Series, which ended here Saturday with a victory by Georgia over Oklahoma State, only 6 of the 176 players were black. (The series involves 8 teams of 22 players each.) Last year, 8 of the 176 were black.</p>
        <p>A study by the American Institutes of Research found that 7.2 percent of all Division I baseball players are black. When the predominantly black schools in Division I are removed, the figure drops to 2.6 percent.</p>
        <p>That number is particularly striking when compared with the percentage of blacks in Division I football, 37 percent, and basketball, 56 percent.</p>
        <p>''The pool of talent is much smaller than coaches would like it to be,'' said Gene McArtor, the Missouri head baseball coach and chairman of the National Collegiate Athletic Association's Division I baseball committee. ''Many of the talented black athletes are heading in directions other than baseball, and it's been a loss for the sport.</p>
        <p>''We have to convince more kids at an early age that baseball offers as many or maybe more opportunities than the other sports they are being attracted to. That's our challenge.''</p>
        <p>With the exception of coaches in the two predominantly black conferences, there are no black head baseball coaches at any of the 269 Division I programs that field baseball teams.</p>
        <p>The survey seems to indicate that Division I college baseball is in a position similar to that of college football and basketball in the 1960's. But while the lack of black athletes then was a result of biased traditions and of laws in some states barring the admission of black students, the reasons for the current low number of blacks in college baseball are more complex.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people have asked me why there aren't more blacks,'' said Skip Bertman, the head baseball coach at Louisiana State. ''In fact, one chancellor came up to me before a game and asked, 'Where are the black athletes?'</p>
        <p>''It's not a racist thing. It's harder to get blacks into college baseball because there are fewer of them attempting to do it, compared with basketball and football.''</p>
        <p>The reasons given for the strikingly low numbers are several: lack of youth baseball programs, particularly in poor urban areas; the steering and gravitation of these same youngsters into basketball and football, and a scarcity of full scholarships, which forces families to foot part of the bill for a college education.</p>
        <p>But the most commonly cited reason - and one of the most compelling - is the fierce competition for high-school athletes from major league teams.</p>
        <p>In fact, pro baseball teams legally do what many big-time college football and basketball programs have been punished for doing: They offer money and other inducements to attract choice players.</p>
        <p>''We have something in baseball that football and basketball don't have,'' Bertman said. ''We have the pro baseball draft, and that takes many of the good high-school black kids right into the professional ranks. That's the biggest point.'' Not surprisingly, money is a strong lure.</p>
        <p>''Because of the economic situation that many of them are in, when they get offered $20,000, they're gone,'' said Ron Polk, the head coach at Mississippi. ''We signed three black athletes in the last three years, and they ended up signing pro contracts out of high school. The ones we've gone after ended up being pretty good drafts and they ended up signing. That happens to a lot of us.'' It's not difficult to see the attraction. Darryl Strawberry received a $210,000 signing bonus from the Mets in 1980. Kiki Jones, a pitcher from Tampa, Fla., signed for $175,000 with the Los Angeles Dodgers last year.</p>
        <p>''Personally, I've seen those blacks who are good at baseball, and they want to achieve instant success,'' said Jeff Hammonds, Stanford's all-America freshman center fielder and one of the few black players in the Pacific-10.</p>
        <p>Hammonds, who starred at Scotch Plains-Fanwood High School in New Jersey, was a ninth-round pick of the Toronto Blue Jays and turned down a reported $250,000 bonus and signed with Stanford.</p>
        <p>But some observers feel there may be more behind the lack of blacks in college baseball than the pull of pro baseball.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's a matter of blacks not wanting to go to college,'' said Don Buford, the Baltimore Orioles' director of instruction. ''I don't think they're being recruited in the numbers that whites are.'' Buford, who is black, played baseball at the University of Southern California before embarking on a 10-year major league career.</p>
        <p>Bertman said that argument might have some merit.</p>
        <p>''Here's what we're guilty of as white middle-class coaches,'' he said. ''I'm guilty of it, my counterparts at The Citadel and Mississippi State and Stanford are guilty of it: We don't scour the inner-city schools for the best black athletes in baseball. Why? Because we don't have to. ''There are so many kids that want to come to play college baseball who send letters and get scouts to send recommendations and whose parents can afford to accept a half-scholarship.''</p>
        <p>Bertman said Louisiana State recently recruited a diamond-in-the-rough type of player from a Baton Rouge inner-city high school. The player is talented, but Bertman said he had to hunt for him.</p>
        <p>Gary Ward, the Oklahoma State coach, disagrees with the premise that white coaches do not seek out black athletes. Before becoming the Oklahoma State baseball coach in 1978, Ward, who is white, coached junior-college basketball and came close to being assistant basketball coach for Eddie Sutton at Arkansas.</p>
        <p>''I've been in the inner city, in Savannah to St. Louis, Chicago to Dallas,'' Ward said. ''Obviously, these kids have great skills. You watch those 5-8, 5-9 kids play basketball and you say, 'Gee, I'd like to have them for two or three years with a bat.'</p>
        <p>''But in the inner-city areas in the North, where the weather is bad and there's no opportunity to play, when these 8- and 9-year-old kids go to city parks and play the hoops game, there's no baseball diamond. If there is a baseball diamond, there's not a local sponsor.</p>
        <p>''When you get into the white affluent sections, they have the real nice city parks, the real nice uniforms, and 1,000 sponsors who give kids the chance to play from T-ball on up.''</p>
        <p>Lyle Mouton Sr., whose son is the only black player on Louisiana State's team, attributes the situation not to a lack of black players in Little League, but to their lack of involvement at the American Legion level.</p>
        <p>''That's where your college coaches go to recruit in the summer,'' said Mouton, who played in the Pittsburgh Pirates organization and has coached in several youth leagues in Louisiana. ''They don't go to the high schools. From all of my coaching, youth baseball, from T-ball through high school, has been dominated by black players.</p>
        <p>''American Legion is where blacks get shelved. And if you don't play American Legion ball, slim chance you'll get to play major college baseball.''</p>
        <p>At the same time, players like Hammonds concede that personal preference and the prestige of a given sport can play a major role in diverting black talent from college baseball. Four of the black players who participated in this year's College World Series admitted that baseball was not their first choice as a sport.</p>
        <p>Mouton's son, Lyle Jr., played basketball for Louisiana State for two season before dropping the sport after last season to concentrate on baseball.</p>
        <p>''I made a decision of the heart,'' he said. ''I wanted to play baseball and wasn't able to, and it hurt me to not be able to play a sport that I loved. So I had to make a life decision. I want to play this sport, and that's what I did.''</p>
        <p>Hammonds was a running back in high school and played until suffering an injury during his senior year. He figured baseball was the most injury-free sport and focused his attentions there.</p>
        <p>Another major factor in the low numbers is the scholarship situation. Unlike big-time college football and baseball, most baseball programs are unable to grant many full athletic scholarships. That means the average recruited athlete will need outside help to pay what the partial scholarship does not cover.</p>
        <p>''A kid who plays baseball has got to have help from home,'' Bertman said. ''So kids go to a community college for less money and stay at home.''</p>
        <p>For a growing number of black families, the opportunity to give a son a college education outweighs the short-term money.</p>
        <p>Last year, Calvin Murray, an outfielder at W. T. White High School in Dallas, turned down a $300,000 bonus offered by the Cleveland Indians and accepted a scholarship to play for Texas.</p>
        <p>When his mother, Virginia, was asked by a reporter how she could resist the lure of a six-figure bonus, she replied that she had told her son to think of the long haul.</p>
        <p>''I tell Calvin I don't care how good he is,'' she said. ''If you're black, you need the education.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
