<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Indians Bill New York Town As Its 99-Year Leases Expire</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="360519"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIANS, AMERICAN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SENECA NATION OF INDIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SALAMANCA (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5D8173CF932A25755C0A966958260" item-length="1182" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Indians Bill New York Town As Its 99-Year Leases Expire</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH KOLBERT, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</byline>
      <dateline>SALAMANCA, N.Y.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In 1892 it seemed like an idea with a future.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In 1892 it seemed like an idea with a future.</p>
        <p>In 1892 it seemed like an idea with a future.</p>
        <p>The people of Salamanca, a railroad town in western New York that had been illegally established on Indian land, received leases to rent the property, each lasting 99 years. The Seneca Indians, in turn, received total payments of $17,000 a year.</p>
        <p>Today, however, only eight months are left to the Salamanca lease. And the once bright future of this town has become a grim obsession.</p>
        <p>Hoping to make up for the inflationary decades they spent collecting 1890's rents, the Senecas have set the price of a new lease at $800,000 a year. They have also asked for an immediate payment of $60 million to make up for the inequities of the original lease.</p>
        <p>Homeowners Alarmed</p>
        <p>Already a tentative agreement has been reached that would grant the Senecas their requests, and that has alarmed the town's white residents, who have been paying as little as $1 for the land under their homes. Many say they would rather burn down their houses than pay the price of the new lease.</p>
        <p>''I shouldn't say this, but I have no intention of paying $2,000,'' said Nancy O'Brien, who owns a dry-cleaning store with a $24-a-year lease.</p>
        <p>As for the immediate one-lump payment of $60 million the Senecas are seeking, Mrs. O'Brien said, ''the whole town isn't worth that much.''</p>
        <p>What makes the Salamanca lease situation different from most modern-day Indian causes is that the Senecas clearly have the upper hand. And they say that while they were badly taken advantage of in the last round of lease negotiations, they have no intention of giving up their advantage this time.</p>
        <p>''When they negotiated the original leases, they thought we weren't going to be here at the end,'' Dennis Lay, president of the Seneca Nation, said. ''I guess we fooled them.''</p>
        <p>Anyone who does not like the terms of the new lease can leave town, he said. ''We're not going any lower,'' he said. ''It's either go or no go.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the situation in Salamanca, a quiet town of 6,600 people, would be easier to resolve if it had a precedent. But it does not. While ranchers out West often lease grazing land on Indian reservations, no other town in the country is built on land leased from an Indian nation, experts say.</p>
        <p>''The situation up there is rather unique,'' said Steve Gleason, a staff assistant at the Bureau of Indian Affairs in Washington.</p>
        <p>Tensions Always There</p>
        <p>Roughly 90 percent of Salamanca -1,700 acres - lies inside the Allegany Reservation, which is nestled against the Pennsylvania border south of Buffalo. The rest of the 22,000-acre reservation, New York State's largest, is home to 3,400 members of the Seneca Nation.</p>
        <p>The Seneca Nation does not own the stores and houses in Salamanca, just the land under them. That means the 2,700 lease owners can buy and sell houses but never hold title to the land.</p>
        <p>Tensions between the whites and the Indians have always been present in Salamanca, though not always spoken about. A main source of friction has been taxes. Many Senecas have moved into Salamanca over the years, but because Indians are exempt from state and local taxes, their presence has increased the tax bill for the town's white residents.</p>
        <p>Now, with the leases about to expire, the hostility is coming out into the open.</p>
        <p>Government Help Sought</p>
        <p>A pamphlet being circulated among whites says: ''White man, you pay Federal, state, county and city taxes, plus $800,000 rent on pieces of earth that the Indian made with his own two hands. Indian, you get a Free Ride!!'' Recently, the consternation over Salamanca's future has begun to spread beyond the town's borders. In Albany and Washington, Salamanca's representatives are pressing the state and Federal governments to split the initial $60 million payment.</p>
        <p>Both of these governments have pledged to help resolve the situation. But both are constrained by financial problems of their own.</p>
        <p>A first-time visitor to Salamanca might have a hard time understanding what all the fuss is about. The town's economy deteriorated long ago, in part because the uncertainty of the lease situation made it impossible to get a mortgage. Half the stores on Main Street are closed, giving the place a half-asleep look, and many of the young people have already left to find jobs elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Nowhere Else to Go</p>
        <p>To many residents, however, Salamanca is the only home they have ever known. The stagnant economy and the uncertain lease situation make it an inexpensive place to live - many homes sell for less than $20,000 - and a large proportion of residents are older people on fixed incomes who have nowhere else to go.</p>
        <p>''People are very uptight about it,'' said one lifetime resident, who identified herself only as a retired school teacher.</p>
        <p>The earliest Salamanca leases were negotiated between the Seneca Indians and white settlers in the mid-1800's when the first railroad companies began to lay tracks through the Allegheny River valley. By many accounts the leases were illegal, but by the time anyone got around to questioning them, Salamanca had become an important railroad hub, and in 1875 Congress, responding to intense lobbying, validated the leases for five years.</p>
        <p>When the five years were up, Congress extended the lease for another 12 years, then for 99 years. The last extension is to expire on Feb. 19, 1991.</p>
        <p>Countdown Begins</p>
        <p>Salamanca has been jittery about its future for years now. Municipal officials have been negotiating a new lease with the Senecas off and on for more than a decade, and for the last three years the local paper, The Salamanca Press, has been printing the number of days left before the lease expires.</p>
        <p>That anxiety only worsened last month, when the team negotiating the new lease announced that it had struck the best deal it could with the Senecas. The deal calls for payments on a new 40-year lease to total $800,000 a year, and it asks the Federal and state governments to pick up the $60 million initial payment. It contains an escalation clause under which payments would increase in tandem with Salamanca's land values.</p>
        <p>Whites in Salamanca greeted the deal with rage, and its fate remains uncertain. For a white owner of a home or business in Salamanca to extend his lease, he will have to sign on to the deal himself, and many whites say they simply will not do so.</p>
        <p>''I think we should say forget it,'' said Shirley Weast, a real estate agent whose lease payments would increase from $7 to $4,700 under the new lease. ''What they're proposing is an absolute death sentence.''</p>
        <p>Just what will happen in February if white residents have not signed new leases is unclear. Some say that their cases would then go to arbitration, while others say it is possible that the land would revert to the Senecas.</p>
        <p>Whatever the whites in Salamanca decide to do, Seneca leaders say they are confident that they will not be cheated this time around. And if the town is frustrated with them, they say they do not have much sympathy.</p>
        <p>''These guys had 99 years to think about the future,'' Mr. Lay, the Seneca president, said. ''It's just poor planning.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
