<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>DirecTV's Stock Has Taken a Beating. Is a Buyback the Fix?</title>
    <meta content="17directv" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/17/technology/17directv.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1710360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="MEDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">DirecTV</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4DF153FF934A25753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>DirecTV's Stock Has Taken a Beating. Is a Buyback the Fix?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">DirecTV's Stock Has Taken a Beating. Is a Buyback the Fix?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been a tough year for shareholders of the DirecTV Group, the satellite television company controlled by Rupert Murdoch.</p>
        <p>Fears about competition from telephone and cable companies have buffeted its stock price, which has fallen 12.9 percent this year. The shares rose 19 cents, or 1.3 percent, on Friday to close at $14.57 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>DirecTV's stock has languished over the past year, amid fears of competition from telephone and cable companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been a tough year for shareholders of the DirecTV Group, the satellite television company controlled by Rupert Murdoch.</p>
        <p>Fears about competition from telephone and cable companies have buffeted its stock price, which has fallen 12.9 percent this year. The shares rose 19 cents, or 1.3 percent, on Friday to close at $14.57 on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>Anxious analysts who have endorsed the stock are hoping shareholders will get a Christmas present as a reward for their loyalty. On Dec. 23, a tax ruling that prohibited DirecTV from buying its own shares will lapse, clearing the way for the company to go on a buying spree if it chooses to do so.</p>
        <p>The analysts point out that the company's healthy balance sheet would permit it to buy back the entire stake of 215 million shares, or 15 percent of the company, that is held by the General Motors Pension Trust, although few of them expect the company to authorize such an aggressive purchase.</p>
        <p>But even a far smaller buyback might give a lift to the stock at a time of increasing concerns about cable competition.</p>
        <p>The cable industry, itself under siege from both the telephone companies and satellite operators, is getting more aggressive at pricing its packages of video, data and voice services. Last week, Comcast, the nation's largest cable company, said it might join in a bid to acquire a stake in AOL from Time Warner, potentially allowing it to offer instant messaging and other AOL services to Comcast customers.</p>
        <p>In June 2004 the Cablevision Systems Corporation introduced a ''triple play'' -- phone calls, Internet access and television channels -- for $89.95 a month. The offer jolted the industry. In just 12 months, Cablevision signed up 174,000 triple-play customers and added about 55,000 new subscribers, the first annual increase for the company in two years, bringing its total to 3 million subscribers. ''Satellite had been eating our lunch,'' Cablevision's chief operating officer, Thomas M. Rutledge, acknowledged in a recent interview.</p>
        <p>Although Cablevision raised the price of the triple play to $115 for subscribers signing up for a second year, Mr. Rutledge said that the churn, or turnover rate, among these subscribers was 18 percent lower than that of other customers.</p>
        <p>The cable packages and Comcast's interest in AOL ''appear to make the competition for home video subscribers more competitive,'' said Craig Moffett, an analyst who follows cable and satellite TV for Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Not that Cablevision has cornered the market. Last year DirecTV added 1.7 million new subscribers, and it added another 730,000 through the second quarter of this year, for a total of 14.7 million subscribers. That makes it the second-largest provider of multichannel home video after Comcast, which has 21 million subscribers.</p>
        <p>In the second quarter that ended June 30, DirecTV reported a profit of $161.5 million, compared with a loss of $13.3 million a year earlier.</p>
        <p>DirecTV's subscriber growth rate has slowed this year, but that may not be all bad. Chase Carey, DirectTV's chief executive, said the company had opted for slower growth as it tried to reduce last year's higher churn levels, which were partly a result of taking on too many customers with weak credit.</p>
        <p>''We have recognized that our churn rate was too high, and we have been monitoring the credit,'' Mr. Carey said.</p>
        <p>Aryeh Bourkoff, a media analyst at UBS Securities, said the market was ''very competitive for video services, and cable is beginning to offer the triple-play bundles, which has improved their competitive positioning, therefore making growth prospects more costly for DirecTV.''</p>
        <p>That specter of increased competition puts pressure on DirecTV to buy its own shares, he said.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Murdoch owns 34 percent of DirecTV's shares through his News Corporation. The General Motors Pension Trust said early last year that it would sell 110 million shares of its stake, though ultimately it sold only half that amount.</p>
        <p>Now there is some speculation that the trust may try to cut a deal with DirecTV to sell its shares to the company at a slight premium, on the theory that DirecTV does not want those shares dumped on the open market. A spokesman for the trust declined to comment, as did Mr. Carey.</p>
        <p>Whether DirecTV will buy shares from the pension trust or the public is not clear, but certainly concern about the sale of the pension fund holdings is weighing on the stock, analysts agree. ''We continue to believe that DirecTV's potential purchase of the G.M. stake would be a big catalyst,'' Douglas Shapiro, of Banc of America Securities, wrote in a recent report. That would eliminate the concern about a major sale that has depressed the stock price.</p>
        <p>Thomas Egan, of Oppenheimer, added: ''They could buy up all its shares with existing cash, which would be a big boost to holders.'' DirecTV has $4 billion in cash and a revolving credit line of $500 million. ''It is the only company in the entertainment space that has more cash than debt,'' Mr. Egan said.</p>
        <p>Owning a satellite TV business had long been a dream of Mr. Murdoch, who is chairman of DirecTV; he bought the shares in 2003 when the company was still a tracking stock of General Motors.</p>
        <p>The link to News Corporation inevitably raises questions of the satellite company's strategy. For example, did DirecTV rush to expand last year, spending heavily for new subscribers but then suffering from high churn, because the additional subscribers gave the News Corporation's cable networks, including Fox News and FX, wider distribution? Mr. Carey says this was not the case.</p>
        <p>Some analysts say they believe that even though growth has slowed, there are opportunities for DirecTV to add families with new homes or those who once had only broadcast TV.</p>
        <p>''As the number of people who take only broadcast declines, the big growth in satellite does not come from cable, it comes from new homes or former broadcast-TV-only homes,'' Mr. Egan said. ''Last year, cable lost between 400,000 and 500,000 customers, but satellite gained about 3.2 million.''</p>
        <p>Not everyone is so sure. Mr. Moffett, of Sanford C. Bernstein, has put a sell rating on the stock, because of competition and because he says he believes the company is entering a tough phase when it will be spending heavily to offer more new equipment: high-definition television and digital video recorders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carey said he was more optimistic because he believed that the cost of equipment was gradually coming down. DirecTV has been able to add subscribers, he said, because ''at the end of the day, the core question is who provides the best television experience.''</p>
        <p>MEDIA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
