<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judges in Trial of Milosevic Order Psychiatric Evaluation</title>
    <meta content="Y14HAG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/14/international/europe/14HAGU.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1440517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Serbia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kosovo (Serbia)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Court of Justice (World Court) (The Hague)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Milosevic, Slobodan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Marlise</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">War Crimes and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War Crimes, Genocide and Crimes Against Humanity</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Yugoslavia</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Milosevic, Slobodan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E5D81630F937A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="820" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judges in Trial of Milosevic Order Psychiatric Evaluation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tribunal Judges Order Psychiatric Evaluation for Milosevic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simons, Marlise</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Nov. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Judges at UN war crimes tribunal in The Hague order psychiatric evaluation of Slobodan Milosevic; former Serb leader's health problems have interrupted hearings, causing delay of almost two months in proceedings (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Slobodan Milosevic's ailing heart has already been checked numerous times; today his judges ordered an evaluation of his mind.</p>
        <p>In a court order issued at the United Nations war crimes tribunal in The Hague, the judges requested ''a written psychiatric report'' about the ''mental condition'' of Mr. Milosevic, the former Yugoslav president, who stands accused of genocide and other crimes in the Balkan wars of the 1990's. They also sought an evaluation of the ''strain'' doctors say Mr. Milosevic is suffering as he conducts his own defense at trial, which began in February.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Slobodan Milosevic's ailing heart has already been checked numerous times; on Wednesday his judges ordered an evaluation of his mind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Slobodan Milosevic's ailing heart has already been checked numerous times; today his judges ordered an evaluation of his mind.</p>
        <p>In a court order issued at the United Nations war crimes tribunal in The Hague, the judges requested ''a written psychiatric report'' about the ''mental condition'' of Mr. Milosevic, the former Yugoslav president, who stands accused of genocide and other crimes in the Balkan wars of the 1990's. They also sought an evaluation of the ''strain'' doctors say Mr. Milosevic is suffering as he conducts his own defense at trial, which began in February.</p>
        <p>The reasons for the judges' request are no secret: Mr. Milosevic's health problems have already interrupted hearings five times -- causing a delay of almost two months. In the past two weeks, ''exhaustion'' has kept him out of court every day but one. Officials said today that hearings would resume next week.</p>
        <p>Zdenko Tomanovic, who heads the legal team that supports Mr. Milosevic outside the courtroom, said he did not yet know what his client's reaction would be. The involvement of a psychiatrist would clearly require Mr. Milosevic's cooperation, but he has often thwarted the court in the past, calling it illegitimate.</p>
        <p>''I understand the judges are interested in his mental capacity, his capacity to concentrate,'' Mr. Tomanovic said in a telephone interview from The Hague. ''They may use this as a reason to impose a defense lawyer. There are some precedents in American cases. But Mr. Milosevic refuses to have a lawyer.''</p>
        <p>Calling on a psychiatrist is unusual but not unheard of, say lawyers familiar with the court's procedures. A Serbian psychiatrist has visited at least two defendants to assess their conduct and was once called in to help a convict cope with a sentence.</p>
        <p>From the beginning, the three international judges have pressed prosecutors to reduce the scope of the complex trial, which involves three Balkan wars and may last two years or more. They have repeatedly expressed concern about Mr. Milosevic's health, as his self-defense -- especially his long cross-examinations of prosecution witnesses -- has clearly taken its toll.</p>
        <p>With their request today, the judges appeared to raise the possibility that the trial may not conclude in its present form. Saying they wanted a full prognosis on Mr. Milosevic's ''future health and his ability to attend court and stand trial.'' They also asked for a new cardiac assessment; the last one was done in July.</p>
        <p>The latest requests stem from the assessment of the prison doctor, Paulus Falke, who informed the court on Tuesday that Mr. Milosevic, 61, still suffered from exhaustion, high blood pressure and stress that affected his state of mind.</p>
        <p>''We have to face reality, the trial is taking its toll,'' a court official said. ''It's not surprising. The burden of a trial is enormous, even without a serious heart condition.''</p>
        <p>Earlier this month Judge Richard May, who presides over the trial, and his two fellow judges called on prosecutors, independent lawyers and Mr. Milosevic himself to suggest ways to avoid an impasse and help end the trial in reasonable time.</p>
        <p>Carla Del Ponte, the chief prosecutor, urged the court to impose a defense counsel ''in order to avoid further disruption and delay and to ensure a fair and expeditious trial.'' By constantly refusing the assistance of counsel, she wrote, Mr. Milosevic ''has inevitably increased the strain on his own health.''</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Nice, the lead prosecutor, told the judges that the indictment, covering crimes attributed to Mr. Milosevic in Bosnia, Croatia and Kosovo in the 1990's, had already reached the ''irreducible minimum.''</p>
        <p>Today the prosecutor's spokeswoman, Florence Hartmann, said a full trial was crucial because the tribunal above all ''has an obligation to the victims of the Balkan wars.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Milosevic has not submitted any suggestions. But last week he called Mrs. Del Ponte's request to impose a lawyer an ''illegal and absurd'' attempt to silence him. He also complained to the two lawyers appointed as ''friends of the court'' to look after his interests, telling them he preferred morning sessions only. When afternoon sessions are held, he said, he has to wait for an hour and a half in a small, windowless room and returns to prison at 5 p.m.</p>
        <p>The friends of the court have not yet made public their proposal. But lawyers familiar with it said it suggests morning hearings only. It also reportedly says that if Mr. Milosevic's health continues to deteriorate because of the trial, it should be terminated ''on medical grounds.'' Finally, if doctors believe it essential for Mr. Milosevic's health, the proposal suggests that the court consider releasing him temporarily.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
