<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shanghai Discovers Its Inner Paris</title>
    <meta content="14PRES$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Travel; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/14/garden/14PRES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1440410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="DESIGN DISPATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shanghai (China)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cranley, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Shanghai</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Shanghai (China)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E3D91F31F937A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shanghai Discovers Its Inner Paris</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shanghai Discovers Its Inner Paris</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>SHANGHAI</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shanghai, once known as Paris of the East, is experiencing renaissance as new wave of foreigners refurbish grand buildings that had been emptied of their charm during decades of Communist-imposed penury; Patrick Cranley is Western entrepreneur instrumental in revitalization and preservation efforts amid scant efforts by municipal government; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PATRICK CRANLEY, one of the Western entrepreneurs revitalizing this once cosmopolitan city, settled into an Art Deco armchair in his sprawling Art Moderne house and sipped a bourbon.</p>
        <p>''It's a placid oasis in the middle of a city operating on hypertime,'' he said of his home, with its high ceilings, stone fireplaces and broad verandas overlooking a large lawn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Today, a new wave of foreigners are refurbishing the grand rooms that had been emptied of their charm by zealous Red Guards and decades of Communist-imposed penury.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PATRICK CRANLEY, one of the Western entrepreneurs revitalizing this once cosmopolitan city, settled into an Art Deco armchair in his sprawling Art Moderne house and sipped a bourbon.</p>
        <p>''It's a placid oasis in the middle of a city operating on hypertime,'' he said of his home, with its high ceilings, stone fireplaces and broad verandas overlooking a large lawn.</p>
        <p>The scene recalls an age when Shanghai was known as the Paris of the East. In the 1920's and 30's, the bungalows and mansions of the city's leafy residential neighborhoods housed thousands of expatriates leading a genteel life far from home. They enjoyed jazz clubs and black-tie balls, horse races and cruises along creeks and canals. They came home to well-stoked fires in Western-style wood-paneled parlors and the shade of elaborate Chinese gardens.</p>
        <p>The Japanese invasion and the Communist revolution ended all that. By the mid-60's, virtually all Westerners had gone, and the houses they left behind were turned into tenements, government offices and public institutions.</p>
        <p>Today, a new wave of foreigners are refurbishing the grand rooms that had been emptied of their charm by zealous Red Guards and decades of Communist-imposed penury. Mr. Cranley and his wife, Tina, who run a consulting firm called AsiaMedia, are among the vanguard.</p>
        <p>The Cranleys, who are in their early 40's, arrived in the city five years ago and quickly spotted one of the casualties of its economic expansion: the pre-World War II residential architecture that gave the city its character.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, construction for an elevated highway flattened a long swath of Art Deco buildings on both sides of what was once Avenue King Edward VII, the road that separated the predominantly British International Settlement from the French Concession. Even the home of Ladislaus Hudec, a Hungarian architect who designed many of Shanghai's most striking buildings, has been razed.</p>
        <p>To bring attention to the vanishing buildings, Mr. Cranley helped found the Shanghai Historic House Association, a group of mostly expatriate residents working to identify endangered buildings and help pay for their preservation.</p>
        <p>''Architecture textures the way we feel, and Shanghai will have a different, indistinct feeling if the lanes and villas are all replaced by high-rises,'' Mr. Cranley said.</p>
        <p>The municipal government has made some effort to save pockets of old Shanghai, including part of a small neighborhood known as New Heaven and Earth, where 1920's buildings are filled with fancy shops and trendy restaurants. But the government's preservation efforts have otherwise been scant, focusing mainly on institutions like the 1925 Hong Kong and Shanghai Bank building, which is the centerpiece of the Bund, the city's famous riverfront strip. Meanwhile, China's nouveau riche prefer things, well, nouveau, and the mainland Chinese generally lack the funds to buy old houses or protect them from the wrecking ball.</p>
        <p>The costly chore of restoring the city's surviving Tudor, Art Deco and Spanish-revival homes has been mostly left to expatriates, whose strategies vary, depending on their means.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Wong, a scion of a major Chinese trading family in prewar Japan and now a Canadian citizen, began salvaging structures slated for demolition several years ago. Today, he has hundreds of dismantled carved-wood interiors sorted and stowed in warehouses. Some buildings are stored almost in their entirety, from roof tiles to floor tiles.</p>
        <p>Walking among the stacks of old wood and stone, in whose shadows unfolded plots and subplots of love and betrayal, he pointed to the balustrade of a staircase leaning against a lintel carved with a classical Chinese scene.</p>
        <p>''Du Yuesheng's house,'' he remarked, identifying the interior of the home of Shanghai's legendary gangster, who controlled many of the city's opium dens and brothels. When the city tore down the house, Mr. Wong bought everything but the bricks and the plumbing.</p>
        <p>He has begun reconstructing a few buildings. A Ming dynasty courtyard house serves as his office. He envisions creating a sort of cultural colony once the place is finished, though the district government would like him to turn it into a tourist attraction.</p>
        <p>Others have taken a more academic approach. Tess Johnston, a former American Foreign Service employee who served as an assistant to John Paul Vann during the Vietnam war, began researching Shanghai's prewar architecture when she first moved here 21 years ago -- a tenure that makes her one of the city's longest-term foreign residents.</p>
        <p>Ms. Johnston has created an exhaustive archive of Shanghai's old neighborhoods, having walked and photographed every street in the French Concession, where much of the city's best residential architecture is concentrated. The archive is stored in antique chests in her home and will eventually go to the Hoover Institution at Stanford University in California.</p>
        <p>Former residents routinely seek her help in finding homes abandoned decades ago. Seeing their elegant dwellings now decrepit and crowded with families may be depressing for them, but it is often exhilarating for Ms. Johnston. ''I am seeing it from the present into the past,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Living in the old houses takes dedication. Few of them have working boilers, so during the winter residents usually rely on space heaters or hot air from dual-use air-conditioners. Water pressure is often weak, the electricity supply meager.</p>
        <p>Shanghai's overheated real estate market has meanwhile pushed the price of even the most run-down old houses to Westchester County levels ($400,000 to more than $5 million, depending on location).</p>
        <p>Because the land is ultimately owned by the state, there is little protection against demolition if the tornado of urban renewal takes an unfortunate turn.</p>
        <p>But the preservationists have made progress by helping to make the old homes fashionable. With foreigners paying $3,000 to $12,000 a month in rent, a small but growing number of local owners are renovating, rather than selling out to developers from Hong Kong, who tend to build high-rises on the sites for the quickest return on their investment.</p>
        <p>And real estate agents now blanket old neighborhoods with fliers looking for owners willing to rent their homes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cranley said that many of the buildings end up gutted and fitted with sheet-rock walls and recessed lighting because only one or two architects or interior designers here are trained in preservation.</p>
        <p>''Our philosophy of historic preservation is that everything about a building is important, part of the story it tells, part of the architect's vision, so it's very important to preserve or restore any part that can be saved,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Once a year, the Shanghai Historic House Association gives a tour, mostly in the French Concession, where the most fashionable people once lived. This year's tour took 230 people to a 1930's house, whose simple facade and black steel door betrayed no hint of the Chinese garden beyond, where the city's oldest Japanese pine tree stands, along with an Italianate stone fountain, its statues beheaded by rampaging Red Guards during the Cultural Revolution.</p>
        <p>''We love living in this old house,'' said Tinita Hughes, who lives there with her husband, a General Motors executive. ''It has character, it has age marks, it has warmth.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hughes said that her favorite time of day is just before dawn, when the street sweepers are out and the storefront noodle and dumpling shops are preparing breakfast.</p>
        <p>''The night parking attendant props his chair in front of our house, the little girl next door watches my dogs, and the restaurateur waves as I pass,'' she said, adding that members of ''the elegant older generation'' often surprise her by stopping and chatting in proper English.</p>
        <p>The Cranleys' home has also been a tour attraction: a three-story manor built by a Chinese textile tycoon in 1946 ''before post-World War II euphoria gave way to apprehension,'' Mr. Cranley said. The tycoon's widow, attended by servants, still lives in a separate apartment on the third floor.</p>
        <p>During the Cultural Revolution, the owners of the house were moved with other wealthy families to another building in the neighborhood. The house became a library until the family got it back in 1982.</p>
        <p>The faint remnants of a Maoist slogan could still be read on the wall surrounding the property until it was painted over this year.</p>
        <p>''It takes time and effort on the part of preservationists to raise public awareness of the value of old buildings,'' Mr. Cranley said, adding that he hopes that the city government will realize that preserving at least some of old Shanghai is good economics.</p>
        <p>''Tourism is big business here and getting bigger,'' he said. ''More important in the long run, I think, is that preservation is good for the city's soul.''</p>
        <p>DESIGN DISPATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
