<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>British Firefighters, Defying Government, Strike Over Wages</title>
    <meta content="Y14BRI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/14/international/europe/14BRIT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1440550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E5D71630F937A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>British Firefighters, Defying Government, Strike Over Wages</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">British Firefighters, Defying Government, Strike Over Wages</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Nov. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Britain's 50,000 full-time firefighters ignore government entreaties and carry out first national pay strike in 25 years, closing city firehouses and leaving military with fleet of aging fire tenders to respond to emergencies; photo; 48-hour walkout is first in series planned before Christmas (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ignoring last-minute government entreaties, Britain's 50,000 full-time firefighters marched out tonight on their first national pay strike in 25 years, closing down most urban firehouses and leaving the military with its fleet of aging fire tenders to respond to emergencies from car wrecks to blazing buildings.</p>
        <p>Some commentators called the strike the government's most serious nationwide confrontation with organized labor since Prime Minister Tony Blair took office in 1997, and thus a major test of Mr. Blair's resolve to resist the brand of labor union activism that bedeviled his party in the past.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Britain's 50,000 full-time firefighters marched out on Wednesday on their first national pay strike in 25 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ignoring last-minute government entreaties, Britain's 50,000 full-time firefighters marched out tonight on their first national pay strike in 25 years, closing down most urban firehouses and leaving the military with its fleet of aging fire tenders to respond to emergencies from car wrecks to blazing buildings.</p>
        <p>Some commentators called the strike the government's most serious nationwide confrontation with organized labor since Prime Minister Tony Blair took office in 1997, and thus a major test of Mr. Blair's resolve to resist the brand of labor union activism that bedeviled his party in the past.</p>
        <p>The 48-hour stoppage is the first in a series planned between now and Christmas Day. It has evoked comparisons with Britain's ''winter of discontent'' in the late 1970's, when a welling of much broader industrial unrest brought down a previous Labor government.</p>
        <p>It also raised questions about strains on the armed forces, already stretched by deployments in the Balkans and poised for possible action in the campaign against President Saddam Hussein of Iraq.</p>
        <p>Some 18,500 members of the army, navy and air force have been ordered to stand in for the striking firefighters, who have rejected an offer of an 11 percent pay raise over two years and are demanding a 40 percent raise to bring their basic annual wage to $46,000.</p>
        <p>The armed forces have some 827 fire tenders, built in the 1950's and known as ''Green Goddesses'' for their color and their onetime logo depicting the goddess of fire. They were last deployed in force in the 1977 firefighters' strike, which lasted nine weeks.</p>
        <p>Thousands of part-time firefighters, who provide more than half of the fire service in rural areas and small towns, have vowed not to strike. But the stoppage has raised worries that the lumbering ''Green Goddesses'' are poor substitutes for the regular Fire Brigade's 5,000 faster vehicles.</p>
        <p>Andy Gilchrist, the leader of the Fire Brigade Union, said firefighters would respond to a ''catastrophic incident'' -- an apparent reference to the kind of terrorist attack of which Mr. Blair warned anew this week.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gilchrist and his members dismissed an appeal by Deputy Prime Minister John Prescott to call off the strike one hour before it began. ''Be reasonable, not unreasonable,'' Mr. Prescott said. ''Suspend the strike. I appeal to all firefighters -- don't walk. Talk.''</p>
        <p>But at 6 o'clock on a gloomy evening, firefighters across the land, some in distinctive brown or navy blue uniforms, walked out of firehouses to form picket lines, locking away their firefighting vehicles and equipment.</p>
        <p>''There's a feeling of sorrow, anger, frustration,'' said Ian McGill, a firefighter in northern England as he went out on strike. ''I walked out of this door with a sad heart.''</p>
        <p>Within five minutes of the start of the job action, a ''Green Goddess'' was reported en route to a blazing car in South Wales.</p>
        <p>In London the strike also brought the closing on safety grounds of 22 of the London Underground's 275 subway stations, themselves the target of a rash of strikes earlier in the year. Adding to the concerns about labor unrest and safety, firefighters and security guards at seven major British airports, including Heathrow, have threatened a series of one-day strikes likely to cause travel chaos over the year-end holidays.</p>
        <p>Other public service workers, like nurses, police officers and teachers, are also expressing discontent about their pay.</p>
        <p>In Parliament today, Mr. Blair accused the firefighters of choosing ''confrontation,'' and he insisted that their demands, if met, would unleash a wave of similar demands for pay increases from teachers, nurses and police officers.</p>
        <p>''No government with inflation at around 2 percent could yield to a wage claim of 40 percent,'' Mr. Blair said. ''It is not just this government that could not contemplate such a thing. There is no government on earth that could yield to such a thing.</p>
        <p>''If we said yes to all, the consequence is so clear that it hardly bears spelling out.''</p>
        <p>The firefighters say their 40 percent pay demand is meant to bring their wages to a level commensurate with their professional skills. They argue that particularly in London, their wages are not enough to feed, house and clothe their families. Many have second jobs.</p>
        <p>For their part, government negotiators have linked their offer of 11 percent over two years to demands for changes in the Fire Brigade's union-backed working conditions, which include provisions like a ban on advance scheduling of overtime work. Mr. Gilchrist, the union leader, called that offer laughable.</p>
        <p>The deployment of troops during the stoppage had an unexpected consequence today, halving the number of soldiers available to parade during the ceremonial state opening of Parliament. Hugh Robertson, an opposition legislator and former army officer, said the strike had also led to the cancellation of leave for soldiers returning from Bosnia.</p>
        <p>''This all goes to show how badly overstretched the army is at present,'' he said. ''I further suspect that a great many of these same troops will soon be on standby for operations in the gulf.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
