<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Turns His Energies To Bush Battle</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="515835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="NEXT LEVEL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIMARIES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, EDMUND G JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TONER, ROBIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Primaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DE1138F931A15750C0A964958260" item-length="1167" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Turns His Energies To Bush Battle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TONER, ROBIN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After all the candidate forums, all the Holiday Inns, all the box lunches, all the tarmac news conferences, all the panic and the exhaustion and the adrenaline buzz of watching large groups of people whipsawed by gossip and rumor and personal attacks, the Democrats finally seem close to choosing a nominee.</p>
        <p>Sometimes it felt like Lonesome Dove, a cross-country cattle drive with amphetamine timing. Now, of course, it will begin anew.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After all the candidate forums, all the Holiday Inns, all the box lunches, all the tarmac news conferences, all the panic and the exhaustion and the adrenaline buzz of watching large groups of people whipsawed by gossip and rumor and personal attacks, the Democrats finally seem close to choosing a nominee.</p>
        <p>Sometimes it felt like Lonesome Dove, a cross-country cattle drive with amphetamine timing. Now, of course, it will begin anew.</p>
        <p>Governor Bill Clinton of Arkansas was making all the appropriate comments last week, saying that he took nothing for granted and would continue to campaign hard for the nomination in the remaining 21 primaries and caucuses. But former Senator Paul E. Tsongas's rueful withdrawal after his losses in Illinois and Michigan left the Governor from Arkansas as the presumed nominee, with seven times the delegates of his remaining rival, the maverick former California Governor Edmund G. Brown Jr.</p>
        <p>Already, Democratic leaders, who created this jam-packed primary schedule in hopes of producing an early nominee -- and, miraculously, seem to have achieved just that -- were turning their attention to George Bush.</p>
        <p>Over at the Democratic National Committee, where memories of how the Democrats were out-campaigned and out-researched in 1988 run deep, they have been clipping and studying and looking for booby traps in the Bush record.  Down at Bush-Quayle headquarters, similar "opposition research" is under way on the Democrats. Out on the campaign trail, the shape of the coming debate is already emerging.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Clinton has his way, this will be an election about change -- yes or no. The 1980's, he argues, are over, their economic policies repudiated, and the country desperately needs a fresh new direction. He campaigned against Mr. Tsongas by calling him a man who wanted to continue "trickle down" economics, notably a cut in the tax on capital gains, rather than redress the inequities of the decade with measures like a middle-class tax cut and greater investment in education and training.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's aides believe his message needs fairly little retrofitting for the general election. From their perspective, he has simply left behind the body double for the real thing. "George Bush is the ultimate believer in the 1980's and the ultimate believer in trickle down," said James Carville, a top strategist for the Clinton campaign. "George Bush wouldn't know change if it ran over him."</p>
        <p>Robert Teeter, the chairman of the Bush campaign, counters calmly that it will be easy to avoid getting trapped in the role of Mr. Status Quo Incumbent, a role that every incumbent who can read polls desperately fears this year. "The obstacle to change is Congress," Mr. Teeter said in an interview on Friday. "Every poll shows that the number of people who recognize that is increasing. And it's not a Republican Congress."</p>
        <p>The Republicans, in other words, are not foolish enough to cede this ground to the opposition. It may be harder for a party in power for 12 years to present itself as an agent of change, but Ronald Reagan did it deftly in 1988: "We</p>
        <p>are</p>
        <p>the change," he told the Republican convention in New Orleans. Ready for Something New</p>
        <p>As Mr. Bush vetoed the Congressional tax measure late last week, asserting that it would not ease the nation's economic plight, there were a lot of references to change.</p>
        <p>"If the Democratic leadership that runs the status quo Congress will not help us change America, we have to change it without them," he said. "Change is nothing to fear." The idea behind all this, of course, is simple enough: Eight out of ten Americans in recent polls say the economy is in bad shape, and huge majorities have told poll takers that they think the country is headed in the wrong direction. Change is the last thing they fear.</p>
        <p>Oratory can only help an incumbent President so much; what Mr. Bush probably needs most is continued improvement in the economy. He has other, related needs: His approval ratings have been hovering at 40 percent. The old Reagan coalition seems to be fraying badly; in the 1980's, a growing economy helped keep socially liberal baby boomers and conservative Christians under the same tent. And Patrick J. Buchanan's angry primary attacks casting Mr. Bush as a man who breaks his word and jettisons his principles have opened some wounds.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Clinton's path is anything but clear, beginning with the approaching primaries in Connecticut and New York. To begin with, there is Mr. Brown, who shows very little inclination to fade away. The endgame with him may not be as difficult as the endgame was with the Rev. Jesse Jackson in 1984 and 1988, because it will not involve the sensitive issue of racial respect; the political always seemed fused with the personal when a nominee negotiated with Mr. Jackson.  Why Democrats Worry</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Brown is viewed by many Democrats as a dangerous opponent because he seems to revel in throwing bombs. The Clinton forces will be trying to undercut his "we the people" appeal by focusing on his support for a flat tax, which they will present as a giveaway to the rich -- which, of course, fits neatly with their general election themes.</p>
        <p>The deeper issue for Mr. Clinton is the fear within the party that some new character issue will emerge. Even those who dislike Mr. Clinton are somewhat amazed at his ability to plow through charges of marital infidelity, of manipulating his draft status to avoid Vietnam, and, most recently, of conflict of interest stemming from the partnership of his wife, Hillary, in a law firm that does business with the state of Arkansas.</p>
        <p>But Democrats still worry. Many in the party believe that anything that distracts the public's attention from the economy this fall will hurt the Democrats' chances.</p>
        <p>The Clintons seem to be trying to appeal to generational solidarity: if the standard is perfection, Mr. Clinton asks, who could pass? And, by extension, should the messy lives of the baby boomers forever foreclose them from power?</p>
        <p>For all of that, Mr. Clinton has been given a great gift. This was a short campaign, waged largely by Presidential novices who were always scrambling for money and the limelight; they fell quickly and they fell hard. They also left with considerable grace, as Mr. Tsongas did last week.</p>
        <p>Always left standing was Mr. Clinton, maneuvering through the complicated politics of South Florida or Chicago's City Hall, picking up endorsements wherever he went, eyes glittering and very, very hungry.</p>
        <p>For all the talk of demographics and the broad forces of economics and culture, Mr. Clinton's campaign teaches once again that simple fire in the belly can do a lot. After the emotional detachment of Michael S. Dukakis, after the ambivalence and calculation of the Democrats who pondered a race last year but decided against it, Mr. Clinton and his crew provide a dose of political id for the Democrats.</p>
        <p>They want the White House and they want it bad.  NEXT LEVEL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
