<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Her Greatest Role</title>
    <meta content="27JEFFERT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="885923"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Eva Le Gallienne</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheehy, Helen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jefferson, Margo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">le gallienne, eva</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Eva Le Gallienne: A Biography (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E1DB1230F934A15753C1A960958260" item-length="1366" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Her Greatest Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Margo Jefferson</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jefferson, Margo</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Margo Jefferson reviews book Eva Le Gallienne: A Biography by Helen Sheehy; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eva Le Gallienne  A Biography.  By Helen Sheehy.  Illustrated. 531 pp. New York:  Alfred A. Knopf. $37.50.</p>
        <p>Eva Le Gallienne claimed descent, and rightly so, from that great line of theatrical master builders and sacred monsters who acted, directed, championed playwrights, ran their own companies and gave their audiences something that felt like intimations of immortality. There was Edwin Booth, Sarah Bernhardt, Eleonora Duse, Henry Irving, Minnie Madden Fiske. But Le Gallienne is one of ours -- a creature of the 20th, not the 19th, century. She was born in 1899, began acting in 1915 and died in 1991. She was a star on and off Broadway; a founder of America's repertory theater movement; a woman of letters who produced forcefully elegant translations of Ibsen and Hans Christian Andersen. And she was the kind of character an actress would long to play: austere and disciplined, lustful and sybaritic; arrogant, high-minded and -- when she chose -- uncannily seductive. Lucky you if you were old enough to have seen her in the flesh, or even in some of those lofty, heavy-breathing 1950's and 60's television productions of theater chestnuts and masterworks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eva Le Gallienne  A Biography.  By Helen Sheehy.  Illustrated. 531 pp. New York:  Alfred A. Knopf. $37.50.</p>
        <p>Eva Le Gallienne claimed descent, and rightly so, from that great line of theatrical master builders and sacred monsters who acted, directed, championed playwrights, ran their own companies and gave their audiences something that felt like intimations of immortality. There was Edwin Booth, Sarah Bernhardt, Eleonora Duse, Henry Irving, Minnie Madden Fiske. But Le Gallienne is one of ours -- a creature of the 20th, not the 19th, century. She was born in 1899, began acting in 1915 and died in 1991. She was a star on and off Broadway; a founder of America's repertory theater movement; a woman of letters who produced forcefully elegant translations of Ibsen and Hans Christian Andersen. And she was the kind of character an actress would long to play: austere and disciplined, lustful and sybaritic; arrogant, high-minded and -- when she chose -- uncannily seductive. Lucky you if you were old enough to have seen her in the flesh, or even in some of those lofty, heavy-breathing 1950's and 60's television productions of theater chestnuts and masterworks.</p>
        <p>Helen Sheehy's book is the second Le Gallienne biography to appear in the last four years. Robert A. Schanke's ''Shattered Applause: The Lives of Eva Le Gallienne,'' published in 1992, takes an aggressive, melodramatic line. Mr. Schanke's Le Gallienne is an imperious diva who is damaged by a distant and critical mother, threatened by a male-dominated theater establishment and tortured by her own vanity as well as her closeted lesbianism. Turn to Ms. Sheehy and you'll find each scene written, directed and played quite differently. (The backdrop of the male-dominated theater establishment remains intact from one book to another, but that's because it remains intact in life from one era to another.)</p>
        <p>Ms. Sheehy's Le Gallienne is an intellectually and emotionally rigorous artist. Her mother is possessive but utterly supportive. Her vanity is largely an excess of perfectionism, and she is true to her sexuality despite the laws and prejudices of the day.</p>
        <p>Of the two writers, Ms. Sheehy has the advantage in terms of research: she had full access to Le Gallienne's diaries, letters, scrapbooks, scripts and unpublished manuscripts. She lets Le Gallienne's words and thoughts take center stage and her prose glides along at a courteous, stately pace. Nevertheless, I think that she is too reverent and pious -- so determined to give us the portrait of a heroine and role model that the darkness and the suffering are muted, rendered in soft, gentle focus.</p>
        <p>And this is a shame -- two flawed interpretations (the first overwrought, the second overly genteel) of a potentially great role. For I do find Le Gallienne heroic, not to mention dashing. She believed that great actors should take in everything -- human and animal behavior, literature, philosophy, music, the skills of a great circus clown, fencer or dancer. She wanted them to draw on every resource of the body, mind and soul. That's what she worked to do and that's why she's worth reading about.</p>
        <p>Her parents were ambitious minor writers in touch with the major writers of their day. Her English father, Richard, was a matinee-idol esthete, a companion of the aging Oscar Wilde and the young W. B. Yeats. Her Danish mother, Julie Norregaard, was a journalist and feminist who revered Ibsen and wrote about fashion and the arts.</p>
        <p>The equation works out nicely: two intellectually progressive artists who champion free thought and free heterosexual love produce a daughter who becomes a major artist and a champion of free thought and free (freely chosen, freely given) homosexual love. On and off the stage, Eva combined her father's fin de siecle grandeur with Julie's controlled and somewhat cutting lucidity. (She also inherited Richard's alcoholism and Julie's intractable solitude.)</p>
        <p>Her parents parted bitterly and dramatically when she was 4: Richard went to America to seek his fortune as a literary lion and Julie moved to Paris, learned millinery and opened her own hat shop. She left the daily supervision of her daughter to a high-minded, upstanding English nanny (a canny substitution for the missing high-minded, upstanding English father), and she supervised Eva's education with passion and intelligence. Great books, theater, art, dance, gymnastics and three languages.</p>
        <p>Eva was stage-struck at the age of 7 when she saw the 62-year-old Bernhardt play Prince Charming in ''The Sleeping Beauty.'' (Don't laugh; what's the point of stage magic if it doesn't work against any and all odds?) She studied acting in London (her first teacher was Constance Collier, whose artful sendup of a thespian pedagogue can be seen in the movie ''Stage Door'') and made her debut on the London stage at the age of 16, playing a cockney maid. She made her debut on the New York stage six months later, offering audiences what she ruefully called an ''astonishing portrait of a colored maid with very bright blue eyes shining out of a smeary chocolate-colored face and speaking a grotesquely bewildering dialect: part British, part cockney, with here and there a dash of Irish.''</p>
        <p>The versatility called for that first year was a little silly. But Le Gallienne became a truly astonishing actress as the 20's and 30's progressed. She played the muted, tenacious and masochistic Julie in ''Liliom'' (we know it by its descendant, ''Carousel''); the imperiously befuddled White Queen in ''Alice in Wonderland''; Juliet; Camille; and Peter Pan. (She was a real lost boy, all dash, jealousy and rage, the screenwriter Stewart Stern recalls: she made flying seem as thrilling and menacing as Marlon Brando would make motorcycle riding 30 years later.) She played the insidious, tormented and masterful Hedda Gabler; she played most of Ibsen's women and echoed Shakespeare's tribute to Cleopatra when she praised their ''infinite variety.''</p>
        <p>In 1926 she left Broadway to found her own repertory theater. The vision of quality plays at modest prices that we associate with pioneers like Margo Jones (the subject of Ms. Sheehy's last book), Zelda Fichlander and Joseph Papp goes back to Le Gallienne. Her motto, displayed on every Civic Repertory Theater program, was: ''The theater should be an instrument for giving, not a machinery for getting.'' Shaky finances forced her to close the company 10 years later, and she spurned the chance to direct the Government's W.P.A. theater division. (Her reasons looked noble then and look willful and shortsighted now.) She tried again with the National Repertory Theater in the 1940's but it, too, folded. And she was thrown into the Gobi Desert that actresses call looking for work after you've entered your middle years.</p>
        <p>She took to the road, lecturing and performing scenes from classic plays (a highbrow variant of the one-woman show that so often awaits women who've entered the middle years). She went through drinking and depression, but began acting, directing and touring with repertory companies.</p>
        <p>''This country robs old people -- especially women -- of confidence in a quite wicked way,'' she said in 1971. Five years later she got the last and the best laugh in a revival of ''The Royal Family,'' George S. Kaufman and Edna Ferber's 1927 homage to the Barrymores and to the nonstop dramas and pratfalls of life in the theater. Le Gallienne was beguiling, she was steely, she floated down a curving flight of stairs and demonstrated some suave fencing moves. She got a death scene too, and she did it magnificently. (If you missed it on stage you can see it on tape at the Museum of Broadcasting.)</p>
        <p>Fanny Cavendish, the grande dame, is alone on stage, reading a script and planning her entrance. She is speaking the lines aloud softly. She walks up a few steps, turns and walks down, arms extended, as if greeting a court or lover. She stops as her body contorts slightly. She tries to stand upright and go on; then as she falls into her chair, her back to us, this trifle of a play has been transformed utterly. We have watched a woman try to vanquish death.</p>
        <p>Margo Jefferson is a cultural critic for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Margo Jefferson is a cultural critic for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
