<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A G.O.P. Stronghold Starts to Lean Toward the Democrats</title>
    <meta content="27HAMP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="AMERICAN PROFILES -- New Hampshire" name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="885738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Hampshire</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rimer, Sara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shaheen, Jeanne (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lamontagne, Ovide</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dole, Bob</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Hampshire</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DE1639F934A15753C1A960958260" item-length="1841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A G.O.P. Stronghold Starts to Lean Toward the Democrats</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARA RIMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rimer, Sara</byline>
      <dateline>DERRY, N.H.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democrats are making inroads in staunchly Republican New Hampshire; State Sen Jeanne Shaheen, Democrat, has wide lead over conservative Republican Ovide Lamontagne in gubernatorial race, Pres Clinton leads Bob Dole and Democrats are in competitive Congressional races; Shaheen has strong support among Republicans, particularly among women; map; table; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The sugar maples that line the roads here are a blaze of gold and red. The farmhouse where Robert Frost once lived and wrote poems has closed to visitors for the season. So has Clam Haven, the seafood shack down the road.</p>
        <p>Still, this fall is not like all the others in Derry. For the first time in 20 years, the Democrats have set up a campaign office in what has been a staunchly Republican town in this staunchly Republican state.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The sugar maples that line the roads here are a blaze of gold and red. The farmhouse where Robert Frost once lived and wrote poems has closed to visitors for the season. So has Clam Haven, the seafood shack down the road.</p>
        <p>Still, this fall is not like all the others in Derry. For the first time in 20 years, the Democrats have set up a campaign office in what has been a staunchly Republican town in this staunchly Republican state.</p>
        <p>''Derry has been a black hole for the Democrats,'' Michael King, the chairman of the New Hampshire Democratic Party, said at a recent celebration marking the opening of the new headquarters. ''Democrats here have been afraid to come out of their houses.''</p>
        <p>Not this year.</p>
        <p>Dozens of Democrats, and even some Republicans reveled on Main Street at the balloon-festooned campaign office in what used to be the Woman's Shop, next to J. J. Pizza. They wore buttons proclaiming their allegiance to Bill Clinton -- and Jeanne Shaheen.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Shaheen, a three-term State Senator with a reputation as a pragmatist, is running for Governor.</p>
        <p>The latest poll by the University of New Hampshire Survey Center for WMUR-TV in Manchester, released earlier this month, gave her a 19-point lead over her conservative Republican opponent, Ovide Lamontagne, the former chairman of the State Board of Education. The same poll showed that 30 percent of Republicans support Mrs. Shaheen. If she wins, she will be the first Democratic Governor in New Hampshire since 1980 -- and the first elected female chief executive in the state's history.</p>
        <p>Rick and Susan Katzenberg, who are Democrats, recently gave a party for Mrs. Shaheen at their house in Amherst and most of the 80 guests were Republican. The Katzenbergs were delighted.</p>
        <p>''We've never had this many Republicans in the house before,'' Mrs. Katzenberg, an antiques dealer, said as neighbors chatted over coffee in her living room.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Shaheen's standing just over a week from Election Day parallels what is happening in national races in New Hampshire. Bill Clinton has a substantial lead here over his Republican challenger, Bob Dole, and Democrats are in competitive races for the Senate and the House.</p>
        <p>This is New Hampshire? Some things used to be certain here. The leaves would change in fall. There would be no sales or income tax. Republicans, for the most part, would dominate the political scene.</p>
        <p>''For the first time in history, this is a two-party state,'' said Dayton Duncan, who was the chief of staff to the last Democratic governor, Hugh Gallen, elected in 1978. ''It used to be that the most Democrats could hope for was one or two races near the top that might be competitive. This is the first time Democrats can compete everywhere.''</p>
        <p>The turn of events for Democrats here has stunned John Ellis, a columnist for The Boston Globe, who has followed New Hampshire politics for 25 years. ''It runs counter to everything I know,'' he said. ''It's as if you told me Fidelity is in the business of making cars. I'd say, 'No, they're in the business of selling mutual funds.' I can't believe any of them can win in New Hampshire. It would be like Utah electing Kennedy and Dukakis.''</p>
        <p>To be sure, no one is ready to predict fundamental, or long-term change in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>''I don't think this is a repudiation of the Republican Party,'' said R. Kelly Myers, director of the University of New Hampshire Survey Center. ''I don't think we're in the midst of a Democratic tide here. What we have is a unique set of circumstances befitting the Democratic Party. The economy has turned around sharply since Clinton took office. It's like night and day here. The President can take the credit for that. And Dole is not an attractive alternative.''</p>
        <p>As for the Governor's race, Mr. Kelly said, Mrs. Shaheen is a moderate at a time when moderate candidates are succeeding.</p>
        <p>''She's running a good campaign,'' he said. ''If you look at previous elections, the Democratic candidates in New Hampshire were not particularly attractive.</p>
        <p>''Come back in two years. The Republicans could own everything again. And don't count them out yet -- even this year.''</p>
        <p>Tom Rath, a lawyer from Concord and longtime Republican political analyst, explained the developments this way: ''Republicans here and all around the country are suffering an enthusiasm deficit. I don't think New Hampshire is changing. We have always been a centrist state. I don't think this means that the ideology or the political leanings of the state have actually changed. It's more a commentary that party identification is less important than it was.''</p>
        <p>He said that the bitter Republican Presidential primary turned off a lot of moderate Republicans. And the Granite State simply has never warmed up to Bob Dole.</p>
        <p>Tom Marquis, a book distributor from Nashua, and a Republican, said that he will vote for Mr. Dole. But his support is hardly enthusiastic.</p>
        <p>''I'd rather vote for three million people other than Bob Dole,'' he said, adding that he has ruled out Bill Clinton as untrustworthy.</p>
        <p>In a state that fiercely proclaims its independence with the motto ''Live Free or Die'' on its license plates, one of the keys to Mrs. Shaheen's success was her decision to take ''the pledge,'' as it is known, to oppose any income or sales tax. In doing so, she may have learned from the experience of a predecessor, Deborah Arnesen, a Democrat, who campaigned as the ''tax lady'' in the 1992 gubernatorial race and advocated a broad-based tax. She lost to Stephen Merrill, a Republican who is not seeking re-election. Ms. Arnesen is now in a close House race.</p>
        <p>There is another explanation: The inclination of women to support Democrats nationally this year extends to New Hampshire. The University of New Hampshire poll shows Mrs. Shaheen, 49 and the mother of three, leading among women by 30 percentage points, though by only 8 points among men.</p>
        <p>''She's bringing New Hampshire into the 21st century,'' said Maureen Barrows, an administrator at a mental hospital who lives in Exeter. ''She's practical. She's someone who pays attention to detail. She's not someone who will waste our money.''</p>
        <p>Most of the guests at the Amherst house party were not only Republicans, they were women. They listened admiringly as Mrs. Shaheen talked about financing statewide kindergarten and lowering electric rates -- the state has the highest in the country.</p>
        <p>Although she is not only trying to capitalize on her sex, women voters clearly relate. ''She has that mom quality,'' saud Kitten Stearns, who intends to vote for Mrs. Shaheen.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Stearns is a moderate Republican. So is Mrs. Barrows.</p>
        <p>''Not all Republicans are right-wing extremists,'' Mrs. Barrows said.. ''There's a group of us who are very, very moderate.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Barrows, who is 60 and ran unsuccessfully for the House in 1992, said she was supporting Mr. Dole. Mr. Lamontagne is another story. Mrs. Barrows, who favors a woman's right to abortion, said some of his positions are extreme.</p>
        <p>The Republican gubernatorial candidate has said that he opposes abortion except in cases where the mother's life is in danger. As chairman of the state board of education, he blocked the state from applying for Federal education money last year because, he said, there were too many strings attached. He also supported the teaching of creationism in public schools in the town of Merrimack, which was battling over the issue a year ago.</p>
        <p>A lawyer, he has never held elective office.</p>
        <p>A month ago, Mrs. Barrows confided her doubts about Mr. Lamontagne to another Republican in town. ''I told him, 'I'd love to be brave enough to vote for Jeanne Shaheen,' '' she said. ''He said, 'Here's her home number. Call Billy.' ''</p>
        <p>Billy, as he is known in New Hampshire, is Bill Shaheen, a lawyer, who gave up his job as district judge to campaign for his wife. Mrs. Barrows told him she wanted to help -- without openly declaring her support. Then, two weeks ago, she decided to go public. ''I said, 'What am I pussyfooting around for? This is nuts.' ''</p>
        <p>Susan McLane, a Republican who served 25 years as a member of the State Legislature, is also supporting Jeanne Shaheen -- and the Democratic candidates for Congress, and Bill Clinton. Last spring Mrs. McLane switched her political registration to Independent. Last month she became a Democrat.</p>
        <p>''I was a liberal Republican,'' Mrs. McLane said. ''The Republican Party changed. I decided it was dishonest to stay Republican.''</p>
        <p>It is the talk of the state. Mrs. McLane, whose husband is the grandson of a former Governor of New Hampshire, was an icon of Republican politics in New Hampshire. She was a state legislator for 25 years. She gave the first party for George Bush in New Hampshire, at her house in Concord, in 1978. Barbara Bush stayed at her lake house.</p>
        <p>''I lent her my bathing suit,'' Mrs. McLane said. ''She forgot hers.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Shaheen was introduced at the Katzenbergs' party by Pixie Lown, a former Republican state legislator. This is the first time Mrs. Lown is supporting a Democratic candidate. She said she was driven to it by the candidacy of Mr. Lamontagne, whom she regards as extreme.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Lamontagne, who is 39 and has three children, has appealed to the state's conservative residents.</p>
        <p>At a recent forum sponsored by the Merrimack Taxpayers Association, the room was filled with his supporters, including April Sarasin, a 37-year-old school bus driver and mother of three. Describing herself as ''pro-life,'' she said she was concerned that there was too much government and feared that tough economic times would return. ''I'm concerned we're not going to be able to keep living in New Hampshire,'' Mrs. Sarasin said. ''We're going to have to move. There are a lot of very vocal liberals moving into town.''</p>
        <p>Even so, the difficulty facing Republicans here was summed up by Duane Martin, who was taking a break between games at the Merrimack Ten Pin Bowling Center.</p>
        <p>A self-described diehard Republican and a carpenter, Mr. Martin discounted the talk about an improving economy in New Hampshire.</p>
        <p>''I'm not making any more money than I was 10 years ago,'' he said. ''The rich are getting richer the poor are getting poorer. The Democrats are giving too much away; the government is out of control.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, he said: ''I'm thinking of voting for Clinton.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
