<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Central America Reminded Of Its Own Era of Conflict</title>
    <meta content="20CENT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/20/international/americas/20CENT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1335285"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latin America</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Managua (Nicaragua)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Castro, Fidel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFD6133EF933A15753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1035" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Central America Reminded Of Its Own Era of Conflict</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Central America Reminded of Its Own Era of Conflict</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gonzalez, David</byline>
      <dateline>MANAGUA, Nicaragua, Oct. 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United States is courting allies in its war against terrorism among Central Asian nations, some saddled with human rights problems; some in Latin America offer cautious advice from their own bitter experience from era when US supported Latin American dictatorships with atrocious human rights records (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The war against terrorism may be focused on Central Asia, but it has revived fears and memories across the political spectrum in Central America, where the United States was long ensnared in civil wars and skulduggery in the battle against Communism.</p>
        <p>El Salvador and Guatemala have eagerly responded to the American effort by beefing up armies and military budgets, alarming human rights advocates who fear a setback to the peace accords that ended long and violent conflicts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The war against terrorism may be focused on Central Asia, but it has revived fears and memories across the political spectrum in Central America.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The war against terrorism may be focused on Central Asia, but it has revived fears and memories across the political spectrum in Central America, where the United States was long ensnared in civil wars and skulduggery in the battle against Communism.</p>
        <p>El Salvador and Guatemala have eagerly responded to the American effort by beefing up armies and military budgets, alarming human rights advocates who fear a setback to the peace accords that ended long and violent conflicts.</p>
        <p>In Nicaragua, where the Sandinistas are seeking to capture the presidency in a tight election next month, campaign advertisements for the right-of-center parties incessantly remind voters of the Sandinista revolution's close ties to terrorist governments.</p>
        <p>But there is fear, too, of unlearned lessons from an era when the United States supported Latin American dictatorships with atrocious human rights records.</p>
        <p>As the United States now courts allies among Central Asian nations torn by regional differences and saddled with their own human rights problems, some people here offer cautious advice from their own bitter experience.</p>
        <p>Sergio Ramírez, a former Sandinista vice president who has since broken with the party, noted that for political reasons, Pakistan and its military ruler have been embraced since the Sept. 11 attacks on the United States.</p>
        <p>''That is what happened in Latin America during the cold war,'' he said. ''The United States dealt with people like Pinochet or Somoza for reasons of national security and allowed them to do what they wanted because they were struggling against Communism. But that guarantee against Communism resulted in greater internal wars and deaths among our own people.''</p>
        <p>It has been difficult, Mr. Ramírez said, to talk about such things, since no one wishes to appear insensitive to the suffering in the United States or to condone terrorist acts. Instead, memories of the region's past conflicts have colored the local response to the attacks in familiar ways.</p>
        <p>Since Sept. 11, Guatemala has sought increases for a presidential security detail that has been linked to human rights abuses and political assassinations. Honduras, which was the base of operations for the contra army that fought the Sandinistas, has sought tens of millions of dollars more for its military.</p>
        <p>In El Salvador, the government cited national security concerns when it sent 400 soldiers and police officers to take over the international airport and main seaport, barring entry to the more than 200 workers employed in cargo handling and security. Legislation was also passed to give the president more control over intelligence matters.</p>
        <p>Coming after years of civil war and military juntas, those moves are troubling to those who now fear that governments might use the fight against terrorism as an excuse to reassert power they lost in peace accords.</p>
        <p>''In part it is a knee-jerk reaction: the small boy wants to be with the big boys, to show his loyalty and to be part of the bigger international picture,'' said the Rev. Rodolfo Cardenal, the vice rector of the University of Central America in San Salvador. ''But it is a bit over the top. The Salvadoran ports are not installations of any real international security interest.''</p>
        <p>He and others in the region said that rather than seek to strengthen armies, governments would be better off cracking down on the lucrative trade in alien smuggling or curtailing violent crime.</p>
        <p>For those who fought in Nicaragua's jungles in the 1980's, the current military campaign in Afghanistan seems familiar. Veterans of the contra army in Nicaragua said that they understood the need for the United States to take quick action, and that they saw the Northern Alliance as their latter-day counterpart. But they also said their battle against a single foe had been less complicated than this one.</p>
        <p>''This is not like Latin America, where the United States strengthened militaries to do away with insurgencies,'' said Fernando Avellán, who was the contras' director of psychological operations. ''There is no insurgent group like Fidel Castro's in Cuba or in Bolivia which can be defeated by strengthening militaries.''</p>
        <p>He argued that the problem was far deeper and that a solution had to get at what he said was the root of the problem between the United States and the Islamic world: the conflict between Israel and the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>The theme of terrorism has become central in Nicaragua's presidential race, in which the Sandinista leader Daniel Ortega is tied in opinion polls with the candidate of the governing Liberal Party, Enrique Bolaños.</p>
        <p>With the Liberals courting several thousand undecided voters who will determine the result of the election, newspapers and television broadcasts have hammered home Mr. Ortega's links to the leaders of Cuba, Iraq and Libya.</p>
        <p>While there is no proof that Mr. Ortega ever met him, one televised spot also shows Osama bin Laden among the rogues' gallery, while an announcer warns people, ''If they could vote in Nicaragua, they would vote for Daniel Ortega.''</p>
        <p>The ads come at a time when the United States has expressed serious concerns over the prospect of a Sandinista victory, given not only Mr. Ortega's allies, but also the Sandinistas' record on human rights and unresolved claims over properties confiscated when they were in power. If the United States reduced its foreign aid or investors decided to look elsewhere, Nicaragua's already weak economy would be further hobbled.</p>
        <p>The Sandinistas, who denounced the terrorists attacks, see the ads as a way to divert attention from accusations of corruption and mismanagement that have dogged the Liberal Party.</p>
        <p>At the same time, some among the Sandinistas have questioned the definition of terrorism, recalling the United States support for the contra army that tried to topple their government. They cite a 1986 World Court ruling against the United States for its role in the mining of Nicaraguan harbors.</p>
        <p>''If the U.S. likes you, you're a freedom fighter,'' said the Rev. Miguel D'Escoto, the former Sandinista foreign minister. ''If they don't like you, you're a terrorist.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
