<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Sophisticated Square Dance, Called by Tharp</title>
    <meta content="02PILL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/02/arts/02PILL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1306335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01EFD81339F931A35754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Sophisticated Square Dance, Called by Tharp</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Sophisticated Square Dance, Called by Tharp</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER DUNNING</byline>
      <dateline>BECKET, Mass., June 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Twyla Tharp's new ''Westerly Round,'' performed on Saturday afternoon at the Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival here, is hard to know but easy to love, the choreographic equivalent of a mirror ball that throws off imagery as well as glints of light.</p>
        <p>Some in the audience saw a bit of Agnes de Mille's ''Rodeo'' in Ms. Tharp's juxtaposition of a tough, isolated woman and genial men. But ''Westerly Round'' could also be enjoyed purely for its formal values. It was as if Ms. Tharp had taken her movement vocabulary, knocked the corners off each move and gesture and poured it all out onto the stage on the turbulent, onrushing tide of the score, Mark O'Connor's ''Call of the Mockingbird.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Twyla Tharp's new ''Westerly Round,'' performed on Saturday afternoon at the Jacob's Pillow Dance Festival here, is hard to know but easy to love, the choreographic equivalent of a mirror ball that throws off imagery as well as glints of light.</p>
        <p>Some in the audience saw a bit of Agnes de Mille's ''Rodeo'' in Ms. Tharp's juxtaposition of a tough, isolated woman and genial men. But ''Westerly Round'' could also be enjoyed purely for its formal values. It was as if Ms. Tharp had taken her movement vocabulary, knocked the corners off each move and gesture and poured it all out onto the stage on the turbulent, onrushing tide of the score, Mark O'Connor's ''Call of the Mockingbird.''</p>
        <p>''Westerly Round'' begins with its four dancers drawn close at the center of the stage. A hint of sun washes over this little family, clustered together in dim blue light. Then the group opens out for an abstracted square dance, a theme that runs through the piece in well-wrought apposition to classical ballet steps and phrases and even a few gymnast's moves.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tharp introduces Eastern European folk elements to the mix later. Mr. O'Connor's folk-tinged score grows sweeter and more meditative, and Ms. Tharp gives John Selya an elegiac moment or two. But for the most part she flings a darting, sharp-edge and hoistable Elizabeth Parkinson into the gentler dance world of Mr. Selya, Benjamin Bowman and Alexander Brady, a world that is complete in itself.</p>
        <p>''Westerly Round'' is also a continual shifting of groups and individuals. Both Ms. Tharp and Mr. O'Connor have taken small means like the tinges of folk movement and music to symphonic-size grandeur in a small, neat package of a dance.</p>
        <p>The costumes were by Santo Loquasto; Jennifer Tipton designed the lighting.</p>
        <p>One of the pleasures of ''Westerly Round'' was Ms. Tharp's use of gestures, often not completed, that recall Jerome Robbins's gift for elusive but highly expressive gesture. Ms. Parkinson has a moment, for example, when she scrutinizes another dancer's foot as if seeking the truth that she will find the next moment when she looks into his face.</p>
        <p>Incompleted but telling gesture gave Ms. Tharp's ''Known by Heart Duet,'' set to a clanking score by Donald Knaack and danced to subtle perfection by Ashley Tuttle and Keith Roberts, its harrowing subtext. There are inventive mixes of dance styles and explorations of partnering here. But what one remembers best is the pugilistic near-miss parries that keep this woman and this man going as a couple in this fast-paced, hard-edged duet.</p>
        <p>The program opened with a performance of ''The One Hundreds,'' a piece Ms. Tharp created in 1969 that featured a crowd of nondancers from the Berkshires.</p>
        <p>The performance was preceded by an amusing rehearsal video by Carmella Vassor and film of the original rehearsals.</p>
        <p>The volunteers came dressed in period clothes and competed for recognition for the most colorful and authentic costumes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tharp also spoke engagingly with the audience beforehand about the making of the piece and dance in general and brought her own company out to show phrases of the piece. To paraphrase the title of the Jerry Lee Lewis rock classic to which the piece was set in part, there sure was a whole lotta talkin' and demonstratin' goin' on here.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
