<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rookie Wears Silver and Black. And Purple.</title>
    <meta content="22HARR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/22/sports/football/22HARR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1458500"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Raiders</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Northwestern University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hack, Damon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Harris, Napoleon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Oakland Raiders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Super Bowl</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Oakland Raiders</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Harris, Napoleon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6D91030F931A15752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="929" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rookie Wears Silver and Black. And Purple.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rookie Wears Silver and Black. And Purple.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, Jan. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Oakland Raiders rookie linebacker Napoleon Harris made good impression this season, both on field and in locker room, where he flaunted appreciation for his alma mater Northwestern University; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his first days of training camp, Napoleon Harris made it a point to walk around the locker room in purple shower slippers from Northwestern University.</p>
        <p>Back and forth, Harris, the Oakland Raiders rookie linebacker, would roam, while his teammates heckled him and his athletically challenged alma mater. That's when Harris became real imaginative.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his first days of training camp, Oakland's Napoleon Harris made it a point to walk around the locker room in purple shower slippers from Northwestern University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his first days of training camp, Napoleon Harris made it a point to walk around the locker room in purple shower slippers from Northwestern University.</p>
        <p>Back and forth, Harris, the Oakland Raiders rookie linebacker, would roam, while his teammates heckled him and his athletically challenged alma mater. That's when Harris became real imaginative.</p>
        <p>''The purple underwear,'' the Raiders' Trace Armstrong said. ''The purple velour is a little over the top, but it's a choice he'll have to live with.''</p>
        <p>It was a bold move for a rookie trying to find his way in a locker room of veterans, but that swagger helped bring Harris from chilly Dixmoor, Ill., where he grew up, to the sunshine of California, where he will work Sunday at middle linebacker in Super Bowl XXXVII against the Tampa Bay Buccaneers.</p>
        <p>Walking onto the field today, surrounded by a number of teammates who have waited their entire lives for this moment, Harris took his place amid the throng and could not wait to start talking, as if being a rookie in the Super Bowl was simply how the script was supposed to unfold.</p>
        <p>Rookie breaks into the league as a 23rd draft pick (one of the four picks the Raiders obtained in trading Coach Jon Gruden to Tampa); rookie learns the intricacies of playing middle linebacker faster than anyone expects; rookie plays so well, the Raiders release the longtime veteran Greg Biekert before the season, handing the job of defensive quarterback to an untested player.</p>
        <p>''He had big shoes to fill when Biekert left, our leader,'' linebacker Bill Romanowski said of Harris. ''The guy has learned really well. He loves to play football. Every time he steps on the field, he takes one step closer to being something great.''</p>
        <p>Even Raiders Coach Bill Callahan understands that the phenomenon of Harris is something supernatural. Harris played mostly on the outside in college and in high school.</p>
        <p>The Raiders have upwards of 16 different fronts and more than 30 blitz packages. ''To replace Biekert, to change gears and call defenses, it's astounding,'' Callahan said.</p>
        <p>If it wasn't football, Harris says, he would have been dominating something else. The N.B.A., maybe. Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Harris's mother, Brenda, a hairstylist, gave him his moxie, he said.</p>
        <p>''I remember being younger, and I came home from school one day and she asked who was the smartest in my class,'' Harris said. ''I said somebody else. I think she whupped me. From then on, I've just had this strong drive to be the best at everything. Grades. Sports. I've had this competitive fire. And the confidence brings on assertiveness.''</p>
        <p>The 23-year-old Harris, who is 6 feet 2 inches and 255 pounds, has been known to raise his voice in the locker room if the music does not agree with him. That goes for situations in the huddle, too, where his words during the season have been as important as Romanowski's or Armstrong's or anyone else's.</p>
        <p>''He's just got a great presence about him,'' Armstrong said. ''Natural leadership capabilities. When you talk to a guy like that, it comes through.''</p>
        <p>Playing next to those who have seen it all has helped Harris, but he has also made his own breaks. It's rare that a rookie can block out the crowd and the cheerleaders and the sensory overload of a game that is so much more complex than it is at the collegiate level.</p>
        <p>Harris's football background still measures up nicely, the detour to Northwestern notwithstanding. Thornton Township High School, which Harris attended, had eight players on N.F.L. rosters this season: linebacker Jack Golden of the Buccaneers, receiver Antwaan Randle El of the Pittsburgh Steelers, receiver Tai Streets of the San Francisco 49ers, linebacker Barry Gardner of the Philadelphia Eagles, defensive back Jermaine Hampton of the Indianapolis Colts, defensive lineman Winfield Garnett of the Minnesota Vikings and offensive lineman Sammy Williams of the San Diego Chargers.</p>
        <p>Just for good measure, Melvin Ely of the Los Angeles Clippers also attended Township and was a teammate of Harris's in basketball.</p>
        <p>Harris considers Randle El like a brother. ''I talked to him this morning,'' Harris said.</p>
        <p>As a teenager, he was sure he was going to attend the University of Michigan until his father, also named Napoleon, died of a heart attack during his junior year of high school. Harris decided to attend Northwestern, 30 minutes from Dixmoor, so he could be close to his mother; brother, Jonathan; and sister, Tomeka.</p>
        <p>''It's something you think about all the time,'' Harris said of his father's death. ''I try not to go back to the past too much, but you have to understand it in order to move forward. I definitely wanted to be the man of the house when the situation was forced upon me. I felt the responsibility for my family to do it.''</p>
        <p>Bill Mosel, Harris's high school football coach, said: ''It was hard for him. He took on all of the responsibilities because he had a brother and a sister at home.''</p>
        <p>It says a lot about why Harris went to Northwestern. And why he has so much pride in that purple.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
