<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Infants in Chinese City Starve on Protein-Short Formula</title>
    <meta content="05MILK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/05/international/asia/05milk.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1579305"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Infant Formulas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Proteins</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Counterfeit Merchandise</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yardley, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wen Jiabao (Prime Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Babies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Counterfeit Merchandise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Proteins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E7DE1E3DF936A35756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1323" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Infants in Chinese City Starve on Protein-Short Formula</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Infants in Chinese City Starve on Protein-Short Formula</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM YARDLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yardley, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>FUYANG, China, April 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Local scam in central China, where protein-short infant formula sickened nearly 200 babies, including at least 13 who died, has resonated into nationwide scandal; consumer protection is often nonexistent in nation where counterfeits and fakes fill shelves, particularly in poorest regions, which often become dumping grounds for cheap, unregulated goods; formula scandal has become blaring news in nation of doting parents; investigators sent by Prime Min Wen Jiabao blame illegal manufacturers around nation and say 45 brands sold in region and elsewhere are substandard; reports of problem had been percolating in city for almost year, with local officials taking no action; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The containers were sealed in plastic, each filled with baby formula that Zhang Linwei and his wife fed to their tiny daughter. Over time, as the baby ate more formula, her cheeks grew fat as balloons, seemingly a sign of good health. Only later did her parents learn it was a sign of starvation.</p>
        <p>Their 5-month-old baby, Rongrong, died last August after doctors told her parents that the low-cost milk powder they had been using was fake.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The bad formula has infected 200 babies with what local residents in central China call "big head disease."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The containers were sealed in plastic, each filled with baby formula that Zhang Linwei and his wife fed to their tiny daughter. Over time, as the baby ate more formula, her cheeks grew fat as balloons, seemingly a sign of good health. Only later did her parents learn it was a sign of starvation.</p>
        <p>Their 5-month-old baby, Rongrong, died last August after doctors told her parents that the low-cost milk powder they had been using was fake.</p>
        <p>They and hundreds of other parents here in central China unwittingly bought bad formula, in which nutritional supplements had been replaced with starch or sugar. Nearly 200 other babies, including at least 13 who died, now have what local residents call ''big head disease.''</p>
        <p>It is a local scam that has resonated into a nationwide scandal, a cruel reminder of how China's problem with fakes and counterfeits extends far beyond knockoff brand clothes and pirated DVD's. With new products filling shelves, consumer protection is often nonexistent, particularly in the poorest regions, which often become dumping grounds for cheap, unregulated goods.</p>
        <p>Food safety is a recurring problem, with regular reports of poisonings at school cafeterias and restaurants. Yet the baby formula scandal has become blaring news in this nation of doting parents because of its predatory, venal quality: manufacturers, unhindered by government, reaped profits by marketing useless powder for infants.</p>
        <p>''At the hospital, when I learned they couldn't save my baby I couldn't help crying,'' Mr. Zhang said. ''These babies are really innocent. Whatever you give them to eat and drink, they will take it.''</p>
        <p>The scandal was publicized in a report on state television on April 19, and the next day Prime Minister Wen Jiabao sent a special investigation team here. Officials arrested at least 22 people involved in making and selling the formula.</p>
        <p>Investigators blamed illegal manufacturers throughout China for the problem and reported that 45 brands sold in Fuyang and elsewhere were substandard. But as the government-controlled news media hailed Beijing's response, another fact became known. Reports of the problem had been percolating in Fuyang for almost a year without any significant action being taken. A few parents like Mr. Zhang had even pressed local disease control officials to test packets of formula. His packet contained only 2 percent protein; the national standard is about 12 percent.</p>
        <p>Yet officials here in Anhui Province did not remove the fake formula from the stores until April, after Prime Minister Wen ordered his investigation, according to local parents and national media reports. What is unclear is whether local officials knowingly allowed the powder to be sold, perhaps for kickbacks. Officials in Fuyang declined repeated telephone requests for interviews.</p>
        <p>''Poor government administration is a key here,'' said Zhang Shouli, a rural affairs advocate and market researcher who has traveled around Fuyang. ''Unless the government steps in, there are always people who will produce those products.''</p>
        <p>Located in the impoverished wheat belt of central China, Fuyang is a gritty railroad center with a reputation for corruption and little government oversight. A former mayor was recently executed on charges of corruption, including taking bribes. A local airport built at enormous cost sits virtually unused.</p>
        <p>The city also has many wholesale markets selling illegal or substandard products. Zhang Linwei, the father, lives in one of the villages outside Fuyang, where he earns about $60 a month making bricks at a kiln.</p>
        <p>His daughter Rongrong was born in March 2003, and since his wife, Liu Li, could not produce enough breast milk, he began spending about $11 a month on formula. They chose a low-cost brand recommended by a friend, and his daughter consumed a container every two or three days.</p>
        <p>But when Rongrong was 4 months old she developed skin rashes, and her face swelled. Alarmed, Mr. Zhang and his wife took her to an unlicensed doctor, who did little.</p>
        <p>They tried another brand of formula, but the baby refused to eat it. Two weeks later they took her to the main hospital in Fuyang, where doctors say her body was so underdeveloped that they could not find a usable vein for a transfusion.</p>
        <p>''The doctor said the baby had malnutrition due to milk powder,'' Mr. Zhang recalled. After a week in the hospital, doctors told him to take her home. She died the next day.</p>
        <p>''She didn't grow,'' Mr. Zhang said. ''From birth to death she had almost no increase in weight.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Liu, the mother, collapsed in shock when her daughter died. ''I'm very sad,'' she said. ''I didn't know this milk was bad.''</p>
        <p>The problem is concentrated in Fuyang, but sick babies have also been reported in Beijing and in the southern city of Guangzhou. Government news media reported that a spot check of baby formula in stores in populous Guangdong Province had found that 33 percent of the brands did not meet national standards. Some brands tested in Fuyang had less than 1 percent protein.</p>
        <p>The scandal has already brought calls for greater regulation, and the official news media have reported that China's highest prosecutorial agency intends to open a nationwide investigation of rampant counterfeit products.</p>
        <p>But such initiatives would require a level of accountability that is often lacking. An immediate problem, exposed during the outbreaks of SARS and avian influenza, is that China's Food and Drug Administration has little real regulatory power.</p>
        <p>A nationwide survey last year of 2,000 food products found that almost 20 percent did not meet national health standards. In March, the state news media reported that of the 106,000 food companies in China, only 17,900 were licensed.</p>
        <p>Most of all, consumers rarely feel empowered to complain.</p>
        <p>''Local farmers and peasants don't know to pursue their rights,'' said Gao Zheng, a local resident whose persistent efforts to push officials in Fuyang helped publicize the scandal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gao, whose infant niece was hospitalized last year, said he had to pay for local officials to test his baby formula and prove it was fake. Earlier this year, he said, a local consumer protection official arranged for a series of meetings with a baby formula distributor to discuss reimbursing. But he said the meetings had been fruitless.</p>
        <p>Outside the main People's Hospital in Fuyang, Zhu Wen, a migrant worker, waited with his wife and their infant son. The baby's head was swollen from months of taking Good Baby milk formula.</p>
        <p>The father said the child's hair had fallen out and pointed to the scaly, irritated skin on his son's scalp. He used Good Baby because it cost half the price of other brands.</p>
        <p>''These companies are taking advantage of our poverty,'' Mr. Zhu said in a later interview away from the hospital. ''They should be punished or executed.''</p>
        <p>He said his family was still paying off other medical debts and could not afford to take their son to a hospital when he first became sick. This week they went to People's Hospital because of reports that sick babies would receive free care. But he said doctors had told him he must pay $120, almost two months' wages.</p>
        <p>He was waiting to see if someone would help him. If not, he said his only recourse would be to return home.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
