<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>West Point Band Makes A Return Engagement</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="610561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHERMAN, ROBERT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DF1539F930A15756C0A965958260" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>West Point Band Makes A Return Engagement</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHERMAN, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A YEAR ago, almost to the day, the West Point Band came to Rye High School to begin a series of free concerts sponsored by the Pulvermann Foundation. Starting slowly, with plans for one or two events a year, the foundation intends to add more presentations until they become a major community asset. The foundation also hopes that its family concerts will influence younger listeners.</p>
        <p>Last year's concert was such a wild success -- with almost as many people turned away as could fit into the auditorium -- that the West Pointers are coming back this afternoon at 3 o'clock. The choice of the United States Military Academy Band is especially apt as Memorial Day approaches: as the senior musical unit of the American Army, the Concert Band has appeared at many historic events (including the return home of the Iran hostages), given joint concerts with the American Symphony and the New York Philharmonic, been conducted by such legendary maestros as Arturo Toscanini and Leopold Stokowski. It should be noted, by the way, that the players are not Academy cadets but top-notch professional musicians who joined the Army expressly to serve as West Point bandsmen and women.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A YEAR ago, almost to the day, the West Point Band came to Rye High School to begin a series of free concerts sponsored by the Pulvermann Foundation. Starting slowly, with plans for one or two events a year, the foundation intends to add more presentations until they become a major community asset. The foundation also hopes that its family concerts will influence younger listeners.</p>
        <p>Last year's concert was such a wild success -- with almost as many people turned away as could fit into the auditorium -- that the West Pointers are coming back this afternoon at 3 o'clock. The choice of the United States Military Academy Band is especially apt as Memorial Day approaches: as the senior musical unit of the American Army, the Concert Band has appeared at many historic events (including the return home of the Iran hostages), given joint concerts with the American Symphony and the New York Philharmonic, been conducted by such legendary maestros as Arturo Toscanini and Leopold Stokowski. It should be noted, by the way, that the players are not Academy cadets but top-notch professional musicians who joined the Army expressly to serve as West Point bandsmen and women.</p>
        <p>The program features concert pieces, show tunes and a number of American favorites, including Gershwin's "Rhapsody in Blue," with the renowned pianist Agustin Anievas as soloist, and Copland's "Lincoln Portrait." As noted, the concert is free but arrival at the school when the doors open at 2:30 P.M. is highly recommended.</p>
        <p>Also free and primed for family fun is "Marathon III: Bach, Beethoven and Be-bop." The event, at the Westchester County Center in White Plains, starts at 11:30 this morning and continues until 6 P.M. The festival includes everything from opera to jazz, symphony to ballet, plus choral singing, art workshops, a children's performathon, arts bazaar and lots more. More information can be obtained by calling the Office of Cultural Affairs at 285-2008 or the Parks Department at 285-7275.</p>
        <p>"Suite Moves and Music," which fuses music and dance, will be held at 3 P.M. today at the Archbishop Stepinac High School in White Plains. The dancer-choreographer Sabatino Verlezza and members of his company have prepared a staged version of Faure's charming "Dolly Suite." The Westchester Conservatory's Brass Choir and Orchestra, under the baton of Elliot Magaziner, have scheduled works by Gabrieli and Britten. The two winners of the conservatory's annual Concerto Competition -- the 13-year-old Ossining pianist Karen Ross and the 14-year-old Bronxville oboist Adam Hollander -- will play works by Mozart and Haydn. The number to call for more information is 761-3715.</p>
        <p>At the Reformed Church of the Tarrytowns, the pianist Suzanne McCormick offers works today by Beethoven, Debussy and Chopin. More information can be obtained by calling 631-4497.</p>
        <p>Another concert at 4 P.M. today will take place at the Emelin Theater in Mamaroneck. The violinist Aaron Rosand plays sonatas by Vivaldi and Brahms as well as Sarasate's "Carmen Fantasy." The recital is a fund-raiser for the Westchester Symphony's Young People's Music Workshop Program. For ticket reservations and information, the number to call is 609-0098.</p>
        <p>Yet another concert is scheduled for 4 P.M. today. The Somers Philharmonic Chorale and High School Chamber Choir will join forces in a program at St. Luke's Episcopal Church. The chorale, revived by John Cuk in January after an eight-year hiatus, and the choir, also under Mr. Cuk's direction as a travelling group within the larger Somers High School Concert Choir, are performing the Mozart's "Requiem" and "Ave Verum." The soloists are Susanne Rossini, Elsa Jean Davidson, Richard Slade and Daniel Simpson. For tickets or more information about either ensemble, the numbers to callare 248-7357 or 248-8585, extension 65.</p>
        <p>Choral music in a more exotic vein is being offered next Wednesday at 12:35 P.M. at Grace Episcopal Church in White Plains. The Hanamizuki Chorus will sing under the direction of Yukiko Oinuma, with Noriko Matsuura as piano accompanist. This unusual ensemble, currently celebrating its 10th anniversary, is made up of Japanese women who live in the county. The group, which takes its name from the Japanese word for the dogwood flower, sings music of many lands. The program lists a Japanese Choral Suite and such international favorites as "El Condor Pasa," "Loch Lomond," "O Sole Mio," "Der Lindenbaum" and -- in a snappy salute to the Big Apple -- "New York, New York." The information number at Grace Church is 949-0384.</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
