<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Intricate Senate Procedure Lends a Hand to Welfare Recipients</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="805900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WELFARE (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DE0DC1639F932A35752C1A963958260" item-length="897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Intricate Senate Procedure Lends a Hand to Welfare Recipients</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With one clean swipe just before midnight Friday, the Democratic minority in  the Senate knocked out of the big budget bill many of the harshest policies involving welfare.</p>
        <p>No longer would the bill force families off welfare after they had been on relief for five years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With one clean swipe just before midnight Friday, the Democratic minority in  the Senate knocked out of the big budget bill many of the harshest policies involving welfare.</p>
        <p>No longer would the bill force families off welfare after they had been on relief for five years.</p>
        <p>No longer would it allow states to deny welfare benefits to unwed mothers younger than 18 or to children born into families already on welfare.</p>
        <p>No longer would the bill provide a bonus to states if their rate of out-of-wedlock births fell.</p>
        <p>The Democrats did not succeed because they mustered a majority vote for their position -- the 46 Democratic senators voted to delete the provisions in question, while the 53 Republicans voted to retain them -- but because of an arcane procedure known as the Byrd rule.</p>
        <p>The Senate's use of the rule raises some question about whether comprehensive welfare legislation, approved by both houses and favored in some form by President Clinton, can become law this year.</p>
        <p>Under this Senate rule, named for its author, Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia, provisions in budget bill can be successfully challenged on a point of order if they produce no change in revenue or spending or if such changes are "merely incidental" to the fiscal items. It takes a three-fifths majority, or 60 votes if all senators are present, to waive the rule.</p>
        <p>The rule does not apply directly to the House, whose budget bill clamps down  more on the poor than does the Senate's. But it will apply to any matter approved by a conference committee before the Senate.</p>
        <p>So the rule is likely to complicate the work of the conference committee that this week is beginning to try to work out the differences between budget bills approved last week by the Senate and the House.</p>
        <p>These are among the elements of the House bill, but not the Senate bill, that may not meet the test of the Byrd rule:</p>
        <p>*Abolition of the Commerce Department.</p>
        <p>*Merger of the Agency for International Development, the United States Information Agency and the Arms Control and Disarmament Agency into the State Department.</p>
        <p>*Repeal of Federal nursing home standards.</p>
        <p>*Overturning new Government regulations on livestock grazing on Federal land.</p>
        <p>*Tightening of the United States embargo on Cuba.</p>
        <p>*Revision of the Endangered Species Act.</p>
        <p>None of these go to the heart of the budget measure, which is supposed to balance the budget in seven years, cut the taxes of middle- and upper-income taxpayers and shift control of most social programs from the Federal Government  to the states.</p>
        <p>But many are important to conservative Republicans in the House, where freshmen have no experience with the strange ways of the Senate. The party leaders may have to twist a good many arms to get these conservatives to vote for the compromise measure that comes out of the conference without these provisions.</p>
        <p>The rule also complicates the politics of welfare legislation, which is going through Congress along two separate tracks.</p>
        <p>The Senate and House have passed separate welfare bills almost identical to the welfare provisions in the budget bills. The notion of overhauling welfare is popular politically, and President Clinton has said he would sign a bill with welfare measures like those in the Senate bill.</p>
        <p>The Republicans who control Congress decided to include the welfare provisions in the budget bill so they could blame Mr. Clinton for vetoing the popular legislation if, as is almost certain to happen, he vetoes the budget bill.</p>
        <p>Senator Bob Dole of Kansas, the Republican leader, said he was reluctant, as  a political matter, to give the President the opportunity to sign the former and veto the latter.</p>
        <p>Then there is the question of a Senate filibuster. Under the rules, budget bills cannot be filibustered. But a separate welfare bill could be. The welfare  bill was approved in the Senate last month by an overwhelming 87-to-12 vote. But many Democrats who voted for it might jump ship if they thought they could sustain a filibuster.</p>
        <p>Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Democrat of New York, the leading opponent of the welfare measure in the Senate, said tonight that he thought most Democrats who voted for the measure last month would join a filibuster if President Clinton drops the word.</p>
        <p>Senator Byrd, who was the Democratic leader from 1977 until 1989 and who sees himself as the guardian of the prerogatives of the Senate, first got his budget  rule approved by the Senate in 1985. It cannot be changed without a three-fifths majority in the Senate.</p>
        <p>The rule was meant to counter the fact that under law only 20 hours of debate are permitted on the huge budget measures known as reconciliation bills. Before  the Byrd rule was imposed, dozens of extraneous elements often managed to sneak  into such bills without debate or the knowledge of many senators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
