<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Retreat on the Hudson</title>
    <meta content="26THU1$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/26/opinion/26THU1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1312269"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pcb (Polychlorinated Biphenyls)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dredges and Dredging</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hudson River</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Electric Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christie (Admr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemicals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hydrocarbons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Machinery and Equipment</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Hudson River</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitman, Christine</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDE173DF935A15754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Retreat on the Hudson</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No Retreat on the Hudson</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial calls on Christie Whitman, head of Environmental Protection Agency, not to scale back on Clinton administration's plan that would require General Electric to spend half-billion dollars to begin long-overdue task of cleaning upper Hudson River of PCB's</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As President Bush's chief environmental officer, Christie Whitman has absorbed plenty of abuse for the administration's generally deplorable environmental record. Some of this criticism has been unfair, and in many cases she has taken the fall for policies dictated by others. But Mrs. Whitman will have only herself to blame if she chooses to scale back the Clinton administration's plan that would require General Electric to spend a half-billion dollars to begin the long-overdue task of cleaning the upper Hudson River of toxic chemicals known as PCB's.</p>
        <p>Rumors have been flying around all week that Mrs. Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, would shortly announce her own dredging plan, one that could well reduce the Clinton administration's plan to a mere pilot project followed by years of additional study and analysis. The reports -- none confirmed by Mrs. Whitman herself -- have emerged from various members of Congress with whom Mrs. Whitman has been conferring and from lower-echelon sources at her agency. Gov. George Pataki of New York took them seriously enough to call Mrs. Whitman on Tuesday and tell her, in firmer language than he has ever used publicly, that he supports the Clinton cleanup plan and that anything less would be unacceptable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Christine Whitman should not scale back the Clinton administration's plan that would require General Electric to clean the upper Hudson River</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As President Bush's chief environmental officer, Christie Whitman has absorbed plenty of abuse for the administration's generally deplorable environmental record. Some of this criticism has been unfair, and in many cases she has taken the fall for policies dictated by others. But Mrs. Whitman will have only herself to blame if she chooses to scale back the Clinton administration's plan that would require General Electric to spend a half-billion dollars to begin the long-overdue task of cleaning the upper Hudson River of toxic chemicals known as PCB's.</p>
        <p>Rumors have been flying around all week that Mrs. Whitman, the administrator of the Environmental Protection Agency, would shortly announce her own dredging plan, one that could well reduce the Clinton administration's plan to a mere pilot project followed by years of additional study and analysis. The reports -- none confirmed by Mrs. Whitman herself -- have emerged from various members of Congress with whom Mrs. Whitman has been conferring and from lower-echelon sources at her agency. Gov. George Pataki of New York took them seriously enough to call Mrs. Whitman on Tuesday and tell her, in firmer language than he has ever used publicly, that he supports the Clinton cleanup plan and that anything less would be unacceptable.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki is hardly alone in these views. The dredging plan is supported by Eliot Spitzer, New York's attorney general, Senators Hillary Rodham Clinton and Charles Schumer, and a majority of the state's Congressional delegation. It is also supported by the federal scientists in E.P.A.'s New York region who have spent nearly a decade assembling a compelling, peer-reviewed case for dredging despite the resolute opposition of General Electric. Mrs. Whitman is obliged under law to consider the thousands of comments collected by her agency during the last few months, and perhaps these comments have had an impact on her thinking. But given her agency's painstaking work over the years, it is hard to imagine what new scientific evidence may have come her way to persuade her that the matter now requires further study.</p>
        <p>Under the plan approved last December, dredges would remove about 2.6 billion cubic yards of sediment containing some 100,000 pounds of polychlorinated biphenyls, or PCB's, from various ''hot spots'' along a 40-mile stretch of the river from Troy north to Fort Edward. The roughly $500 million cost would be borne by G.E., whose upriver plants dumped the chemicals in the river before they were declared illegal in 1977.</p>
        <p>G.E. has never denied its responsibility for the chemicals but has wrangled bitterly with state and federal agencies over how best to handle the problem. The company has argued that most of the chemicals are safely buried in the river's sediments and that the only ''active'' PCB's are those still leaking from two old upriver plants -- leaks the company has already spent $160 million trying to plug. But the E.P.A. argues that in an active, free-flowing river like the Hudson, the sediments are constantly discharging chemicals into the water column and must therefore be dredged.</p>
        <p>This page has endorsed the agency's analysis and its plan, and has called upon General Electric to do the statesmanlike thing and join Washington and Albany in a comprehensive effort to restore one of America's great rivers. Mrs. Whitman should now reaffirm the federal commitment to this task.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
