<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Virtual Memorial Tells Soldiers' Stories</title>
    <meta content="11weveterans" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1768203"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="WESTCHESTER/LARCHMONT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Larchmont (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mamaroneck (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Larchmont Historical Society</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Santos, Fernanda</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Veterans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2DA1531F932A25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Virtual Memorial Tells Soldiers' Stories</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FERNANDA SANTOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Santos, Fernanda</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Web-based memorial set up by Larchmont Historical Society that tells stories of 94 of 122 soldiers whose names are engraved on memorials within Larchmont and unincorporated part of Mamaroneck, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE image is etched in his memory: a woman caressing the name of a soldier at the Vietnam Veterans Memorial in Washington. Ned Benton, a college professor and history buff, wondered about the story behind that name, which made him think about the stories behind the names of the dozens of soldiers memorialized in the Village of Larchmont, where he lives.</p>
        <p>Eight years ago, as the village was updating its Web site, Mr. Benton and his colleagues at the Larchmont Historical Society had an idea: Why not use the Internet to tell the stories of these soldiers? The challenge was to uncover the information.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE image is etched in his memory: a woman caressing the name of a soldier at the Vietnam Veterans Memorial in Washington. Ned Benton, a college professor and history buff, wondered about the story behind that name, which made him think about the stories behind the names of the dozens of soldiers memorialized in the Village of Larchmont, where he lives.</p>
        <p>Eight years ago, as the village was updating its Web site, Mr. Benton and his colleagues at the Larchmont Historical Society had an idea: Why not use the Internet to tell the stories of these soldiers? The challenge was to uncover the information.</p>
        <p>On Memorial Day, the project had its debut on the Web at www.memorials.larchmonthistory.org. It has photographs and biographical sketches of 94 of the 122 soldiers whose names are engraved on memorials within the 10538 ZIP Code, which encompasses the Village of Larchmont and the unincorporated part of the Town of Mamaroneck. The site tells when the soldier was born, how and where he died, and in some cases, gives the obituary. It tells the soldier's unit and where his memorial is.</p>
        <p>''With a real memorial, when you touch a person's name, it brings about memories,'' said Mr. Benton, a professor of public administration and criminal justice at John Jay College and the historical society's Web master. ''An online memorial can never replace a real memorial, but it offers another way of touching the name of a person.''</p>
        <p>The site is made up of information culled from newspaper articles, military databases and the historical society's archives, among other sources, Mr. Benton said. Contributions are encouraged.</p>
        <p>It lists soldiers who died in World Wars I and II, the Korean War and the Vietnam War. (There have not been any deaths among the soldiers from Larchmont and Mamaroneck who are in Iraq and Afghanistan.) Even though the Village of Larchmont was not incorporated until 1891, Mr. Benton said, he hopes to add the names of soldiers who died during the Civil War.</p>
        <p>Jerry Newberry, public affairs director at the Veterans of Foreign Wars headquarters in Kansas City, Mo., and a Vietnam veteran, said in a telephone interview that he didn't know of any similar community-based sites, although there are state and national ones. He said the virtual memorial ''is a tremendous way, in these modern days, to pay tribute to those who have given their lives for their country, and an example to be followed by other communities.''</p>
        <p>The memorial is to be dedicated on Nov. 11, Veterans Day. John Isbister, 76, of Larchmont hopes that by then he will have found a picture of his uncle John Isbister Jr. riding his beloved motorcycle, and have it added to the Web site. Mr. Isbister's uncle died of meningitis in World War I.</p>
        <p>''My uncle died before I was born, so I'm looking forward to finding out more about him,'' Mr. Isbister said.</p>
        <p>''This memorial is a marvelous idea,'' he said. ''To most of the people who live in Larchmont these days, soldiers like my uncle were just names on a plaque. Now, they will mean something, even to people who have no connection to them.''</p>
        <p>WESTCHESTER/LARCHMONT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
