<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tight Quarters And Ample Servings</title>
    <meta content="11wedine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1768205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="DINING/BRONXVILLE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Babbone (Bronxville, NY, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gabriel, Alice</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E2DA1531F932A25755C0A9609C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tight Quarters And Ample Servings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALICE GABRIEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gabriel, Alice</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alice Gabriel reviews Babbone restaurant in Bronxville, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anthony and Federico Terzano -- first-generation Italian-Americans, brothers and partners in the storefront restaurant Babbone -- are big, personable guys who, in the great Italian tradition, want to feed you to make you happy. On a recent night, Freddy, who works up front, came to our table with both an apology (''We're a little jammed up in the kitchen'') and a plate of boccie-size meatballs to tide us over.</p>
        <p>His brother, Tony, cooks with as much muscle as finesse, with little regard for calories, which is not to say that his hearty, Abruzzese-style cuisine is not delicious. In her classic book ''Italian Regional Cooking,'' Ada Boni describes the Abruzzo's ''historical tradition of gigantic meals,'' manifest in the panarda, a colossal feast dating to antiquity. Mr. Terzano's plus-size portions do nothing if not honor his ancestry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anthony and Federico Terzano -- first-generation Italian-Americans, brothers and partners in the storefront restaurant Babbone -- are big, personable guys who, in the great Italian tradition, want to feed you to make you happy. On a recent night, Freddy, who works up front, came to our table with both an apology (''We're a little jammed up in the kitchen'') and a plate of boccie-size meatballs to tide us over.</p>
        <p>His brother, Tony, cooks with as much muscle as finesse, with little regard for calories, which is not to say that his hearty, Abruzzese-style cuisine is not delicious. In her classic book ''Italian Regional Cooking,'' Ada Boni describes the Abruzzo's ''historical tradition of gigantic meals,'' manifest in the panarda, a colossal feast dating to antiquity. Mr. Terzano's plus-size portions do nothing if not honor his ancestry.</p>
        <p>He credits his immigrant parents and grandmother with showing him the way around a kitchen, and the menu offers several dishes inspired by Mamma and Nonna. There is pasta e fagiolini, a delicious bean soup strewn with ribbons of basil; pizza Margherita, distinguished by its crackly crust and candylike San Marzano tomatoes; and pillowy ricotta gnocchi tossed in a rich, fennel-spiked bolognese.</p>
        <p>Mr. Terzano, who once cooked in the Marines, is not a total throwback; he eagerly argues the merits of key limes and Meyer lemons. His Caesar salad showed admirable restraint; crisp, finely chopped romaine hearts and delicate croutons were bound by a light, creamy dressing with just a breath of garlic. (On the other hand, the tri colore salad, a mountain of arugula, radicchio and endive, could have fed a family of four.)</p>
        <p>The Terzanos are making the most of a small space. The decor, which has a certain sweetness to it, seems to have been culled from tag sales. Decorative elements include a tropical fish lamp, a bird cage, a plastic lei, a straw-covered Chianti bottle and a modest tapestry of the Last Supper. Pink, beaded light fixtures and curtains stretched taut on brass railings do their best to dress things up. The menu design, italic script on faux parchment, is stubbornly old-fashioned. The soundtrack of accordion music and Italian tenors seems just right.</p>
        <p>The tight quarters can magnify problems. One night, the dining room was hazy with smoke from the kitchen (we could smell lamb roasting before we even entered the restaurant); as soon as the air-conditioning was turned up, the smoke dissipated. On a busy Saturday, in what was more worthy of a comedy act, our waiter set the table after we had been seated, letting spoons and forks pretty much fall where they may. Service over all was friendly and attentive.</p>
        <p>We began with a huge portion of tender grilled Rhode Island squid on a bed of field greens, which had a wonderful smokiness -- Babbone could do a brisk business in this dish alone. In a house specialty, baby clams and mussels were steeped in a garlicky broth of white wine and white bean purée. Roasted red pepper added a sweet note to slices of fresh mozzarella and ripe tomato. Clams oreganato, hooded with damp bread crumbs, were the only real disappointment.</p>
        <p>Second courses were generally less winning than starters. Most came with beautifully cooked green beans or asparagus, but also with tired roasted potatoes. I liked the full-flavored eggplant lasagna, and the sautéed veal medallions with prosciutto and melted Gruyère in a Cognac sauce. But a baby hen was smothered by caramelized onions; shrimp scampi were sticky with flour; pappardelle with wild mushrooms and truffle oil was as salty as surf; and a piece of delicate sole was overpowered by vinegary capers and artichoke hearts.</p>
        <p>Like a good relief pitcher, dessert saved the game. Mr. Terzano's light, boozy tiramisù reminded me of why people got excited about tiramisù in the first place. His beautifully textured American cheesecake had a sour cream float and a hint of key lime (although decorative dollops of cannoli filling gilded the lily). Full-bodied coconut sorbet came packed in a coconut shell. There are tartuffos for the kids, and for adults, parting shots of limoncello and strong espresso.</p>
        <p>Babbone  502 New Rochelle Road  Bronxville  (914) 665-4722</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>THE SPACE -- Intimate Chester Heights storefront restaurant with modest décor bustles on weekends, relaxes on weeknights. Wheelchair access through front door.  THE CROWD -- Families with young children in tow, tattooed men in their best T-shirts, and older couples all seem at home.  THE BAR -- The pocket bar, hidden behind a glass block wall, has a handful of seats. The wine list is sensibly short and moderately priced.  THE BILL -- Dinner entrees, $17.95 to $24.95. (Discover and Diners Club not accepted.)  WHAT WE LIKE -- Grilled calamari with roasted garlic aioli, pasta e fagiolini, Caesar salad; ricotta gnocchi with Bolognese sauce, eggplant lasagna, veal medallions with prosciutto and Gruyère; coconut sorbet, American cheesecake, tiramisù.  IF YOU GO -- Open Tuesdays through Fridays, noon to midnight; Saturdays, 4 p.m. to midnight; Sundays, 4 to 10 p.m. Reservations recommended on weekends. Parking is limited in front.  Reviewed June 11, 2006</p>
        <p>DINING/BRONXVILLE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
