<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>UPN Names TV Executive As President</title>
    <meta content="T17NETW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="958287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Paramount Network</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Valentine, Dean</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salhany, Lucie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970917T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE5D61538F934A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="561" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>UPN Names TV Executive As President</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Paramount Network names Dean Valentine, longtime executive with Walt Disney studio, as its new president; Valentine succeeds Lucie Salhany, who will resign this month (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a long-awaited announcement, the United Paramount Network, one of two would-be fifth networks, yesterday named Dean Valentine, a longtime executive with the Walt Disney studio, as its new president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valentine's name had been mentioned for the position as early as a month ago but last-minute contract details delayed the official announcement until yesterday, said Kerry McCluggage, the chairman of the Paramount Television Group, one of the joint owners of UPN, along with the Chris-Craft Industries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a long-awaited announcement, the United Paramount Network, one of two would-be fifth networks, yesterday named Dean Valentine, a longtime executive with the Walt Disney studio, as its new president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valentine's name had been mentioned for the position as early as a month ago but last-minute contract details delayed the official announcement until yesterday, said Kerry McCluggage, the chairman of the Paramount Television Group, one of the joint owners of UPN, along with the Chris-Craft Industries.</p>
        <p>As president of Walt Disney Television and Walt Disney Television Animation, Mr. Valentine had supervised such shows as ''Home Improvement,'' ''Ellen'' and the Disney afternoon franchise of cartoons.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valentine succeeds Lucie Salhany, who had announced in April that she would be leaving UPN this month.</p>
        <p>The network remains locked in a struggle with another aspiring new network, the WB Network, owned by Warner Brothers, for a place among the larger broadcast competitors. Mr. Valentine said that it was logical that the two young networks would be compared, but he wanted to play down the ''tension between us.''</p>
        <p>Instead, he said, he wants to push UPN into some new directions, moving it beyond what he called ''any narrow category or ethnic group.''</p>
        <p>While the latest ''Star Trek'' vehicle, ''Voyager'' is its most popular program, UPN has been criticized in some places for an overdependence in its early schedules on shows that appeal heavily to black viewers. The network currently broadcasts one entire night of shows featuring all-black casts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valentine said: ''Many of those shows have done quite well for UPN. But there's a ceiling to them. We want to broaden our reach.'' He added that he expected to have some impact on UPN's program decisions quickly, though it will be some time before that translates into shows on the air.</p>
        <p>''It's a tad early to lay out our game plan,'' Mr. Valentine said. ''Sometime in the next year to year and a half I think you'll start to see my influence over the programming.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Valentine said he planned no immediate staff changes.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCluggage said Mr. Valentine's appointment reaffirmed the commitment of Paramount and its parent company, Viacom Inc., to UPN. He acknowledged that the network continued to lose money but said that was expected.</p>
        <p>''We're ahead of our original estimates,'' he said, adding that the partners continued to have faith in their initial purpose in starting the network. ''We wanted to improve the value of the stations we own. The way to do that was to supply them with original programming in prime time. We've already seen an increase in the value of the stations.''</p>
        <p>He added that the network was ''more than halfway'' to profitability. ''We're very happy where we are right now,'' Mr. McCluggage said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Valentine began his career at Disney in 1988. Earlier he had worked in comedy development and at NBC after leaving his original career as a journalist. He wrote for such magazines as Time, Life and The Saturday Review.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
