<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Russians to Test Space Mirror As Giant Night Light for Earth</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="582421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIR (SPACE STATION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIGHT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLASTICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">USSR (FORMER SOVIET UNION)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEARY, WARREN E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Stations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Plastics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDF1630F931A25752C0A965958260" item-length="1670" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Russians to Test Space Mirror As Giant Night Light for Earth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEARY, WARREN E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RUSSIAN scientists are planning soon to unfurl a glistening sheet of plastic in space as a first step toward testing an intriguing notion about turning night into day -- or at least twilight.</p>
        <p>Tucked aboard a Progress cargo spacecraft attached to the Mir space station is an experiment called Znamya, or Banner, that will test the idea of using a mirror in space to reflect sunlight down to Earth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RUSSIAN scientists are planning soon to unfurl a glistening sheet of plastic in space as a first step toward testing an intriguing notion about turning night into day -- or at least twilight.</p>
        <p>Tucked aboard a Progress cargo spacecraft attached to the Mir space station is an experiment called Znamya, or Banner, that will test the idea of using a mirror in space to reflect sunlight down to Earth.</p>
        <p>If all goes as planned, the Banner payload will be deployed next month to unfurl into a 65-foot-diameter disk of aluminum-coated plastic film. The experiment will test the feasibility of illuminating points on Earth with light equivalent to that of several full moons.</p>
        <p>Russian engineers say it should also teach them a lot about handling thin sheets of plastic in space, a step toward developing large sails to propel ships in space using the faint force of sunlight.</p>
        <p>"This should be a marvelous technical demonstration," said James E. Oberg of Houston, an expert on Russian space programs who wrote the book "Red Star in Orbit."</p>
        <p>"It's an idea they've talked about for a long time, and now they will have a chance to see if it works."</p>
        <p>The Sun is always shining somewhere on Earth, of course, if not always where people need or want it. But what if someone put a big reflector high in space to peer over the curvature of Earth, capture some of the Sun's rays and shine them down on the dark side?</p>
        <p>In much the way a schoolchild playing with a hand mirror learns to reflect a spot of light from a bright window into the crannies of his room, some scientists believe they can put large, orbiting mirrors above Earth that could illuminate darkened areas below with spots of reflected sunlight that measure tens of miles across.</p>
        <p>If it can be done, proponents say, providing sunshine at night could save billions of dollars each year in electrical lighting costs, extend twilight hours during planting and harvesting seasons to aid farmers, allow more working hours on large construction projects and help in rescue and recovery operations after natural disasters like earthquakes and hurricanes.</p>
        <p>A consortium of state-owned companies and agencies in Russia, headed by the NPO Energia space company, is sponsoring the mirror-solar sail demonstration. The project is using some donated equipment, and engineers and technicians are volunteering their time. Proponents of the project hope a successful test will attract financial support from Western companies and the Russian Government.</p>
        <p>The idea of using mirrors in space like giant spotlights was proposed in 1929 by Hermann Oberth, a German scientist and space visionary. The idea was further developed by scientists in the United States and in the former Soviet Union, where it remains particularly popular because of its potential usefulness for lighting northern Siberia and other areas near the Arctic Circle during the long polar nights.</p>
        <p>Although both the Pentagon and the National Aeronautics and Space Administration considered solar reflectors from time to time in the last two decades, they never developed them.  Ambitious Goals</p>
        <p>But Russian theorists have eagerly proposed solar reflector systems that could constantly illuminate areas the size of several cities every night. The most ambitious proposal foresees a constellation of 100 reflectors, each 1,300 feet in diameter with a surface area of 30 acres.</p>
        <p>Initial operational systems, using reflectors 650 feet in diameter, would have 24 to 36 mirrors in northern inclination orbits either 620 miles or 3,700 miles above Earth, proponents say. A reflector could light a spot by itself or several could be focused on the same area for continuous illumination or greater brightness, scientists say, producing the light of up to 50 full moons. These mirrors, which would pivot as they passed overhead to keep their light on the same spot, could illuminate surface areas 35 miles to 55 miles across.</p>
        <p>While the idea of space mirrors fascinates some, others have wondered about possible environmental effects of interrupting the normal day-night cycle of animals and plants, particularly if the practice became widespread.</p>
        <p>Even extended daylight would affect the development and behavior of flora and fauna, and might influence local weather. After Soviet scientists first proposed launching a demonstration reflector satellite in 1984, the Soviet Academy of Sciences set up a committee to investigate possible ecological effects.</p>
        <p>Proponents of space mirrors say there is no evidence to date that reflected sunlight would cause harm, but agree on the need for environmental studies. Light from space would be both clean and renewable, they note, and would replace generated electricity and its associated pollution.</p>
        <p>"Illumination of this type will not have an impact on local environmental conditions, such as warming of the atmosphere," said Nikolay N. Sevastianov, director general of the experimental reflector program, which has been named Noviy Svet, or New Light.</p>
        <p>"Other possible impacts to the environment are being studied and are part of the on-going project," he said in a written response to questions sent to him in Moscow. Resistance to Change</p>
        <p>Dr. Roald Sagdeev, former director of the Soviet Academy of Science's Space Science Institute and now director of the East-West Science and Technology Center at the University of Maryland in College Park, said advocates of a Soviet space mirror began promoting the idea 15 years ago. But authorities in the space program were skeptical, he said, because the benefits were uncertain.</p>
        <p>"While some people would be happy with light from space, others might not like it," Dr. Sagdeev said in an interview. "In all of the dark areas of the sub-Arctic, people have adapted to the natural cycles they have and may not want it to change."</p>
        <p>The mirror proposal faces technical hurdles, like developing a pointing system that can keep a spot of light trained on a specific area of the ground as the reflector travels through space at almost 18,000 miles an hour, Dr. Sagdeev said. But he added that it probably could be made to work. "Technically, you could put up a big mirror," he said, "but the issue is finding a use for it."</p>
        <p>Space mirror proponents say successful tests with Banner and similar future spacecraft will prove the concept and its usefulness.</p>
        <p>The Progress spacecraft carrying the 88-pound Banner experiment as a secondary payload docked with the Mir space station on Oct. 30. The reflector was to have been deployed in December, but Russian space authorities delayed it because of the upcoming linkup to Mir of a Soyuz-TM spacecraft. The Soyuz will test a new docking system that an American space shuttle will use to hook up with Mir in 1995. Planners decided to leave the Progress in place to keep the space station balanced during the Soyuz test.</p>
        <p>Plans now call for the Mir astronauts to fit the drum containing Banner into the docking port of the Progress before the unmanned supply ship leaves the station on Feb. 4 or 5. When the Progress is 500 feet from Mir, Banner is to be deployed by an electric motor that spins its drum and unfolds the eight-segment reflector disk like a Japanese fan. The mirror will orbit at an altitude of about 225 miles, and from Earth will look like a bright star . Light of Three Moons</p>
        <p>The plastic reflector has no support frame and its circular shape is to be maintained by the rotation of the drum, its designers say. Dropping to a lower orbit than Mir, Progress will sue maneuvering thrusters to point and position the mirror to reflect sunlight to specific spots on Earth.  After three to five days of tests, both Banner and Progress will re-enter the atmosphere and burn up.</p>
        <p>During the tests, Russian engineers say the small reflector should cast light equivalent to three to five full moons over an area of Earth measuring about three miles in diameter. They hope the astronauts will be able to see and photograph the spot as it moves across the night side of the planet.</p>
        <p>Vladimir S. Syromiatnikov, the mission manager for NPO Energia, said the reflected light from this simple test should move over the ground swiftly, visible to observers as a brief flash. In the sky, Banner should look like a bright star to those within the beam of light, and under certain conditions, he said, this artificial star might be visible in the daytime.</p>
        <p>The test is also drawing attention worldwide from engineers and space enthusiasts who are interested in the concept of solar sailing, in which gossamer sails hundreds or thousands of feet long and wide would harness the pervasive pressure of sunlight in the vacuum of space to move ships.</p>
        <p>Studies by NASA and others indicate that solar sailing is a feasible way of propulsion that would free spacecraft from having to carry heavy chemical fuel. But like the space reflector idea, no government has supported the concept with money to test it. For years, private groups in the United States, Russia, Japan and Europe have proposed an international race to the Moon using different kinds of sails. But the effort remains Earthbound because of a lack of funds. First Test of Solar Sail</p>
        <p>"A lot of people are excited about the Russian test because it will mark the first time a solar sail is deployed," said Dr. Louis D. Friedman, executive director of the Planetary Society, a national public membership organization in Pasadena, Calif., that promotes space exploration.</p>
        <p>Dr. Friedman, who headed a major NASA study of solar sailing in the mid-1970's, said both reflectors and sails used the same materials and principles. While the Banner test is too short and too low in the atmosphere to test solar-sail flight, it should be a good test of deployment and material handling.</p>
        <p>"There is only so much testing and modeling that you can do on Earth, because you really can't answer some questions unless you go into space," Dr. Friedman said in an interview. "I'm jealous. It's a neat test and I wish we were doing it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
