<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bridge</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="582389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGE (CARD GAME)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUSCOTT, ALAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZHOU QI</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DF153EF931A25752C0A965958260" item-length="286" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bridge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TRUSCOTT, ALAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In American bridge terms, the most important import from China in 1992 occurred at Christmas: The leading Chinese tournament director became a permanent resident of Flushing, Queens.</p>
        <p>His Chinese name is Zhou Qi, but in the Western world he is known as George Chow. He is a talented player as well as organizer, as the diagramed deal, played a decade ago, demonstrates. As South, he arrived in five diamonds doubled after his opponents had bid to four spades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In American bridge terms, the most important import from China in 1992 occurred at Christmas: The leading Chinese tournament director became a permanent resident of Flushing, Queens.</p>
        <p>His Chinese name is Zhou Qi, but in the Western world he is known as George Chow. He is a talented player as well as organizer, as the diagramed deal, played a decade ago, demonstrates. As South, he arrived in five diamonds doubled after his opponents had bid to four spades.</p>
        <p>The contract would have been easy to make if West had led the spade ace. But he led the club seven, and South had to plan very carefully. Out of 100 players, 99 would routinely play low from the dummy and would be headed for defeat: West would be in a position to win the first trump lead, underlead the heart ace and score a club ruff.</p>
        <p>But Chow diagnosed a singleton lead, recognized the danger and found an ingenious countermove. He won with the club ace in dummy, dropping the jack from his hand, and led the spade king. He discarded the heart four, which was a scissors coup, cutting the defenders' communications. It deprived East of the entry he needed to give his partner a club ruff.</p>
        <p>West took the spade ace and underled his heart ace. South ruffed and led a low trump. West chose to take the ace and lead his remaining trump, so South was in dummy with the jack, and was able to score three club tricks by leading the club nine for a finesse.</p>
        <p>The result would have been the same if West had played low on the trump lead, allowing the jack to win immediately, for the club finesse would have been equally effective. If West ruffed the club nine with the trump ace, dummy's remaining trump would take card of the declarer's club ten.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
