<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Revolution, A Russian Restoration</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19941014T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="717794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN SERVICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOLUNTEERS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <org class="indexing_service">RANDOM HOUSE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOONAN, WENDY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Volunteers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE2DA173CF930A25753C1A962958260" item-length="1786" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Revolution, A Russian Restoration</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WENDY MOONAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MOONAN, WENDY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN the Consulate of the Russian Federation in New York opens its doors to the public for the first time on Oct. 26, guests should not be surprised if the hosts play Mussorgsky's "Pictures at an Exhibition" as the trays of pirogi and shot glasses of Stolichnaya Cristall are passed around.</p>
        <p>The 20-year restoration of this 1902 Beaux-Arts palazzo at 9 East 91st Street, overlooking the Cooper-Hewitt Museum, has been detoured by politics (the Soviet Union's move into Afghanistan), impeded by nature (a decade of exposure to the elements) and galvanized by glasnost (i.e., American generosity).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN the Consulate of the Russian Federation in New York opens its doors to the public for the first time on Oct. 26, guests should not be surprised if the hosts play Mussorgsky's "Pictures at an Exhibition" as the trays of pirogi and shot glasses of Stolichnaya Cristall are passed around.</p>
        <p>The 20-year restoration of this 1902 Beaux-Arts palazzo at 9 East 91st Street, overlooking the Cooper-Hewitt Museum, has been detoured by politics (the Soviet Union's move into Afghanistan), impeded by nature (a decade of exposure to the elements) and galvanized by glasnost (i.e., American generosity).</p>
        <p>But it took an American book publisher to spur the project toward completion, cannily timing it for an exhibition of historical Russian and Soviet photographs that will be presented at a gala book party in the consulate that evening. The official opening is not until January.</p>
        <p>The tale begins with Random House, which has just published "The Russian Century," a coffeetable tome with 320 pictures documenting the history of the country from the Romanovs' vast empire of 1900 to the Russian Federation of today. Two British researchers spent a year visiting Russian archives, museums and 50 photographers to collect the pictures. Almost none of the pictures have been seen before in the West; in fact, some were discovered in an elevator shaft at the K.G.B. headquarters.</p>
        <p>How did this cash-strapped country ever find the wherewithal to revamp a lavishly ornamented landmark that just happened to be a wreck? Though the building had been designed by Carrere &amp; Hastings, the architects of the New York Public Library, "everything was a big mess," said Ivan A. Kuznetsov, the consul general of the Russian Federation in New York.</p>
        <p>Paint was peeling from the 18-foot-high walls. Bits of plaster were falling from the elaborate ceilings. Dampness had seeped into the paneling in the Elizabethan-style library. Though the Russians were repairing and updating the building's infrastructure, the second floor with its grand public rooms, was in ruins.</p>
        <p>The project's czar-in-charge was not a Russian, however, but Harold Evans, president and publisher of Random House, whose staff sweet-talked roughly a dozen professionals, from silk weavers to photo technicians to caterers, into working gratis for up to six months. Mr. Evans also enjoined Random House and a few friends with deep pockets to make up some of the difference. If it was a labor of love for Mr. Evans, who got the idea after happening on a trunkful of 1917 Russian pictures in a London picture library, it was sheer labor for Terren Baker, a partner in Whirlwind &amp; Company, the exhibition designers. "We are not being paid a cent for our design," she said with amazement.</p>
        <p>The limestone house, designed to resemble a 16th-century Roman palace with a 50-by-28-foot Louis XVI-style ballroom, indoor squash court and infirmary, was given to Emily Vanderbilt Sloane and John Henry Hammond as a wedding present by the bride's father, William D. Sloane. Mr. Sloane had bought the land from the man across the street, Andrew Carnegie.</p>
        <p>The Hammonds and their five children (including John Jr., the jazz impresario who discovered Count Basie and Billie Holiday, and Alice, who married Benny Goodman) lived there for 44 years, attended to by 16 servants and steeped in teetotaling propriety.</p>
        <p>"Mother's parties were never too much fun and never lasted too long because no liquor was served," said Rachel Hammond Breck, now 86.</p>
        <p>The house was sold in 1946 to a doctor, who transformed a portion of it into an eye hospital before selling it to the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics in 1975.</p>
        <p>The Soviets then bought the house next door, No. 11, which was converted into offices; the Federation is housed there now. But in 1979, while the buildings were being restored, the Soviet troops moved into Afghanistan and President Carter severed diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union. The consulate was closed before it had ever opened.</p>
        <p>When the Russians returned in 1992, Mr. Kuznetsov was astounded by the effects of 12 years of neglect, especially on No. 9. Water had seeped in from the roof, forming a pond in the basement, the floorboards squeaked and the plumbing, furnace and elevators no longer functioned. "My job was to bring the building back to life," he said.</p>
        <p>A crew of 16 skilled Russian artisans arrived at Mr. Kuznetsov's request. He has been supervising these workers for two years.</p>
        <p>"The men come for 9 or 10 months, then go back to Moscow, and others arrive," he said. "They live on the top floor, under the roof."</p>
        <p>From 8 A.M. to 6 P.M. the workmen can be found painting, scraping, plastering, gilding or hammering on scaffolds under the careful eye of a foreman, Vladimir Yakimchuk. They have one hour off for lunch, a 10-minute smoking break each hour, and they listen to Frank Sinatra -- a favorite song is "Come Fly With Me" -- as they work.</p>
        <p>"You can't expedite work with a whip," Mr. Yakimchuk said. "For every type of job, you have to have the time and the right kind of worker." When he didn't, he had to request a specialist from Moscow.</p>
        <p>At 6 P.M., the men watch the Moscow news via satellite. For recreation, they retreat upstairs to their easels and art supplies, which are housed in a paneled bedroom where Mr. Hammond used to practice his golf swing with crocheted cotton balls. Here, some of them spend their evenings painting scenes of the Russian countryside in winter, complete with sleighs and silhouettes of church steeples.</p>
        <p>The men, who do not speak much English, rarely leave the building. When they do, mostly on weekends, it's to fish for carp along the Hudson River, shop at Bloomingdale's or visit museums. "After all, we're on Museum Mile," Victor Yevseyek, a vice consul, pointed out.</p>
        <p>The Russian Government pays their rent, transportation and salaries in American currency. They buy their own food, however, and cook their borscht in the mansion's basement kitchen.</p>
        <p>During the Hammonds' day, food took so long to travel from below ground to the dining room that its arrival was greeted with general dismay. "Father said he'd never had a hot meal," Adele Hammond Emery, 92, recalled.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kuznetsov said that when Random House first contacted him about co-sponsoring an exhibition, "they said they could make the restoration go quicker," and he understood the implication: it would be much faster to do it together.</p>
        <p>"We had the workers," he said. "They had the archives with the history of the house, and they could find professional architects and designers."</p>
        <p>For the funds necessary to mount the photographs in the exhibition, Mr. Evans went to a Russophile friend, Ted Forstmann, the senior partner of Forstmann Little &amp; Company, a leveraged buyout firm, and chairman of Gulfstream Aerospace Corporation.</p>
        <p>"I had a Russian nanny as a child," Mr. Forstmann said. "I also studied Russian literature at college."</p>
        <p>The only Americans who will be paid -- and only for their costs -- are the curtain fabricators, International Blind Contractors, whose workers are installing the elaborate double-lined draperies the Ashley Studio designed for the ballroom, music room and library; the caterer, Mark Fahrer, and Whirlwind for its materials.</p>
        <p>Random House went into high gear to persuade these talents to donate their services and to organize their collective efforts. If Mr. Evans was the czar, Stanley Barrows, the former chairman of the interior-design department at the Fashion Institute of Technology and mentor of such gilt-edged decorators as Mario Buatta and Albert Hadley, became the commissar.</p>
        <p>Mr. Barrows proved to be a tough taskmaster. "An absolute perfectionist," said Sam Paxhia, one of his former students, who spent 50 hours searching the city for chandeliers, rugs and Louis XVI reproductions for the ballroom, dining room and library, which have yet to be ordered. "Stanley is great, but sometimes his suggestions are so demanding that they are a little hard to hear."</p>
        <p>On one occasion, for instance, Mr. Barrows thought the Russian workers were skimping on the amount of gold on the moldings in the ballroom and demanded that the work be redone. It was.</p>
        <p>He told Ashley Studios and American Silk Mills to change the color combinations in their draperies at least three times. They did. He insisted that the panels in the ballroom be repainted, too, in a shade of pale almond green called eau de Nil. The Russians workers had never heard of it but they did as directed.</p>
        <p>The more the professor demanded, the more the Russians apparently liked him. Though the workers could not understand a word that Mr. Barrows uttered -- he spoke through a translator -- they followed him from room to room with an office chair so that the 80-year-old design doyen could rest as he reviewed their work.</p>
        <p>"I agreed with all of Professor Barrow's proposals," said Mr. Kuznetsov, who has yet to order a single piece of furniture.</p>
        <p>In fact, whether the renovation will be completed in time is uncertain. "Today I invited our Minister of Foreign Affairs, Andrei Kozyrev, and our Ambassador to the U.S., Yuli Vorontsov, who was the one responsible for buying this building in 1975, to come to our official opening on Jan. 31," Mr. Kuznetsov said. "And they have agreed to come."</p>
        <p>But will the paint be dry on the walls? And will the draperies hang straight?</p>
        <p>"I have a small worry," Mr. Kuznetsov admitted.  Classical Draperies</p>
        <p>"THE draperies for the Russian Consulate may not be the grandest we've ever done, but they are certainly the most classical," said Diane Nixon of the Ashley Studio. She and Robert Ashley (shown together below) created patterns for the restoration project. They also persuaded American Silk Mills to donate 200 yards of fabric.</p>
        <p>The Ashley Studio, a London partnership that moved to New York in 1989, creates fabrics for architects and couturiers, including Givenchy.</p>
        <p>The studio donated three exclusive designs. For the ballroom (sketch at right), they adapted a chain of daisies and roses from the paneling into a stripe (in background). An arabesque inspired the pattern for the music room.</p>
        <p>In the Tudor library, Mr. Ashley used the strapwork pattern on the barrel-vault ceiling for the Austrian shades. "We consider ourselves the special-effects people of the textile world," he said. History On Display</p>
        <p>The book that helped spur a renovation is "The Russian Century" (Random House). More than 100 old photographs published in the book will be on view from Oct. 27 through Nov. 8 in the restored rooms, like the one at left, at the Consulate of the Russian Federation in New York. Below, political prisoners pose with revolutionary banners in 1917.</p>
        <p>Correction:  October 14, 1994, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in The Home Section yesterday about renovations to the Russian Consulate in New York misstated the status of diplomatic relations between the United States and the Soviet Union following the invasion of Afghanistan in 1979. President Jimmy Carter barred the opening of the consulate then; he did not sever diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 14, 1994, Friday</p>
        <p>An article in The Home Section yesterday about renovations to the Russian Consulate in New York misstated the status of diplomatic relations between the United States and the Soviet Union following the invasion of Afghanistan in 1979. President Jimmy Carter barred the opening of the consulate then; he did not sever diplomatic relations with the Soviet Union.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
