<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Accounts of a Retrieval Of Gifts Vary, Lawyers Say</title>
    <meta content="Y29STA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1042363"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wiretapping and Other Eavesdropping Devices and Methods</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maryland</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Sun Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Neil A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Currie, Betty</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Kenneth W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lindsey, Bruce</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tripp, Linda R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wiretapping and Other Eavesdropping Devices and Methods</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DF1F3CF93AA1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Accounts of a Retrieval Of Gifts Vary, Lawyers Say</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL A. LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Neil A</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lawyers say grand jury has heard different accounts from Monica S Lewinsky and Betty Currie, Pres Clinton's personal secretary, about the retrieval of the gifts Clinton gave Lewinsky, a focus of Kenneth W Starr's investigation of possible obstruction of justice by Clinton; say Currie testified that Lewinsky had telephoned her last winter and told her to come by her apartment for the gifts; say Lewinsky testified that Currie had just showed up, presumably on Clinton's instructions; Bruce Lindsey, deputy White House counsel, testifies again before grand jury; photo; Baltimore Sun reports that Linda R Tripp, who recorded conversations with Lewinsky, was told when she bought the tape recorder she used that it was illegal to record telephone conversations secretly in Maryland (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Monica S. Lewinsky and Betty Currie, President Clinton's personal secretary, have offered a grand jury different versions of one element in the investigation of obstruction of justice by Mr. Clinton, lawyers familiar with their accounts said today.</p>
        <p>The contrasting accounts concern who told Mrs. Currie to show up at Ms. Lewinsky's apartment last winter to retrieve gifts that Mr. Clinton had given Ms. Lewinsky, the lawyers said. Mrs. Currie testified that Ms. Lewinsky, a former White House intern, had telephoned her and told her to come by and get the gifts; Ms. Lewinsky testified that Mrs. Currie had simply shown up, presumably having been told to do so by Mr. Clinton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Monica S. Lewinsky and Betty Currie, President Clinton's personal secretary, have offered a grand jury different versions of one element in the investigation of obstruction of justice by Mr. Clinton, lawyers familiar with their accounts said today.</p>
        <p>The contrasting accounts concern who told Mrs. Currie to show up at Ms. Lewinsky's apartment last winter to retrieve gifts that Mr. Clinton had given Ms. Lewinsky, the lawyers said. Mrs. Currie testified that Ms. Lewinsky, a former White House intern, had telephoned her and told her to come by and get the gifts; Ms. Lewinsky testified that Mrs. Currie had simply shown up, presumably having been told to do so by Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>Kenneth W. Starr, the Whitewater independent counsel, is investigating whether the President sought to obstruct justice by trying to conceal the gifts, including some T-shirts, a hatpin, a brooch and souvenirs from New York and Martha's Vineyard, from lawyers for Paula Corbin Jones, a former Arkansas clerical employee who had sued Mr. Clinton for sexual misconduct.</p>
        <p>As part of their unsuccessful effort to demonstrate that Mr. Clinton and Ms. Lewinsky had an intimate relationship, Ms. Jones's lawyers had asked Ms. Lewinsky to turn over any gifts she had received from the President. The Jones lawyers wanted to demonstrate a pattern of sexual misbehavior by him with subordinates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's advisers hope that the testimony of Mrs. Currie, who has been cast before the public as an honorable witness, would tend to support an interpretation that Ms. Lewinsky orchestrated the transfer of gifts herself without the President's involvement and thus he did not obstruct justice.</p>
        <p>But the conflicts in testimony between Ms. Lewinsky and Mrs. Currie may ultimately be less important than the conflict in testimony between Ms. Lewinsky and the President himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton testified before the grand jury nearly two weeks ago that he had told Ms. Lewinsky she had no choice but to comply with the subpoena from the Jones lawyers to turn over the gifts, lawyers familiar with his testimony said. Ms. Lewinsky has testified that Mr. Clinton counseled her that she would not have to turn over the gifts if they were no longer in her possession, other lawyers said.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Starr's investigation moves toward its conclusion, Bruce Lindsey, one of Mr. Clinton's closest and longest-serving advisers, testified again before the grand jury today. The White House had tried to block the testimony of Mr. Lindsey, the deputy White House counsel, on grounds it would violate the President's right to confidential legal advice. The Supreme Court agreed to hear the matter after it reconvened  in October but refused to order Mr. Starr to wait until then before hearing from Mr. Lindsey.</p>
        <p>In a related inquiry, Linda R. Tripp, the former Lewinsky colleague who recorded their conversations about a Presidential affair, was told when she bought the tape recorder that it was illegal to record telephone conversations secretly in Maryland, The Baltimore Sun reported today.</p>
        <p>The Sun said that a clerk at the Radio Shack store where Mrs. Tripp had bought the recorder had testified before the Maryland grand jury that is investigating Mrs. Tripp for possible wiretapping violations. The clerk, Antoine Burrell, 21, told The Sun, ''I know she was told.'' He did not elaborate.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Tripp was an important figure in starting the investigation of whether Mr. Clinton had a sexual liaison with Ms. Lewinsky and then tried to cover it up. She took hours of recorded conversations with Ms. Lewinsky to Mr. Starr, who quickly sought authority to expand his investigation of the failed Whitewater land deal.</p>
        <p>The Sun reported that the policy of the Radio Shack store was to inform all customers about the Maryland law.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
