<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Rangers Roll On, but the Party Is Just Starting -- Sixth Straight Victory Puts Garden Fans In Seventh Heaven</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="685052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON CAPITALS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Washington Capitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0DD1E30F937A35756C0A962958260" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Rangers Roll On, but the Party Is Just Starting -- Sixth Straight Victory Puts Garden Fans In Seventh Heaven</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ranger fans are getting giddy. They are parading around Madison Square Garden with tinfoil replicas of the Stanley Cup. They are waving whisk brooms that signify a series sweep.</p>
        <p>This shows a bit of hubris just two games into the second round of a four-round tournament, but these people aren't known for humility in victory or suffering in silence. They think they've waited long enough for a trophy -- since 1940. They act as if it is due them. And, with the way things are going for their team, this just might be their year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ranger fans are getting giddy. They are parading around Madison Square Garden with tinfoil replicas of the Stanley Cup. They are waving whisk brooms that signify a series sweep.</p>
        <p>This shows a bit of hubris just two games into the second round of a four-round tournament, but these people aren't known for humility in victory or suffering in silence. They think they've waited long enough for a trophy -- since 1940. They act as if it is due them. And, with the way things are going for their team, this just might be their year.</p>
        <p>Last night, they celebrated a 5-2 victory over the Washington Capitals, which gave their Rangers a 2-games-to-0 lead in the best 4-of-7-game Eastern Conference semifinal.</p>
        <p>It was their sixth victory in six playoff games, a team record, and this one was an example of what happens to a good team on a winning streak: They won even though they were outplayed most of the way. And they won because Esa Tikkanen decided to put himself on the ice at a pivotal moment.</p>
        <p>It came midway through the second period, with the score tied at 2-2. The Rangers had just finished killing off a penalty to Mark Messier, allowing no shots on their goal during the two-minute span.</p>
        <p>The top line went on the attack in the Washington zone and Pat Peake of Washington was about to be penalized by Referee Kerry Fraser for pulling down Adam Graves.</p>
        <p>But the referee delayed the whistle because the Rangers had possession of the puck. Goalie Mike Richter left his net so the Rangers could add an extra attacker. It turned out to be Tikkanen, who jumped over the boards and joined the sustained action in the Washington end.</p>
        <p>"Everybody was excited and Mike Keenan was screaming, 'Sit down! Sit down!' " Tikkanen said. "So I just jump on the ice and go. You have to be sneaky in this game."</p>
        <p>Brian Leetch, at the left point, slid the puck over to Mark Messier, on the right side. With Glenn Anderson tying up two Capitals in front of the crease, Messier sent a pass diagonally to the side of the net, where Tikkanen lurked. Goalie Rick Tabaracci had gone down, anticipating a shot from Messier, and Tikkanen was able to direct the puck over the line from a sharp angle.</p>
        <p>Keenan, the coach, had a slightly different explanation of why Tikkanen was on the ice.</p>
        <p>"We had a random selection," he said, "but Tikk was very alert. Esa read the play well and it was just spontaneous. We decided right then that he would be the player."  This Replay Works</p>
        <p>Messier and Tikkanen had tried the same play a few seconds before.</p>
        <p>"Almost an identical play," Messier said. "And Tikk didn't make any mistake on the second one."</p>
        <p>It turned out to be the clinching goal of the game. Midway through the third period, the Rangers added two more, by Adam Graves and Stephane Matteau, just 19 seconds apart. Joe Kocur and Sergei Zubov scored the other Ranger goals.</p>
        <p>Kevin Hatcher and Mike Ridley scored for the Capitals, who played without top playoff scorer Michal Pivonka, out with a groin muscle pull, and goalie Don Beaupre, also out with a groin muscle pull. Calle Johansson has missed both games with nerve damage in his knee.</p>
        <p>Joe Juneau, Washington's flashy center, was once again without a goal or an assist. He had no shots on goal, was on the ice for two Ranger goals, and chose to pass the puck when he was in position to shoot. Kocur in the Right Place</p>
        <p>Aside from Tikkanen's effort, the other big goal for the Rangers was by Kocur, giving them a 1-1 tie at 16:42 of the first period at a time when the Capitals held a clear advantage in play.</p>
        <p>During a muscular burst of forechecking in the Capitals' zone, Kocur fought off a check and kept his stick low to turn in a shot by Aleksandr Karpovtsev. Both Kocur and Gilbert were parked in the slot, in front of Tabaracci, and both occupied the attention of Washington defenders. Kocur had been knocked down by John Slaney, but got up to make the play.</p>
        <p>"I still don't know what happened," said Kocur, who wasn't sure he touched the puck. "I just felt the defenseman on me. I didn't know what was going on."</p>
        <p>Kocur, generally employed as an intimidation specialist, said the only job of his line, which also included Sergei Nemchinov, was "to just create some disturbances. Get a couple of hits. Get the fans into the game."</p>
        <p>As if they need encouragement? SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>ADAM GRAVES led the team with six shots on goal. . . . The series resumes with Games 3 and 4 in Landover, Md., on Thursday and Saturday nights. . . . BRIAN BURKE, senior vice president of the National Hockey League, scoffed at the between-games discussion, initiated by the Rangers, about Washington players targeting Ranger players for intimidation tactics late in Game 1. "This whole thing has been blown way out of proportion, a lot of trash talk," Burke said. "It's a dead issue. It just isn't a big deal. A mountain has been made out of a molehill. I can't believe the life this thing has taken on for no reason." Game 2 had less nasty stuff, although JAY WELLS of the Rangers got two minutes for cross-checking at the final buzzer and TODD KRYGIER of Washington got a 10-minute misconduct.  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
