<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Personal Health</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Health Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="552608"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LYME DISEASE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTIBIOTICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TICKS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW ENGLAND JOURNAL OF MEDICINE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRODY, JANE E</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">HEALTH PAGE (NYT)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PERSONAL HEALTH (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Lyme Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lyme Disease</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antibiotics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insects</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DC1738F935A1575BC0A964958260" item-length="1265" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Personal Health</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jane E. Brody</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRODY, JANE E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATTITUDES about Lyme disease, a bacterial infection spread by ticks, range from a fatalistic "If I get it, I get it" to near hysteria whenever a suspicious speck is found on one's body. Some people fail to take the antibiotics their physicians prescribe for a suspected case of Lyme disease, while others demand such treatment even when doctors tell them it is not needed.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, physicians are often in a quandary about how to treat patients who say they have been bitten by ticks. Knowing that antibiotics can prevent the onset of Lyme disease in the relatively few people who become infected, should they take no chances and prescribe antibiotics for each patient who reports a tick bite, thus risking many unnecessary bad reactions to the medication? Should they insist on proof that it was a kind oftick that carries Lyme disease? Should they rely on the results of often inaccurate diagnostic tests? Or, knowing that antibiotics not only prevent Lyme disease but also cure it in its early stages, should they wait to see if classic symptoms develop before prescribing treatment?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATTITUDES about Lyme disease, a bacterial infection spread by ticks, range from a fatalistic "If I get it, I get it" to near hysteria whenever a suspicious speck is found on one's body. Some people fail to take the antibiotics their physicians prescribe for a suspected case of Lyme disease, while others demand such treatment even when doctors tell them it is not needed.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, physicians are often in a quandary about how to treat patients who say they have been bitten by ticks. Knowing that antibiotics can prevent the onset of Lyme disease in the relatively few people who become infected, should they take no chances and prescribe antibiotics for each patient who reports a tick bite, thus risking many unnecessary bad reactions to the medication? Should they insist on proof that it was a kind oftick that carries Lyme disease? Should they rely on the results of often inaccurate diagnostic tests? Or, knowing that antibiotics not only prevent Lyme disease but also cure it in its early stages, should they wait to see if classic symptoms develop before prescribing treatment?</p>
        <p>Adding to the physician's dilemma are two facts. First, patients can be unreliable about monitoring themselves for early signs of infection and returning later for diagnosis and treatment, even when there is a relatively high risk of contracting Lyme disease. Second, the disease is a great masquerader; its early symptoms mimic those of many other ailments, and its signs are sometimes so minimal as to be missed entirely. But no matter how minor the early symptoms, the disease can sometimes progress to produce long-lasting debilitating symptoms that, in rare cases, may no longer respond to therapy. A Treatment Guide</p>
        <p>Last week The New England Journal of Medicine published an analysis of the risks and benefits of prescribing preventive antibiotics. Until better diagnostic tests become available, the guidelines can help physicians and their patients decide how best to deal with a tick bite that could conceivably transmit Lyme disease.</p>
        <p>According to Dr. David Magid, an emergency-medicine specialist at Denver General Hospital and the principal author of the analysis, the primary objective of the advice is to provide patients with the maximum possible benefit while exposing them to the lowest risk of getting a serious illness or having an avoidable reaction to treatment. The guidelines are also intended to minimize the costs of medical care.</p>
        <p>Given the unreliability of currently available diagnostic tests, the analysis says, preventive antibiotics can be very useful, but only for a relative handful of patients who may be at risk of developing Lyme disease.</p>
        <p>The guidelines say that if a patient's chances of developing Lyme disease following a tick bite are 3.6 percent or higher, antibiotics should be taken without undue delay because the potential benefits of the therapy will greatly outweigh any risks. But if the chances of infection are less that 1 percent, it is best to wait and see because the risk of bad reactions to the antibiotic in such cases overwhelms the foreseeable benefits of preventing illness. Between these extremes, the analysis showed, it is a judgment call. Depending on the patient's circumstances -- like the person's state of health, distance from medical care and likelihood of complying with a medical regimen -- and on the level of concern about Lyme disease, the physician may or may not recommend preventive treatment.</p>
        <p>From the patient's perspective, the analysis should be very reassuring, for it very clearly shows how unlikely it is for the average person to get Lyme disease, even if the person is bitten by a deer tick in areas of the country where the Lyme bacterium is well established. According to Dr. David T. Dennis of Denver, Lyme disease expert for the Centers for Disease Control, current data show that even in high-risk areas, like Westchester County and Eastern Long Island in New York, no more than 5 percent of bites by the ticks that could conceivably carry Lyme disease result in infection. And even if a person is bitten by a tick that is actually infected, only about one bite in 10 will result in transmission of the infectious agent.</p>
        <p>But the guidelines also have some important limitations. The treatment advice applies only to people who know they have been bitten by the extremely tiny deer ticks that most frequently carry the Lyme disease bacterium, Borrelia burgdorferi, a spiral microorganism of the kind called a spirochete. That leaves out three-fourths of Lyme disease patients because only 25 percent of the people who contract the disease can recall being bitten by a tick. That is not hard to understand because the deer tick, in its most common feeding stage, is at most the size of a sesame seed when fully stuffed with blood.</p>
        <p>The main problem is how to know so precisely what the chances are of becoming infected. To determine this, the physician would have to know the region where the tick bite occurred, the proportion of ticks carrying the spirochete in that area and how long the tick might have been feeding on the person before being discovered and removed. Making a Decision</p>
        <p>Dr. Magid and his co-authors -- Dr. Brian Schwartz of Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health, Dr. Joseph Craft of Yale University and Dr. J. Sanford Schwartz of the University of Pennsylvania -- listed 11 states where Lyme ticks are most widely established: Massachusetts, Connecticut, Rhode Island, New York, New Jersey, Pennsylvania, Delaware, Maryland, Wisconsin, Minnesota and California. There are also isolated areas where the tick is established in Illinois, Maine, New Hampshire, Iowa, Indiana, Michigan, North Carolina, Virginia, Arizona, Utah, Oregon and Washington.</p>
        <p>Of these, Dr. Magid said, preventive antibiotic treatment is clearly warranted only in areas like Westchester, where 40 to 50 percent of the ticks are infected with the Lyme bacterium. In the rest of the Northeast and Mid-Atlantic states and in the Upper Midwest, preventive treatment can be helpful in some cases, especially where there may be local pockets of infection.</p>
        <p>But for the rest of the country, including the Pacific Northwest, where only about 5 percent of Lyme-carrying ticks are infected, preventive treatment does not pay, the analysis showed. In such cases it is better to wait to see if symptoms develop or a diagnostic test turns positive before administering antibiotics.</p>
        <p>The authors also advise against preventive treatment for people who cannot produce either the culprit tick or a reliable description of a Lyme-carrying tick because their chance of getting Lyme disease is "probably less than 1 percent," Dr. Magid said.</p>
        <p>Preventive treatment usually involves the antibiotic tetracycline, which should not be taken by women who are more than three months' pregnant, by women who are nursing infants or by small children. However, when preventive treatment is prescribed, it is important to take the full series of doses: two or three times a day for two weeks to one month. Completing the full course of treatment is even more critical for patients who develop suspicious symptoms, such as a bull's-eye rash and flu-like symptoms or patients who have a positive diagnostic test.</p>
        <p>For anyone who ventures outdoors -- even just into the yard -- in an area where Lyme disease is well established, Dr. Dennis strongly urges a daily tick check of the entire body. Removing ticks within 24 to 36 hours of their arrival greatly reduces their chances of transmitting the infection.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
