<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Regulators Seek Limits On Insurer Sales Pitches</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="673160"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INSURANCE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REGULATION AND DEREGULATION OF INDUSTRY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINES (PENALTIES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STATES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FLORIDA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">METROPOLITAN LIFE INSURANCE CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF INSURANCE COMMISSIONERS</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940308T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6D61F3AF93BA35750C0A962958260" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Regulators Seek Limits On Insurer Sales Pitches</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL QUINT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State insurance regulators are moving closer to sharply limiting how sales agents may describe the future benefits of life insurance policies, despite strong objections from insurance companies and agents.</p>
        <p>Approval of the changes by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners is more likely because of recent reports of improper sales activities by some agents of the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, regulators said yesterday. A report describing how Met Life improperly sold insurance policies disguised as retirement or savings plans to about 60,000 customers was issued by the Florida Insurance Commissioner on Sunday. The report led commissioners to approve a plan to fine Metropolitan $20 million.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State insurance regulators are moving closer to sharply limiting how sales agents may describe the future benefits of life insurance policies, despite strong objections from insurance companies and agents.</p>
        <p>Approval of the changes by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners is more likely because of recent reports of improper sales activities by some agents of the Metropolitan Life Insurance Company, regulators said yesterday. A report describing how Met Life improperly sold insurance policies disguised as retirement or savings plans to about 60,000 customers was issued by the Florida Insurance Commissioner on Sunday. The report led commissioners to approve a plan to fine Metropolitan $20 million.</p>
        <p>At a meeting of the association yesterday in Denver, a special committee said it favored a law that would stop agents from using any future projections of a policy's benefits in their sales presentations, except for the death benefit and the gradual increases in the cash value of the policy that are guaranteed by the insurance company.  Similar Mutual Fund Rule</p>
        <p>The proposed rule is similar to that governing mutual funds, which are not allowed to predict the future, only to indicate past performance. It would require agents to explain to customers that past performance may not be a good guide to the future.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, agents could discuss the additional value policy holders of identical products have received in the past from dividends and other nonguaranteed payments. Companies that persist in using sales illustrations that include projections of nonguaranteed benefits could be penalized and required to pay customers according to the claims the projection used.</p>
        <p>The rule is intended to curb the widespread use by agents of computer printouts of insurance policy benefits that exaggerate how the policy's value grows as the company pays dividends to the holder. When interest rates declined in the last five years, many projections made in earlier years proved to be far too optimistic.</p>
        <p>The stand taken by regulators was unchanged from December, despite complaints by insurance companies that it would make their products appear less attractive compared to alternative investments.</p>
        <p>William N. Albus, senior general counsel for the National Association of Life Underwriters, which represents life insurance sales agents, said illustrations of future benefits "are essential to explaining how a policy works." He suggested that agents should be allowed to project current dividends into the future and include an example of how a policy would look if its dividends were reduced by one percentage point.  No 'Workable' Alternatives</p>
        <p>David J. Lyons, Iowa's insurance commissioner, said insurance companies and agents "have not presented any alternatives that seemed workable and that satisfied our desire to protect consumers."</p>
        <p>The insurance commissioners are not expected to recommend the proposal as a law that states should pass until June. But for now, Mr. Lyons said, "the public's and the politicians' perceptions of sales abuses have been so raised that people are ready to accept more radical approaches."</p>
        <p>Insurance companies have, however, persuaded regulators to change some parts of the proposed rules. One idea, to give consumers the right to sue insurance companies about misleading sales tactics, has been deleted.</p>
        <p>Mary Griffin, an insurance expert at Consumers Union, a consumer advocacy organization, said many insurance officials had threatened to fight in state legislatures to stop the association's proposal from becoming law. "Their opposition makes one wonder if anything can be done without Federal regulation of the industry," she said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Griffin said regulators still needed to address other sales practices, like the selling of products that are inappropriate to an individual's needs, as well as requiring the disclosure of the agent's commission.  Licensing Is Sought</p>
        <p>In other actions, the insurance commissioners issued a proposal to require licensing of companies that buy insurance policies of individuals who are close to death, and need cash for medical bills.</p>
        <p>In response to complaints that many of these companies pay too little for the policies, commissioners recommended that consumers with a life expectancy of less than six months receive 90 percent of an insurance policy's face amount, falling to 70 percent for those with a life expectancy of 18 months or more.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
