<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Objections to F.C.C. Deal With Nextel Over Spectrum</title>
    <meta content="25SPEC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/25/technology/25spectrum.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1592006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Emergency Telephone Numbers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nextel Communications Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mathematics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Emergency Telephone Numbers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Nextel Communications Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E3DB1F39F936A15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="659" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Objections to F.C.C. Deal With Nextel Over Spectrum</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">New Objections to F.C.C. Deal With Nextel Over Spectrum</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN BELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belson, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reports that FCC will soon approve plan to resolve fight over wireless spectrum used by Nextel Communications sets off new round of acrimony and threats of litigation; FCC wants Nextel to give up part of 800-megahertz spectrum it uses for its mobile phone operations, which have encroached on networks used by police and fire departments, in exchange for space in 1.9-gigahertz spectrum, which is used by its competitors; Nextel hopes to make swap without having to bid competitively in auction; competitors denounce such a swap as a giveaway and insist on auction (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reports that the Federal Communications Commission will soon approve a plan to resolve a fight over the wireless spectrum used by Nextel Communications has set off a new round of acrimony and threats of litigation involving regulators, mobile phone companies and public safety agencies.</p>
        <p>At issue is Nextel's use of 800-megahertz spectrum for its mobile phone operations and the future of valuable 1.9-gigahertz spectrum used by its rivals. Nextel, the country's sixth-largest cellphone provider, has seen its operations encroach on networks used by police and fire departments with similar radio spectrum for emergency communications.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reports that the Federal Communications Commission will resolve a fight over the wireless spectrum used by Nextel Communications has set off litigation threats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reports that the Federal Communications Commission will soon approve a plan to resolve a fight over the wireless spectrum used by Nextel Communications has set off a new round of acrimony and threats of litigation involving regulators, mobile phone companies and public safety agencies.</p>
        <p>At issue is Nextel's use of 800-megahertz spectrum for its mobile phone operations and the future of valuable 1.9-gigahertz spectrum used by its rivals. Nextel, the country's sixth-largest cellphone provider, has seen its operations encroach on networks used by police and fire departments with similar radio spectrum for emergency communications.</p>
        <p>Since Sept. 11, regulators have tried to free up more space for public safety agencies by getting Nextel to give up some of its holdings in return for other spectrum. Other cellular companies have denounced that swap as a giveaway and argued that Nextel, like other carriers, should have to bid for any new spectrum that it acquires.</p>
        <p>In an interview on CNBC television Wednesday, Michael K. Powell, the chairman of the F.C.C., said that he hopes to conclude a deal soon to end the bitter three-year fight. Wire reports, citing people close to the matter, said the chairman would support Nextel's plan to spend more than $5.4 billion to cede some of its 800-megahertz spectrum to public safety groups, to reorganize other parts of that space, and to receive 1.9-gigahertz spectrum in return.</p>
        <p>The tab for the move is more than three times the amount Nextel offered to spend last year. The proposal does not include any money to be paid for the new 1.9-gigahertz spectrum Nextel hopes to receive.</p>
        <p>Some analysts have said that Nextel, to avoid an auction, may be forced to pay an additional amount to the government for the new spectrum, but it is unclear how much.</p>
        <p>Mr. Powell wants to resolve the issue in the next few weeks, a move analysts say is prudent because of the presidential election. President Bush, eager to reinforce his record on homeland security, does not want to be viewed as impeding public safety priorities, analysts said.</p>
        <p>''The F.C.C. is in a bind and they have to resolve this as soon as possible given the world we live in and with elections coming up,'' said Patrick J. Comack, an analyst at Guzman &amp; Company in Coral Gables, Fla. ''This is an issue where there is such passion from the cops and firemen that it was impossible for Mr. Bush to ignore it.''</p>
        <p>Nextel hopes to make the spectrum swap without having to bid competitively in an auction, a proposal that has angered its competitors who are pressuring regulators and Congress to block the plan.</p>
        <p>House Budget Committee Chairman Jim Nussle, an Iowa Republican, plans to introduce a bill today that would force the F.C.C. to transfer any money raised from the sale of the spectrum to the Treasury.</p>
        <p>Nextel's rivals, most prominently Verizon Wireless, also argue that Nextel is offering to pay far less for the new spectrum than what it would have to pay through an auction. Verizon Wireless has said the 1.9-gigahertz spectrum Nextel wants is worth at least $5 billion, regardless of what Nextel must pay to vacate the 800-megahertz spectrum.</p>
        <p>Steve Largent, the chief executive of the Cellular Telecommunications and Internet Association, said that his association is pushing the F.C.C. to either hold an auction for the 1.9-gigahertz spectrum, or give Nextel less valuable 2.1-gigahertz spectrum that he says is closer in value to the amount Nextel is spending.</p>
        <p>Mr. Largent does not advocate that his association take its case to court, but he and many analysts expect Nextel's rivals to sue to block the F.C.C. from approving Nextel's plan. That, they say, could delay resolution of the problem for several years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
