<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="610243"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF1138F932A15756C0A965958260" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>John A. Rollwagen withdrew his nomination as Deputy Secretary of Commerce. The former chief executive of Cray Research said it was not an S.E.C. investigation into insider trading that changed his mind but rather his "culture shock" at dealing with government processes.  [ Page D1. ]</p>
        <p>A bipartisan group of Senators threw an obstacle in the path of President Clinton's budget plan, offering an alternative with fewer tax increases and deeper spending cuts.  [ A1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>John A. Rollwagen withdrew his nomination as Deputy Secretary of Commerce. The former chief executive of Cray Research said it was not an S.E.C. investigation into insider trading that changed his mind but rather his "culture shock" at dealing with government processes.  [ Page D1. ]</p>
        <p>A bipartisan group of Senators threw an obstacle in the path of President Clinton's budget plan, offering an alternative with fewer tax increases and deeper spending cuts.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>The former chief of Drexel Burnham Lambert was barred from any supervisory role in the securities industry for three years. The penalty against Frederick H. Joseph, the former executive, and an identical one against Edwin Kantor, a Drexel supervisor, concluded the Government's investigation of Drexel.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Computer companies warned the F.C.C. that they would develop a separate standard for high-definition television if the Government chose a technology favored by broadcasters.  [ D5. ] Markets</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average rose 23.25 points to 3,523.28, another record, after a late surge aided by extraordinarily heavy computerized trading.  [ D10. ]  Shares shorted neared record levels on the New York and American exchanges early this month.  [ D20. ]</p>
        <p>Some companies are offering 50-year bonds, just weeks after the Treasury slashed its auctions of 30-year bonds.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar declined and the mark's gains were muted, while gold rose modestly.  [ D17. ]  A Midwest cold snap lifted corn and soybean futures.  [ D17. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Leonard Tow, who runs a small public-utility company, Citizens Utilities in Stamford, Conn., received $21.6 million last year, according to an independent valuation.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Investors in Spectrum Information Technologies began selling, and the stock, which has topped the Nasdaq most-active list for the last three days, plunged $5.75, to $6 a share.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Chrysler sued to end a dealer franchise, claiming that a Maryland dealer provided poor customer service.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>A $1.18 billion all-cash offer by Carl C. Icahn was rejected by the bankrupt E-II Holdings and its creditors.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Applause but no ovation greeted Citicorp's hiring of Christopher J. Steffen, the cost-cutter who quit Eastman Kodak.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Sony and Matsushita Electric reported steep drops in earnings for the fiscal year that ended March 31.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Computer Associates's net income rose 72 percent, and its mainframe software business grew 21 percent for the year.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Triton Energy said tests confirmed a huge oil find in Colombia. One analyst said the news would save the company.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Cargill will enter the recycling business, building a plant in Minnesota to make plastic out of corn and potatoes.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>The owner of Jack-in-the-Box and two buyout groups agreed to acquire Restaurant Enterprises.  [ D3. ] International</p>
        <p>Plant closings and dismissals cause psychological distress in Japan because unemployment is considered shameful.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>A German labor leader was accused of insider trading based on information he gained as a member of Daimler-Benz's board.  [ D2. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Speculative frenzy surrounds the stock of Andrea Electronics, and yesterday the American Stock Exchange said its trades would have to be on a cash basis. Kurt Eichenwald: Market Place.  [ D10. ]</p>
        <p>BMW will trumpet its cars' value and safety, as well as performance, in a new advertising campaign intended to broaden its market. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D21. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
