<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Delays Sewage Release at E.P.A. and Whitman's Urging</title>
    <meta content="15SEWA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="909068"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">East River (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency (Epa)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Herszenhorn, David M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whitman, Christine Todd (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970215T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D8123FF936A25751C0A961958260" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Delays Sewage Release at E.P.A. and Whitman's Urging</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID M. HERSZENHORN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Herszenhorn, David M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City delays plan to dump some 500 million gallons of raw sewage into East River during repairs to city's sewage treatment system, citing pressure from Gov Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey and Environmental Protection Agency; Whitman comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City officials were planning to dump about 500 million gallons of raw sewage into the East River during repairs to the city's sewage treatment system, but the dumping was postponed at the last minute under pressure from Gov. Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey and the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, state and city officials said last night.</p>
        <p>The repair work, on a waste water pumping station at East 13th Street and Avenue C in Manhattan, was scheduled to begin early this morning and run for four days. The last time the shutdown of such a large station occurred, requiring the dumping of raw sewage, was in 1987, city officials said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City officials were planning to dump about 500 million gallons of raw sewage into the East River during repairs to the city's sewage treatment system, but the dumping was postponed at the last minute under pressure from Gov. Christine Todd Whitman of New Jersey and the Federal Environmental Protection Agency, state and city officials said last night.</p>
        <p>The repair work, on a waste water pumping station at East 13th Street and Avenue C in Manhattan, was scheduled to begin early this morning and run for four days. The last time the shutdown of such a large station occurred, requiring the dumping of raw sewage, was in 1987, city officials said.</p>
        <p>But the plan was postponed last night after an angry Governor Whitman telephoned Gov. George E. Pataki of New York to say that New Jersey would go to Federal court to prevent it.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman said she was afraid the sewage could harm shellfish beds and create other environmental problems on the Jersey Shore. ''My reaction was pretty violent and pretty immediate,'' she said last night. ''This is obviously totally unacceptable.''</p>
        <p>New York City officials said they had planned the repairs for about two years, had obtained the necessary permit from the State Department of Environmental Conservation a month ago and had met all legal requirements for notifying the public. Although Mrs. Whitman said she knew nothing of the plan until yesterday, city and state officials in New York said that last month they had informed the Interstate Sanitation Commission, some of whose members were appointed by Mrs. Whitman.</p>
        <p>Charles G. Sturcken, chief of staff of the city's Department of Environmental Protection, said the agency had agreed to a request by the Environmental Protection Agency that the work be postponed until after officials meet next week to discuss the impact of the raw sewage.</p>
        <p>''What we have done in deference to the request by the E.P.A. is we have postponed the shutdown of the pumping station until all the parties can sit down and discuss what issues they may have,'' Mr. Sturcken said. ''The E.P.A. wanted to discuss the amounts of discharge for the bypass, the impact on New Jersey and the impact on shell fishing in New Jersey.''</p>
        <p>The repair work, on two 48-inch gate valves, would require the city to shut the waste water pumping station, which sends about 140 million gallons of sewage a day across the East River to a treatment plant near Newton Creek in Brooklyn. Instead, the raw sewage would be pumped directly into the river, as it was before sewage treatment began in the late 1930's.</p>
        <p>The pumping station is one of the largest of about 50 such units around the city, officials said. The repairs  were intended to modernize the station so future repairs could be done without a complete shutdown.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sturcken and other officials said the dumping had been planned for a time when it would have the least environmental impact; it was to begin on a winter weekend because water use is lower and there are fewer people on the water.</p>
        <p>And city officials were quick to point out that they had complied with all laws. ''The city did everything properly in this instance,'' Colleen Roche, a spokeswoman for Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, said. ''Because of the concerns raised just this evening by the E.P.A., the city has agreed not to go forward.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sturcken said that advertisements announcing the plans to dump raw sewage appeared last week in three weekly neighborhood newspapers. He said the plans were not discussed with community boards or other local groups because it was not required.</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman's aides said she became furious when she learned of the plan shortly after 6 P.M., while en route to a feast marking the end of Ramadan, the Muslim holy month. ''Unless all of New York City got a massive case of Montezuma's revenge last week, I can't see how you can justify this kind of dumping,'' Mrs. Whitman said.</p>
        <p>Bob Friant, a spokesman for Mrs. Whitman on environmental issues, said New Jersey officials saw the potential for serious damage to shellfish beds as far south as the Navesink River in Monmouth County.  ''We are going to have to close our shellfish beds,'' he said. ''And we have grave concerns about the psychological damage in terms of spoiling beaches.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Whitman directed New Jersey officials to seek the help of the E.P.A. in blocking the dumping. She also said that the New Jersey State Attorney General, Peter G. Verniero, was prepared to seek an injunction in Federal Court to prevent the repair work from proceeding.</p>
        <p>Gary Sheffer, a spokesman for the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, which approved the repair work, said bypassing waste water pumping stations was rare but sometimes necessary.  Mr. Sheffer said Governor Pataki had approved of the postponement.</p>
        <p>The E.P.A.'s permission was not needed for the repairs, though state and local officials said the Federal agency was aware of the plan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Friant said New Jersey officials did not care who granted permission for the repairs.</p>
        <p>''All we knew was we were talking about an unprecedented amount of sewage,'' he said. ''Whether or not they got their permit from New York State, quite honestly, doesn't mean anything to us.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
