<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Evolution in Europe;   LATVIA LAWMAKERS MOVE TO DISSOLVE LINKS TO MOSCOW</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="350448"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DC1E38F936A35756C0A966958260" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Evolution in Europe;   LATVIA LAWMAKERS MOVE TO DISSOLVE LINKS TO MOSCOW</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ESTHER B. FEIN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>RIGA, Latvia, May 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Defying Moscow's warning to curb separatist movements, the Latvian Parliament today declared the beginning of a transition period leading to establishment of the republic's independence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Defying Moscow's warning to curb separatist movements, the Latvian Parliament today declared the beginning of a transition period leading to establishment of the republic's independence.</p>
        <p>Defying Moscow's warning to curb separatist movements, the Latvian Parliament today declared the beginning of a transition period leading to establishment of the republic's independence.</p>
        <p>The action was taken despite the Kremlin's continuing economic sanctions against Lithuania, the neighboring Baltic republic, which declared itself fully independent of Moscow eight weeks ago, and despite growing official criticism of similar moves by Estonia, the third of the three Baltic states.</p>
        <p>Lithuanian Example</p>
        <p>But the Latvian legislators seemed mindful of the consequences suffered by Lithuania, now in its third week of a partial fuel blockade by Moscow, and eager to maintain the talks that they have begun with the Kremlin over Latvia's future relationship with the Soviet Union. Estonia's Parliament pledged on March 30 to restore full independence gradually; since then, President Mikhail S. Gorbachev has offered Estonia a special status in what he has described as a new kind of Soviet confederation if it drops its plan for independence.</p>
        <p>The Latvian document stops short of declaring a complete break between Latvia and the Soviet Union and explicitly states that for the most part the Soviet Constitution and laws continue to be valid here during the transition period.</p>
        <p>Faces Serious Opposition</p>
        <p>While the Latvian approach was cautious, the declaration still faced serious opposition in the Parliament, though not enough to prevent the two-thirds majority needed for it to pass. In protest, 57 deputies refused to take part in a vote that they called premature and dangerous. The declaration was adopted by a vote of 138 in favor, none opposed and 1 abstention.</p>
        <p>It is not clear how Moscow will react to the Latvian declaration. The Kremlin could regard the move as a conciliatory gesture or a sign of confrontation and defiance.</p>
        <p>''I think there will be some kind of conflict with Moscow,'' said Anatolijs Gorbunovs, who was re-elected this week as chairman, or president, of the Latvian Parliament.</p>
        <p>''We didn't fulfill certain things that Moscow asked of us - for example, we specified that we are re-establishing the independent state of Latvia and we formally declared a transition period,'' he said. ''But the way we did it is very important. We think we left the door open and that our dialogue with Moscow will still continue.''</p>
        <p>Moscow has said that any republic is free to leave the Soviet Union if it follows the law on secession recently established by the Soviet Parliament, which includes the support of two-thirds of the voters in a public referendum, a negotiation period of up to five years with Moscow and other republics on territorial, financial and other matters, and final approval by the full Soviet Congress.</p>
        <p>The Baltic republics, Latvia, Estonia and Lithuania, assert that they are not bound by the new Soviet law because they were illegally incorporated into the Soviet Union. All three were independent nations when they were occupied by the Soviet Army in 1940 as a result of a secret treaty between Stalin and Hitler and then annexed.</p>
        <p>Lithuania and Estonia have already rejected outright the possibility of using the secession law as a means of breaking with the Soviet Union. Latvia said as much today. The declaration states the republic's application to join the Soviet Union was ''invalid from the moment of adoption,'' and the document further describes Latvia's desire not to secede, but rather to ''restore de facto the free, democratic and independent republic of Latvia.</p>
        <p>Conciliatory Tone Explained</p>
        <p>But one of the main actions taken by Lithuania and Estonia that angered the Kremlin was the suspension of the Soviet Constitution in those republics. In its declaration, the Latvian Parliament re-establishes the constitution of the former independent Latvian republic. But the declaration immediately suspends that constitution until it can be revised and adopted, except for articles ''expressing the constitutional and legal foundation of the Latvian state.''</p>
        <p>Those articles do not challenge outright the authority of the Soviet Constitution, and the declaration leaves standing Soviet laws that do not contradict Latvian sovereignty.</p>
        <p>The declaration further guarantees new rights to all Soviet citizens who choose to continue living in the republic.</p>
        <p>Latvian legislators said today that any conciliatory tone in their declaration was not a response to the Kremlin's tough stance toward Lithuania. Caution, they said, was dictated by the fact that independent-minded deputies won two-thirds of the seats in the Parliament only narrowly. People of Latvian descent make up barely half the population of their own republic, and many non-Latvians oppose independence.</p>
        <p>''The situation in Latvia itself objectively dictated what I would call not caution but our realism,'' said Dainis Ivans, leader of the Popular Front, one of the first grass-roots orgnizations to call for Latvian independence, and first deputy chairman of the Parliament. ''But there should be no question about what we have done. We have taken the first step on the road to independence.''</p>
        <p>Many deputies at the session today said that that road was chosen hastily and without sufficient consideration, prompting dozens of them to refuse to take part in the vote.</p>
        <p>''The fate of a nation shouldn't be decided in three hours,'' said Anatoly Alekseyev, leader of Interfront, an organization composed mainly of non-Latvians opposed to Latvian independence. Mr. Alekseyev was the lone deputy to walk out of the parliamentary chamber in protest during the vote.</p>
        <p>''I sat and ate soup for lunch while I read through ther documents,'' he said. ''This is not right. They should have given the deputies several days to read them, they should have published them in the paper and allowed people to express their opinion.''</p>
        <p>At Rally, Flowers and Tears</p>
        <p>Alfreds Rubiks, head of the Latvian Communist Party faction loyal to Moscow, said the declaration could bring strikes and possibly violence within the republic and possible economic sanctions from Moscow.</p>
        <p>A small group of people opposed to independence stood with Soviet flags outside Parliament today as several dozen held a small demonstration.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of supporters of independence waited anxiously alongside them. After the vote, the deputies left, passing through a crowd in the Old City's cobbled streets. The people embraced the legislators and many wept as they pressed flowers into the deputies' arms as they walked to a rally of several thousand people gathered at sunset of the banks of the Daugava River.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
