<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seidman Vows to Set His Own Exit Date</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="350458"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAVINGS AND LOAN ASSOCIATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">RESOLUTION TRUST CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL DEPOSIT INSURANCE CORP (FDIC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TREASURY DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASH, NATHANIEL C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEIDMAN, L WILLIAM (CHMN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings and Loan Associations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD71F38F936A35756C0A966958260" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seidman Vows to Set His Own Exit Date</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASH, NATHANIEL C</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The unusual public negotiations between L. William Seidman and the White House continued today, with the manager of the savings and loan bailout insisting that he would pick the time of his departure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The unusual public negotiations between L. William Seidman and the White House continued today, with the manager of the savings and loan bailout insisting that he would pick the time of his departure.</p>
        <p>The unusual public negotiations between L. William Seidman and the White House continued today, with the manager of the savings and loan bailout insisting that he would pick the time of his departure.</p>
        <p>In his first extensive public comments on the question, Mr. Seidman said that President Bush ''did not ask me to leave'' and ''did not encourage me to leave'' and that the timing ''is truly my decision.''</p>
        <p>The remarks, seen as an attempt by Mr. Seidman to maintain his dignity while not defying the President, capped a week in which comments by White House officials and President Bush himself made it clear that the Administration would like Mr. Seidman to leave well before his term ends in October 1991.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidman's comments came after his appearance before a House Banking Committee panel on the savings and loan bailout. As chairman of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, he is also chairman of the Resolution Trust Corporation, the agency created by Congress to administer the bailout and spend at least $50 billion over the next two years.</p>
        <p>The F.D.I.C. chief, who is highly regarded in Congress both for his skill as a banking regulator and his candor about the size of the savings crisis, has frequently clashed with top officials at the Treasury and John H. Sununu, the White House chief of staff. Industry experts say Mr. Sununu and Treasury Secretary Nicholas F. Brady are leading the effort to force Mr. Seidman out.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidman has been a thorn in the side of the Administration for some time. During talks over the bailout legislation, Mr. Seidman broke with the Administration by seeking added powers for his agency. In addition, he persuaded Congress to approve a measure that would prevent the President from arbitrarily removing the head of the F.D.I.C. Mr. Seidman has also been outspoken in saying that the Administration's estimates of the bailout's costs are low and that Treasury officials have intervened excessively in the day-to-day running of the bailout.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, President Bush, in an attempt to mute Congressional and industry criticism of the White House's increasing pressure on Mr. Seidman, both praised him and made his departure final by saying that he heartily agreed with Mr. Seidman's recommendation that his successor be the Federal Reserve Board's chief banking regulator, William Taylor. Mr. Taylor is on loan from the Fed to serve as chief executive of the oversight board of the Resolution Trust Corporation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidman said today that he would remain at least until the end of June, a date he has set to complete a plan by the trust corporation to sell or liquidate 141 ailing institutions at a cost to the public of almost $57 billion. But Mr. Seidman left open the possibility that he might stay longer.</p>
        <p>''President Bush did not speed up my decision,'' he said. ''I have been saying for several months that I planned to leave once the R.T.C. is up and running,'' but he added that he would decide when that time is.</p>
        <p>Until the so-called June 30 project is completed, he said, ''I will not think about what I am going to do.''</p>
        <p>Praise From Panel Members</p>
        <p>In Mr. Seidman's appearance before the House panel, which has in the past received him warmly, the tone was somber.</p>
        <p>''One of the bright spots in this whole mess has been Mr. Seidman,'' said Representative Charles E. Schumer, Democrat from Brooklyn. ''The Administration should be on its hand and knees begging you to stay.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidman cautioned the lawmakers against expecting quick results from the savings and loan rescue, saying that even a year from now the end will not be in sight.</p>
        <p>''Don't be impatient,'' he told lawmakers with a hint of nostalgia. ''This is a long, hard job. It isn't going to be accomplished anytime soon.''</p>
        <p>Warning on Interest Rates</p>
        <p>Mr. Seidman pointed to a recent rise in interest rates as a double threat.</p>
        <p>First, the increased borrowings by the Treasury that are needed to finance the rescue push up interest rates, putting pressure on consumers and the economy. Then, higher interest rates generally translate into lower real estate values, which increases the bailout's cost to the taxpayer.</p>
        <p>''The real pain of what is taking place, on everything from increased Government borrowing to the effect on real estate markets, is still being felt,'' Mr. Seidman said. ''I think it is very important that no one expect by this time next year we'll all feel great.''</p>
        <p>As he has in the past, Mr. Seidman stressed that the losses in the savings and loan industry, which are increasing at a rate of $28 million a day, will not be stemmed until all the real estate acquired by Resolution Trust has been sold to the private sector.</p>
        <p>Price Cutting Is Planned</p>
        <p>To speed up asset sales, the agency has significantly liberalized its sales guidelines to allow considerable markdowns on property that is not selling well.</p>
        <p>He reiterated that the bailout was almost certain to cost more than the Bush Administration has predicted. He took exception, however, to the estimates by Comptroller General Charles A. Bowsher, who last month said the cost of the bailout, plus interest expenses on the borrowings, could be as much as $500 billion during a 30-year period.</p>
        <p>''It's like buying a $100,000 house and saying that it really is $300,000 because you are taking out a mortgage on it,'' Mr. Seidman said.</p>
        <p>At the hearing, lawmakers lavished praise on the F.D.I.C. chairman, gave cautious support to Mr. Taylor and asked Mr. Seidman what advice he had for Mr. Taylor.</p>
        <p>''The first thing I'd say is take a hard look before accepting the job,'' he said. ''And don't expect a lot of praise.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
