<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Golf;   Daniel Captures L.P.G.A. Crown</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="372672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DANIEL, BETH</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LADIES PROFESSIONAL GOLF ASSN TOURNAMENT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DC1138F933A05754C0A966958260" item-length="343" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Golf;   Daniel Captures L.P.G.A. Crown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>BETHESDA, Md., July 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Beth Daniel shot a 66 today to overcome a five-shot deficit and win the Ladies Professional Golf Association Championship, her first major title in 12 years on the tour.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Beth Daniel shot a 66 today to overcome a five-shot deficit and win the Ladies Professional Golf Association Championship, her first major title in 12 years on the tour.</p>
        <p>Beth Daniel shot a 66 today to overcome a five-shot deficit and win the Ladies Professional Golf Association Championship, her first major title in 12 years on the tour.</p>
        <p>In beating Rosie Jones by one shot, Daniel collected $150,000, the largest paycheck in L.P.G.A. Tour history. Jones, who entered the final round with a two-shot lead, had a chance to force a playoff. But she lipped a 50-foot birdie attempt on the final hole to finish with a 72 for the day and a total of three-under 281. Daniel ended at four-under 280.</p>
        <p>''It's been 12 long, hard years, and to finally win a major, it feels real good,'' Daniel said. ''This makes my whole career worthwhile.''</p>
        <p>Good Start</p>
        <p>The 33-year-old Daniel started the day five strokes behind Jones but moved into contention by opening the final round with three birdies in a row. ''I just kind of rolled on from there,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Daniel birdied Nos. 12 and 13, then made four consecutive pars before missing a 6-footer for par on No. 18. That gave Jones a chance to pull even, but her crucial putt hit the left side of the cup and spun away.</p>
        <p>''That last putt was in the hole the whole way,'' Jones said. ''I'm shaken, but I feel very pleased with my play today.''</p>
        <p>It was Daniel's second victory in seven days - she won the Phar-Mor near Youngstown, Ohio, in a playoff on Monday - and her fourth victory this year.</p>
        <p>Only Two Break Par</p>
        <p>The third-place finisher, Dawn Coe, shot a 72 for a 284 total, which made Daniel and Jones the only players to break par over 72 holes on the demanding Bethesda Country Club course. Daniel has always fared well on the Bethesda layout. She won the Greater Washington Open on the course last year and finished second in the now-defunct tournament in 1988.</p>
        <p>Jones earned $92,500 with her 12th top-10 finish of the season.</p>
        <p>Sue Ertl was fourth at 285. Betsy King and Patty Sheehan were among four players at 286, and five players, including Pat Bradley and Ayako Okamoto, finished at 287. The defending champion, Nancy Lopez, was in a group of six players at 288.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
