<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLINTON RESPONDS TO HYDE'S QUERIES; YIELDS NO GROUND</title>
    <meta content="28CLIN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1065513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lying</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broder, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hyde, Henry J (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Impeachment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981128T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EEDD1039F93BA15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1649" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLINTON RESPONDS TO HYDE'S QUERIES; YIELDS NO GROUND</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN M. BRODER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broder, John M</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Clinton insists once again that he had not lied under oath about Monica S Lewinsky, in terse, formal responses to 18 questions submitted by House Judiciary Com; but he reiterates that he had misled his family, his aides and nation about the relationship; sheds little new light on issues surrounding the impeachment inquiry; many of his answers are spare and unyielding, simply denying that he had lied in earlier testimony, referring to previous statements or to grand jury testimony of major witnesses; Clinton was asked repeatedly whether he had lied to friends and advisers about Lewinsky; three times he acknowledges that he misled people but says he already apologized for it; in statement accompanying his responses, Clinton says that, for him, Lewinsky affair 'long ago ceased to be primarily a legal or political issue'; says he will continue to fight against impeachment as he continues to seek forgiveness from his family and nation (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Clinton insisted once again today that he had not lied under oath about his affair with Monica S. Lewinsky, in terse, formal responses to 81 questions submitted by the House Judiciary Committee. But he reiterated that he had misled his family, his aides and the nation about the relationship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton shed little new light on issues surrounding the impeachment inquiry, a goal his lawyers set when they received the committee's questionnaire on Nov. 5. Many of his replies are spare and unyielding, simply denying that he lied in earlier testimony, referring to previous statements or to the grand jury testimony of major witnesses. He was asked repeatedly whether he had lied to friends and advisers about Ms. Lewinsky; three times he acknowledges that he misled people but says he already apologized for it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Clinton insisted once again today that he had not lied under oath about his affair with Monica S. Lewinsky, in terse, formal responses to 81 questions submitted by the House Judiciary Committee. But he reiterated that he had misled his family, his aides and the nation about the relationship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton shed little new light on issues surrounding the impeachment inquiry, a goal his lawyers set when they received the committee's questionnaire on Nov. 5. Many of his replies are spare and unyielding, simply denying that he lied in earlier testimony, referring to previous statements or to the grand jury testimony of major witnesses. He was asked repeatedly whether he had lied to friends and advisers about Ms. Lewinsky; three times he acknowledges that he misled people but says he already apologized for it.</p>
        <p>In a statement accompanying his responses, Mr. Clinton said that, for him, the Lewinsky affair ''long ago ceased to be primarily a legal or political issue.'' He said he would continue to fight against impeachment as he continued to seek forgiveness from his family and the nation. [Text, page A13.]</p>
        <p>The Judiciary Committee is drawing up three possible articles of impeachment against the President while the White House and its allies are seeking to negotiate a lesser punishment, like a Congressional resolution of censure. The articles under consideration would allege perjury, obstruction of justice and witness tampering and abuse of power.</p>
        <p>Some of the committee's questions suggested an intent to elicit answers at variance with those in Mr. Clinton's previous sworn testimony to help build a perjury case against him.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Clinton and his lawyers did not offer any new explanations. Mr. Clinton does not acknowledge any inconsistencies or falsehoods in his testimony, and if the committee wants to find perjury, they will have to do it without his help, one of Mr. Clinton's advisers said.</p>
        <p>Representative Henry J. Hyde, chairman of the Judiciary Committee, who had threatened to subpoena Mr. Clinton if his replies were not sent to the panel by Monday, offered no substantive response this evening to Mr. Clinton's submission.</p>
        <p>''The committee will now carefully review those responses,'' he said in a statement.</p>
        <p>For the first time, Mr. Clinton acknowledged today that in the hours after the Lewinsky matter became public on Jan. 21, he discussed how to handle it with Dick Morris, a political adviser who had been embroiled in his own sex scandal, in the 1996 Presidential campaign.</p>
        <p>In response to the committee's questions, the President said he was aware that Mr. Morris had conducted a poll on public attitudes about the Lewinsky revelations to gauge whether the President should publicly admit the affair to defuse the scandal. But Mr. Clinton said he did not recall telling Mr. Morris, ''We just have to win, then,'' when told that the public would not tolerate admissions by the President of obstruction of justice or subornation of perjury.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Clinton also acknowledged for the first time that his lawyers and his re-election campaign had hired two well-known private investigators, Terry F. Lenzner and Jack Palladino. But Mr. Clinton provided only a vague description of their duties, saying they were engaged for ''legal and appropriate tasks'' and ''a variety of matters.''</p>
        <p>The President also said he had consulted with Betsey Wright, his chief of staff and scandal control officer when he was Governor of Arkansas, ''on a wide range of matters.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Morris, in grand jury testimony in August, described Mr. Lenzner, Mr. Palladino and Ms. Wright as part of a ''White House secret police operation'' used to dig up dirt on the President's political opponents. White House officials have denied the existence of such a unit and said that the private detectives and Ms. Wright were used only for legitimate investigative jobs.</p>
        <p>The Judiciary Committee sought answers to numerous questions that arose from the lengthy referral of Kenneth W. Starr, the independent counsel, to help determine whether Mr. Clinton was guilty of impeachable offenses.</p>
        <p>Republican aides said the panel had hoped to secure concise factual responses from the President to questions that gave rise to Mr. Starr's accusations that Mr. Clinton committed perjury, obstruction of justice, witness tampering and abuse of power in his efforts to conceal his relationship with Ms. Lewinsky.</p>
        <p>But the President and his lawyers frustrated the committee's effort with a series of terse answers that for the most part repeated Mr. Clinton's earlier assertions and offered little new insight on a matter that has produced thousands of hours of testimony and tens of thousands of pages of commentary. One White House adviser, speaking on the condition of anonymity, said the answers to most of the questions were already in the public record. ''I don't think the ball has been moved much by this exercise,'' this adviser said.</p>
        <p>David E. Kendall, Mr. Clinton's lead private lawyer, said the President's 24-page response to the committee was made ''in good faith'' and in an effort to provide ''as much information as possible.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kendall, in a letter accompanying the President's replies, states emphatically, ''the President did not commit or suborn perjury, tamper with witnesses, obstruct justice or abuse power.'' He referred to earlier reports to the panel in which the President acknowledged an improper personal relationship with Ms. Lewinsky but asserted that none of his actions warranted impeachment.</p>
        <p>James M. Jordan, a spokesman for the Democrats on the Judiciary Committee, called the panel's questionnaire ''a silly, redundant and wholly partisan political exercise.''</p>
        <p>He added, ''Clearly, the committee majority is interested less in shedding new light on the allegations against the President than in playing frivolous semantical games.''</p>
        <p>In a brief introduction to today's reply to the committee's questionnaire, Mr. Clinton says that he intends to vigorously contest the impeachment inquiry now before the committee. However, the President adds, ''the fact that there is a legal defense to the various allegations cannot obscure the hard truth, as I have said repeatedly, that my conduct was wrong. It was also wrong to mislead people about what happened, and I deeply regret that.''</p>
        <p>The President also told the panel that the impeachment inquiry ''long ago ceased to be primarily a legal or political issue and became instead a painful personal one, demanding atonement and daily work toward reconciliation and restoration of trust with my family, my friends, my Administration and the American people.''</p>
        <p>In today's document, Mr. Clinton repeatedly states that the answers he gave in his deposition in the Paula Corbin Jones sexual misconduct lawsuit and in his grand jury testimony in the Lewinsky investigation were not ''false and misleading.''</p>
        <p>He also claims a faulty memory on many of the central charges in the investigation, including the subject of numerous telephone conversations he had with Ms. Lewinsky and with his close friend Vernon E. Jordan Jr., who helped Ms. Lewinsky find a job. Mr. Clinton says that he does not believe he saw an affidavit Ms. Lewinsky signed for the Jones case denying a sexual relationship, ''although I cannot be absolutely sure.''</p>
        <p>In response to a number of questions -- about the affidavit, about Mr. Jordan's job search on Ms. Lewinsky's part, about gifts they exchanged -- Mr. Clinton repeatedly says, ''I do not recall'' or ''I do not remember.''</p>
        <p>And he resorts again to the verbal gymnastics that Mr. Starr and many in Congress consider to be at best disingenuous and at worst perjurious.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton was asked whether he had affirmed that Ms. Lewinsky's affidavit denying a sexual relationship was true. He referred the committee to his January deposition and his August grand jury testimony. ''I believe at the time that she filled out this affidavit, if she believed that the definition of sexual relationship was two people having intercourse, then this is accurate,'' Mr. Clinton said.</p>
        <p>The Judiciary Committee asked the President a number of questions about one of the central aspects of the Lewinsky investigation, a meeting Mr. Clinton had with his personal secretary, Betty Currie, the day after he was questioned by the Jones lawyers in his January deposition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton acknowledged calling her in to work on a Sunday and asking her questions about what she knew about his relationship with Ms. Lewinsky.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr said in his report that the questions -- like, ''Monica came on to me and I never touched her, right?'' and ''You were always there when she was there, right?'' -- were evidence of an illegal effort to tamper with a potential witness in the Jones lawsuit.</p>
        <p>In today's reply to the committee, Mr. Clinton said, ''I believe that I asked her certain questions, in an effort to get as much information as quickly as I could, and made certain statements, although I do not remember exactly what I said.''</p>
        <p>But he also asserted that he never encouraged Mrs. Currie to lie before the grand jury.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also said that, in the immediate aftermath of the revelation of the relationship with Ms. Lewinsky, he had told many friends and senior advisers that he had not had a sexual affair with her.</p>
        <p>''As I have previously acknowledged, I did not want my family, friends or colleagues to know the full nature of my relationship with Ms. Lewinsky,'' Mr. Clinton said in today's response. ''I misled people about this relationship. I have repeatedly apologized for doing so.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr characterized these misleading comments, which White House aides repeated in public in the President's defense, as an abuse of Presidential power, one of the 11 possible grounds for impeachment cited in his report to Congress.</p>
        <p>TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
