<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Romance Does Not Stop Even After the Race Begins</title>
    <meta content="04MARA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/04/sports/04MARA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1244346"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="MARATHON 2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hollander, Sophia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leiningen, Boris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leiningen, Cheryl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Savitt, Elvia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Savitt, Randy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Fashion, Beauty and Fitness</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New York City Marathon</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marathon Running</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Running</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E3D71739F937A35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1056" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Romance Does Not Stop Even After the Race Begins</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOPHIA HOLLANDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hollander, Sophia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article focuses on two couples--Boris and Cheryl Leiningen and Elvia and Randy Savitt--who met, fell in love, ran together and married against backdrop of New York City Marathon; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cheryl Riegler fidgeted under the steady drizzle drifting onto the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge, fiddling with the layers of gloves, hats, shorts, shirts and plastic, and fretting about everything that could go wrong. It was 1997 and Riegler, then a 36-year-old nurse practitioner, was about to run in her third New York City Marathon, with her boyfriend Boris Leiningen, who had started running six months earlier so he could spend more time with her. She worried that they were going to get wet, contract a rash, feel something pull or burn or break, and that Leiningen, 38, would not be able to finish.</p>
        <p>The cannon went off. Leiningen turned to her.</p>
        <p>''I was wondering if you'd marry me,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cheryl Riegler fidgeted under the steady drizzle drifting onto the Verrazano-Narrows Bridge, fiddling with the layers of gloves, hats, shorts, shirts and plastic, and fretting about everything that could go wrong. It was 1997 and Riegler, then a 36-year-old nurse practitioner, was about to run in her third New York City Marathon, with her boyfriend Boris Leiningen, who had started running six months earlier so he could spend more time with her. She worried that they were going to get wet, contract a rash, feel something pull or burn or break, and that Leiningen, 38, would not be able to finish.</p>
        <p>The cannon went off. Leiningen turned to her.</p>
        <p>''I was wondering if you'd marry me,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Of course I will,'' she said, distractedly. ''I've told you that a hundred times.''</p>
        <p>''No,'' he said. ''I mean it.''</p>
        <p>He took out the ring. She began to shake.</p>
        <p>''It's so funny, because I'm pretty intuitive,'' she said this week as she prepared to watch the marathon from the sideline. The couple are expecting their first child in February, in time for her to start training for next year. ''I was totally surprised.''</p>
        <p>They spent the whole race recounting how Boris had planned his proposal and, when their breath began to lag, inspiring themselves with promises about the future.</p>
        <p>The New York City Marathon, which attracts roughly 30,000 runners from around the world each year, has affected many lives. But for some, it has had an even deeper impact. It has introduced them to the person they would marry.</p>
        <p>Two marriage ceremonies have been performed on race day, according to the New York Road Runners Club, one at the eight-mile mark and one near the start, at Fort Wadsworth on Staten Island.</p>
        <p>Elvia and Randy Savitt met in 1991 at the Road Runners packet-stuffing party eight days before the marathon. Elvia was a first-time volunteer, Savitt was the first person she met, and she dismissed him immediately. He had on black jeans and a T-shirt: ''hard rock,'' as she would describe him later. But, then, ''I took another look,'' Elvia said. ''And I was like, 'Not bad.' ''</p>
        <p>He offered to buy her lunch -- which was free courtesy of the Road Runners club. ''She didn't know that,'' he said, laughing.</p>
        <p>At the pasta party the day before the marathon, they scribbled phone numbers on napkins. But Randy never expected to hear from Elvia again. The next day, he ran the marathon and staggered over to the baggage buses, sweaty and exhausted. Elvia was waiting on the top step of the bus.</p>
        <p>''What took you so long?'' she said.</p>
        <p>She cleared an entire seat for him to lie down on, and gave him a stack of sandwiches she had saved.</p>
        <p>Elvia had begged the organizers to let her work on the bus so that she could see Randy again.</p>
        <p>''I can see how the runners come when they're tired and no one's there,'' Elvia said. ''You don't have a shoulder, somebody to lean on to experience that with you. It's an accomplishment.''</p>
        <p>Two years later, they were married.</p>
        <p>''I figure eight days before the marathon is like our anniversary,'' said Randy, an electrician from Queens. ''It's just a regular day, but deep down it's an anniversary.''</p>
        <p>In their engagement picture, Randy is wearing a medal and decked out in marathon running gear, while Elvia is wearing work clothes.</p>
        <p>Cheryl and Boris Leiningen used a marathon motif in their wedding. Their wedding invitations were superimposed on an 8 x 10 photograph of the couple crossing the finish line together.</p>
        <p>On their honeymoon, they traveled to Hawaii to compete in the Honolulu marathon.</p>
        <p>Cheryl was somewhat astonished when Boris offered to begin running with her on their second date. ''It was a symbol that he really wanted to spend time with me to put up with that gruesome training,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But as they ran early in the morning, or after dinner, and confided bits and pieces of their lives, they fell in love. Boris, who had never run before, slowly caught up until he and Cheryl could glide through 10 miles along the Jersey Shore, chatting easily.</p>
        <p>''It was probably annoying,'' Cheryl said. ''Here I was running for 20 years and here comes this guy and after six months we're running at the same pace.''</p>
        <p>They made a pact never to run alone again.</p>
        <p>''You never know what happens, those moments where you say, 'This is ludicrous, I don't want to run anymore,' '' said Boris, who is a business development manager for an engineering firm in New York. ''But running with someone else, the other person can say, 'Come on, come on, we've got to finish this.' ''</p>
        <p>Cheryl added, ''You have someone to laugh with. You run this marathon and then you see the man holding his one leg, running with a prosthesis, another who's blind, the people along the streets who put together a band, or the little old lady handing out heart candies, or in one part of the race this 70-year-old man passed me. Or the man who ran into the pizza parlor, got a piece of Sicilian and was running with that and a Coke. If you're running alone you appreciate these events, but you wouldn't remember any of them.''</p>
        <p>Randy still runs alone. He said Elvia's enthusiasm for his training has waned, but he still has the old, faded napkin with her phone number from the pasta party nine years ago.</p>
        <p>''Everybody has a good luck charm,'' said Savitt, who will be running in his 15th straight marathon tomorrow. ''It keeps the streak going.''</p>
        <p>The Leiningens' charms are the hats they wore during their first marathon, with their names and the year embroidered on the side. They have worn it every marathon they have run together since, adding inscriptions each time.</p>
        <p>''So maybe when like we're 80 years old, they'll be really torn and smelly,'' Cheryl said. ''But we'll say we have to wear them.''</p>
        <p>MARATHON 2000</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
