<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Conglomerates of Congestion</title>
    <meta content="30AUTO$11" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/30/automobiles/30AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1329582"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westwood One Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Infinity Broadcasting Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metro Networks Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Shadow Broadcast Services</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tele Atlas North America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mobility Technologies Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moran, Tim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Westwood One Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E0DC163DF933A0575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1952" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Conglomerates of Congestion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Conglomerates of Congestion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM MORAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moran, Tim</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on radio traffic-reporting industry focuses on Westwood</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>YOU are stuck in the Bronx on the approach to the Whitestone Bridge, stalled out in the ''mixing bowl'' of the Washington Beltway or rattling behind a glacier of trucks on Detroit's astoundingly potholed I-94 when the friendly voice of a local traffic reporter blurts from the radio.</p>
        <p>Or at least you think the voice is local.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The local traffic reporter on the radio may not be as local as you think.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>YOU are stuck in the Bronx on the approach to the Whitestone Bridge, stalled out in the ''mixing bowl'' of the Washington Beltway or rattling behind a glacier of trucks on Detroit's astoundingly potholed I-94 when the friendly voice of a local traffic reporter blurts from the radio.</p>
        <p>Or at least you think the voice is local.</p>
        <p>''I've stood behind the people who are on the air -- they call them anchors -- and listened to the same person have one name and one voice on one station, then, a minute later, another name and another voice on another station,'' said Larry Sweeney, vice president and general manager of ''dynamic traveler content and new-business development'' for Tele Atlas North America.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney sees more traffic than the average driver. He was recently in Marrakesh, Morocco, for a conference on global traffic management, having hopped there from a Detroit meeting on getting real-time traffic information into individual cars.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sweeney knows that when it comes to traffic, there is just one giant consolidator and provider of information for most of North America, and that is Westwood One of New York. Westwood, which is managed by Infinity Broadcasting -- part of the Viacom media empire -- is best known as a producer of more than 150 programs carried on 7,700 radio and television stations. But with subsidiaries that include Metro Networks and Shadow Broadcast Services, it delivers traffic information to 2,200 radio stations -- almost 90 percent of the national market.</p>
        <p>In an alliance with Westwood One, Tele Atlas provides digital map-based traffic information for in-car navigation and other systems in 68 urban areas. By the end of this year, that number is expected to rise to 70; Tele Atlas's goal is to reach 100 markets.</p>
        <p>When a helicopter hovers over a clogged freeway in most American cities, it is probably a Westwood One flight. When the radio voice gives ''traffic on the eights'' -- or the tens, or some other regular hourly time -- it is likely to be the voice of a Westwood anchor speaking in her (or his) local persona about roads she (or he) knows only from a remote map.</p>
        <p>In New York City, for example, all three all-news AM stations -- WCBS, WINS and WBBR -- plus about 60 other radio and television outlets in the region carry Westwood One traffic data, all of it gathered partly from a fleet of aircraft that Westwood One owns or charters.</p>
        <p>The Sept. 11 terrorist attacks have disrupted flights over urban areas, and traffic reporting is no exception. While flights by airplanes are being allowed in rural areas, traffic helicopters remain grounded and there has been essentially no aerial traffic reports since the attacks.</p>
        <p>''We're in constant communication with the F.A.A., and we hope for a return to normalcy,'' said Shane Coppola, executive vice president of Westwood One. Meanwhile, the pilots have joined more than 3,000 traffic reporters nationally trying to work at street level.</p>
        <p>Traffic information is informally estimated to be a $500 million business in North America. Broadcasters eager to deliver a high-interest service that will stop listeners from channel-surfing give Westwood, without charge, the minute or so of air time needed to broadcast traffic and weather. In most cases, Westwood sells the advertising sponsorship out of that time; the information on the average traffic spot takes less than 20 seconds. The advertising money keeps the helicopters and airplanes aloft; finances the radio and cellular phone communications that keep the information flowing, and operates the data centers and coordinating teams whose work could rival that of the busiest air traffic control center.</p>
        <p>The system is generally effective compared with Europe's, where government ownership of traffic data and broadcast media means delays of up to 25 minutes before road incidents are reported to drivers.</p>
        <p>''I know in Europe I will ignore the various messages that come up for traffic,'' said Steve Millstein, president and chief executive of ATX Technologies of Irving, Tex.  ATX is a player in North America in telematics, including the delivery of traffic information by wireless phone. Mr. Millstein said the European delay makes it pointless to tell drivers to leave a road at a certain exit and return at another point.</p>
        <p>In the U.S., that ''latency'' is just five minutes. That's how long it takes to get a flurry of drivers' cellphone calls, verify the reported delay by flying overhead for a look, tapping a roadside camera for a picture or receiving confirmation from police officers at the scene. The purity of traffic data is increasingly important as service providers try to do more with it. Automakers, in-car communications companies and wireless network businesses would all like to sell traffic information to drivers using telematics systems.</p>
        <p>That means a different kind of traffic data collection from what has existed under various programs run by federal and state agencies for several decades. The government emphasis has been on increasing overall road capacity by managing the total flow of traffic; officials of transportation departments have done a good day's work when the average driver's travel time drops by 5 minutes, because that means thousands of hours of drive time were saved over all.</p>
        <p>Individual drivers, though, have more selfish concerns. ''From a traveler's viewpoint, they want to know if a road is closed and they're going to miss their airplane,'' Mr. Sweeney said.</p>
        <p>Receiving traffic over a wireless phone connection, while expensive, presents the biggest current challenge to broadcast services.</p>
        <p>''It's a matter of how you want to deliver it,'' Ingrid Kjelstrup, ATX senior project manager, said of traffic information. ''Using the data we get has not been the problem. For us, there's been the other issues of: do you want to deliver it by a radius, or ahead of you X-amount of miles, or in an entire area? If you live in a city, five miles ahead of you may be way too much information.''</p>
        <p>It takes a lot of manipulation to pull together some of the new-technology predictions of traffic-watching gurus. Traffic.com, a service of Mobility Technologies of Wayne, Pa., is developing some new forms of traffic information. In a licensing partnership between governments and the private sector, Traffic.com has been installing digital radar sensors on tall poles along main roads in urban areas. A year ago, the company completed its Pittsburgh installation; half of Philadelphia is similarly sensor-equipped.</p>
        <p>The radar-based detectors, run by Java computer language applications, feed data to a complex series of mathematical algorithms. By crunching the numbers, Traffic.com can give the real-time flow rate and speed for traffic in any lane of a monitored roadway. The output can reveal a developing problem, and, when tied in to other systems, can reveal whether a traffic snarl is due to a rollover accident or a stray dog crossing the road.</p>
        <p>''There will be a point in time, as the data is aggregated, when we will be able to say if you are driving the Schuylkill Expressway from downtown Philadelphia to King of Prussia, that trip should take you 47.5 minutes on Monday afternoons with dry weather,'' said Jim Smith, director of marketing for Traffic.com.</p>
        <p>The Pittsburgh effort has been closely watched, because the city has a little bit of everything that snarls traffic: mountains, river valleys, bridges, tunnels and a wide mix of old and new highways. Further complicating the issue are an industrial rush hour, a white-collar rush hour, a mix of urban and suburban driving and a flow of interstate traffic through town, along with seasonal weather conditions. If you can make it there, the Traffic.com engineers say, you can make it anywhere.</p>
        <p>Traffic.com may gather an unprecedented amount of information on heavily traveled urban roads, but still must work within a larger traffic-reporting system. Its service could cooperate with Westwood One's existing structure, or compete with it. Nobody in the industry is quite sure what will happen, because even the main players have been flopping between competition, cooperation and even acquisition in a rapid evolution led by technology and fed by demand for more information.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, some would-be participants say the car itself should collect and report data. Among them is Ken Liu, chief executive of InfoGation of San Diego. Cars connected to the Internet, he said, could report their positions and draw a huge picture of traffic flow -- what he called the ''holy grail'' of traffic data.</p>
        <p>The difficulty is the chance of doing more harm than good. ''You could send everybody to another traffic jam,'' Mr. Liu said. ''The first 20 who got the alternate route get through, but everybody else just gets blocked.''</p>
        <p>Data collection experts differ on what kind of a road sample might be needed for an accurate, predictive system; some hold that good data could be developed even with fewer than 6 percent of cars reporting. Others think that far more cars would be needed for a good sample. One question: How to take junk information -- like that from a parked, but connected, car -- out of the sample?</p>
        <p>Privacy is another concern. If a third party follows your car electronically for traffic data, couldn't it also spy on you to find out where you were going or how long you stayed? It's a touchy ethical dilemma.</p>
        <p>Right now, Big Brother doesn't need to collect much information; drivers are eager to contribute, like the 100 Houston volunteers who call themselves the Citizens Highway Information Patrol. It reports to Traffic.com, which knows of no other such group in its service areas.</p>
        <p>Still more drivers are eager to share their own traffic experiences over the cellphone numbers supplied by Westwood One and subsidiaries.</p>
        <p>It's the new call of the open road.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
