<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Happy Ending, but Rights Issue Casts Shadow on Royal Romance</title>
    <meta content="30DUTC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/30/international/30DUTC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1329643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Netherlands</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Argentina</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simons, Marlise</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zorreguieta, Maxima</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zorreguieta, Jorge</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Willem Alexander (Crown Prince)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Netherlands/Amsterdam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Royal Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Debating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Amsterdam</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kok, Wim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EEDF143DF933A0575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Happy Ending, but Rights Issue Casts Shadow on Royal Romance</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Happy Ending, but Rights Issue Casts Shadow on Royal Romance</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARLISE SIMONS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simons, Marlise</byline>
      <dateline>AMSTERDAM</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jorge Zorreguieta, wealthy Argentine rancher, signs document saying he agrees to stay away from wedding of his daughter, Maxima, to Prince Willem-Alexander of Netherlands, thus averting crisis in royal family; many Dutch politicians and historians say Zorreguieta was moral accomplice to abuses during Argentina's military dictatorship from 1976 to 1983; he has not been linked to atrocities, but Dutch government feared violent protests on wedding day if he attended (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There has been a sigh of relief across the country, above all in Amsterdam, over royal wedding plans, now that a careful diplomatic intervention has paid off.</p>
        <p>When Europe's royalty gather for the wedding of Prince Willem-Alexander, 34, and Maxima Zorreguieta, an Argentine, 30, in Amsterdam next February, the father of the bride will be non grata. In exchange for giving his daughter the chance of becoming queen of the Netherlands, the father, Jorge Zorreguieta, has signed a document saying that he agrees to stay away from the wedding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There has been a sigh of relief across the country, above all in Amsterdam, over royal wedding plans, now that a careful diplomatic intervention has paid off.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There has been a sigh of relief across the country, above all in Amsterdam, over royal wedding plans, now that a careful diplomatic intervention has paid off.</p>
        <p>When Europe's royalty gather for the wedding of Prince Willem-Alexander, 34, and Maxima Zorreguieta, an Argentine, 30, in Amsterdam next February, the father of the bride will be non grata. In exchange for giving his daughter the chance of becoming queen of the Netherlands, the father, Jorge Zorreguieta, has signed a document saying that he agrees to stay away from the wedding.</p>
        <p>The problem is not the prince's vivacious fiancée, a banking executive who used to live in New York. Little has been said about the fact that she is a commoner, or even that she is a Roman Catholic while the  royal family is staunchly Protestant.  At issue is her father's politics.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zorreguieta, a wealthy rancher, was a deputy minister of agriculture during the military dictatorship that ruled from 1976 to 1983 and killed more than 7,000 people. He has not been linked to atrocities. But many Dutch politicians and historians say he showed an enthusiasm for military rule has made him a moral accomplice to the abuses.</p>
        <p>As word leaked out that Queen Beatrix and her husband, Claus von Amsberg, had invited their potential  in-laws to dinner at the palace, the furor grew.</p>
        <p>Royal marriages in Europe have  long been the subject of intrigues and tussles over wealth, power and lineage. But this may be the first time a royal wedding was nearly blocked by a human rights problem. One opponent, Maarten Mourik, a former Dutch ambassador to Unesco, filed suit accusing Mr. Zorreguieta and the former Argentine junta of crimes against humanity.</p>
        <p>The public mood mattered because under the Constitution, Parliament must approve the spouse of an heir to the throne.</p>
        <p>The marriage and succession questions have fanned a long-dormant debate about the purpose of the monarchy.</p>
        <p>The prince let it be known that he would rather abandon the throne and have a wedding in Buenos Aires than lose his bride.</p>
        <p>It took political imagination to find a solution. Even if Parliament approved the wedding, the government feared violent protests on the wedding day.</p>
        <p>Prime Minister Wim Kok secretly dispatched Max van der Stoel, a former foreign minister, to convince Mr. Zorreguieta that for his daughter to be accepted without troubles, he could not attend the wedding. The Argentine politician insisted that he was innocent of any wrongdoing.</p>
        <p>It took three visits by Mr. Van der Stoel, and when Mr. Zorreguieta still appeared vague about his intentions, the envoy got him to commit himself in writing that he would stay away. The public approved. ''Maxima can't be held accountable for what her father did, and she's very likable and down to earth,'' said Michelle de Ree, a law student. ''But in this country we absolutely cannot give her father a place of honor at an official ceremony.''</p>
        <p>When the engagement was announced in the spring, the future  bride enchanted the Dutch by distancing herself -- in newly learned and fluent Dutch -- from the Argentine military government and her father's role. ''What happened in that period was terrible,'' she said, adding that she abhorred the military  regime and ''the disappearances, the tortures, the murders and all the other terrible events of that time.''  As for her father, she said, ''I regret that while doing his best for agriculture, he did so during a bad regime.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
