<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Streetscapes/161 West 93rd Street; A Building That Recalls the Days After Pearl Harbor</title>
    <meta content="30SCAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/30/realestate/30SCAP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1329312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="Streetscapes"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Japanese-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cherry Trees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nippon Club (Former New York Club)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gray, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Takamine, Jokichi (1854-1922)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions/Western States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Streetscapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Great Homes/Destinations/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Japanese-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pearl Harbor (Hawaii)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D9143AF933A0575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="878" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Streetscapes/161 West 93rd Street; A Building That Recalls the Days After Pearl Harbor</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">161 West 93rd Street: A Building That Recalls the Days After Pearl Harbor</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gray, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Streetscape column on former Nippon Club on West 93rd Streeet in Manhatan, which was built in 1912 by Jokichi Takamine, man who brought about gift of cherry trees that blossom in Washington, DC; building, which was closed down, seized and sold off by federal government after attack on Pearl Harbor, is now a church in which virtually no signs of Japanese decor survive; photos (Streetscapes column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER the attack on Pearl Harbor on Dec. 7, 1941, Japanese restaurants were closed down, Japan's embassy was shut and Japanese-Americans who had been in the country for decades were sent to internment camps. A few traces of the aftermath of Pearl Harbor survive in New York, especially in an elegant 1912 building at 161 West 93rd Street that was seized by the federal government during World War II.</p>
        <p>The building, between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenues, is now a Seventh-Day Adventist Church, but few New Yorkers know that it was originally the Nippon Club, built by Jokichi Takamine, who brought about the gift of the cherry trees that blossom in Washington.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Now a church, the 1912 Nippon Club was seized after the attack.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER the attack on Pearl Harbor on Dec. 7, 1941, Japanese restaurants were closed down, Japan's embassy was shut and Japanese-Americans who had been in the country for decades were sent to internment camps. A few traces of the aftermath of Pearl Harbor survive in New York, especially in an elegant 1912 building at 161 West 93rd Street that was seized by the federal government during World War II.</p>
        <p>The building, between Columbus and Amsterdam Avenues, is now a Seventh-Day Adventist Church, but few New Yorkers know that it was originally the Nippon Club, built by Jokichi Takamine, who brought about the gift of the cherry trees that blossom in Washington.</p>
        <p>Takamine, born in 1854 in Takaoka, Japan, learned English in school and studied science. He achieved financial success by forming his own artificial-fertilizer company and moved to New York in the 1890's, where he did research in applied chemistry. In 1901 he isolated the hormone adrenaline in his laboratory.</p>
        <p>In 1905 he organized the Nippon Club, and in 1912 the club put up its own building. Takamine, the president, had a town house at 334 Riverside Drive, between 105th and 106th Streets.</p>
        <p>The Nippon Club's architect, John Vredenburgh Van Pelt, was a careful designer who wrote books on the history of ornament. He annotated the facade drawing for the building, ''brick colors to be selected to give the effect desired by the architect.''</p>
        <p>The building is now painted, but the magazine Edison Monthly wrote in 1915 that ''something in the architecture, alien but not at all bizarre, attracts one to this substantial building in light gold brown brick.''</p>
        <p>It continued that ''the broadly projecting ledge of the cornice is the only discoverable hint of Asia'' on the exterior, and that the interior also was subdued as to Japanese influence, with ''a charm of finish, a certain subtlety of ornament, that transforms the conventional, rendering the place exotic and curious.''</p>
        <p>There was also, in the kitchen, ''a queer-looking fish table, marble topped and knife girdled, a device indispensable to the requirements of the Nippon appetite.''</p>
        <p>Carved sycamore chairs, upholstered in gold leather and laced with delicate flower patterns, were brought from Japan, along with deep gold screens, deeply carved marble-topped tables and lanterns of sycamore slats and rice paper.</p>
        <p>The club frequently entertained Americans. At a 1914 dinner for Baron Chinda, the Japanese ambassador to the United States, the guests included the financier August Belmont and the banker Jacob H. Schiff.</p>
        <p>IT was around that time that Takamine arranged the donation of several thousand cherry trees from Tokyo to Washington. After his death in 1922 his body lay in state at the Nippon Club, covered by Japanese and American flags.</p>
        <p>A dinner in February 1940 was exclusively Japanese, as 250 gathered at the club to celebrate the 2,600th anniversary of the founding of the empire, with folk songs and sake, presided over by the Japanese consul general, Kaname Wakasugi, who led a low bow to the flag of the rising sun. The New York Times quoted him as saying that Japan was going to ''do our best in a humble way to make this world a better place.''</p>
        <p>Tensions increased between Japan and the United States, and on Dec. 6, 1941, The Times reported that the Japan Institute, a Japanese cultural mission at 630 Fifth Avenue, was closing because of an American freeze on Japanese assets. The director was Tamon Mayeda, a Nippon Club member.</p>
        <p>After the attack on Pearl Harbor, about 200 of the 2,500 Japanese nationals in New York and its suburbs were taken into custody. Among them was Yasuo Matsui, an architect living in White Plains who was born in Japan but had come to the United States in the early 1900's. He had designed or co-designed major structures like 40 Wall Street and the Starrett-Lehigh Building. He later resumed his career.</p>
        <p>At the Nippon Club, 12 Japanese members were escorted by police to their homes, and the club was closed. It was confiscated by the Office of the Alien Property Custodian, and in 1943 the office put the building up for sale. In early 1944 it was bought by the Elks for a clubhouse, complete with its furniture; the club said that the interior would be remodeled and that the Japanese artifacts would be sold to art collectors.</p>
        <p>After the war the Nippon Club reestablished itself elsewhere and now has quarters on the first seven floors of a 21-story tower at 145 West 57th Street, built in 1991.</p>
        <p>Its old building on 93rd Street is now the Templo Adventista. The church bought the building in 1968. Its pastor, Gilberto Alvis, said that the congregation numbers about 300.</p>
        <p>The exterior brick is covered with white paint, but the deep cornice is weathered down to the bare metal. The interior is neat and trim, but it appears that none of the Japanese décor has survived -- except for a heavy, timber-style stair baluster topped with large brass finials.</p>
        <p>Streetscapes</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
