<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Late Substitute, Nunes Lifts Syracuse</title>
    <meta content="30EAST$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/09/30/sports/ncaafootball/30EAST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1329747"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Alabama (USA)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlantic Coast Conference</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Green, William</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFD7143DF933A0575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="765" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Late Substitute, Nunes Lifts Syracuse</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Late Substitute, Nunes Lifts Syracuse</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of eastern college football scores; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Syracuse 44 East Carolina 30</p>
        <p>Troy Nunes threw four touchdown passes and James Mungro scored the decisive touchdown on a 6-yard run early in the fourth quarter as Syracuse beat visiting East Carolina, 44-30.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Troy Nunes threw four touchdown passes and James Mungro scored the decisive touchdown on a 6-yard run early in the fourth quarter as Syracuse beat visiting East Carolina.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Syracuse 44 East Carolina 30</p>
        <p>Troy Nunes threw four touchdown passes and James Mungro scored the decisive touchdown on a 6-yard run early in the fourth quarter as Syracuse beat visiting East Carolina, 44-30.</p>
        <p>The victory was the third straight for Syracuse (3-2) and avenged a loss last year to the Pirates (2-2).</p>
        <p>Boos rang down from the sparse Carrier Dome crowd of 36,347 when Nunes was announced as the starter.</p>
        <p>R. J. Anderson, who had won the job, was held out at the start of the game because of the flu and played only two series.</p>
        <p>The boos continued when Nunes had a pass deflected and intercepted after driving the Orangemen to midfield on their third possession of the game. But by game's end, Nunes was a star, completing 17 of 27 passes for 296 yards. He tied a team record for touchdown passes in a game.</p>
        <p>A game official, Gerry Bram, had a major heart attack and collapsed near midfield in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Bram was unconscious and barely breathing on his own when rescue workers raced to his aid, according to the Syracuse team physician, Dr. Irving Raphael. He was in intensive care at University Hospital last night and breathing with the aid of a machine.</p>
        <p>Boston College 31 Army 10</p>
        <p>Brian St. Pierre threw for two touchdowns and linebacker Scott Bradley returned an interception 27 yards for another as Boston College (3-1) beat visiting Army (0-3).</p>
        <p>The Eagles won despite a slow start from running back William Green, who was held to 73 yards on 28 carries until a 42-yard score midway through the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Green, who entered the game as the nation's third-leading rusher, with 485 yards, finished with 115 yards on 29 carries.</p>
        <p>North Carolina 17 North Carolina State 9</p>
        <p>Darian Durant threw two touchdown passes to Kory Bailey as North Carolina followed its upset of Florida State with a victory against visiting North Carolina State.</p>
        <p>The Tar Heels (2-3, 2-1 Atlantic Coast Conference) held the ball for most of the game as the Wolfpack (2-1, 0-1) failed to generate much offense against the nation's 19th-ranked defense until the final five minutes.</p>
        <p>Virginia 31, Duke 10</p>
        <p>Bryson Spinner threw two touchdown passes and Billy McMullen caught two as Virginia beat visiting Duke, the Cavaliers' third straight victory and the Blue Devils' 16th straight loss.</p>
        <p>Virginia (3-1, 2-0 A.C.C.), which won its first two games by a total of 3 points, led by 17-3 at halftime and was never challenged as the Blue Devils (0-4, 0-2) lost their 19th in 21 games since winning, 24-17, at Virginia in 1999.</p>
        <p>Maryland 32 West Virginia 20</p>
        <p>Bruce Perry ran for 153 yards and a touchdown as surprising Maryland stayed unbeaten with a victory over visiting West Virginia (2-2).</p>
        <p>It was the fourth straight 100-yard game for Perry, who carried 31 times and caught 2 passes for 28 yards as the Terrapins improved to 4-0 for only the second time since 1978.</p>
        <p>Villanova 31, Richmond 30</p>
        <p>Brett Gordon threw for 376 yards and 4 touchdowns as visiting Villanova capped a 16-point rally in the fourth quarter to beat Richmond. A 30-yard field goal by Casey Hannon with a second left in the game gave the Wildcats the lead and the victory.</p>
        <p>IN OTHER GAMES</p>
        <p>L. J. McKanas ran for 161 yards and 2 touchdowns to lead NORTHEASTERN over visiting DELAWARE, 20-7. . . . Matt Merklinger scored four touchdowns as MONMOUTH shut out visiting CANISIUS, 42-0. . . . Mike Cerchio threw three touchdown passes -- two to Andrew Turf -- as visiting FAIRFIELD defeated IONA, 26-21. . . . Fullback Jon George ran for two touchdowns to lead ALBANY to a 28-18 victory over visiting STONY BROOK. . . . Mike Carney threw a team-record five touchdown passes as host FORDHAM defeated GEORGETOWN, 48-13. . . . Blake Abbott kicked four field goals, including a Northeast Conference-record 50-yarder, as visiting WAGNER beat ST. JOHN'S, 34-7. . . . Justin Holtfreter threw for 321 yards and 2 touchdowns as visiting SACRED HEART defeated SIENA, 34-0. . . . Derek Clayton's 68-yard touchdown, followed by two field goals from James Galea, gave visiting ST. PETER'S a 13-7 victory over MARIST.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
