<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Big Rivalry Becomes a Big Rout For Undefeated Arizona State</title>
    <meta content="24ARIZ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="COLLEGE FOOTBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="891853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Arizona State University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Arizona</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEFDB123DF937A15752C1A960958260" item-length="809" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Big Rivalry Becomes a Big Rout For Undefeated Arizona State</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>TUCSON, Ariz., Nov. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Arizona State University's football team defeats team from University of Arizona, 56-14 (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Its hope for a matchup of undefeated teams in the Rose Bowl -- with a chance at the national championship on the line -- had vanished hours earlier in Columbus, Ohio.</p>
        <p>Ohio State's loss to Michigan was beyond Arizona State's control. But the Sun Devils still had their own undefeated record to preserve -- and they had to do it in the home of their most hated rival, Arizona, before an Arizona Stadium record crowd of 59,920, and with the knowledge that they had lost 11 of the last 14 meetings between these two teams and that the Wildcats were undefeated at home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Its hope for a matchup of undefeated teams in the Rose Bowl -- with a chance at the national championship on the line -- had vanished hours earlier in Columbus, Ohio.</p>
        <p>Ohio State's loss to Michigan was beyond Arizona State's control. But the Sun Devils still had their own undefeated record to preserve -- and they had to do it in the home of their most hated rival, Arizona, before an Arizona Stadium record crowd of 59,920, and with the knowledge that they had lost 11 of the last 14 meetings between these two teams and that the Wildcats were undefeated at home.</p>
        <p>Big game? No question. Nasty game? Without a doubt. Good game? Hardly. In the 70th meeting between Arizona and Arizona State, the Sun Devils routed the Wildcats, 56-14. Arizona State (11-0) has already defeated Nebraska, the two-time defending champion, but it still needs help to win its first national championship.</p>
        <p>''If we're undefeated and Nebraska beats Florida, Florida State, whoever, in the Sugar Bowl, we're the only undefeated team left,'' said Arizona State Coach Bruce Snyder, mindful that Florida and Florida State play each other next Saturday in Tallahassee. ''There may be somebody else who is voted national champion. But we should be, in my opinion.''</p>
        <p>Arizona State still has to defeat Ohio State in the Rose Bowl, of course, but first things first. Arizona State was still savoring its biggest victory over Arizona since 1951. The Sun Devils outgained the Wildcats by 651 yards to 170, 450 to 44 on the ground.</p>
        <p>Sun Devils quarterback Jake Plummer has built a reputation for last-minute heroism, but for the most part he merely had to watch what unfolded in front of him today.</p>
        <p>And Plummer, who had never beaten the Wildcats, liked what he was watching: an awesome ground game, a sure-handed receiver and an inspiring, hard-hitting, big-play defense that got three sacks on Arizona's mobile quarterback, Keith Smith.</p>
        <p>Arizona didn't find the game nearly as enjoyable, particularly when Snyder left Plummer in the game to give him a chance to break Danny White's school record for touchdown passes. When Plummer tried for the record breaker with the Sun Devils already ahead by 42-7 early in the fourth quarter, it led to a series of melees. At that point, the game had been over for what seemed like hours.</p>
        <p>That was because Terry Battle, the 5-foot-11-inch junior tailback who plays in Plummer's shadow, scored three touchdowns in the first half, the last coming with 1 minute 17 seconds remaining to give the Sun Devils an insurmountable 28-7 lead.</p>
        <p>Battle ran for 143 yards on 23 carries, with many of the yards coming as a result of the blocking of fullback Jeff Paulk. And when the  6-foot-1-inch, 245-pound Paulk was not bulldozing holes for Battle, he was rumbling for 82 yards on 9 carries.</p>
        <p>When he wasn't handing off, all Plummer had to do was loft a pass somewhere near Keith Poole. Poole caught 4 passes for 123 yards and a pair of touchdowns.</p>
        <p>He also had a one-handed catch over the middle in triple coverage on a third-down play early in the third quarter.</p>
        <p>''That slant he caught one-handed is one of the greatest catches I've ever seen,'' Plummer said. ''You might say that everyone catches a one-hander once in a while, but he was getting hit in the ribs, another guy hit him in the back, and he got it one-handed. He never ceases to amaze me.''</p>
        <p>The catch set up his second touchdown, a leaping grab from 40 yards out that enabled Poole to tie the school record for touchdown catches -- and put to rest any hopes Arizona had of a comeback.</p>
        <p>Plummer finished 10 of 19 for 201 yards, with 3 touchdowns and 2 interceptions. The last one came at the Arizona 2 and was returned 98 yards for a touchdown by Wildcats safety Mikal Smith with 12:18 to play.</p>
        <p>The fighting broke out during the return and Snyder removed Plummer at that point, leaving him tied with White with 64 touchdown passes.  It was a mean game. Five players were ejected during the course of the game and eight personal fouls were called. Arizona State, which started the biggest fight, might have been taking out a decade of frustration on its southern rival.</p>
        <p>''This is our house now,'' Paulk said as he walked off the field, waving his index finger high in the crisp desert air.</p>
        <p>Pasadena awaits.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
