<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Maestro of the Magic Arts Returns to His Roots</title>
    <meta content="24WITC$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THEATER" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="891489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Popular Entertainers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Magic and Magicians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">David Copperfield</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Witchel, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Copperfield, David</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Dreams and Nightmares (Show)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magic and Magicians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E1DE113AF937A15752C1A960958260" item-length="2396" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Maestro of the Magic Arts Returns to His Roots</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX WITCHEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Witchel, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses preparations for magician David Copperfield's big magic show Dreams and Nightmares; drawing,</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DAVID SETH KOTKIN WAS BORN IN Metuchen, N.J., 40 years ago; David Copperfield was born when David Kotkin turned 18, at the suggestion of the wife of a New York Post reporter. Which is why his passport reads ''David Kotkin, a k a David Copperfield.''</p>
        <p>''The Pickwick drawings looked kind of like me as a kid,'' the world-famous magician maintains. And while that is not remotely true, judging from the home-movie clip in his show, ''Dreams and Nightmares,'' beginning previews on Tuesday at the Martin Beck Theater and opening on Dec. 5, he has not only kept the name, but, sniping press reports to the contrary, claims to have finished the Dickens novel in its entirety. ''My life is certainly not as taxing or dreary as what he had,'' he concedes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DAVID SETH KOTKIN WAS BORN IN Metuchen, N.J., 40 years ago; David Copperfield was born when David Kotkin turned 18, at the suggestion of the wife of a New York Post reporter. Which is why his passport reads ''David Kotkin, a k a David Copperfield.''</p>
        <p>''The Pickwick drawings looked kind of like me as a kid,'' the world-famous magician maintains. And while that is not remotely true, judging from the home-movie clip in his show, ''Dreams and Nightmares,'' beginning previews on Tuesday at the Martin Beck Theater and opening on Dec. 5, he has not only kept the name, but, sniping press reports to the contrary, claims to have finished the Dickens novel in its entirety. ''My life is certainly not as taxing or dreary as what he had,'' he concedes.</p>
        <p>There's an understatement for the ages. In 1996 alone, Mr. Copperfield's big-spectacle magic shows (he has made the Statue of Liberty disappear on television and walked through the Great Wall of China) earned him $22 million. And his fiancee of three years is the supermodel Claudia Schiffer, most recently featured on the cover of the Victoria's Secret catalogue sporting a diamond-encrusted brassiere worth $1 million. Talk about having it all.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Copperfield works hard for his money; he performs 500 shows a year to predominantly sold-out houses, including many in Europe and Asia where tickets can go for up to $300 each. Indeed, his five-week Broadway run (16 performances a week) boasts nearly $5 million in advance ticket sales. Last month, on a Monday night in San Antonio, 2,400 people turned up for his 9 P.M. show, following the 2,400 who had seen it at 6 P.M. When Mr. Copperfield made his entrance in black jeans, black cowboy boots, black leather jacket, teased mane of black hair and thick black eyebrows, he planted his long, skinny legs in a triumphant V and looked decidedly less like a Pickwick drawing than a cross between Barry Manilow and the Black Stallion.</p>
        <p>The audience was agog as Mr. Copperfield flew through the air, was cut in half by a laser, and along with a female assistant was sucked into a wind machine that seemed to blow him into the auditorium. Music blared, lights flashed and everyone sighed, ''Oooh,'' as if on cue.</p>
        <p>Once the house was emptied he came out front to talk. No one is allowed backstage because of the classified top-secret magic tricks that lurk there.</p>
        <p>Well, that snow in his finale was great. What was it made of?</p>
        <p>Mr. Copperfield sat in an orchestra seat. ''If I didn't tell Michael Eisner, I'm not going to tell you,'' he said. Ah.</p>
        <p>We made plans to meet the following weekend for a drive from Manhattan to Metuchen to tour his hometown and visit his high school. Would it be open on a Sunday? ''For me it will be,'' he declared.</p>
        <p>A cleaning woman approached, holding out a crumpled napkin for his autograph. ''Oh, that's nice,'' he cracked, signing it. The woman bowed her thanks and backed away. It seemed the perfect time for everyone to disappear.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, as Mr. Copperfield directed his driver to Metuchen, he was all chat and charm. There in the back seat was David Kotkin, star-struck Jersey boy, primed for a resplendent homecoming of sorts on the eve of his Broadway debut. ''The last time I was in Metuchen was a year ago with Claudia,'' he said. ''She said it was just like where she grew up.'' And where was that? ''A suburb of Dusseldorf.''</p>
        <p>The two certainly have a lot in common. They met in Germany, actually, in 1993 during a show of Mr. Copperfield's when he picked her out of the audience to help him. She mentioned something about french fries and later that night at a party, he made some appear especially for her. ''It was no big deal,'' he said. ''I had one of my people get them. It made her smile.'' He blushed. ''When you're a guy and meet a girl the first time, you do whatever it takes.''</p>
        <p>Sometimes when Mr. Copperfield speaks, it's hard to remember that he's 40. He seems poised to beseech anyone he can find to clap if they believe in Tinkerbell, but there's an underlying vibe of his own that seems to say: Of course, I don't believe. But I know how to make you believe.</p>
        <p>''There are two very distinct groups of people in the audience,'' he said. ''One group tries to figure it out and one group cries at 'E.T'. I'm right in the middle. Before you create wonders there must be wonder. Though I rarely get to feel that anymore.''</p>
        <p>He draws much of his inspiration, he says, from the movies. ''Don't ask me what ones,'' he said, ''but if I really get affected by it, I go back and see the camera angles, where the cuts are, where the music starts. I allow myself to be the audience fully and then I go back and say I want to affect them that way using magic. Magic is my paint.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, magic has been very, very good to Mr. Copperfield. Since his school days as The Great Davino, he has been honing his act. ''Dreams and Nightmares,'' was developed with Francis Ford Coppola, who also supervised the look of the show, which was written by the playwright David Ives to give it a story line for Broadway, in place of a variety show format.</p>
        <p>Curiously, Mr. Copperfield keeps himself apart from other magic headliners, claiming never to have seen a performance of Siegfried and Roy's or Ricky Jay's, though he has seen Penn and Teller. The duo's Penn Jillette once said of Mr. Copperfield: ''His straitjackets have shoulder pads.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Hochwald, vice president of business development at Pace Theatrical Group, has been booking Mr. Copperfield's shows for 12 years and attributes his popularity in part to the 17 television specials he has done since 1977. ''David's audience has expanded every year,'' he said in a telephone interview. ''In general, magic is still perceived as a tux, top hat and cane, an ancient art stuck in a rut. David is a master showman who has created almost a rock-and-roll persona.''</p>
        <p>BUT IT WAS BROADWAY, Mr. Copperfield says, that has always inspired him. ''I really did sneak into Broadway shows, starting when I was 12,'' he said. ''At 'Pippin,' the ushers let me sit on the floor.'' He also coached Ben Vereen on sleight-of-hand for the number 'Magic to Do.' Why did the veteran actor trust a 16-year-old kid hanging around the stage door?</p>
        <p>''He is an innovator,'' Mr. Vereen said recently. ''You immediately saw his potential, the talent, the sincerity. I even went out to his high school to talk. When someone is so young and inventive and brings that determination to the table, you can't ignore it. I am so proud of him.''</p>
        <p>The car arrived in Metuchen. ''Where the hell are we?'' mused its native son, while the driver peered at him in the rear-view mirror. We passed a funeral parlor. ''Oh!'' gasped the magician excitedly, ''The son of that guy was the bully. When I was a little kid, he threw me on the floor and stepped on my face.'' His eyes shone with animation. ''This is great!''</p>
        <p>We pulled into a driveway, before a collection of red-brick garden apartments, where the sign said ''Redfield Village.'' Mr. Copperfield walked to the front, pointing to number 1A-3. ''This is where I was born,'' he announced. ''I was an only child. We were so poor, my parents and I had the same room.''</p>
        <p>He walked toward the rear, past other buildings in the complex. ''God, look at this. It's so small, man. Even the bricks are small.''</p>
        <p>Back in the car, he couldn't find the high school. While the driver searched, Mr. Copperfield spoke of his father, Hy Kotkin, who owned a men's clothing store, and Rebecca, his mother, who was an insurance adjuster. The couple have retired to San Diego and until recently, ran their son's fan club. (Really.)</p>
        <p>''I am in awe of this kid,'' Mr. Kotkin said in a telephone interview. ''What he wanted always with magic was to make an art form out of it and he accomplished just that. He's a perfectionist. He always has been. As a kid he could be a loner and be perfectly happy. He never had to come to his mother and say 'What should I do now, Mommy?' He always had an inventive mind.''</p>
        <p>The car drove up to the high school and surprise, surprise, it was locked. Mr. Copperfield jiggled the front latch. Nothing. He walked around the back, past a soccer game, keeping his face turned away from the crowd. But the sight of a tall guy in black jeans and a black leather jacket raised a few eyebrows anyway.</p>
        <p>One woman called, ''David, what are you doing out of class?'' It was his drama teacher, who in a dramatic twist of her own turned out to be Judy Muller, the ABC reporter based in Los Angeles, back for a weekend of fall colors. ''He was a typical 15-year-old kid, awkward, like they all were,'' she said. When she discovered that he was locked out of the school, she laughed heartily: ''You made the Statue of Liberty disappear and you can't get into the high school?'' He practically hung his head.</p>
        <p>Settling down on some bleachers in an adjacent field, Mr. Copperfield looked at the school building. ''In high school we all want to fit in and be right,'' he said. ''Magic was my way of being O.K.''</p>
        <p>He still works harder than he has to, constantly developing new material. ''That's very rare in my business,'' he said. ''Being cut in half with a laser as I am doesn't exist in magic books. My death saw is also new technology. I take big risks and I fail. Every day is a battle for me.''</p>
        <p>He's certainly winning it financially. He squirmed at the mention of money, but aware of the crowd that had gathered to watch him, stopped and held still. ''I'm very unmotivated by the money aspect,'' he said. ''I put my money into three things: my show, my museum and my personal life.''</p>
        <p>The International Museum and Library of the Conjuring Arts represents an investment, he said, of more than $10 million, and consists of the world's foremost collection of books (80,000) on magic and memorabilia. It used to be the Mulholland Library of Conjuring and the Allied Arts located in Los Angeles, where it was curated by Ricky Jay. But its former owner's financial difficulties forced its sale.</p>
        <p>''I'm not that interested in the history of magic,'' Mr. Copperfield said, ''but I bought it because it's the shoulders of the giants I stand upon.''</p>
        <p>The museum is somewhere in Nevada (he won't say where) and is not open to the public. There's that secrecy thing again. ''It doesn't need to be secret, it needs to be respected,'' he said. ''If a scholar or journalist needs a piece of magic history, it's there.''</p>
        <p>As to his personal life, Mr. Copperfield says he is ''trying to normalize it, get private time with my fiancee. We take great vacations, to Bali, Phuket, private islands. We're alone on those islands with a video machine and we watch 'The Producers,' which is my favorite movie, and eat popcorn. That's getting back to normal for me. Creating the environment to do that sometimes is expensive. And you have to be flexible enough to move that environment. It's like in 'The Wizard of Oz,' when she wakes up and says, 'This is my bed and my room and you're all here.' That's what I have and that's home to me.''</p>
        <p>Yes, but the fact remains that Mr. Copperfield has no residence of his own. ''I'm a traveling salesman,'' he said. ''I'm obliged to take my wares to new audiences all the time. I do 500 shows a year because I like it. I'm just passionate.''</p>
        <p>The sun was hitting the bleachers then, and it became clear that the crowd gathered in the parking lot was not going to leave until their star got up to sign autographs.</p>
        <p>A boy asked for four and Mr. Copperfield complied cheerfully. More followed and he said to a man standing nearby, ''I remember you, you were the history teacher.'' The man smiled. ''I remember you too, when you were The Great Davino.'' Mr. Copperfield finished the autographs and held up the pen. ''Whose fake Montblanc?'' he asked. Silence. No one claimed it.</p>
        <p>IN THE CAR AGAIN, Mr. Copperfield recalled his three-week enrollment at Fordham University which ended when he was cast in a show called ''The Magic Man.'' He studied acting at HB Studios while he took demo tapes of his magic act around town. ''The television producer Joe Cates sold me to ABC as host of a TV special,'' he recalled. ''Then CBS saw me and took me on.''</p>
        <p>What made him salable? ''I'm using magic as an art form, as theater,'' he said. ''I try to make the audience feel emotional things. I'm a movie but at the end of the movie I'm also a human being. That makes it honest.''</p>
        <p>It would seem he has everything he could hope for and more, though as the day darkened, so it seemed, did his mood.</p>
        <p>''I wish I had more peace in my life,'' he said, looking out his window. ''There's always going to be that lady in the front row not smiling. That's the one you care about.'' You do? Even if the other 3,000 people like you?</p>
        <p>He nodded. ''That's probably what keeps me going, what makes Sammy run here.''</p>
        <p>Then talk turned toward television. ''Do you ever see those 'Whatever Happened To' shows?'' he asked. ''That makes you work really hard.'' He knocked his knees together anxiously. ''I don't want to be on that show.''</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
