<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="24RESU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="891847"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E2DB123DF937A15752C1A960958260" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RACING</p>
        <p>Mr. Bluebird Wins</p>
        <p>Mr. Bluebird won his third straight race yesterday, and for the eighth straight time ran first or second, when he took the Red Smith Handicap at Aqueduct by two lengths.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RACING</p>
        <p>Mr. Bluebird Wins</p>
        <p>Mr. Bluebird won his third straight race yesterday, and for the eighth straight time ran first or second, when he took the Red Smith Handicap at Aqueduct by two lengths.</p>
        <p>The 5-year-old son of Crafty Prospector bided his time while Rice set the pace for Allen Paulson and Bill Mott, then rallied in the homestretch to score over Ops Smile, with Raintrap third and the favored Diplomatic Jet fifth. The winner, owned by Thomas Warfield and trained by John Kimmel, ran the mile and three-eighths on the turf course in 2:161/5  under Mike Smith, paid $11.60 for $2 and earned $90,000.</p>
        <p>Aqueduct tried a racing gimmick for its third race, an amateur riders' event with regular betting. But after the race was won by Cop a Kiss, things came unraveled. The stewards declared an inquiry and later  ruled the race no contest because the winning rider, listed as Carlos Castro, was discovered to be someone named Angel Monserrate. All bets were declared off and the money, which totaled $181,799, was refunded. Monserrate, who had been ejected from New York tracks last year, was arrested.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
        <p>Norman in Command</p>
        <p>Greg Norman, seeking his fifth Australian Open title and second in a row, will take a four-shot lead into today's final round in Sydney. Norman shot a one-under-par 71 yesterday in the third round, coping well with windy conditions. In second is Sweden's Klas Eriksson, who fired a four-over 76. Tiger Woods shot his best round of the tournament, a one-under 71. (AP)</p>
        <p>SOUTH AFRICA ROLLING: In Cape Town, Ernie Els and Wayne Westner combined for a 14-under-par performance yesterday, giving South Africa a whopping 13-stroke lead after three rounds of the World Cup of Golf. Scotland was in second place, with the United States third. (AP)</p>
        <p>N.B.A.</p>
        <p>Hornets Beat Pistons</p>
        <p>Anthony Mason scored 8 of his 18 points in the final 4 minutes 44 seconds and Charlotte capitalized on the absence of Grant Hill, who re-injured his wrist, for a 93-85 victory over the Detroit Pistons.</p>
        <p>The loss was the first in six road games this year for the Pistons, who came in with a record of 10-1. (AP)</p>
        <p>MAGIC 76, PACERS 73: Orlando held Indiana without a field goal over the final nine minutes and used a late 13-0 run to gain the victory in Market Square Arena. The Magic outscored the Pacers by 21-10 in the fourth period as Indiana shot 2 for 16. Orlando finished with six players in double figures, led by Horace Grant, Darrell Armstrong and Derek Strong with 12 apiece. Reggie Miller led Indiana with 24 points. (AP)</p>
        <p>SKIING</p>
        <p>Inexperience Prevails</p>
        <p>A relative upstart in World Cup Alpine skiing, 20-year-old Claudia Riegler of New Zealand, won the Cafe de Colombia slalom race in Park City, Utah. Finishing with an overall time of 1:36.50, Riegler was a mere .07 seconds faster than the veteran racer from Sweden, Pernilla Wiberg, 26.</p>
        <p>CROSS-COUNTRY</p>
        <p>Junior Wins State Title</p>
        <p>Steve Slattery of Mount Olive High won the New Jersey State High School Cross-Country Championship yesterday in Holmdel with the meet's fastest time in five years. Slattery, a 16-year-old junior, clocked 15 minutes 48.7 seconds on the hilly Holmdel Park 5,000-meter course.Adam Daniels of Seton Hall Prep placed second in 15:52.2. In the team standing, Christian Brothers Academy of Lincroft collected its ninth state title.</p>
        <p>The undefeated Ramsey High senior Dana Satir won the girls' title in 18:52.3, catching Abbey Hartman of Ocean City who was second in 18:58.6. Red Bank Catholic captured the girls' team title.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
