<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Are Stymied By Florida's Luongo</title>
    <meta content="27RANG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/11/27/sports/hockey/27RANG.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1538706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Florida Panthers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Diamos, Jason</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Florida Panthers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Florida Panthers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Luongo, Roberto</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDD143AF934A15752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Are Stymied By Florida's Luongo</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers Are Stymied by Floridas Luongo</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Diamos, Jason</byline>
      <dateline>SUNRISE, Fla., Nov. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers tie Florida Panthers, 3-3; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roberto Luongo snatched what would have been the Rangers' first three-game winning streak this season out of thin air Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Luongo, the Florida Panthers' goalie, made a sensational glove save on a wicked Petr Nedved wrist shot from the right point with 10.3 seconds remaining in regulation, and the Rangers settled for a 3-3 tie.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roberto Luongo snatched what would have been the Rangers first three-game winning streak this season out of thin air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roberto Luongo snatched what would have been the Rangers' first three-game winning streak this season out of thin air Wednesday night.</p>
        <p>Luongo, the Florida Panthers' goalie, made a sensational glove save on a wicked Petr Nedved wrist shot from the right point with 10.3 seconds remaining in regulation, and the Rangers settled for a 3-3 tie.</p>
        <p>Considering the Rangers trailed by 3-1 early in the second period, they figured to be satisfied with the point on the road. The Rangers, who are 0-2-5 this season in overtime, have now recorded at least a point in their last five games, with four of those games on the road.</p>
        <p>In two outstanding efforts, they defeated Ottawa on Sunday and shut out Tampa Bay on Tuesday, both behind their backup goalie, Jussi Markkanen.</p>
        <p>Mike Dunham, the Rangers' No. 1 goaltender, was back in action after missing the previous four games with a hip flexor injury. But Dunham looked shaky early, even though the Rangers grabbed a 1-0 lead 4 minutes 44 seconds into the game on Mark Messier's team-leading 10th goal of the season.</p>
        <p>Messier took a pretty diagonal pass from Matthew Barnaby and chipped an even prettier backhander past Luongo on the fly from off the right post for his second goal in two games on this trip.</p>
        <p>The Rangers could have easily made it 3-0 before eight minutes elapsed. But Aleksei Kovalev missed the net from the slot and Luongo stopped Brian Leetch from off the left post.</p>
        <p>The Panthers came back with three consecutive goals, two by the former Islander forward Olli Jokinen, to take a 3-1 lead.</p>
        <p>Valery Bure tied the score at 1-1 on the power play at 10:14 of the first period.</p>
        <p>Jokinen gave the Panthers a 2-1 lead at 13:58, when he swept in a loose puck from off the left post. Jokinen then got an unassisted goal only 48 seconds into the second period when he swooped around Rangers defenseman Boris Mironov, who made an ill-advised attempt to pokecheck the puck away from Jokinen at the blue line.</p>
        <p>Jokinen blew past Mironov and in on Dunham on a two-on-one break, with defenseman Vladimir Malakhov back. As Malakhov fell, Jokinen picked the top right corner of the net for his 10th goal of the season.</p>
        <p>Dunham grew sharper as the game progressed. ''I felt a little rusty, but I had enough work in the first period where I got through it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At 4:24 of the second period, Eric Lindros scored his third goal of the season with a power-play deflection of a shot by Leetch to make it 3-2.</p>
        <p>Then it was time for the defensive pairing of Mironov and Malakhov to redeem itself with a little help from Kovalev late in the second period. At the Rangers' blue line, Kovalev skated circles around Florida's Juraj Kolnik, first passing the puck to himself around Kolnik, then making a backhand pass between Kolnik's legs to Malakhov at the left point Kovalev had vacated.</p>
        <p>As Malakhov skated down the left wing, he threaded a pass to Mironov, who was rushing down right wing, through Florida defenseman Mike Van Ryn's legs in the slot. Mironov redirected the puck home at 18:24. The Rangers had rallied to tie the score at 3-3.</p>
        <p>''I knew this was a risky play, but that's the kind of risk we had to take,'' Kovalev said.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to even think what would have happened if he would have gotten the puck from me,'' he said of Kolnik.</p>
        <p>Malakhov, recounting his pass between Van Ryn's legs and his rush with his fellow defenseman Mironov, said: ''I was thinking, if I get caught I'd be in deep trouble. With me and Bobo up front and nobody in the back, they'd get a breakaway for sure.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>ANSON CARTER left the game after being slashed on the right wrist in the third period. The wrist was badly swollen but X-rays were negative. . . . JAMIE LUNDMARK was a healthy scratch for the third consecutive game.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
