<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bomb Kills 5 in Baghdad; Iraqi Official Was Target</title>
    <meta content="23BAGH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/23/international/middleeast/23BAGH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1583982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: ATTACK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fisher, Ian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sheikhli, Abdul-Jabbar Youssef Al- (Deputy Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3DC163EF930A15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1030" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bomb Kills 5 in Baghdad; Iraqi Official Was Target</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bomb Kills 5 in Baghdad; Iraqi Official Was Target</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fisher, Ian</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, May 22</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Car bomb explodes in Baghdad outside home of Abdul-Jabbar Youssef al-Sheikhli, deputy minister in charge of security; four guards and one female bystander are killed, and minister is among those wounded; neighbors had been uneasy, fearing al-Sheikhli would be target; photos; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another senior Iraqi official was the target on Saturday of a suicide car bomb, which killed at least five people and wounded the official at his home on a quiet residential street in eastern Baghdad. The powerful blast rattled houses and threw two cars through a concrete wall onto the official's front lawn.</p>
        <p>The attack came five days after Ezzedine Salim, the president of the Iraqi Governing Council, was killed by a suicide bomber as he waited at a checkpoint outside the main American headquarters downtown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Another senior Iraqi official was the target today of a suicide car bomb, which killed at least five people and wounded the official at his home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Another senior Iraqi official was the target on Saturday of a suicide car bomb, which killed at least five people and wounded the official at his home on a quiet residential street in eastern Baghdad. The powerful blast rattled houses and threw two cars through a concrete wall onto the official's front lawn.</p>
        <p>The attack came five days after Ezzedine Salim, the president of the Iraqi Governing Council, was killed by a suicide bomber as he waited at a checkpoint outside the main American headquarters downtown.</p>
        <p>Neighbors in the Baladiyat neighborhood of Baghdad said they had feared that any Iraqi official was now a likely target -- and that they had repeatedly asked the police guarding the official, Abdul-Jabbar Youssef al-Sheikhli, the deputy minister in charge of security, to close off the street.</p>
        <p>''Every day I have dreamt that a bomb would explode because we live next to him,'' said Ali Zaidan, 45, Mr. Sheikhli's next-door neighbor. He sat on the sidewalk with a bandaged wound on his left leg. ''Living next to him has been a bad omen for me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Sheikhli, like Mr. Salim a member of the Shiite Muslim Dawa Party, was reported in stable condition. The nature of his wounds was not immediately reported. Several witnesses said that four security guards, possibly Iraqi police officers, were killed along with one passer-by, possibly a woman.</p>
        <p>Military officials have said they expect an increase in violence here as the June 30 deadline approaches for the transfer of some sovereignty to Iraqis -- and in Baghdad in recent days explosions, often unexplained, have rung out several times a day. Early Saturday afternoon, at least three loud blasts were heard near the main United States headquarters here. The headquarters is a frequent target of mortar and rocket attacks, usually harmless. Military officials could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>The deaths of two American soldiers were also reported Saturday. One soldier was killed and three were wounded when their vehicle was attacked by a car bomber near Mahmudiya, south of Baghdad. A military statement did not say when the attack occurred. The area is a frequent site of attacks against the military and civilian foreigners; earlier this month, eight soldiers were killed there by a car bomb.</p>
        <p>The second death occurred Friday, the military said, when a marine was killed near Camp Falluja in what was described as an accident while ''conducting security and stability operations.''</p>
        <p>The car bomb on Saturday exploded about 8 a.m. on a street that witnesses said was largely empty except for a few commuters and parents taking their children to school.</p>
        <p>Amir Ali, 38, said he was driving to his job at the Ministry of Trade when he saw a white Chevrolet Caprice zigzagging toward Mr. Sheikhli's home. It exploded in the middle of the street, he said, blowing at least three cars off the pavement, two of which landed in the front yard of Mr. Sheikhli's home.</p>
        <p>''The security guards tried to stop him but because of the explosion they just flew in the air,'' Mr. Ali said. His uncle was caught in the explosion, he said, as he drove his three children to school. The uncle's black Nissan sat perhaps 20 yards from the blast site, the roof dented and the rear window blasted out. The children were unhurt, Mr. Ali said, but the uncle was sent to the hospital.</p>
        <p>Dr. Dahar Faris al-Jabouri, 45, a neurosurgeon, said he was eating breakfast with his wife, a gynecologist, when a ''very large'' explosion went off. ''I never heard such a thing like that.''</p>
        <p>Doors blew off their hinges, he said, windows shattered and something hit his wife so hard that it fractured her left arm.</p>
        <p>Like several other people in the neighborhood, Dr. Jabouri laid responsibility for the attack on the bomber, Iraqi politicians and the American military alike. If the American military cannot keep Iraq safe, he said, they should let Iraqis do so.</p>
        <p>''Let the Iraqi people govern themselves, with security and authority, as with other nations in the world,'' he said angrily.</p>
        <p>On the street, littered with shattered glass, twisted metal and bloody pieces of wood, one woman collapsed in grief when she heard that her husband was among the dead. ''Where is he?'' she shrieked over and over.</p>
        <p>Samir Shaker Mahmoud al-Sumeidi, who was recently appointed interior minister, visited the site and was surrounded by neighbors upset about the blast. ''It would seem that the criminals do not want the law to prevail or the security men to implement it,'' he told reporters. ''I want every honorable man in this country to condemn this crime.''</p>
        <p>THE STRUGGLE FOR IRAQ: ATTACK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
