<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yachting; San Diego Seeking Little Cup</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="407309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOATS AND BOATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CATAMARANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL CATAMARAN CHALLENGE TROPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SAILBOATS AND SAILING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO (CALIF)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LLOYD, BARBARA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Diego</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ferries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sailboats and Sailing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6DD143EF93AA35751C1A966958260" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yachting; San Diego Seeking Little Cup</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA LLOYD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LLOYD, BARBARA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As if having the America's Cup isn't enough, government officials in the San Diego area are going after the Little America's Cup. The trophy has some of the same history as its illustrious namesake. In 1985, the Little America's Cup was lost by United States yachtsmen to Australia and the Australians have successfully defended it twice. This month, San Diego sailors will try to win it back.</p>
        <p>The Little America's Cup was established in 1961 by the Sea Cliff Yacht Club of Long Island. Known as the International Catamaran Challenge Trophy, the award of small silver sails isn't as prestigious as the gilded urn of the America's Cup. But the multihull racing it fosters attracts yachting's most advanced designers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As if having the America's Cup isn't enough, government officials in the San Diego area are going after the Little America's Cup. The trophy has some of the same history as its illustrious namesake. In 1985, the Little America's Cup was lost by United States yachtsmen to Australia and the Australians have successfully defended it twice. This month, San Diego sailors will try to win it back.</p>
        <p>The Little America's Cup was established in 1961 by the Sea Cliff Yacht Club of Long Island. Known as the International Catamaran Challenge Trophy, the award of small silver sails isn't as prestigious as the gilded urn of the America's Cup. But the multihull racing it fosters attracts yachting's most advanced designers.</p>
        <p>Gino Morelli, the multihull designer who was instrumental in creating Dennis Conner's Stars &amp; Stripes catamaran in 1988, has designed a twin-hulled sailboat for the Little America's Cup. The 25-foot catamaran has been sent from San Diego to Melbourne, Australia, where it is expected to begin racing next Sunday.</p>
        <p>The effort is the brainchild of Brian Bilbray, the San Diego County Supervisor. Bilbray, a multihull sailor, has been closely involved as a county official with plans for the 1992 America's Cup series in San Diego. With the international event stalled in the New York courts for two years, Bilbray embraced the idea of the Little America's Cup as an interim challenge. Playing Waiting Game</p>
        <p>"It was a waiting game," Jeff Stafford, Bilbray's administrative assistant, said of the court impasse. At stake was whether Michael Fay of New Zealand would be awarded the America's Cup for New Zealand, or whether it would go to San Diego. San Diego officials at the time estimated that the event could bring the area as much as $1 billion in revenue. Bilbray argued that the Little America's Cup also had economic potential.</p>
        <p>Bilbray persuaded local governments to support a Little America's Cup campaign. If San Diego sailors won the catamaran trophy, it would bring another sailing event to the area, he said. "It is a perfect way to highlight the South Bay as a sailing center and tourist spot," Stafford said.</p>
        <p>As the syndicate chairman, Bilbray enlisted the Chula Vista Yacht Club, a club south of San Diego, as a sponsor. He raised $85,000 in support from local municipalities along the South Bay waterfront: Chula Vista, National City, Coronado and Imperial Beach. Another $100,000 came from the Port of San Diego, a state government agency that has committed $8.3 million for the 1992 America's Cup match series.</p>
        <p>The local communities raised the money from hotel taxes, a levy designed to further enhance tourism, said Stafford. For the area to reap the cup's benefits, the San Diego team needed to bring the Little America's Cup trophy back from Australia.</p>
        <p>An overall budget of $750,000, which also includes corporate and private donations, includes about $160,000 for building Freedom's Wing, the San Diego syndicate's new high-tech boat. Two-Man Crew</p>
        <p>The catamaran, capable of speeds up to 30 knots, has a crew of two Californians: Pete Melvin of Westminster, and Steve Rosenberg of Long Beach, who were former teammates on the ProSail professional multihull circuit. They will begin racing next week against another challenger, a catamaran from La Rochelle, France. The winner of a four-of-seven race series is slated to compete against the Australian defender beginning Jan. 12.</p>
        <p>"I think if we get through the French with our noses clean, that will give us the experience we need to race the Australians," Morelli said last week. "We'll have three weeks in Melbourne to get ready for them."</p>
        <p>The boats they are racing are C Class catamarans. The multihulls have few design limits: a length of 25 feet; a width of 14 feet, 300 square feet of sail area; and a two-man crew. Yacht designers strive to build the lightest boats to gain a speed advantage. Morelli said his team's design weighs about 400 pounds.</p>
        <p>Experience has shown in the Little America's Cup that getting to the starting line is as important as winning the race. In the last event, staged in Melbourne in the winter of 1989, a challenger from the Cabrillo Yacht Club of San Pedro, Calif., was on site but unable to race. The lightweight but fragile catamaran capsized and its rig fell apart during the starting sequence of the match-racing series.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
