<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Travel Advisory</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="407336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D91E3EF93AA35751C1A966958260" item-length="1365" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Travel Advisory</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mideast Crisis Makes Cruises Alter Course</p>
        <p>Enthusiasm for taking cruises to the eastern Mediterranean has all but disappeared because of tensions in the Middle East. Two deluxe cruise lines, Crystal Cruises and the Seabourn Cruise Line, have responded by canceling their plans to operate ships in the region next year.</p>
        <p>Duncan Beardsley, president of Seabourn, said, "People are still interested in the Mediterranean, but not the eastern part."</p>
        <p>Seabourn, based in San Francisco, said it had rerouted six cruises of the Seabourn Pride, a 204-passenger ship, which had been scheduled to embark from Venice and make stopovers in Istanbul between May and August. Instead of Istanbul, Seabourn said the ship will make stopovers in Lisbon, Nice and other western Mediterranean ports.</p>
        <p>Crystal, based in Los Angeles, said its 960-passenger Crystal Harmony, which was to make seven cruises in the eastern Mediterranean between August and November, would be recalled to the United States. Crystal said the ship would likely operate between New York and Montreal, with stopovers in New England. Before the tensions arising from Iraq's seizure of Kuwait, the ship's destinations were to have included Istanbul, Odessa and Alexandria.</p>
        <p>"We are responding to our guests' requests," said Darlene Papalini, a Crystal spokeswoman. "There is just a reluctance to travel to the eastern Mediterranean." Both companies said passengers who had booked passage on the canceled cruises were being offered alternative routes or their money back. Polar Voyage On Soviet Ship</p>
        <p>Western passengers can travel aboard a nuclear-powered Soviet icebreaker when she sets off July 26, 1991, from Murmansk to Nome, Alaska, via the North Pole. After the voyage -- said to be the first complete transpolar voyage on any vessel -- the ship, the Sovetsky Soyuz, will depart from Nome (pending United States Government approval) on Aug. 19 and return to Murmansk through the Northeast Passage, bound for remote towns in northern Siberia, offshore islands and the North Cape of Norway.</p>
        <p>The two 21-day voyages, offered by Salen Lindblad Cruising, will cost from $25,000 to $32,000 a person, depending on the choice of cabin.</p>
        <p>The 500-foot vessel has 48 twin cabins, two lounges, a dining room, pool and sauna and lecture theater. The ship attains a cruising speed of 18.8 knots at sea and 10 knots through ice five feet thick.</p>
        <p>The ship has two lounges as well as a dining room, two saunas, gymnasium, indoor pool and a 100-seat tiered lecture theater with stage. Information: Salen Lindblad Cruising, 203-967-2900 or 800-223-5688. Eurailpass for Car and Trains</p>
        <p>Eurailpass will introduce three programs for 1991 and expand its destinations. For the first time, the pass -- allowing unlimited train travel in 17 countries -- will be valid throughout unified Germany, including Berlin. Eurailpass also has introduced a EurailDrive Pass, which offers travelers the combined use of rail and rental car in 16 countries.</p>
        <p>The program allows four days of rail travel and three days of Hertz car rental within a 21-day period. The per-person rate, when two or more people travel together, is $269 for an economy car, $289 for a small car and $299 for medium size. In this plan, the rental car may be returned to any city in the country where the car was picked up.</p>
        <p>Eurailpass has also expanded its Youthpasses for next year. Travelers under the age of 26 may use the rail system for 15 individual days of second-class travel during a three-month period for a cost of $340; 30 days of travel during that period costs $540.</p>
        <p>The declining value of the dollar has led to price increases for most other Eurailpasses. In 1991, the consecutive-day price structure will be: $390 for 15 days of first-class travel; $498 for 21 days; $616 for a month; $840 for two months, and $1,042 for three months. Fifteen days of first-class travel between April 1 and Sept. 30 will be $298 a person, for travel by three or more people. Further information may be obtained by writing: Eurailpass, Post Office Box 325, Old Greenwich, Conn. 06870. Club France Offers Benefits</p>
        <p>Francophiles can help the new American Center in Paris (opening in 1992) as well as earn benefits related to travel in France by joining the new Club France formed by the French Government Tourist Office. The annual membership of $65 includes a $15 contribution to the American Center. Membership benefits, which the tourist office says begin Jan. 1, include entry in monthly drawings for round-trip air tickets to Paris and for FrenchRail and rail-and-drive passes. Members also receive a subscription to the quarterly France Magazine, a newsletter and a Michelin Red Guide to France. Members also get reductions at certain hotels in France, room upgrades, or free breakfast or dinner at some establishments and shopping and car-rental discounts. To join, send a check for $65 payable to the French Government to the French Government Tourist Office, 610 Fifth Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10020 A $6 Dinner In Prague</p>
        <p>PRAGUE -- The kosher restaurant in Prague's Jewish Town Hall, long a lunchtime haunt of tourists and local people, Jews and non-Jews alike, recently began serving evening meals. The dinnertime ambiance -- tablecloths, low lights and a pianist -- is more sophisticated than the clamor at lunchtime.</p>
        <p>One simple set menu, changing daily, is available at lunch, which costs about $3.50. In the evening, there is a more ambitious choice of three set menus ranging from $2 to $6 and, unlike at lunch, alcoholic beverages are served. The $6 dinner, called the supermenu, includes appetizer, soup, fish, vegetables, main meat course, dessert and fruit, coffee or tea.</p>
        <p>The restaurant, in a high-ceilinged, ground-floor hall of the bright pink Old Jewish Town Hall on Maiselova Street, is around the corner from the Old-New Synagogue and the various parts of the Jewish Museum, including the Old Cemetery. The Town Hall, originally built in the 16th century and still the headquarters of the Prague Jewish community, is a five-minute walk from the Old Town Square. -- RUTH GRUBER Diversions For Children</p>
        <p>For children who ask "Are we there yet?" the American Automobile Association offers a "Travel Activity Book," which includes pictures to color and a variety of puzzles and games. Most items in the 144-page book, which is organized by state, are related to travel and help introduce youngsters to geography, nature and history. The book can be purchased at many bookstores and at most A.A.A. offices. The list price is $4.95.  REPAIRING STORM DAMAGE TO VERSAILLES GARDENS</p>
        <p>PARIS -- A stroll through the gardens of Versailles as winter approaches reveals the results of efforts by gardeners who, with the help of volunteers, soldiers and Boy Scouts, have restored some of the beauty after a devastating storm last February. Winds of 100 miles an hour took 1,300 trees, including 39 along the Tapis Vert, the main axis of the garden between the chateau and the canal.</p>
        <p>Gaps in the walls of trees that define the major areas of the garden designed by Andre Le Notre, the landscape architect, are to be found throughout the park, but the most serious damage was done to the bosquets, openings in the wooded parts containing fountains, statues and benches. The Room of the Chestnuts was left with no chestnuts at all.</p>
        <p>However, the debris has been carried away and 40 new trees planted. A mix of other, faster-growing trees and some hardwood varieties have been set out. These new plantings allow one to feel something of the effect of the young Versailles, evoking the appearance of the garden under Louis XIV.  The restoration work on the north side has proceeded more slowly than on the south. A substantial area is still closed to the public, and many fallen trees remain on the ground. Both Trianons also suffered important losses.</p>
        <p>An informational exhibit has been set up by the staff of the chateau around the Basin of Apollo near the canal. It points out that this is the third time that Versailles has lost most of its old trees.</p>
        <p>The gardens are open until dusk every day; admission is free. -- GUY WALTON</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mideast Crisis Makes Cruises Alter Course</p>
        <p>Enthusiasm for taking cruises to the eastern Mediterranean has all but disappeared because of tensions in the Middle East. Two deluxe cruise lines, Crystal Cruises and the Seabourn Cruise Line, have responded by canceling their plans to operate ships in the region next year.</p>
        <p>Duncan Beardsley, president of Seabourn, said, "People are still interested in the Mediterranean, but not the eastern part."</p>
        <p>Seabourn, based in San Francisco, said it had rerouted six cruises of the Seabourn Pride, a 204-passenger ship, which had been scheduled to embark from Venice and make stopovers in Istanbul between May and August. Instead of Istanbul, Seabourn said the ship will make stopovers in Lisbon, Nice and other western Mediterranean ports.</p>
        <p>Crystal, based in Los Angeles, said its 960-passenger Crystal Harmony, which was to make seven cruises in the eastern Mediterranean between August and November, would be recalled to the United States. Crystal said the ship would likely operate between New York and Montreal, with stopovers in New England. Before the tensions arising from Iraq's seizure of Kuwait, the ship's destinations were to have included Istanbul, Odessa and Alexandria.</p>
        <p>"We are responding to our guests' requests," said Darlene Papalini, a Crystal spokeswoman. "There is just a reluctance to travel to the eastern Mediterranean." Both companies said passengers who had booked passage on the canceled cruises were being offered alternative routes or their money back. Polar Voyage On Soviet Ship</p>
        <p>Western passengers can travel aboard a nuclear-powered Soviet icebreaker when she sets off July 26, 1991, from Murmansk to Nome, Alaska, via the North Pole. After the voyage -- said to be the first complete transpolar voyage on any vessel -- the ship, the Sovetsky Soyuz, will depart from Nome (pending United States Government approval) on Aug. 19 and return to Murmansk through the Northeast Passage, bound for remote towns in northern Siberia, offshore islands and the North Cape of Norway.</p>
        <p>The two 21-day voyages, offered by Salen Lindblad Cruising, will cost from $25,000 to $32,000 a person, depending on the choice of cabin.</p>
        <p>The 500-foot vessel has 48 twin cabins, two lounges, a dining room, pool and sauna and lecture theater. The ship attains a cruising speed of 18.8 knots at sea and 10 knots through ice five feet thick.</p>
        <p>The ship has two lounges as well as a dining room, two saunas, gymnasium, indoor pool and a 100-seat tiered lecture theater with stage. Information: Salen Lindblad Cruising, 203-967-2900 or 800-223-5688. Eurailpass for Car and Trains</p>
        <p>Eurailpass will introduce three programs for 1991 and expand its destinations. For the first time, the pass -- allowing unlimited train travel in 17 countries -- will be valid throughout unified Germany, including Berlin. Eurailpass also has introduced a EurailDrive Pass, which offers travelers the combined use of rail and rental car in 16 countries.</p>
        <p>The program allows four days of rail travel and three days of Hertz car rental within a 21-day period. The per-person rate, when two or more people travel together, is $269 for an economy car, $289 for a small car and $299 for medium size. In this plan, the rental car may be returned to any city in the country where the car was picked up.</p>
        <p>Eurailpass has also expanded its Youthpasses for next year. Travelers under the age of 26 may use the rail system for 15 individual days of second-class travel during a three-month period for a cost of $340; 30 days of travel during that period costs $540.</p>
        <p>The declining value of the dollar has led to price increases for most other Eurailpasses. In 1991, the consecutive-day price structure will be: $390 for 15 days of first-class travel; $498 for 21 days; $616 for a month; $840 for two months, and $1,042 for three months. Fifteen days of first-class travel between April 1 and Sept. 30 will be $298 a person, for travel by three or more people. Further information may be obtained by writing: Eurailpass, Post Office Box 325, Old Greenwich, Conn. 06870. Club France Offers Benefits</p>
        <p>Francophiles can help the new American Center in Paris (opening in 1992) as well as earn benefits related to travel in France by joining the new Club France formed by the French Government Tourist Office. The annual membership of $65 includes a $15 contribution to the American Center. Membership benefits, which the tourist office says begin Jan. 1, include entry in monthly drawings for round-trip air tickets to Paris and for FrenchRail and rail-and-drive passes. Members also receive a subscription to the quarterly France Magazine, a newsletter and a Michelin Red Guide to France. Members also get reductions at certain hotels in France, room upgrades, or free breakfast or dinner at some establishments and shopping and car-rental discounts. To join, send a check for $65 payable to the French Government to the French Government Tourist Office, 610 Fifth Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10020 A $6 Dinner In Prague</p>
        <p>PRAGUE -- The kosher restaurant in Prague's Jewish Town Hall, long a lunchtime haunt of tourists and local people, Jews and non-Jews alike, recently began serving evening meals. The dinnertime ambiance -- tablecloths, low lights and a pianist -- is more sophisticated than the clamor at lunchtime.</p>
        <p>One simple set menu, changing daily, is available at lunch, which costs about $3.50. In the evening, there is a more ambitious choice of three set menus ranging from $2 to $6 and, unlike at lunch, alcoholic beverages are served. The $6 dinner, called the supermenu, includes appetizer, soup, fish, vegetables, main meat course, dessert and fruit, coffee or tea.</p>
        <p>The restaurant, in a high-ceilinged, ground-floor hall of the bright pink Old Jewish Town Hall on Maiselova Street, is around the corner from the Old-New Synagogue and the various parts of the Jewish Museum, including the Old Cemetery. The Town Hall, originally built in the 16th century and still the headquarters of the Prague Jewish community, is a five-minute walk from the Old Town Square. -- RUTH GRUBER Diversions For Children</p>
        <p>For children who ask "Are we there yet?" the American Automobile Association offers a "Travel Activity Book," which includes pictures to color and a variety of puzzles and games. Most items in the 144-page book, which is organized by state, are related to travel and help introduce youngsters to geography, nature and history. The book can be purchased at many bookstores and at most A.A.A. offices. The list price is $4.95.  REPAIRING STORM DAMAGE TO VERSAILLES GARDENS</p>
        <p>PARIS -- A stroll through the gardens of Versailles as winter approaches reveals the results of efforts by gardeners who, with the help of volunteers, soldiers and Boy Scouts, have restored some of the beauty after a devastating storm last February. Winds of 100 miles an hour took 1,300 trees, including 39 along the Tapis Vert, the main axis of the garden between the chateau and the canal.</p>
        <p>Gaps in the walls of trees that define the major areas of the garden designed by Andre Le Notre, the landscape architect, are to be found throughout the park, but the most serious damage was done to the bosquets, openings in the wooded parts containing fountains, statues and benches. The Room of the Chestnuts was left with no chestnuts at all.</p>
        <p>However, the debris has been carried away and 40 new trees planted. A mix of other, faster-growing trees and some hardwood varieties have been set out. These new plantings allow one to feel something of the effect of the young Versailles, evoking the appearance of the garden under Louis XIV.  The restoration work on the north side has proceeded more slowly than on the south. A substantial area is still closed to the public, and many fallen trees remain on the ground. Both Trianons also suffered important losses.</p>
        <p>An informational exhibit has been set up by the staff of the chateau around the Basin of Apollo near the canal. It points out that this is the third time that Versailles has lost most of its old trees.</p>
        <p>The gardens are open until dusk every day; admission is free. -- GUY WALTON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
