<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pop and Jazz in Review</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="558489"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIO CITY MUSIC HALL (NYC)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNETT, TONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRAWFORD, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDD1E3BF937A1575AC0A964958260" item-length="1082" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pop and Jazz in Review</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Holden</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>'The Music of Andrew Lloyd Webber'</p>
        <p>Radio City Music Hall</p>
        <p>When Michael Crawford was asked by Andrew Lloyd Webber eight years ago to appear in his musical "The Phantom of the Opera," the English actor and singer assumed that the composer envisaged him playing Raoul, the show's second male lead. For the next year he studied the character as portrayed by Nelson Eddy in a 1943 Hollywood adaptation of the story. It was only when Mr. Crawford auditioned for the show that he discovered Mr. Webber had the title role in mind for him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>'The Music of Andrew Lloyd Webber'</p>
        <p>Radio City Music Hall</p>
        <p>When Michael Crawford was asked by Andrew Lloyd Webber eight years ago to appear in his musical "The Phantom of the Opera," the English actor and singer assumed that the composer envisaged him playing Raoul, the show's second male lead. For the next year he studied the character as portrayed by Nelson Eddy in a 1943 Hollywood adaptation of the story. It was only when Mr. Crawford auditioned for the show that he discovered Mr. Webber had the title role in mind for him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crawford offered this reminiscence from the stage of Radio City Music Hall on Tuesday evening by way of introducing "All I Ask of You," a song from "Phantom" that he never got to sing on Broadway because it belonged to the character he said he had "wasted a whole year" studying. Mr. Crawford's soaring performance, in a duet with Cathy Porter, was one of several in "The Music of Andrew Lloyd Webber," a lavish touring tribute to the composer, that showed him to be the supreme interpreter of Mr. Lloyd Webber's romantic ballads.</p>
        <p>The tribute, which had the first of 14 performances at the Music Hall on Tuesday evening, is an exceptionally well sung and carefully staged anthology of some two dozen selections from Mr. Lloyd Webber's musicals (excluding "Aspects of Love"), plus an excerpt from his Requiem and a theme he composed for the Olympic Games in Barcelona.</p>
        <p>Directed by Arlene Phillips, the evening features an ensemble of 12 first-rate singers and a 52-piece orchestra, led by Paul Bogaev, performing in front of a slide-show backdrop of logos from various Lloyd Webber musicals. Mr. Lloyd Webber's starchy oratorical melodies, performed here by top-notch operatic voices, have never sounded better.</p>
        <p>Mr. Crawford has both the voice and the dramatic clout to be able to wrestle Mr. Lloyd Webber's biggest songs to the ground. Even at its softest, his creamy tenor retains a gripping emotional tension. At peak moments, his voice rises to a ferocious bark that never loses its musical footing. At Tuesday's show, he turned songs from "Evita" ("And the Money Kept Rolling In"), "Jesus Christ Superstar" ("Gethsemane"), and "Phantom" (a gargantuan "Music of the Night") into flamboyant high drama.</p>
        <p>His were not the only memorable performances. Elizabeth Ward's beautifully shaded reading of "Don't Cry for Me, Argentina," Juliet Lambert's "Think of Me" and "Wishing You Were Somehow Here Again," and Laurie Beechman's "Memory" were also outstanding.</p>
        <p>If the performances flattered Mr. Lloyd Webber's songs, they also reinforced the impression of his music as defiantly old-fashioned. Despite the rockish, electronic pulses that run through his music, stylistically his songs are still a throwback to Sigmund Romberg, spiced with Spanish dance rhythms and inflated with a churchy pomposity.</p>
        <p>Richard Rodgers, Leonard Bernstein and Stephen Sondheim are melodic modernists compared with Mr. Lloyd Webber, for their songs have a conversational fluency lacking in his. Among his lyrical collaborators, none has been able to make his songs flow easily, although Tim Rice has come closest.</p>
        <p>Despite its bravura performances and aura of official cheer, "The Music of Andrew Lloyd Webber" is not an intimate show. An exercise in ceremonial glitz, it has all the warmth of a guard-changing ritual in front of Buckingham Palace on a frigid winter morning. Tony Bennett  Radio City Music Hall</p>
        <p>Midway through Tony Bennett's Friday-evening concert -- between "The Shadow of Your Smile" and "Fly Me to the Moon" -- the 66-year-old singer danced a little jig that was as endearing as it was gawky.</p>
        <p>As much as anything he sang, the dance seemed to express Mr. Bennett's exuberant acknowledgment that he has reached a golden moment in a singing career of more than 40 years. For vocally, Mr. Bennett has never been in surer command. Just how sure was evidenced by his performance of "Fly Me to the Moon": the microphones were turned off, and he belted a semioperatic rendition of the Bart Howard standard that carried easily through much of the hall.</p>
        <p>The style Mr. Bennett has settled upon in the autumn of his career is a potent mixture of sophisticated jazz-flavored saloon singing and the passionate Mediterranean street style of his earliest hit, "Boulevard of Broken Dreams." A typical performance begins quietly and stealthily, then builds, often suddenly, to a triumphant, declamatory finish. Especially in his jazzier numbers, the singer punches out the key words in a lyric.  In "Old Devil Moon," the opening number of his show, that word was "love"; in "For Once in My life" it was "life"; in "Speak Low" it was "old."</p>
        <p>Practiced by a less-experienced artist, such stylistic and dynamic extremes might seem corny and overblown. But the combination of Mr. Bennett's gregarious personality and musical know-how carried it off. One peak in a show that had no weak moments was a mighty, strutting "There'll Be Some Changes Made," which the singer punctuated with joyous shouts. Another was a quiet, exquisitely phrased "Solitude," which exploded only at the last moment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bennett has just released a superb album of songs in tribute to Frank Sinatra, titled "Perfectly Frank" (Columbia), which he recorded with the Ralph Sharon Trio, which accompanied him onstage with members of the Count Basie Orchestra. If the record pays homage to a singer who probably exerted the greatest single influence on Mr. Bennett's style, it also represents a happy declaration of independence from that influence.</p>
        <p>Just how sharply the musical personalities of Mr. Bennett and Mr. Sinatra diverge was illustrated during a segment of songs from "Perfectly Frank." Where Mr. Sinatra's version of "I've Got the World on a String" suggests the triumphant crow of a satisfied rooster, Mr. Bennett's is a mellower expression of a joy he wishes to communicate to others. Where Mr. Sinatra's "One for My Baby" is an edgy, booze-soaked lament for a failed romance, Mr. Bennett's is a genial, swinging toast to a relationship he has successfully put behind him.</p>
        <p>The differences between the two artists can be distilled in their almost opposite approaches to Cole Porter's "All of You." In Mr. Sinatra's hands, it has always been an ode to the "east, west, north, south" of a woman's body. But when Mr. Bennett sang "I love all of you" at Radio City on Friday, with his arms outstretched, he directed those words straight at the audience.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
