<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Christopher Meets Syrian and Sees Progress on Israel Talks</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="816294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISRAEL-INTERNATIONALRELATIONS-SYRIA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SYRIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SYRIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DAMASCUS, SYRIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRISTOPHER, WARREN M (SEC) SHIMON PERES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE1DB1739F935A25751C1A963958260" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Christopher Meets Syrian and Sees Progress on Israel Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMEMANN, SERGE;</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, Dec. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Secretary of State Warren Christopher met for four hours today with President Hafez al-Assad of Syria and reported "substantial progress" toward opening peace negotiations with Israel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher did not reveal the substance of his talks in Damascus, but his unusually upbeat tone gave the sense that Mr. Assad had responded positively to the appeals for new talks issued by Prime Minister Shimon Peres of Israel in  the month since he succeeded the assassinated Yitzhak Rabin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Secretary of State Warren Christopher met for four hours today with President Hafez al-Assad of Syria and reported "substantial progress" toward opening peace negotiations with Israel.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher did not reveal the substance of his talks in Damascus, but his unusually upbeat tone gave the sense that Mr. Assad had responded positively to the appeals for new talks issued by Prime Minister Shimon Peres of Israel in  the month since he succeeded the assassinated Yitzhak Rabin.</p>
        <p>Last Tuesday, Mr. Peres used an address to the United States Congress to invite Mr. Assad to join him in seeking a final end to the Arab-Israeli conflict. Mr. Peres declared that he was setting no conditions on the talks and  was open to any format.</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher's trip to Damascus was the first follow-up to that appeal, and the Secretary said he was prepared to return to Damascus on Sunday, and again later, if further contacts were required.</p>
        <p>He was not expected to make any further official announcement until after the end of the Jewish Sabbath on Saturday evening, although he attended a private dinner with Mr. Peres tonight.</p>
        <p>"We had positive and constructive discussions with President Assad here today," Mr. Christopher told reporters in Damascus after meeting the Syrian leader.</p>
        <p>"Based upon the constructive discussions today, I can say that the parties clearly want to press forward," he said. "The remainder of my time here will be  spent trying to find the best way, the best process, the best means to press forward as the parties definitely want to do."</p>
        <p>Although the soundings so far have centered only on reopening talks, and not  on any of the substantive issues separating Israel and Syria, the force of Mr. Peres's challenges and the changed political equation since Mr. Rabin's assassination a month ago have created a new momentum on the last unsettled front of the 47-year-old Arab-Israeli conflict.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Rabin, Israel had insisted that initial talks focus exclusively on  security matters, and two attempts at negotiations over the last year fizzled and collapsed. Before his death, Mr. Rabin had all but abandoned the Syrian track until after Israeli elections, which are scheduled for next November.</p>
        <p>But on taking Mr. Rabin's place, Mr. Peres almost immediately issued a new challenge to Syria, abandoning the insistence on security talks, which he never  favored, and inviting Mr. Assad to take the lead in concluding a comprehensive peace.</p>
        <p>The major issue dividing Israel and Syria is the Golan Heights, a plateau between the two countries that offers the occupant a strategic view of the adversary. Israel seized the Golan in 1967, and maintains a surveillance post there over the south Syrian plains. Other issues in dispute include Syria's control over Lebanon, and the operations of Islamic guerrilla forces there.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Peres has not declared what Israel is prepared to cede or demand, but he has repeated Mr. Rabin's formula that the "depth of withdrawal" from the  Golan will equal the "depth of peace."</p>
        <p>The implication is that Israel would cede all or most of the heights if it received assurances of full security and a comprehensive peace signed by most Arab countries.</p>
        <p>While it remained unknown what exactly Mr. Assad said to Mr. Christopher, the tightly controlled Syrian press has responded positively to Mr. Peres's statements.</p>
        <p>Israeli officials say they believe that one reason Mr. Assad may be interested in opening negotiations now is that the assassination of Mr. Rabin revealed to him that Israelis are really divided over the issue of peace with Arabs, and that future administrations may not have the political leeway to negotiate that Mr. Peres does for now.</p>
        <p>Although the agreement with the Palestinians calls for negotiations on the final settlement of the occupied territories to begin in May, Mr. Peres is said  to believe that the Palestinians and Israelis will not be ready yet to continue.</p>
        <p>Israeli troops are now withdrawing from Arab cities in the West Bank, and the Palestinians are to hold elections to a ruling council in January.</p>
        <p>But if major progress can be made with Syria, the stage would be set to combine the next phase of Palestinian talks with the Syrian talks, leading, in Mr. Peres's view, to a comprehensive peace by the end of the century.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
