<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fasten Seat Belt. Start Engine. Deflate Ego.</title>
    <meta content="31MYJO$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/31/business/yourmoney/31MYJO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1515853"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="MY JOB"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drivers Education</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Carr's Driving School</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olsen, Patricia R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carr, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drivers Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E5D71139F932A0575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="661" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fasten Seat Belt. Start Engine. Deflate Ego.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Fasten Seat Belt. Start Engine. Deflate Ego.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN CARR; Written with Patricia R. Olsen.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olsen, Patricia R; Carr, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Carr, manager of Carr's Driving School in Point Pleasant Beach, NJ, comments on his experiences with various driving students through the years; photo (M) (My Job column)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONCE, a kid wearing a baseball hat backward got into the driver's training car and pushed the seat back as far as it would go. He confidently put his left hand in the 12 o'clock position on the steering wheel, placed his right hand on the console next to him, looked at me and said ''Let's go.''</p>
        <p>He couldn't drive worth a darn. Kids are so excited about driving that they think they know more than they do. Usually, when I take them to a parking lot and set up the cones to practice parallel parking, it takes them down a notch.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>NCE, a kid wearing a baseball hat backward got into the driver's training car and pushed the seat back as far as it would go. He confidently put his left hand in the 12 o'clock position on the steering wheel, placedhis right hand on the console next to him, looked at me and said</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONCE, a kid wearing a baseball hat backward got into the driver's training car and pushed the seat back as far as it would go. He confidently put his left hand in the 12 o'clock position on the steering wheel, placed his right hand on the console next to him, looked at me and said ''Let's go.''</p>
        <p>He couldn't drive worth a darn. Kids are so excited about driving that they think they know more than they do. Usually, when I take them to a parking lot and set up the cones to practice parallel parking, it takes them down a notch.</p>
        <p>Our instructors spend a lot of time preparing students for every possible occurrence. Once, I had just gone through the drill with one girl about what to do when coming to a traffic light. We were approaching a green light just as it turned yellow and she gave every indication she was going to keep going. All of a sudden she slammed on the brakes.</p>
        <p>There was an 18-wheeler behind us. He leaned on the horn, swerved onto the shoulder, passed us on the right and continued through the yellow light. The girl was in her own little world and just said, ''Gee, that was a big truck.''</p>
        <p>Another time, a friend of mine was sitting in the back seat to learn how to be an instructor. We were rounding a corner near the ocean in Asbury Park and approaching a line of parked cars. I had taught the student driver to coast into a turn with his foot at the ready, slightly above the brake. As he started the turn, he hit the gas and shot straight for the line of cars. I slammed both feet on my brake -- the extra one for instructors -- and pitted my foot strength against his. My head was pushing against the roof and I could feel my friend's nails digging into my shoulder. The driver finally took his foot off the gas and I was able to slow the car just in time.</p>
        <p>A few years ago, the parents of a teenager with limited mobility in his left hand called and asked if we would work with their son. He had no fine motor skills in that hand, and other driving schools said they couldn't help him. The parents bought a device like a knob for the steering wheel, and an extension for the signal indicator for one of our cars. We gave the teenager 12 hours of instruction instead of the normal 6. He was thrilled when he passed the test. We still get thank-you notes from the family.</p>
        <p>Around that same time, a 76-year-old woman, whose husband had died, wanted lessons. She took 40 hours of instruction and failed the driving test twice before she passed it. I don't think the woman ever drove much; she just wanted to prove to herself that she could get her license. She and her female instructor still get together for lunch.</p>
        <p>My father, who ran the business before he passed away in 1995, used to make up short poems to help students. One was, ''Always be safe and follow at a distance, and you'll never need first aid's assistance.'' He also told teenagers to watch out for the two-headed, one-armed monster. In other words, he told them, don't sit close together in the driver's seat, and keep both hands on the wheel.</p>
        <p>MY JOB</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
