<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants Make Final Cuts a Day Early</title>
    <meta content="31GIANTS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/31/sports/football/31giants.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1516171"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Giants</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030831T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE4DD1438F932A0575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="916" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants Make Final Cuts a Day Early</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giants Make Final Cuts of Training Camp a Day Early</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Aug. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By 8 a.m. today, relieved smiles filled the Giants' locker room. The congratulations had been passed around. The anxious moments were done. There was no list, no dramatic announcement. Those who fell victim to the Giants' final cuts had been told quietly by Coach Jim Fassel. By 8, everyone left in the Giants' locker room was still a Giant.</p>
        <p>The celebrations were quiet and reflective.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was no list, no dramatic announcement. Those who fell victim to the Giants' final cuts had been told quietly by Coach Jim Fassel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By 8 a.m. today, relieved smiles filled the Giants' locker room. The congratulations had been passed around. The anxious moments were done. There was no list, no dramatic announcement. Those who fell victim to the Giants' final cuts had been told quietly by Coach Jim Fassel. By 8, everyone left in the Giants' locker room was still a Giant.</p>
        <p>The celebrations were quiet and reflective.</p>
        <p>Running back Ron Dayne sat at his locker, smiling at the fuss that had been made over his spot on the edge of the cuts. He still has no idea if he will dress for the opening game on Sept. 7 against St. Louis, but that is an issue for another day.</p>
        <p>''I'm ready to go watch some films,'' Dayne said with a characteristic shrug. ''I wasn't really worried about it. If that was the case, they would have cut me earlier in the year when I didn't show up for minicamp.''</p>
        <p>Jim Finn exhaled. After a rather disastrous final preseason game with two holding penalties, he had still been the pick as the Giants' fullback over Charles Stackhouse, who was cut.</p>
        <p>Matt Bryant knew he no longer had to look over his shoulder at Mike Hollis, who was brought in to take over his kicking duties but then injured his back in a preseason game. Hollis will most likely go on injured reserve, which puts him out for the season, but may instead receive an injury settlement.</p>
        <p>Bryant's performance in preseason -- he missed only one field goal and was better than Hollis on kickoffs -- made the turn of events easier on the Giants.</p>
        <p>''They're in great hands with Bryant,'' Hollis said. ''He had a great camp, and they'll be fine.''</p>
        <p>Also out of the mix is long snapper Ryan Kuehl, brought in this off-season to help solve the Giants' special teams adventures. Kuehl said he would probably have surgery on the nerve in his right elbow, putting him out for the season on injured reserve. A newcomer, Carson Dach, will handle the snapping duties.</p>
        <p>The Giants will not announce the cuts until the N.F.L. deadline Sunday afternoon, but the actual cutting had been done when the players reported shortly after 7 a.m. Their early day was forced by tonight's Bruce Springsteen concert. The team had to be out of the stadium by early afternoon.</p>
        <p>Those clearing out their belongings were Stackhouse, offensive guard Tam Hopkins, offensive tackle Barrett Brooks, tight end Darnell Dinkins, defensive end Frank Ferrara, cornerback Rod Babers, defensive end Radell Lockhart, linebacker Josh Hotchkiss, receiver Daryl Jones, safety Clarence LeBlanc, cornerback Calvin Spears and punter Steve Cheek.</p>
        <p>The Giants have until 4 p.m. Sunday to make it official, and to decide on the injured-reserve status of Hollis and Kuehl.</p>
        <p>''That doesn't mean this roster is etched in concrete,'' Fassel said. ''There will be changes. They can be based on injury, they can be based on lack of performance by somebody. There were some difficult decisions to make. I'm confident we made the right decisions, but that doesn't mean guys can take a deep breath and say, 'O.K., I'm here.'''</p>
        <p>The relief inside the locker room was countered by the disappointment outside it.</p>
        <p>Stackhouse made the roster last season as a rookie but found himself supplanted this time around.</p>
        <p>''It's football,'' he said. ''I'm kind of surprised, but the coach has got to do what he's got to do. I know for a fact I'll end up somewhere else.''</p>
        <p>Dinkins also made the team last year, but the Giants drafted Visanthe Shiancoe in the third round, and Dinkins's inconsistency put him far behind Marcellus Rivers, the player he would have had to beat out.</p>
        <p>Hopkins came into training camp penciled in as the starter at right guard but was pushed aside by a rookie, David Diehl, and found himself out of the mix. Another rookie, Wayne Lucier, will back up that guard spot as well as center.</p>
        <p>Those still on the inside were looking at the day as a fresh start. For the rookies, it meant finally getting their own lockers instead of having to share. For Finn, it means he gets to play within shouting distance of his hometown, Fair Lawn, N.J.</p>
        <p>For Dayne, he is not quite sure what it means, other than he still has some kind of role with the team that drafted him No. 1 in 2000.</p>
        <p>''I'm just doing my part to help,'' he said. ''Whenever I get in, hopefully I can help. I'm just ready to get a little playing time or whatever.''</p>
        <p>His role is far from defined. Fassel flopped him and Dorsey Levens as Tiki Barber's backup. When Fassel did start him -- Barber did not play in the preseason finale against Baltimore -- Dayne responded with a dud of a performance: 13 yards and a fumble.</p>
        <p>Still, Dayne found himself among the relieved. The cuts had come and he was not gone.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
