<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Space Shuttle Launching Delayed by Navigational Equipment Flaw</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="449565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE SHUTTLE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLUMBIA (SPACE SHUTTLE)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL AERONAUTICS AND SPACE ADMINISTRATION (NASA)</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space Shuttle</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DB1639F931A35755C0A967958260" item-length="508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Space Shuttle Launching Delayed by Navigational Equipment Flaw</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN E. LEARY,</byline>
      <dateline>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla., June 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The space agency called off the launching of the shuttle Columbia this morning after problems were discovered in a navigation device.</p>
        <p>The flight, which had already been delayed 10 days by other technical problems, cannot go up until at least Wednesday because of the time it will take to replace the navigation equipment and get the winged spaceplane ready for another attempt, said officials of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The space agency called off the launching of the shuttle Columbia this morning after problems were discovered in a navigation device.</p>
        <p>The flight, which had already been delayed 10 days by other technical problems, cannot go up until at least Wednesday because of the time it will take to replace the navigation equipment and get the winged spaceplane ready for another attempt, said officials of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration.</p>
        <p>The latest problem delaying the 41st flight of the space shuttle cropped up early this morning after the vehicle had been loaded with half a million gallons of fuel and technicians were testing other systems for the 8 A.M. launching. One of three inertial measurement units, devices that gauge the movement of the shuttle in flight so that it always knows its position, could not be calibrated with the other two, said Robert Sieck, the launch director. A Cumbersome Process</p>
        <p>"Every time we'd query it to tell us where we are, it gave a different answer," Mr. Sieck said at a briefing. To remove the 58-pound unit and replace it with a spare will require building a special platform, a cumbersome process that results in at least a four-day delay, he said.</p>
        <p>Although a shuttle can fly back from space with only one of the navigation units, engineers prefer that all three be operating, said Robert Crippen, NASA's space shuttle director. If only two units are available after a failure and they begin giving different readings, he said, it would be difficult to tell which one was faulty without another device serving as a reference.</p>
        <p>The crew of seven astronauts had been set to blast off today on what was to be a nine-day medical examination in space to test the effects of weightlessness. The tests are to take place in a special medical laboratory called Spacelab, which is in the shuttle's cargo bay.</p>
        <p>"We're very disappointed this happened," said the mission commander, Col. Bryan D. O'Connor of the Marine Corps. "We all realize that there are millions of parts involved in this vehicle and that it's a miracle when we do launch."</p>
        <p>Colonel O'Connor said he and the mission pilot, Lieut. Col. Sidney M. Gutierrez of the Air Force, planned to go to Edwards Air Force Base in California on Sunday to practice landings at the primary return site. The remainder of the crew was to stay at the Kennedy Space Center here for rest and reviewing the mission plan.</p>
        <p>The other crew members are three physicians, Dr. James P. Bagian, Dr. Margaret Rhea Seddon and Dr. Francis A. Gaffney, and two scientists, Dr. Millie Hughes-Fulford and Dr. Tamara E. Jernigan.</p>
        <p>The four men and three women are to use the 21,000-pound laboratory to perform the most detailed medical tests ever done in space to check the effects of weightlessness, readjustment to gravity and any physiological changes that occur during almost 10 days in space.</p>
        <p>Earlier problems with computer components and fuel temperature sensors caused cancellation of the flight on May 21, a day before its last intended liftoff.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
