<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 'Happy Fella' With Less Offers More</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="449971"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GOODSPEED OPERA HOUSE (EAST HADDAM, CONN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICHARDS, DAVID</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MOST HAPPY FELLA, THE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SONG OF SINGAPORE (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DA153EF931A35755C0A967958260" item-length="1589" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 'Happy Fella' With Less Offers More</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David Richards</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICHARDS, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With so many big, expansive musicals all around us today, we sometimes forget how satisfying an intimate one can be.</p>
        <p>Like "The Most Happy Fella" by Frank Loesser.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With so many big, expansive musicals all around us today, we sometimes forget how satisfying an intimate one can be.</p>
        <p>Like "The Most Happy Fella" by Frank Loesser.</p>
        <p>Oh, I know, "The Most Happy Fella" wasn't an intimate musical when it had its premiere on Broadway in 1956. Although Mr. Loesser insisted he had written "a musical comedy -- with a lot of music," most of the critics viewed it as a vastly more ambitious undertaking -- not quite opera, but heading there. The show was almost totally sung, with only snippets of dialogue breaking up wave upon wave of cascading melodies. In three acts, not the usual two of musical comedy, it elevated the dusty story of an aging Italian immigrant farmer in the Napa Valley and his mail-order bride to that epic plane where love becomes Love, and Forgiveness battles Jealousy for a man's Happiness.</p>
        <p>The pit orchestra alone was made up of 35 musicians.</p>
        <p>However, at the tiny Goodspeed Opera House (in East Haddam, Conn.), which is launching the summer season in splendid fashion with "The Most Happy Fella," the orchestra is down to two pianists, and the set designer, John Lee Beatty, has seen fit to cover over the unoccupied part of the pit with planking. Those performers courageous enough to venture to the edge, do so knowing the whites of their eyes will be visible from the back row.</p>
        <p>That used to be firing range. What it means in this instance is that the Goodspeed is free to remove all the capital letters from musical. The cast members are singing their hearts out -- no question of that -- but they are also singing what's in their hearts with the delicate shadings and quiet misgivings that would be lost in a larger hall. The subtleties more than compensate for the reduction in scale. In fact, a paradoxical law of the theater kicks in. A small production, fully realized, can actually seem bigger than an extravaganza with nothing much on its mind.</p>
        <p>Our recent musicals, from "Shogun" to "Miss Saigon," have pushed the limits of physical space -- the one proving that yes, you can sink a Dutch galleon on stage if you're willing to sink a few million bucks into the machinery; the other convincingly demonstrating the use of the stage as a heliport. But inevitably, for all of the technological advances, there's the back wall of the theater to contend with. Inner space, on the other hand, is limitless. It extends as far as the performers are able to take us.</p>
        <p>"The Most Happy Fella" produced its share of popular hits -- "Standing on the Corner," "Joey, Joey, Joey" and "Big 'D,' " that foot-stomping celebration of Dallas. Elsewhere in the show, however, Mr. Loesser also gave expression to a full-throated lyricism that was far less common in the Broadway musical of the day. "Somebody Somewhere," "Mamma, Mamma," "Please Let Me Tell You," and that soaring duet for the show's unlikely lovers, "My Heart Is So Full of You," plunge unhesitatingly into the tumult of souls ravaged by the confusion and bliss of loving.</p>
        <p>The mixture of Broadway pizazz and semi-operatic arias was once taken as evidence of the show's split personality. In the light of today's pop operas ("Les Miserables," "The Phantom of the Opera," "Miss Saigon"), Mr. Loesser seems to have been boldly ahead of his time.</p>
        <p>The pop opera, however, has a tendency to divide its characters into two groups, the good and the bad (with a subdivision for the ugly), while Mr. Loesser's characters -- waitresses, farmhands, small-town folk -- occupy the fertile in-between ground. Tony (Spiro Malas), the prosperous Italian farmer, is probably as good as they come, a man not only wise enough to forgive his bride for the one-night fling that has left her pregnant, but generous enough to accept the child as his own. In Mr. Malas's glorious performance, so open as to be childlike, we also see that Tony is lonely, embarrassed about his age, his faltering English, his girth and, most of all, terribly frightened that a woman won't be able to sense the warmth inside him.</p>
        <p>As Rosabella, the San Francisco waitress he courts with sweet-talking letters and a fraudulent photograph, Sophie Hayden turns up in Napa, "wanting to be wanted, needing to be needed." But there's just as much hesitation in her, and she's quick to persuade herself that she's landed in a fix. The actress starts out weary, a little puffy, not quite pretty, then blooms ever so warily. She is no more a traditional romantic lead than Mr. Malas, but quite the nicest aspect of "The Most Happy Fella" is that by the time the two do fall into each other's arms, the pairing looks and feels absolutely right. The spirit has totally remade the flesh, which, when you think of it, is usually how love operates.</p>
        <p>The secondary love interest hews to a more traditional Broadway formula that calls for the girl to be brash, wisecracking and full of pep; and the boy to be good-natured, a bit nitwitted and full of pep. Still, playing Rosabella's best friend and a goofy farmhand, Liz Larsen and Guy Stroman bring dollops of freshness to their roles. The choreographer, Liza Gennaro, hasn't given them a whole lot of original things to do with their feet, but since they can't keep their hands off each other, the failing is not critical.</p>
        <p>Charles Pistone, for his part, barely has to lift a finger as the foreman who seduces Rosabella. His sultry voice does it all and the way he handles the dip in the first measures of "Don't Cry" very nearly qualifies as a caress in itself. But then the singing everywhere is first-rate, if never so spirited as when Mark Lotito, Buddy Crutchfield and Bill Nabel are celebrating "Abbondanza." There's a delirious nuttiness about their manner that encompasses the arrogance of the headwaiter, the panache of the four-star chef and the zeal of the Sicilian street vendor.</p>
        <p>With all due respect to Mr. Loesser, Gerald Gutierrez has directed "The Most Happy Fella" as if it were a</p>
        <p>play</p>
        <p>with a lot of music. He's on the lookout for the first sparks of awareness and the second doubts -- all those early stirrings that precede a big change of heart and make it inevitable. Directors of musicals generally rely on broader strokes. Of course, this kind of detail work is possible only in a theater like the Goodspeed, where a twinkle does the work of a twinkle and a sigh can be a sigh. No magnification required, none desired.</p>
        <p>"The Most Happy Fella" doesn't have to come to us. We don't have to go to it. We're all in it together. Cozy. Warm. Rewarding. 'Song of Singapore'</p>
        <p>For "Song of Singapore," Mr. Beatty (busy man these days) has taken the club hall of the Polish Army Veterans of America, District No. 2, and turned it into Freddy's Song of Singapore Cafe, a No. 1 dive. Located on Irving Place at 15th Street in Manhattan, it's very much a Terry and the Pirates kind of hangout, with lots of red lacquer and paper lanterns. Fantastical dragons snake along the walls and curl around the columns, while a real dragon lady (Cathy Foy), her imperious eye peeled for trouble, drifts among the tables, trailing cigarette smoke and such aphorisms as "Danger is in the round eye of the beholder."</p>
        <p>On the bandstand, the blind Cockney bandleader Freddy S. Lyme (Michael Garin) is putting the Malayan Melody Makers and its lead vocalist, Rose, through their paces. The time is 1941 and, according to the periodic radio announcements, the Japanese are advancing down the Malay peninsula at a furious clip. This may be the last night for Freddy's Song of Singapore Cafe, but for the next few hours, at least, it's music, intrigue and disgusting-looking hors d'oeuvres, as usual.</p>
        <p>"Song of Singapore" isn't exactly a musical, although it has an original score by Mr. Garin, Erik Frandsen, Robert Hipkens and Paula Lockheart. It's more than just a cabaret entertainment, since it can also claim a dopey book by all of the above, plus Allan Katz. Maybe you could call it an "environment in two acts." More than once, I had the sinking sensation that I'd stumbled into the Singapore Pavilion at Disney World, except that the Disney folks would probably do it better and shorter.</p>
        <p>Under the direction of A. J. Antoon, the show makes a concerted effort to involve the spectators, if not directly in the action at least tangentially, by inviting them to join a conga line or unleashing a reeling "Hindu hootch hound" in their midst. You're frisked at the door and bar girls, their satin dresses slit up the side, do a hefty traffic in come-hither looks. Some people may find the participatory pretenses amusing. I guess you've got to be in the right mood. Or drunk. To that end, the establishment offers a mixed drink called the Frank Sumatra for $6.50.</p>
        <p>Periodically, the musicians -- especially, the percussionist, Oliver Jackson Jr. -- whip up some flurries of excitement. But the good times are pitched at you as if fun could only be delivered by the shovelful. Chief among the pitchers is Donna Murphy, who as Rose, the amnesiac songstress, is introduced at one point as "a girl who will steal your heart and then forget where she put it." Ms. Murphy's desperation is not so much that of one trying to get out of Singapore as it is that of one trying to break into show business.</p>
        <p>The light touch is not greatly in evidence and no one connected with "Song of Singapore" will ever stand accused of holding back. That's the hitch. Like the Goodspeed's "Most Happy Fella," "Song of Singapore" creates a cozy atmosphere. But only so the performers can subsequently blow it to smithereens.  SUNDAY VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
