<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Still Life of Summer, in Words</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk - SummerTimes Supplement" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="449617"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D81E38F931A35755C0A967958260" item-length="868" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Still Life of Summer, in Words</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN SCHWARTZ;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a subway platform it becomes summer sooner. An afternoon in late April; a long delay. No trains on either side of the station; no breeze as an express goes through. The white tiles on the wall at the far end of the tunnel are uninformed by the first exciting seconds of the lights of the local you hope for. You are annoyed but not late. What you anticipate is air-conditioning.</p>
        <p>In New York it is summer well before the banner is raised. A humid-harsh two or three days in mid-May, and then in early June a week or so posing as calendar-spring does injury to the loopy notion that this time things might stay pretty much as they are forever.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a subway platform it becomes summer sooner. An afternoon in late April; a long delay. No trains on either side of the station; no breeze as an express goes through. The white tiles on the wall at the far end of the tunnel are uninformed by the first exciting seconds of the lights of the local you hope for. You are annoyed but not late. What you anticipate is air-conditioning.</p>
        <p>In New York it is summer well before the banner is raised. A humid-harsh two or three days in mid-May, and then in early June a week or so posing as calendar-spring does injury to the loopy notion that this time things might stay pretty much as they are forever.</p>
        <p>Summer.</p>
        <p>I am spun around by many feelings in the summer. It is the most tenacious season of the year, with long stretches that offer no hope of even a momentary pause. There are those who are at ease in the summer, who thrive in its oppression. In the 1950's and 60's, the theater critic Richard Watts Jr. returned from his European holiday every July 31 to spend August in Manhattan, unoppressed. And many children obliviously slide through the time in high spirits, happily grappling with each passing minute.</p>
        <p>Not so, me. I experience the summer as exhausting, cunning, like the gin and vodka that tell some of the tale. So contradictory a season, its days of ocean linked to all the days and weeks of ocean summers so many years ago; fathers soon replaced by women soon replaced by children, your own, gingerly toeing the surf, then racing back, shrieking joyfully in hot sand.</p>
        <p>But consider human longing, particularly visible in the summer, in the eyes, in the gait, the heat bearing down, wearing down the deepest defenses, until feelings find an opening and storm the palace, and you are suddenly hostage, held to the flame of missed connections, to beams of extraordinary light, to the delayed epiphany that you are diminishing.</p>
        <p>And yet. This New York City of ours is filled with summer music, some of it furious in the streets, much of it privately historic: "Hey Jude" on someone's tape in Carl Schurz Park, Sinatra on a taxi radio, "Blue Bayou" from a cashier's booth in a parking lot, Mozart in the subway on a solitary flute; Mozart in the early morning, tucked into coffee; Mozart in Merkin Concert Hall, gracious and healing.</p>
        <p>The taste of summer!</p>
        <p>The white corn is first, along Route 27 on Long Island between Water Mill and Wainscott. Then the official corn, defining yellow, sweet, silk corn. The tomatoes, dark red, that you can spot a block away outside a Korean market are arriving earlier each year from New Jersey and Long Island. A summer breakfast: a large tomato (that you have been caring for) thickly sliced, a Vidalia onion (easily found these days) less thickly sliced, absolutely fresh leaf basil, all arranged with respect on San Francisco sourdough bread sprinkled with cold-pressed Tuscan extra-virgin olive oil.</p>
        <p>And one Corona beer.</p>
        <p>The meager strips of tuna that pass for sashimi in restaurants are like single peanuts or chips. I seek out the two-pound hunks of bluefin from Montauk, the toro, or belly meat. Every now and then, standing outside the Citarella fish market or Balducci's in Manhattan, eating cubed tuna like popcorn, I think of the Japanese longliners lurking off Montauk, loaded down with yellowfin and albacore. The voyage home must take at least three weeks, it seems to me, all the way down to the Panama Canal, then passing finally into the Pacific for the last long leg of the journey. Bluefin generally travels by plane in its June-to-November season. Headed, gutted, iced and coffined in Montauk, it is whisked to J.F.K. in (I imagine) early-morning fog, and flown out of our summer, like contraband.</p>
        <p>Baseball plays its middle moments in late July, displayed in a Trader Horn window, one at-bat prolonged by many foul balls. I have stood in the streets (East 86th Street; Broadway and 98th Street; West 23d Street) in dreadful Saturday heat watching those foul balls. A long camera shot from the press box might reveal a runner on second and Doug Drabek still out there for Pittsburgh. It's about a quarter to 6, and that means the Pirates probably have a two- or three-run lead, because their starter is still in there so late in the afternoon. I can read the pores of his cheeks on 10 screens.</p>
        <p>A half-hour goes by, and I am still out there.</p>
        <p>Jimmy Durante often asked: "Did you ever get the feeling that you wanted to stay? Then you got the feeling that you wanted to go?"</p>
        <p>New York in the summer.</p>
        <p>The calliope can be heard before the carousel comes into view.</p>
        <p>Books are sold outdoors.</p>
        <p>Once in a while a batter, standing at a home plate only a few yards from the West Side Highway, will strike a ball to the promenade level of Riverside Park, about 30 feet above the playing field in left and center. The drive, a Ted Williams high fly rather than a Wade Boggs liner, will travel on and on in peculiar slow motion, like a blimp, the ball finally landing among startled and unaware bench-sitters. In that suspended moment all players and bystanders will cease movement. You will find, after seeing this happen, that the rest of your day will be altered by the suggestion of joy.</p>
        <p>ESSAY Jonathan Schwartz, a longtime personality on WNEW-AM, is the music correspondent for the NBC News program "Sunday Today" and the at-large columnist for GQ.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jonathan Schwartz, a longtime personality on WNEW-AM, is the music correspondent for the NBC News program "Sunday Today" and the at-large columnist for GQ.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
