<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Salute Berries in Ways Plain and Fancy</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="449917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BERRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910602T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DB123FF931A35755C0A967958260" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Salute Berries in Ways Plain and Fancy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE berry season has arrived. Strawberries to purchase at farm stands or to gather at farms that permit pickers are the first of a succession of locally grown berries that ripen through the fall.</p>
        <p>After the strawberries come raspberries and blueberries, then blackberries, then raspberries again. Finally, some areas will have locally grown cranberries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE berry season has arrived. Strawberries to purchase at farm stands or to gather at farms that permit pickers are the first of a succession of locally grown berries that ripen through the fall.</p>
        <p>After the strawberries come raspberries and blueberries, then blackberries, then raspberries again. Finally, some areas will have locally grown cranberries.</p>
        <p>Gooseberries, mulberries, wild strawberries and fresh currants are some of the other berry crops that are available from specialty farms and produce stands in the summer.</p>
        <p>All of these berries add bright summer flavor and color to dessert tarts, cakes, puddings, ice creams, sauces, preserves and other confections. Most are excellent either cooked or uncooked.</p>
        <p>Cranberries must be cooked; because of their extremely high water content, strawberries, whether cultivated or wild, tend to be better when used uncooked.</p>
        <p>The exception is when they are combined with other berries or fruits or used to make jams. Unlike raspberries or blueberries, when strawberries are cooked both the color and flavor tend to fade.</p>
        <p>Use fresh strawberries whole or sliced to fill a cake, to pave the top of a cheesecake or, standing at attention, with a brushing of glaze, to make a fruit tart.</p>
        <p>Splash them with liqueur and combine them with softly whipped cream or yogurt to make a lighter dessert or use them in a fruit "soup" garnished with a scoop of sorbet.</p>
        <p>Always rinse the berries before hulling them so they do not become waterlogged. And when the season for strawberries has ended, be prepared to move on to the next variety on the market. The following recipes, for strawberries, can be used with other berries.</p>
        <p>The Paris-Brest, a kind of giant cream puff, offers a variation on strawberry shortcake. It is a production number that takes time to prepare but the results are both impressive and delicious.</p>
        <p>The parfait, on the other hand, requires only a few minutes and, depending on the type of yogurt used, can be made totally fat free. Strawberry Paris-Brest</p>
        <p>Total time: 2 hours, plus cooling</p>
        <p>Small amount of butter and flour for preparing baking sheet  1 cup water  1/4 pound unsalted butter, in small pieces  1 teaspoon almond extract  3/4 cup sugar  3/4 cup flour  1/2 cup finely ground blanched almonds  4 large eggs, at room temperature  1/4 cup water  1 cup heavy cream  2 to 2 1/2 pints ripe strawberries, hulled</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 375 degrees. Lightly butter a baking sheet and dust it with flour. Mark a circle nine inches in diameter in the flour.</p>
        <p>2. Bring the water to a boil in a medium-sized saucepan. Add the butter, one-half teaspoon of the almond extract and 1 tablespoon of the sugar. When the butter has melted, lower the heat and add the flour and ground almonds all at once, stirring vigorously, until a smooth mass forms that leaves the sides of the pan. Continue beating over low heat a minute or so longer, until the mixture begins to film the bottom of the pan.</p>
        <p>3. Remove from heat and beat in the eggs one at a time, beating each until it has been thoroughly incorporated in the paste before adding the next. Beat until the mixture is smooth and glossy. If desired, the cooked water, butter, flour and almond mixture can be transferred to a food processor and the eggs added one at a time through the feed tube with the machine running, until a smooth, glossy mixture forms.</p>
        <p>4. Using a large spoon, drop high mounds of paste next to each other just inside the circle traced on the baking sheet, forming a ring 9 inches in diameter, about 2 inches wide and 2 inches high. Gently smooth the top with a knife dipped in water.</p>
        <p>5. Place in the oven and bake for one hour, until the ring is brown and there are no beads of moisture on the surface. Using a sharp knife, pierce the finished ring in several places along the side to allow steam to escape. Shut off the oven and return the ring to the oven for 20 minutes to dry. Transfer it to a rack and allow it to cool to room temperature. Place the rack on a sheet of foil.</p>
        <p>6. Mix one-half cup of the sugar with one-fourth cup of water in a skillet. Boil over medium-high heat, swirling the pan until the sugar dissolves, until the syrup becomes a rich honey color. Immediately dribble the caramel syrup over the top of the ring in an irregular pattern and allow the syrup to harden for 10 minutes.</p>
        <p>7. Carefully split the ring in half horizontally.</p>
        <p>8. Whip the cream until softly peaked. Add the remaining sugar and almond extract and whip until stiff. Spread half the whipped cream over the bottom half of the ring. Arrange the strawberries in a single layer on the cream. Top with the remaining whipped cream and cover with the top half of the ring. If desired, fill the center of the ring with more strawberries, and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings. Strawberry-Yogurt Parfaits</p>
        <p>Total time: 10 minutes</p>
        <p>1 pint ripe strawberries, hulled and halved  3 tablespoons light brown sugar  8 ounces plain whole milk or fat-free yogurt  Mint leaves for garnish.</p>
        <p>1. Place half the berry slices in each of four large stemmed goblets. Sprinkle each portion with a teaspoon of the sugar.</p>
        <p>2. Stir the yogurt to smooth it, then spoon all but one-fourth cup of it over the berries. Top with the remaining berries and a dollop of the remaining yogurt. Sprinkle with the remaining sugar and garnish each serving with a mint leaf.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.  FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
