<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nicole Elkon, Neal Wolin</title>
    <meta content="01ELKO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/06/01/fashion/weddings/01ELKO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1493349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELKON, NICOLE LOUISE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WOLIN, NEAL STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030601T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06EED81F31F932A35755C0A9659C8B63" item-length="405" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nicole Elkon, Neal Wolin</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Nicole Elkon, Neal Wolin</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nicole Louise Elkon and Neal Steven Wolin were married last evening in East Hampton, N.Y. Rabbi David J. Gelfand performed the ceremony at the Jewish Center of the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>Ms. Elkon, 35, is keeping her name. She was until February the chief of staff and the director of communications for the 9/11 United Services Group, an organization in New York that coordinates long-term assistance by 13 charities for victims of the September 11 attacks and their families. She was a special assistant and deputy director of scheduling to President Clinton from 1995 to 1997 and then was the director of planning until 1999 for the National Security Council. Ms. Elkon graduated from McGill University.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nicole Elkon, Neal Wolin Nicole Louise Elkon and Neal Steven Wolin were married last evening in East Hampton, N.Y. Rabbi David J. Gelfand performed the ceremony at the Jewish Center of the Hamptons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nicole Louise Elkon and Neal Steven Wolin were married last evening in East Hampton, N.Y. Rabbi David J. Gelfand performed the ceremony at the Jewish Center of the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>Ms. Elkon, 35, is keeping her name. She was until February the chief of staff and the director of communications for the 9/11 United Services Group, an organization in New York that coordinates long-term assistance by 13 charities for victims of the September 11 attacks and their families. She was a special assistant and deputy director of scheduling to President Clinton from 1995 to 1997 and then was the director of planning until 1999 for the National Security Council. Ms. Elkon graduated from McGill University.</p>
        <p>She is the daughter of Mimi Liebeskind and André Elkon, both of New York. Her father is a director for private-client investments at Oppenheimer &amp; Company, the New York financial services concern. Her mother is a consultant for the retail clothing and manufacturing industry in New York and is the president of the board of Business and Industry for the Arts in Education, an organization in New York that sponsors literacy programs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wolin, 41, is an executive vice president and the general counsel at the Hartford Financial Services Group, the insurance and financial services business in Hartford. He worked at the National Security Council from 1993 to 1995, first as the deputy legal adviser, and then as the executive assistant to the National Security Adviser. He was with the Treasury Department from 1995 until 2001, working as the deputy general counsel and then as the general counsel.</p>
        <p>A summa cum laude graduate of Yale, the bridegroom received a master's degree in development economics from Oxford University in England. Mr. Wolin also has a law degree from Yale. He is the son of Doris W. Wolin and Harry S. Wolin of Evanston, Ill. His mother is the director of Israel Experience, a program of the Jewish Federation of Metropolitan Chicago that assists young adults on trips to Israel. His father is a partner in Cohon, Raizes &amp; Regal, a Chicago law firm.</p>
        <p>Although the bride and bridegroom both worked in the White House during the Clinton administration, they did not meet until July 2001, when a mutual friend introduced them.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS/CELEBRATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
