<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>EASTERN COLLEGE REPORT</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="670485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DB113BF930A15751C0A962958260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>EASTERN COLLEGE REPORT</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>March Madness is just around the corner, and most schools have just two or three games left in the regular season. Here are the favorites and a few outside shots to win conference tournaments, with an automatic bid to the N.C.A.A. tournament on the line: Big East</p>
        <p>Although UConn (23-3 over all, 13-2 in the conference) will probably run away with the regular-season conference championship, 18th-ranked Syracuse has a good chance to improve its 17-5 record, since it plays Seton Hall at home tonight and St. John's Sunday at Madison Square Garden, then Miami next week.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>March Madness is just around the corner, and most schools have just two or three games left in the regular season. Here are the favorites and a few outside shots to win conference tournaments, with an automatic bid to the N.C.A.A. tournament on the line: Big East</p>
        <p>Although UConn (23-3 over all, 13-2 in the conference) will probably run away with the regular-season conference championship, 18th-ranked Syracuse has a good chance to improve its 17-5 record, since it plays Seton Hall at home tonight and St. John's Sunday at Madison Square Garden, then Miami next week.</p>
        <p>The Orangemen have two players -- junior forward Lawrence Moten and point guard Adrian Autry -- in the top seven scoring leaders for the Big East.</p>
        <p>"Our big guys have improved all season long," Coach Jim Boeheim said. "And Autry has been a great leader with the younger guys. Even when he wasn't scoring earlier in the year, he kept those guys in the game."</p>
        <p>An intense Big East matchup will be Georgetown-Syracuse next week. The winner could carry the momentum into the Big East tournament, which will be played March 10-13, but it is likely that both schools will get an invitation to the N.C.A.A. tournament, in addition to Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Seton Hall, however, is hoping for an N.I.T. bid. "We're up against the wall," Coach P. J. Carlesimo said. "The conference tournament is going to be important, but I think the next three games are more important. The N.C.A.A. committee weighs the regular-season games more heavily." Patriot League</p>
        <p>Fordham sits in first place for both men and women. For the men, Coach Nick Macarchuk has somehow lifted a team that is 12-13 over all to 9-4 in the conference, and the Rams hold a half-game lead over Colgate (8-5). Both schools, along with Holy Cross and Navy, have a shot to tie for first place in the regular-season standing. All tournament games will be played at Navy on March 4 and 5.</p>
        <p>Senior forward Sherwin Content has an outside shot at winning the Haggerty Award, which goes to the area's top player. Content averages 16.2 points and 7.8 rebounds. Northeast</p>
        <p>Rider (18-7, 14-3) clinched the regular-season title and the top-seeded spot for the tournament by beating Fairleigh Dickinson, 89-81, last night. But when conference tournament games begin Feb. 28, chances are that no clear favorite will emerge until the championship game March 6. There were eight teams playing .500 or better going into last night, and that includes conference play.</p>
        <p>F.D.U came into the Rider game tied for fourth place, but this team thinks it is better than that.</p>
        <p>"We feel we have underachieved, with all the hype at the beginning of the season and getting picked to finish No. 1," Assistant Coach Bob Holford said.</p>
        <p>The best player in the league is Marist's Izett Buchanan. The 6-foot-6-inch senior guard had 12 double-doubles in scoring and rebounds this season, and is ranked eighth nationally in scoring, averaging 25.8. The Red Foxes are one of those dangerous teams tied for fourth place that could get hot for a week and ruin Rider's league-leading season. M.A.A.C.</p>
        <p>Canisius (19-5, 10-2) beat Siena (19-6, 9-4) in overtime Monday to take a narrow lead in the Metro Atlantic Athletic Conference. But Manhattan (15-9, 8-4) and St. Peter's (14-11, 8-5) have shown all season that they are capable of beating the leaders and could shake things up in the conference tournament, March 4-7. All games will be played in the Knickerbocker Arena in Albany.</p>
        <p>Manhattan could advance in the tourney, but will need the fifth-year senior Carey Edwards to be ready. Edwards suffered a broken foot early this month after averaging 15.1 points to lead the Jaspers. He just started hobbling around without his crutches, so if he is ready in two weeks, he will probably be behind in conditioning. Ivy League</p>
        <p>Tired of watching Duke and North Carolina on TV? Want a great weekend of basketball? Then head to Princeton, N.J., or Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>No. 1 through 4 in the conference standing all play each other in an Ivy League showdown. On Friday, No. 1 Penn (19-2, 9-0) plays host to Yale (8-14, 5-5) and No. 2 Princeton (14-7, 7-2) is at home to Brown (11-11, 5-5).</p>
        <p>Then, on Saturday, Brown plays at Penn and Yale visits Princeton. These games are crucial because the Ivy League does not have a conference tournament, so the regular-season champion gets the automatic N.C.A.A. bid. Penn is favored -- the Quakers got 42 points in the A.P. poll this week -- but won't clinch the title outright unless it wins both games this weekend and Princeton loses both.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
