<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arts in America; A Visual Radio Show With Birds and Guilty Psychics</title>
    <meta content="19ARTS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1003194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">WBEZ-FM (Chicago)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Public Radio</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glass, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Belluck, Pam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02EED71139F93AA25750C0A96E958260" item-length="1249" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arts in America; A Visual Radio Show With Birds and Guilty Psychics</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Pam Belluck</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Belluck, Pam</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, March 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>This American Life, radio program produced by WBEZ-FM in Chicago and broadcast nationally on public radio network, is drawing rapt and sometimes enraptured following; hour-long program hosted by Ira Glass features concoction of true stories, audio art, monologues, fiction and found recordings--each piece carefully sculptured with music, almost like movies; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Chickens and turkeys,'' says Ira Glass, ''more than other animals, are a mirror of ourselves, of our desires, of our needs.''</p>
        <p>This, of course, makes no sense. But something in the way Mr. Glass says these words on the radio, something in his quizzical, confiding voice makes you buy in. ''When we tell stories about poultry, we are telling stories about ourselves.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Chickens and turkeys,'' says Ira Glass, ''more than other animals, are a mirror of ourselves, of our desires, of our needs.''</p>
        <p>This, of course, makes no sense. But something in the way Mr. Glass says these words on the radio, something in his quizzical, confiding voice makes you buy in. ''When we tell stories about poultry, we are telling stories about ourselves.''</p>
        <p>For the next hour on the air, the stories spin loose. This day the theme is ''Poultry Slam.'' The finger-puppet opera about Chicken Little -- in Italian. The guy whose family killed chickens by cutting off their heads. The Louisiana duck-hunting imbroglio. The woman who photographs a rooster as if it were Fabio.</p>
        <p>''If you spend enough time around chickens,'' Mr. Glass riffs earnestly, ''and you are a halfway empathetic or observant person, I think it's inevitable that at certain times in certain ways, the boundary between the human world and the chicken world will get blurred.''</p>
        <p>Rest assured, the radio show called ''This American Life'' is not devoted to edible birds each week. Most of the themes are more trenchant. Death, for example. Or near death. Or religion. Or Frank Sinatra.</p>
        <p>''The theme is just a McGuffin,'' Mr. Glass said, using Alfred Hitchcock's word for a disposable plot device that draws you in so you can discover the real point. ''It's anything we like.''</p>
        <p>So far, this hour, home-grown at Chicago's public radio station, WBEZ, and broadcast nationally at different times, is drawing a rapt, sometimes enraptured following. (In New York, it is broadcast at 11 A.M. Saturdays on WNYC-AM at 820.)</p>
        <p>People write in to say they have sat around the radio as if it were television. They talk about driving miles out of their way so they don't have to stop the car before the show ends. People have placed personal ads listing as one of their attributes that they listen to ''This American Life.''</p>
        <p>''I had to express to you the most ebullient gratitude for producing 'This American Life,' '' Jennifer Hart wrote from Kentucky. ''The gratitude I express is the same as is felt, perhaps, by someone lost and stranded somewhere in a deep wilderness when they spy a scrap of newspaper or a cigarette butt.''</p>
        <p>The show, which started just over two years ago, won a Peabody Award in its first year. Initially picked up by 9 stations when it went national in June 1996, it is now distributed to nearly 250 stations by Public Radio International. A couple of months ago, during one of the ritual fund-raising drives for WBEZ, normally worldly public radio listeners flooded phone lines with pledges when Mr. Glass offered to personally deliver pizza to every 10th caller. The show raised more in a single hour than ''All Things Considered'' did in two and a half hours.</p>
        <p>''It's a very visual radio show,'' said Gay Talese, who read his 1966 Esquire piece, ''Frank Sinatra has a Cold,'' for a Sinatra program that was typically counterintuitive, including a 1962 performance in which the singer croons marvelously but also makes racist jokes about Sammy Davis Jr. ''Here was radio in the 1990's in a way that hadn't been done in decades. Here I was getting sound television. It was very fulfilling.''</p>
        <p>''This American Life'' is an elastic concoction of true stories, audio art, monologues, fiction and found recordings, each piece carefully sculptured with music, almost like the movies. There is always a governing idea, sometimes a silly one, but usually some serrated slice of the relationships or situations people find themselves in.</p>
        <p>In ''Your Dream, My Nightmare,'' a black man and his white wife take a guided tour of a Tennessee plantation. In ''How to Get Money From Strangers,'' a writer becomes a telephone psychic and describes the guilt he feels as callers put faith in him.</p>
        <p>In ''Pray,'' an associate producer spends weeks with evangelists who try to convert her as she watches them pray to save souls all over Colorado Springs. And in this year's Valentine's Day show, a woman and her husband confront the fact that, years into their marriage, she has become obsessed with an old boyfriend.</p>
        <p>Some of the stories are the confessional idiosyncrasies of members of the show's staff or their friends. For a show about charting things in life that should not be quantified, an old college roommate of an associate producer was persuaded to talk about a flow chart she kept of her relationships with men. Mr. Glass has put his mother, Shirley Glass, a therapist in Baltimore, on the air for a show on parents' keeping secrets from their kids. (He had accidentally discovered she was considered an expert on sex.)</p>
        <p>''What do orphaned writers do for ideas?'' Sarah Vowell, a contributing editor, asked at one of the weekly story meetings.</p>
        <p>One might think this would make for a narrow, self-absorbed program, but avid listeners say it comes off quite the opposite, sounding somehow universal because the tales are intimately painted or pried open.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glass, whose owlish glasses and cropped hair make him look much younger than his 38 years, was a longtime National Public Radio reporter who conceived the show in part so work from people like David Sedaris, the neurotically satirical writer, could be showcased unabridged. From the WBEZ studio on Chicago's Navy Pier, jutting out into Lake Michigan, Mr. Glass, who tells a few of the stories himself and laces the others together with narrative comments, sounds intimate and amused on the air, as though he is sipping a cup of coffee during a very hip fireside chat.</p>
        <p>''Most of the voices sound like they shouldn't be on the radio,'' said Ms. Vowell, whose pieces included firing a cannon with her firearms-obsessed father. Her voice sounds like a petulant child's; she calls it a ''snotty 6-year-old.''</p>
        <p>''I feel we sound like human beings,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The casual cadence belies the excruciating care with which the show is produced. Mr. Glass spent years developing his style, and he writes out his words beforehand. In each story, he manipulates pauses so they underscore an arresting image.</p>
        <p>At a recent story meeting, Julie Snyder, an associate producer, talked about an idea someone had pitched about his father wanting him to become a mathematician.</p>
        <p>''The only amazing thing was that his dad told him math bedtime stories,'' Ms. Snyder said.</p>
        <p>''We could do a math show,'' Mr. Glass offered.</p>
        <p>''My math teacher told a great story once,'' said Nancy Updike, another associate producer. ''He was in Germany as a kid, playing ball. And a Jewish kid's ball goes into the German kids' court. He picks up the ball and takes it over to the fence and hands it to one of the Jewish guys. Years later, he reads that story in Henry Kissinger's memoirs. He handed the ball to Henry Kissinger!'' At least that was the story told.</p>
        <p>Paul Tough, another staff member, had a thought: ''We could do a whole show in which people tell stories in which the last line is, 'And that boy was Henry Kissinger.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
