<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making Books; One Publisher, Two Faces</title>
    <meta content="19BOOK$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980320T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1003199"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Disney, Walt, Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Random House</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arnold, Martin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eisner, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hiaasen, Carl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Making Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D61139F93AA25750C0A96E958260" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making Books; One Publisher, Two Faces</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Martin Arnold</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Arnold, Martin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Martin Arnold's column examines conflict at Random House, which is planning to publish a harsh critique of Walt Disney Co by Carl Hiaasen but is also publishing an acclamatory autobiography of Michael Eisner, Disney chief executive; Hiaasen piece is part of a new literary series, The Library of Contemporary Thought (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nerves jangled, and there was some consternation and even perhaps a moment of second thought when it recently dawned at Random House Inc. that one arm of the publishing company was about to trash Disney as a sinister force while another was preparing an acclamatory autobiography of Michael Eisner, Disney's chief.</p>
        <p>And although everyone denies it, this literary yin and yang didn't exactly please the Disney people, according to several people in the publishing world who are involved with the books. All spoke on condition of anonymity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nerves jangled, and there was some consternation and even perhaps a moment of second thought when it recently dawned at Random House Inc. that one arm of the publishing company was about to trash Disney as a sinister force while another was preparing an acclamatory autobiography of Michael Eisner, Disney's chief.</p>
        <p>And although everyone denies it, this literary yin and yang didn't exactly please the Disney people, according to several people in the publishing world who are involved with the books. All spoke on condition of anonymity.</p>
        <p>''Disney would at least have liked the Eisner book to come out first,'' one executive said. Another, at Random House, would only say, somewhat drolly, of the circumstances, ''That's fraught,'' leaving the ending to the imagination, since Disney is notably controlling and thin-skinned.</p>
        <p>The cause for the Disney angst and the publisher's brief trepidation is a particular book in a new series called ''The Library of Contemporary Thought'' that was introduced last month. The slender books, basically 15,000-word magazine articles, will be published, one each month, by Ballantine, a Random House Inc. publishing group.</p>
        <p>In production for May publication in the pamphlet-like series is ''Team Rodent: How Disney Devours the World,'' by Carl Hiaasen, the newspaper columnist and author of best-selling crime novels.</p>
        <p>The conflict arises, to the extent  there is one, because Random House is planning publication early next year of Mr. Eisner's autobiography/ memoir, written in collaboration with Tony Schwartz, whose previous books included Donald Trump's best-selling ''The Art of the Deal.''</p>
        <p>Ballantine's advance publicity blurb for the Hiaasen book describes it in this punchy way: ''With their recent takeover of Times Square, Disney has spread its power even further than before. In this controversial book, author Carl Hiaasen explores the absolute power of Disney, and how they are doing their best to destroy our culture and our ecology. Fans of The Mouse beware -- Hiaasen is taking him on and pulling no punches!''</p>
        <p>Fighting words for even the wimpiest Mouseketeer. Indeed, one wonders if, in light of the rumors, Ballantine mightn't tone down the blurb a bit in the future.</p>
        <p>As for the book itself, Alberto Vitale, chairman and chief executive officer of Random House Inc., denied that Mr. Eisner or anyone at Disney had complained about the Hiaasen work, and said, ''It's a big place here, with lots of points of view. I'm comfortable with the two books.''</p>
        <p>Random House Inc. has four publishing groups, and each group has its own imprints, so it is sometimes difficult for each to know what the others are doing.</p>
        <p>''This is a strength of Random House, to let the chips fall where they may,'' one of its editors said. Mr. Vitale did, however, cancel a book scheduled by Crown, a Random House imprint, that parodied one of Crown's most profitable authors, Martha Stewart, saying he ''certainly didn't feel obligated to publish a book knocking one of our money authors.''</p>
        <p>John Dreyer, the Walt Disney Company's corporate spokesman, also cited the range of viewpoints at a large publishing company like Random House. He, too, denied that anyone at Disney was crabby about the Hiaasen book. Nonetheless, several people in publishing said that Mr. Eisner definitely wanted his autobiography published first, before the Hiaasen attack.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hiaasen said ''everything I heard filtered down, is second hand, that they might not be thrilled.''</p>
        <p>No one is claiming that this new series will be as influential as, say, the Federalist papers, or as biting as Addison and Steele, but Linda Grey, who heads Ballantine, said that the projected ''books are part of the cultural exchange of the country,'' which would make them pretty weighty indeed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hiaasen is one of 11 authors, including former President Jimmy Carter, who have been signed up so far to write for the series. Each writer received a $100,000 advance against royalties, and each title is scheduled to have a 75,000-copy first printing, and to sell for between $7.95 and $9.95. The books are, in fact, longer than most magazine articles, although The New Yorker has summoned its readers occasionally to make the sacrifice of reading some really long magazine pieces, for which its writers do not receive $100,000.</p>
        <p>The first book in the series, Vincent Bugliosi's ''No Island of Sanity: Paula Jones v. Bill Clinton -- The Supreme Court on Trial,'' was yanked out of its scheduled order for April and was rushed into bookstores to ride the wave of Monica Lewinsky publicity; its first printing was upped to nearly 150,000 copies, with 140,000 shipped.</p>
        <p>So far, sales have been tepid. Next out will be John Feinstein's ''The First Coming: Tiger Woods -- Master or Martyr.'' The advance blurb promises a ''no punches pulled look'' at ''the ego and greed that surround this 21-year-old master.''</p>
        <p>Other authors signed on are Pete Hamill, Seymour M. Hersh, Anna Quindlen, Robert Hughes, Susan Isaacs, Robert Schlossberg and, writing together, William Sterling and Robert Waite. Ms. Grey said that the ''basic idea is for writers and other professionals'' to write on ''subjects that are meaningful to them.''</p>
        <p>''They fill a gap in the market place; there will be quickness and currency, but a potential to build a backlist,'' Ms. Grey said, adding that the books will be ''humorous, provocative and different.''</p>
        <p>''We've asked writers and others, 'What's on your mind?' and the response has been terrific,'' she said. As well it might be, with writers being paid $6.67 a word, or ''book book''-size advances for 15,000 words.</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 20, 1998, Friday  The Making Books column yesterday, about writers who have been signed up for a new Random House series, ''The Library of Contemporary Thought,'' misstated a given name. The writer is Edwin Schlossberg, not Robert.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 20, 1998, Friday</p>
        <p>The Making Books column yesterday, about writers who have been signed up for a new Random House series, ''The Library of Contemporary Thought,'' misstated a given name. The writer is Edwin Schlossberg, not Robert.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
