<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Defends Dismissals Of 3 Who Wore Blackface</title>
    <meta content="09BROA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/09/nyregion/09BROA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1455111"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fires and Firemen</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weiser, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Locurto, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steiner, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Walters, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sprizzo, John E (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor Day</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fires and Firefighters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Giuliani, Rudolph W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEEDE113EF93AA35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="694" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Defends Dismissals Of 3 Who Wore Blackface</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Giuliani Defends Dismissals of 3 Who Wore Blackface</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN WEISER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Weiser, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former New York City Mayor Rudolph Giuliani testifies in federal court in Manhattan about firings of police officer Joseph Locurto and firefighters Jonathan Walters and Robert Steiner, who are seeking reinstatement; they were dismissed following 1998 Labor Day parade in Broad Channel, Queens, in which they wore blackface; men contend their actions were entertainment protected by First Amendment and that firings violated their rights; their lawyers contend that Giuliani orchestrated firings by publicly commenting on incident to deflect past criticism for racial insensitivity; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani testified yesterday that as New York City mayor, he immediately called for the firing of a police officer and two firefighters for their participation in a racist 1998 Labor Day parade float because he feared the possibility of ''civil unrest leading to violence and riots.''</p>
        <p>''My response was that it was very offensive,'' Mr. Giuliani said, ''it was outrageous, and that it had the potential of causing serious disruption, civil unrest, and concerned me greatly.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani testified yesterday that as New York City mayor, he immediately called for the firing of a police officer and two firefighters for their participation in a racist 1998 Labor Day parade float becausehe feared the possibility of</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rudolph W. Giuliani testified yesterday that as New York City mayor, he immediately called for the firing of a police officer and two firefighters for their participation in a racist 1998 Labor Day parade float because he feared the possibility of ''civil unrest leading to violence and riots.''</p>
        <p>''My response was that it was very offensive,'' Mr. Giuliani said, ''it was outrageous, and that it had the potential of causing serious disruption, civil unrest, and concerned me greatly.''</p>
        <p>But the judge who is presiding over the trial in a lawsuit over the firings questioned the appropriateness of the mayor's quick condemnation of the men and suggested that his strong response had landed the matter in court.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani noted that the parade, in which the men wore blackface, took place in Broad Channel, Queens, not far from Howard Beach, the site of racial violence in 1986, and said that he wanted no uncertainty among the public about how he felt.</p>
        <p>''The reality is if you equivocate in circumstances like that,'' he said, ''that creates the opening for people to exploit and create unrest.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani was testifying in Federal District Court in Manhattan in a civil trial stemming from lawsuits filed by Joseph Locurto, the fired police officer, and the former firefighters, Jonathan Walters and Robert Steiner, who are all seeking reinstatement.</p>
        <p>After the parade, in which the men rode on a float titled ''Black to the Future: 2098,'' the mayor said of Mr. Locurto: ''The only way this guy gets back on the police force is if the Supreme Court of the United States tells us to put him back.''</p>
        <p>The men say that their actions were entertainment protected by the First Amendment, and that the firings violated their rights.</p>
        <p>Their lawyers also contend that Mr. Giuliani orchestrated the firings because he had been widely criticized for racial insensitivity, particularly in the Police Department's handling of the so-called Million Youth March in Harlem, just days before.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani denied that he had directed the firings or that he had acted because of any such controversy, and said that if the police and fire commissioners at the time, Howard Safir and Thomas Von Essen, had not agreed that the men should be fired after investigating the matter, they could have ruled the other way.</p>
        <p>But the judge, John E. Sprizzo, who is presiding over the trial without a jury, noted that the fire and police commissioners ''work for you and serve at your pleasure.''</p>
        <p>''You are the boss,'' the judge remarked at one point. ''You're No. 1, like President Bush is No. 1.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani replied, ''But I wasn't the boss of the disciplinary process,'' saying the commissioners had independence in such matters.</p>
        <p>Judge Sprizzo said, ''If that were truly your state of mind, the statements you made were really most improper.'' The judge also said that the mayor's remarks had political overtones. ''The statement was designed for public consumption,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani replied, ''It was designed to avoid disruption in the city.''</p>
        <p>But the judge again later questioned the remarks: ''You wanted to make the city feel you were on top of this situation, and would be very tough on it. If you had just gone weaker, you might have not had the political impact, but you would not be here. None of us would be here.''</p>
        <p>Later, Mr. Von Essen testified that he had originally concluded that what he called the firemen's ''horrible mistake'' did not warrant dismissal, ''but I didn't see the big picture.'' He later changed his mind, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
