<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In New Jersey, Abuse Issues Won't Go Away</title>
    <meta content="09FAMI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/09/nyregion/09FAMI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1455071"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Newark (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kocieniewski, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Faheem</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Abuse</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DE113EF93AA35752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="964" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In New Jersey, Abuse Issues Won't Go Away</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In New Jersey, Abuse Issues Won't Go Away</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID KOCIENIEWSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kocieniewski, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article reviews history of prior attempts to repair New Jersey's child welfare system following tragic death of Faheem Williams, whose emaciated body was found decomposing in Newark basement; system, like so many in other states, is underfunded, lacks coordination with other government agencies and garners little political support (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1996, the last time New Jersey's political leaders were shocked into overhauling the State Division of Youth and Family Services, elected officials promised to do everything possible to prevent the kind of wrenching child abuse deaths that the agency had too often been unable to avert.</p>
        <p>A child advocacy agency released a report documenting a system so overburdened that some caseworkers only investigated child abuse complaints involving broken bones, prompting Gov. Christie Whitman to impanel a commission to study the issue. The panel found that state social workers often failed to investigate abuse claims thoroughly or offer adequate protection to endangered children, and made nearly 400 recommendations to reduce caseloads, improve worker training and provide more oversight of child abuse investigations. Mrs. Whitman also committed $28 million in additional money to increase staffing, training and supervision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In 1996, the last time New Jersey's political leaders were shocked into overhauling the State Division of Youth and Family Services, elected officials promised to do everything possible to prevent the kind of wrenchingchild abuse deaths that the agency had too often been unable to avert.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In 1996, the last time New Jersey's political leaders were shocked into overhauling the State Division of Youth and Family Services, elected officials promised to do everything possible to prevent the kind of wrenching child abuse deaths that the agency had too often been unable to avert.</p>
        <p>A child advocacy agency released a report documenting a system so overburdened that some caseworkers only investigated child abuse complaints involving broken bones, prompting Gov. Christie Whitman to impanel a commission to study the issue. The panel found that state social workers often failed to investigate abuse claims thoroughly or offer adequate protection to endangered children, and made nearly 400 recommendations to reduce caseloads, improve worker training and provide more oversight of child abuse investigations. Mrs. Whitman also committed $28 million in additional money to increase staffing, training and supervision.</p>
        <p>Child welfare advocates say that the state has made only incremental progress in reducing case levels and monitoring investigations, and that the system remains so underfunded and poorly supervised that it simply cannot handle the crush of complex child abuse cases it now confronts.</p>
        <p>Many of the problems now faced by Youth and Family Services are common to child welfare agencies across the nation: sporadic financing; little coordination between social service providers and other government agencies that might help; and many dangerous and complex cases.</p>
        <p>New Jersey child welfare advocates also say that they face another problem: the state is so highly suburbanized that it is difficult to maintain sustained political support for social service programs that are considered urban issues.</p>
        <p>''Abused children, by definition, have no political clout,'' said Thomas Blatner, the former director of Youth and Family Services under Gov. Thomas H. Kean. ''In New Jersey, there is also a limited number of advocates for them, so you get an increase of funding after a crisis, but a waning of support once the crisis fades and there are other issues competing for state resources.''</p>
        <p>This week, an angry Gov. James E. McGreevey pledged to reform Youth and Family Services after the reports that state social workers had failed to investigate child abuse complaints at a home in northern Newark where three young boys had been chained and abused in the basement. The corpse of one child, Faheem Williams, 7, was found decomposing in a plastic storage bin. His two brothers were emaciated, but are now hospitalized and in stable condition.</p>
        <p>Mr. McGreevey has ordered caseworkers to visit every home where a child abuse claim has been reported, and he directed his commissioner of human services to deliver him a comprehensive plan to reorganize the child welfare system by tomorrow.</p>
        <p>The history of previous attempts to repair the system suggests that it will take a sustained and costly investment to address the systemic problems that have plagued the agency for decades.</p>
        <p>In 1982, after a series of child abuse deaths in Passaic County, Governor Kean ordered a major reorganization of the state's child welfare agency and increased the budget and staffing. As years passed and the crisis faded, however, the agency's financing was reduced and many of the programs atrophied.</p>
        <p>The report issued by Mrs. Whitman's panel in 1998 described a system in crisis: poorly paid, undertrained caseworkers given unmanageable caseloads; supervisors who provided little oversight; and unclear and inconsistent guidelines on how to evaluate the danger of any particular home and when a child should be removed.</p>
        <p>Governor Whitman devoted $28 million to creating nearly 500 new caseworker jobs during her second term. Charles Venti, who ran the department from 1998 until last year, said that those resources helped the agency conduct more thorough investigations and give workers more training.</p>
        <p>But Children's Rights Inc., a New York nonprofit group, sued the state in 1999, saying that the pace of the changes was too slow. Cecelia Zelkind, executive director of the Association of Children of New Jersey, said the agency was in such disarray before 1998 that it needed almost total rebuilding.</p>
        <p>''The word triage is appropriate,'' she said. ''The 1998 report found that the agency had been so starved for resources that the last few years have been spent trying to restore its foundation. The terrible death in Newark indicates that there is a whole new tier of problems that have not yet been addressed.''</p>
        <p>The most glaring shortcoming is the number of caseloads handled by Youth and Family Service employees, which often far exceed national standards. The state also lacks a computer tracking system to help caseworkers and supervisors monitor complaints and investigations, even though the federal government made financing available for such systems a decade ago.</p>
        <p>An assortment of embarrassing investigative failures by the agency raise questions about the thoroughness of the agency's investigations and the scrutiny offered by midlevel supervisors.</p>
        <p>The department had open files on 10 of the 27 children who died of abuse or neglect in 2001, and had closed case files on 6 others. Among those was a 7-year-old Hunterdon County boy who died of hypothermia in March 2001, after his adoptive parents punished him by forcing him to sit outside without a coat. Caseworkers had failed to investigate previous instances of abuse by the family, according to court testimony.</p>
        <p>The agency actually received a $12 million increase in 2001, to hire 66 new caseworkers. Last year, it received a $3.2 million increase.</p>
        <p>Although the state faces another budget shortfall this year, Mr. McGreevey will now be pressured to give a more substantial increase to the agency.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
