<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sadness and Anger After a Legend Is Mugged</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="709568"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBBERIES AND THEFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSAULTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">DETROIT (MICH)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PARKS, ROSA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BENNET, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Detroit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DA1738F932A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="1031" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sadness and Anger After a Legend Is Mugged</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BENNET,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BENNET, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Aug. 31</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Her face bruised and her lip swollen, Rosa Parks, the mother of the civil rights movement, seemed more sad than angry today as she quietly described being robbed and beaten in her bedroom here on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>"I regret very much that some of our people are in such a mental state that they would hurt and rob an older person," Mrs. Parks said as she sat in living room of her modest, rented home, five blocks from the boulevard named in her honor. "In these times, none of us seem to be safe from this type of treatment and violation by a sick-minded person."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Her face bruised and her lip swollen, Rosa Parks, the mother of the civil rights movement, seemed more sad than angry today as she quietly described being robbed and beaten in her bedroom here on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>"I regret very much that some of our people are in such a mental state that they would hurt and rob an older person," Mrs. Parks said as she sat in living room of her modest, rented home, five blocks from the boulevard named in her honor. "In these times, none of us seem to be safe from this type of treatment and violation by a sick-minded person."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks, who is 81, said her assailant appeared not to recognize her, although she is known throughout the neighborhood. Indeed, her suspected attacker, who made off with less than $100, was known there, too.  Based on her description of the suspect, neighbors found and held the man for the police this afternoon.</p>
        <p>Deputy Chief Benny Napoleon said the name of the suspect, who is 28, would not be released until he was charged, probably on Thursday morning. The suspect is likely to be charged with breaking and entering, and assault and battery.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks urged people not to read too much into the attack. But inevitably, she reflected on how things had changed since 1955, when she sat down on a Montgomery, Ala., bus and in her soft but firm voice said she would not yield her seat to a white man, setting off a 381-day bus boycott and a revolution against Jim Crow law. 'Still Have a Long Way to Go'</p>
        <p>"Many gains have been made," she said, her hands folded in her lap and her hair crossed in two silver braids over her head. "But as you can see, at this time we still have a long way to go and so many of our children are going astray."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks's neighbors, who said they viewed her not as a celebrity but as a communal grandmother -- a source of warm greetings and birthday cards -- took a less compassionate tone. To many, the attack was particularly galling because it was apparently committed by a black man.</p>
        <p>"For her to have been a legend, to have paved the way for our race, and yet, the same young man who beat her, she struggled to better his own life," said James Foster, a 70-year-old neighbor. "It's outrageous."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks said the attack left her fearful for the first time on the tidy, West Side block where she has lived for six years.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks's lawyer, Gregory J. Reed, said she would spend the night in a temporary room in a gated, guarded apartment complex downtown, then move into an apartment there when one becomes available.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks moved to Detroit in 1957, after her role in the Montgomery bus boycott made it impossible for her to find work there, Mr. Reed said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks continued working as a seamstress, then joined the staff of Representative John Conyers Jr., Democrat of Michigan, in 1965, retiring in 1988, said her executive assistant, Elaine Steele. Her husband, Raymond, died in 1979. In the 80's, Mrs. Parks founded the Rosa and Raymond Parks Institute for Self Development to help the city's children. Mayor Is Outraged</p>
        <p>In a statement from Martha's Vineyard, where he is vacationing, Mayor Dennis W. Archer said: "I personally and deeply resent any of our citizens' being assaulted and becoming victims of crime. It is more insulting when Rosa Parks, who sat down to give us an equal opportunity to compete, becomes a victim of crime in her own home."</p>
        <p>Several of Mrs. Parks's neighbors worried that news of the attack would further damage Detroit's tattered reputation, just as the first signs of a turnaround are appearing. "We're starting to change, and this is just going to drag us down," Derek Shirley, 26 said. "For something to happen to a lady that did so much for the black cause -- that ain't right."</p>
        <p>Some of Mrs. Parks's neighbors caught the suspect at a nearby grocery and liquor story. "Apparently they know this guy from the neighborhood," Deputy Chief Napoleon said. He said he did not know if the man, who is suspected in two other burglaries, was roughed up.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks said that as she prepared for bed on Tuesday evening, she heard a loud noise downstairs, and then a man calling out. When she came down, the man told her that someone had broken in her back door, but he had chased him away. Mrs. Parks has a security system, but it was disconnected after malfunctioning last year, Ms. Steele said. What the Intruder Said</p>
        <p>"He wanted to protect me, is what he said, and he wanted me to give him some money," Mrs. Parks said. He asked for three or four dollars, then followed Mrs. Parks upstairs as she went to get it. Once in her bedroom, however, the man, whom Mrs. Parks said reeked of alcohol, demanded all her money. She resisted.</p>
        <p>"That's when he started pushing me around and hitting me," she said. As she fell on her bed, trying to pull her money out of her pocket, the man continued to strike her in the face.</p>
        <p>"I had never been hit in that manner in my life," she said. "I was screaming and trying to ask him not to hit me." Once she gave him her money, Mrs. Parks said, the man left.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks then phoned Ms. Steele, who lives across the street, and Ms. Steele called the police. The police took between 45 and 50 minutes to reach her home, a fact that infuriated some of her friends. In Need of Medical Help</p>
        <p>Deputy Chief Rudy Thomas said the attack "didn't receive priority one, when life endangerment is imminent." Instead, Mrs. Parks' more urgently needed medical attention, he said. He said the city's Emergency Medical Service responded within about 11 minutes of the 911 operator's call.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks was taken to Detroit Receiving Hospital, where she was treated for her bruises and released.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Parks said she had intended to move several months ago to the apartment complex, called Riverfront Apartments, because she was tired of going up and down stairs. But Mr. Reed said the complex had recently told her that they had no room. Today, the complex speedily arranged for the temporary room.</p>
        <p>Many of her neighbors saw her moving as an ominous sign. "We're going to lose her, right?" said Moses Miles, 64. "Anytime we can't protect our great leaders, we're in trouble."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
