<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>42-Story Rental Tower To Rise on 8th Avenue</title>
    <meta content="15REAL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/15/nyregion/15REAL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1440769"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Residential Real Estate"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Moinian Group</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garbarine, Rachelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Office Buildings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021115T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D81430F936A25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="769" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>42-Story Rental Tower To Rise on 8th Avenue</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">42-Story Rental Tower to Rise on 8th Avenue</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RACHELLE GARBARINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Garbarine, Rachelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Workers lay foundation for 42-story rental tower on east side of Eighth Avenue between 53rd and 54th Streets; project continues influx of apartment towers along avenue in West 40's and 50's; building, at 900 Eighth Avenue, is being developed by Moinian Group of Manhattan; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Workers are laying the foundation for a 42-story rental building that will fill the block on the east side of Eighth Avenue between 53rd and 54th Streets. The project continues the influx of apartment towers along the avenue in the West 40's and 50's.</p>
        <p>The building, at 900 Eighth Avenue, is being developed by the Moinian Group of Manhattan and will have 393 apartments. Also planned are a four-story, 550-car garage, which will replace a city-owned garage that once occupied the site, and 10,000 square feet of street-level stores.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Workers are laying the foundation for a 42-story rental building that will fill the block on the east side of Eighth Avenue between 53rd and 54th Streets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Workers are laying the foundation for a 42-story rental building that will fill the block on the east side of Eighth Avenue between 53rd and 54th Streets. The project continues the influx of apartment towers along the avenue in the West 40's and 50's.</p>
        <p>The building, at 900 Eighth Avenue, is being developed by the Moinian Group of Manhattan and will have 393 apartments. Also planned are a four-story, 550-car garage, which will replace a city-owned garage that once occupied the site, and 10,000 square feet of street-level stores.</p>
        <p>The building will join three rental buildings completed since 1997 on or near the corner of West 50th Street and Eighth Avenue, together totaling 945 apartments.</p>
        <p>There are other projects under way on Eighth Avenue or planned nearby. One is the Biltmore, a 51-story structure with 464 rental units that the Jack Parker Corporation and the Moinian Group are building at the northeast corner at 47th Street, next to the Biltmore Theater.</p>
        <p>Another developer, Harwood Properties, is in the early planning stages for a residential building on the southwest corner of 44th Street and Eighth Avenue that would include a garage for 436 cars.</p>
        <p>Under current zoning, a City Planning Department spokesman said, a 25-story, 241-apartment structure could be built on that site without any special permits. The developer, however, has indicated that he plans to seek permission for a structure of up to 28 stories, with 317 apartments.</p>
        <p>The development of the AOL Time Warner residential and office complex on the old New York Coliseum site to the north and the revival of 42nd Street to the south have bolstered developer interest in Eighth Avenue. The new residential towers sit where parking garages, X-rated movie houses and tenements had dotted the avenue, considered the dividing line between Times Square and Clinton.</p>
        <p>Joseph Moinian, chief executive of Moinian, said the potential of the once-seedy avenue factored into his decision in 1997 to buy the 900 Eighth Avenue site. He acquired it along with development rights from an abutting structure for $34 million from an earlier developer.</p>
        <p>In the intervening years, the Moinian Group ran the formerly city-owned garage while it sought financing and approvals for the apartment building. Because of the development rights, the building will be seven stories taller than zoning would have originally allowed. The developer also got a special permit from the city to build a garage as big as the old one.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moinian, like most other rental developers in or near the Eighth Avenue corridor, is building a so-called 80-20 project. In return for the developer's keeping 20 percent of the apartments affordable to low-  and moderate-income tenants, the city or state issues bonds to provide low-rate mortgages to developers, who are also eligible for, among other things, a 20-year tax abatement from the city.</p>
        <p>The Moinian Group got $136.5 million from the New York State Housing Finance Agency and a letter of credit from KeyBank, said Richard Bassuk, president of the Singer &amp; Bassuk Organization, a mortgage brokerage in Manhattan and the developer's financial adviser.</p>
        <p>Andrew S. Heiberger, president of Citi Habitats, a residential brokerage, said that rents had leveled off in the area and that vacant apartments were starting to accumulate. Average rents in buildings in the West 50's are $47 a square foot annually, or $2,662 monthly, for a typical 680-square-foot, one-bedroom, Mr. Heiberger said, with rents in the West 40's at 10 to 15 percent less.</p>
        <p>At the Biltmore, leasing is expected to start in February, said Kimberly Cafaro, a vice president at Jack Parker. The average rents for the studio to two-bedroom units are to be $1,900 to $3,900 a month.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moinian said rents at 900 Eighth Avenue, which is to be completed in early 2004, had not been set. The studio, one-  and two-bedroom apartments will have 600 to 1,200 square feet. Amenities planned at the building, designed by Frank Williams &amp; Partners Architects of Manhattan, include a health club and a fifth-floor landscaped terrace. HRH Construction is the project's construction manager.</p>
        <p>Residential Real Estate</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
