<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ANGOLA'S LEADER SEEMS THE VICTOR</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="561262"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHEATING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION RESULTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ANGOLA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOBLE, KENNETH B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOS SANTOS, JOSE EDUARDO (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAVIMBI, JONAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Angola</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cheating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D9133CF934A35753C1A964958260" item-length="531" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ANGOLA'S LEADER SEEMS THE VICTOR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH B. NOBLE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NOBLE, KENNETH B</byline>
      <dateline>LUANDA, Angola, Oct. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jose Eduardo dos Santos and his ruling party appear to have won Angola's first democratic elections, but electoral authorities announced today that they would withhold the official results pending a recount.</p>
        <p>The decision was made after complaints by Jonas Savimbi, the former rebel leader, that the elections last week were tainted by widespread cheating. He hinted that there could be a return to civil war, and there were signs that diplomats and others were trying to persuade Mr. Savimbi to accept defeat peacefully.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Jose Eduardo dos Santos and his ruling party appear to have won Angola's first democratic elections, but electoral authorities announced today that they would withhold the official results pending a recount.</p>
        <p>The decision was made after complaints by Jonas Savimbi, the former rebel leader, that the elections last week were tainted by widespread cheating. He hinted that there could be a return to civil war, and there were signs that diplomats and others were trying to persuade Mr. Savimbi to accept defeat peacefully.</p>
        <p>In interviews in recent days, many of the nearly 800 international observers here have expressed confidence in the integrity of the vote.  Ex-Rebel's Warning</p>
        <p>But a senior official for the rebel group, Abel Chivakuvuku, warned local authorities Monday not to publish final returns or they would "bear the responsibility for whatever happens next." Diplomats interpreted the comment as a threat that disorder would follow if the results were released today as planned.</p>
        <p>[ At the United Nations, the Security Council issued a late-night statement expressing "concern" at reports that Mr. Savimbi might refuse to accept defeat and that his generals had threatened to leave the newly formed unified Angolan Army.</p>
        <p>[ It decided to send a three-member delegation immediately to Angola to encourage the parties to respect the terms of the peace accord that paved the way for the elections. ]</p>
        <p>Efforts to negotiate directly with Mr. Savimbi have been frustrated, diplomats said. "We don't know if he's still here or has left for the bush," one remarked.</p>
        <p>He added that a number of diplomats, including Herman J. Cohen, the Assistant Secretary of State for African Affairs, had been trying with increasing urgency to reach Mr. Savimbi, to no avail.</p>
        <p>Mr. Savimbi's group, the National Union for the Total Independence of Angola, known as Unita, its Portuguese acronym, emerged from the bush in May 1991 after a cease-fire mediated by Portugal, and the party is struggling fitfully to convert itself from a guerrilla army into a political party. 'Trying to Bring Him Back'</p>
        <p>"We are trying to bring him back into the process," a senior Western diplomat said, adding, "If he does go back into the bush, he's poltically dead. The international community will isolate him."</p>
        <p>The need to negotiate with Mr. Savimbi has become all the more urgent since a group of senior Unita military officers announced Monday night that they were withdrawing their forces from Angola's unified army. Unofficial tallies released this morning by the National Electoral Council, with about 90 percent of the votes counted, showed Mr. Dos Santos with 50.9 percent of the vote in the Presidential contest and Mr. Savimbi polling 39.4 percent.</p>
        <p>Despite Mr. Dos Santos's 11-point margin, however, it was not clear whether he will keep the overall majority needed to avoid a run-off election.</p>
        <p>Rival opposition leaders were far behind. Holden Roberto, the leader of the National Front for the Liberation of Angola, one of three guerrilla movements that fought Portuguese rule, had 2.2 percent of the vote. The leader of a minor party, Louis dos Passos, received 1.39 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
