<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. SAID TO PLAN BOSNIA ULTIMATUM URGING AIR STRIKES</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="667692"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="CONFLICT IN THE BALKANS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EMBARGOES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABC-TV POLL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTH ATLANTIC TREATY ORGANIZATION (NATO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E5D61738F93AA35751C0A962958260" item-length="1257" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. SAID TO PLAN BOSNIA ULTIMATUM URGING AIR STRIKES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 8</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States will propose that NATO give the Bosnian Serbs a week to lift the siege of Sarajevo or face air strikes by allied planes on their artillery positions in the mountains surrounding the city, senior American and European officials said today.</p>
        <p>Pursuing a two-track strategy, drafted in response to the deadly attack on Sarajevo's main marketplace on Saturday, the Clinton Administration also wants to link the ultimatum to peace initiatives, the officials said. Mr. Clinton approved the package of military and diplomatic proposals on Monday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States will propose that NATO give the Bosnian Serbs a week to lift the siege of Sarajevo or face air strikes by allied planes on their artillery positions in the mountains surrounding the city, senior American and European officials said today.</p>
        <p>Pursuing a two-track strategy, drafted in response to the deadly attack on Sarajevo's main marketplace on Saturday, the Clinton Administration also wants to link the ultimatum to peace initiatives, the officials said. Mr. Clinton approved the package of military and diplomatic proposals on Monday night.</p>
        <p>The new military approach, which will be presented at a meeting of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization in Brussels on Wednesday, appears to have widespread support among the allies, but differences of approach remain, and its approval is not certain. Nor is it known whether the Bosnian Serbs or their Muslim foes would be prepared to comply with its terms. Poll Favors Bombing</p>
        <p>The Administration's plan represents Mr. Clinton's response to widespread calls for the United States to do something to help halt the carnage in Bosnia. An ABC-TV poll released today indicates that a majority of Americans favor bombing Bosnian Serb gun positions ringing Sarajevo, as long as America's allies take part in the attacks.</p>
        <p>Fifty-one senators, meanwhile, urged Mr. Clinton to ignore a United Nations arms embargo and unilaterally arm the Muslim-led Bosnian Government so it can better defend itself. "In our view, if the United States takes the first decisive step, our allies will follow," said a letter from the senators, led by Bob Dole of Kansas, the Republican leader, and Joseph I. Lieberman, Democrat of Connecticut.</p>
        <p>The Bosnian Serb leader, Radovan Karadzic, said today that any plane attacking Serbian forces would be shot down, the Belgrade-based Tanyug press agency reported. Two Aides Sent to Europe</p>
        <p>Seeking to demonstrate that he is also becoming active in reinvigorating the stalled Bosnian peace talks, Mr. Clinton ordered Peter Tarnoff, the Under Secretary of State for Political Affairs, and Charles E. Redman, the special envoy for Bosnia, to go to London, Paris and Bonn to offer fresh ideas for a peace agreement.</p>
        <p>Officials would not say what the new ideas are, but they insisted that the United States was still determined not to impose a settlement on the Bosnian Muslims. But still open is the question of whether the West is essentially asking the Bosnian Government to curb its military campaign to regain lost territory in exchange for Sarajevo's security.</p>
        <p>Under the American military proposal, NATO would give an ultimatum to the Bosnian Serbs, who have relentlessly attacked Sarajevo for months, to move their tanks and artillery 20 kilometers, or 12.5 miles, from the center of the city.</p>
        <p>The Bosnian Muslims, who Secretary of State Warren Christopher has called "the aggrieved party," would have the use of their own heavy weapons monitored by United Nations forces in and around Sarajevo.</p>
        <p>Seven days after the ultimatum goes into effect, heavy weapons of the Bosnian Serbs found within the restricted zone would be subject to bombing attacks, which would be carried out by American and other NATO planes in coordination with the peacekeeping troops. The plan also states that NATO could issue the ultimatum under existing United Nations authority and would not have to seek approval of the United Nations Security Council, where Russia would be able to use its veto.</p>
        <p>An early draft of the proposal, which was distributed to the NATO allies on Monday, included the deployment of advanced radar that could locate and relay sources of artillery fire.</p>
        <p>But that provision is now under review. American officials are concerned that deploying the radar would thrust NATO into a direct ground combat role in the Balkans. The radar equipment and the troops who would operate it would have to come from the United States, Britain, France or Germany.  Similar to French Plan</p>
        <p>The American plan is similar to a French plan that has been under discussion at NATO this week. Under the French plan, the Bosnian Serbs would have 10 days to withdraw their heavy weapons 30 kilometers, or 18.75 miles, from the center of Sarajevo. But a senior French official involved in the discussions said the two countries were essentially in agreement, and a senior United States official suggested that there might be some compromise on both the timing and the size of the restricted zone.</p>
        <p>France, which is the largest contributor of troops to the United Nations force in Bosnia, prefers a 10-day ultimatum to give as much defensive protection as possible to its troops, who protect the Sarajevo airport, in the event of retaliation against them.</p>
        <p>The French plan also states that NATO can approve the ultimatum in the absence of a new Security Council resolution.</p>
        <p>Indeed, a resolution adopted last spring designating Sarajevo as one of six protected "safe havens" in Bosnia authorizes air strikes if necessary to deter attacks against the safe areas and to protect the withdrawal of military and paramilitary units other than those of the Bosnian Government. Vote Must Be Unanimous</p>
        <p>Any vote on the ultimatum by the North Atlantic Council, the political arm of NATO, which is meeting in Brussels on Wednesday, must be unanimous, and there was still some opposition among NATO members.</p>
        <p>Canada's Foreign Minister, Andre Ouellet, said on Monday that air strikes could imperil the 2,000 Canadian soldiers in the United Nations peacekeeping mission in Bosnia, and lead to Serbian blockades of aid deliveries.</p>
        <p>The Greek Government spokesman, Evangelos Venizelos, said in Athens today that Greece opposed any armed intervention in the conflict.</p>
        <p>In remarks to reporters today, Mr. Christopher said the United States was poised to unveil some ideas for giving new life to the stalled peace talks.</p>
        <p>"You'll be hearing more about that from us in the next couple of days as some further steps unfold," Mr. Christopher said at a photo-taking session with Foreign Minister Manuel Tello of Mexico. Mr. Christopher added that the military and diplomatic steps were interlinked and advised the Bosnian Serbs to view American statements as evidence that the Administration was "proceeding on a determined course."  Vagueness Is Seen</p>
        <p>But French, British and Spanish officials today described Mr. Christopher as quite vague in talking about what the United States intends to do regarding the peace talks.</p>
        <p>"The Secretary keeps saying the United States doesn't want to put pressure on the Muslims, but I told him we have to get together and try to fix what kind of offer will satisfy the Muslims," said Javier Solana, the Spanish Foreign Minister, in a telephone interview from Spain. Spanish troops serve in the peacekeeping force in Bosnia. "We have to take advantage of this momentum and we are looking forward to the new American proposals, but so far we don't know what they will be," he said.</p>
        <p>If, as expected, the United States gets more involved in the peace talks, it will represent a further shift in policy toward Bosnia. Thus far, Washington has steadfastly refused to become identified with the current peace plan, which would partition Bosnia into enclaves for each of the three Bosnian factions.</p>
        <p>The Administration has also argued that any peace that is imposed on the Bosnian Government, which has vowed to fight on to regain lost territory, would be impossible to enforce and would unfairly punish the victims of aggression.</p>
        <p>CONFLICT IN THE BALKANS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
