<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bring On Devils, the Rangers Say, and for Good Reason</title>
    <meta content="13RANG$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HOCKEY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="901577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lapointe, Joe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E4DE1338F930A25752C0A961958260" item-length="898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bring On Devils, the Rangers Say, and for Good Reason</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lapointe, Joe</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Rangers defeat New Jersey Devils, 3-0; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers have a winning record against only one team in the Atlantic Division. But it's a pretty good team: the Devils, who fell last night by 3-0 at Madison Square Garden in the second meeting of the season between the two teams. In the first, the Rangers won by 6-1.</p>
        <p>''It's a funny league this year,'' said Colin Campbell, the Ranger coach. ''Funny things happen.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Rangers have a winning record against only one team in the Atlantic Division. But it's a pretty good team: the Devils, who fell last night by 3-0 at Madison Square Garden in the second meeting of the season between the two teams. In the first, the Rangers won by 6-1.</p>
        <p>''It's a funny league this year,'' said Colin Campbell, the Ranger coach. ''Funny things happen.''</p>
        <p>Wayne Gretzky helped break open a close and unfunny game by setting up two goals -- by Ulf Samuelsson and Luc Robitaille -- in the first three minutes of the third period. Mark Messier had given the Rangers a 1-0 lead in the first period with his 25th goal of the season, most on the team.</p>
        <p>Goalie Mike Richter stopped 33 shots -- maybe 10 of them dangerous -- to earn his third shutout of the season. Martin Brodeur, the Devils' goalie, gave up the three goals and was replaced midway through the third period by Mike Dunham.</p>
        <p>''They can play a pretty methodical, boring game,'' Richter said of the Devils. ''But they're always within striking distance.''</p>
        <p>Richter said the game had ''a level of caution'' but added, ''As slow as it was, I don't think it lacked intensity.''</p>
        <p>Brodeur, not Richter, will play in the All-Star Game on Saturday in San Jose, Calif. Along with Buffalo's Dominik Hasek, Brodeur will back up the Eastern Conference starter, John Vanbiesbrouck of Florida.</p>
        <p>Richter wishes he could be there too. In his last All-Star Game appearance, at the Garden in 1994, Richter was the most valuable player. He hasn't appeared in one since.</p>
        <p>''No two ways about it, I'd like to be selected,'' said Richter, who quickly added that he doesn't have anything against Brodeur. ''It's not like there are bad players going in my place.''</p>
        <p>Still, he labeled himself ''disappointed, especially after last year, when I had good stats but I was injured.''</p>
        <p>Richter's record is 21-10-3. He lost his previous game, a 4-3 decision against Tampa Bay on Wednesday night at the Garden. Before that, he was 14-0-2.</p>
        <p>Richter began the season with Team USA and was the most valuable player in the tournament as the Americans won the World Cup. But in his first 15 Ranger decisions, Richter was 6-9-1.</p>
        <p>Last night's result ended the Rangers' streak without a victory at three games and extended the Devils' such streak to four games. It also increased the Rangers' lead over the Devils to 5 points in the chase for third place in the Atlantic. The Rangers have played five more games.</p>
        <p>The Devils were 0 for 4 on the power play; the Rangers had no power plays. A team spokesman said it has been at least four and a half seasons since the Rangers went without a power play for a whole game.</p>
        <p>''We weren't really happy with our power play tonight,'' Campbell said, with wry humor. In recent games, the Rangers have frequently been asked if referees are punishing them for Messier's scathing denunciation of a referee on Jan. 2.</p>
        <p>The Rangers play once more before the All-Star Game break, tonight at the Garden against the Islanders. They will wear their new, dark jerseys featuring the head of the Statue of Liberty.</p>
        <p>Messier noted that the game ''will be our 48th game in 101 nights.''</p>
        <p>''That's a lot of hockey for a lot of reasons,'' he said. ''We got off to such a slow start, we've had to really bear down for the last month and a half.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers rookie Vladimir Vorobiev, on his first shift of his first game in the National Hockey League, assisted on Messier's goal. Vorobiev, called up from Binghamton late last week because of a kneeinjury to Aleksei Kovalev, fed the puck to Messier in the neutral zone. The captain picked up speed, raced down the right wing and fired a long, low wrist shot from the circle that beat Brodeur on the stick side at 3 minutes 18 seconds of the opening period. It was a shot Brodeur probably should have stopped. But it is also one of Messier's trickiest shots, one that has victimized many goalies as he fires from his off wing to the long side.</p>
        <p>Kovalev is out for the season because of a tear of the anterior cruciate ligament in his right knee. He is expected to undergo surgery soon and to be ready for next season.</p>
        <p>Samuelsson scored at 57 seconds of the third with a long wrister after joining the rush. Robitaille scored at 2:51 by finishing a rink-length rush and an exchange of passes with Gretzky.</p>
        <p>With the rugged left wing Darren Langdon back in the lineup for the first time in 14 games after recovering from a sprained right knee, Campbell used him in tandem with Shane Churla, another bruising wing, who plays the right side.</p>
        <p>Sometimes, they skated with Messier. At other times, they flanked Gretzky. The Rangers have become concerned lately that opponents have been roughing up Gretzky. But the only fight was between Eric Cairns, the large rookie defenseman for the Rangers, and Randy McKay, the veteran Devils forward. Cairns scored a multipunch decision.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
