<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nicaragua Rebels Agree to Start Disbanding Troops in Honduras</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="337344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NICARAGUA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HONDURAS</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHAMORRO, VIOLETA BARRIOS DE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">OBANDO Y BRAVO, MIGUEL (CARDINAL)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Honduras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Nicaragua</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Honduras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DB103BF937A15750C0A966958260" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nicaragua Rebels Agree to Start Disbanding Troops in Honduras</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Nicaraguan rebels agreed today to disband their forces in Honduras by April 20, five days before the inauguration of President-elect Violeta Barrios de Chamorro of Nicaragua.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Nicaraguan rebels agreed today to disband their forces in Honduras by April 20, five days before the inauguration of President-elect Violeta Barrios de Chamorro of Nicaragua.</p>
        <p>The Nicaraguan rebels agreed today to disband their forces in Honduras by April 20, five days before the inauguration of President-elect Violeta Barrios de Chamorro of Nicaragua.</p>
        <p>Miguel Cardinal Obando y Bravo, the Archbishop of Managua, announced the agreement in Tegucigalpa, Honduras, after a seven-hour negotiating session with contra leaders and representatives of Mrs. Chamorro.</p>
        <p>The United States-backed rebels had previously refused to demobilize before Nicaragua's Sandinista leadership ceded control of the army to the newly elected government. A communique issued at the end of the talks said the rebels agreed to compromise because Mrs. Chamorro's victory in the Feb. 25 election had ''established a process of democratization'' in Nicaragua.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, the estimated 10,000 Nicaraguan rebels in Honduras, where the main contra bases are located, would immediately begin leaving their bases to concentrate their forces in security zones in Nicaragua supervised by the United Nations. [''The Nicaraguan Resistance begins its return to Nicaragua today,''</p>
        <p>The Associated Press quoted a rebel negotiator, Oscar Sovalbarro, as saying. ''The process will culminate on April 20 with the goal of reincorporating its members into the civilian society.'']  Mrs. Chamorro's representatives promised to assume responsibility for the wounded contras and to establish a committee with contra representatives that would oversee the demobilization.</p>
        <p>Appeal for Aid Is Planned</p>
        <p>The new government would also appeal to international donors for humanitarian aid to the rebels who disband and their families.</p>
        <p>If the agreement is observed, it would mark the end of the rebels' nine-year war against the Sandinista Government, which has cost about 30,000 lives and stirred debate in the United States for much of the past decade. The Reagan Administration financed much of the contra effort.</p>
        <p>Bush Administration officials, who had joined Mrs. Chamorro in pressing the rebels to disband, expressed satisfaction with the announcement by Cardinal Obando y Bravo.</p>
        <p>''We think this is an important step forward,'' said Bernard W. Aronson, the Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs. ''We hope the United Nations will respond to make this process successful.''</p>
        <p>Guarding Contras' 'Dignity'</p>
        <p>''This is a remarkable achievement in terms of where the situation was a few days ago,'' said Crescencio S. Arcos, the American Ambassador to Honduras, who pushed the negotiations with President Rafael Leonardo Callejas of Honduras. ''We were able to preserve the sense of dignity,'' he said, referring to the contra leaders, ''which was the most difficult task.'' [President Daniel Ortega Saavedra said he fully supported an agreement to begin disbanding the rebels, Reuters reported. ''As President of Nicaragua, I fully support this accord,'' he told reporters at the airport in Managua. ''I believe it goes in the direction of achieving peace and eliminating the war that has caused so much suffering, so much harm to the Nicaraguan people.'']  Since Mrs. Chamorro's overwhelming election victory over President Ortega, Sandinista leaders have repeatedly warned that they could not guarantee a peaceful transition unless the contras disbanded first. The rebels said they would not lay down their arms unless the Sandinistas first demobilized.</p>
        <p>The standoff was a matter of pride as much as security. The Sandinistas declared that they had won the war against the contras; the rebels said Mrs. Chamorro's victory was largely the product of their efforts to force Managua to hold elections.</p>
        <p>The rebels agreed to disband after Mrs. Chamorro's negotiators assured them that the Sandinistas had guaranteed that she would be commander-in-chief of the armed forces and security apparatus and have the power to appoint the top officials of the Defense and Interior ministries.</p>
        <p>Chamorro's Pledges</p>
        <p>Mrs. Chamorro has pledged to end the military draft and to demobilize much of the army and police forces, which number about 60,000 men.</p>
        <p>She has pleaded with the contras to demobilize as a way of helping Nicaragua begin its healing process. The country's economy has been ravaged by two civil wars since 1977, when the Sandinistas began their insurrection against the regime of Gen. Anastasio Somoza Debayle.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
