<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trump's Castle Is Shifting To Publicly Held Company</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="860351"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRUMP'S CASTLE CASINO RESORT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TRUMP HOTELS &amp; CASINO RESORTS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUMP, DONALD J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E1DC1239F935A15755C0A960958260" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trump's Castle Is Shifting To Publicly Held Company</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Bloomberg Business News</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trump Hotels and Casino Resorts said yesterday that it had formally agreed to buy Trump's Castle Casino Resort in Atlantic City from Donald J. Trump for about $525 million.</p>
        <p>The transaction, which Mr. Trump planned earlier this year, will unite his four casinos in one publicly traded company. Trump Hotels owns the Trump Taj Mahal and Trump Plaza in Atlantic City, and the Trump Indiana riverboat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trump Hotels and Casino Resorts said yesterday that it had formally agreed to buy Trump's Castle Casino Resort in Atlantic City from Donald J. Trump for about $525 million.</p>
        <p>The transaction, which Mr. Trump planned earlier this year, will unite his four casinos in one publicly traded company. Trump Hotels owns the Trump Taj Mahal and Trump Plaza in Atlantic City, and the Trump Indiana riverboat.</p>
        <p>Atlantic City is a hot market, so he's getting a premium for his property," said Matthew Russo, a casino industry analyst at Sands Brothers &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>Trump's Castle is in the city's Marina district, north of the Boardwalk.</p>
        <p>Wall Street was not pleased with the deal, which would dilute current shareholders' stake in Trump Hotels. The company's shares fell $2.375 to close at $25.75 yesterday in heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>"It's definitely dilutive," said Marvin Roffman, a casino analyst at Roffman  Miller &amp; Associates in Philadelphia, of the transaction.</p>
        <p>Under the transaction, Trump Hotels will acquire the casino for equity interests in its limited partnership unit that are exchangeable into 5.84 million shares of its common stock, plus about $885,000 in cash. It will also assume about $314 million of Trump's Castle debt along with $38.7 million it paid earlier to repurchase another portion of Trump's Castle debt.</p>
        <p>In purchasing that debt, Trump Hotels acquired the exclusive right to buy the casino for a six-month period.</p>
        <p>The transaction will increase Mr. Trump's ownership, including warrants, to 40 percent from 29 percent of the company's outstanding shares, the company said.</p>
        <p>The company expected to save $10 million a year from acquiring Trump's Castle. That's on top of savings of $20 million annually from the sale by Mr. Trump of his Taj Mahal casino to the public company earlier this year, the company said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Russo said the combined properties would produce $500 million in cash flow in 1998. For 1996, excluding the addition of Trump's Castle, Mr. Russo expects the company to generate $285 million in cash flow.</p>
        <p>The transaction "makes sense because of the critical mass," Mr. Russo said, adding, "There is definitely some synergies in costs."</p>
        <p>Two weeks ago, Mr. Trump proposed to spend $175 million to add a hotel tower  to the casino and build a 430-foot yacht.</p>
        <p>The Trump announcement comes as other casino companies announce expansive plans for the Marina district. Mirage Resorts Inc., which is based in Las Vegas, Nev., and does not have an Atlantic City casino, is planning a complex of three casinos on 150 acres of vacant municipal land it was given by the city.</p>
        <p>Of the three casinos, Mirage plans to build one itself and jointly develop another with the Las Vegas-based Boyd Gaming Corporation. Circus Circus Enterprises Inc., also based in Las Vegas, will build and operate the third casino.</p>
        <p>The transaction, expected to close by Sept. 30, requires Trump Hotels shareholder approval.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
