<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FINANCIAL DEBATE DIVIDES DEMOCRATS AS ELECTIONS NEAR</title>
    <meta content="27DEMS$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1057403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981027T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E0DD133CF934A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1428" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FINANCIAL DEBATE DIVIDES DEMOCRATS AS ELECTIONS NEAR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Leading Democrats in Congress angrily accuse White House and Democratic National Committee of hurting House and Senate campaigns by husbanding resources to erase party's debt and to help Vice President Al Gore kick off Presidential campaign of 2000; accuse party officials of inadvertently discouraging loyalists from voting, and of dampening fund-raising efforts by making dire predictions that party could lose as much as 25 House seats; are particularly furious at national committee, saying it has fallen woefully short of past elections in financing efforts to help House and Senate candidates, especially at time when Republicans are in final days of most ambitious party-paid advertising campaign in any non-Presidential election year; Democratic Party has struggled to raise $11 million in highly publicized 'unity' program to help candidates in 1998, despite original goal of $18 million (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leading Democrats in Congress have angrily accused officials at the White House and the Democratic National Committee of hurting House and Senate campaigns by husbanding resources to erase the party's debt and help Vice President Al Gore kick off his own campaign in 2000.</p>
        <p>The Congressional Democrats also assert that top party officials are inadvertently discouraging party loyalists from voting, and are dampening fund-raising efforts, by making dire predictions that the party could lose as many as 25 House seats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leading Democrats in Congress have angrily accused officials at the White House and the Democratic National Committee of hurting House and Senate campaigns by husbanding resources to erase the party's debt and help Vice President Al Gore kick off his own campaign in 2000.</p>
        <p>The Congressional Democrats also assert that top party officials are inadvertently discouraging party loyalists from voting, and are dampening fund-raising efforts, by making dire predictions that the party could lose as many as 25 House seats.</p>
        <p>The finance chairman of the party's Congressional Campaign Committee, Representative Charles B. Rangel of Manhattan, was so incensed about the party's modest stated goals that he had this advice for the party chairman: ''Keep your money and shut up your mouth.''</p>
        <p>Officials on both sides of the argument say the feuding, only one week before Election Day, is a giant distraction at a time the party needs to stay focused on a common enemy, the Republicans, who are in the final days of the most ambitious party-paid advertising campaign in any non-Presidential election year.</p>
        <p>While rifts are common within both parties, the current schism among Democrats is unusually bitter. And it comes at a time when the usual stakes of an off-year election are even higher with the impeachment inquiry pending before Congress.</p>
        <p>Democratic lawmakers say they are particularly furious at the national committee, saying it has fallen woefully short of past elections in financing efforts to help House and Senate candidates. In fact, the Democratic Party has struggled to raise $11 million in a highly publicized ''Unity'' program to help candidates this year, despite an original goal of $18 million.</p>
        <p>And although the two organizations that help finance the party's candidates, the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee and the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee, wanted to divide the $11 million raised, the party took a third for itself. It was unclear how the party planned to spend that money, but it had a $15 million debt and has had to spend more than $12 million paying legal bills related to 1996 campaign finance investigations.</p>
        <p>Party officials said they did not have a precise figure of how much less the committees were taking in from the national party this year. But, as an example, in the last midterm election, in 1994, the party made a transfer of $2 million to the Congressional Campaign Committee. So far this year, the party has  transferred only $715,000 to the committee.</p>
        <p>Democrats in Congress are also angry that officials in the party have argued publicly that, given historical trends, anything less than a 25-seat loss for House Democrats would be a victory. Party officials said such remarks were intended to lower expectations so even large losses will not be interpreted as a referendum on whether President Clinton should be impeached.</p>
        <p>But officials at the Senatorial and Congressional committees complain that such talk is at odds with their own public predictions that the Democrats could pick up seats.</p>
        <p>In an interview today, Representative Rangel was unusually belligerent, saying he was outraged at recent public comments by Gov. Roy Romer of Colorado, the general chairman of the Democratic National Committee, that the party could lose many House seats.</p>
        <p>''Frankly, I don't know what the hell the D.N.C. does. Let him do what he has to do for the President,'' Mr. Rangel said of Mr. Romer. ''He's not entitled to an opinion of Congressional races. He's an appointee. It happens to all of us. You get on television and you become an expert.''</p>
        <p>Accusing the Democratic National Committee of being stingy, he said: ''Keep your money and shut up your mouth. What damn credibility has he got as Governor of Colorado? He just should shut up. He's a nice man, but he's not giving us any damn money.</p>
        <p>''Is it like the whole world is waiting to see what's going to happen in November based on the Governor's evaluation of Congressional seats?'' Mr. Rangel continued. ''Give me a break!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel was so infuriated that he upbraided Mr. Romer in a telephone conversation on Thursday. ''Rangel was exactly correct to call Romer on that,'' said Representative Martin Frost of Texas, chairman of the Democratic Congressional Campaign Committee. ''Romer is simply wrong. We're going to pick up seats.'' The party, Mr. Frost said, has been so starved for money that ''we told our candidates they couldn't rely on the national party coming in and helping them. They had to put it together themselves.''</p>
        <p>The Democratic National Committee has been so unhelpful, Mr. Frost added, that his own committee ''has taken the role that historically the D.N.C. would have filled in some areas.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Romer, in turn, accused the party's Democratic leaders of ''misplaced grousing.'' He said: ''We were $15 million in debt. We borrowed as much as our banks would loan us, to be honest about it.''</p>
        <p>Asked about Mr. Rangel's frustrations, Mr. Romer said: ''Charlie is concerned that when he is out motivating his troops he wants to say, 'We're going to win the majority back.' That's what you say when you're out there on the stump. But if I'm going to keep my credibility, I can't give you campaign rhetoric and say, 'That's my expectation.' I want them to win a majority. That's just a hard reach.''</p>
        <p>In all but one midterm election since the Civil War, the party of the President has lost ground in the House of Representatives, from 2 to 96 seats.</p>
        <p>Several House Democratic officials -- including backers of Representative Richard A. Gephardt of Missouri, the minority leader, who is considering running for President -- suggested that the White House was sitting on money so the party would be well-positioned to help Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Douglas Sosnik, a senior White House adviser, disputed that Mr. Clinton had been inattentive to the financial needs of candidates. ''The President has spent a tremendous amount of time fund-raising on behalf of House and Senate candidates for the past two years,'' he said. ''If you have any doubts, look up how many articles have been written about how much time he has spent going to fund-raisers.''</p>
        <p>Another top White House official said the Congressional Democrats were too demanding, and unrealistic. ''They're whining,'' said the official, who spoke on the condition of anonymity. ''Everybody wants more money, and they're just looking for someone to blame.''</p>
        <p>At the core of the clashes are competing interests at the highest levels of the Democratic Party. They are in some ways an escalation of strains from 1994 when Congressional Democrats accused Mr. Clinton of costing them control of the House, and 1996, when they said he did not do enough to help the party try to regain the House.</p>
        <p>''It's unfortunate that the leaders of the party can't get together and agree on a single approach to these last weeks,'' said Mark Mellman, a Democratic pollster whose clients include Mr. Gephardt and Senator Tom Daschle of South Dakota, the minority leader. ''All these committees are united in wanting to help Democrats. But the political imperatives work in different directions for different elements of the Democratic Party, whether you're talking about how money should be spent or how expectations should be set.''</p>
        <p>Several state Democratic leaders have also complained that they need more money, particularly since the Republican Party raised tens of millions of dollars more than the Democrats in this election.</p>
        <p>''It's never enough and we need more,'' said Art Torres, chairman of the California Democratic Party. ''My only frame of reference is '96. It was much more generous last time, but that was a Presidential year.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Torres added that he understood that ''it's really tough when you're in the middle of a campaign to make sure you take care of your party as well as the debt.''</p>
        <p>To compensate for the shortfall in fund-raising for the Unity program, the party took out a $3 million loan last month that was divided between the campaign committees. But on a conference call with Mr. Clinton last month, party officials said, Congressional Democrats asked for $8 million. Participating in the call, the officials said, were Mr. Gephardt, Mr. Daschle, Mr. Frost and Senator Bob Kerrey of Nebraska, the Senatorial Campaign Committee chairman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Romer said he had no apologies for not raising more money. ''We've pumped the well dry,'' he said.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Rangel was not impressed. ''He's a nice person,'' he said. ''When he's quiet.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
