<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Face Lift for Galleria in White Plains</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="520575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOPPING CENTERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GALLERIA AT WHITE PLAINS (NY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRENNER, ELSA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE5D71339F931A25757C0A964958260" item-length="1360" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Face Lift for Galleria in White Plains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELSA BRENNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRENNER, ELSA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LIKE many shopping centers of its vintage, the Galleria at White Plains has begun to show its years. The 880,000- square-foot enclosed mall in the heart of the city's urban downtown area is due for a face lifting, say its owners, who are planning to spend $8 million on the project.</p>
        <p>"Times change," said Gerald M. Cope, a Philadelphia architect who has been hired to design changes for the mall, which was completed in 1980. "The Galleria is looking a bit tired. It needs to be more contemporary, more upbeat." Most shopping centers, the architect said, need refurbishing every 10 or 12 years to keep pace with shifts in marketing and consumer trends.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LIKE many shopping centers of its vintage, the Galleria at White Plains has begun to show its years. The 880,000- square-foot enclosed mall in the heart of the city's urban downtown area is due for a face lifting, say its owners, who are planning to spend $8 million on the project.</p>
        <p>"Times change," said Gerald M. Cope, a Philadelphia architect who has been hired to design changes for the mall, which was completed in 1980. "The Galleria is looking a bit tired. It needs to be more contemporary, more upbeat." Most shopping centers, the architect said, need refurbishing every 10 or 12 years to keep pace with shifts in marketing and consumer trends.</p>
        <p>Last week the White Plains Common Council approved the first phase of plans to renovate the Galleria's entrance on Main Street, a project that is to begin within a month.</p>
        <p>Because the Galleria is a town center "in the true sense of the word and not standing in the middle of a field somewhere like a suburban mall," Mr. Cope said, his plans attempt to address two needs: to blend the design of the entranceway with the surrounding downtown area and at the same time adorn it with lanterns and display windows to call attention to the shops inside. Other Malls Announced</p>
        <p>Long-range plans call for renovation of another entrance on Grove Street, a new color scheme and fresh landscaping inside the mall, reglazing existing skylights to allow more natural light to shine through, new flooring throughout the mall and increased seating in the Food Court for the estimated 12,000 customers who visit the mall each day.</p>
        <p>The Galleria's face lifting coincides with recent announcements that developers of two proposed shopping centers in White Plains have finally received financing for their projects and are planning to begin construction this year. Developers for a third project are optimistic that their plans will proceed once financing is obtained.</p>
        <p>Although James L. Czech, president of the real estate investment and management group in Chicago that manages the Galleria, said the threat of competition posed by the new malls had not influenced his company's decision to revamp the shopping center, merchants here welcomed news of the renovation.</p>
        <p>"If they don't give this place a better look, it's going to go downhill, and we will lose our customers," said Atonio Calero, owner of the Hairstylist, a beauty salon that has been in the Galleria since it opened.  Making a Good First Impression</p>
        <p>"The mall is so old looking," said Daneen Harrison, a saleswoman at T-Shirts Plus. "It's so dark and boring compared to Danbury Fair Mall."</p>
        <p>Agreeing with the merchants, Mr. Cope said, "The whole architecture needs to be lighter and lacier, like a backdrop, so the stores can sparkle."</p>
        <p>"In malls, first impressions are terribly important," he added. "And shoppers today are very discerning."</p>
        <p>Despite competition from newer regional malls in Connecticut and New Jersey, and despite the impact of the recession, which has hit the retail sector of the economy especially hard, Mr. Czech, president of J.M.B. Retail Properties Corporation, said the Galleria maintained a 90 percent occupancy rate last year and its 150 stores have continued to average about $405 a square foot yearly in revenues.</p>
        <p>"That's a very healthy number," said Mr. Czech, whose company manages 93 malls in the United States. "The Galleria continues to be in the top five malls in the country" in terms of sales per square foot.</p>
        <p>"We read a lot about an economic downturn, and some tenants may not be thriving," he said. "But in general, sales at malls remain strong, despite the outside forces."</p>
        <p>Shopping centers, an expert in the field agreed, appear to be somewhat recession proof. "Malls aren't built in reference to a specific economic environment; they are in it for the long haul," said Donald L. Pendley, director of public relations for the International Council of Shopping Centers in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The trade council's research confirmed that stores in the 37,975 shopping centers nationwide fared better than other retail establishments in the last several years. Overall retail sales for the country, Mr. Pendley said, were 2 percent better last year than in 1990, whereas retail sales in shopping centers averaged 3.5 percent higher during the period.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, the difficult economic climate has, in at least one way, helped merchants in shopping centers. Renovations of existing malls are taking place at an unprecedented pace because developers, faced with the reduced availability of loans for commercial real estate, are finding it difficult to obtain money to build new centers, Mr. Pendley said.</p>
        <p>As more dollars are funneled back into aging malls and more emphasis is placed on the visual appeal of malls, retailers in shopping centers are reaping the benefits -- along with the landlord who usually gets a percentage of the sales after the tenant reaches a certain break-even point, Mr. Pendley said.  A Medium-to-Large Mall</p>
        <p>The Galleria, which is owned by Cadillac Fairview U.S., a Canadian-based consortium of pension funds, and J.M.B., is considered a medium-to-large mall. With its two anchor stores -- J. C. Penney and Abraham &amp; Straus -- it is slightly larger than the Stamford Town Center, which occupies 875,000 square feet, but smaller than the Danbury Fair Mall, which has 1.3 million square feet.</p>
        <p>The Galleria -- a mall where prices are generally in the upper-middle range -- has what Mr. Czech called "a broad-based appeal" for customers.</p>
        <p>Of the three other malls that developers are planning to build here, one would be what is known as a power mall, with competitively priced goods, and the others would be fashion malls selling more expensive merchandise than is generally offered at the Galleria.</p>
        <p>"If and when other malls come to White Plains," Mr. Czech said, "these renovations now will insure that we maintain the foothold and the type of customer base we have established here. I don't see us in competition." Other Malls Will be 'More Upscale'</p>
        <p>At the Athlete's Foot, a sporting-goods store in the Galleria, the assistant manager, Lisa Azimi, said she was not worried about the possibility that two fashion malls might move nearby.</p>
        <p>"The other malls are going to be more upscale," she said. "It's not a threat to us, because the average person from White Plains won't go over there to spend a couple of hundred dollars on a handbag. Those malls are going to be more for the Fifth Avenue types."</p>
        <p>In addition to revamping the entrances and redesigning the interior of the mall, the developer is sharing with the city the costs of upgrading parking lots serving the mall.</p>
        <p>The enclosed parking areas are owned by the city, which is responsible for maintaining and policing the area. The lots, with 2,815 metered parking spaces, are being repainted, and new lighting is being installed. The cost of the project is expected to be about $1.4 million. Parking Lot Crime Called Minuscule</p>
        <p>"In the last couple of years, the city has been combating a perception problem, that the parking area is not safe," said Kevin D. Fish, director of the White Plains Parking Authority.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Fish said the crime rate in the lots was minuscule, he said the city was nevertheless installing high-pressure sodium lighting and more signs, "so people feel better."</p>
        <p>With 50,000 cars using the lots each week, there is "only a car theft now and again, or maybe a car radio stolen," said Capt. James Harding of the White Plains Police Department. A Look Back to the 1970's</p>
        <p>As the plans moved ahead last week for the Galleria and the proposed shopping centers, Mayor Alfred Del Vecchio looked back to the late 1970's when leaders here were debating whether to tear down an old courthouse to allow the mall to be built in its place.</p>
        <p>"We decided then to take a decaying city center and revitalize it when other civic leaders were putting their malls on the outskirts of town," the Mayor said.</p>
        <p>"Without development, White Plains would have been history," he said, "just another garbage pail on the map, like what happened to too many other downtown areas."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
