<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peruvian Official Assails Pressure From U.S.</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="520682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUPS D'ETAT AND ATTEMPTED COUPS D'ETAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC
OPINION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PERU</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASH, NATHANIEL C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLACKER MILLER, AUGUSTINO (MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUJIMORI, ALBERTO (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Peru</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD9163AF931A25757C0A964958260" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peruvian Official Assails Pressure From U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASH, NATHANIEL C</byline>
      <dateline>LIMA, Peru, April 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In an interview before his departure for talks in Washington, Peru's Foreign Minister bitterly criticized the Bush Administration for putting pressure on other governments to isolate President Alberto Fujimori, who seized broad power last Sunday in what many people are calling a civil-military coup.</p>
        <p>The Foreign Minister, Augustino Blacker Miller, said in the interview late Friday night that Mr. Fujimori's action had wide popular support among Peruvians and wondered how the United States could be so "naive" as to lump Peru's situation with the military takeover in Haiti last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In an interview before his departure for talks in Washington, Peru's Foreign Minister bitterly criticized the Bush Administration for putting pressure on other governments to isolate President Alberto Fujimori, who seized broad power last Sunday in what many people are calling a civil-military coup.</p>
        <p>The Foreign Minister, Augustino Blacker Miller, said in the interview late Friday night that Mr. Fujimori's action had wide popular support among Peruvians and wondered how the United States could be so "naive" as to lump Peru's situation with the military takeover in Haiti last year.</p>
        <p>"We feel that if we have the support of the Peruvian population, eventually we will get the support of the world because the world cannot deny the fact that this is not a dictatorship when you have 90 percent of popular support," the Foreign Minister said.</p>
        <p>Late Sunday, President Fujimori dissolved Congress and the judiciary, arrested more than two dozen members of Congress and suspended the Constitution. He said the actions were necessary to confront severe challenges from Maoist Shining Path guerrillas and drug traffickers as his Government tries to address dire economic problems. He has promised to restore democracy and free elections under a new constitution.</p>
        <p>United States officials have condemned the move as a coup and cut off all but humanitarian aid to the Fujimori Government. On Friday President Bush said he would support submitting Peru to "outside pressure," including economic sanctions, to promote a return to democracy.</p>
        <p>Behind the United States pressure is concern that Mr. Fujimori's actions could set a dangerous precedent for other Latin countries at a time when the continent is enjoying broad democratic rule for the first time in decades.</p>
        <p>The Organization of American States on Monday is to hold an emergency meeting on the Peruvian situation. Mr. Blacker Miller is scheduled to present the Peru's case at the meeting.</p>
        <p>The Foreign Minister said he was encountering an intense effort by the United States to dissuade Latin and European Governments from showing any support for what he described as Mr. Fujimori's attempt to "create a real democracy in Peru."</p>
        <p>He added that strains in the relationship between Peru and the United States in recent months over anti-drug efforts prompted the Fujimori Government not to warn officials in Washington of its intention to seize broad powers.</p>
        <p>The Peruvian Foreign Minister traced strains in the relationship with Washington to the San Antonio summit meeting of seven countries on drugs in February, at which the United States pressured Lima to accept tougher drug interdiction measures.</p>
        <p>Since the takeover, those strains have only increased. The Assistant Secretary of State for Inter-American Affairs, Bernard W. Aronson, arrived in Lima the day Mr. Fujimori announced his seizure of power. Fuming, Mr. Aronson canceled a meeting with Mr. Fujimori and returned to Washington.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blacker Miller said that while every approach to the United States for help and understanding since the coup has been rebuffed, he has met with a more tolerant reception in Europe and Japan. "The reaction in Europe is, 'We believe you are confronting extraordinarily difficult odds in your fight to proceed with development and therefore we are not going to cry wolf until we see that you are not meeting your promises,' " he said.</p>
        <p>Tired, and obviously concerned about the outcome in Washington, the Peruvian Foreign Minister said the seizure of power early this week had been planned for more than two months.</p>
        <p>"When you are looking at things from the frying pan it is hard to believe that they could look any worse," he said. "When you are in the frying pan and others are holding the pan, you are the one who is burning, not they."</p>
        <p>Mr. Blacker Miller said that he had advised Mr. Fujimori earlier that if radical changes were not made soon the situation with terrorism, a stagnant economy and drug trafficking could get so bad that "we might have a real military coup by the end of the year."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
