<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>If You're Thinking of Living in: Bay Shore</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="520616"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BAY SHORE (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SENFT, BRET</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living In</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D61438F931A25757C0A964958260" item-length="1312" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>If You're Thinking of Living in: Bay Shore</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRET SENFT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SENFT, BRET</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BAY SHORE is a hamlet of wealth alongside poverty -- of mansions on the Great South Bay waterfront a mile from low-income housing. Like many Long Island communities, its downtown was hard hit in the early 1960's by the opening of nearby shopping malls.</p>
        <p>Residents say, however, that it offers quiet, well-kept streets, a respected school system and waterfront recreation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BAY SHORE is a hamlet of wealth alongside poverty -- of mansions on the Great South Bay waterfront a mile from low-income housing. Like many Long Island communities, its downtown was hard hit in the early 1960's by the opening of nearby shopping malls.</p>
        <p>Residents say, however, that it offers quiet, well-kept streets, a respected school system and waterfront recreation.</p>
        <p>To spur downtown business, the Town of Islip -- as an unincorporated area, Bay Shore is governed by and responsible to the town -- has created service roads and parking behind Main Street to ease traffic and rezoned downtown, reducing the commercial area and introducing residential. And a renewed popular spirit has helped stabilize the community.</p>
        <p>"Bay Shore is going to re-happen," said Ken Turrisi, an architect-developer and 10-year resident.</p>
        <p>Its history is rooted in large estates. John Mowbray bought most of what is now the eastern part of the hamlet from the Penataquit Indians in 1708. To the west, Stephen Van Courtlandt had built his Sagtikos Manor in 1692 in what is now West Bay Shore. Such large holdings were later subdivided, and housing developed on individual lots.</p>
        <p>"That's why, today, you go anywhere off Main Street and see seven, eight houses in a row, and none are the same," said John G. Pullis, president of the Bay Shore Historical Society.</p>
        <p>The community changed names several times: Penataquit to Sodom (briefly) to Mechanicsville. By the 1880's, it became Bay Shore, an apt description, and was a burgeoning resort town.</p>
        <p>After World War I, however, rail service expanded and its grand hotels and boarding homes declined as tourists went east to the Hamptons or took the steamboat to Fire Island (Fire Island ferries still operate off the foot of Maple Avenue).</p>
        <p>Energies shifted to entertainment and commerce. The Regent moviehouse opened on Main Street in 1915, as did a Vitagraph film studio on Fourth Avenue (its productions starred Fatty Arbuckle, Norma Tallmadge and Marie Dressler).  In 1926, the ornate Bay Shore Theater opened on West Main, with both vaudeville and movies. In the 40's and 50's, downtown had a Sear's, a Loeser's, a Friedman's and thriving smaller businesses.</p>
        <p>Manus H. O'Donnell, a 37-year resident and assistant school superintendent for personnel, recalled Main Street in the 50's: "Friday night was like Fifth Avenue on the Easter Parade. Really -- you had trouble moving along the sidewalks."</p>
        <p>But the early 1960's brought a huge mall to Sunrise Highway: the 857,000-square-foot South Shore (with Macy's and J. C. Penney), where a 400,000-square-foot expansion is planned.Businesses and major supermarkets followed.</p>
        <p>In the early 1970's, deinstitutionalized mental-health patients from nearby Central Islip and Pilgrim State Hospitals drifted to downtown; in 1977, Suffolk County's largest social-services center opened between Third and Fourth Avenues north of Main, providing welfare, Medicaid and parole programs.</p>
        <p>OLD hotels (converted to single-room-occupancy residences) and shabby apartments above stores filled with welfare clients and former patients. Drug traffic and prostitution increased downtown. But recent meetings between business leaders and town councilmen have led to legislation calling for phasing out S.R.O.'s and apartments above stores along Main Street by January 1997. The Chamber of Commerce has noted a tenfold increase in attendance at such meetings in the last two years.</p>
        <p>Away from the blighted downtown areas, housing prices range from $1 million-plus for waterfront estates to $150,000 for colonials around Southside Hospital and $125,000 for ranches and split-levels in northern and western sections, according to Lorraine Lovgren, owner of Century 21 on East Main Street and president of the Chamber of Commerce.</p>
        <p>There are 1,313 rental apartments, 312 units in co-ops and just one condominium, the 128-unit Windermere, with two tennis courts and an outdoor pool. Its prices range from $179,000 for a two-bedroom unit to $250,000 for a five-bedroom.</p>
        <p>Eric G. Ramsey Jr. Associates on West Main Street noted an increase in starter home sales. Although Ramsey specializes in waterfront properties, Mr. Ramsey said, "We're selling a lot of affordable housing in the $150,000 to $250,000 range."</p>
        <p>Robert and Anne Marie Virgilio moved from Islip soon after their wedding in 1990 to a two-bedroom colonial in the Brightwaters Farms section west of downtown. Mr. Virgilio, who works at the New York Stock Exchange, commutes from Babylon, where the Long Island Rail Road's diesel service changes to electric.</p>
        <p>"A lot of young families have bought into the area," he said. "During the summer, this is a great place to be. We have a boat. Docking in the town marina  [ with 503 slips, the largest on the South Shore ]  is tough to find, but you can get a slip at a private home."</p>
        <p>There are about 350 slips at four private marinas, said Frank Mina, the owner of Shoreline Marina, and "hundreds more" privately owned.</p>
        <p>Ervina Lew, a lifelong resident and writer who teaches in Brentwood, lives with her husband, Robert, in a high-ranch on Penataquit Point with a panoramic view of the bay. "The kids who grow up here, whether rich or poor, have the experience of knowing they are living in a microcosm of the real world," she said, and the waterfront "provides everyone with recreational opportunities usually reserved for the privileged."</p>
        <p>The school district has 4,500 students in seven buildings: Three primary (grades K-2), two intermediate (3-5), Bay Shore Middle School on Brook Avenue (6-8), and Bay Shore High School on Third Avenue (9-12). Busing assures a racially and economically balanced school population.  There is a dual Spanish/English language enrichment program taught to all K and first-grade children, reflecting the community's 12 percent (and growing) Hispanic population.</p>
        <p>THE high school has a marching band that has won major county and state awards, an orchestra, a theater program and a full complement of sports. In 1989, the school district was one of 139, out of a statewide total of 740, chosen for a pilot program for the state's Excellence and Accountability Program to improve quality through community involvement and curriculum development.</p>
        <p>St. Patrick's, a Roman Catholic elementary school on Main Street, offers K-8 education to the parish's 4,600 families.</p>
        <p>New development includes construction of 13 units for the elderly by Mr. Turrisi, the developer, on the long-condemned Baybright Hotel site; conversion of the Bay Shore Movie Theater (closed since 1981) to the Great South Bay Y.M.C.A., with a pool, weight training room, gym, and pre-school, and development of the old Regent moviehouse -- for years a porno theater -- to a first-run cinema, whose adjacent adult bookstore is to be replaced by a walkway to town-built parking.</p>
        <p>Main Street has, among other things, Muscles (a popular yogurt/fast food place), RSVP Tuxedos, Bay Shore Lighting and H.A. Kalt Boutique and Shoes, a local fixture since April 12, 1937. But most residents go to Sunrise Highway and its shopping complexes for goods and services. Fine waterfront restaurants include Porky &amp; Glenn's at 24 Cottage Avenue, Captain Bill's on Ocean Avenue and Harbor House on Maple Avenue at water's edge.</p>
        <p>Golf enthusiasts have three county and two town courses a short drive from Bay Shore.</p>
        <p>Since 1987, a Community Forum has guided member civic associations in addressing local issues, such as reviewing plans for the former Bay Shore Drive-In site (soon to be a nine-acre Home Depot Center, with 19 acres as housing for the elderly or partial commercial use), or organizing an antidrug, midnight vigil along Second Avenue.</p>
        <p>"It's empowerment of the people, working in harmony with the government, to bring about positive change in the community," said the forum president, Selwyn Powell.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
