<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bridge</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="720375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGE (CARD GAME)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUSCOTT, ALAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EFD7173FF937A15753C1A962958260" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bridge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TRUSCOTT, ALAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you are dummy and peek into a defender's hand, you lose rights: You may not point out an irregularity, or warn partner against leading from the wrong hand.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, there is a strong temptation to peek at both defenders' hands and in one circumstance it is easy. If you are playing bridge on the Imagination computer network, the three other players are miles away and the program shows dummy all 52 cards. That lets dummy have some fun instead of sitting in ignorant idleness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you are dummy and peek into a defender's hand, you lose rights: You may not point out an irregularity, or warn partner against leading from the wrong hand.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, there is a strong temptation to peek at both defenders' hands and in one circumstance it is easy. If you are playing bridge on the Imagination computer network, the three other players are miles away and the program shows dummy all 52 cards. That lets dummy have some fun instead of sitting in ignorant idleness.</p>
        <p>On the diagramed Imagination deal played recently, Richie Oshlag of Memphis was the dummy in four hearts and could see all four hands. He saw the need to play the ace of hearts and drop the king, and hoped that his partner, Dave Smith of Raleigh, N.C., would be equally perceptive looking at two hands. He was.</p>
        <p>The opening lead was a diamond, and South played low from dummy and ruffed East's queen. It was already probable that West held the heart king, based on a bidding inference: East's original pass marked him with at most 12 high-card points and probably fewer.</p>
        <p>The first trick indicated that East had begun with six high-card points in diamonds, and he was sure to have the ace or king of clubs. Why? Because West would have led an A-K combination in preference to a diamond from the jack. That gave East 9 or 10 points, and the guarded heart king was most unlikely.</p>
        <p>So South might well have played the heart ace at the second trick, collecting the king and earning applause. Instead he chose to postpone the issue, and led clubs twice. This allowed him to locate the club ace, and the winning play of the heart ace became clear.</p>
        <p>Following are winners of major regional titles in Kiamesha Lake, N.Y., Friday and Saturday:</p>
        <p>Stratified Open Pairs A, Charles Sharf of South Hempstead, L.I., and Joseph Byrnes of Lynbrook, L.I.</p>
        <p>B, Jan Cohen of Montville, N.J., and Bob Vogel of Upper Montclair, N.J.</p>
        <p>C, Geraldene Walker of Albany and Harvey Kevorkian of Bennington, Vt.</p>
        <p>Stratified Women's Pairs A and B, Carol Irelan and Joan Dziekanski of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>C, Nobuko Kono of Larchmont, N.Y., and Hiroku Iazu of Scarsdale, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Stratified Senior Pairs A, Natalie and Dan Hertz of Harrison, N.Y.</p>
        <p>B and C, Rodger Kelly of Pine Bush, N.Y.. and Ernest Wagner of Grahamsville, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Flighted Open Pairs A, Abe Pineles of Yardley, Pa., and Richard De Martino of Riverside, Conn.</p>
        <p>B, Ray Chang of Hackensack, N.J., and Jeffrey Lagarias of Summit, N.J.</p>
        <p>Stratified Senior Pairs A, Ruth Stober of Great Neck, L.I., and Lila Perlstein of Roslyn Heights, L.I.</p>
        <p>B, Leon Cohen of Monsey, N.Y., and Stanley Sternberg of Scarsdale, N.Y.</p>
        <p>C, Joan and Jerome Shifter of East Rockaway, L.I.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
