<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Diplomatic Mission on 5-Nation Africa Tour</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="720335"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">AFRICA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MALAWI</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">TALBOTT, STROBE (DEPUTY SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRENCH, HOWARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Malawi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Malawi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E6D9173FF937A15753C1A962958260" item-length="665" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Diplomatic Mission on 5-Nation Africa Tour</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD W. FRENCH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRENCH, HOWARD W</byline>
      <dateline>MZUZU, Malawi, Oct. 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With concern growing over possible violence in neighboring Mozambique, a senior American delegation visited this newly democratic country today as part of a five-nation African tour intended to improve peacekeeping on a continent scarred by civil wars and refugee crises.</p>
        <p>Officials said the mission, led by Deputy Secretary of State Strobe Talbott, was a departure for American diplomacy in Africa, where Washington has decided to increase military cooperation with the growing number of countries that have switched to multiparty democracy after decades of dictatorships.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With concern growing over possible violence in neighboring Mozambique, a senior American delegation visited this newly democratic country today as part of a five-nation African tour intended to improve peacekeeping on a continent scarred by civil wars and refugee crises.</p>
        <p>Officials said the mission, led by Deputy Secretary of State Strobe Talbott, was a departure for American diplomacy in Africa, where Washington has decided to increase military cooperation with the growing number of countries that have switched to multiparty democracy after decades of dictatorships.</p>
        <p>The effort, which centers on providing training, logistical, financial and intelligence aid to the newly democratic countries, is intended to encourage their efforts to contain conflicts in neighboring states. Officials say such conflicts threaten peace and economic development throughout the continent.</p>
        <p>"There is no shortage of African countries willing to take part in peacekeeping efforts," Mr. Talbott said in an interview. "But they also come forward to us and say, 'We are developing countries, we have the World Bank and I.M.F. looking over our shoulders, and we don't have the capacity to do it by ourselves.' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Talbott said that after civil wars in Somalia and Rwanda, where the United Nations sponsored peacekeeping and the United States provided airlift and other logistical support, Washington was studying the idea of providing C-137 transport planes to a regional organization of southern African countries to help them respond rapidly to crises.</p>
        <p>In addition to talks with political leaders in Zimbabwe and Malawi, Mr. Talbott has addressed groups of soldiers and officers, telling them that "as a result of the U.N.'s being overburdened, the international community is in danger of not being able to respond quickly enough to new crises when they occur."</p>
        <p>After visiting Malawi, Mr. Talbott's delegation will stop briefly in Zaire before going to Ghana and Ivory Coast.</p>
        <p>Ghana, which is head of the West African Economic Community, has played a lead role in mediation efforts in Liberia. Zimbabwe and Malawi have been among the most active African countries in peacekeeping efforts on the continent, playing significant roles in Somalia and Rwanda.</p>
        <p>In addition to Rwanda, and neighboring Burundi, where clashes have sent refugees streaming into Zaire, officials in Zimbabwe and Malawi expressed concern over the long civil wars in Liberia and Angola, and worsening political conditions in Africa's most populous country, Nigeria.</p>
        <p>But their deepest immediate concern is over the potential for renewed strife in Mozambique, where national elections to be held on Thursday and Friday may seal the end of 20 years of civil war. The conflict has created costly refugee crises and disrupted overland transportation throughout the region.</p>
        <p>Efforts to build a national army from the two warring sides have stalled badly, and diplomats have expressed concern over recent statements by Afonso Dhlakama, the former rebel leader, in which he has said that the only way his party can lose is if there is fraud.</p>
        <p>International observers, who believe that the governing Frelimo party is the strong favorite in the vote, say Mr. Dhlakama's statements are ominously reminiscent of Angola's rebel leaders, who resumed their civil war after they lost that country's first national elections.</p>
        <p>A further element of worry comes from the Association of Demobilized Soldiers, which represents 75,000 fighters from both the rebel and Government armies, and has warned of unrest if its members are not guaranteed jobs by "the politicians."</p>
        <p>"We cannot talk about peacekeeping until we have talked about the urgent situation on the ground in Mozambique," said Malawi's Foreign Minister, Edward Bwanali, shortly after meeting here with Mr. Talbott. "After the elections there is the chance that everything will turn out all right. That is our hope, but we fear there could also be a new tragedy."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
