<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="495107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D61631F93AA25751C1A967958260" item-length="565" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Shrinking G.M.</p>
        <p>G.M. said it would close 21 of its 125 assembly and parts-making plants in North America over the next few years, and eliminate 70,000 jobs, or nearly 18 percent of its employees in the U.S. and Canada.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Shrinking G.M.</p>
        <p>G.M. said it would close 21 of its 125 assembly and parts-making plants in North America over the next few years, and eliminate 70,000 jobs, or nearly 18 percent of its employees in the U.S. and Canada.  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>By not announcing which of two plants it would close, G.M. put the lives of 3,400 workers in Texas in limbo.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>G.M. singled out factories that make some of its slow-selling larger cars.  [ D4. ] Companies</p>
        <p>USAir could soon run the Trump shuttle, with an option to buy it after five years. It is reportedly close to signing an agreement under which Donald J. Trump would no longer be held personally responsible for some shuttle debt.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Frederick H. Joseph, former Drexel head, was censured by the Big Board and barred from association with member firms for two years.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Walt Disney and Jim Henson Productions said they had struck a deal for Disney to distribute 30 years' worth of Henson's Muppet programming on home video.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Ameritech said it planned to use attrition and layoffs to trim its work force by nearly 2,300, or 3 percent, over several years.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Digital Equipment told analysts it was facing a probable quarterly operating loss. The stock plunged $4.75.  [ D7. ]</p>
        <p>I.B.M. and Siemens said that together they had built the first prototype of a 64-megabit chip.  [ D7. ]</p>
        <p>The United Arab Emirates' airline said it would buy 14 Boeing 777 mid-sized jets, in a deal worth about $2 billion.  [ D3. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>Alan Greenspan gave Congress a bleak assessment of the economy, but he suggested that bad times would be over by election day.  [ A1. ]  Excerpts from the testimony.  [ D15. ]</p>
        <p>The liquidators of B.C.C.I. have tentatively agreed to place more than $100 million in a fund to assist two American banks that had been secretly owned by the bank.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>For a nationwide computer data "superhighway," a debate has erupted over whether the Government gave an unfair advantage to a joint venture of I.B.M. and MCI.  [ D7. ]</p>
        <p>Businesses plan to increase investments by 5.4 percent next year, the Government said, after cutting plant and equipment spending in 1991 for the first time in five years.  [ D15. ]</p>
        <p>A Connecticut insurer will sell the first long-term nursing-home policy to be co-sponsored by a state government.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>The French Government said it would form a high-technology conglomerate by combining Thomson Consumer Electronics and Thomson's semiconductor activities with the civilian activities of the state-owned Atomic Energy Commission.  [ D2. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Stocks closed mixed as blue chips rallied after some early weakness. The Dow rose 5.81, to 2,908.09.  [ D10. ]</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury notes and bonds fell on the Fed's apparent decision not to cut short-term rates again immediately.  [ D18. ]</p>
        <p>Cotton prices tumbled, with analysts citing sales by farmers and merchants.  [ D19. ]  The dollar settled mostly lower.  [ D19. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Westinghouse Credit nearly destroyed its parent by making reckless real estate loans. Talking Deals.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>With the Soviet turmoil, German banking shares should be hurt, but they're not. Market Place.  [ D10. ]</p>
        <p>R. J. Reynolds is about to embark on another multimillion-dollar ad and promotion campaign to reverse the sales slide of its largest cigarette brands. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D21. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
