<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Turkey Seeks Security Advantage In Region's New Ex-Soviet Nations</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="538864"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">TURKEY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">COMMONWEALTH OF INDEPENDENT STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BALKAN STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAMM, HENRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD1438F934A15755C0A964958260" item-length="581" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Turkey Seeks Security Advantage In Region's New Ex-Soviet Nations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HENRY KAMM,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KAMM, HENRY</byline>
      <dateline>ISTANBUL, Turkey, June 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The gathering of leaders of 11 nations of the Balkan Peninsula and the former Soviet Union was described this week by Turkish and other participants as a Turkish initiative to draw advantage from the collapse of Communism and its founder state.</p>
        <p>The meeting concluded Thursday with a declaration for economic cooperation and good neighborliness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The gathering of leaders of 11 nations of the Balkan Peninsula and the former Soviet Union was described this week by Turkish and other participants as a Turkish initiative to draw advantage from the collapse of Communism and its founder state.</p>
        <p>The meeting concluded Thursday with a declaration for economic cooperation and good neighborliness.</p>
        <p>Senior Turkish officials said in interviews granted on condition of anonymity that Turkey regarded the breakup of the adversary superpower on its eastern border as a boon for its security but not an unmixed blessing. They said the staid stability of the Soviet Union had been replaced by active and potential conflict that threatened to destabilize this region.</p>
        <p>The most heated confrontation pits Azerbaijan against Armenia over Armenia's threat to its neighbor's possession of Nagorno-Karabakh, a largely Armenian-inhabited enclave. A senior Foreign Ministry official said Turkey remained evenhanded despite Armenia's claims to the contrary and the fact that Azerbaijanis have ethnic and religious ties to Turks.  'Advisers' to Azerbaijanis</p>
        <p>But he conceded that Turkey was "not completely oblivious to the demands of Azerbaijan in the military field." He denied that Turkey provided arms but stressed that it had military attaches in Azerbaijan. Diplomatic definitions get "blurred," the official said, indicating that the attaches acted as "advisers" to the Azerbaijani forces.</p>
        <p>"There is a tilt in favor of Azerbaijan because Azerbaijan is right," he said. "It is the aggressed party."</p>
        <p>The official said Turkey was also feeling tremors from the instability and tensions in Georgia and Moldova and between Russia and Ukraine. He said the 11-nation conference represented an effort to create "an environment of security around us."</p>
        <p>"We are at an intersection of great regional events, including conflict and opposing tendencies in the new world order," he said. "The disintegration of Communism has brought a greater threat of Islamic fundamentalism."</p>
        <p>Since the crumbling of its empire early in this century, this nation of 58.5 million mainly Muslim people has built a republic that resolutely rejects a role for Islam outside the mosques, as part of a commitment to modernism and a Western orientation.</p>
        <p>The official said this orientation, which has strongly resisted the growing spread of Islam as a political force, has made Turkey a "role model" for the former Soviet republics in the Transcaucasus and Central Asian, now independent states. In addition to Azerbaijan, they are Uzbekistan, Turkmenistan, Kazakhstan and Kyrgyzstan.  With Turkey, they make up a vast, strategically vital region stretching from the Balkans to China's borders.</p>
        <p>"They are all Turkic people, speaking languages we understand," the official said. "We are like long-separated relatives rediscovering one another. It means a general enhancement of the position of Turkey. We were all alone; now there are five others."  Emulating the West</p>
        <p>In the Turkish view, this country serves as a model for the former Soviet nations because compared with them Turkey is modern, economically and militarily powerful, more advanced toward Western-style democracy and a component of the Western world, which the others want to emulate.</p>
        <p>"You went away on horseback and now come back on a plane," the senior diplomat said he was told by a Kyrgyzstan official who recalled the westward migration of Turkic people more than 1,000 years ago.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
