<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Summerall's Struggle With Alcohol</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="538958"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOLISM</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUMMERALL, PAT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SANDOMIR, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3D7103FF934A15755C0A964958260" item-length="762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Summerall's Struggle With Alcohol</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SANDOMIR, RICHARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Friends urged Pat Summerall to get help. So did his bosses and co-workers. But Summerall's need to confront the alcoholism that threatened his life and career was crystallized in a letter from his daughter.</p>
        <p>"She said, 'I'd always been proud we'd had the same last name, but now I can't say that.' " said Summerall, his eyes misty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Friends urged Pat Summerall to get help. So did his bosses and co-workers. But Summerall's need to confront the alcoholism that threatened his life and career was crystallized in a letter from his daughter.</p>
        <p>"She said, 'I'd always been proud we'd had the same last name, but now I can't say that.' " said Summerall, his eyes misty.</p>
        <p>He made the recollection yesterday in the lobby of a White Plains hotel, not far from the Westchester Country Club, where he will return to work today as an announcer for CBS at the Buick Classic golf tournament.</p>
        <p>"We've worked with Pat for a period of time as he's struggled with his problem with alcoholism," said Neal Pilson, the president of CBS Sports. "We've provided various levels of support. We were very pleased when he agreed to a course of treatment at the Betty Ford Center and we assured him that he could return to his work provided he successfully completed treatment. We were in close touch with the professionals at Betty Ford and continue to stay in touch."</p>
        <p>Summerall had not been on the air since April 12 at the Masters. He lacked the smoothness that characterizes his announcing style. He knew, and so did his superiors, that the drinking had to stop and he entered the Betty Ford Center in Palm Springs, Calif. He stayed 33 days, and returned to his home in Florida late last month. Hospitalized in 1990</p>
        <p>In late 1990 Summerall was hospitalized with a bleeding ulcer that was aggravated by a toxic combination of painkillers and alcohol. He vowed to give up the drinking that had become part of his life.</p>
        <p>"I had not had a drink for seven months after the hospital," he said. "Then I said, 'I'm fine.' " He resumed drinking. But it was no longer fun.</p>
        <p>From his days as a football player to his career in sportscasting, he loved being the last guy at the bar, telling the best stories, having the grandest time. Now, at the age of 62, he had to hide the drinking and deny the problem.</p>
        <p>"Drinking wasn't any fun when people weren't around," he said.</p>
        <p>Intervention by a circle of friends convinced him to head for the Betty Ford Center, where he lived in a dorm with 20 others, rose by 6 A.M., shared one copy of a newspaper with the other "inmates," as the patients called themselves, attended counseling sessions and lectures until 9:15 P.M. and had 15 minutes of phone time and one hour of TV weekly.</p>
        <p>Admitting his dependency was difficult. Tales From Treatment</p>
        <p>"I sat at meetings where you have to introduce yourself and say your problem," he said. "Some people never got the courage to say it. It was tough to say, 'I'm Pat and I'm an alcoholic.' "</p>
        <p>After a while, the other patients shed their interest in Summerall's renown. And he proved responsible enough to be named a "granny," or a go-between for complaints by patients against the clinic's staff.</p>
        <p>"After a while I became more aware of what alcohol did to me," he said, "and I wanted to live a hell of a lot longer."</p>
        <p>Summerall came around to a simple belief: "The person I was before doesn't work."</p>
        <p>He wrote a letter to his alcoholism, telling what he felt. He and his counselor also tried to connect his alcoholism to his childhood. He was raised by an aunt, an uncle and a grandmother and said "I didn't know my parents well enough to judge."</p>
        <p>"I'm not sure we made the link," he said. "I don't think my counselor felt he got to the bottom of it." Group Therapy Sessions</p>
        <p>Rehabilitation also included group therapy with Summerall's wife, Kathy, their two sons and one daughter.</p>
        <p>"In a group with my oldest son, the counselor asked me, 'When's the last time you said you loved your son?' I said, 'I can't remember.' Then he asked, 'When's the last time you hugged him?' I thought and said, 'When I got him out of the crib.' He said, 'Would you like to do it now?' I said, 'Yes.' "</p>
        <p>He said he left the Betty Ford Center not feeling the need to drink. On the bus to the airport for a flight home to Florida, a man asked, "Is CBS going to let you on the air when you sober up?"</p>
        <p>On the flight, a stewardess asked, "Would you like a drink?" Summerall said he took ice water.</p>
        <p>He attends at least two Alcoholics Anonymous meetings weekly. His memory has improved. He is answering the hundreds of letters that came to him. His drink of choice is diet soda. He's eager to work.</p>
        <p>"Do I feel an urge to drink now?" he said. "I feel guilty. I don't. I feel fortunate. At an A.A. meeting last week, a guy said to his wife, 'I don't want a drink, I just want to sit on a bar stool.' She asked for how long. He said, 'Two weeks.' "  TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
