<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-U.S. Envoy Says Yeltsin Misspoke on M.I.A.'s</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="538997"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VIETNAM WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MISSING IN ACTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRISONERS OF WAR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA (RUSSIAN REPUBLIC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">YELTSIN, BORIS N (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOON, MALCOLM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vietnam War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920627T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DE1130F934A15755C0A964958260" item-length="625" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-U.S. Envoy Says Yeltsin Misspoke on M.I.A.'s</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, June 26</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American co-chairman of the commission searching for missing Americans in Russia said today that President Boris N. Yeltsin "misspoke" when he said American prisoners of war might still be there.</p>
        <p>"It's clear to me that he misspoke, because we have found nobody here that will tell us that Mr. Yeltsin's information was correct based on solid information," Malcolm Toon, a former United States Ambassador to Moscow, told reporters here. "I think he was acting genuinely, but I think he misspoke."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American co-chairman of the commission searching for missing Americans in Russia said today that President Boris N. Yeltsin "misspoke" when he said American prisoners of war might still be there.</p>
        <p>"It's clear to me that he misspoke, because we have found nobody here that will tell us that Mr. Yeltsin's information was correct based on solid information," Malcolm Toon, a former United States Ambassador to Moscow, told reporters here. "I think he was acting genuinely, but I think he misspoke."</p>
        <p>Mr. Toon, the commission co-chairman, made his remarks as he ended a five-day mission prompted by comments the Russian President made as he flew to Washington for a state visit last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Toon's conclusion that Mr. Yeltsin misspoke supported previous responses from Moscow, Hanoi and Washington, where baffled officials insisted that no evidence had been found to support his assertion that Vietnam-era prisoners had been held in the Soviet Union. The commission is also looking into reports about prisoners from World War II and the Korean War.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin's comments prompted a flurry of questions and demands. A group of American and Soviet investigators rushed off to Pechora, in the heart of Siberia, to check out a vague report that an American named David Markin or Marken had been spotted in a labor camp.</p>
        <p>Mr. Toon said that no such person had been found and that although the investigation continues, "I think we're going to wind up with absolutely zero."</p>
        <p>He said the Russians had agreed to issue a statement within two weeks declaring unequivocally whether any Americans were still alive in the former Soviet Union. But after his meetings in Moscow, he said, "my gut feeling is that there's nobody alive under Russian control."</p>
        <p>Mr. Toon said a team of American investigators would remain in Moscow. He said that some of them had "intelligence backgrounds," and that the Russians were wary that their only purpose "was to get into their files." He said he had warned the investigators against any extra snooping. The Russian files, he added, were a "mess."</p>
        <p>He said Mr. Yeltsin "probably misunderstood some of the information that was given him" when he made his statement.</p>
        <p>In an interview with NBC during his flight to Washington last week, Mr. Yeltsin was asked if it was true that American prisoners of war from Vietnam had been transferred to the Soviet Union. He replied: "Our archives have shown that it is true. Some of them were transferred to the territory of the former U.S.S.R. and were kept in labor camps. We don't have complete data and can only surmise that some of them may still be alive."  No Evidence Found</p>
        <p>Bush Administration officials and members of the Senate Committee on P.O.W.-M.I.A. Affairs have maintained since Mr. Yeltsin made those remarks that they have seen no evidence to back up his statements.</p>
        <p>In a letter delivered to the committee on June 12 accompanying documents about American prisoners sent to the Soviet Union in World War II and Korea, Mr. Yeltsin wrote:</p>
        <p>"With respect to the U.S. citizens listed as missing in action in Vietnam and other countries in Southeast Asia, no data are yet available. We know only that several American soldiers who evaded fighting in Vietnam were clandestinely moved from the territory of Japan to the territory of the U.S.S.R. The records show that these Americans stayed in the U.S.S.R. for a short period of time and later went to various European countries."</p>
        <p>Russian archivists have said it may be years or even decades before archives from the Vietnam War are opened.</p>
        <p>Before leaving, Mr. Toon taped an appeal that will be broadcast nationwide on Sunday over Russian television asking for any information on missing Americans.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
