<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prices of Treasury Issues Plunge</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="390136"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOND PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GILPIN, KENNETH N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD163AF933A25753C1A966958260" item-length="973" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prices of Treasury Issues Plunge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GILPIN, KENNETH N</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Prices of Treasury securities plummeted and interest rates rose sharply yesterday, as market participants saw rising oil prices, a weaker dollar and a continuation of the Federal budget negotiations as strong reasons to sell securities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Prices of Treasury securities plummeted and interest rates rose sharply yesterday, as market participants saw rising oil prices, a weaker dollar and a continuation of the Federal budget negotiations as strong reasons to sell securities.</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities plummeted and interest rates rose sharply yesterday, as market participants saw rising oil prices, a weaker dollar and a continuation of the Federal budget negotiations as strong reasons to sell securities.</p>
        <p>''I was sort of at a loss to explain why people were buying so strongly on Friday, so I can't say that I'm surprised the market is getting killed right now,'' one trader of government bonds said. ''And even though we have given back half of the gains that were made in the last week or so, I wouldn't be a buyer here either, particularly of bonds. With the dollar and oil acting the way they are, that is not a good trade.''</p>
        <p>Traders and analysts said that auctions of seven-year Treasury notes and 30-year bonds issued by the Resolution Funding Corporation coming today and Thursday served as another impulse to unload positions.</p>
        <p>Difficult Auction Foreseen</p>
        <p>''With the dollar weak and confidence in Washington at a low ebb, it will be very difficult to auction seven-year and 30-year debt,'' said Ward McCarthy, a managing director at Stone &amp; McCarthy Research Associates, a Princeton, N.J., research concern. ''It will take more rate concessions to get these securities sold.''</p>
        <p>Late yesterday, the seven-year notes were offered on a when-issued basis at a price to yield 8.68 percent.</p>
        <p>As Mr. McCarthy suggested, reaction in the financial community to the latest twist in the Federal budget negotiations was decidedly negative. The only positive, dealers said, was that the agreements allow the Government to meet its debt obligations for the next two weeks, thereby avoiding default. However, market participants said they were not optimistic that the Oct. 19 deadline for producing a budget would be met.</p>
        <p>''As far as I'm concerned, Congress has moved us back to square one on the budget,'' another bond trader said.</p>
        <p>The Election Factor</p>
        <p>''Now we have a dozen different Congressional committees that are going to be participating in the budget process, and there is an election in about a month. I would be very surprised if anything gets done before the election. What they will probably go for is another agreement that pushes out a decision until the middle of November.''</p>
        <p>The Treasury, which would have had to postpone auctions of all securities had the budget agreement not been reached and the Federal debt ceiling not been raised, was able to hold its regular auction of three-month and six-month bills yesterday.</p>
        <p>At the auction, three-month bills were sold at an average discount rate of 7.19 percent, compared with an average rate of 7.18 percent at last week's sale.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, bids on the new six-month bills produced an average yield of 7.21 perccent, unchanged from a week ago.</p>
        <p>Secondary Rates Near 9%</p>
        <p>In the secondary market for Treasury securities, yesterday's selloff pushed long-term interest rates back up close to 9 percent.</p>
        <p>In late trading, the 8 3/4 percent 30-year bonds of 2020 were offered at a price of 97 27/32, down more than 1 1/2 points, or more than $15 for each $1,000 face amount of securities. That pushed the yield to 8.95 percent, up from 8.81 percent in overseas trading on Monday, when United States credit markets were closed.</p>
        <p>Treasury note prices were also pummeled.</p>
        <p>By late in the day, the 8 3/4 percent 10-year notes were offered at 99 21/ 32, down more than a point, to yield 8.80 percent.</p>
        <p>And traders of two-year notes, who said the budget agreement reached late Monday would likely delay any move by the Federal Reserve to lower short-term interest rates, pushed down the price of the 8 1/8 percent two-year notes by 6/32, to an offered price of 100 13/32, to yield 7.89 percent.</p>
        <p>New York Issues Slump</p>
        <p>In the secondary market for tax-exempt municipal bonds, traders said the sharp selloff in Treasury issues as well as an announcement from the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation that it might lower its A- rating on outstanding New York City securities helped to push prices of the city's issues down by about 1/2 point.</p>
        <p>The announcement by the ratings agency came as no surprise. Less than a month ago, Standard &amp; Poor's issued a gloomy assessment of the city's economic and fiscal condition that coincided with New York's most recent public debt offering.</p>
        <p>Municipal bond traders said that the sharp downturn in Treasury issues helped to push down prices of most actively quoted municipal issues by 1/2 point to 3/4 point.</p>
        <p>Baltimore Gas Bonds</p>
        <p>In the investment-grade corporate bond market, the Baltimore Gas and Electric Company offered $200 million of five-year first mortgage bonds through an underwriting syndicate led by Salomon Brothers.</p>
        <p>The 9 1/8 percent bonds, which mature Oct. 15, 1995, were priced at $99.77 to yield 9.183 percent, 75 basis points, or hundredths of a percentage point, over the prevailing yield on the Treasury's 8 1/2 percent five-year notes at the time of pricing.</p>
        <p>The securities are rated A-1 by Moody's Investors Service and A+ by Standard &amp; Poor's.</p>
        <p>Following are the results of yesterday's auction of three-month and six-month Treasury bills:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>$</p>
        <p>3-Mo. Bills</p>
        <p>6-Mo. Bills</p>
        <p>Average Price</p>
        <p>98.183</p>
        <p>96.355</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>7.19%</p>
        <p>7.21%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>7.42%</p>
        <p>7.59%</p>
        <p>High Price</p>
        <p>98.198</p>
        <p>96.365</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>7.13%</p>
        <p>7.19%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>7.36%</p>
        <p>7.56%</p>
        <p>Low Price</p>
        <p>98.177</p>
        <p>96.350</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>7.21%</p>
        <p>7.22%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>7.45%</p>
        <p>7.60%</p>
        <p>Accepted at low price</p>
        <p>33%</p>
        <p>99%</p>
        <p>Total applied for</p>
        <p>$21,504,030</p>
        <p>$23,079,335</p>
        <p>Accepted</p>
        <p>$9,401,030</p>
        <p>$9,403,675</p>
        <p>N.Y. applied for</p>
        <p>$17,981,595</p>
        <p>$19,873,990</p>
        <p>N.Y. accepted</p>
        <p>$7,173,595</p>
        <p>$7,410,440</p>
        <p>Noncompetitive</p>
        <p>$1,759,625</p>
        <p>$1,430,460</p>
        <p>Both these issues are dated Oct. 11, 1990. The three-month bills mature Jan. 10, 1991 and the six-month bills, April 11, 1991.</p>
        <p>CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
