<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After the Louisiana Deluge, Players Find a Texas Toehold</title>
    <meta content="10twins" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/10/sports/10twins.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1700874"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D71331F933A2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="1062" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After the Louisiana Deluge, Players Find a Texas Toehold</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">After the Louisiana Deluge, Players Find a Texas Toehold</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Sept. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Jyrell Gaddies, a 16-year-old defensive back, enrolled at Eisenhower Senior High School here this week, he asked the football coach, Daryl Phipps, how many fans the home stadium could hold.</p>
        <p>''Twelve,'' Phipps said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two weeks after Jyrell and Tyrell Gaddies helped their high school in New Orleans win its opening game, they are set to play for a new school in Houston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Jyrell Gaddies, a 16-year-old defensive back, enrolled at Eisenhower Senior High School here this week, he asked the football coach, Daryl Phipps, how many fans the home stadium could hold.</p>
        <p>''Twelve,'' Phipps said.</p>
        <p>''Twelve hundred?'' Gaddies said, the awe evident in his voice.</p>
        <p>''No,'' Phipps responded. ''Twelve thousand.''</p>
        <p>With that, Gaddies and his twin brother, Tyrell, were officially welcomed to Texas high school football.</p>
        <p>Two weeks after the Gaddies twins helped John F. Kennedy Senior High School in New Orleans win their opening game, they stood in the Eisenhower weight room between third and fourth period on Friday, wearing their new black-and-gold jerseys for the first time. They checked themselves out in the mirror and nodded their approval. ''We're the Eagles now,'' said Tyrell, a 6-foot-2, 220-pound tight end. ''We used to be the Cougars. We've gone from the land to the air.''</p>
        <p>More precisely, they have gone from the Seventh Ward in New Orleans to a suburb north of Houston that has produced such National Football League standouts as Dante Hall and Aaron Glenn. Whether the Gaddies twins alter the competitive balance of football in the Aldine School District remains to be seen. For now, they are satisfied just to have lockers for the first time in their lives. ''It feels like we're in college,'' Tyrell said.</p>
        <p>Back in New Orleans, the twins were starting a high-school booster club to buy an ice machine and mats for the football team. At Eisenhower, they have free athletic tape, cleats without holes, and coats and ties for game days. ''All of this happened to us for a reason,'' said Jyrell, who, at 6-foot-1 and 168 pounds, is considerably smaller than his brother.</p>
        <p>When Eisenhower plays Saturday night at its home field, Thorne Stadium, the twins will be on the sideline. They can participate in practices, meetings and team meals, but they cannot play a varsity game until the district schedule starts Sept. 24. The University Interscholastic League, which oversees high school sports in Texas, requires that in-season transfers wait 15 days before being allowed to compete in varsity athletics.</p>
        <p>The league is trying to protect players who were dislocated by Hurricane Katrina from the intensity of Texas high school football. Charles Breithaupt, the league's director of athletics, said Friday that he had received several calls this week accusing coaches of recruiting hurricane victims, even contacting them at shelters. Although not one of the accusations has been confirmed, Breithaupt has warned coaches that they will be punished if they are found to be taking advantage of the situation. ''When we heard that coaches might be going to the Astrodome looking for players, we said we'd treat them like looters,'' Breithaupt said. ''That would be despicable behavior.''</p>
        <p>The Gaddies twins approached Eisenhower officials shortly after they moved into the area, where they were living with family friends, and asked to enroll for their junior year. Eisenhower, which has taken in 20 students from Louisiana and Mississippi, promised the new students that they could continue whatever extracurricular activities they had been participating in. One new student was a cheerleader at her high school in New Orleans, and she will be a cheerleader at Eisenhower.</p>
        <p>''This puts them right back where they were,'' said the Eisenhower principal, Alonzo Reynolds III.</p>
        <p>Nobody on campus has any idea how much the Gaddies twins will be able to contribute this season, or whether they will be able to help turn Eisenhower, now 0-2, into a contender. Phipps knows only the 100-yard times that the twins have reported and the positive first impression they have made on their peers. ''These kids can help us without even stepping on the field,'' Phipps said. ''They help just being able to share.''</p>
        <p>Students ask them to recount the story of their harrowing drive from New Orleans to Houston before Hurricane Katrina hit. Teammates ask them to bring Cajun food to school. Girls coo when they hear their accents. The Eisenhower quarterback, Freddie Brown, takes them to class if they're lost. And the voice of the school, a 17-year-old broadcaster and ordained minister named Vincent Powell, welcomes them with a televised message shown in every classroom.</p>
        <p>''I went off script for a minute because I got a little emotional,'' Powell said. ''I almost started to cry. It feels like the first day of school all over again. We're starting over. And there's nothing like starting over.''</p>
        <p>Though the high school football season in New Orleans has been canceled, it is just beginning in Texas. The Gaddies twins hope there will be no hard feelings if they pry starting positions from incumbent players. If they are relegated to the bench, they say, they won't care. ''If I block for other guys, if I back up other guys, that's great,'' Tyrell said. ''I'm just glad I have a home.''</p>
        <p>He has heard from fellow John F. Kennedy players who scattered to Atlanta, Baton Rouge, La., Mississippi and Alabama. Most have found new teams. A couple are still searching. ''If I get in touch with our running backs, I'm going to tell them to come over here,'' Jyrell said. ''Our team in New Orleans had real good running backs.''</p>
        <p>The twins used to talk about winning the Louisiana state championship. Now they talk about winning the Texas state championship. They used to dream about playing for the L.S.U. Tigers. Now they dream about playing for the Texas Longhorns.</p>
        <p>''I'm just dying to go to college in Texas,'' Jyrell said. ''In this state, football is crazy. The dudes are big. Whew, are they big.''</p>
        <p>The Gaddieses entered the weight room on Friday, determined to catch up. They lifted a couple of barbells beneath a sign that read: ''Eagles to the Dome.''</p>
        <p>For two 16-year-olds from the Seventh Ward, the Astrodome is no longer just a shelter. It is also a playoff site.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
