<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Balkan Presidents Meet In Ohio to Try to End War</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="806063"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CONFLICT IN THE BALKANS: THE OVERVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CROATIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DAYTON (OHIO)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA &amp; HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">EUROPEAN UNION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TUDJMAN, FRANJO (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILOSEVIC, SLOBODAN (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">IZETBEGOVIC, ALIJA (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLBROOKE, RICHARD C (ASST SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Croatia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Ohio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E3DA1639F931A35752C1A963958260" item-length="1246" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Balkan Presidents Meet In Ohio to Try to End War</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELAINE SCIOLINO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCIOLINO, ELAINE</byline>
      <dateline>DAYTON, Ohio, Nov. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Barely suppressing their mutual distaste, three Balkan Presidents came together today at an American military base for ambitious peace talks aimed at ending four years of terror and bloodshed in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>It was the first time the three men -- Slobodan Milosevic of Serbia, Alija Izetbegovic of Bosnia and Franjo Tudjman of Croatia -- have met face to face since they held a series of unsuccessful meetings in Yugoslavia in 1991 on the eve of the country's division and disintegration into war. Thus just bringing them into the same room represented a considerable achievement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Barely suppressing their mutual distaste, three Balkan Presidents came together today at an American military base for ambitious peace talks aimed at ending four years of terror and bloodshed in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>It was the first time the three men -- Slobodan Milosevic of Serbia, Alija Izetbegovic of Bosnia and Franjo Tudjman of Croatia -- have met face to face since they held a series of unsuccessful meetings in Yugoslavia in 1991 on the eve of the country's division and disintegration into war. Thus just bringing them into the same room represented a considerable achievement.</p>
        <p>But the basic questions that they failed to settle four years ago and that have since provoked Europe's worst conflict since World War II remain unresolved: Can Bosnia survive, and what degree of self-government should be given to the Serbian minority living within its borders?</p>
        <p>"We have an urgent and important purpose today," Secretary of State Warren Christopher said in opening the conference, which included representatives of France, Britain, Germany, Russia and the European Union. "We're here to give Bosnia and Herzegovina a chance to be a country at peace, not a killing field; a place where people can sleep in their homes, walk to work and worship in their churches, mosques and synagogues without fear of violence or death."</p>
        <p>The United States, which hopes to keep the negotiations shrouded in secrecy and the three Presidents away from the television cameras, did not allow them to speak at the opening ceremony or answer a reporter's question about the prospects for peace.</p>
        <p>And in a sign that the United States intends to control public disclosures about the talks, the State Department spokesman, Nicholas Burns, told reporters  tonight that Mr. Milosevic and Mr. Tudjman agreed in a separate meeting today to a positive joint statement.</p>
        <p>The statement, which Mr. Burns read aloud but did not release, declared their willingness to work toward full normalization of relations, including a mutual respect for human rights and the return of refugees, as well as the peaceful resolution of eastern Slavonia, a piece of Croatian territory that was seized by Serbs early in the war.</p>
        <p>There was an air of awkwardness in the antiseptic, fluorescent-lit meeting room in the Hope Hotel Conference Center, named after Bob Hope, and the body language of the three Balkan leaders as well as the choreography of the Americans revealed much more than the official statements.</p>
        <p>The main players -- including the three Presidents, the Europeans, Mr. Christopher and Richard C. Holbrooke, the chief American negotiator -- strode into the meeting room one by one. Each President was escorted into the room by the senior American diplomat serving in his country.</p>
        <p>That allowed Mr. Christopher to avoid having to shake the hand of Mr. Milosevic, whom the Bush Administration said should be tried on war crimes charges.</p>
        <p>But other handshakes were important to the American side today, and as soon as the group sat down around a small round table, Mr. Holbrooke gave Mr. Christopher a cue to rise, move toward the three Presidents, and nudge them into shaking hands with one another.</p>
        <p>For the most part during the open-ended peace talks, the three Presidents will not meet face to face, but will relay their negotiating positions to each other via Mr. Holbrooke.</p>
        <p>As the meeting opened on the 8,242-acre Wright-Patterson Air Force Base outside Dayton, about 100 demonstrators gathered outside the gates to protest Mr. Milosevic's presence and call for the independence of Kosovo, the province of Serbia populated mainly by ethnic Albanians.</p>
        <p>"We will not negotiate with the war criminal," one sign said. "Milosevic's place is in The Hague, not Dayton," another said, referring to the center of the international war crimes tribunal.</p>
        <p>Before the opening ceremony, Mr. Christopher conferred with the three Presidents in their personal quarters for about 45 minutes each.</p>
        <p>He brought Mr. Izetbegovic, whose country the United States considers the "victim" in the war, a personal message from President Clinton to assure him of  the American commitment to preserve the unity of the Bosnian state and strengthen its federation with Croatia, according to Mr. Burns. As for Mr. Tudjman, Mr. Christopher "congratulated" him on the results of parliamentary elections on Sunday, which his party won by a large enough margin  to keep a majority in Parliament.</p>
        <p>But human rights organizations and independent American election monitors have criticized the election because the Serbs of the Krajina region were banned from voting, but ethnic Croats living in Bosnia were allowed to vote. Even some  senior State Department officials said the United States should be protesting the results, not praising them .</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Milosevic, Mr. Christopher expressed "grave concern" about reported massacres of Bosnians by the Bosnian Serbs, particularly paramilitary groups, in Srebrenica and Banja Luka. Mr. Milosevic, who has been authorized by  the Bosnian Serb leaders to speak on their behalf during the peace talks, has always denied that he was involved in any massacres they have carried out or has any influence to stop them.</p>
        <p>Asked for Mr. Milosevic's assessment of the meeting with Mr. Christopher, a Serbian delegate said, "The President was satisfied."</p>
        <p>Mr. Christopher is said to distrust Mr. Milosevic and his intentions. The Secretary did, however, supported an unsuccessful move in the Administration last week to have the United Nations Security Council suspend most economic sanctions against Serbia during the the talks.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Christopher was asked during one of three back-to-back television interviews today whether there was any doubt that Mr. Milosevic was involved in  massacres last summer in Srebrenica, he sidestepped the issue, saying only that  the United States was spending more than any other country to support the war crimes tribunal in The Hague and that the issue of a potential indictment of Mr. Milosevic "is not our judgment to make."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Christopher also said NATO peacekeeping forces might not go into Bosnia if the two Bosnian Serb leaders indicted as war criminals were still in power.</p>
        <p>"We can't really expect that forces of NATO would be there at the same time those individuals were in positions of power," he said of Radovan Karadzic, the  Bosnian Serb leader, and Gen. Ratko Mladic, the military commander.</p>
        <p>The American side imposed a news blackout on all the parties except Mr. Christopher and Mr. Burns.</p>
        <p>Entering the conference hall, however, the Bosnian Foreign Minister, Muhamed  Sacirbey, said, "If it fails, it won't fail because of us."</p>
        <p>In an earlier interview, he laid out his country's position, including a demand that Mr. Milosevic deliver those indicted for war crimes to the tribunal.</p>
        <p>"You cannot speak of peace in Dayton and continue to have ethnic cleansing in Banja Luka," he paraphrased his President as telling Mr. Christopher.</p>
        <p>Mr. Holbrooke expects the peace talks to last about two weeks, although Carl  Bildt, the former Swedish Prime Minister who represents the European Union, believes that agreement could be reached within a week.</p>
        <p>CONFLICT IN THE BALKANS: THE OVERVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
