<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Faithfull Discovers a Rocker Within Weill</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="754404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROTHSTEIN, EDWARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAITHFULL, MARIANNE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDF1539F932A25757C0A963958260" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Faithfull Discovers a Rocker Within Weill</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD ROTHSTEIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROTHSTEIN, EDWARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The theme of last weekend's programming by the Brooklyn Philharmonic Orchestra at the Brooklyn Academy of Music was vaguely titled "Paradise Lost," promising to connect Mahler's paean to heaven in his Fourth Symphony, Kurt Weill's cabaret songs and a centennial celebration honoring Hindemith.</p>
        <p>But no one could fool the audience, which would have yawned at the prospects of extensive Hindemith, and which rightfully yawned on Friday night during a disjointed reading of the Mahler conducted by Dennis Russell Davies. Listeners really turned out in force because of the presence of Marianne Faithfull, a singer whose name invokes all the cliches that once attached to the triumvirate of sex, drugs and rock-and-roll. After surviving a series of addictions, suicide attempts and troubled liaisons, Ms. Faithfull has become a chanteuse of the post-counterculture years. The melancholic, bluesy ballads on her 1987 recording, "Strange Weather," have been described as "music to slit your wrists by," and its growly, disturbing presentation of songs of introspective suffering was a prelude to the singer's growing interest in Kurt Weill.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The theme of last weekend's programming by the Brooklyn Philharmonic Orchestra at the Brooklyn Academy of Music was vaguely titled "Paradise Lost," promising to connect Mahler's paean to heaven in his Fourth Symphony, Kurt Weill's cabaret songs and a centennial celebration honoring Hindemith.</p>
        <p>But no one could fool the audience, which would have yawned at the prospects of extensive Hindemith, and which rightfully yawned on Friday night during a disjointed reading of the Mahler conducted by Dennis Russell Davies. Listeners really turned out in force because of the presence of Marianne Faithfull, a singer whose name invokes all the cliches that once attached to the triumvirate of sex, drugs and rock-and-roll. After surviving a series of addictions, suicide attempts and troubled liaisons, Ms. Faithfull has become a chanteuse of the post-counterculture years. The melancholic, bluesy ballads on her 1987 recording, "Strange Weather," have been described as "music to slit your wrists by," and its growly, disturbing presentation of songs of introspective suffering was a prelude to the singer's growing interest in Kurt Weill.</p>
        <p>Her interpretations of Weill were the main point of the weekend. She began with "Seven Deadly Sins," performed with the Brooklyn Philharmonic on Friday and Saturday nights (joined by singers from the Hudson Shad), and ended on Sunday afternoon with a "Weimar Cabaret" with Paul Trueblood as pianist, primarily paying tribute to Weill's collaborations with Bertolt Brecht. Sandra Bernhard even made an appearance as a special guest, singing Mac heath to Ms. Faithfull's Jenny in the "Tango Ballade" from the "Threepenny Opera."</p>
        <p>These performances were sometimes uneven, sometimes compelling and always fascinating. They ended up suggesting a different theme from the one that Joseph Horowitz, the orchestra's executive director, had in mind during a panel conversation with participants on Sunday. Ms. Faithfull's Weill connected him not with Hindemith, but with rock culture.</p>
        <p>It was astonishing, in fact, how often Brecht's lyrics to "Seven Deadly Sins" (1933), translated by W. H. Auden and Chester Kallman, seemed to refer directly to Ms. Faithfull, whose autobiography, chronicling her relationship with Mick Jagger as well as her self-destructive addictions, was being sold in the lobby. Weill's composition, dripping with irony, partly mocks middle-class morality, almost making the seven deadly sins seem like sensible attributes. In her sardonic, clipped, nervy rendition on Friday, Ms. Faithfull's sepulchral alto (she sang the work an octave lower than written), displayed a worn, sandpapery rasp that seemed to come from direct experience of sins and sarcasm.</p>
        <p>The scars of that experience meant that her cabaret singing also had some powerful moments, particularly when Weill breaks his bitter patter with swooping choral lyrics that dip into the mellow range of the voice. Such passages from "Alabama Song" or "Surabaya Johnny," which seem to recall lost sentiments or articulate longed-for unions, were haunting, reaching down into a well of deep sentiment that also surfaced in such non-Weill favorites as "Boulevard of Broken Dreams."</p>
        <p>What prevented these performances from being more powerful was a strange dramatic uncertainty. The girlish ingenue, the wounded lover, the lusty wench and the disillusioned idealist cohabited uneasily, the voice often turning from sweet to raucous in a single phrase; the masks seemed too fluid and ill defined. Perhaps this had something to do with the series of disillusionments in Ms. Faithfull's autobiography: after living Brecht's lessons in the flesh, she came to see herself, she writes, as a "tormented specimen" who spent her youth in the "willful and heedless pursuit of hedonism." These are not the conclusions of a Weillian balladeer.</p>
        <p>It even seemed at times as if Ms. Faithfull couldn't take the songs completely seriously. They were often treated as poses, which is what happened when Ms. Bernhard came on stage for the tango. Instead of suggesting a sultry sexual inversion in which Ms. Bernhard's soprano played dominating male to Ms. Faithfull's husky female, Weill's song became merely a game. Ms. Faithfull's banter also seemed to jar with a cabaret atmosphere. Her dangerously tight, high-cut black dress and spike-heel shoes were just another costume; she endearingly joked with the audience about the fake brandy she sipped or the risk she ran of tripping and breaking her leg.</p>
        <p>And where was Hindemith in all of this? He seemed like Weimar's answer to Weill and Brecht, tentatively testing the anti-bourgeois world in his Dadaist early period (the 1922 Kammermusik No. 1 was given a comic-strip skittishness by members of the orchestra), then settling for its opposite, represented in the dour and dutiful 1938 Piano Duet, played by Lukas Foss and Mr. Davies. As for Mahler, Marilyn Taylor's warm and focused performance of the final movement's soprano aria was a reminder of a kind of sincerity that Hindemith eventually took on as a mannerism and Weill's music later strove for. There were times it could be felt under Ms. Faithfull's cabaret poses as well.  MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
