<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="754463"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DE123AF932A25757C0A963958260" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dollar Recovers as Officials Argue Over Responsibility The dollar recovered to 84.02 yen in New York after one of its most sharp declines in modern times earlier in the day, falling 4 percent to 80.15 yen. The drop intensified a bitter round of finger-pointing by America's main economic rivals about who bears the responsibility for fixing the problem.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dollar Recovers as Officials Argue Over Responsibility The dollar recovered to 84.02 yen in New York after one of its most sharp declines in modern times earlier in the day, falling 4 percent to 80.15 yen. The drop intensified a bitter round of finger-pointing by America's main economic rivals about who bears the responsibility for fixing the problem.</p>
        <p>American officials and their counterparts abroad debated whether to intervene, but apart from Japan's central bank, they did not act. Still, traders became fearful of losing billions if they were caught short, and they began a buying spree that brought the dollar back somewhat. A1.  CBS Earnings Lower Than Expected  CBS reported after the stock market closed that first-quarter earnings were half what Wall Street expected, falling to $21.9 million, or 32 cents a share. D11.  Earnings Up for Chip Makers  Motorola's earnings rose nearly 25 percent in the first quarter, and Advanced Micro Devices, another leading maker of semiconductors, said that strong demand for its chips helped net income rise 14 percent. D5.  The Dow Jones industrials rose 5 points, to 4,198.15, with technology stocks gaining on the expectation of a surge in earnings at Motorola, which reported after the market closed. D12.  Frontier to Acquire ALC  Frontier has agreed to buy ALC Communications in a stock swap valued at about $1.8 billion, which would create the fifth-largest long-distance company. D2.  U S West to Issue Cable Stock  U S West will issue a new class of stock for its cable and wireless businesses, setting the stage for a series of possible changes in the ownership structure of Time Warner. D2.  Goodyear Names President  Goodyear named Samir Gibara president and chief operating officer, putting him in line to succeed Stanley Gault as chief executive. D9.  Putting DNA to Work  Some researchers are planning systems that would use DNA to do computations that would in some cases thwart even the fastest supercomputers. C1.  S.E.C. Addresses Broker Ethics  In an attempt to address concern about broker ethics, the S.E.C. is recommending that brokerage firms pay identical commissions for both proprietary and nonproprietary products and avoid sales contests. D6.  Shopping in Cyberspace Gets Closer  The three largest consumer on-line information systems and two major Internet software companies have agreed on a common technical standard for conducting secure transactions on the Internet. D5.  Copyright Law Ignored in Russia  Copyright laws are brazenly flouted in Russia, and there is almost no film, compact disk or software that cannot be found for a fraction of what it costs in the United States. A3.  Coke Recalls Famous Blunder  Coca-Cola held an unprecedented meeting with employees to mark the 10th anniversary of its decision to replace its 99-year-old soft-drink formula with a sweeter "new Coke." The company's top executives faced a crowd of 600 employees and answered questions about its famous gaffe. D4.  Plan Could Affect Fabled Center  A proposal to amend the charter of Rockefeller Center Properties would clear the way for Goldman, Sachs and its Whitehall Street Real Estate Fund to buy a 19.9 percent stake in the trust. Market Place. D12.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
