<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Raiders Reluctantly Face the Fact That They Are No Longer Feared</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19950412T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="754537"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES RAIDERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEORGE, THOMAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Oakland Raiders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DC1431F932A25757C0A963958260" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Raiders Reluctantly Face the Fact That They Are No Longer Feared</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas George</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GEORGE, THOMAS</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>These are among the traits that have made the Los Angeles Raiders in their 35-year history one of pro football's most successful franchises: strong college drafts; physical, nasty and intimidating play; the deep pass; a driven, cunning and controlling owner in Al Davis, and a way of doing business that is cloaked and clouded in secrecy.</p>
        <p>The Raiders have wrapped themselves in this homespun blanket of security. For the Raiders, it is us against the world. Us against the league.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>These are among the traits that have made the Los Angeles Raiders in their 35-year history one of pro football's most successful franchises: strong college drafts; physical, nasty and intimidating play; the deep pass; a driven, cunning and controlling owner in Al Davis, and a way of doing business that is cloaked and clouded in secrecy.</p>
        <p>The Raiders have wrapped themselves in this homespun blanket of security. For the Raiders, it is us against the world. Us against the league.</p>
        <p>This attitude has served them well: 18 playoff berths, 14 divisional crowns and 3 Super Bowl championships. Yet the Raiders will tell you that the greatness of their organization is in its future.</p>
        <p>Well, in view of their recent past, their fans wonder. We wonder. Continuity has been missing. Winning, too.</p>
        <p>The National Football Conference has won the last 11 Super Bowls and the Raiders were the last American Football Conference team to steal the big show. In the years since then, these are the shriveled fruits for the Raiders: three losing seasons, two .500 seasons, six seasons with no playoffs (including last season) and a 3-5 playoff mark including that 51-3 debacle at Buffalo in the 1990 A.F.C. championship game.</p>
        <p>Each team in the pro game is chasing the Dallas Cowboys and the San Francisco 49ers. The National Football League draft of college players next Saturday and Sunday is all about securing more weapons for the chase. And the 1995 season is all about who will emerge to challenge the elite, particularly in the A.F.C. Resurgent New England? Feisty and surprising San Diego? Defense-minded Pittsburgh?</p>
        <p>The Raiders?</p>
        <p>You've heard the old lines. It used to be that when the Raiders came to town it meant locking your children indoors. Turning out the lights. They were skull and crossbones and they were brute and bad and made you shiver before the first snap. Nowadays, with the exception of the Denver Broncos, no team quivers at playing the Raiders. They simply line up and smack them the way the Raiders used to.</p>
        <p>This has forced the Raiders in general and Davis in particular to take a long, hard look at where this franchise has been, where it is and where it is going. If the self-examination has been true, the exercise has been, in part, painful.</p>
        <p>The American Football League glory years. The Super Bowl victories. John Madden leaving as coach in 1979 after 10 strong seasons. Tom Flores continuing the tradition but finishing in despair after a 5-10 season in 1987. The outside experiment, with Davis selecting Mike Shanahan from Denver as his first coach without Raider ties. He lasted 20 games and won 8 before being replaced by Art Shell early in the 1989 season. The Marcus Allen brouhaha with Davis that eventually wound up with Allen going to Kansas City. And now the unimaginable: Shell dismissed and serving as an offensive line coach at divisional rival Kansas City.</p>
        <p>Add to that riveting cycle of events the fact that the Raiders in philosophy and in scheme have been forced to re-examine their foundation.</p>
        <p>In philosophy, Davis controls. He has tremendous impact on practices. On game day. On the game plan. He is deeply loyal to his players but, according to the former Raider defensive end Howie Long, can be as deeply vindictive. The players used to walk in fear of him and several still do. More of them, however, view him as the direct cause of the franchise's problems.</p>
        <p>Some, it must be said, have bitter feelings simply over the new landscape in free agency and the differences in player salaries. Others, however, simply are turned off by his meddling. How can it be meddling when the guy who owns the team gives it direction? Easily, the players say. A team can have only one coach. Shell was reduced to a puppet, they say. Shanahan, too, said as much about his experience as the Raiders' head coach.</p>
        <p>Today's Generation X players -- the Raiders included -- are not inclined to sit by silently. Davis has always counted on control, but it is slipping. Receiver Tim Brown is the latest Raider to voice his concerns over the lack of continuity between ownership, coaches and players in giving the team direction. Davis has counted on the Raiders always being linked to their past glory. The problem is, too many of today's Raiders could care less about the past. And Davis has lost much of their respect, primarily over his handling of Allen and Shell.</p>
        <p>Then there is the offensive scheme. The Raiders have always loved to throw the football deep. Today's defenses favor putting maximum pressure on quarterbacks and offenses have responded with hot receivers, with passes underneath to backs or quick outs to wide-outs. But through last season, the Raiders continued to live and die by the big play. It was more of the latter.</p>
        <p>The Raiders made nine scoring plays of 40 or more yards last season. Eighteen N.F.L. teams produced more. The Raiders allowed 50 sacks. Even the Jets and Colts allowed fewer (28 apiece). The Raiders finished last season 19th in the league in offense, 21st in rushing and 16th in passing. They also set a league record with 156 penalties for 1,186 yards lost. That is only 326 yards fewer than they gained rushing.</p>
        <p>They entered 1994 as a Super Bowl favorite. They opened with a 44-14 loss at San Francisco. They ended with a 19-9 loss at home to Kansas City, when a victory would have earned them a playoff berth.</p>
        <p>Now they turn to Mike White, who has been an assistant coach here since 1990 and was head coach at California for five seasons and at Illinois for eight. He is the first Raider coach since their very first one -- Eddie Erdelatz in 1960 -- to arrive with head coaching experience.</p>
        <p>White, who designed flexible offenses at Illinois, is not believed to have been a primary candidate to replace Shell until he sold himself to Davis. He got a one-year contract.</p>
        <p>White's task is to get the Raiders offense in gear while maintaining the Davis principles. The defense is solid.</p>
        <p>The offense is laden with talent, and even that asset has become a problem. We need two footballs, the Raiders say. No, one will do. Keep spreading it around while insuring that the playmakers like Brown and Raghib Ismail touch the ball in open spaces where they can create. Emphasize, and be as creative with, the running game. Move the quarterback, Jeff Hostetler, around in his drop and in the pocket to give him and defenses a more varied look.</p>
        <p>There are positive signs. The Hall of Fame cornerback Willie Brown is back as a direct liaison with players in their personal and career development. This is one way Davis, through Brown, can recapture his players' respect and attention. Former 49ers receiver Mike Wilson, who is young and full of promise as a coach, is the new teacher among the receivers. The Raiders have never recovered, mentally or physically, from the loss of Bo Jackson but they have added running back Derrick Fenner via free agency from the Bengals. He should help.</p>
        <p>And in one of the most effective changes, Fred Biletnikoff moves from receivers coach into quality control -- his job, in part, is to examine the Raiders and to examine their tendencies as if he were an opponent. He is to report and the Raiders are to adapt.</p>
        <p>That is the key word here. Adapt. It is one the Raiders by nature do not like. If greatness is in their future, however, it is one they will grow to love.  ON PRO FOOTBALL  Correction:  April 12, 1995, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A article yesterday about the Los Angeles Raiders misstated the dates of the National Football League's college draft. It will be conducted April 22 and 23, not this weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 12, 1995, Wednesday</p>
        <p>A article yesterday about the Los Angeles Raiders misstated the dates of the National Football League's college draft. It will be conducted April 22 and 23, not this weekend.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
