<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jazzy Tapping On Camera and Onstage</title>
    <meta content="20JAZZ$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="DANCE REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="910096"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jazz Tap Ensemble</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEED7163EF933A15751C0A961958260" item-length="709" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jazzy Tapping On Camera and Onstage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews performance by Jazz Tap Ensemble at the Joyce Theater; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Looking for a night out? The Jazz Tap Ensemble, with its percussive dancers performing to a live jazz trio, often in homage to old masters, should top any list this week.</p>
        <p>Celebrating a decade of appearances at the Joyce Theater, the troupe, directed by Lynn Dally in Los Angeles since 1979, has added a technological novelty. During some of the dances performed on Tuesday night at the opening of a week's run at the Joyce (175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea), cameramen directed by the experimental video artist Dennis Diamond came on stage and provided live shots of the dancers and musicians.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Looking for a night out? The Jazz Tap Ensemble, with its percussive dancers performing to a live jazz trio, often in homage to old masters, should top any list this week.</p>
        <p>Celebrating a decade of appearances at the Joyce Theater, the troupe, directed by Lynn Dally in Los Angeles since 1979, has added a technological novelty. During some of the dances performed on Tuesday night at the opening of a week's run at the Joyce (175 Eighth Avenue, at 19th Street, Chelsea), cameramen directed by the experimental video artist Dennis Diamond came on stage and provided live shots of the dancers and musicians.</p>
        <p>These close-ups, projected on a backdrop, made for an exercise in perception. The detailed complexity of the footwork, often shot from behind, contrasted with the bigger picture onstage. Live, the dancers created shapes and sounds while the video images zeroed in on the virtuosity that flashes by almost too quickly in the ensemble's loose natural style.</p>
        <p>This understated style can border on blandness and that quality, oddly, works to the group's advantage. The Jazz Tap Ensemble does not offend: its generosity of spirit is felt not only in its overt tribute to great jazz composers and great tap dancers but also in the camaraderie of its dancers.</p>
        <p>Absent is the competitive edge that stems from the challenge dances of rhythm tap, to name the type of dancing to which Ms. Dally and her friends pay allegiance. The musical trio, consisting of Jerry Kalaf, its drummer and director, as well as Eric Ajaye (bass) and Dave Scott (piano and trumpet) is cool rather than hot, although rich texture is never missing (as seen in the Duke Ellington and Thelonious Monk numbers). At its best, the ensemble brings out the personal style of each dancer while retaining its silky smooth homogeneity. Personnel changes this year have reduced the number of dancers to five. The newcomers Carol Christiansen, Becky Twitchell and Channing Cook Holmes have joined the veterans, Ms. Dally and Sam Weber, who is the equivalent of a virtuoso pianist.</p>
        <p>Ellington's ''Caravan'' introduced the group's unison discipline. Interpolated into a series of loose and light skips is a stream of constantly changing footwork.</p>
        <p>Percussive sound, not a concern with how the entire body looks, is Jazz Tap's trademark, as the season's premieres illustrate. Mr. Weber pours out a rhythmic cascade in ''All the Things You Are,'' danced to Mr. Kalaf's arrangement of Jerome Kern. His mock stiffness gives way to heel-to-heel tapping and a witty waddle. ''Solo,'' with Mr. Ajaye playing Victor Young's ''Beautiful Love,'' shows off Ms. Dally's signature weight-shifting style. The video cameras capture aspects of Mr. Weber's artistry, contrasted with the more innocent exuberance of Ms. Twitchell and Ms. Christiansen in ''Doxy,'' created by the late master Eddie Brown.</p>
        <p>''Speak Low,'' a premiere choreographed by Ms. Dally, brings out Ms. Christiansen's wholesome air in rhythms that alternate the emphatic with the chattering. The music is by Kurt Weill.</p>
        <p>''Monk Suite '97'' includes new and past choreography set to Thelonious Monk's recordings (his widow was in the audience, as was Harold Nicholas of the Nicholas Brothers). Mr. Weber was a standout in ''Straight, No Chaser,'' a space-covering solo full of directional changes. After her reverie, '' 'Round Midnight,'' Ms. Dally and the group gave the suite an artful finale with ''Epistrophy.''</p>
        <p>The new ''Hands On,'' choreographed by Mr. Weber and set to music by Mr. Kalaf, offered the most elaborate collaboration between Mr. Diamond and the live performers. The filmed images looked abstract as the cameramen shot over a drummer's shoulder and echoed the circular form in an adjoining picture of the footwork. The camera was anything but intrusive and enhanced the unison work and the solos: Mr. Holmes's staccato style produced especially vivid rhythmic nuances.</p>
        <p>The cameras concentrated on the excellent musical trio as it performed Mr. Kalaf's new tribute to a fellow musician, Bill Evans, ''Sept. 15, 1980,'' the date Evans died. The images here were not abstract and the collaboration as a whole added to a viewer's appreciation of both dancers and musicians. ''Jimmy Slyde'' and several other numbers completed the program.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
