<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mix, Patch, Promote and Lift; A Showman Speeds the Makeover of Ted Turner's Empire</title>
    <meta content="15KELL$25" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/15/business/media/15KELL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1309575"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Turner Broadcasting System Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aol Time Warner</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wb Television Network</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rutenberg, Jim</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kellner, Jamie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia/Atlanta</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television and Radio Programming</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Georgia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Georgia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Georgia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Georgia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Georgia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Georgia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Georgia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Georgia)</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Atlanta (Georgia)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">AOL Time Warner Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, Ted</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Turner, Ted</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E7DE123BF936A25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="3850" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mix, Patch, Promote and Lift; A Showman Speeds the Makeover of Ted Turner's Empire</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Showman Speeds the Makeover of Ted Turner's Empire</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM RUTENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rutenberg, Jim</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTA</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Turner Broadcasting System chief executive Jamie Kellner, chosen by AOL Time Warner to combine Turner empire with WB and use AOL's breadth and power to move them away from tiny basic cable niches toward network-size ratings; his mission is to promote synergy within his empire, orchestrate cross-promotion and help parent company sell advertising packages that span all of its outlets; graphs of viewers; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JAMIE KELLNER sat back and gazed out the window as the Gulfstream V corporate jet began its gentle glide into this city, his new home. Down below, a billowy carpet of green trees and brush was broken up by a glassy lake. ''I didn't know there was water there,'' he said. Mr. Kellner, who was looking for a place to live, paused, then added, ''I wonder how I get a piece of that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner, who at 54 is square-jawed and street tough even though he now lives luxuriously, was talking real estate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Jamie Kellner is a man who has made his career stealing audience from the major television networks. Now he is at it again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JAMIE KELLNER sat back and gazed out the window as the Gulfstream V corporate jet began its gentle glide into this city, his new home. Down below, a billowy carpet of green trees and brush was broken up by a glassy lake. ''I didn't know there was water there,'' he said. Mr. Kellner, who was looking for a place to live, paused, then added, ''I wonder how I get a piece of that.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner, who at 54 is square-jawed and street tough even though he now lives luxuriously, was talking real estate.</p>
        <p>But he might as well have been referring to the prime-time, network television audience. That is what he thinks about most of the time, and this day in early June was no exception.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner is one of the great poachers in the television industry, a man who has made his career -- first at the fledgling Fox, then at the upstart WB -- stealing large chunks of audience from the three dominant broadcast networks. Now he is at it again, chosen by AOL Time Warner to take the old Ted Turner empire of CNN, TBS and TNT, combine it with WB, use AOL's breadth and power and head them all into the territory of network-size ratings, not the tiny niches occupied by all basic cable networks.</p>
        <p>In a sense, Mr. Kellner, as chief executive of the Turner Broadcasting System, embodies AOL's strategy to make sure that the whole is greater than the sum of its parts. His mission is to promote synergy within his empire, to orchestrate cross-promotion and to help the parent company sell advertising packages that span all of its outlets.</p>
        <p>There are skeptics. Synergy is a buzzword, but often requires convincing and even coercing people who are accustomed to working at cross-purposes to work together. And basic cable networks have yet to regularly draw audiences anywhere near the size of those of the broadcast networks.</p>
        <p>''I think that's a perfectly good ambition,'' said Stephen Chao, who, as president of USA Cable, the cable division of USA Networks, is Mr. Kellner's chief cable competitor. ''How you get there is the question.''</p>
        <p>The Turner networks -- like all established cable networks -- are struggling just to maintain their market share in the face of newer, narrowly focused rivals like Home &amp; Garden, the Travel Channel, Animal Planet and the promise of even more.</p>
        <p>Considering that the Turner cable networks generate an estimated 10 percent of AOL Time Warner's revenue and cash flow, Mr. Kellner faces huge pressure just to keep them at current levels, especially in a soft advertising market.</p>
        <p>That is why Mr. Kellner, a gravelly voiced New York native,  has worked fast since taking the job in March.</p>
        <p>At CNN, he rehired the popular financial news anchor, Lou Dobbs, and talked with CBS about a possible news alliance. In his most controversial move, he approved the hiring of Andrea Thompson, an actress on ABC's ''N.Y.P.D. Blue,'' as a Headline News anchor. Her hiring added to the nervousness at CNN, recently shaken by the layoff of 400 workers. It came soon after Mr. Kellner, the Hollywood insider who helped bring to television ''The Simpsons'' and ''Married . . . With Children,'' had declared that the news network needed more showmanship.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner assuaged some of their fears, however, on Monday, when he announced that he had chosen Walter Isaacson, the Time Inc. editorial director and former managing editor of Time magazine, as CNN's new chairman and chief executive, succeeding Tom Johnson.</p>
        <p>At TBS and TNT, Mr. Kellner has increased promotion of shows and pulled wrestling off the schedules.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Mr. Kellner said, he wants to find programming for the Turner entertainment networks that will attract the sort of audience drawn by ''The Sopranos'' or ''Sex and the City'' on HBO. Eventually, he said, he would like to start new cable networks, like a music channel to compete with Viacom's MTV. He has his team brainstorming other ideas for channels.</p>
        <p>But before he can get to that, he said, ''We've got to get our decks cleared.''</p>
        <p>At the top of his list is fixing CNN, preferably before it becomes an identifiable drag on AOL Time Warner's share price. The shares, which now trade at $49.81, are up 43 percent this year, but off 12 percent from their 2001 high on May 21.</p>
        <p>The problems at CNN, which brings in more than $1 billion a year, have been well publicized. With increased competition from MSNBC, CNBC and the Fox News Channel, CNN's share of the cable news audience has dropped to 24 percent this year from nearly 39 percent four years ago, Nielsen Media Research data shows. During that time, Fox News Channel's share has grown to 22 percent from 6 percent. (In those years, the cable news audience has generally fluctuated between 1 million and 1.4 million people.)</p>
        <p>AOL Time Warner considers CNN a crucial asset in its ''AOL Anywhere'' strategy. The company hopes that CNN's news reports -- and accompanying advertising -- will be viewed online around the world, on wireless devices and on television.</p>
        <p>Many in the television industry regard CNN as boring, unfocused and outmoded, right down to James Earl Jones's oft-repeated, earnest, promotional voice-over, ''This . . . is CNN.'' (You probably won't hear it quite as much anymore; at a recent promotional meeting, executives expressed an appetite for something new, raised the idea of getting rid of it, but quicky concluded that maybe it should at least run less often, or that Mr. Jones should rerecord it.)</p>
        <p>CNN descended from the old network television news model, growing up on a peas-and-carrots diet of sober news analysis and straightforward reports. Competitors -- Fox News Channel, a unit of the News Corporation; CNBC, owned by General Electric; and MSNBC, owned jointly by G.E. and Microsoft -- have brought something new to cable news that viewers seem to like: fun. Using flashy graphics, brash talk-show hosts, fewer traditional news reports and more features, they have gained viewers -- consistently, not just for breaking news.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Kellner, CNN's original mission of making ''news the star'' -- and not relying on the network-style news celebrities -- is ''a little old-fashioned, you know?''</p>
        <p>''If it was the only one, it could be about just straightforward journalism,'' he added. ''But we're in a marketplace that's incredibly competitive today.''</p>
        <p>He also said, ''There's a lot of technique in television you can use to make things more exciting; television is a personality medium.''</p>
        <p>Within weeks of taking the job at Turner, Mr. Kellner put out the message that the network was in search of big stars. And in fact CNN has begun to reach out to top news talents, like NBC's Katie Couric and ABC's Diane Sawyer, though Mr. Kellner's team does not seem to expect either one of them to show up tomorrow in a CNN anchor's chair.</p>
        <p>He also devised plans for a street-side New York studio, where CNN is considering basing a prime-time news program with Aaron Brown and its new talk show with Jeff Greenfield. And Mr. Kellner oversaw a makeover of Headline News to give it younger appeal, using music and Internet-style graphics.</p>
        <p>ALMOST immediately, Mr. Kellner and Garth Ancier, a longtime colleague in entertainment programming who came with him to Turner shortly after leaving NBC, started weekly meetings with top CNN executives to discuss network promotion, programming and scheduling. They are using  focus groups to learn what news interests viewers. And they are intensifying ratings analyses. As they see it, the network's journalists are good at journalism, but lack what Mr. Ancier calls ''Basic TV 101.''</p>
        <p>''It wasn't part of the culture,'' he said in an interview. ''It was, 'Let's just be the best journalistic organization that we can be.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner and Robert W. Pittman, the AOL co-chief operating officer and a founder of MTV, learned to their surprise that CNN was not heavily promoting its own shows.</p>
        <p>''If you looked at CNN, they were just doing sort of generic promos,'' Mr. Pittman said as he toured the CNN newsroom here with Mr. Isaacson last week. ''They wouldn't say what's on tonight; they wouldn't say what's on in 10 minutes. If this many people watch it and they try so little to get them to watch, imagine what happens when you actually try to get them to watch.''</p>
        <p>CNN has started promoting its programs aggressively, and executives say the change is contributing to a stabilization of the network's ratings. At this time last year, CNN's audience was down 35 percent from 1999. Now, it is down just 2 percent from last year. During the second quarter of this year, CNN's audience actually grew 11 percent in prime time from the corresponding period of 2000, without huge breaking-news events.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner said the rehiring of Mr. Dobbs had helped. After Mr. Dobbs left CNN to start a space-related Web portal called Space.com two years ago, his signature business news show, ''Moneyline,'' lost more than 30 percent of its audience. It was overtaken in the ratings by CNBC's ''Business Center.''</p>
        <p>But in his first eight weeks back at CNN, Mr. Dobbs has narrowed the gap. His average audience between 6:30 and 7:30 p.m. has grown to 208,000 from 192,000; the total for ''Business Center'' during that hour has fallen to 246,000 from 303,000.</p>
        <p>PERHAPS a testament to the impact of CNN's flashy rivals, there are fewer groans from the journalistic establishment over the merger of news and showmanship, exemplified by the hiring of the actress to be a news anchor.</p>
        <p>None other than Tom Goldstein, the dean of the Graduate School of Journalism at Columbia University, said, ''They haven't done anything at CNN, except for maybe that one appointment, that's cause for great concern.'' He added, ''All these people have been running up against the form -- how do you keep something lively and interesting 24 hours a day?  This is a huge challenge.''</p>
        <p>Students of CNN might expect all of this talk of stars and promotion to deeply bother the network's staff of journalists, who have been a somewhat demoralized bunch</p>
        <p>But even CNN journalists have been willing to give Mr. Kellner's plan a chance, and to even put up with the return of Mr. Dobbs, considered by some to be bombastic. (His return has not been totally without tension: CNN agreed to change the title of ''Moneyline'' to ''Lou Dobbs Moneyline'' to herald his return. The  apostrophe was omitted to signal that he did not own the program. Mr. Dobbs said of that, ''I would always prefer that in all things, grammar be honored, but that's all right.'')</p>
        <p>One senior CNN correspondent, discussing Mr. Kellner's overall plan for the network two weeks ago, said, ''We know that he has to make CNN more watchable, bring dynamism to CNN and give the network a face of the future.''</p>
        <p>But the correspondent, who spoke on condition of anonymity because of the subject's sensitive nature, did express some angst at Mr. Kellner's Hollywood background, especially in the wake of the resignation of Mr. Johnson, a former publisher of The Los Angeles Times. ''But Jamie has to do this without forsaking CNN's past, without making it less journalistic, and maybe that's a contradictory mission,'' the correspondent said. ''We're either on the verge of totally blowing it or getting it right.''</p>
        <p>After Mr. Kellner named Mr. Isaacson as CNN chairman, this correspondent expressed relief. He said of Mr. Isaacson's lack of experience running a television operation: ''You can teach television; you can't teach curiosity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner offered Mr. Isaacson the chairman's job within two days of Mr. Johnson's resignation. He had been consulting with Mr. Isaacson, and had grown to see him as part of a new generation of post-cold-war editors who have had to deal with shifting tastes of the American public.</p>
        <p>As managing editor of Time magazine starting in 1996, Mr. Isaacson made what was considered a sagging, outdated, but still important magazine livelier and more appealing to young audiences with heavier coverage of science, technology and pop culture. He reduced coverage of foreign events.</p>
        <p>To Mr. Kellner, Mr. Pittman and Gerald M. Levin, the chief executive of AOL Time Warner, CNN in 2001 is not all that different from Time circa 1996. They want Mr. Isaacson to give CNN the same makeover he gave Time.</p>
        <p>But he will confront serious issues -- including scarce resources and whether to merge with CBS News or ABC News, both of which have discussed with CNN a possible partnership. During an interview here last week, however, Mr. Levin said that if CNN ever reached an agreement with another network, it would not relinquish control. ''CNN will always be in the driver's seat,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner's new role at CNN, and Mr. Isaacson's appointment as its chairman, have certainly raised the sense of competition at Fox News Channel. As a reminder of the fight, Fox posted this quotation from Mr. Kellner in its newsroom: ''Give us six months to a year. We will be ahead of Fox.''</p>
        <p>''They've hired a damned good guy in Isaacson; I expect a pitched battle,'' said Roger Ailes, the Fox News chief executive. ''They'll be up some weeks; we'll be up some weeks. In the end, somebody will win with the American people. I believe it will be us.''</p>
        <p>AOL Time Warner's ambitions for CNN are only part of the puzzle for Turner Broadcasting. Although Mr. Kellner said CNN had plenty of ''headroom to grow'' in the ratings, the news audience is somewhat limited.</p>
        <p>But the nation has an endless hunger for entertainment, and Mr. Kellner hopes he can bring network-level ratings to TBS and TNT, Turner's two general-interest cable channels. TBS ranks third in ratings for basic cable networks; TNT is fifth.</p>
        <p>TBS, which started in 1976, was among the first general interest, basic cable services. Many viewers know it for movies, basketball, Atlanta Braves baseball games and James Bond marathons. TNT, which started 12 years later, shows original movies, golf, and reruns of shows like ''ER'' and ''Law &amp; Order.''</p>
        <p>Although AOL Time Warner has emphasized its subscription businesses -- HBO, the Time Inc. magazines, the AOL Internet service -- the advertiser-supported television networks are also important. The company intends to be a major force in interactive television, where viewers will get movies and programs on demand and advertisers will sell directly to the viewers.</p>
        <p>Advertiser-supported basic cable, filled with reruns of old network shows, movies, cartoons, sports and documentaries, has yet to regularly reach network-level ratings with original programming. Only World Wrestling Federation matches have consistently achieved such numbers.</p>
        <p>Over all, the most-watched cable network in prime time last quarter was Lifetime, the network aimed at women, with an average audience of 1.5 million homes. In the broadcast television ratings race that ended in May, the most-watched network was CBS, with 8.8 million homes.</p>
        <p>Expanding the audiences of TNT and TBS is tougher than ever, as many more channels are added to subscription television through satellite TV and digital cable.</p>
        <p>Richard A. Bilotti, a media analyst at Morgan Stanley, said a study that he conducted recently found that in homes with digital cable or satellite television -- about 30 percent of all American homes with television -- viewers spend up to 40 percent of their time switching between relatively low-rated cable networks like the Golf Channel or Home &amp; Garden network and the various premium networks like Showtime and HBO. The bigger broadcast and basic cable networks accounted for the rest of the time.</p>
        <p>AS digital cable and satellite television proliferate, ''the fragmenting is going to get worse,'' Mr. Bilotti said. For the more established networks, he said, ''if you just stay still and don't change your programming mix, you're guaranteed to lose audience every year.''</p>
        <p>But, like other analysts, he said he thought that Mr. Kellner could help TNT and TBS grow. That opinion is widely held because Mr. Kellner built a career around taking audience away from the big networks --  the fuel for his rugged confidence.</p>
        <p>In 1986, he was recruited to head Fox from the syndication world by Barry Diller and Rupert Murdoch. The team that Mr. Kellner led there, including Mr. Ancier and Brad Turell in promotion, made itself famous by first focusing on the young audiences that Mr. Kellner concluded the Big Three networks had neglected. It found hits in shows like ''Married . . . With Children'' and ''The Simpsons.''</p>
        <p>But his run there was not without problems. After Mr. Diller left the network, he and Mr. Murdoch did not agree on its direction. Mr. Kellner resigned in 1993.</p>
        <p>Within months, he devised plans to start the WB in partnership with Tribune Broadcasting and Time Warner's Warner Brothers. There his team, again including Mr. Ancier and Mr. Turell, made headway with younger audiences with shows like ''Buffy the Vampire Slayer'' and ''Felicity.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kellner acknowledges that he once resented living in the long shadows of Mr. Diller and Mr. Murdoch. In a corporate twist, they are now his main competitors.</p>
        <p>''Whenever you have big stars like Barry Diller and Rupert Murdoch, a lot of the light gets shined on them, whether they did it or not,'' Mr. Kellner said last Tuesday from the WB New York sales offices. ''Does that upset me? It doesn't upset me anymore. Back in those days, it hurt my feelings, probably.''</p>
        <p>At WB, he bumped up against Mr. Turner, who thought Time Warner's money would be better spent buying NBC than financing WB. Mr. Turner, the AOL Time Warner vice chairman whose operational duties were taken away last spring, went on to foster a culture at Turner that did not exactly cooperate with the WB. The children's television programmers at the Cartoon Network, for example, would not work with counterparts at WB. And at WB, programmers did not communicate with those of the Turner networks.</p>
        <p>NOW it is up to Mr. Kellner to change the culture once set against his network. He plans to use the WB, in concert with the Turner cable networks and the AOL Internet service, to pump up all of their ratings and even to help start new cable channels.</p>
        <p>For instance, Mr. Kellner said, he could foresee a music network promoted heavily with WB's young audience. Viacom's MTV and VH-1 networks are the only widely distributed music channels, and Mr. Kellner said that ''it just seems ridiculous to me that one company should control almost all of the space.''</p>
        <p>''Someone should give it a college try,'' he added.</p>
        <p>His plan to raise ratings for the existing empire is based on the heavy promotion of programming between the Turner cable channels and WB -- and the sharing of programming so that revenue and ratings rise.</p>
        <p>So a repeat of ''Charmed,'' a WB series about pretty young witches, may also be shown weekly on TNT. By showing a program on WB and on one of the cable channels -- or both -- Turner is giving a single episode of a series a larger audience so that it can sell more advertising time for that episode at a higher rate.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, Mr. Kellner said, he intends to use his Hollywood connections, getting producers and writers  to create original programming on cable. His inspiration is HBO, which has unnerved major network executives with the success of ''The Sopranos.''</p>
        <p>Some television analysts doubt that basic cable can create a blockbuster show. The big networks, with huge resources, try to create them every year, as do premium cable channels like Showtime and HBO, which can offer viewers the sort of R-rated programming that television and basic cable generally cannot.</p>
        <p>Mr. Turell, his promotions executive, said a cable breakthrough in ratings ''is just a goal.''</p>
        <p>''It doesn't mean you have to get there, but if you're going in that direction, it can become immensely profitable,'' he added. ''Nobody said we could do it at Fox; they said we couldn't do it at WB. That doesn't scare us.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bilotti of Morgan Stanley said basic cable networks had been handicapped because they lacked real programmers.</p>
        <p>''The cable industry for 20 years was defined as reusing older programming, so the main job of head of a cable programming division was to sell advertising,'' he said. ''Now it's a different story.''</p>
        <p>Of Mr. Kellner, he said: ''The thing he's going to bring to the cable industry is, he's a programmer.''</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Kellner is now effectively sitting in Mr. Turner's chair, he has not forgotten the way Mr. Turner treated his network. Mr. Kellner said he had since discussed it with Mr. Turner, who has told him that he dismissed WB out of frustration with Time Warner for not supporting him in his quest to buy NBC.</p>
        <p>And now that he is in Mr. Turner's office, he appears to understand where Mr. Turner was coming from.</p>
        <p>''If you could own NBC and the WB,'' he said, ''you'd have a really powerful multiplex.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, it could probably never happen. ''The price would be astronomical,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
