<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>St. Bart's to Open Its Doors to an Adversary</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="442930"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ST BARTHOLOMEW'S CHURCH (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OFFICE BUILDINGS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">PROTESTANT EPISCOPAL CHURCH</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MUNICIPAL ART SOCIETY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">DUNLAP, DAVID W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910504T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DD173DF937A35756C0A967958260" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>St. Bart's to Open Its Doors to an Adversary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. DUNLAP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DUNLAP, DAVID W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Peace may never come to the roily realm of New York City real-estate development, but a remarkable cease-fire has been declared that is to be played out next month under the Byzantine dome of St. Bartholomew's Church on Park Avenue.</p>
        <p>Having lost what it presented as a life-and-death struggle to build a skyscraper on the 50th Street side of its property, St. Bartholomew's is to be the host of the annual meeting of the Municipal Art Society, a leading opponent of the church's development plans.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Peace may never come to the roily realm of New York City real-estate development, but a remarkable cease-fire has been declared that is to be played out next month under the Byzantine dome of St. Bartholomew's Church on Park Avenue.</p>
        <p>Having lost what it presented as a life-and-death struggle to build a skyscraper on the 50th Street side of its property, St. Bartholomew's is to be the host of the annual meeting of the Municipal Art Society, a leading opponent of the church's development plans.</p>
        <p>Like ancient combatants, each side is still wary of the other. But both sides discern a symbolic importance in a gathering of preservationists at the very church that came to epitomize the religious community's struggle against the landmarks law.</p>
        <p>St. Bartholomew's, which has given up hope of building an office tower on its land, may soon begin a multimillion-dollar fund-raising campaign to maintain and preserve its landmark buildings, and could use the support of the civic group and its allies.  'To Get On With Our Work'</p>
        <p>"I will take help from anywhere that it comes," said the Rev. Thomas D. Bowers, rector of the Episcopal church. "We would really like to be free to get on with our work and let others help take care of this building."</p>
        <p>Kent L. Barwick, president of the Municipal Art Society, said he hopes that it and others "will help in any way they can to insure the future of St. Bartholomew's."</p>
        <p>It is the second time in two months that the Municipal Art Society -- which concerns itself with art, architecture and city planning -- has declared so public a truce with such a celebrated adversary. In April, it joined with Donald J. Trump to help plan the future of his vast development site on the West Side of Manhattan.</p>
        <p>"I do think reconciliation is in the wind," Mr. Barwick said. "I think a lot of people are hungry for it.</p>
        <p>"We're not planning to go out of business, to fall asleep or to leave our watchdog role," he added. "But if we can find ways to work with the religious community, as well as responsible members of the development community, I think we should. And we mean to."</p>
        <p>The rapprochement with St. Bartholomew's can be traced to March, when the United States Supreme Court refused to hear the church's constitutional challenge to its landmark designation.</p>
        <p>Under that designation, the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission rejected two plans for an office tower that would have replaced the church's Community House. The panel said that a tower would clash with the neighboring sanctuary and overwhelm it. It also rejected the church's claim of hardship.</p>
        <p>That has left church leaders to do what they had warned for a decade they could not do: sustain both a physical landmark and a spiritual mission.</p>
        <p>Raymond L. Vandenberg, the chancellor, or counsel, to St. Bartholomew's vestry, said, "We had to reach out to the people who were opposing the solution the church had come up with 10 years ago, since our solution had been blocked by the courts."</p>
        <p>About renting the church to the Municipal Art Society for its meeting, he said, "It was a perfect symbolic gesture to demonstrate a request for assistance from the groups that felt the church was worth fighting for."</p>
        <p>"The city has more or less adopted this building as an oasis in the rush of midtown Manhattan," he said. "And in that sense, it's the community's responsibility. It cannot ask us to cut back our religious mission in order to preserve the building. It has to help."</p>
        <p>Mr. Vandenberg said the church might start a fund-raising campaign for the buildings, which were designed by Bertram Grosvenor Goodhue and his successor firm, Mayers, Murray &amp; Philip. The goal might be in the tens of millions of dollars.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Barwick is not ready to discuss any financial commitments.</p>
        <p>"Obviously," he said of the church leaders, "it's up to them to make their case. And I don't know that they're going to make a case that the church is about to fall down." Parish Is Divided</p>
        <p>Even within the congregation, opinions differ widely on what the church needs. J. Sinclair Armstrong, who led a parish faction opposed to development, put the total maintenance figure at $3.1 million, citing a court decision in the case.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Fletcher Hodges 3d, senior warden of the church, said that to sustain both the buildings and the church's mission, the endowment would have to be raised to $30 million, from $9 million.</p>
        <p>"The loss of this major asset, this piece of developable property, is a tremendous diminishment of the church's ability to carry out its mission," Mr. Hodges said. "There is no way that art groups can replace that by stepping up to bat to support buildings."</p>
        <p>Even as he prepares "to embrace them" on June 12, Father Bowers said he would have a sobering message for members of the Municipal Art Society:</p>
        <p>"This city is in danger of losing its soul. If they kill the churches, kill the institutions, and save the buildings, they'll have a dead city. It's a monumental tragedy and misunderstanding. And it worries me to death."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
