<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Singapore And U.S. Near A Trade Deal</title>
    <meta content="Y20TRAD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/20/business/worldbusiness/20TRAD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1442173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Singapore</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Andrews, Edmund L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zoellick, Robert B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeo, George (Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Singapore</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Singapore</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E1DE1639F933A15752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="862" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Singapore And U.S. Near A Trade Deal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Singapore and U.S. Near a Trade Deal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDMUND L. ANDREWS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Andrews, Edmund L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US reaches tentative free-trade agreement with Singapore; new agreement, if completed and approved by Congress, would eliminate tariffs on about $33 billion in trade between two countries and would give American banks and service companies more access to one of Asia's main financial centers; US trade representative Robert B Zoellick comments; photo of Zoellick with Singapore's Trade Min George Yeo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States reached a tentative free-trade agreement with Singapore today, the first of what the Bush administration hopes will be a web of similar deals worldwide.</p>
        <p>But even after two years of work, and talks that stretched until just before dawn this morning, the two countries could not reach a final agreement because of disputes about Singapore's ability to impose capital controls in a financial crisis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States reached a tentative free-trade agreement with Singapore, the first of what the Bush administration hopes will be a web of similar deals worldwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States reached a tentative free-trade agreement with Singapore today, the first of what the Bush administration hopes will be a web of similar deals worldwide.</p>
        <p>But even after two years of work, and talks that stretched until just before dawn this morning, the two countries could not reach a final agreement because of disputes about Singapore's ability to impose capital controls in a financial crisis.</p>
        <p>The new agreement, if completed and approved by Congress, would eliminate tariffs on about $33 billion in trade between the two countries and would give American banks and service companies more access to one of Asia's main financial centers.</p>
        <p>It is probably more important as an indicator of the United States' new strategy in opening up global trade markets.</p>
        <p>That strategy increasingly relies on negotiating deals with individual countries and small regions, in part to build support for more ambitious projects, like a ''free trade agreement for the Americas'' and a new global trade agreement at the World Trade Organization.</p>
        <p>In addition to Singapore, the White House hopes to wrap up a free-trade deal with Chile by the end of the year. It is also starting talks with five countries in Central America and with Australia, and it is trying to open talks with other countries in Southeast Asia.</p>
        <p>But the United States is actually behind the European Union, which has already negotiated its own market-opening deals with Chile and several other countries.</p>
        <p>Reaching an agreement with Singapore is easier than with many countries because it has historically been a free-trade port for imported goods and it is a high-wage country with a modern service-based economy.</p>
        <p>The Bush administration is still wrestling with Chile, eight years after the United States first proposed a free-trade deal with that country, on how it will enforce its labor and environmental regulations.</p>
        <p>Negotiating a free-trade deal with Australia will face far larger political obstacles because Australia is one of the United States' biggest rivals in global agriculture production.</p>
        <p>American agriculture remains highly protected by both tariffs and government subsidies, and farm lobbies have enormous political influence in Washington.</p>
        <p>In Singapore, American officials have yet to persuade leaders that they should forsake the ability to block companies from moving money out of that island nation in times of financial crisis.</p>
        <p>Robert B. Zoellick, the United States trade representative, told reporters in Singapore today that the two countries had achieved the substance of a free-trade agreement. Officials from both countries said they hoped to resolve the last obstacle in the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zoellick has sharply accelerated his push for bilateral free-trade deals since late July, when Congress passed legislation that gives the administration the authority to negotiate trade deals and then submit them to Congress for a simple yes-or-no vote without changes or amendments.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zoellick's strategy is based on what he calls ''competitive liberalization,'' the idea that a bilateral trade agreement with one country puts pressure on others to seek their own deals with the United States.</p>
        <p>Immediately after he finished talks in Singapore, Mr. Zoellick flew to a meeting in Manila today of economic ministers from Southeast Asian nations, including the Philippines, Indonesia, Malaysia and Thailand.</p>
        <p>''I firmly believe that a process of competitive liberalization will enhance our ability'' to negotiate broader market-opening agreements, Mr. Zoellick told reporters in Singapore today.</p>
        <p>Because Singapore has always been a free port for most imported goods, the agreement would not affect American exports of products. The main effect for American companies is in opening markets for services, like banking and investment management, legal services, engineering, and architecture.</p>
        <p>Just today, in a nod to the proposed agreement, the Monetary Authority of Singapore said it would gradually lift its restrictions on licenses for American banks, allowing them to offer a full range of services and expand their networks of branches and automated teller machines.</p>
        <p>The agreement would also expand the ability of foreign law firms, most of which are prohibited from practicing local law, to operate in Singapore.</p>
        <p>Singapore would be freed from tariffs on exports to the United States. One of its biggest benefits would be to get tariff-free treatment for products whose components are largely produced on two nearby islands in Indonesia, where wages are much lower.</p>
        <p>Negotiators from both countries said they hoped to resolve the issue of capital controls quickly, clearing the way for a final deal.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Zoellick apparently did not break down Singapore's resistance on another issue: its longtime ban on chewing gum, a prohibition ordered to keep the nation's streets and sidewalks cleaner.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
