<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coaches Hit Links and Talk Shop</title>
    <meta content="13NFFL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="PRO FOOTBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="929646"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cadillac Nfl Classic Golf Tournament</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970513T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DC1E39F930A25756C0A961958260" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coaches Hit Links and Talk Shop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <dateline>CLIFTON, N.J., May 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Outlook for Cadillac National Football League Golf Classic (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Cadillac National Football League Golf Classic began its fifth season today at the Upper Montclair Country Club with practice rounds for several PGA Senior Tour players, 56 National Football League players and 8 head coaches.</p>
        <p>With training camp only two months away, the coaches Lindy Infante, Jeff Fisher, Kevin Gilbride and Mike Ditka were in swing with football while swinging their golf clubs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Cadillac National Football League Golf Classic began its fifth season today at the Upper Montclair Country Club with practice rounds for several PGA Senior Tour players, 56 National Football League players and 8 head coaches.</p>
        <p>With training camp only two months away, the coaches Lindy Infante, Jeff Fisher, Kevin Gilbride and Mike Ditka were in swing with football while swinging their golf clubs.</p>
        <p>Infante saw his Indianapolis Colts wilt under injury last season. On the team's 53-man roster, 48 different players were starters. Then, during the off season, Infante had to deal with rumors that the Colts were trying to trade their star running back, Marshall Faulk.</p>
        <p>''I don't even want to talk about the injuries -- on a scale of 1 to 10, we had the worst case, a 10,'' Infante said. ''As far as Marshall is concerned, the people that talked about that just didn't know what they were talking about. First of all, when you trade a player like that, the bonuses in his contract are accelerated. There is no way we could stand that with our cap situation. But most importantly, Marshall is the No. 1 guy in our offense.''</p>
        <p>Fisher's Oilers would like to open training camp at the Tennessee State University campus in Nashville and play for the next two seasons at the Liberty Bowl in Memphis. In 1999 they would move into a new stadium in downtown Nashville.</p>
        <p>''That's our hope,'' Fisher said. ''Nothing has been decided yet. People ask me about the situation playing in Houston last year, and I don't like to make excuses. But look at it this way: We were 6-2 on the road and 2-6 at home. I think that speaks for itself.''</p>
        <p>Gilbride, who coached Jacksonvilles' offense as the Jaguars reached the American Football Conference championship game, is the San Diego Chargers' new coach.</p>
        <p>''We have some holes to fill,'' Gilbride said. ''We made our list and we've been filling them.''</p>
        <p>Signed via free agency from the Atlanta Falcons was the versatile back Eric Metcalf. Gained via the draft was North Carolina tight end Fred Jones.</p>
        <p>''More than anything, Metcalf gives us a chance to have a guy who can make impact plays on special teams,'' Gilbride said.</p>
        <p>Ditka was hired as Saints coach in January.</p>
        <p>''We've got a good staff and we have a lot of athleticism on this team,'' he said yesterday. ''We need to put a couple of players into the mix. And, most of all, we've got to change the attitude of the players and the organization. We've got to get them thinking that we, too, have the right to win. Why not us?''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
