<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democratic Official Admits Less Scrutiny of Donations</title>
    <meta content="02MONE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="POLITICS: THE FUND RAISERS" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="887154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICS: THE FUND RAISERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berke, Richard L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thornberry, B J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dodd, Christopher J (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fowler, Donald L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Huang, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1D71638F931A35752C1A960958260" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democratic Official Admits Less Scrutiny of Donations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berke, Richard L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Democratic National Committee executive director B J Thornberry acknowledges that the party had abandoned procedure set up years ago to detect contributions from donors with questionable backgrounds; Thornberry says she will take 'full responsibility' in place of party's two chairmen, Sen Christopher J Dodd and Donald L Fowler; Thornberry also says that John Huang, central figure in controversy who was party's chief fund raiser for Asian-Americans, was hired in December 1995 by Fowler at $60,000 annual salary; she says a position--vice chairman for finance--had been created for Huang to give him added status as he raised money among Asian-Americans (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A senior official of the Democratic National Committee, which has been under fire for accepting questionable campaign contributions, acknowledged today that the party had abandoned a procedure set up years ago to detect contributions from donors with questionable backgrounds.</p>
        <p>The admission came in an interview with B. J. Thornberry, the committee's executive director, who has kept a low public profile but was put forward today to answer for the party. She said she would take ''full responsibility'' in place of the party's two chairmen, Senator Christopher J. Dodd and Donald L. Fowler, who she said were too busy campaigning to address the questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A senior official of the Democratic National Committee, which has been under fire for accepting questionable campaign contributions, acknowledged today that the party had abandoned a procedure set up years ago to detect contributions from donors with questionable backgrounds.</p>
        <p>The admission came in an interview with B. J. Thornberry, the committee's executive director, who has kept a low public profile but was put forward today to answer for the party. She said she would take ''full responsibility'' in place of the party's two chairmen, Senator Christopher J. Dodd and Donald L. Fowler, who she said were too busy campaigning to address the questions.</p>
        <p>In the first extensive interview given by a party official in the wake of fund-raising questions that have engulfed the Democrats, Ms. Thornberry also said that John Huang, a central figure in the controversy who was the party's chief fund raiser for Asian-Americans, was hired in December 1995 by Mr. Fowler at a $60,000 annual salary. She said a position -- vice chairman for finance -- had been created for Mr. Huang to give him added status as he raised money among Asian-Americans. ''In this particular community, it was helpful for him to have a title,'' she said, adding that no one else had that title.</p>
        <p>Explaining why the Democrats did not have more stringent procedures for reviewing donations, Ms. Thornberry said the party had been so awash in cash and so understaffed that it depended on fund raisers to weed out suspicious donors. But past party officials recalled that in the 1992 and 1988 campaigns, there had been stricter procedures in place, including data-base searches and other checks of large donors.</p>
        <p>''Virtually any fund-raising compliance is very heavily reliant on the due diligence of the fund raiser,'' Ms. Thornberry said. She said there was ''no way in the world'' to do a data-base check on 25,000 to 30,000 checks. She went on: ''The problem with doing due diligence on contributors is, number one, you don't want to invade people's privacy. And you don't want to do your due diligence in a way that chills your fund-raising environment. So it's a very delicate process.''</p>
        <p>In recent days, Ms. Thornberry, who was hired only last March, said she had instituted new safeguards requiring that every check of more than $10,000 be ''personally reviewed'' by the party's legal counsel, who is to conduct a data-base check or other examination of first-time donors or other contributors who appear questionable. And the deputy legal counsel is to look at every check of any size.</p>
        <p>As part of its fresh effort to identify questionable donors, the Democratic National Committee said today that it was returning contributions totaling $75,000 from a Richard Tienken of New Jersey. Had the committee used a data base to vet those contributions earlier, it would have found news articles from 1991 detailing Federal District Court testimony by a Mafia informer in a racketeering trial that described a New Jersey man named Richard Tienken as having had business dealings with a captain in the Luchese crime family.</p>
        <p>In the interview, Ms. Thornberry said it had been her decision for the party not to file its most recent fund-raising report with the Federal Election Commission, a decision that broke a practice of two decades and was reversed after a firestorm of protest. She said the party's lawyers had told her such a report was not necessary because the money was not going directly to candidates for Federal office. As a result, she said, she did not want the party wasting time in the close of an election campaign completing the report.</p>
        <p>''Our deputy legal counsel was looking through a F.E.C. informational newsletter or something toward the end of September,'' Ms. Thornberry said of Neil Reiff, the deputy. She said that she, Mr. Reiff, and Joseph Sandler, the chief counsel, had discussed the matter and that she had decided there was no need to make the filing. ''It's important to know that we didn't have a meeting -- around here you kind of do things on the fly.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Thornberry said: ''Frankly, the light bulb didn't go on. And the reason it didn't go on was because so much else was happening. It's the most boneheaded thing I've ever done. Our error was not revisiting this -- and not putting it in a political context. We had created a perception that we were trying to hide something.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Thornberry insisted that neither she nor any other party official had approached the party's counsel about finding a way to avoid filing the report.</p>
        <p>Today, the party filed the 2,000-page pre-election report with the election commission. The report included at least one donation that was missing from a rough financial accounting that was released last Tuesday: $500,000 from Arnold Hiatt, chief executive officer of the Stride Rite Foundation, which is affiliated with the shoe manufacturer.</p>
        <p>The controversy over Mr. Huang, who has logged dozens of visits to the White House, took another turn today when the White House announced that there was another John Huang who works for Vice President Al Gore. Michael D. McCurry, the White House press secretary, said that at least 19 of the 75 recorded visits by a Mr. Huang to the White House between the summer of 1995 and the end of September were by the Mr. Huang who works for Mr. Gore.</p>
        <p>Ms. Thornberry, a former deputy chief of staff to Bruce Babbitt, the Interior Secretary, said she did not know any details of the purpose of the visits to the White House by the fund raiser Mr. Huang. She said she had been too busy with her other duties to look into his role.</p>
        <p>Ms. Thornberry said, however, that she had raised questions with the party's counsel, Mr. Sandler, when Mr. Huang said he was planning a trip last May to Taiwan. She said she had approved the trip after getting approval from the counsel.</p>
        <p>''Frankly, I had questions about that at the time,'' she said. ''I did not have conversations with John. But our legal counsel was satisfied that he had a very narrow scope of work: to see if there was any potential to raise money from Americans living abroad.'' She said her concern had been the trip's expense and ''whether it was an appropriate activity for somebody from the D.N.C.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Thornberry said that even before the new system of vetting donations had been in place, the party had a practice of returning donations from questionable sources. But of the eight such donations described by her and her staff, all have been returned in the weeks since the fund-raising controversy erupted.</p>
        <p>A former senior official at the Democratic National Committee, speaking on the condition of anonymity, said the party had far stricter procedures in the past. ''In the '88 campaign, at the D.N.C., we had a committee of lawyers who did a Lexis-Nexis on every contributor that came in over $10,000,'' the official said. ''We turned down six $100,000 checks because we were concerned about where they came from. If that had been done this time around, you wouldn't have had this situation with strange money coming in.''</p>
        <p>POLITICS: THE FUND RAISERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
