<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Approach: Slow and Steady</title>
    <meta content="Y12REV$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/12/technology/12REVI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1285041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Silicon Valley (Calif)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markoff, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/John Markoff</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Entrepreneurship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">San Francisco</location>
        <location class="online_producer">California</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Palo Alto</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Santa Clara</location>
        <location class="online_producer">San Jose</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Mountain View</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Sawhorse Partners</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Cisco Systems Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sun Microsystems Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Accel Partners</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Microsoft Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Levy, Steven</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Galanos, Greg</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1D91431F931A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1423" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Approach: Slow and Steady</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MARKOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Markoff, John</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Auctioning off computer hardware from failed dot-com companies signals that Silicon Valley is plunging into financial abyss unparalleled for decades in high-technology region, but it also shows that entrepreneurial fervor, if not gold-rush mentality, is still very much alive; some analysts worry about impact that such dot-com fire sales are having on equipment makers, most visible beneficiaries of boom, but many economists say recycling of equipment has been part of high-technology life cycle; employment remains surprisingly strong; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the junkyards, crushed cars and broken glass in this city's warehouse district, Walt Morton spends his days hunting for deals on computer hardware from failed dot-com companies.</p>
        <p>The auctioning off of the infrastructure of the not-so-new economy is one sign that Silicon Valley is plunging into a financial abyss unparalleled for decades in this high-technology region.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Among the junkyards, crushed cars and broken glass in this city's warehouse district, Walt Morton spends his days hunting for deals on computer hardware from failed dot-com companies.</p>
        <p>The auctioning off of the infrastructure of the not-so-new economy is one sign that Silicon Valley is plunging into a financial abyss unparalleled for decades in this high-technology region.</p>
        <p>At the same time, Mr. Morton and others like him are evidence that the entrepreneurial fervor that led to the boom is still very much alive, and that sprouts seem to be emerging from the rubble.</p>
        <p>As he examined a pizza-box-size server computer and an auctioneer barked out prices, Mr. Morton reflected that he might well be the first sign of a new era rather than an observer of the final moments of the old one.</p>
        <p>''All the people I know who lost their jobs are trying to start new companies,'' he said. But he added that their approach this time was radically different from the gold-rush mentality of the quickly fading dot-com era: ''We're part of a whole new wave of cheap start-ups.''</p>
        <p>A former executive at America Online who is now chief executive of an Internet start-up in San Francisco, Sawhorse Partners, Mr. Morton explores several auctions each week.</p>
        <p>''If these are cheap, enough I might buy a couple of them,'' he said, eyeing a stack of computers sitting in a corner of a warehouse. He estimated that the infrastructure he built for his last start-up at a cost of $200,000 would now be less than $18,000.</p>
        <p>The shift in the market has created an unfamiliar paralysis among Silicon Valley's venture capitalists, many of whom have a dazed look as they watch previous bad investments crumble and try to figure out what the next hot investment will be. As a result, the area's venture-capital-to-entrepreneur ecosystem has abruptly stalled, at least temporarily.</p>
        <p>While some analysts have worried about the impact that such dot-com fire sales are having on equipment makers like Cisco, Dell and Sun Microsystems, the most visible beneficiaries of the boom, many economists noted that the recycling of  equipment has always been a part of the high-technology life cycle, in which most start-up companies either fail or are acquired. Employment, at this point, remains surprisingly strong.</p>
        <p>''I think the whole dot-com layoff thing has been blown out of perspective,'' said Steven Levy, an economist at the Center for the Continuing Study of the California Economy, in Palo Alto, noting that in the last three months, the San Francisco Bay area has recorded historically low unemployment rates.</p>
        <p>The California Employment Development Department reported this month that the state's unemployment rate dropped to 4.5 percent in February, a 32-year low. (It was 4.4 percent in December 1969.) The unemployment rate last month in Santa Clara County, which largely defines Silicon Valley, was 1.7 percent, indicating that only 17,600 people were jobless in a work force of 1,004,900.</p>
        <p>Even in San Francisco, which has been more dependent on e-commerce start-ups, unemployment was 3.2 percent, up from 2.6 last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Morton is one sign that while the dot-com bubble has burst and expectations have been ''reset'' -- in the current jargon of the e-commerce neighborhood known as South of Market Street -- the start-up culture here is now deeply ingrained.</p>
        <p>Big Storage, a South-of-Market start-up with 30 employees that largely missed the dot-com boom, turned profitable in March, two months ahead of schedule. The company, which sells Linux-based disk arrays to companies that need large data storage systems, once felt embarrassed that it was not on the public offering bandwagon but was now finding it easier to expand.</p>
        <p>''Last year, each month I would apologize to my board of directors for not finding more business,'' said Big Storage's chief executive, Sam Bogach. Now, he says, missing the boom was a blessing.</p>
        <p>Many Silicon Valley executives said the shift was away from the era of easy-money dot-com start-ups and  back to a climate that more closely resembled the original Silicon Valley up-from-the-garage ethos.</p>
        <p>''You're no longer viewed as a loser if you have a cheap office space; you're perceived as smart,'' said Paul Kocher, chief executive of Cryptography Research, who is financing a small start-up to develop an e-commerce application.</p>
        <p>Indeed, it may be that venture capitalists, who until recently were among the biggest beneficiaries of the boom, are now the biggest victims of the downturn.</p>
        <p>''The V.C.'s are hiding under their desks right now,'' said Anthony Perkins, co-author of ''The Internet Bubble,'' a 1999 book that predicted the dot-com shake-out.</p>
        <p>''Most of them,'' Mr. Perkins said,  ''are facing up to the fact of whatever percentage of their deals that were stupid. They're shooting all the lame horses.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perkins's company, Red Herring Communications, which publishes the business and technology magazine Red Herring, had a round of layoffs not long ago, but Mr. Perkins said that when he checked recently, he discovered that all but one of the former employees had found a  job -- and that the one person was not looking.</p>
        <p>Of 742 venture capital firms in Silicon Valley, he said, 192 were created within the last 18 months, a situation that will inevitably lead to a pruning of the venture community in the months ahead. That, in turn, will lead to a consolidation in the power and influence of venture firms like  Sequoia and Kleiner Perkins Caufield &amp; Byers.</p>
        <p>And if the venture capital industry is in shock, that has created a domino effect among start-up companies.</p>
        <p>''These guys are schizo right now,'' said David House, chief executive of Allegro Networks, a start-up router company in San Jose, Calif. ''They've just raised their billion-dollar funds and they're scared. Now everyone wants to be the second guy to invest, not the first.''</p>
        <p>From the point of view of the venture capitalists, the entrepreneurs have also grown more cautious.</p>
        <p>''We think it's a wonderful time to be a bold entrepreneur,'' said Jim Breyer, managing partner of Accel Partners in Palo Alto, Calif. ''But unfortunately we're not seeing a lot of people with those ideas. It's too bad.''</p>
        <p>The current period, Mr. Breyer said, was similar to the one venture capitalists went through in the late 1980's and early 1990's, when most people thought Microsoft had won the PC platform wars and they were only interested in incremental ideas.</p>
        <p>Today, most executives here remain convinced that the Internet is not a fad and that it has only begun to transform the economy. But they are now grasping for specific trends, with profit potential, to seize upon.</p>
        <p>''There are no fads right now,'' said Sheldon Breiner, a longtime Silicon Valley inventor who is now an independent investor. ''Six months ago it was optical switching and a year ago it was business-to-business, but now I don't know of a fad.''</p>
        <p>There are those who said that the absence of fads was a good thing and that the economy in Silicon Valley was being led back to its fundamentals in technology, where it has always excelled.</p>
        <p>''Two years ago you couldn't recruit anyone into the semiconductor industry,'' said Andrew Rappaport, a partner at August Capital, a venture firm in Menlo Park, Calif. ''They all wanted to go to a dot-com. Now they're all coming back and the talent pool is growing.''</p>
        <p>And some venture capitalists remain enthusiastic, certain that they are only one company away from the Next Big Thing.</p>
        <p>''We've gone from irrational exuberance to irrational pessimism,'' said Greg Galanos, a partner at Softbank Venture Capital in Mountain View, Calif., adding: ''Have I told you about Danger Research? Wait until you see what they're doing!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
