<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Collusion Checks Are Signal of End Of Owners' Error</title>
    <meta content="25CHAS$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/25/sports/baseball/25chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1584414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chass, Murray</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Steinbrenner, George</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7DC143EF936A15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Collusion Checks Are Signal of End Of Owners' Error</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">End of the Owners' Error: The Collusion Checks Are In</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Murray Chass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Murray Chass On Baseball column discusses $280 million settlement for Major League Baseball owners' collusion and distribution of checks to more than 650 players for damage done by owners conspiring to keep players at certain salaries (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JACK MORRIS, the star free-agent pitcher, offered George Steinbrenner the opportunity to have an arbitrator decide his salary. Andre Dawson, another star free agent, gave Dallas Green, the Cubs' general manager, a signed contract with the salary line left blank, to be filled in by Green.</p>
        <p>Ah, the good old days of collusion. They are gone now, at least those days of collusion. Some people on the players' side -- agents, for example -- suspect they are operating in new days of collusion. But the old days are finally over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some people on the players' side - agents, for example - suspect they are operating in new days of collusion. But the old days are finally over.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JACK MORRIS, the star free-agent pitcher, offered George Steinbrenner the opportunity to have an arbitrator decide his salary. Andre Dawson, another star free agent, gave Dallas Green, the Cubs' general manager, a signed contract with the salary line left blank, to be filled in by Green.</p>
        <p>Ah, the good old days of collusion. They are gone now, at least those days of collusion. Some people on the players' side -- agents, for example -- suspect they are operating in new days of collusion. But the old days are finally over.</p>
        <p>With the distribution of checks to more than 650 players containing interest payments on damage awards the players previously received, the case is closed 18 years after it began and 13 years after the owners agreed to pay the players $280 million as settlement for their transgressions -- which they have never admitted, incidentally.</p>
        <p>The only management person who is known to have acknowledged collusion publicly -- and it preceded him -- was Fay Vincent. Even his predecessor as commissioner, Bart Giamatti, rejected the notion that the owners had conspired to keep players in their places and their salaries in check by declining to sign other teams' free agents.</p>
        <p>Even though two arbitrators had found the owners guilty of violating the collective bargaining agreement in 1985 and forward, Giamatti, upon becoming commissioner in 1989, said, ''I myself for the last two years have seen what they seem to have seen from a somewhat different angle.''</p>
        <p>The current commissioner, Bud Selig, who operated the Brewers in those days and was a major force in the owners' labor efforts, has always refrained from discussing collusion, as recently as yesterday.</p>
        <p>Whether or not they admitted their guilt, the owners paid for it, though they got away cheaply. Had they played the free-agent game fairly and above board, they most likely would have spent more than an additional $280 million on player salaries.</p>
        <p>Not only did they get a good deal on the settlement figure, but the accord put the onus of distribution on the union. When all checks were written, the total, with interest, came not to $280 million, but $434 million.</p>
        <p>''A money manager in Nashville managed the money under the guidelines of the framework of the settlement,'' Steve Rogers, the former pitcher, now a union official, said. ''It was very conservatively invested.''</p>
        <p>The list of awards takes up 67 pages, single-spaced. The list, a copy of which was obtained by The New York Times, shows that 10 players who are still playing received awards, as did 12 former players who are now major league managers and 14 former players who now are Hall of Fame players.</p>
        <p>In other words, the payout period lasted so long players had time to retire and observe their mandatory five-year waiting period for entry into Cooperstown. ''It had a heartbeat of its own,'' Rogers said.</p>
        <p>When someone told Michael Weiner, another union official, that it was hard to believe it had taken this long but also hard to believe it was over, he said, ''I'd agree with both of those statements.''</p>
        <p>The process that the union developed to be as fair as possible to players is what created the extended procedure. Players filed claims (about 4,500), the union developed a framework of distribution, players filed objections if they so chose, and hearings were held on the objections.</p>
        <p>Tom Roberts and George Nicolau, the arbitrators who heard the grievances that found the owners guilty of collusion, presided over the objection hearings. From that point, Roberts supervised the distribution of the settlement funds.</p>
        <p>Only one player, Steve Garvey, strayed outside the system. Awarded only a pittance ($5,000), he sued in federal court and lost. He won on appeal, but the case went to the Supreme Court, which overturned the appellate court ruling.</p>
        <p>Like the other players who received awards, Garvey gained additional money in interest and wound up with $9,146.64, a far distance from the largest awards.</p>
        <p>Bob Horner, who last played in 1988, gained the biggest award, $7,034,112, including interest. He was followed by Lance Parrish, $5,866,599; Jack Clark, $4,406,238; Doyle Alexander, $4,068,115; Kirk Gibson, $3,710,398, and Doug DeCinces, $3,709,504.</p>
        <p>Morris, whom the Yankees never did sign, much to Steinbrenner's agony, received $3,124,615. That collusion existed was evident when Steinbrenner let him walk out of his hotel in Tampa that December day in 1986 unsigned. Finding no other teams interested in him, Morris re-signed with Detroit.</p>
        <p>Collusion reared its ugly head, too, in the Dawson case. Richard Moss, who served as the agent for Morris and Dawson, recalled yesterday a lunch he had with Dallas Green when Dawson was a free agent.</p>
        <p>''I went to Chicago and met with Dallas; we had lunch at a hotel near the airport,'' Moss said. ''He told me he was drooling for Dawson and would love to sign him, but couldn't under the rules right now. When we gave them the blank contract, he feigned outrage at the contract, but he was delighted.''</p>
        <p>Filling in the blank to complete the contract and sign Dawson, Green wrote $650,000, but only $500,000 guaranteed. Dawson's interest-enhanced award was $3,281,146.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
