<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lewis Runs Over Falcons, and Defense Runs Down Vick</title>
    <meta content="20ravens" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/20/sports/football/20ravens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1806232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Atlanta Falcons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Baltimore Ravens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Baltimore Ravens</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Atlanta Falcons</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lewis, Jamal</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E2D9153EF933A15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lewis Runs Over Falcons, and Defense Runs Down Vick</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Lewis Runs Over Falcons, and Defense Runs Down Vick</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM HIMMELSBACH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Himmelsbach, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE, Nov. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Wearing a black knit cap, black wind pants and a gray-and-purple warm-up shirt, Ray Lewis paced the sideline at M&amp;T Bank Stadium, antsy as ever.</p>
        <p>Lewis, the Baltimore Ravens' All-Pro linebacker, missed his second consecutive game because of a bruised back, and he could only watch as his teammates faced the Atlanta Falcons on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Running back Jamal Lewis scored three touchdowns to sending the Ravens to a victory over the Falcons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Wearing a black knit cap, black wind pants and a gray-and-purple warm-up shirt, Ray Lewis paced the sideline at M&amp;T Bank Stadium, antsy as ever.</p>
        <p>Lewis, the Baltimore Ravens' All-Pro linebacker, missed his second consecutive game because of a bruised back, and he could only watch as his teammates faced the Atlanta Falcons on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''He said he'd give anything to get one snap,'' Ravens defensive end Trevor Pryce said. ''And you looked in his eyes and he was serious, dead serious.''</p>
        <p>After running back Jamal Lewis scored his third touchdown of the game, sending the Ravens to a 24-10 victory, Ray Lewis could no longer help himself.</p>
        <p>Jamal Lewis jogged to the sideline, and his teammates patted his helmet. When he reached Ray Lewis, who stood near a bench, he received a celebratory shoulder bump, sending him to a seat.</p>
        <p>For Ray Lewis, it was not quite chasing Michael Vick, the Falcons' dynamic quarterback, but the rest of the Baltimore defense had taken care of that on a cool and cloudy afternoon. The Ravens sacked Vick five times and did not allow him to become comfortable in the pocket.</p>
        <p>The Falcons, who entered the game averaging a league-high 198.9 rushing yards, were held to 186 total yards, 104 of which came on the ground. Vick completed 11 of 21 passes for 127 yards and ran for 54 yards on six carries.</p>
        <p>''He's really elusive,'' Ravens linebacker Bart Scott said of Vick. ''But when you have a shot, you have to take it, because those shots add up.''</p>
        <p>It was the third loss in a row for the Falcons (5-5), who three weeks ago seemed destined for a National Football Conference playoff berth but are now as wobbly as a table with a bad leg. The Falcons played without their injured defensive ends, Patrick Kerney and John Abraham, and the injured cornerbacks Jason Webster and Jimmy Williams.</p>
        <p>''What are you going to do, quit?'' Falcons Coach Jim Mora said. ''That's what people do who don't love to compete.''</p>
        <p>For the Ravens (8-2), Sunday's win continued an offensive renaissance that began four weeks and four wins ago, when Coach Brian Billick fired the offensive coordinator, Jim Fassel, and took over the play calling. After averaging 14.8 points in the season's first six games, Baltimore's offense has averaged 22.7 points since Billick took the reins Oct. 29.</p>
        <p>Baltimore quarterback Steve McNair has been a steadying influence during his team's streak, but until Sunday, Jamal Lewis had done little to complement him.</p>
        <p>Lewis ran for 2,066 yards and 14 touchdowns in 2003, but he was indicted on federal drug conspiracy charges in February 2004. That October, he pleaded guilty to using a cellphone to help set up a drug deal.</p>
        <p>Lewis was suspended for two games in the 2004 season and served a four-month prison term after the season. Last season, Lewis ran for a career-low 906 yards. Before Sunday's game, he had scored only two touchdowns and was averaging 64.2 yards a game this season.</p>
        <p>But against the Falcons, Lewis notched the second three-touchdown game of his career and finished with 91 yards on 22 carries.</p>
        <p>''It kind of felt like old times,'' said Lewis, who is from Atlanta. ''It's really not me; it's the offensive line just pushing guys down the field.''</p>
        <p>After trudging through a nondescript first half, with the only points coming on a 13-yard touchdown pass from Vick to Michael Jenkins, the Ravens controlled the third quarter.</p>
        <p>Matt Stover's 29-yard field goal made the score 7-3, and the Ravens forced Atlanta to punt after three plays.</p>
        <p>B. J. Sams returned the punt 59 yards to the Falcons' 17. Sams was a spark throughout the game, totaling 212 return yards, the second most ever allowed by Atlanta.</p>
        <p>On third-and-goal from the 2, Lewis found a canyon-size opening on a draw play and darted across the goal line, giving Baltimore a 10-7 lead with 4 minutes 32 seconds to play in the quarter. The Falcons tied the score at 10-10 with Morten Andersen's 21-yard field goal two and a half minutes later, but Sams took the ensuing kickoff 59 yards to the Atlanta 37.</p>
        <p>McNair hit tight end Todd Heap for 9 yards on first down, and Lewis motored for 12 yards on second down. On first down from the 16, Lewis took a hit at the 2 and fell backward into the end zone.</p>
        <p>''Jamal was determined to get the extra yard even when he had three guys on his back,'' McNair said of Lewis, who added a 5-yard touchdown run late in the fourth quarter. ''And that's the determination we're used to seeing from him.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
