<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Food Notes</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="720806"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941026T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E0D7153FF935A15753C1A962958260" item-length="966" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Food Notes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Florence Fabricant</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Merchants' Halloween</p>
        <p>A number of food shops and restaurants in Greenwich Village will be doling out Halloween treats to children from 3 to 5:30 P.M. on Monday.</p>
        <p>The door-to-door Halloween party, in the Bleecker Street neighborhood between the Avenue of the Americas and Seventh Avenue, is sponsored by a new group called Merchants of Greenwich, organized by Ken Lipsmeyer, the owner of 9 Jones Street restaurant. Each participating shop and restaurant will display a large orange sign with a pumpkin. Children must be accompanied by an adult.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Merchants' Halloween</p>
        <p>A number of food shops and restaurants in Greenwich Village will be doling out Halloween treats to children from 3 to 5:30 P.M. on Monday.</p>
        <p>The door-to-door Halloween party, in the Bleecker Street neighborhood between the Avenue of the Americas and Seventh Avenue, is sponsored by a new group called Merchants of Greenwich, organized by Ken Lipsmeyer, the owner of 9 Jones Street restaurant. Each participating shop and restaurant will display a large orange sign with a pumpkin. Children must be accompanied by an adult.</p>
        <p>In Westchester, Mrs. Green's Natural Market, 780 White Plains Road, Eastchester, will hold a pre-Halloween party with samples of healthy snacks to encourage children to choose these over junk food. The event will start on Saturday at noon. Children should come in costume. Help for Pie Crusts</p>
        <p>As fall's apple crop finds its way into pies, bakers might be interested in a new gadget, Mrs. Anderson's Pie Crust Shield. This simple re-usable metal ring is placed on the crimped edge of the crust to prevent it from over-browning. It also helps keep the rim of the crust in place.</p>
        <p>It was invented by Georgette Anderson of Portland, Ore., who donated the design to the Challenge Center, a rehabilitation agency there, where it is being manufactured. The center receives income from the sale of the shield.</p>
        <p>It is sold at Zabar's, 81st Street and Broadway, for $1.59, and at Complete Kitchen, 863 Post Road, Darien, Conn., for $4.95. Bakery on Avenue A</p>
        <p>Sticky Fingers, a sliver of a bake shop at 131 Avenue A (near Ninth Street), is more generally known by its nickname, Sticky's. It should also be known for its excellent coffeecake -- Grandma's sour-cream cake -- veined with nuts and cinnamon, $7; and for tasty muffins, including blackberry-walnut and apple-bran, $1.80 each. The bakery does a better job with these homey items than with massive, dense brownies, $1.75. A Move for Chez Bernard</p>
        <p>Bernard Eloy, whose small butcher shop on Thompson Street in SoHo also carried prepared foods, has moved to larger quarters: Chez Bernard, 323 West Broadway (near Canal Street), also in SoHo. Now there are tables where customers can order his French-style ham on baguettes, plates of good country pate and duck mousse, as well as other charcuterie, salads and baked goods.</p>
        <p>Small cafe tables share the airy front room with a large farmhouse table that seats up to 14 people. Sandwiches are $4.25 to $5.95 to take out and about a dollar more if eaten at the tables. Mr. Eloy also prepares platters and does catering. He can be reached at (212) 343-2583. Gift to Culinary Institute</p>
        <p>Colavita USA, which has been importing olive oil from Italy to America since 1978, has given $1.5 million to the Culinary Institute of America in Hyde Park, N.Y. The money will be used to build and run the Colavita Center for Italian Cuisine on the Hyde Park campus. It will permit regional Italian cooking to be a regular part of the school's curriculum. Another $1.5 million has to be raised to finance the project fully. Chocolate for a Cause</p>
        <p>Here's a lush, adult treat not just for Halloween. PB Select is a new, elegant little candy bar made of ultra-creamy peanut butter in milk chocolate and sold mostly in fancy food stores and groceries. It comes in two sizes: 1.5 ounces for about 70 cents and half an ounce for 25 cents.</p>
        <p>Some of the proceeds from the bars, which are marketed by Public Label Brands in Pittsburgh, are donated to the Ryan Fund, an organization in Philadelphia that supports camps for children with muscular dystrophy.</p>
        <p>And to put a bit of a damper on the delight, the label reveals that eating a bar will add 300 calories, more than half of them from fat, to the day's count.  Paris Restaurant Guide</p>
        <p>Just added to the series of handsome Knopf Guides to various cities and countries is a lavish one devoted entirely to Parisian restaurants. "Restaurants of Paris" (Knopf Guides, Alfred A. Knopf, $25) features detailed profiles of 100 significant restaurants and then gives the basics for these as well as for another 250 places.</p>
        <p>There is a surfeit of lists and charts focusing on the food, prices, features, specialties and, for many of them, Michelin ratings comparing 1993 with 1973. The book is crammed with color illustrations and maps and is only slightly larger than a well-stuffed Filofax.</p>
        <p>Missing are popular spots like the venerable L'Ami Louis, the hot new La Regalade and the Relais du Parc, where Joel Robuchon is the consultant.</p>
        <p>The guide gives a history of Parisian restaurants, charts of ingredients (which would have been helpful in French as well as in English), writers' and artists' views of various Parisian restaurants and information about ethnic cuisines and wine.  Wine and Food Tastings</p>
        <p>Some wine and food tastings to put on the calendar include a free sampling of nonalcoholic wines made in Europe, tomorrow and Saturday from 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. at Dean &amp; DeLuca, 560 Broadway, at Prince Street.</p>
        <p>A Taste of Hoboken, to benefit the Hoboken-North Hudson Y.M.C.A., will be held tomorrow from 6:30 to 9:30 P.M. at Stevens Institute of Technology in Hoboken, N.J. Tickets are $30 and will be sold at the door. For information: (201) 963-4100.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Wine Council is holding a wine and food tasting Tuesday from 6 to 8:30 P.M. at the Puck Building, 295 Lafayette Street (at Houston Street) to benefit the James Beard Foundation. Tickets, $60, must be purchased in advance from the foundation, (212) 675-4984.</p>
        <p>The Puck Building will also be the venue for a food and wine tasting, on Nov. 3 from 7 to 10 P.M., to benefit the Momentum Project, an organization that helps people with AIDS. Tickets, $100, can be reserved by calling (212) 987-3350.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
