<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gordon Lights Up Daytona And Nears Another Title</title>
    <meta content="19AUTO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055327"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="HORSE RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pepsi 400 (Auto Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Bashir, Tarik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gordon, Jeff</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Wheel Spin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobile Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D6163DF93AA25753C1A96E958260" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gordon Lights Up Daytona And Nears Another Title</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARIK EL-BASHIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Bashir, Tarik</byline>
      <dateline>DAYTONA, Fla., Oct. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeff Gordon wins Pepsi 400 auto race at Daytona, Fla; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Champagne is not on ice just yet, but it certainly looks as if Jeff Gordon will soon be celebrating another Nascar Winston Cup championship, his second straight and third in four years.</p>
        <p>Gordon took his 11th checkered flag this season and got his first career victory in October on Saturday night in the Pepsi 400 at Daytona International Speedway, the first stock car race under the lights there. The victory gave Gordon a 358-point lead over Mark Martin, who, with just three races left on the schedule, has virtually no chance of catching him. Martin, driving a Ford, finished 16th on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Champagne is not on ice just yet, but it certainly looks as if Jeff Gordon will soon be celebrating another Nascar Winston Cup championship, his second straight and third in four years.</p>
        <p>Gordon took his 11th checkered flag this season and got his first career victory in October on Saturday night in the Pepsi 400 at Daytona International Speedway, the first stock car race under the lights there. The victory gave Gordon a 358-point lead over Mark Martin, who, with just three races left on the schedule, has virtually no chance of catching him. Martin, driving a Ford, finished 16th on Saturday.</p>
        <p>Gordon, who has scored top-five finishes in the each of the last three restrictor-plate races, can, with a good run, clinch the title next week at Phoenix. He needs to finish 32d or better in each of the final three races, at Phoenix, Rockingham, N.C., and Atlanta.</p>
        <p>''Awesome! Awesome!'' Gordon's crew chief, Ray Evernham, shouted over the radio as the No. 24 Dupont Monte Carlo hit the finish line. ''Hey, Jeff, it's October, buddy, it's October.''</p>
        <p>To which Gordon replied: ''You better believe it. Yes it is. Yes it is.''</p>
        <p>Gordon, who had 39 career victories before Saturday but had become notorious for registering them before October, took the lead for good with 37 laps remaining.</p>
        <p>The race was red-flagged because of rain with six laps to go and ended under caution when a car spun on the final lap. Gordon piloted his Chevy around the 2.5-mile, high-banked oval at an average speed of 144.549 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>''We figured that somebody would say this was actually a July race that was run in October,'' Gordon said after winning his 40th.</p>
        <p>Saturday's race was originally scheduled for July 4th, but raging forest fires and smoke in the surrounding area forced its postponement. The fires, which charred more than 30,000 acres, came within one mile of the speedway.</p>
        <p>Bobby Labonte, who won the pole last Thursday, continued his success in restrictor-plate races, driving his way back from seventh place to take second. Mike Skinner was third.</p>
        <p>''I thought we were going to run on Gordon off Turn 4 there,'' Labonte said, referring to an inside move he made on the race leader in the last lap. ''But I didn't get any help.''</p>
        <p>In addition to being the first stock car race under the lights at Daytona, the race marked the first time in the series that restrictor plates, which limit horsepower and thus speed, had been used on the cars in consecutive weeks. (Talladega, the only other track where cars are fitted with restrictor plates, was the site of the previous weekend's race.)</p>
        <p>About the new lighting system at Daytona, Gordon said: ''The lights were fantastic. I think they did a great job here. There was no problem from the drivers' standpoint as far as shadows.''</p>
        <p>PIT STOPS</p>
        <p>Winston announced this week that it would continue the million-dollar bonus program next season. The ''No Bull 5'' $1 million-dollar bonus, which was created this season to celebrate Nascar's 50th anniversary, was handed out three times to drivers (twice to JEFF GORDON and once to DALE JARRETT) and three times to fans. Next year, the five bonus races will be the Daytona 500, Las Vegas 400, Coca-Cola 600, Pepsi Southern 500 and Winston 500.</p>
        <p>HORSE RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
