<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="19DIGE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055286"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2DB163DF93AA25753C1A96E958260" item-length="871" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Possible Kroger Merger Draws Traders' Interest  Wall Street is speculating that the Kroger Company, the nation's largest supermarket chain, will buy Fred Meyer, the owner of the Ralphs Grocery chain in Southern California, in a move that would create the first grocery chain spanning most of the nation.</p>
        <p>Fred Meyer's shares soared $3.6875, or 8 percent, to $49 on the New York Stock Exchange on Friday. The stock has gained 27 percent since Oct. 8. Kroger's shares fell $1.1875, to $48.75. [Page C8.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Possible Kroger Merger Draws Traders' Interest  Wall Street is speculating that the Kroger Company, the nation's largest supermarket chain, will buy Fred Meyer, the owner of the Ralphs Grocery chain in Southern California, in a move that would create the first grocery chain spanning most of the nation.</p>
        <p>Fred Meyer's shares soared $3.6875, or 8 percent, to $49 on the New York Stock Exchange on Friday. The stock has gained 27 percent since Oct. 8. Kroger's shares fell $1.1875, to $48.75. [Page C8.]</p>
        <p>When a Loss Could Be a Victory  In the Byzantine world of telecommunications regulation, a loss before the United States Supreme Court could turn out to be a victory for local telephone companies, when it comes to the prices long-distance companies pay for access to local networks. News Analysis. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Celebrating Every Man's Inner Guy  Maxim, described by magazine consultants as the Playboy of the 1990's, is an unlikely success story at a time when the competition in the men's magazine market is heated and most men's titles are aiming for a sophisticated, advertiser-friendly audience. Instead of encouraging sophistication, Maxim encourages its readers to exist in a perpetual state of chest-thumping, girl-chasing, adolescent jokesterism. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Helping World Spend Its Free Time  Time Out, the listings magazine that began 30 years ago in a London basement, has found its way in the world. The magazine's name now adorns not just editions in London and New York, but also franchises in Rome and Paris, along with an array of eating, drinking and shopping guides. [C4.]</p>
        <p>Perils of Covering Parent Company  A shelved investigative report by an ABC News reporter about hiring and safety practices at Disney World, the Florida theme park owned by ABC's parent, Walt Disney, illustrates the thorny problems journalists have in examining their own companies. [C8.]</p>
        <p>Debate Over Census of Newsrooms  As the governing board of the American Society of Newspaper Editors prepares to meet in Miami tomorrow, a proposal that women be counted in the annual newsroom census of minority journalists will most likely provoke a good deal of debate. [C6.]</p>
        <p>Levi Ads Focus on Gay Consumers  Intensifying its efforts to reach younger, more fashion-conscious consumers, Levi Strauss, the nation's largest apparel advertiser, is embarking on its most ambitious marketing campaign aimed at gay men and lesbians. Levi Strauss is one of a growing number of companies aiming sales pitches at gays and lesbians for products from cars to computers. Stuart Elliott: Advertising. [C11.]</p>
        <p>Congress Rewrites Copyright Law  Congress moved to rewrite American copyright law earlier this month when it passed two hotly contested pieces of legislation concerning extended protection for 20th-century cultural icons and infringement on line. Sabra Chartrand: Patents. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Lawmakers finished work on a number of other bills affecting the information technology industry, receiving high marks from the industry despite failing to act on several pieces of legislation. [C6.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
