<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chip Thieves Are Arrested After a Sting In California</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="833593"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROBBERIES AND THEFTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTER CHIPS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAN JOSE (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SILICON VALLEY (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION (FBI) FEDERAL BUREAU OFINVESTIGATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, CAREY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/San Jose</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDF1E39F932A35750C0A960958260" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chip Thieves Are Arrested After a Sting In California</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAREY GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, CAREY</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Feb. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The armed robbers of Silicon Valley were striking high-tech companies every 10 days or so, making off with computer chips and other components worth more than their weight in gold. With workers terrorized and losses in the millions, the F.B.I. and the San Jose police began an undercover operation 18 months ago.</p>
        <p>By today, in the wake of the biggest crackdown on thieves of computer components in the country, dozens of suspected high-tech brigands were under arrest, caught in a sweeping raid that involved more than 500 police and Federal officers on Wednesday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The armed robbers of Silicon Valley were striking high-tech companies every 10 days or so, making off with computer chips and other components worth more than their weight in gold. With workers terrorized and losses in the millions, the F.B.I. and the San Jose police began an undercover operation 18 months ago.</p>
        <p>By today, in the wake of the biggest crackdown on thieves of computer components in the country, dozens of suspected high-tech brigands were under arrest, caught in a sweeping raid that involved more than 500 police and Federal officers on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The operation led to more than 120 arrests mainly in Silicon Valley, about 45 of them on Wednesday and the rest over recent months, the authorities said today.</p>
        <p>"It's like Willie Sutton 50 years ago," said Lee Altschuler, chief of the United States Attorney's Office in San Jose. "'Why do you rob banks?' 'Because that's where the money is.' "</p>
        <p>Silicon Valley has been plagued, Mr. Altschuler said, by "very sophisticated, armed takeover robberies where people would go in with handguns, long guns, and  semi-automatic weapons in a sort of paramilitary style, armed with duct tape and Flexicuffs, and in a very short time steal chips."</p>
        <p>The thieves typically depend on insiders for intelligence on where and how to steal the chips, which are flecks of processed silicon used for computer memory  and other functions. Then they sell them on a thriving gray market, offering them to computer makers in Asia or re-selling them in the United States.</p>
        <p>Part of the chips' allure is that they are so tiny that a thief can easily walk away with hundreds of thousands of dollars' worth in a small paper bag. And because most chips have no serial numbers, they cannot be traced.</p>
        <p>The Federal Bureau of Investigation hopes that would-be chip thieves will now be likelier to think twice, said Mark J. Mershon, who heads the agency's San Francisco division and who oversaw the operation, because "they won't know whether the next person they're introduced to is an undercover F.B.I. or police  person."</p>
        <p>More than 400 Silicon Valley businesses had been robbed by chip thieves in the last 18 months. The businesses range from giants like Sun Microsystems to small companies of 100 employees. The apparent record for a heist was $9.9 million worth of computer parts stolen from Centon Electronics in Irvine, Calif., in May.</p>
        <p>The F.B.I. said the undercover operation had focused on four violent gangs and named four men as masterminds: Nam Pham, 40, of San Jose; Minh Duong, 43, of Santa Clara; Thach Tran, 28, of San Jose; and Binh Dong, 40, of Milpitas -- all of them arrested on Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The suspects captured in the sweep on Wednesday were variously accused of armed robberies at warehouses, trafficking in crack cocaine, kidnapping executives, selling machine guns and dealing in stolen property, among lesser crimes. So far, no one has been killed in a Silicon Valley computer robbery.</p>
        <p>Central to the undercover operation was a phony storefront business in San Jose called Prospect Distribution, an invitation-only enterprise in which law-enforcement officers used hidden video cameras and tape recorders to capture clients' incriminating actions.</p>
        <p>The chip thieves had sophisticated set-ups of their own, hiding behind business fronts with names like Computer Component Sales and engaging in elaborate counter-surveillance around the companies they planned to rob, the authorities said. They relied on various methods to get inside help, from intimidating security guards to leaning on employees with gambling debts.</p>
        <p>Responding to the growing crime threat, many companies have moved away from the casual atmosphere that once characterized their premises toward something of a fortress approach. Because trucks are easily hijacked, some companies have switched to armored cars for chip shipments; many have also installed security cameras, instituted strict searches and cut down on inventory.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mershon said that he could not say how many of the 400 robberies had been committed by those under arrest but that he believed that it was "a very large percentage."</p>
        <p>Three armed men were caught on Wednesday as they were on their way to commit  another robbery, the San Jose police said, and investigators with the Internal Revenue Service are following the trail of money from sales of stolen chips, hoping to to make more arrests.</p>
        <p>"Yesterday's arrests took out, root and branch, a significant number of defendants," Mr. Altschuler said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
