<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports Of The Times;O'Donnell Comes Into The Billfold</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="833612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREE AGENTS (SPORTS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PITTSBURGH STEELERS NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARATON, HARVEY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'DONNELL, NEIL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Harvey Araton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Pittsburgh Steelers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E6DE1E39F932A35750C0A960958260" item-length="797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports Of The Times;O'Donnell Comes Into The Billfold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ARATON, HARVEY</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, L.I.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HE walked across the small stage to the podium with the facing green helmets, and his first message for the starving fans of the worst team in professional football was a promise to present himself in a manner befitting a team whose coach lines players up in numerical order for the national anthem.</p>
        <p>"I apologize for the outfit," Neil O'Donnell said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HE walked across the small stage to the podium with the facing green helmets, and his first message for the starving fans of the worst team in professional football was a promise to present himself in a manner befitting a team whose coach lines players up in numerical order for the national anthem.</p>
        <p>"I apologize for the outfit," Neil O'Donnell said.</p>
        <p>Coincidentally or not, he was dressed in black, a Pittsburgh Steelers color, and charcoal gray. As if to demonstrate how uncertain he may have been about leaving a Super Bowl team for the 3-13 Jets, he said there just wasn't enough time to find something green. "I'll have to check the closet," O'Donnell said.</p>
        <p>He might be better off going to his wallet.</p>
        <p>No matter how many times O'Donnell reiterated his longtime desire to call Giants Stadium home, it could not have been the uniform that brought him here. Home? Just to get to the Jets' Hofstra University practice facility, O'Donnell had to span two toll bridges and the Cross County parkway from his off-season residence in Morris County, N.J.</p>
        <p>O'Donnell is the Jets' new quarterback today because Leon Hess pumped more fuel into his pocket than Pittsburgh was willing to. The Steelers have a couple  of less expensive young quarterbacks, Kordell Stewart and Jim Miller, to console them. The Jets had a roster to overhaul, and plenty of money with which to work.</p>
        <p>This notion of performing for family and friends can be overrated, O'Donnell  being a case in point. He is the youngest of nine children, which meant he and his wife, Leslie, spent the two weeks before the last Super Bowl playing ticket- and hotel-booking agent.</p>
        <p>"Let's close the chapter on the Super Bowl," Leslie O'Donnell said, waving off the subject, as if she were talking to a Cowboys fan. "It was a lot of rooms."</p>
        <p>The Jets' offer was a lot of cash, a reported $25 million for five years, including a fat $7 million signing bonus.</p>
        <p>Home in the National Football League is apparently where the most room under  the hard salary cap is.</p>
        <p>Nothing wrong with that attitude. Nothing at all. And for those who are wondering what possesses a man to jump the Steelers after six progressively successful seasons, O'Donnell minced no words when he said: "The Pittsburgh Steelers had plenty of opportunities to sign Neil O'Donnell."</p>
        <p>They didn't exactly throw themselves between him and the free-agent market. They didn't get into an 11th-hour bidding war. They didn't even retain Ron Erhardt, his favorite offensive coordinator. They wanted O'Donnell back under their terms, which is like telling an unrestricted free agent he is not wanted at all.</p>
        <p>"The cap breaks up happy marriages," Leigh Steinberg, O'Donnell's agent, said.</p>
        <p>In a league where the figures on a player's contract are often not worth the  paper they're printed on, where few contracts are guaranteed, monogamy is merely a dreamer's state of mind. The Jets simply seduced O'Donnell harder. Rich Kotite snapped up Erhardt and Pat Hodgson, formerly the Steelers' tight ends coach. He  bought bookend tackles, David Williams and Jumbo Elliott, to protect his next quarterback.</p>
        <p>Kotite at least deserves credit for being ready with a plan the Giants don't  have.</p>
        <p>Whether O'Donnell is good enough to be made the fourth-highest-paid player in the N.F.L. is really an irrelevant issue. The ugliest boy in school does what he must to get a good-looking date. Considering where the Jets are coming from,  they'll gladly pay extra for a quarterback capable of leading them to a place alongside the many American Conference Super Bowl losers.</p>
        <p>Forget the interceptions O'Donnell threw against Dallas on Jan. 28. Remember  those completions against Indianapolis on Jan. 14. Start with the fourth-and-8 bullet that kept them alive against the Colts, and the bomb to Ernie Mills that  set up the winning touchdown.</p>
        <p>The worst things you can say about O'Donnell is that he speaks of himself in  the third person too much, and without the expansive flair of Boomer Esiason. He obviously is no fair-haired prince, no Troy Aikman. He is more working man than  leading man. His dark, rugged looks bear a slight resemblance to Warren Beatty,  himself a one-time quarterback in a Hollywood remake called "Heaven Can Wait."</p>
        <p>For O'Donnell, it certainly will. Heaven, wherever it is, just didn't have as much cap room as the Jets.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
