<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Search for a Few Good Bands Out of 1,000</title>
    <meta content="19cmj" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/19/arts/music/19cmj.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1703413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cmj Music Marathon</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rock Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Arcade Fire</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New Pornographers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Blackalicious</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Banhart, Devendra</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bowie, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050919T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E5D71F31F93AA2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="714" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Search for a Few Good Bands Out of 1,000</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Search for a Few Good Bands Out of 1,000</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles Critic's Notebook column on recent CMJ Music Marathon in New York City, where 1,000 bands compete for major label contracts and listener loyalty; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a terrible time to try to become a rock star. Major labels are obsessed with hit singles and quick profits, and don't nurture talent because small independent labels will do it for them. Radio stations are in a stranglehold of consolidation and payola. Internet file-sharing may be making it harder to turn a hit into a sales blockbuster, while consumers have so many choices that they have grown fickle. It's hard for something out of the ordinary to get a hearing, and nearly impossible to get a second chance.</p>
        <p>So why did more than 1,000 bands make their way to New York City to play brief club sets at 25th annual CMJ Music Marathon? There were 12,000 official participants this year (including those bands), from college-radio disc jockeys to label presidents, and another 4,000 bands wanted those club slots.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Among the thousand other bands, there were more worthy musicians than anyone could possibly attend at CMJ Music Marathon which ended last weekend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a terrible time to try to become a rock star. Major labels are obsessed with hit singles and quick profits, and don't nurture talent because small independent labels will do it for them. Radio stations are in a stranglehold of consolidation and payola. Internet file-sharing may be making it harder to turn a hit into a sales blockbuster, while consumers have so many choices that they have grown fickle. It's hard for something out of the ordinary to get a hearing, and nearly impossible to get a second chance.</p>
        <p>So why did more than 1,000 bands make their way to New York City to play brief club sets at 25th annual CMJ Music Marathon? There were 12,000 official participants this year (including those bands), from college-radio disc jockeys to label presidents, and another 4,000 bands wanted those club slots.</p>
        <p>That's because it's a great time to be in a new band. Technology allows cheap, do-it-yourself recording, and nearly every computer is a CD manufacturer. Listeners are no longer limited by what's available at the local record store and on radio or television. The Internet can pick up word-of-mouth and multiply it exponentially, turning a local band into an international buzz and opening up a sustainable touring circuit.</p>
        <p>The contradictions of the music business were heard during the Music Marathon's daytime panel discussions, which veered between do-it-yourselfer cheerleading and practical warnings. What started as a gathering of college-radio programmers -- CMJ stands for College Media Journal -- and the people who would court them has grown, over the decades, into a larger, more amorphous sprawl of showcases and brand positioning. For many, college radio has been supplanted by the Internet as the early-warning system for new music.Panels also discussed the growing influence of music blogs like www.pitchforkmedia.com and www.fluxblog.org, which provide direct links to downloadable songs chosen by idiosyncratic music obsessives. Predictably, there was a panel about how to market to them.</p>
        <p>Mostly, the CMJ Music Marathon is where everyone is hoping to run across a few good bands. Like many college radio stations, CMJ offered a little of everything: hip-hop, metal, jazz, world music, dance electronica. But CMJ's staple is still the self-conscious, proudly quirky rock that fills the college-radio charts tabulated by the weekly CMJ New Music Report.</p>
        <p>The marathon's flagship concert was by the Arcade Fire, last year's CMJ buzz band, from Montreal. A year ago, it played overcrowded club dates; now, it filled Central Park Summerstage's Rumsey Playfield, and had the guest imprimatur of none other than David Bowie, who joined the Arcade Fire for one of his own songs, ''Queen Bitch,'' and one of theirs, ''Wake Up.''</p>
        <p>Among the thousand other bands, there were more worthy musicians than anyone could possibly attend. My deeply unrepresentative sampling included a few sure things: the smart, un-gangsta hip-hop of Blackalicious, the caffeinated, literary pop-rock of the New Pornographers, and the neo-hippie free associations of Devendra Banhart, who had turned from spacy to droll as he led his band, Hairy Fairy. There was proudly retro 1960's psychedelia from the power trio Wolfmother and from Dungen, a Swedish rocker who had both the golden curls and the wail of a younger Robert Plant.</p>
        <p>There was brilliant, sustained noise-rock from Parts and Labor -- minimalists with a monumental impact -- and splintered, jumpy, incessantly quick-changing noise-hardcore from Xbxrx, which wore sailor suits and thanked its audience for downloading its songs free. Apollo Sunshine, a Boston band, made straightforwardly tuneful songs go haywire: cranking up the noise, suddenly mutating into psychedelic jams or mathematical riffing. The Joggers, from Portland, Ore., and Ghosty, from Lawrence, Kans., both set up intricate guitar patterns around wistful vocal harmonies. Tom Vek, from London, played stark, blunt, disillusioned songs driven by riffs out of garage-rock and punk-funk. And Orenda Fink, a songwriter from Georgia, held an audience rapt with stately folk-rock songs about devils and angels. I don't expect to hear any of these bands on commercial radio. But at CMJ, a few good bands are reason enough to return next year.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
