<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Man Behind, and in Front of, the Governor</title>
    <meta content="Y29CHE$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/29/politics/29CHEN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1251178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CONTESTING THE VOTE: A RUNNING MATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transition Between Administrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cheney, Dick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gore, Al (Vice Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2000</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E1DB153DF93AA15752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1254" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Man Behind, and in Front of, the Governor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dick Cheney, recovering from mild heart attack, has plunged into nuts and bolts of setting up administration for Gov George W Bush; is working from makeshift study in his McLean, Va, townhouse because he has been denied keys to government transition offices while election is still in dispute; is veteran of five presidential transitions since 1969, while Bush campaign organization is short on government experience; will meet with Bush at his Texas ranch to discuss transition; he seems at ease in standing in for Bush, who distances himself from legal wrangling by remaining off camera; Bush allies hold Cheney's roles underscore Bush's skill as delegator; some Republican officials admit Cheney has seemed on verge of overshadowing Bush; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Gov. George W. Bush named Dick Cheney on Sunday to prepare the transition to the White House, he fit him into the role he had always had in mind for his running mate: running things.</p>
        <p>Four days after leaving the hospital where he was recovering from a mild heart attack, Mr. Cheney has plunged into the nuts and bolts of setting up an administration that is not quite official yet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Gov. George W. Bush named Dick Cheney on Sunday to prepare the transition to the White House, he fit him into the role he had always had in mind for his running mate: running things.</p>
        <p>Four days after leaving the hospital where he was recovering from a mild heart attack, Mr. Cheney has plunged into the nuts and bolts of setting up an administration that is not quite official yet.</p>
        <p>Denied the keys to government transition offices, Mr. Cheney is working from a makeshift study off the kitchen in his town house in McLean, Va., contacting prospective cabinet members, hunting for rental offices and sketching a legislative agenda for a Bush administration.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney, a former White House chief of staff, secretary of defense and head of a major oil services company, is also a veteran of five  presidential transitions since 1969, an invaluable asset to a Bush campaign organization that is short on government experience.</p>
        <p>''When Dick Cheney was chosen, it was clear to me that Bush picked him to be his partner in governing, much more than his campaign running mate,'' said Haley Barbour, a former chairman of the Republican National Committee. ''And everything since the election has borne that out.''</p>
        <p>Ari Fleischer, a spokesman for the Bush campaign, who announced today that Mr. Cheney would discuss the transition with the governor at his Texas ranch this week, summed up the views of many campaign advisers by saying, ''Dick Cheney is one of Washington's wise men.''</p>
        <p>Long before he suffered his fourth heart attack in 22 years, the campaign script called for Mr. Cheney,  59, a former Wyoming congressman, to bring his low-key, businesslike approach to the chaotic task of overseeing the staffing of an administration with more than 1,000 nominees who require Senate confirmation, drafting a federal budget and bridging the partisan chasm on Capitol Hill.</p>
        <p>''It's totally Cheney's time,'' said Mary Matalin, a Republican consultant. ''He exudes this calmness, steadiness, maturity and sense that the job will get done, even though everyone will be hysterical.''</p>
        <p>Reading from handwritten notes at a 20-minute news conference on Monday, Mr. Cheney said the next weeks would define the initial course of the fledgling administration.</p>
        <p>His imprint has already been felt. By many accounts, he was largely responsible for bringing in James A. Baker III, the former secretary of state, as Mr. Bush's chief representative in Florida.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker spent most of election night in Mr. Cheney's hotel suite in Austin, Tex. The two have known each other since the Ford administration, when Mr. Cheney was chief of staff and Mr. Baker was an under secretary of commerce.</p>
        <p>In another sign of Mr. Cheney's growing importance in the transition, the campaign has sought to keep Mr. Bush off camera and above the legal wrangling by judiciously parceling out his public appearances. It has fallen to Mr. Cheney to present the ticket's public face.  Whether it was on ''Prime Time Live'' on ABC on Nov. 16, at the news conference on Monday, or in his appearances today on ''Today'' on NBC and ''Larry King Live'' on CNN, Mr. Cheney seemed utterly at ease, a reassuring ballast to the confusing and often angry turmoil swirling around this contested election.</p>
        <p>Bush allies say this underscores the governor's skill as a delegator  and his desire as an executive to have a decision brought to him when it is ready.</p>
        <p>''This allows Bush to stay back a bit and avoid criticism, and still move forward to get things done,'' said C. Boyden Gray, a former counsel to Governor Bush's father, President George Bush.</p>
        <p>But the strategy is not risk-free.  When Mr. Bush has come out, he has appeared at times timid and tense, some Republican officials acknowledge, and Mr. Cheney has seemed on the verge of overshadowing him.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Dick Cheneys of the world are beloved by the Bushes in part because they are not likely to upstage their boss. They are phlegmatic but dutiful and competent soldiers who serve the leader but let him shine undimmed.</p>
        <p>As one prominent Republican official who is friendly with Mr. Cheney and the Bushes said of the governor's relationship with Mr. Cheney: ''It is complete trust, a very important word in the world of the Bushes.''</p>
        <p>That Mr. Cheney is so active so soon after his hospitalization has surprised even some of his biggest backers. Mr. Cheney's doctors said he had suffered a mild heart attack, and gave him the go-ahead to return to his normal activities on Monday after taking the weekend off.</p>
        <p>While many doctors might support this advice, others would not. Dr. Douglas P. Zipes, head of cardiology at the Indiana University School of Medicine, in Indianapolis, who is president-elect of the American College of Cardiology, said in an interview he would not return a heart attack patient to work in three days.</p>
        <p>Work aside, Mr. Cheney is getting out of the house. On Saturday, he went to ''Men of Honor'' with his family; on Sunday he attended church; and tonight, Mr. Cheney attended a reception in Washington in honor of David O. Cooke, a longtime Pentagon administrator.</p>
        <p>On Monday, Mr. Cheney waved off questions about his health at the end of the news conference. This morning on ''Today,'' Mr. Cheney insisted that he had already ''revealed a great deal'' about his health and said he would ''probably'' offer more in the future. But Mr. Cheney has rejected repeated requests by The New York Times to be interviewed about his medical condition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney is scheduled to meet with his doctors at George Washington University Hospital on Wednesday for what the secretary's spokeswoman, Juleanna Glover Weiss, called ''a routine follow-up exam.''</p>
        <p>But some senior Republicans still express lingering concerns over how Mr. Cheney's health could affect a smooth White House operation.  While Andrew H. Card, whom Mr. Bush has designated White House chief of staff, is seen as an effective manager, some Republicans expressed fears that if Mr. Cheney were incapacitated, it would rob the administration of the man most capable of standing up to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney is on track to become an even more involved and influential vice president than Al Gore, if Mr. Gore's contest fails.</p>
        <p>Not only is Mr. Cheney emerging as the ticket's standard-bearer in the transition phase, Republicans say, but by dint of his experience and his relationship with Mr. Bush, he is in position to act as de facto co-chief of staff, an uber national security adviser, a shadow secretary of defense and even, perhaps, a demi-president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cheney would never publicly acknowledge all this. But Vin Weber, a former Republican congressman, assessed it as other friends and associates do when he said, ''We're beginning to see the outlines of a vice president who can truly take on any responsibility assigned to him by the president and seem natural at it.''</p>
        <p>CONTESTING THE VOTE: A RUNNING MATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
