<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Digital Gains More Than Fourfold</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="438358"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY EARNINGS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DIGITAL EQUIPMENT CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHAPIRO, EBEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6DD1438F93AA25757C0A967958260" item-length="485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Digital Gains More Than Fourfold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EBEN SHAPIRO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHAPIRO, EBEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Digital Equipment Corporation said yesterday that its quarterly profits had increased more than fourfold, and the shares of the nation's No. 2 computer maker jumped $4, or 6 percent, to $70.375, on the New York Stock Exchange. It was the third-most-active Big Board stock, with 2.3 million shares changing hands.</p>
        <p>The earnings were slightly below Wall Street's expectations, but Digital's stock rose as high as $74.25 in early trading, apparently because investors were pleased by the progress the company had made in restructuring its business and cutting costs. During the quarter, more than 2,200 people left the company, through layoffs and attrition, out of a work force of about 120,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Digital Equipment Corporation said yesterday that its quarterly profits had increased more than fourfold, and the shares of the nation's No. 2 computer maker jumped $4, or 6 percent, to $70.375, on the New York Stock Exchange. It was the third-most-active Big Board stock, with 2.3 million shares changing hands.</p>
        <p>The earnings were slightly below Wall Street's expectations, but Digital's stock rose as high as $74.25 in early trading, apparently because investors were pleased by the progress the company had made in restructuring its business and cutting costs. During the quarter, more than 2,200 people left the company, through layoffs and attrition, out of a work force of about 120,000.</p>
        <p>After I.B.M. posted a large loss last week, investors were nervous that other large computer makers would report disappointing results. "People were braced for a very bad quarter for Digital," said Richard Chu, an analyst with Cowen &amp; Company in Boston. "The worst simply did not materialize."</p>
        <p>Digital, based in Maynard, Mass., said it earned $116.6 million, or 94 cents a share, in its third quarter, compared with $24.9 million, or 20 cents a share, in the period a year ago. Last year's results included a $150 million restructuring charge. Revenues Advance by 8%</p>
        <p>Revenues for the quarter were $3.52 billion, up 8 percent from $3.26 billion last year.</p>
        <p>The quarter's results were reduced by the effects of the consolidation of Digital-Kienzle, a Germany company in which Digital recently acquired a 65 percent stake from Mannesmann A.G. for $230 million. Digital said that without the consolidation, earnings would have been $1.14 a share. Digital also paid $62.7 million in income taxes for the quarter. Last year, the company paid no taxes in the quarter.</p>
        <p>Still, the makers of large computers will continue to be affected by the sluggish economy. "The difficult economic environment of the past several quarters is still with us," said John F. Smith, Digital's senior vice president for operations. He said customers were delaying investments in technology, particularly in large systems.</p>
        <p>The company said its work station business doubled in the last year, while the weak economy hurt orders for its larger VAX 9000 computers.</p>
        <p>The company has shipped about 250 systems so far, a number far below analysts' expectations.</p>
        <p>While analysts question how successful the line of computers will be, Digital said orders for its high-end machines would improve along with the economy. Mr. Chu, the analyst, said, "You will find a large degree of skepticism on that point."</p>
        <p>Mr. Chu said the most positive feature of the quarter was that Digital's revenue growth outstripped growth in expenses for the first time in memory.</p>
        <p>"While there are significant questions about the demand outlook, they are at least on top of the cost curve, which has not been the case until recently," he said.</p>
        <p>COMPANY EARNINGS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
