<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Acting Is a Great Deal More Than Skin Deep; From Time of Slavery</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="438553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SEPARATE BUT EQUAL (TV PROGRAM)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910419T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D71730F93AA25757C0A967958260" item-length="302" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Acting Is a Great Deal More Than Skin Deep; From Time of Slavery</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a person of mixed racial ancestry, primarily Dutch and African, I have always been sensitive to the values attached to skin color among American blacks, discussed by Richard G. Carter (Op-Ed, April 6). But he never explains why shades of black are important.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>As a person of mixed racial ancestry, primarily Dutch and African, I have always been sensitive to the values attached to skin color among American blacks, discussed by Richard G. Carter (Op-Ed, April 6). But he never explains why shades of black are important.</p>
        <p>Mr. Carter might have noted the importance of America's preferential treatment of lighter-skinned black people in the telling of our country's history. Slave owners typically selected lighter-skinned blacks to be house servants, often including the slave owner's illegitimate progeny in that group, while darker blacks were relegated to hard labor in the fields.</p>
        <p>Also at that time, while Georgia refused to confer equal status on blacks and whites, it did pass laws to give mulattos limited property and business rights that did not extend to darker people of apparently unmixed African descent.</p>
        <p>The black faces that make it still tend to be those with lighter complexions -- look at television news people, entertainers, fashions models, politicians, religious leaders -- suggesting that lighter still means more acceptable, more marketable.</p>
        <p>Many people in the black community have internalized this value -- look at skin-lightener ads in Ebony and Jet magazines from only 20 years ago -- or railed against it.</p>
        <p>In the case of Thurgood Marshall, I don't suggest that his lighter skin was his ticket to the Supreme Court. I don't know if Justice Marshall would identify his complexion as important to the formation of his identity or his opportunities.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if Hollywood were making a movie about W. E. B. Du Bois, a light-skinned man who struggled with complexion issues much of his life, to cast a dark-skinned actor in the role would be to repaint history. LISE FUNDERBURG New York, April 7, 1991</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
