<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Thirty Years' War</title>
    <meta content="15BASS$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/15/opinion/15BASS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1408509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Notes From Yaak"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bass, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Eco-tourism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Montana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wilderness Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forests and Forestry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Montana</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bass, Rick</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020715T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2D91E30F936A25754C0A9649C8B63" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Thirty Years' War</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Thirty Years' War</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Rick Bass</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bass, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>YAAK, Mont.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Op-Ed article by Rick Bass, resident of rural Yaak, Mont, opposes building of roads in national forests and other wilderness areas; says seemingly endless dispute, which has raged for past 30 years, has cast pall over entire communities; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Where I live, some people decide whether to wave at each other, or even speak a greeting of the day, based on whether the person across from them supports protection of the last roadless areas here. This despite the fact that the timber in these areas is a nonissue: roadless areas are the farthest, most rugged, least productive areas, which is why roads haven't been built there yet.</p>
        <p>It's estimated that the last remaining roadless areas in our national forests -- a total of about 58.5 million acres across 39 states -- contain less than two-tenths of 1 percent of the nation's timber. Yet the divisiveness over such an insignificant amount of timber casts a poisonous pall over entire communities. Some powerful elements in the timber and mining industries are trying wherever they can to scare local millworkers and businesses into believing we can't afford to protect these lands. Here in western Montana this can mean warnings of mill closings and labeling environmentalists as terrorists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>How long must the fight for America's wilderness go on?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Where I live, some people decide whether to wave at each other, or even speak a greeting of the day, based on whether the person across from them supports protection of the last roadless areas here. This despite the fact that the timber in these areas is a nonissue: roadless areas are the farthest, most rugged, least productive areas, which is why roads haven't been built there yet.</p>
        <p>It's estimated that the last remaining roadless areas in our national forests -- a total of about 58.5 million acres across 39 states -- contain less than two-tenths of 1 percent of the nation's timber. Yet the divisiveness over such an insignificant amount of timber casts a poisonous pall over entire communities. Some powerful elements in the timber and mining industries are trying wherever they can to scare local millworkers and businesses into believing we can't afford to protect these lands. Here in western Montana this can mean warnings of mill closings and labeling environmentalists as terrorists.</p>
        <p>In my own valley, the Yaak -- a gnarly, rank, mosquito-ridden jungle that's been subject to countless clearcuts in the last half-century -- there's still not a single acre of roadless land protected as wilderness. Only 15 small roadless areas remain eligible for protection -- the largest is only about 35,000 acres, and the smallest, 1,000 acres -- little more than gardens, from the perspective of the Western landscape.</p>
        <p>To date, it's a 30-year war, ever since the United States Forest Service inventoried these last roadless areas for wilderness designation in 1972. Must it be this way for another 30 years? Rural communities of 50 or 100 people fighting over philosophical scraps of land that really belong to every American?</p>
        <p>When I began this fight, I was a young man, and went hiking almost every day in many of these public treasures, though almost always with a dull worry in my heart, knowing that these places were not protected for future generations. I'm middle-aged now, with a middle-aged man's responsibilities. Yet still my heart is heavy with that worry of my younger days: How can we defend the nation's last roadless areas?</p>
        <p>We've been arguing for decades that building roads in our national forests, where the Forest Service sells public resources (often at a loss), leaves behind damaged land whose repair the taxpayers are left to finance. At last count, the projected cost for such repairs was $8.4 billion. We've been arguing about the necessity of genetic and ecologic diversity. Grizzlies and other rare and endangered species like bull trout depend on the sanctuary provided by roadless areas. We've been arguing that local economies adjacent to wilderness areas are often thriving.</p>
        <p>But political recognition of the merits of these arguments has been long delayed. The Clinton administration began the process of establishing permanent protection for these lands in 1998. The Forest Service held hundreds of public meetings over the course of two years, and received an overwhelming public response in favor of protection. But the Bush administration requested further analysis, complaining that there hadn't been enough local input. Last fall over 80 percent of the residents in Idaho, Wyoming and Montana who responded during a second comment period asked -- again -- for the land to be protected. Recognizing this public will, Representatives Jay Inslee of Washington and Sherwood Boehler of New York have introduced an amendment to an appropriations bill for the Interior Department to protect roadless areas. Votes on this proposal are expected as early as this week.</p>
        <p>I admit I've grown a bit tired of arguing for the beauty and the economic benefits of wilderness, of the need to protect the endangered species that rely on these lands. I am sick of the polls, which show again and again that we want these lands protected. But what I am not sick of is beseeching, on behalf of wilderness, and the future. If these last wildlands had been protected yesterday -- or last year, or the year before -- little if anything would have changed. That's the point. We choose to live, vacation and work in these lands, hoping they will remain as much the same and secure as possible. Is that so radical?</p>
        <p>The Wilderness Act of 1964 passed the House by 373 to 1. I am still naïve enough -- and patriotic enough -- to believe that a vote for protecting our last roadless areas can still pass beyond the brittle barriers of party lines: that conservatives can still know what it means to conserve, and liberals what it means to liberate. That we can have joy and logging, both; that we can survive, and then flourish, with our wilderness.</p>
        <p>Notes From Yaak Rick Bass is the author, most recently, of ''The Hermit's Story.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Rick Bass is the author, most recently, of ''The Hermit's Story.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
