<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Island Nation Loses a Bridge As Philippine Airlines Fails</title>
    <meta content="Y25PHIL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1049110"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philippine Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Estrada, Joseph (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980925T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E6D71739F936A1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1278" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Island Nation Loses a Bridge As Philippine Airlines Fails</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <dateline>HONG KONG, Sept. 24</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Demise of Philippine Airlines in short run could raise acute transportation problems for 76 million people of island nation who relied on airline to hop from island to island; in long run, Governemnt officials and airline analysts say collapse will be remembered more as blow to national pride--and to prestige of Pres Joseph Estrada, for whom labor dispute was major test of leadership; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>What happens when a sprawling island nation suddenly loses its national airline?</p>
        <p>That question reverberated through the Philippines today, on the morning after Philippine Airlines ceased flying. The airline, Asia's oldest, shut down at midnight on Wednesday after the President of the Philippines, Joseph Estrada, failed in a final effort to resolve a bitter labor dispute.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>What happens when a sprawling island nation suddenly loses its national airline?</p>
        <p>That question reverberated through the Philippines today, on the morning after Philippine Airlines ceased flying. The airline, Asia's oldest, shut down at midnight on Wednesday after the President of the Philippines, Joseph Estrada, failed in a final effort to resolve a bitter labor dispute.</p>
        <p>In the short run, the demise of Philippine Airlines could raise acute transportation problems for the 76 million people of the archipelago who relied on the airline to hop from island to island. The Government and several domestic airlines are scrambling to plug the holes in the air network.</p>
        <p>In the long run, Government officials and airline analysts said the collapse would be remembered more as a blow to national pride -- and to the prestige of Mr. Estrada, for whom the dispute was a major test of leadership.</p>
        <p>''In terms of image, we're badly affected,'' said Roberto Ram Antonio, the under secretary of tourism. ''It's the pride of a country to have a flag carrier that represents the Philippines in different markets abroad.''</p>
        <p>But Philippine Airlines had become a threadbare symbol. It lost $338 million over four years and was staggering under $2.1 billion in debt. After the unions rejected a proposal that would have allowed the airline to slash costs, its owner, the billionaire Lucio C. Tan, made good on his threat to close the doors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Antonio said the Government's priority was to reassemble its domestic route network. Philippine Airlines carried 80 percent of domestic traffic until it encountered severe financial trouble last June, when it cut local destinations to 16, from 36. Analysts warned that the Philippine economy could be crippled if people and cargo were not able to move smoothly around the country.</p>
        <p>''You've got a country with 7,000 islands,'' Scott Gibson, the head of research at ABN Amro in Manila, said. ''You need a well-developed domestic airline.''</p>
        <p>The Government said two smaller domestic airlines, Cebu Pacific Air and Air Philippines, would expand  service to fill the vacuum. Today, both airlines were arranging to lease planes from Philippine Airlines, commonly known as P.A.L.</p>
        <p>At the moment, Mr. Antonio said, the airlines had only a fraction of Philippine Airlines' domestic capacity. But he added, ''I'm very confident that we will be able to solve this problem by the end of October.''</p>
        <p>Analysts said an overly rapid expansion could create safety hazards. Several Air Philippines planes have already been grounded because of Government concerns about maintenance standards. In February, a Cebu Pacific DC-9 crashed into a mountain, killing all 104 people on board.</p>
        <p>Analysts also noted that some domestic Philippine Airlines routes were unprofitable, and only existed because of an agreement between the airline and the Government. If the Government wants to continue serving remote or outlying islands, they said, it may have to subsidize those routes.</p>
        <p>Though the collapse of Philippine Airlines will have less of an impact on international air travel, its loss will still be felt. Singapore Airlines has already doubled its economy-class fares between Singapore and Manila to exploit the exit of its only competitor on that route. Cathay Pacific Airways, which serves the heavily traveled Hong Kong-Manila route, said it would not immediately lift fares.</p>
        <p>Mr. Antonio said the Government was also encouraging foreign carriers to increase their flights to the Philippines. Japan Airlines recently agreed to schedule 36 additional flights from Japanese cities to the resort island of Cebu, between now and year's end.</p>
        <p>''Flag carriers are not really needed, provided that the government is willing to give the routes to foreign carriers,'' said David A. Sherman, a consultant who heads the transportation practice at A. T. Kearney Ltd. in Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>Some experts said no flag carrier was better than a second-rate one. ''It may have been the first airline in Asia, but it was carrying a lot of excess baggage,'' Jim Eckes, an aviation consultant at Indoswiss Ltd. in Hong Kong, said. ''It just has never been well managed, from the Marcos era on.''</p>
        <p>But this is where national pride comes in. Mr. Antonio said Philippine Airlines was a valuable tool in the country's marketing efforts. At airports from London to Los Angeles, its planes were large, rolling billboards for the country. Though some detractors said P.A.L. stood for ''Planes Always Late,'' fans of the airline said it exuded the warmth and cheer of the Philippines.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the airline's staff marked the long-threatened shutdown on Wednesday in a characteristically emotional fashion. Employees at Manila's airport hugged and wept, while the pilot of the last incoming flight, from Tokyo, walked off the plane singing a variation on the 1970's hit song ''We May Never Love Like This Again.'' His version: ''We may never fly this plane again.''</p>
        <p>It was a miserable end for an airline that started out in 1941 with one plane carrying five passengers on a 125-mile flight from Manila to the northern city of Baguio.</p>
        <p>The allure of owning a flag carrier has fueled rumors that Philippine Airlines may be sold to another foreign carrier. Mr. Estrada said in a Bloomberg News report today that three airlines had already expressed interest: Northwest Airlines, Cathay Pacific, and Eva Airways of Taiwan.</p>
        <p>''I'm not convinced we've seen the end of P.A.L.,'' said Peter Negline, an airline analyst at Salomon Smith Barney in Hong Kong.</p>
        <p>If no buyers resurrect Philippine Airlines, its creditors could face a protracted and messy fight to get their money back. Bankruptcy law in the Philippines is not as developed as that of other countries, and Philippine Airlines is the biggest corporate failure in the country since the Asian economic crisis began more than a year ago.</p>
        <p>The company has suspended payments on its $2.1 billion in debt for two months. When it resumes payments, analysts said the line of creditors would include local and foreign banks, plus export-import banks in the United States and Europe. Because the company's debts are as large as its assets, analysts said the creditors could wind up dickering over planes.</p>
        <p>Complicating the process is that the second-largest local creditor, Allied Bank, is owned by Mr. Tan, who also owns the airline. One of the richest men in the Philippines, Mr. Tan took control of the carrier in 1994 and has vast interests in tobacco, brewing and real estate. Nick Cashmore, a banking analyst at ABN Amro in Manila, estimated the bank's exposure at $76 million.</p>
        <p>Two other potential casualties of the collapse are Airbus Industrie and the Boeing Company. Mr. Eckes said Philippine Airlines had recently acquired 16 Airbus planes, with another 12 on order. It also ordered several 747's from Boeing. The airline may return many of these planes as part of the liquidation process.</p>
        <p>For Mr. Estrada, the closing of Philippine Airlines is a bitter denouement to what had become a passionate campaign. During the negotiations, the Government offered the airline a bridge loan of $34 million for two months until new investors could be found. Mr. Estrada met with both sides until Wednesday evening but failed to break the deadlock.</p>
        <p>''I have done all that I can as president because I know it will affect our country, not just the jobs of the labor union, but the jobs and businesses connected with Philippine Airlines,'' he said afterward.</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
