<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dealer in Art and, Some Say, a Dealer in Secret Police Data</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604679"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIVACY, RIGHT OF</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BULLOCK, ROY E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D81E3FF936A15757C0A965958260" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dealer in Art and, Some Say, a Dealer in Secret Police Data</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Roy E. Bullock has recently become one of the best-known collectors in the Bay area, but it is not his Japanese wood block prints that has attracted attention. Rather, the collection that is raising curiosity and anger is his data base of 12,000 people and 500 organizations, including some culled from confidential police files.</p>
        <p>Like any careful collector, Mr. Bullock sorted and labeled what he had, dividing his world into categories: "ANC" for supporters of the African National Congress in South Africa, "Skins" for right-wing extremists like skinheads and neo-Nazis, and "Arabs" for critics of Israel. The rest fell under two headings: "Pinkos" for liberals and "Right" for conservatives.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Roy E. Bullock has recently become one of the best-known collectors in the Bay area, but it is not his Japanese wood block prints that has attracted attention. Rather, the collection that is raising curiosity and anger is his data base of 12,000 people and 500 organizations, including some culled from confidential police files.</p>
        <p>Like any careful collector, Mr. Bullock sorted and labeled what he had, dividing his world into categories: "ANC" for supporters of the African National Congress in South Africa, "Skins" for right-wing extremists like skinheads and neo-Nazis, and "Arabs" for critics of Israel. The rest fell under two headings: "Pinkos" for liberals and "Right" for conservatives.</p>
        <p>Then, critics say, he began to spread his collection around. Law-enforcement investigators here say he sold and traded the names and other information to police agencies, the Anti-Defamation League of B'nai B'rith and at least one foreign government.</p>
        <p>The collection, which Mr. Bullock acknowledges he has been compiling for more than 30 years, has drawn accusations of domestic spying and invasions of privacy. Lawsuit and Investigation</p>
        <p>Although no criminal charges have been filed, his activities are the subject of a civil lawsuit and are being investigated by the District Attorney's office here, which says the Anti-Defamation League has people like Mr. Bullock in cities around the country who have close ties with some law-enforcement officials.</p>
        <p>Barbara S. Wahl, a lawyer for the league, says that the group does have a network of "researchers" and that they do have close ties to law-enforcement agencies in many cases. "But the A.D.L. does not run a spy ring nationwide," she said.</p>
        <p>As reports of Mr. Bullock and his intelligence-gathering emerged in news accounts over the past four months, they began to raise eyebrows in largely liberal San Francisco. And when a flood of documents supporting government search warrants became public two weeks ago, the case began to evoke cries of outrage.</p>
        <p>Part of the District Attorney's investigation involves Mr. Bullock's relationship with Thomas Gerard, a former police inspector here who has been accused by plaintiffs in the lawsuit of tapping into law-enforcement and government computers and feeding the information to Mr. Bullock.</p>
        <p>Exactly what Mr. Bullock, 58, does do to support himself is hazy. He is often described as an art dealer, and he says most of that part of his life involves Japanese prints. He calls himself a researcher, but the evidence available in public documents indicates that his steadiest work seems to be on contract to the Anti-Defamation League, collecting information about people. Trading and Selling Information</p>
        <p>He has admitted in court papers and in an interview that he is not a passive information gatherer, having infiltrated racist groups, tapped into telephone message systems and paid informers. In addition, according to public documents, he has traded information with law-enforcement officers, who gave him motor vehicle records and criminal rap sheets. And he says that for four years he sold some of his information to a man calling himself "Louie," who he said was an agent for the South African Government.</p>
        <p>There is nothing illegal about collecting information that is in public records, which is what makes up most of Mr. Bullock's data. But the District Attorney's investigation is aimed at finding out how far Mr. Bullock and Mr. Gerard went beyond that, including whether they used police authority to obtain the names of postal box owners.</p>
        <p>The investigation began in December, when the District Attorney's office began looking into Mr. Gerard's use of official information. A short time before that, Mr. Gerard retired from the police force and moved to the Philippines. The authorities are now trying to find him for questioning.</p>
        <p>"The heart of this investigation is the violation of privacy and individuals' rights to exercise First Amendment freedoms," said District Attorney Arlo Smith. "People should feel free to go to assemblages without the fear that their license numbers will be taken down in the parking lot and classified information about them given out to private individuals." 'Massive Spying' Charged</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith said the investigators are trying to determine if there had been violations of California's laws on privacy, eavesdropping and disclosure of confidential records.</p>
        <p>The civil lawsuit was filed April 14 by 19 people who have been publicly critical of Israel and South Africa. It is a class action, on behalf of everyone affected by the gathering of such information, and it charges Mr. Bullock, Mr. Gerard, the Anti-Defamation League and the head of the league's San Francisco office with violating the plaintiffs' privacy.</p>
        <p>The suit also says a "massive spying operation" was run to discredit people and cause them "loss of reputation, jobs or economic benefit."</p>
        <p>"If I thought this was just about finding out who the skinheads were, I wouldn't object," said Paul N. (Pete) McCloskey Jr., a former Republican Congressman from California who is representing the plaintiffs, including his wife, Helen.</p>
        <p>Another plaintiff, Yigal Arens, the son of former Defense Minister Moshe Arens of Israel, said, "I've never done anything more than sometimes in public, sometimes in private, said what I think."</p>
        <p>The case has caused confusion for some liberals because the Anti-Defamation League, an organization they believed was keeping tabs on racist or violent groups, has now been accused of spying on them. 'Outraged' by Pinko Listin</p>
        <p>"If it were the White Ayran Resistance and the Klan they were spying on, I probably wouldn't get upset about it," said Anne Poirier, who is involved with groups supporting anti-apartheid efforts in South Africa and is a plaintiff in the lawsuit. "But because it was about me, I care. I'm outraged that I'm on the Pinko list."</p>
        <p>The Anti-Defamation League was founded 80 years ago to gather information about anti-Semitic groups. Since then it has thrown a wider net, opposing all forms of hate groups.</p>
        <p>Melvin Salberg, the league's national chairman, flew here from New York on April 15 to defend the group. "We have been in the trenches fighting for civil rights," he said in an interview. "We have it as our mission to find out what racist groups are doing and saying so we can properly combat them."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bullock said in an interview that he had not done anything wrong. His motivation, he said, has been a "repellent interest in hate groups, religious bigots, assorted kooks and radicals," an interest he said he developed in high school.</p>
        <p>Although the laws have changed in the past 40 years to restrict spying by law-enforcement agencies on citizens, Mr. Bullock's methods have remained the same throughout his career. He said he had infiltrated organizations by passing himself off for months at a time as a white supremacist or as a sympathizer to Arab causes.</p>
        <p>Despite the lawsuit and investigation, Mr. Bullock aggressively defends his activities. "I feel I have rendered a service to fight bigotry in every form," he said. "I'm very proud of what I've done."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
