<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gulf War Is Said to Have Cost the Region $676 Billion in 1990-91</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604656"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSIAN GULF WAR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN LABOR</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAUDI ARABIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D8173FF936A15757C0A965958260" item-length="664" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gulf War Is Said to Have Cost the Region $676 Billion in 1990-91</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By YOUSSEF M. IBRAHIM,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">IBRAHIM, YOUSSEF M</byline>
      <dateline>RIYADH, Saudi Arabia, April 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two years after the end of the Persian Gulf war, a new report estimates that the conflict cost the region $676 billion in 1990 and 1991, not counting vast damage to the environment and a continuing suppression of the rate of economic growth in the region.</p>
        <p>The report, prepared by the Arab Monetary Fund in conjunction with two other Arab economic institutions and released at the fund's annual meeting last week in Damascus, Syria, estimates that $51 billion that would otherwise be invested in the region's economies continues to be held in foreign accounts as a result of the war.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two years after the end of the Persian Gulf war, a new report estimates that the conflict cost the region $676 billion in 1990 and 1991, not counting vast damage to the environment and a continuing suppression of the rate of economic growth in the region.</p>
        <p>The report, prepared by the Arab Monetary Fund in conjunction with two other Arab economic institutions and released at the fund's annual meeting last week in Damascus, Syria, estimates that $51 billion that would otherwise be invested in the region's economies continues to be held in foreign accounts as a result of the war.</p>
        <p>This flight of capital has abated in large oil-producing countries like Saudi Arabia, the report said, but was continuing in Kuwait, where billions of dollars continue to be transferred abroad by Kuwaitis who feel insecure about the future at home.</p>
        <p>The continuing effects of the war are felt most broadly in the loss of income for millions of Arab and Asian expatriate workers who were employed for decades in Saudi Arabia, Kuwait, Iraq and elsewhere in the gulf. The foreign workers' remittances provided significant boosts to the economies of Yemen, Egypt, the Philippines, Bangladesh, Pakistan and India.</p>
        <p>The loss of earnings by these workers has been estimated by the fund's study -- prepared in conjunction with the Arab Petroleum Exporting Countries Organization and the Arab Fund for Economic and Social Development -- at $23 billion in 1990 and 1991.</p>
        <p>While expatriate workers have found their way back to Kuwait and Saudi Arabia, their numbers have been much smaller. Political barriers stand in the way of some expatriates; for instance, hundreds of thousand of Palestinians who worked in Kuwait are no longer welcome there because they are perceived as being sympathetic to the Iraqis.</p>
        <p>But for many others, there are simply no jobs. Iraq, Kuwait and Jordan have seen their economies shrink considerably and are no longer in need of the armies of foreign workers that they had before the war.</p>
        <p>The report's figures are based on data from scores of Arab banks and financial institutions.</p>
        <p>Last week's report drew a grim picture of the future, saying the economic boom experienced by many Arab economies in the four years that preceded the war, with annual rates of growth that averaged 7 percent, turned into a negative growth rate of 7 percent in 1991. There were no figures available for last year, although the fund reported that there has been some improvement in the last few months. Kuwait Surplus Drained</p>
        <p>By far the largest economic casualties of the war were Kuwait, which was invaded by Iraq in August 1990, and Iraq, which was pounded in a United States-led military campaign that culminated in the ousting of Iraqi troops from Kuwait in February 1991.</p>
        <p>The Arab Fund says the war wiped out two-thirds of Kuwait's financial surplus, the so-called Fund for Future Generations, which stood at $100 billion just before the conflict began. The tiny emirate, with a population of 600,000 Kuwaitis and as many expatriates, is still paying to repair extensive damage to its infrastructure, its oil industry and its environment, in addition to the expenditures for the international military campaign and the cost of new weapons to defend itself.</p>
        <p>But Kuwait, which has resumed oil exports of 1.7 million barrels a day, is slowly recovering. Iraq's war bill is far higher, and the losses appear to have no end in sight. Destroyed infrastructure, factories, telecommunications and roads have cost the Baghdad Government $256 billion at last count, and the continuing deprivation of revenues from oil exports is inflating Iraq's losses daily.</p>
        <p>Rather than submit to United Nations conditions for the lifting of an international embargo on Iraqi oil, the Baghdad Government is living off savings, which are estimated by various Arab officials at nearly $30 billion before the war, but which are said to have dwindled considerably.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
