<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ikea's New Realities: Recession and Aging Consumers</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">IKEA GROUP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOBERG, ANDERS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAMPRAD, INGVAR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6DC1F38F936A15757C0A965958260" item-length="1754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ikea's New Realities: Recession and Aging Consumers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</byline>
      <dateline>JARFALLA, Sweden</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is a cold, gray morning in this suburb of Stockholm, but hundreds of people are lined up for the opening of a vast new Ikea store.</p>
        <p>"Welcome to cheap land," says Anders Moberg, the genial president of the Ikea Group, using a pun based on Smaland, the name of the region of Sweden where the furniture retailer was founded. Then he cuts a large yellow and blue ribbon and watches, smiling, as the crowd rushes past in search of sofas, tables, beds and other goods that the company aims to sell for 10 percent to 30 percent less than other furniture retailers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is a cold, gray morning in this suburb of Stockholm, but hundreds of people are lined up for the opening of a vast new Ikea store.</p>
        <p>"Welcome to cheap land," says Anders Moberg, the genial president of the Ikea Group, using a pun based on Smaland, the name of the region of Sweden where the furniture retailer was founded. Then he cuts a large yellow and blue ribbon and watches, smiling, as the crowd rushes past in search of sofas, tables, beds and other goods that the company aims to sell for 10 percent to 30 percent less than other furniture retailers.</p>
        <p>Ikea, virtually unknown outside Scandinavia two decades ago, has grown accustomed to opening-day crowds as it has pushed rapidly into Europe, North America and Asia. Along the way, it has built something of a cult following, especially among young, price-conscious consumers.</p>
        <p>But Ikea executives have fewer reasons to smile nowadays. After an expansion binge that nearly doubled the number of stores and nearly quintupled sales in less than a decade, the company is stopping to catch its breath. And as it looks around, what it sees is not entirely encouraging.</p>
        <p>The worldwide economic slowdown has hit the company's most important markets especially hard. Germany, which accounted for 29 percent of Ikea's sales last year, has slipped into a downturn, and Scandinavia, with 22 percent of sales, has been unable to pull itself out of a two-year slump.</p>
        <p>Worldwide sales this year should be roughly flat, excluding revenues from new stores, Mr. Moberg said. And there is no way of knowing whether the downturn will end soon or deepen. "Since we have such a chaotic situation in the world it's difficult to make predictions," Mr. Moberg said.</p>
        <p>Ikea is also facing demographic shifts that are forcing it to try to broaden its appeal to older and wealthier consumers.</p>
        <p>It plans to open 11 stores this fiscal year, which ends Aug. 31, down from 17 last year. And it has no immediate plans to add to the existing 12 stores in the United States. Openings will drop even lower over the next several years, and Ikea executives are pausing to take stock. "Of course growth is important," Mr. Moberg said. "But the first priority for me is to take care of existing Ikea."</p>
        <p>From 10 stores in five countries in 1974, Ikea will have grown by the end of this summer to 119 stores in 24 countries.</p>
        <p>Millions of customers have gone to the stores -- large showrooms next to huge self-service warehouses usually situated just outside of large cities -- and lugged home heavy cartons of Ikea furniture, which is packed and sold unassembled to keep the company's costs and prices low. They have spread out the dozens of pieces and stared hard at the sometimes incomprehensible instructions, wondering whether the savings are worth the hassle of do-it-yourself assembly.</p>
        <p>Some have muttered, "Never again." But enough have kept going back for the moderate prices, the simple Scandinavian designs and the large selection of colors, styles and materials to make Ikea one of the world's fastest-growing retailers.</p>
        <p>WHILE Ikea has no direct rival in store size and selection of goods, its designs and pricing strategies have been widely imitated.</p>
        <p>Sales in the last fiscal year were reported at $3.2 billion at current exchange rates. A nonprofit Dutch foundation set up by Ikea's founder, Ingvar Kamprad, owns Ikea and does not disclose its profits. The foundation, Stichting Ingka, sometimes makes investments outside of the Ikea Group. It recently acquired the Habitat chain of home furnishings retailers from Storehouse P.L.C. of Britain (except for the Conran's Habitat stores in the United States). It will operate them separately from Ikea.</p>
        <p>Company executives said the bulk of any profits go back into Ikea itself, financing its growth and keeping debt levels low. Ikea's challenges will not end with the recession. Most of its customers are relatively young and its furniture has always been designed with their tastes and financial limitations in mind. But worldwide the population is aging. Ikea is already expanding its product line to include more traditional -- and more expensive -- styles favored by older consumers -- fully assembled sofas, for example, that customers can order with a wide choice of fabrics and have shipped to them directly from the supplier.</p>
        <p>But in trying to broaden its appeal, Ikea risks diluting its identity and becoming just another big furniture retailer. "We can't have something for everybody," said Mr. Moberg. "But we will have a reasonably wide range, enough to be an option for 40 or 50 percent of any country's population."</p>
        <p>IKEA was founded in 1943 by Mr. Kamprad, who was then just a teen-ager, to serve very price- and quality-conscious neighbors. Sweden at the time was a relatively poor nation, particularly the residents of the central region known as Smaland.</p>
        <p>A native of the region (the name Ikea comes from his initials plus the first letter of his village, Elmtaryd, and his parish, Agunnaryd), Mr. Kamprad developed a furniture line to meet those needs. He sold it first through a catalogue and then through a showroom in 1954. The first real store didn't open until 1958, in Almhult, the Smaland town that remains the headquarters of Ikea's Swedish operations and its spiritual home.</p>
        <p>As Ikea became successful, and Mr. Kamprad grew older, he confronted a common problem in Sweden: extremely high inheritance taxes. Concluding that the company would have to be broken up or sold off if it remained Swedish-owned at his death, he set up the Stichting Ingka foundation in Amsterdam, with himself as chairman, and transferred to it 100 percent ownership of Ikea. He moved the company's international headquarters to Denmark. He himself moved to Switzerland.</p>
        <p>Today, at 66, Mr. Kamprad -- whose wealth is estimated by Forbes at $2.8 billion -- is a Sam Walton-like figure. He appears unannounced in stores for a look around. He oversees product development and purchasing operations. He guards against any weakening of the corporate culture he imposed, a culture that spurns hierarchy and bureaucracy and virtually outlaws perks. (Mr. Moberg, the president, and all other top executives travel coach class and stay at budget hotels. At dinner the night before the store opening in Jarfalla, Mr. Moberg and his top lieutenants discussedwhich bus to take from the airport to save a few dollars.)</p>
        <p>Nowhere is penny pinching more important to Ikea than in its dealings with its 1,800 suppliers. Ikea does little manufacturing of its own, so is always seeking ways to exert more influence over the companies from which it buys the furniture it sells. Its sheer size helps. But Ikea executives said they were increasingly becoming more active in helping the suppliers to become more efficient.</p>
        <p>Goran Stahlgren, Ikea's top purchasing executive in Sweden, recalled a recent meeting at which the company decided to help the suppliers shop around for better quality materials, lower prices, or both.</p>
        <p>"Maybe they have the competence, but they don't have the time or the temperament to search the world for raw materials," Mr. Stahlgren said. "We can help with that."</p>
        <p>IKEA also sends people to study suppliers' operations and to suggest more efficient methods. At Brantorp, a Swedish maker of wooden drawers and doors for kitchen cabinets and bureaus, Ikea recommended that the supplier move up to two shifts a day, and helped justify the change by ordering larger quantities. The move allowed Brantorp to reduce its unit costs. Ultimately, Ikea executives said, the change should lower the supplier's prices by 15 percent to 20 percent.</p>
        <p>Some Ikea executives said the company had sometimes concentrated too much on what its suppliers could build efficiently rather than on asking consumers what they wanted to buy.</p>
        <p>In the United States, for example, Ikea made a classic outsider's mistake by selling beds only in European sizes, which standard American mattresses and sheets don't fit. It later stocked compatible sheets in some stores, but sales were not good, so it recently decided to simply order American-sized beds.</p>
        <p>That's the kind of shift in thinking, said Marvin S. Traub, the former chairman of Bloomingdale's, that will help Ikea as it expands into markets farther and farther from its home base. "They're learning more and more about the U.S. market," said Mr. Traub, who last fall purchased the American stores of Conran's Habitat. "There will be opportunities for them to grow."</p>
        <p>Because Ikea has continued to open new stores even as other battered retailers slowed or stopped, Mr. Moberg said his company could benefit some from the continued economic sluggishness.</p>
        <p>"I see this as a good opportunity to take market share," he said. "Value for money is very important to the consumer." THE AMERICAN CONNECTION</p>
        <p>"The United States has been a good market for us, and there's a huge potential there," said Anders Moberg, president of the Ikea Group.</p>
        <p>"But when as a Swede you go to a huge country like the U.S. and say, 'Ooh, markets, markets, markets,' it can be dangerous," he added. "It's not one market, it's a lot of different markets. We have to concentrate on areas rather than trying to be everywhere."</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for Ikea, its biggest American market is the Los Angeles area, which has five of the company's 12 American stores. California has seen few signs of the recovery that seems to be taking hold in much of the nation.</p>
        <p>Since establishing a beachhead outside Philadelphia in 1985, the Ikea Group has also opened stores near New York -- in Elizabeth, N.J., and Hicksville, L.I. The other American stores are outside Washington, Baltimore, Pittsburgh and Houston.</p>
        <p>"They've put together a critical mass of furniture and furnishings," said Walter K. Levy of Levy Kerson Associates, a retail consulting firm in New York. "It's value priced and pretty well made. It's ubiquitous-contemporary in style. The chances of finding what you want are pretty high -- and you can take it home with you. That's a pretty good formula." One that is very hard for competitors like Crate and Barrel and Pier 1 to match.</p>
        <p>The company plans to spend the rest of this year concentrating on improving its supplier relationships in the United States and improving its distribution system.</p>
        <p>Only then will Ikea consider expanding, Mr. Moberg said, most likely on the East and West Coasts, where the company has good distribution and invested in marketing efforts to build up its name.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
