<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Parcells, Little Errors Can Make a Big Difference</title>
    <meta content="07JETS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1052131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Rams</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/St. Louis Rams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981007T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E4DF173BF934A35753C1A96E958260" item-length="939" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Parcells, Little Errors Can Make a Big Difference</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on New York Jets preparing for game against St Louis Rams (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the moments after the Jets' impressive 20-9 victory on Sunday over the previously-unbeaten Miami Dolphins, Bill Parcells sounded less than impressed. While his team celebrated, Parcells was focusing instead on what he called ''awfully dumb things'' that the Jets continue to do even in victory.</p>
        <p>A day later, Parcells was still unwilling to revel in the Jets' second consecutive victory, which evened their record at 2-2 and improved their American Football Conference Eastern Division mark to 2-0. He has seen premature celebrations too many times and seen the mistakes that a team gets away with in Week 4 come back to haunt them in the most important games of the season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the moments after the Jets' impressive 20-9 victory on Sunday over the previously-unbeaten Miami Dolphins, Bill Parcells sounded less than impressed. While his team celebrated, Parcells was focusing instead on what he called ''awfully dumb things'' that the Jets continue to do even in victory.</p>
        <p>A day later, Parcells was still unwilling to revel in the Jets' second consecutive victory, which evened their record at 2-2 and improved their American Football Conference Eastern Division mark to 2-0. He has seen premature celebrations too many times and seen the mistakes that a team gets away with in Week 4 come back to haunt them in the most important games of the season.</p>
        <p>''There's a sign in the hallway up here, and I tell the players this all the time,'' Parcells said at Weeb Ewbank Hall in the Jets' Hofstra University training site at Hempstead, N.Y. ''It says, 'Dumb players do dumb things. Smart players very seldom do dumb things.' It's right out in the hallway. They read it every day when they come down the steps.</p>
        <p>''These things occur occasionally. If they occur at the wrong time, they just send you home for the season or keep you from winning the critical game. That has a big part in the eventual circumstances that evolve for the year. For the most part, I try to emphasize to the players the things that cause you to lose games and that most games are lost one way or another.</p>
        <p>''A lot of times the inability of a player to exercise proper judgment under pressure can be a reason for that. So, I just try to call it to their attention. Fortunately, it didn't cost us on Sunday. Hopefully, we can improve on it.''</p>
        <p>What Parcells has seen is the little things, a foolish penalty or a failed assignment. On Sunday, there was a blocked field-goal attempt, a sack of Vinny Testaverde on which he fumbled the ball away with the Jets on the Miami 24-yard line, and a personal foul penalty on Matt O'Dwyer after an extra point, forcing the Jets to kick off from their own 15-yard line. It did not cost them this time. But Parcells is certain that it will if they do not correct these errors soon.</p>
        <p>''It's not that I didn't let them enjoy the victory,'' Parcells said. ''Look, it's as simple as this. Last week against the Colts, we had an extra point blocked. We roughed the kicker on a field goal. That's four points. This week we had a field goal blocked and we got a sack-fumble that kept us from at least another field goal, or a touchdown. That's 10 points.</p>
        <p>''That sounds like a little thing because we won one game, 44-6, and another game by 11 points. It sounds like a little thing, but I'm going to say this again, 25 percent of the games in this league are decided by 3 points or less and 50 percent of the games in this league are decided by 7 points or less. And we're averaging giving away 5 points a week for the last two weeks. Now it's just a question of time before that comes back to haunt us.''</p>
        <p>''So let them enjoy it,'' Parcells continued. ''I'll let them enjoy it, but I'm not in the enjoyment business myself and I know what causes you to lose games, better than the players know, and it's my job to let them know. You can call it keeping the pressure on. You can call it whatever you want.''</p>
        <p>Pepper Johnson, who has been with Parcells for two championship seasons with the Giants, said: ''It makes sense to me. It's only reasonable. We got to .500. Whoop-de-doo. If we get to 8-8, are we going to be happy then? I'm not by no means satisfied with just a win over Miami. We got our heads above water. It's not a lot to brag about when you won two championships in your past and you expect a lot from yourself and from your teammates. For 10 more weeks, if we can keep this up, then you'll see a smile on my face.''</p>
        <p>It's doubtful that Parcells will be smiling. He even had criticism for Curtis Martin, who had rushed 36 times for 108 yards.</p>
        <p>''I don't know what Curtis had,'' Parcells said. ''But all I know is that he ran out of bounds to stop the clock with 55 seconds left.''</p>
        <p>Martin, who had stepped out of bounds on a run round the right end with 59 seconds remaining, knew immediately that he was about to incur the wrath of Parcells, noting: ''I felt horrible. I looked up and I could see those big, blue eyes staring at me.''</p>
        <p>Those stares, the harsh words, are what the Jets must endure now. But the 34-year-old Johnson believes that his younger teammates will learn.</p>
        <p>''My personal opinion, I would bet that the majority don't really understand,'' Johnson said. ''But you have some young guys that are willing to learn. They are observing, listening to the coach, listening to everything that he's saying. By now, it should be making some headway.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
