<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Disk Jockey Challenges an Oil Company</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="206046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOYCOTTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIO</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH AFRICA, REPUBLIC OF</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WBCN-FM (BOSTON, MASS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHELL OIL CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLD, ALLAN R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAQUIDARA, CHARLES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boycotts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEFDF1F31F931A25751C1A96E948260" item-length="1003" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Disk Jockey Challenges an Oil Company</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN R. GOLD, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLD, ALLAN R</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, Dec. 11</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A leading disk jockey here has been urging his listeners to boycott Shell Oil products and cut up the company's credit cards to protest its parent's involvement in South Africa.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A leading disk jockey here has been urging his listeners to boycott Shell Oil products and cut up the company's credit cards to protest its parent's involvement in South Africa.</p>
        <p>A leading disk jockey here has been urging his listeners to boycott Shell Oil products and cut up the company's credit cards to protest its parent's involvement in South Africa.</p>
        <p>Since August, the disk jockey, Charles Laquidara of WBCN-FM, has regularly used a few minutes of his popular morning rock-and-roll radio program, ''The Big Mattress,'' to wage what he calls a Shellshock campaign. Between airings of Cream's ''White Room'' and R.E.M.'s ''Orange Crush,'' Mr. Laquidara and a group of entertainers and politicians have inveighed against Shell's ties to South Africa and that nation's apartheid policy.</p>
        <p>Radio stations, like most businesses, do not usually bite a hand that feeds them, especially a big name like Shell. And most rock and roll disk jockeys are content to play records and talk about the music, leaving politics to other broadcasters and other radio formats. But WBCN's management has tolerated, albeit warily, Mr. Laquidara's anti-Shell campaign, citing his popularity and respect for his First Amendment rights. The Complaint About Shell</p>
        <p>Underlying Shellshock is the contention that the Shell Oil Company's parent, the multinational Royal Dutch/Shell Group, buttressess apartheid by continuing to do business in South Africa. Many multinational companies have sold their businesses in that nation in the face of similar protests.</p>
        <p>''The word is getting out,'' Mr. Laquidara said. ''Shell Oil is a bad guy.''</p>
        <p>A Shell spokesman responded that the company and Royal Dutch/Shell want to see apartheid eliminated quickly and peacefully, but that disinvestment in South Africa would accomplish little toward that end. Mr. Laquidara's campaign is ''very unfair and misguided,'' the spokesman, Norman Alstedter, said.</p>
        <p>There are mixed signals about whether the Shellshock campaign, which is now winding down, has cost the station money. Shell has not advertised on any New England radio station since before the campaign began. But the available evidence indicates that even if Shell has stopped advertising on WBCN in response to Shellshock, it would not be a serious blow to the station. Shell accounts for less than 1 percent of the station's $15 million in annual revenue, according to a broadcast executive with knowledge of the Boston radio market. A Popular Show</p>
        <p>With a small amount at stake, it was unlikely that the station's management would risk alienating the voluble Mr. Laquidara by muzzling him. His 6 A.M. to 10 A.M. drive-time show is a big favorite among listeners - and advertisers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Laquidara, a fixture of Boston rock and roll radio for 18 years, has helped make WBCN the most popular radio station in the city and the top revenue producer in the nation's seventh-biggest radio market.</p>
        <p>''Charles Laquidara is worth much more to the radio station than what they have lost,'' said a WBCN employee who knew the situation.</p>
        <p>WBCN is owned by the Infinity Broadcasting Corporation, which bought the station in 1978 for $3.6 million. Today, it is valued at more than $75 million, said Mel Karmazin, president and chief executive. Infinity, formed in 1972, is the largest radio company when measured by annual revenue, at $100 million, Mr. Karmazin said. Based in New York, Infinity went private in a $485 million leveraged buyout in August.</p>
        <p>The company owns 15 stations and is represented in all of the country's top 10 markets, Mr. Karmazin said. It already has experience with outrageous radio personalities: Infinity owns WXRK in New York, which employs the frequently off-putting Howard Stern. Cut-Up Credit Cards</p>
        <p>Mr. Laquidara, 39 years old, said he has received strong listener support for his campaign and collected nearly 1,000 cut-up credit cards. He intends to pass on the chopped plastic to members of a national Shell boycott campaign in a ceremony at Boston's City Hall on Tuesday. At that gathering, Mayor Raymond L. Flynn is scheduled to sign an executive order banning the purchase of Shell products for city use.</p>
        <p>Mr. Laquidara said he first considered an anti-Shell radio campaign when he heard about the company's business dealings in South Africa through a national Shell boycott campaign. That movement, which began in April 1986, is composed of labor, church and anti-apartheid groups.</p>
        <p>After several months of discussion with his management, Mr. Laquidara said, the station let him proceed with the understanding that his comments did not represent its views.</p>
        <p>''They absolutely don't encourage it, don't sanction it and have tolerated it,'' he said. Mr. Laquidara, who gives management credit for permitting his campaign, said he nevertheless thought the station's management was relieved that Shellshock was coming to an end. ''I'm sure if I could monitor their blood pressure, it would be lower next Tuesday,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Laquidara said he thought that management would have allowed the campaign to continue if he had wanted it to, but, as an entertainer, he could make the campaign work for only so long and hoped someone else would continue to sound the message.</p>
        <p>Asked whether the campaign had hurt the station, Mr. Karmazin said, ''I'm not sure it has cost us at all.'' He said the station's advertising spots have been filled throughout Shellshock and each month has seen record revenue.</p>
        <p>But the station's general manager, Tony Berardini, is quoted in the Dec. 3 issue of Billboard as saying: ''Yes, it hurt the station in sales, but not badly. There's been no discernible backlash.'' Mr. Berardini did not return telephone calls.</p>
        <p>Shell has not advertised on radio in New England since July, Mr. Alstedter said, and has no plans to do so. Shellshock began in August. The company said it had not approached the station about Mr. Laquidara's campaign.</p>
        <p>The boycott has apparently had no effect on Shell's sales in Massachusetts, Mr. Alstedter said, although some individual dealers have been hurt. According to the Lundberg survey, Shell was the No. 2 gasoline marketer in the state in 1987, with a 12.5 percent share.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
