<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Baking in the Summer Can Yield Satisfying Desserts</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="375473"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900812T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D91638F931A2575BC0A966958260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Baking in the Summer Can Yield Satisfying Desserts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: AS unappealing as the thought of baking might be on a hot summer's day, the abundance of fruit in the market makes it compelling. Dessert planning is often resolved by filling pastry or topping cake with peaches, plums, nectarines or berries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: AS unappealing as the thought of baking might be on a hot summer's day, the abundance of fruit in the market makes it compelling. Dessert planning is often resolved by filling pastry or topping cake with peaches, plums, nectarines or berries.</p>
        <p>AS unappealing as the thought of baking might be on a hot summer's day, the abundance of fruit in the market makes it compelling. Dessert planning is often resolved by filling pastry or topping cake with peaches, plums, nectarines or berries.</p>
        <p>There are short cuts. Pasty shells and sponge cakes can be purchased, brushed with jam or spread with whipped cream or pastry cream, then layered with fruit. A sparkling glaze made of warmed, strained jelly gives it a professional finish.</p>
        <p>Blueberries can be used either cooked or uncooked, baked in the pastry or to top a just-baked tart. When spread on a still-warm lemon filling, they sink in and collapse a bit, adding their flavor to the filling. A cheese tart glazed with honey makes a good base to hold a blueberry topping.</p>
        <p>A warm blueberry gallete is a shallow, tart-like dessert made with the berries, or other fruit, baked on a pastry and topped with a crunchy nut and sugar mixture. This one deserves to be served warm, perhaps with whipped cream or ice cream on the side. The others are best fully chilled. Here are three recipes for those who are not daunted by baking in summer.</p>
        <p>Blueberry-Lemon Tart</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 30 minutes</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 45 minutes</p>
        <p>Pastry for an eight- or nine-inch tart.</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons orange marmalade</p>
        <p>4 eggs</p>
        <p>3/4 cup sugar</p>
        <p>Y cup fresh lemon juice</p>
        <p>6 tablespoons unsalted butter, melted and cooled</p>
        <p>2 cups blueberries.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 425 degrees. Line a tart pan with the pastry and prick the bottom. Line the pastry with foil and weight with dry beans or pastry weights. Bake about six minutes, remove the foil and the weights and bake about five minutes longer, until the pastry is just beginning to color. Remove it from the oven.</p>
        <p>2. Brush the bottom of the tart shell with the marmalade.</p>
        <p>3. Beat the eggs with the sugar and lemon juice. Stir in the butter. Pour this mixture into the tart shell. Return the tart to the oven and bake until the lemon custard has set, 25 to 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>4. Remove the tart from the oven and while still hot cover the top completely with the blueberries. Allow to cool to room temperature, then chill before serving.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Blueberry Cheese Tart With Pecan Crust</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 20 minutes</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 50 minutes</p>
        <p>1 1/4 cups pecans</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons dry bread crumbs</p>
        <p>1 1/4 cup sugar</p>
        <p>10 ounces cream cheese, softened</p>
        <p>2 eggs</p>
        <p>1/4 cup plus 3 tablespoons honey</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon lemon juice</p>
        <p>1 1/2 tablespoons grated lemon rind</p>
        <p>2 cups blueberries.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 375 degrees.</p>
        <p>2. Place the nuts, bread crumbs and sugar in a food processor and process until the nuts are finely ground. Press the nut mixture into the bottom and sides of an eight or nine-inch tart pan. Place in the oven and bake six to eight minutes, until the crust begins to color. Remove the pan from the oven and reduce the temperature to 325 degrees.</p>
        <p>3. Place the cream cheese, eggs, one-fourth cup honey, the lemon juice and rind in the food processor and process until well blended. Pour this mixture into the nut crush, place it in the oven and bake 40 minutes, until the surface is firm to the touch.</p>
        <p>4. Remove it from the oven and allow to cool, then chill it. Spread the remaining honey over the top of the tart, then cover the top completely with the blueberries.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 to 10 servings.</p>
        <p>Blueberry Gallette</p>
        <p>Preparation time: 25 minutes</p>
        <p>Cooking time: 35 minutes</p>
        <p>2 cups walnuts</p>
        <p>3/4 cup flour</p>
        <p>Pinch of salt</p>
        <p>6 tablespoons cold unsalted butter</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons ice water (approximately)</p>
        <p>3/4 cup light brown sugar</p>
        <p>2 cups blueberries</p>
        <p>2 tablespoons melted unsalted butter.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 425 degrees.</p>
        <p>2. Chop the nuts fairly fine in a food processor. Remove one cup and reserve. To the rest of the nuts add the flour and salt and process until the nuts are finely ground. Dice the cold butter, add to the food processor and pulse until the butter is about the size of peas. With machine running add enough water to form a ball of dough.</p>
        <p>3. Place the dough on a floured surface and pat it into a circle about one-half inch thick. Place it in an eight- or nine-inch tart pan with a removable bottom and press it evenly into the pan, creating a rim about one-half inch high.</p>
        <p>4. Mix the reserve nuts with the brown sugar and sprinkle half this mixture over the dough. Spread the blueberries over this mixture, then sprinkle the remaining nut mixture over the blueberries. Drizzle with the melted butter.</p>
        <p>5. Place in the oven and bake about 30 to 40 minutes, until the pastry and topping are lightly browned. Serve while still warm.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
