<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Lance Armstrong, Success Is No Longer Measured in Races Alone</title>
    <meta content="07CYCL$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1022914"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Armstrong, Lance</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litsky, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980607T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E2D9163AF934A35755C0A96E958260" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Lance Armstrong, Success Is No Longer Measured in Races Alone</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, June 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lance Armstrong, world and US professional bicycle road-racing champion, comments on how his successful bout with testicular cancer has changed his life; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were times during that awful siege when Lance Armstrong, whose self-confidence had always matched his extraordinary cycling ability, was not sure he would live, let alone race again. The testicular cancer he had ignored had spread to his abdomen and brain, and doctors gave him at best a 50-50 chance to survive.</p>
        <p>After surgery in October 1996, extensive chemotherapy and 18 months away from competition, he has survived and is racing again. But the ordeal has changed him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were times during that awful siege when Lance Armstrong, whose self-confidence had always matched his extraordinary cycling ability, was not sure he would live, let alone race again. The testicular cancer he had ignored had spread to his abdomen and brain, and doctors gave him at best a 50-50 chance to survive.</p>
        <p>After surgery in October 1996, extensive chemotherapy and 18 months away from competition, he has survived and is racing again. But the ordeal has changed him.</p>
        <p>He is no longer the brash wunderkind who, at age 21, won the world and United States professional road-racing championships and a stage of the Tour de France. At 26, the brashness has diminished, partly because of his health travails, partly because of natural maturity, partly because of the added responsibilities of his recent marriage. Partly, too, because he had seldom wondered about his future. Now he wonders. To start with, he is unsure what will make his comeback successful.</p>
        <p>''That's all relative,'' he said in an interview this week. ''How do you relate a success or failure? Do I get back to the level I was at previously? No. That probably will never be. But I survived a deadly illness when I should have died. That's success, so it wouldn't be fair to call my return a failure.</p>
        <p>''It's uncertain. It will be very tough and I'm just very cautious. I want to be realistic. I don't want to raise my expectations too high and be disappointed. It's better to be conservative and shoot for minor objectives for now. It's really like starting over.''</p>
        <p>The starting over began in March in the seven-day Paris-Nice race in France. Halfway through the first day, he realized his mind was not ready, so he quit the race and returned home to train more.</p>
        <p>Now he is back, stronger mentally and physically. He is the leader of the United States Postal Service team, one of the favorites in Sunday's $120,160 United States pro championship here. The 156-mile race, with 10 trips up the Manayunk Wall and its 17 percent grade, is built for the old Armstrong, but race fitness comes through extensive racing, and he is not there yet.</p>
        <p>''When I started training again in February,'' he said, ''my lack of fitness gnawed at me. It's in perspective now. It's not going to come back overnight. I'm sure it will come back if I give it enough time, but I don't know how much time is enough. It's better to do a day at a time. I can see just riding out this year and creating some base. The early indication is that it's not impossible.''</p>
        <p>Armstrong was fit enough to have raced Tuesday in Lancaster, Pa.; Wednesday in Wilmington, Del., and Thursday in Trenton. He finished second in Lancaster to Frankie Andreu, a longtime teammate.</p>
        <p>''Lancaster wasn't a World Cup or anything,'' Armstrong said, ''but I hadn't done seven race days this year and most riders there had done 30 or 40. But clearly I was in the race. If that is any indication, I can come back.''</p>
        <p>That Lancaster performance impressed Andreu.</p>
        <p>''He's doing good,'' Andreu said. ''He's a little more relaxed than he used to be, but I don't know if he's enjoying it more. Maybe he doesn't feel he's under as much pressure. Before, he felt he had to win.''</p>
        <p>Mark Gorski, the manager of the Postal Service team, said Armstrong had made immense progress in recent months.</p>
        <p>''He's doing great,'' Gorski said. ''I think he's adjusted. In Paris-Nice, he learned he was not ready to compete at his old level and may never be. I think he has accepted that. I think he's at peace with himself.</p>
        <p>''I don't think he will be back to his old level, and I'm not disappointed in that. What he's doing now is a huge accomplishment. It would be unfair to him to expect more.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, there are new interests. Last week, the Lance Armstrong Foundation for cancer research, awareness and education grossed almost half a million dollars in fund-raisers in Austin, Tex., where Armstrong lives.</p>
        <p>Here, he visited with cancer patients at a children's hospital Friday and took part in a cancer-facility fund-raiser today.</p>
        <p>''When I leave a hospital,'' he said, ''I feel so thankful that I was once there and lived that life and have come out of it and am hopefully cured. At the same time, it's always hard for me because I relate. I don't think I'm that far from going back.''  CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
