<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The New Faces of Reality TV</title>
    <meta content="26SALA$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/26/arts/television/26salamon.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040926T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1614194"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Home Box Office</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Evangelista, Frankie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Salamon, Julie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Family Bonds (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Home Box Office</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Fox Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">ABC Inc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">MTV Networks</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Upn</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801EED91339F935A1575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1897" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The New Faces of Reality TV</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The New Faces of Reality TV</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE SALAMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Salamon, Julie</byline>
      <dateline>Medford, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on extension of reality television to younger 'stars' like Frankie Evangelista, eight-year-old Long Island boy whose family's intimate life is captured on new HBO series Family Bonds; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 8-year-old Frankie Evangelista's unassuming Long Island neighborhood, it's perfectly normal on a summer night to see children bouncing balls or hesitantly learning to ride their bikes. Frankie does these things, too. But when he takes part in childhood's pleasures and embarrassments, he is usually followed by a camera crew -- and has been for more than a year.</p>
        <p>He isn't an actor, but he is appearing on national television, in the new HBO reality series called ''Family Bonds'' (Sundays at 9 p.m., Eastern). Viewers will observe his family's most intimate moments: Frankie crying as he learns to ride a bike, his mother listing how many times a night she has sex with Frankie's father, and Frankie's older sister giving birth, including a close-up shot of the baby emerging from her vagina.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The introduction of children to the genre was probably inevitable. But the networks seem to understand that they are in dicey ethical territory.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 8-year-old Frankie Evangelista's unassuming Long Island neighborhood, it's perfectly normal on a summer night to see children bouncing balls or hesitantly learning to ride their bikes. Frankie does these things, too. But when he takes part in childhood's pleasures and embarrassments, he is usually followed by a camera crew -- and has been for more than a year.</p>
        <p>He isn't an actor, but he is appearing on national television, in the new HBO reality series called ''Family Bonds'' (Sundays at 9 p.m., Eastern). Viewers will observe his family's most intimate moments: Frankie crying as he learns to ride a bike, his mother listing how many times a night she has sex with Frankie's father, and Frankie's older sister giving birth, including a close-up shot of the baby emerging from her vagina.</p>
        <p>''All I know is that I'm going to be famous,'' said Frankie, sitting on his front lawn for an interview a few weeks before the show's premiere. He seemed oblivious to the cameraman taping as he talked, the sound man standing by with a boom and the newspaper photographer taking pictures of the entire scene. He gave the impression that being a star in his own life was a perfectly natural way to be.</p>
        <p>Frankie, in fact, is just one of dozens of new underage reality TV stars. Previously, the genre mainly featured adults -- consenting adults, who presumably understood the ramifications of sharing their quirks, romances and breakdowns with an audience of millions. But this season, reality TV is turning youthward. On the Fox summer show ''Trading Spouses'' and ABC's ''Wife Swap,'' children are subjected to experiments in which their mothers are taken away for several weeks to live with other families, while they have to adjust to new, temporary moms. MTV will offer ''Laguna Beach,'' which will chronicle the trials and tribulations of wealthy, attractive teenagers in Orange County. In December, the N, MTV's sister network for younger viewers, will carry ''Best Friend's Date,'' showing teenagers on blind setups, and ''Girls vs. Boys: Montana,'' a ''Survivor'' knock-off that stars youngsters.</p>
        <p>''Is it indecent?'' Sheila Nevins, president of HBO's documentary division, said of children's participation in reality TV shows. ''I don't know. Probably. But real people are the items now. But Frankie is a major nonvictim of this so far. Judy Garland had a much harder time.''</p>
        <p>When asked about the perils of underage participation in reality TV, several mental health professionals focused on parental involvement. After all, no minor can appear on these shows without their parents' permission, and in many cases, the child's participation is the parent's idea. ''It's not so much being on TV that's problematic for any of the children, it's coming from families that would agree to play and be played with in this way,'' said Margaret Crastnopol, a psychoanalyst in Seattle who recently watched ''Trading Spouses.'' But Elaine Heffner, a New York psychotherapist with a specialty in early childhood development, declined to condemn the parents who enlist their children in reality TV shows. ''I think there's some hubris in saying to a parent, 'You have some nerve letting your child being part of this series you've agreed to be in,''' said Dr. Heffner. ''It's something I personally would not want to expose my children to but it's nobody's business unless they're really involved in child abuse.''</p>
        <p>Lynn Bradley is one of the mothers on tonight's debut episode of ABC's ''Wife Swap.'' (The show will be broadcast at 9 p.m. EST). A modest woman who drives a school bus and chops wood in rural New Jersey, she trades places with a pampered woman from Manhattan who shops while nannies tend her children. She and her husband first became involved in the show, she said, when they answered an ad in a local newspaper. Why did she agree for her family, including her 12- and 13-year-old daughters, to participate? ''Mostly it was something we could all participate in as a family,'' she said. ''We were evaluated by a psychiatrist to make sure the kids were able to handle it.''</p>
        <p>The networks that put on these shows seem to understand that they are in dicey ethical territory. ''I would be embarrassed to admit how many hours went into the discussion of chaperones and safety,'' said Sarah Tomassi Lindman, vice president of programming and production for the N, which is broadcasting the youth-dating and ''Survivor''-type shows. Oddly, the public relations representative for Fox's ''Trading Spouses'' would not allow the children featured on the show to be interviewed by a newspaper reporter, even though his network is putting the same children on national television. ''We're sensitive when it comes to the kids,'' he explained in an e-mail message.</p>
        <p>Given reality TV's insatiable desire for new subjects, the introduction of children to the genre was probably inevitable. ''The heart of the American sitcom is the American family,'' said Stephen Lambert, an executive producer of ''Wife Swap.'' ''Reality television is moving toward replacing a lot of traditional sitcoms,'' he continued, as the new TV device for exploring and fantasizing about how families operate.</p>
        <p>Like almost everything on television, it's also not new. Public television broke this barrier in 1973 with ''An American Family,'' the 12-part, real-life soap opera about the Loud family of Santa Barbara, Calif. During the series the father learned of his son's homosexuality and the mother decided to file for divorce. The notoriety achieved by the Louds is unlikely to be repeated by today's subjects, simply because the Louds exposed themselves long before it became a relatively common practice. Also, today's reality shows are softer, with little sociological pretense. ''This is a lot lighter,'' said Steven Cantor, the 35-year-old producer of ''Family Bonds.'' ''This is entertainment with commercial appeal.''</p>
        <p>To recruit participants for ''Girls vs. Boys,'' the N did a nationwide casting call over a period of about 12 weeks, said Ms. Lindman, the programming executive there. ''We had hundreds and hundreds of kids at every location, some of whom were familiar with the channel and some who just saw a flyer in the mall that said, 'Hey, want to be on TV?'''</p>
        <p>But being cast isn't as simple as it may seem. The camera doesn't love most people. Producers look for the same qualities in child-reality-TV stars as they want in actors: the ability to project happiness and anxiety in a way that makes people respond. ''Frankie is way more telegenic and charismatic than his friends,'' said Mr. Cantor, the producer of ''Family Bonds.''</p>
        <p>Underage reality TV participants seem completely untroubled by the exposure for which they've enlisted themselves; in fact, they say they've thoroughly enjoyed their experiences. Laura Bradley, 13, Lynn's daughter, reported feeling a rush of pleasure when cameras invaded her New Jersey home for 10 days. ''They say once you're in front of the camera you get addicted, and I think that's true,'' she said. ''I like the feeling of the camera all the time and I don't mind the fact that people are going to see me on TV.'' Frankie Evangelista finds the whole thing preferable to acting ''because you don't have to read a script,'' he said. (Indeed, to accommodate children's schedules, some networks film their shows over the summer or on Christmas breaks.) Still, in a later interview, he expressed a desire to start acting in fictional TV series -- preferably on ''Full House'' (a show that has been in repeats for nearly 10 years).</p>
        <p>Frankie's mother, Flo Evangelista, was the only family member who was at first reluctant to participate in ''Family Bonds.'' A voluptuous blonde who was interviewed wearing a low-cut black T-shirt embossed with the words ''Von Bitch'' on the chest, Ms. Evangelista says she capitulated because her husband, Tom, a bail bondsman, convinced her that the series would be good for the family business. She now says she has accepted the exposure. ''This is our life,'' she said. ''The only difference is someone is filming and it's going to be aired. We all feel we have nothing to hide.'' As if to prove her point, the corner of the room in which she was interviewed held a toilet and shower, unhidden by a door or curtain.</p>
        <p>Ms. Evangelista said she did become concerned when she saw how readily Frankie took to a news conference that was part of an HBO publicity tour in Los Angeles this summer. ''I don't want it to go to his head and have him become a stuck-up brat,'' she said. ''And kids are cruel. I don't want him to get picked on.'' Indeed, two days after ''Family Bonds'' was broadcast, Frankie said that another child at school had teased him, saying that despite his TV appearance, Frankie was still an unknown. ''I felt the kids at school were a little bit jealous,'' he said.</p>
        <p>That concern was echoed by Mr. Cantor, who has become embedded with this family; he and his crew eat dinner with them as often as three or four times a week. ''We try not to use anything that might embarrass him,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cantor began his career as a documentary filmmaker but, like many of his colleagues, has ended up in the reality television business (he's one of the producers of UPN's ''Amish in the City''). His first film, a short documentary nominated for an Academy Award, was ''Blood Ties: The Life and Work of Sally Mann,'' about the controversial photographer. Ms. Mann, of course, is known for taking startlingly revealing photographs of her own young children, pictures that have raised concern about the effects of such exposure on children. But Mr. Cantor says Ms. Mann's photos, many of which showed her children nude, were far more invasive than his show. ''Sally threw this childhood innocence thing to the wolves,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Yet perhaps because he became a parent himself for the first time last year, Mr. Cantor says he has been protective of Frankie. ''If he cries too easily, I don't want people to think he's a sissy. If he hadn't learned to ride his bike after he cried, we wouldn't have used it. If that makes it less real, so be it.''</p>
        <p>As relatives swarmed in and out of his family's busy household, Frankie discussed what it was like to watch his life as it unfolds on ''Family Bonds,'' which he watched with a large audience at an HBO screening.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was funny when I was crying learning to ride my bike,'' he said. ''It was hysterical.''</p>
        <p>How did he feel when he heard his mom talking about sex on TV?</p>
        <p>''I closed my ears,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Did it embarrass him?</p>
        <p>''How would I know?'' he replied. ''My ears were covered.''</p>
        <p>Is there anything he wishes were not on television?</p>
        <p>He looked at Mr. Cantor, who was sitting nearby, and smiled. ''I hope everything you filmed ends up on TV.''</p>
        <p>TELEVISION</p>
        <p>Correction:  September 26, 2004, Sunday  Because of a production error, a brief passage is omitted in Arts &amp; Leisure today at the continuation from Page 26 to Page 27, in an article about children who appear in reality television shows. The affected sentence, referring to the possible negative effects of publicity on cast members of the HBO series ''Family Bonds,'' should read, ''That concern was echoed by Mr. Cantor, who has become embedded with this family; he and his crew eat dinner with them as often as three or four times a week.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: September 26, 2004, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of a production error, a brief passage is omitted in Arts &amp; Leisure today at the continuation from Page 26 to Page 27, in an article about children who appear in reality television shows. The affected sentence, referring to the possible negative effects of publicity on cast members of the HBO series ''Family Bonds,'' should read, ''That concern was echoed by Mr. Cantor, who has become embedded with this family; he and his crew eat dinner with them as often as three or four times a week.''</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
