<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What a Difference a Day Makes: The Sting of Late Fees</title>
    <meta content="26FEES" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/26/business/yourmoney/26fees.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1614372"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAYMONEY: SPENDING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Alster, Norm</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Poland Spring</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Consumer Action</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E2DB1E39F935A1575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What a Difference a Day Makes: The Sting of Late Fees</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">What a Difference a Day Makes: The Sting of Late Fees</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORM ALSTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Alster, Norm</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Advice on avoiding and fighting high fees for paying bills late; businesses of all sorts seem to have discovered that such punitive fees are lucrative; proliferation of such fees has caught eye of both regulators and class-action lawyers, opening some new options for consumers; table of key points; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JOHN ESCUDERO'S job as a purchasing agent at the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center -- whose new telescope will study the dark matter between stars -- is a demanding one. Still, he says, he is generally punctual about paying his bills. But in December, when Mr. Escudero sent Sprint a check a day late for his cellphone service, he was hit with a $40 fee.</p>
        <p>Considering that he had been waiting for months for a promised rebate on the phone, Mr. Escudero, who lives in San Jose, Calif., was furious. ''I'm a good customer,'' he said. ''I'm almost never late. For them to zap me like that, I was really irate.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dangerous to ignore but difficult to contest, late charges frustrate consumers. But for the companies that collect them, the fees can provide welcome revenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JOHN ESCUDERO'S job as a purchasing agent at the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center -- whose new telescope will study the dark matter between stars -- is a demanding one. Still, he says, he is generally punctual about paying his bills. But in December, when Mr. Escudero sent Sprint a check a day late for his cellphone service, he was hit with a $40 fee.</p>
        <p>Considering that he had been waiting for months for a promised rebate on the phone, Mr. Escudero, who lives in San Jose, Calif., was furious. ''I'm a good customer,'' he said. ''I'm almost never late. For them to zap me like that, I was really irate.''</p>
        <p>Sprint acknowledged that it does impose a late fee on payments that are one day late but would not comment further.</p>
        <p>Dangerous to ignore but difficult to contest, late charges frustrate consumers. But for the banks, mortgage servicers, cable companies and others that collect them, the fees can provide welcome revenue.</p>
        <p>Although credit card, mortgage and cable customers have long been subject to late fees, businesses from cellphone companies to bottled-water vendors seem to have discovered that such punitive fees can be a tonic for the bottom line.</p>
        <p>Late charges are generally legal, as long as companies credit payments promptly and make deadlines clear. But some states may bar specific industries, like utilities, from imposing them. Most banks that issue credit cards are legally based in states that impose few restrictions on late fees.</p>
        <p>Consumer choices for fighting late fees are limited. Most experts advise paying them promptly and then protesting. But the proliferation of late charges has caught the eye of both government regulators and class-action lawyers, opening some new options for customers.</p>
        <p>In November, the Federal Trade Commission and the Department of Housing and Urban Development won a $40 million settlement for customers of Fairbanks Capital, now called Select Portfolio Servicing, a large mortgage servicer in Salt Lake City. One of the F.T.C.-HUD contentions was that Fairbanks had not posted consumer mortgage payments promptly, thereby unfairly generating late charges.</p>
        <p>Select has not confirmed or denied the accusations, but the company said it has been working for more than a year on making its practices more consumer-friendly.</p>
        <p>And the F.T.C. is investigating other servicers. ''There are some out there that use late fees and other tactics to cheat consumers,'' said Joel Winston, associate director at the agency's division of financial practices.</p>
        <p>Late fees vary widely. Mortgage servicers generally charge no more than 5 percent of the overdue balance. But some consumer companies are charging much stiffer fees. Poland Spring, the bottled-water supplier, charges a $15 late fee, which may even exceed the monthly balance on a home delivery account. The fee is required to cover the costs of bill collection and of providing a service before payment, said a spokesman for Nestlé Waters, the parent company.</p>
        <p>In the credit card industry, late charges more than doubled from 1997 to 2003, to an average of $31.44 per billing cycle, according to CardWeb.com, which tracks the fees.</p>
        <p>And more customers are being penalized. ''The credit card companies have taken steps to insure that more people pay late fees,'' said Ken McEldowney, executive director of Consumer Action, a nonprofit consumer advocacy group.</p>
        <p>Many banks have eliminated grace periods after due dates, he said, and almost 60 percent have cutoff hours: a check received after 10 a.m. on a due date, for example, may not be credited until the next day.</p>
        <p>Consumers' anger grows when they call customer service lines only to be put on hold. And some companies, aiming to steer all dialogue to the Internet, charge for phone transactions -- no matter how long the consumer has to listen to recorded refrains like ''Your business is important to us.''</p>
        <p>Kate Rutter, a Web site designer in California, was assessed a $60 late fee on a Wells Fargo mortgage payment in June, even though, she said, a month had passed since she had closed on the mortgage and she had never received a statement. And she was then charged an additional $25 for making her payment by phone.</p>
        <p>She protested to a customer service representative and had the $60 fee waived, but not the $25 phone charge. Wells Fargo did not return calls seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Of course, an unpaid late fee, particularly on a credit card or mortgage, can lead to damaging reports to credit bureaus, as well as higher future interest rates. A late fee on one card may mean rate increases on that card and others, Mr. McEldowney said, because card companies and credit bureaus continually swap information. Consumers should ''eliminate all but one or two credit cards,'' he advised. ''A good customer,'' he added, ''does have some leverage.''</p>
        <p>But mortgage customers must deal with servicing firms that buy loan portfolios -- and cannot easily dump a collector. Some servicers, said Jack M. Guttentag, an emeritus finance professor at the Wharton School of the University of Pennsylvania, ''will play games in terms of not recording a payment when it should be recorded.''</p>
        <p>Short of litigation, customers have few options. One recourse is to file a claim under Section 6 of the Real Estate Settlement Procedures Act. (Forms are available from the housing department at www.hud.gov or at Professor Guttentag's Web site, www.mtgprofessor.com.) This will freeze further actions by the servicer until there is a resolution, which is required within 60 days. Of course, the servicer acts as bill collector, judge and jury. An adverse decision can be appealed to HUD or the courts. But experts warn against ignoring late fees on mortgages because a small charge can set off a nightmarish sequence of events.</p>
        <p>The danger is that unpaid fees, in industry parlance, can ''pyramid.'' Some companies add interest and secondary late fees to an unpaid charge. And if a consumer sends in a mortgage payment of $1,500 but neglects to pay a $75 late fee, some servicers apply the $1,500 to the late fee first, leaving the consumer $75 in arrears. The same thing may happen month after month, sometimes without explanation on the statement, eventually setting off a series of credit reports, payment delinquencies and even foreclosure.</p>
        <p>The handling of late charges was a central issue in the F.T.C.-HUD settlement with Fairbanks, said Mr. Winston of the F.T.C. He said Fairbanks had not posted payments promptly and had allocated subsequent payments to late fees, putting the consumer in default -- at which point Fairbanks would ''start moving toward foreclosure.''</p>
        <p>Fairbanks agreed to the $40 million settlement and paid an additional $15 million to settle class-action suits.</p>
        <p>Ocwen Federal Savings, another large servicer, was recently required by the Office of Thrift Supervision, a division of the Treasury Department, to sign an agreement that mandates numerous changes in its servicing practices. Pending class-action suits accusing Ocwen of not posting payments promptly, among other practices, have been consolidated in Federal District Court for the Northern District of Illinois. The Ocwen general counsel, Paul Koches, denied that Ocwen had deliberately failed to post payments promptly.</p>
        <p>MR. WINSTON said he hoped that the industry ''has gotten the message'' from the Fairbanks case. But he warned that other mortgage servicers were under scrutiny.</p>
        <p>Consumer victories can take time, if they come at all. Walking away from the company may provide quicker satisfaction. Mr. Escudero says he will switch vendors once his Sprint contract is up. Ms. Rutter has already transferred her mortgage from Wells Fargo to Bank of America, calling the switch ''hugely satisfying.''</p>
        <p>SUNDAYMONEY: SPENDING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
