<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now, an Advance Look At Those Big Paychecks</title>
    <meta content="26AGENDA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/26/business/yourmoney/26agenda.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1614375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE AGENDA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgeehan, Patrick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stock Options and Purchase Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0DB1E39F935A1575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now, an Advance Look At Those Big Paychecks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Now, an Advance Look at Those Big Paychecks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY PATRICK McGEEHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcgeehan, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Public companies, which traditionally reported past pay of top managers in following fiscal year, are beginning to provide more timely disclosure under new Securities and Exchange Commission rules requiring separate filings for variety of events; accelerated disclosures give shareholders chance to react by submitting proposals for inclusion on proxy statements; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to disclosing how senior executives are paid, American corporations have traditionally handed their shareholders a rear-view mirror. A few months into a new fiscal year, most public companies divulge how much they paid their top managers in the previous one. Occasionally, an irate investor attends the annual meeting to rail against the excesses, but by then the checks have been cut and cashed.</p>
        <p>Lately, however, companies have started offering a more timely peek at executive pay. Since Aug. 23, the Securities and Exchange Commission has required separate filings for a variety of events, including the signing or amendment of important contracts. The new rule has produced a stream of details that otherwise would have been buried deep in quarterly or year-end earnings reports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under S.E.C. new rules, bonus targets for senior executives are disclosed now, not later.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to disclosing how senior executives are paid, American corporations have traditionally handed their shareholders a rear-view mirror. A few months into a new fiscal year, most public companies divulge how much they paid their top managers in the previous one. Occasionally, an irate investor attends the annual meeting to rail against the excesses, but by then the checks have been cut and cashed.</p>
        <p>Lately, however, companies have started offering a more timely peek at executive pay. Since Aug. 23, the Securities and Exchange Commission has required separate filings for a variety of events, including the signing or amendment of important contracts. The new rule has produced a stream of details that otherwise would have been buried deep in quarterly or year-end earnings reports.</p>
        <p>On Thursday, Martha Stewart Living Omnimedia disclosed the terms of a five-year contract with Ms. Stewart that she signed on Sept. 17. After she serves her five-month prison sentence for obstruction of justice, Ms. Stewart will receive a salary of $900,000, an annual bonus of $495,000 to $1.35 million and a $100,000 expense account, the company reported. Upon signing, she also received a fee of $200,000.</p>
        <p>A week earlier, Coca-Cola disclosed that the annual salary of its new chairman and chief executive, Neville Isdell, is $1.5 million and that his bonus could be as much as $6 million in cash and $10.5 million in stock. That revelation gave Coke's shareholders a more complete picture of the deal that lured Mr. Isdell out of retirement. The company had already disclosed that it gave him 450,000 stock options and 150,000 shares of restricted stock. So any investors who wondered whether Mr. Isdell had returned purely for the challenge of reinvigorating a flagging icon now have their answer.</p>
        <p>Those filings revealed pay plans that investors might otherwise not have spotted until the companies sent out proxy statements before their next annual meeting. The accelerated disclosures give shareholders a chance to react by submitting proposals that could be included on those proxies and put to a vote.</p>
        <p>''The earlier you have this stuff, the better,'' said Nell Minow, a vocal critic of corporate governance and the editor of The Corporate Library in Portland, Me. ''It's always better to have it right away.''</p>
        <p>In some cases, companies are disclosing unusual incentive plans that may help investors decide whether to buy or sell a stock. For example, J.Jill Group, a retailer of women's clothing, reported that it had established a ''fall season special bonus plan'' that could double the pay of its chief executive over the last six months of the year if profits exceed goals. According to the company's summary of the plan, J.Jill's chief executive, Gordon R. Cooke, could collect a bonus equal to half his annual salary if the company's preliminary earnings per share exceeded the company's goal for the last two quarters of 2004.</p>
        <p>Such an emphasis on short-term results might scare off some investors, but Gilbert W. Harrison, the chairman of Financo, an investment bank that specializes in retailing, applauded J.Jill for its creativity. ''Everybody has to get more and more creative in order to incentivize employees, and stock options are not necessarily the way to go in today's world,'' Mr. Harrison said. J.Jill did not respond to requests for comment.</p>
        <p>Under the new rules, companies are disclosing some details of employment arrangements that are considerably more esoteric than the size of a paycheck. In some cases, the reports have become fodder for speculation among employees and shareholders.</p>
        <p>Last week, Merrill Lynch &amp; Company reported in a filing that its chief executive, E.Stanley O'Neal, and other officers had agreed to give six months' notice before joining a competitor and before hiring away Merrill employees. The firm asked them to sign the agreements before it renewed their severance arrangements.</p>
        <p>A spokesman for Merrill, Bill Halldin, said the firm had merely ''enhanced the restriction on working for competitors and hiring Merrill Lynch employees to protect the company's interests in the event of an executive's departure.'' But the filing set off a guessing game among some Merrill brokers about who might be leaving or if the firm was being dressed up for sale. Mr. Halldin declined to comment on that speculation.</p>
        <p>Heather R. Badami, a partner at Bryan Cave L.L.P., a law firm in Washington, said it was probably inevitable that the new S.E.C. rules would have some unintended consequences. ''There is a risk that companies will overdisclose in an abundance of caution here,'' she said. ''If investors are getting pop-ups every time an executive enters into any kind of an arrangement, there may be investor confusion.''</p>
        <p>She said that there was a benefit in having companies publish all the details of executive pay once a year, along with an explanation of how the amounts were determined and why. The new filings generally do not provide any context and may lead investors to jump to false conclusions, she said.</p>
        <p>But Ms. Minow said she was sure that companies would find ways to take advantage of the new disclosure rules and even more certain that the requirements would not put a dent in the amounts that chief executives take home. ''They'll always find other pockets to stuff,'' she said. ''If companies demonstrated one-tenth the ingenuity in running their businesses as they do in coming up with ways to pay their C.E.O.'s, we would all get rich.''</p>
        <p>THE AGENDA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
