<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Patrol, and Now on Edge</title>
    <meta content="25voices" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/25/nyregion/25voices.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1835690"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Powell, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pekearo, Nicholas T</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marshalik, Yevgeniy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bell, Sean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police Brutality and Misconduct</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kelly, Raymond W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6DE1230F936A15750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1624" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Patrol, and Now on Edge</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">On Patrol, and Now on Edge</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL POWELL; Cassi Feldman, Manny Fernandez and Michael Wilson contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Powell, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City police officers say they are underappreciated and underpaid, their uniforms rendering them walking targets; comments reflect spate of attacks on officers, including fatal shooting of two auxiliary officers in Greenwich Village, and indictment of three detectives in shooting of Sean Bell in Queens; younger officers often speak of feeling embattled, while veterans seem inclined to distinguish between potential for violence and reality, which is that it is rare; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The news has been dreadful for two weeks now, a steady rain of shootings and beatings and knifings and indictments for members of the nation's largest police department. Even officers stoic by nature confess to being rattled.</p>
        <p>Police Officer Nelida Flores gives a tour of her beat in Greenwich Village: This is where a drunk knocked her out cold, this is where she tackled a beefy guy twice her (diminutive) size, this is where some guy called her a sellout for wearing police blues.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>After being celebrated for a drop in crime, police officers now say they’re underappreciated and underpaid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The news has been dreadful for two weeks now, a steady rain of shootings and beatings and knifings and indictments for members of the nation's largest police department. Even officers stoic by nature confess to being rattled.</p>
        <p>Police Officer Nelida Flores gives a tour of her beat in Greenwich Village: This is where a drunk knocked her out cold, this is where she tackled a beefy guy twice her (diminutive) size, this is where some guy called her a sellout for wearing police blues.</p>
        <p>Her nickname is ''the pit bull''; she loves her job and shrugs off insults.</p>
        <p>Now this voluble woman falls silent. She stands at the corner of Sullivan and Bleecker Streets, a few steps from where, 11 days ago, a gunman killed Auxiliary Officers Yevgeniy Marshalik, whom everyone called Eugene, and Nicholas T. Pekearo. They both reported to Officer Flores.</p>
        <p>''My body is shaking -- I'm in a fog really.'' She shakes her head, a thick ponytail flowing from beneath her hat. ''I loved Nick and Eugene. I promised their parents I'd take care of them. It's a nightmare I can't wake up from.''</p>
        <p>The 36,500-strong New York City Police Department is a vast and balkanized kingdom, bisected by units and divisions. After being celebrated for the crime drop in the mid-1990s, when relatively few citizens and reporters questioned their tactics, officers now say they're underappreciated and underpaid, their uniforms rendering them walking targets.</p>
        <p>Such sentiments are not new, but the storm of the past few weeks, with the attacks and the legal charges, feeds a palpable sense of worry and grievance and, sometimes, anger.</p>
        <p>An officer with six years on the beat stood outside a high school near Union Square in Manhattan last week. He ticked off the mayhem of the past two weeks: A plainclothes officer shot in Harlem, a transit officer stabbed on a subway platform in Brooklyn, the two auxiliaries gunned down, and three detectives indicted in Queens. (In the latest attack, a gunman fired at officers responding to a shooting outside a Bronx deli on Friday night, though none were hit.)</p>
        <p>The officer said he felt ''very scared, very panicked.''</p>
        <p>''We never know when we go outside what is going to happen to us,'' he said. ''We are an easy target.''</p>
        <p>Another officer in the Bronx said he used to wear ''N.Y.P.D.'' T-shirts when he was off duty. Not anymore. He plans to buy a shirt with a removable chest plate that he can use off duty, at a cost of about $1,000.</p>
        <p>''It feels like open season on cops,'' he said. ''It really feels like you got a target on your back.''</p>
        <p>These two officers were among a dozen interviewed last week, most of whom spoke on the condition of anonymity because it is against department policy to do so without approval. The Police Department asked Officer Flores -- and two of her precinct's commanding officers -- to speak on the record.</p>
        <p>A sergeant in Brooklyn with a decade in uniform waved off talk of fear: He is annoyed. For a grand jury to indict the three detectives in the shooting of Sean Bell just two days after two auxiliary officers were killed? That is a bitter draught to swallow.</p>
        <p>The sergeant took a poke at a minister and a councilman who led the call for indictments, whose names evoke snorts of disgust from some officers: ''I'd like to see the Rev. Al Sharpton or Charles Barron chase down an armed gunman when they've got nothing but a stick.''</p>
        <p>If the pendulum of public opinion is swinging back a touch, some of the reasons are grounded in recent history. Police tactics accompanying the city's 14-year-drop in crime often drew complaints. The street crimes unit gained a reputation for frisking far more African-Americans than it arrested; the department eventually disbanded the unit in the face of protests and lawsuits.</p>
        <p>But if many black residents are unwilling to credit such explanations, their views could reflect the past decade's alienation.</p>
        <p>''Look, we understand that some of these tactics are intrusive and that a lot of people don't like them,'' said Police Commissioner Raymond W. Kelly. ''We need to do a better job of saying: 'Hey, we got the wrong person. We apologize.' ''</p>
        <p>Police officers stopped 508,540 people last year, an average of 1,393 per day. That was up from 97,296 stops in 2002; the police said the rise was due in part to more faithful reporting.</p>
        <p>New York City remains much safer not just for civilians but also for police officers. In 1971, 14 officers died in the line of duty. Eleven died violently in 1974. Last year, two officers died, which is in keeping with the recent trend.</p>
        <p>Some police discontent may owe little to the two bloody weeks. Eugene O'Donnell, a professor at John Jay College of Criminal Justice and a former beat officer in the city, said the department focused on driving down crime numbers to the exclusion of more subtle measures. Just as teachers balk at being measured by test scores, police officers bridle at constantly being told to bring in better numbers.</p>
        <p>''We're driving enforcement in a bad way, and it's demoralizing for cops,'' Mr. O'Donnell said. ''The job is not seen as having the luster it once did.''</p>
        <p>No officer expects riches, but the pay is not great by New York City standards. Officer Flores, 38, makes around the median household income in the city, which is just under $60,000. ''I live paycheck to paycheck,'' she said. ''I told my daughter, 'Keep your grades up, because you need the scholarship.' ''</p>
        <p>Lt. Michael Casey, 40, who works alongside Officer Flores in the Sixth Precinct, agreed that the salary was not so hot. But he shrugged off suggestions that the events of the past two weeks, not least the indictments in Queens, might inhibit officers.</p>
        <p>''When you're chasing after a guy with a gun, I guarantee you're not thinking of a legal case in Queens,'' Lieutenant Casey said. ''You're not thinking of anything until it's over and you exhale.''</p>
        <p>Other officers said they read of the indictments with a nagging thought: But for the grace of different assignments, they might be facing similar charges. ''I don't know what was going through their heads,'' a five-year veteran in the Bronx said of the indicted detectives. ''They might have made a mistake, but I don't think they deserve to be facing criminal charges.''</p>
        <p>He said self-doubt roiled him. ''Every car I pull over, I think, 'Am I going to get indicted for this?' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Police Department statistics suggest that officers overcome such worries. Arrests as a result of stops more than doubled last year from 2002, and summonses more than quintupled.</p>
        <p>Officers said the recent violence served to remind them that armor and armaments provide just so much protection. Once a suspect pulls a gun or a knife and an officer responds, anything can happen.</p>
        <p>''When you engage in an argument with a perp or whatever, you have to be in the officer's shoes,'' explained a young officer with three months on the beat in East Harlem. ''When you're shooting, you don't realize how many times you shoot. It goes so fast, you don't realize.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kelly, who fired his gun three times as a young beat officer, said he gained an acute awareness that bullets fly in unintended directions. ''You're running around and the adrenalin is surging, and, quite frankly, sometimes that's the attraction of it,'' Mr. Kelly said. ''But you also have to exhale and think.''</p>
        <p>Age and experience might figure in. Younger officers often spoke of feeling embattled, while veterans seemed inclined to distinguish between the potential for violence and the reality, which is that it is rare.</p>
        <p>Back in the Sixth Precinct, where the two young auxiliary officers died, the randomness confounds. One square mile, the Sixth Precinct runs from the Hudson River to the prosperous center of Greenwich Village.</p>
        <p>A shopkeeper on Bleecker Street spotted Officer Flores, walked over and gave her a long embrace. A woman with a worn face and a gray ponytail waved: ''Hi, officer.''</p>
        <p>Officer Flores waved back, then explained that she had arrested the woman ''like six times for drug possession.''</p>
        <p>The most common crime here is grand larceny, which the precinct commander, Deputy Inspector Theresa J. Shortell, defined thusly: ''It means some lady went to the bathroom at a restaurant and left her purse in her chair.'' Inspector Shortell rolled her eyes. ''I mean, you know, hello?''</p>
        <p>Yet last week Inspector Shortell found herself handing the departmental colors to a bereaved mother.</p>
        <p>Officer Flores resisted the notion, put forward by a number of the officers interviewed, that officers feel like passengers on the Titanic. She has been knocked dizzy, the bureaucracy sometimes gets to her, the salary could be better -- but still.</p>
        <p>''I'm nosy, I like to be in people's business, I can take a drunk out at the knees,'' she said, smiling. ''Most days I enjoy coming to work.''</p>
        <p>She walked down a darkened Sullivan Street, to where Officer Marshalik, 19, died and then to where Officer Pekearo, 28, died. She examined the handwritten notes and the tulips, roses and carnations taped to a lamppost. ''They were trying to do what I taught them, they were trailing behind until he turned around,'' she said. ''Their parents used to worry, and I would say: 'You tell them that I'll be your mother away from home.' ''</p>
        <p>There was silence. Rain misted on her visor.</p>
        <p>''I think every cop wants to get out, retire, without shooting a gun,'' she said. ''But danger is always there. You know that, and still your heart breaks.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
