<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Notes From Laredo; Tracing Clues Along the Border</title>
    <meta content="23MICH$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/23/opinion/23MICH.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1417939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Border Patrol (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Michelini, Dennis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Illegal Aliens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Texas</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Border Patrol</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E1DA143CF930A1575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1337" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Notes From Laredo; Tracing Clues Along the Border</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Notes From Laredo: Following Footprints Across the Border</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Dennis Michelini</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Michelini, Dennis</byline>
      <dateline>LAREDO, Tex.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dennis Michelini Op-Ed article on reading of footprints and other parts of his work as US Border Patrol agent tracking illegal immigrants in south Texas; notes nauseating and sad encounters he has had with bodies of men who died trying to cross harsh landscape; says country has right to maintain and protect its borders; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's night, and I'm tracking a group of 20 illegal immigrants through the thick and tangled brush of south Texas. About 30 miles to my left, the subdued orange glow of the closest city, Eagle Pass, gently illuminates the night sky. It's quiet out here. Besides the wind and the occasional yapping of coyotes, nothing stirs. The terrain lacks much in the way of topography.</p>
        <p>When I do manage to come to the top of a moderate rise, I can see the blinking red light of a radio tower off in the distance. I've been following this group for the last three miles from the Rio Grande. Their guide, or more correctly, the smuggler, is leading his entourage toward that tower. From there he'll scoot around the southern side of Eagle Pass and either sneak them past the Border Patrol checkpoint or to a staging house in Crystal City. If he walks them to a pickup location on the highway, I'll have a reasonable chance of catching the group. But if he guides them into Crystal City, I will lose them, unable to pick up their trail on the sidewalks and paved roads of the neighborhoods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A country has a right to maintain and protect its borders, to stand on a point and say, "We start here."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's night, and I'm tracking a group of 20 illegal immigrants through the thick and tangled brush of south Texas. About 30 miles to my left, the subdued orange glow of the closest city, Eagle Pass, gently illuminates the night sky. It's quiet out here. Besides the wind and the occasional yapping of coyotes, nothing stirs. The terrain lacks much in the way of topography.</p>
        <p>When I do manage to come to the top of a moderate rise, I can see the blinking red light of a radio tower off in the distance. I've been following this group for the last three miles from the Rio Grande. Their guide, or more correctly, the smuggler, is leading his entourage toward that tower. From there he'll scoot around the southern side of Eagle Pass and either sneak them past the Border Patrol checkpoint or to a staging house in Crystal City. If he walks them to a pickup location on the highway, I'll have a reasonable chance of catching the group. But if he guides them into Crystal City, I will lose them, unable to pick up their trail on the sidewalks and paved roads of the neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Next time you step off the sidewalk in a park, stop and take a look at your footprint. To a Border Patrol agent, what you left is called ''sign.'' The act of looking for sign is called ''cutting.'' Whether you are a pilot, as I am now, or a field agent on the ground, as I was for five years, cutting for sign is essentially the same.</p>
        <p>All along the Texas portion of the Rio Grande, from as far east as El Paso, through Big Bend National Park, past the city of Del Rio, to where the river eventually spills into the gulf, Border Patrol agents cut for sign left by illegal immigrants trekking north, northeast or east on their way to prearranged pickup sites along roads or to staging houses securely nestled in small communities.</p>
        <p>Out of the tangled mess of immigration laws and policy falls our simple job of cutting for sign. We have our helicopters, night-vision goggles, seismic sensors and surveillance cameras. Still, there is a wondrous simplicity in walking out tracks. You can't tell a person's race from a footprint or profile a person from a Converse tennis shoe. They are all equal -- in that they all shouldn't be here.</p>
        <p>As Border Patrol agents, we are often asked why we stop these poor people who only wish to come here to work. I understand that we're a nation of immigrants but I believe a country has a right to maintain and protect its borders, to stand on a point and say, ''We start here.'' I don't mind drawing that line in the sand, literally or figuratively.</p>
        <p>Each shift starts with agents making cuts across large sections of their assigned area. Generally, we follow the largest group, but sometimes we just look for the one that has passed through most recently. A freshly made footprint shines. The soil beneath has been pressed in one direction. It is similar to patterns children make running their fingers up and down their corduroy pants. Wind eventually disturbs this uniformity, and while you can still make out the pattern of the shoe, the shine has faded.</p>
        <p>To an agent, a group that is shining is hard to pass up, because he knows it is just ahead, maybe resting in the next arroyo. He can tell how old a sign is by the animal or insect marks across it. Maybe the cactus the group walked across and nicked is still wet. Or if an agent is tracking a group at night, he might notice the absence of spider webs strung between the brush.</p>
        <p>But often it is the sole of the shoe that leaves the most clues. Agents have all kinds of names for the patterns etched into the soles: lazy S, running W, Converse, flat-soled boot, thin-lined, circle in the heel, circle in the toe. The combination of distinct tread designs and total number of footprints identifies groups. As these groups march through the brush, they inevitably walk across the signs of other groups. Groups are constantly criss-crossing each other. They're not physically bumping into one another, but passing the same watering holes, windmills, tanks, reservoirs, arroyos and fence lines.</p>
        <p>A group can walk about three miles an hour. Often it is led by a guide who is part of a much larger trafficking organization that helps transport people to cities across the country. But the guide's only job is to get them to the pickup locations. Sometimes after a guide shepherds his group across a drag -- a swath of soft dirt that agents create to capture footprints -- he'll break a branch off a bush and brush the group's sign off the dirt. Occasionally a group will walk across in their socks or backward. I knew one guide who spread out empty burlap sacks to hide signs. A good guide will know the poorly maintained or grassy areas of a particular drag, and lead his group to those places. Groups walk single file. On a dark night, even though people in the group may be no more than an arm's length away from one another, it is easy for groups to become disorganized.</p>
        <p>I've followed many groups through the ranches in this area, and while I don't always know exactly where I am at any given time, I know I can always find a way out. A person who becomes disoriented out there could stay that way for hours. It turns hot -- to 100 degrees or more sometimes -- very quickly. Water is scarce. If you are already lost and unable to find a road or a city, chances are you will not know where to find water.</p>
        <p>When an agent comes across a dead body, the first thing he will notice is the attempt the person made to undress. The first time I saw this I thought it was done in an effort to cool off. But I later learned that as death approaches -- but while the person is still alive and conscious -- the body can swell. That's why people peel off their shoes and socks off and unbuckle their belts. Their jeans become puffed and tight. They usually lie on their backs under a piece of brush. I've found socks carefully folded, small knapsacks neatly arranged beside bloated corpses, a small handkerchief across a face.</p>
        <p>Once, when looking for identification, I came across some pictures a dead man had in his wallet. One of the pictures was of him and a very young girl, a child really, sitting on a pool table. On the back was a message written to him from his daughter: ''Te extraño. Regresa a casa pronto. Te Amo, Isela.'' (''I miss you. Come home soon. Love, Isela.'')</p>
        <p>It is a nauseating and unnatural sensation to come across a dead man. Some of the bodies are nothing more than scattered bones. Some have blackened skin and are oozing dark goo and maggots. All are, of course, a purposeless loss. Yet there they are, lying about, year after year. It is really of no importance what someone like me feels when they come across a dead body. I'm not the one dead. I've not suffered a tragedy.</p>
        <p>I remember looking at that girl's picture, the one on the pool table, and thinking that perhaps right now she is someplace in Mexico playing with dolls in her house or helping her mother change her new brother's diapers. And that in eight or 12 hours, or however long it will take, her little picture of the world will be destroyed.</p>
        <p>Dennis Michelini is an agent with the United States Border Patrol.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Dennis Michelini is an agent with the United States Border Patrol.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
