<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Rare Memoir Of a Massacre Returns Home</title>
    <meta content="23ANTI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/23/arts/design/23ANTI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1417873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="ANTIQUES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Rare Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Deerfield (Mass)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Historic Deerfield (Deerfield, Mass, Museum)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, John (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moonan, Wendy</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Redeemed Captive Returning to Zion, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Antiques</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rare Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Massachusetts</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Historic Deerfield</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DEFDA173CF930A1575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1245" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Rare Memoir Of a Massacre Returns Home</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Rare Memoir of a Massacre Returns Home</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Wendy Moonan</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moonan, Wendy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Wendy Moonan Antiques column on eBay auction of first edition of 1707 book The Redeemed Captive Returning to Zion by Rev John Williams; book, one of only 13 first editions known to exist, is about February 29, 1704 French and Indian raid on Deerfield, Mass; book was purchased by Historic Deerfield museum for $13,750; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The French and Indian raid on Deerfield, Mass., on Feb. 29, 1704, was not the first attack on the fledgling village, founded in 1669, but it was the most devastating: in all, 56 people were killed; 112 men, women and children were taken prisoner; and half the town was torched. The event, known as the Deerfield Massacre, is considered a critical event in New England frontier history.</p>
        <p>The only eyewitness account of the raid and the hardships suffered by the prisoners is ''The Redeemed Captive Returning to Zion,'' published in 1707. But Historic Deerfield, the town's 50-year-old museum of early American history, had no first edition of the book that had put the town on the map. Until this year -- when a cliffhanger of an auction on eBay, brought to the museum's attention by a descendant of the author, ended with the museum's paying $13,750 for one of only 13 first editions known to exist.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Historic Deerfield, the Massachusetts town's 50-year-old museum of early American history, recently acquired a first edition of a book that is the only eyewitness count of the Deerfield Massacre in 1704.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The French and Indian raid on Deerfield, Mass., on Feb. 29, 1704, was not the first attack on the fledgling village, founded in 1669, but it was the most devastating: in all, 56 people were killed; 112 men, women and children were taken prisoner; and half the town was torched. The event, known as the Deerfield Massacre, is considered a critical event in New England frontier history.</p>
        <p>The only eyewitness account of the raid and the hardships suffered by the prisoners is ''The Redeemed Captive Returning to Zion,'' published in 1707. But Historic Deerfield, the town's 50-year-old museum of early American history, had no first edition of the book that had put the town on the map. Until this year -- when a cliffhanger of an auction on eBay, brought to the museum's attention by a descendant of the author, ended with the museum's paying $13,750 for one of only 13 first editions known to exist.</p>
        <p>The raid came at a time when the French were trying to prevent the English from settling in northern New England. To send a message, French officers in Quebec organized an offensive on Deerfield, the northernmost settlement in New England. French officers led an army of more than 200 Abenaki, Mohawk and Huron Indian warriors from Montreal south to the exposed little town in western Massachusetts. Just before dawn, taking advantage of the deep snowdrifts, they scaled the palisades of Deerfield's fort to surprise the 291 sleeping residents.</p>
        <p>The warriors swept into the town, breaking open doors, smashing windows and slaying the groggy occupants. The residence of the village minister, the Rev. John Williams, was one of the first they reached. They already knew he was the most important man in town. They tied him up while they killed two of his children, a 6-year-old son and a 6-week-old daughter. The minister recalled how he awoke to see 20 Indians ''with painted faces and hideous acclamations'' rushing into his bedroom.</p>
        <p>After three hours of looting and pillaging, the raiders set several houses and barns on fire, then gathered up the captives, including Williams, his wife, Eunice, and five surviving children. They quickly marched the captives north in three feet of snow, before they could be overtaken by rescuers. Thus began a 300-mile forced march to New France, via what is today White River Junction, the Winooski River, the eastern shore of Lake Champlain and the Richelieu River.</p>
        <p>The trek was incredibly arduous. Those who couldn't keep up were tomahawked to death, including Mrs. Williams, who was still weak from childbirth. Some 21 prisoners did not make it. The minister went lame, his feet so raw that every night he had to wring the blood from his socks. But he survived the ordeal with his body and his faith intact.</p>
        <p>In Canada, the captives were divided among various tribes, Catholic institutions and the French authorities. Most were eventually ransomed back to the English, though Williams was one of the last to get home. (His daughter Eunice was adopted by an Indian family, married a Mohawk and refused to leave, despite her father's repeated efforts.)</p>
        <p>In 1706, two years after his capture, the minister was delivered by ship to a hero's welcome in Boston. He soon returned to Deerfield, to rebuild the town and his flock. It was then that he wrote his eyewitness account, which was issued by the Boston publisher Samuel Phillips. The tale of terror and tragedy resonated: it was an immediate best seller in 1707 and went through nine editions by 1800. It is still in print (Applewood Books, Cambridge, Mass.).</p>
        <p>''The raid was a trial of the minister's faith, a metaphor for the trials of faith that all the settlers were going through,'' said William G. Reese, a New Haven antiquarian book dealer. ''The book recounts a quintessential moment in the early frontier experience of New England's settlers.''</p>
        <p>Don Friary, the director of Historic Deerfield, called it ''the seminal book in the history of Deerfield.''</p>
        <p>Last January, David Bosse, the librarian at Historic Deerfield, received an e-mail from John Williams, a descendant of the minister, who lives in Honolulu. Mr. Williams reported that there was a first edition of ''The Redeemed Captive'' for sale on eBay; it was already too expensive for him, but he thought it might interest the museum.</p>
        <p>''I check eBay for items on Deerfield every couple of days,'' said Mr. Williams, an amateur genealogist and a member of the Deerfield Descendants Society.</p>
        <p>Historic Deerfield welcomed his news. ''It was a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity for us,'' Mr. Bosse said. ''I thought it was too good to be true.''</p>
        <p>It was. It was only the fifth day of a 10-day online auction. Mr. Friary and Mr. Bosse watched anxiously as the book was bid up to $2,000. Mr. Friary put down a pre-emptive bid of $4,000.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Bosse called the seller, a used-book dealer in Warren, Pa. ''He had no idea what he had,'' Mr. Bosse said. ''I told him Historic Deerfield wanted to buy the book but if we got it we needed to compare it to other first editions, to verify its authenticity, before paying for it. He was very accommodating -- after we gave him a letter from our bank saying we had the funds to pay for the book.''</p>
        <p>The bidding continued to go up. Mr. Friary was outbid. He decided to put in another high bid. Then things got exciting. ''With 30 seconds left in the auction, someone else placed a multi-thousand-dollar bid,'' Mr. Bosse said. ''We were being 'swiped,' which evidently happens a lot, but I was never much of an eBay user.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Friary got the book, for $13,750. ''It looked for a while like it was going to be an incredible bargain,'' Mr. Bosse said. ''The seller was in absolute shock at the price it brought.''</p>
        <p>And maybe it was a bargain. The 13 known copies of the first edition of ''The Redeemed Captive'' are in various libraries and museums in North America and Europe, and one of the last copies to be sold went to the Clements Rare Book Library at the University of Michigan for $10,000 in 1967, Mr. Reese said.</p>
        <p>After the purchase, Mr. Bosse had seven days to examine the book. He compared it to the first editions at the Houghton Library at Harvard and the Massachusetts Historical Society, and is convinced it is genuine. He said it had its original binding but was missing 16 pages. (Mr. Reese said, ''It would be worth $75,000 to $100,000 if it were complete.'')</p>
        <p>Then Mr. Friary called another descendant of the minister, John Williams of Hastings-on-Hudson, N.Y., for help. ''I grew up with pictures of John Williams's house in Deerfield in my library,'' Mr. Williams said. ''I even built a house that reflected the characteristics of the 18th-century houses in Deerfield. It's in Vermont, right on the route the captives took in 1704.''</p>
        <p>He was happy to contribute to the purchase. ''The book is where it ought to be,'' he said.</p>
        <p>So one John Williams alerted Deerfield to the sale of the Rev. John Williams's book, and another John Williams helped pay for it. Perfect redemption.</p>
        <p>ANTIQUES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
