<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shape of a Halo Around a Galaxy Hints at Dark Matter</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="706621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STARS AND GALAXIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRACO (CONSTELLATION)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATURE (JOURNAL)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SACKETT, PENNY D (DR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3DC1130F935A2575BC0A962958260" item-length="1245" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shape of a Halo Around a Galaxy Hints at Dark Matter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WILFORD, JOHN NOBLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GIVEN that stars, gas and dust almost surely account for only a small fraction of the total mass of the universe, astronomers are desperately seeking the rest of the universe, the invisible missing mass known as dark matter. Their search has so far brought a fitful mix of contradictory findings.</p>
        <p>True to form, in recent weeks the widening search for dark matter has taken one tentative step forward, and perhaps one backward.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GIVEN that stars, gas and dust almost surely account for only a small fraction of the total mass of the universe, astronomers are desperately seeking the rest of the universe, the invisible missing mass known as dark matter. Their search has so far brought a fitful mix of contradictory findings.</p>
        <p>True to form, in recent weeks the widening search for dark matter has taken one tentative step forward, and perhaps one backward.</p>
        <p>The step forward, reported last week, is the intriguing discovery of a faint glow of light around a spiral galaxy in the constellation Draco. Many galaxies are surrounded by luminous halos, but this appears to be the first one with the shape expected for a halo composed of dark matter. Astronomers think they are seeing stars distributed in such a way that they trace the presence of the galaxy's dark matter, or else they might actually be glimpsing light from the dark matter itself.</p>
        <p>Dr. Penny D. Sackett, an astrophysicist at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, N.J., said that these observations of light appeared to be the first that could reveal the distribution of the dark matter supposed to exist in such abundance and to form halos around galaxies.</p>
        <p>The existence of such dark matter has long been inferred from theory and observations of galactic shapes and rotational patterns, which must be influenced by the gravity of an unseen mass. Indeed, computer simulations show that galaxies remain stable only if they are surrounded by spherical halos of considerable unseen material. Astronomers estimate that at least 90 percent of the mass in the universe has yet to be observed directly. Knowing the nature, amount and location of this mass could explain the present structure and ultimate fate of the universe.</p>
        <p>Reporting the new findings in the journal Nature, Dr. Sackett's team of astronomers wrote: "While searching for faint starlight away from the plane of the edge-on spiral galaxy NGC5907, we have found that the galaxy is surrounded by a faint luminous halo. The intensity of light from this halo falls less steeply than any known luminous component of spiral galaxies, but is consistent with the distribution of dark mass inferred from the galaxy's rotation curve." Possible Cosmological Clue</p>
        <p>The scientists speculated that perhaps this halo formed very early in the universe's history.</p>
        <p>The observations were made by Dr. Heather L. Morrison, an astronomer at the National Optical Astronomy Observatories in Tucson, Ariz., in collaboration with Dr. Todd A. Boroson of the same organization and Paul Harding of the University of Arizona's Steward Observatory in Tucson. For the observations they used an advanced electronic camera, called a charge-coupled device, mounted on a relatively small 35-inch telescope at the Kitt Peak National Observatory in Arizona.</p>
        <p>Because the halo is approximately one two-hundredths as bright as the background brightness of the night sky, the astronomers had to be extremely careful in their analysis of light detected from the galaxy. They produced computer models of the bright part of the galaxy, subtracted this light from the total light and what remained was the halo.</p>
        <p>"We were right at the limit of what was possible," Dr. Sackett said in an interview.</p>
        <p>Other astronomers said the research was an interesting and potentially significant contribution to the dark-matter quest. They questioned whether the light could be from the actual dark matter itself, but agreed that it could be starlight tracing the presence of the invisible mass.</p>
        <p>Dr. Morrison is conducting further observations of the galaxy, which is 35 million light-years away, to measure the color, or wavelength distribution, of the halo light. This could help determine whether the dark matter is made up of extremely low-mass stars, perhaps with one-tenth the mass of the Sun, and whether they are responsible for the faint halo. WIMP or Macho?</p>
        <p>One of the most vigorous debates in astrophysics concerns the identification of dark matter. Some of the cosmic dark matter, supplying the gravitational force that presumably holds the universe together, may include neutrinos, known particles that may have some mass, and hypothesized elementary particles called WIMPs, for weakly interacting massive particles. Other dark matter, especially that thought to be in galactic halos, may be dim objects made of the same kind of matter as the atoms that make up the stars, planets and people. These objects are called Machos, for massive compact halo objects.</p>
        <p>Many of the Machos are presumed to be dead stars and substellar objects, those with masses too small to ignite the fusion that makes stars shine. By their nature, these objects would be too dim to be seen from Earth.</p>
        <p>But three groups of astronomers announced last year that they had detected signatures of what they took to be massive compact objects in the halo surrounding the Milky Way, Earth's home galaxy. Their cautious reports were hailed as the first identification of the long-sought dark matter.</p>
        <p>Following a proposal by Dr. Bohdan Paczynski, a Princeton University astrophysicist, these teams searched for Machos in the Milky Way by looking for their predicted gravitational effects on the light from a distant star. If the starlight passed near a Macho on its way to Earth, the otherwise invisible object would reveal its presence by bending the light gravitationally and focusing it, a phenomenon known as microlensing.</p>
        <p>Two teams, an American-Australian group led by Dr. Charles Alcock of Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory in California and a French team led by Dr. Michel Spiro of the National Center for Scientific Research near Paris, detected several microlensing events involving stars in the Large Magellanic Cloud, a nearby galaxy, and Machos in the Milky Way halo. A third team of Polish and American scientists, headed by Dr. Paczynski, made similar detections by looking in toward the central bulge of the Milky Way. The bulge rises so high above the plane of the galactic disk where the solar system is that a direct line to bulge stars runs through some of the galaxy's halo.</p>
        <p>But, in what may be a step backward in the dark-matter mystery, doubt has been cast on these reported observations. Unanswered Questions</p>
        <p>In Nature two weeks ago, Dr. Kailash Sahu of the Astrophysics Institute of the Canary Islands suggested that the reported microlensing events could be explained by ordinary stars, not Machos. The observed event rate, he pointed out, was well below the expected rate, if the microlensing was caused by Machos in the Milky Way halo.</p>
        <p>Dr. Paczynski acknowledged, in an article in the July issue of Physics Today, that Dr. Sahu's analysis "makes it not unreasonable to imagine that all the events seen in the direction of the Magellanic Cloud also are due to faint stars, and that no one has seen any Machos yet."</p>
        <p>Dr. Alcock cautioned that it is premature to write off a spherical halo around the Milky Way dominated by Machos. His team, re-examining their data and Dr. Sahu's argument, has made calculations showing that for intervening stars to be the cause of the microlensing they would probably have to be 10 times as massive as the Sun, and so should be easily visible.</p>
        <p>"We think that he is probably incorrect," said Dr. Tim Axelrod, a Lawrence Livermore astrophysicist on the team, referring to Dr. Sahu. "But there are some uncertainties still to be dealt with."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
