<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bosnia Muslims and Croats Clash, Ignoring a Cease-Fire Agreement</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="635756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY ACTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOSTAR (BOSNIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUDETIC, CHUCK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2D7133CF933A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bosnia Muslims and Croats Clash, Ignoring a Cease-Fire Agreement</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHUCK SUDETIC,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SUDETIC, CHUCK</byline>
      <dateline>SARAJEVO, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Sept. 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forces of the Muslim-led Government Army advanced against Croatian militiamen in central Bosnia and near Mostar today in intense fighting despite a cease-fire that was supposed to have taken effect on Saturday, local news reports said.</p>
        <p>The renewed clashes dimmed hopes that a comprehensive peace plan brokered by the United Nations might win approval at a meeting of Bosnian Serbs, Croats and Muslims tentatively scheduled for Tuesday at the airport here in Sarajevo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Forces of the Muslim-led Government Army advanced against Croatian militiamen in central Bosnia and near Mostar today in intense fighting despite a cease-fire that was supposed to have taken effect on Saturday, local news reports said.</p>
        <p>The renewed clashes dimmed hopes that a comprehensive peace plan brokered by the United Nations might win approval at a meeting of Bosnian Serbs, Croats and Muslims tentatively scheduled for Tuesday at the airport here in Sarajevo.</p>
        <p>Mediators announced on Thursday that Muslims and Serbs had made a breakthrough in their negotiations on the peace plan, which calls for Bosnia and Herzegovina to be divided into three ethnically based republics. The main change, mediators said then, was that the two sides had agreed that referendums could be held in each of the three republics to decide whether they would remain part of Bosnia. Settlement Doubted</p>
        <p>But today Government officials here expressed doubt that the meeting would even take place and said there was no chance for any comprehensive settlement unless the Serbs and Croats allowed the proposed Muslim-dominated region to regain more of the land captured since the war began 17 months ago.</p>
        <p>The Bosnian television reported tonight that the Bosnian Army had captured parts of Medved, a strategic highland area just outside Mostar that is within artillery range of the Croatian stronghold of Siroki Brijeg, as well as positions near the central Bosnian town of Bugojno.</p>
        <p>Croatian artillery units also continued to pound Mostar a day after fierce barrages on Saturday that left 19 people dead and 26 wounded in the Muslim half of the divided city, the television reported.</p>
        <p>In central Bosnia, an Army attack on the Croatian-controlled town of Vitez left at least 9 people dead and 30 wounded, the Croatian radio reported.</p>
        <p>All Croatian positions between Vitez and the nearby Croatian-held town of Novi Travnik were under Bosnian Army attack, the Croatian radio report said. Artillery and small arms fire also continued on the two-lane road linking Vitez with Croatian-held Busovaca, but reports from the scene said the Bosnian Army forces had failed several times to capture the highway. 10 Croatians Reported Killed</p>
        <p>The Bosnian Army began coordinated attacks in the Vitez area on Saturday, United Nations officials said, adding that at least 10 Croatian fighters died on the first day. Occasional shell blasts and the rattle of machine-gun fire echoed through Sarajevo tonight.</p>
        <p>The Sarajevo radio and television news reports described the Bosnian Army's initiative as a "counteroffensive," but it is clear from the news reports and statements by Bosnian Government officials that the leadership in Sarajevo is trying to capture as much land as possible from the Croats before it signs any peace deal.</p>
        <p>Bosnian Government officials criticized a co-chairman of the international mediation effort, Lord Owen of Britain, for having announced last week that there was a good chance that the Bosnian Government would sign the accord at the meeting on Tuesday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
