<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Times Magazine Getting New Look</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="635781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK TIMES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULZBERGER, ARTHUR OCHS JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D71F3FF933A1575AC0A965958260" item-length="327" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Times Magazine Getting New Look</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A complete redesign of The New York Times Magazine, which will double the amount of editorial matter in the main section of the magazine and introduce new features and columns, was announced yesterday by Arthur Sulzberger Jr., publisher of The New York Times. The first issue will appear on Sunday, Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>"We are reinvesting in The New York Times Magazine, building on The Times's reputation for quality journalism and exciting display," Mr. Sulzberger said. "The magazine is unique in that it comes to readers on Sunday, when people especially enjoy reading. The magazine will maximize this opportunity by giving something new and special to readers, while offering advertisers a spectacular all-color environment."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A complete redesign of The New York Times Magazine, which will double the amount of editorial matter in the main section of the magazine and introduce new features and columns, was announced yesterday by Arthur Sulzberger Jr., publisher of The New York Times. The first issue will appear on Sunday, Oct. 31.</p>
        <p>"We are reinvesting in The New York Times Magazine, building on The Times's reputation for quality journalism and exciting display," Mr. Sulzberger said. "The magazine is unique in that it comes to readers on Sunday, when people especially enjoy reading. The magazine will maximize this opportunity by giving something new and special to readers, while offering advertisers a spectacular all-color environment."</p>
        <p>Each issue will contain a major centerpiece article. Other articles will be shorter and, in most cases, will be contained on one page apiece. However, articles may vary in size and format to enhance texture and readability.</p>
        <p>Other features will include a personality profile, narrative photo stories, commentary and new rotating columns by Times writers. William Safire's On Language, the Hers and About Men columns and the crossword puzzle will continue to appear.</p>
        <p>The redesign was overseen by Jack Rosenthal, editor of the magazine, and Adam Moss, editorial director. The magazine will also include more photographs and substantially more color, with full color available throughout the magazine. And the logo on the cover will be smaller to make the illustration larger and the design more dramatic.</p>
        <p>Style coverage will be expanded, with increased use of colorful photos and graphics. Travel articles will appear for the first time in the magazine, augmenting those in the Travel section. Also included in Style will be columns on fashion, food and recipes, design, beauty, wine and a new frontispiece by the magazine's style writers talking about fashion, food and design as experienced by readers in their daily lives.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
