<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mt. Sinai Changing Allocation Of Rooms as Bias Inquiry Starts</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="642869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PREGNANCY AND OBSTETRICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICAID</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOCTORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MOUNT SINAI HOSPITAL (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, CHARISSE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Pregnancy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicaid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pregnancy and Obstetrics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931019T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD6103DF93AA25753C1A965958260" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mt. Sinai Changing Allocation Of Rooms as Bias Inquiry Starts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARISSE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JONES, CHARISSE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mount Sinai Medical Center will change the way it assigns rooms to maternity patients on Medicaid, ceasing a practice of keeping all such poor patients on one floor, the Dinkins administration said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Hospital officials said the Medicaid patients, who are attended by staff physicians at the hospital, were kept together to make it easier for the doctors to care for them. The hospital denied that any discrimination was involved and insisted that services were the same for all patients.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mount Sinai Medical Center will change the way it assigns rooms to maternity patients on Medicaid, ceasing a practice of keeping all such poor patients on one floor, the Dinkins administration said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Hospital officials said the Medicaid patients, who are attended by staff physicians at the hospital, were kept together to make it easier for the doctors to care for them. The hospital denied that any discrimination was involved and insisted that services were the same for all patients.</p>
        <p>But Deputy Mayor Cesar A. Perales said last night that the hospital president, Dr. Jack Rowe, had said the practice would be changed immediately to avoid any appearance of bias. 'Very Clear' in Position</p>
        <p>"He was very clear in his position that he did not believe these were policies intended to segregate patients," Mr. Perales said, "but that he would change the practice so that there would clearly be integration of Medicaid patients on both floors."</p>
        <p>The changes came after a Daily News article yesterday said Medicaid patients -- most of them black or Hispanic -- were grouped primarily on the fourth floor, where they were given rooms and services of a lower standard than those offered to privately insured patients on the floor above.</p>
        <p>The State Health Department said yesterday that it was investigating those allegations, which might violate state hospital rules.</p>
        <p>"We're going to assess compliance with our regulations, which say all patients should have their health-care needs met and should be availed of the same services," said Frederick J. Heigel, director of the State Health Department's hospital services bureau.</p>
        <p>A hospital spokesman said last night he was unaware of any plans to change hospital procedures, and Dr. Rowe could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>The hospital said it does maintain two floors and that patients are directed to one or the other in part on the basis of whether they can afford private rooms. Patients on public assistance would generally not be able to pay for such rooms. The hospital said in a statement that there was no difference in the quality of care on the two floors but that some amenities were different.</p>
        <p>The state hospital code, which governs hospital care as well as patients' rights, prohibits discrimination based on a number of factors including race, religion and whether payment is coming from government programs or private insurers.</p>
        <p>In a press statement, Mount Sinai officials said that though the hospital has two obstetrics floors, "there is absolutely no difference in the standard of care provided, although there are some differences in amenities."</p>
        <p>The assignment of patients to particular rooms at the hospital on the Upper East Side hinges on a number of factors, the statement said. Private rooms, for which patients pay an additional charge, are only available on one floor, so all patients assigned or awaiting such rooms are on the same floor, it said.</p>
        <p>Patients without private physicians are assigned a Mount Sinai physician, the statement added, and receive room assignments "that facilitate the ability of attending physicians to supervise their care." Mount Sinai "welcomes and is cooperating fully with this review," it said.</p>
        <p>Two state officials were at the hospital yesterday, beginning to conduct interviews and gather records, Mr. Heigel said. Besides assessing the services offered, he said, health officials will seek to determine if there has been a mixture of patients receiving Medicaid and private insurance on the two floors and if there is any medical justification for patients being placed in certain locations.</p>
        <p>Investigators will also be looking into an allegation that Medicaid patients are not receiving information on breast-feeding and infant care, another requirement under state regulations, Mr. Heigel said. Mount Sinai officials contend that such educational services are available to all patients, either before their hospitalization or after delivery.</p>
        <p>If the hospital is found in violation of any state regulations, it will be issued a statement of deficiencies, Mr. Heigel said. Normally, hospitals are then given 10 working days to offer a plan of correction and a schedule to put it into place. The state would decide if the plan was satisfactory.</p>
        <p>"Our main concern would be that they comply with regulations," Mr. Heigel said. If the hospital does not comply, he said, it could be fined $2,000 for each violation.</p>
        <p>The Daily News inquiry, conducted over several months, found that an informal steering process apparently led to a separation of patients. All women were treated in the same labor and delivery area. But rooms on the fourth floor contain as many as four beds, while those on the fifth floor have one or two beds, many with their own bathrooms and showers, the article said.</p>
        <p>One former patient interviewed yesterday said that though she had private insurance and saw vacant rooms on the fifth floor during her stay, she was given a room on the floor below. She said she thought her room assignment, and what she called sometimes lackadaisical treatment by the staff, might have been because she is black. 'Devastating' Experience</p>
        <p>"Just the whole experience was devastating, but I never followed up," said the patient, Karen Gagnon, who gave birth to her daughter at the hospital on Nov. 7, 1989. "The room that I had was horrendous. It was in dire need of paint. It was dark. I was very depressed."</p>
        <p>Before having her child, Mrs. Gagnon said she and her husband had been given a tour of the maternity ward, where she was shown rooms on the fifth floor. "You'd think it was a different hospital," she said of the accommodations. She added that she felt she was treated differently when she went to the hospital alone, as opposed to being with her husband, who is white. "The whole attitude of people was different," she said.</p>
        <p>When told of Mrs. Gagnon's case, Mel Granick, a hospital spokesman, said that "in terms of specifics of what this individual patient may be saying, we can't comment until we have a chance to look into it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
