<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rules to Simplify Mutual Fund Documents</title>
    <meta content="Y11FUN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1001293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Protection</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E5D71330F932A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rules to Simplify Mutual Fund Documents</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mutual fund investors are likely to begin seeing shorter, easier-to-understand disclosure documents this summer under new rules adopted by Securities and Exchange Commission (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mutual fund investors are likely to begin seeing shorter, easier-to-understand disclosure documents this summer under new rules adopted today by the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>The regulations will give fund companies, for the first time, the option of selling shares to investors using only a summary pamphlet, known as a fund profile, and delivering the full prospectus later. Currently, fund companies are required to distribute a full prospectus to prospective shareholders before making a sale.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mutual fund investors are likely to begin seeing shorter, easier-to-understand disclosure documents this summer under new rules adopted today by the Securities and Exchange Commission.</p>
        <p>The regulations will give fund companies, for the first time, the option of selling shares to investors using only a summary pamphlet, known as a fund profile, and delivering the full prospectus later. Currently, fund companies are required to distribute a full prospectus to prospective shareholders before making a sale.</p>
        <p>In addition, the new rules require the use of clearer, more concise language and graphs in the main prospectus and the elimination of lengthy, technical descriptions of a fund's operations.</p>
        <p>Together, the two measures should make it easier for investors to directly compare the risks, rewards and costs of mutual funds, commissioners and fund industry officials said.</p>
        <p>Fund companies can begin circulating streamlined prospectuses and the new fund profiles on June 1. All mutual funds will be required to complete the overhaul of their sales documents by Dec. 1, 1999.</p>
        <p>Arthur Levitt Jr., the chairman of the commission, called the two initiatives ''the most sweeping changes in our approach to disclosure in a generation.'' The commission voted 3 to 0, with two members absent, to approve the rules.</p>
        <p>Full details of the rules will be available later this week. S.E.C. staff members said that under the new rules both the full prospectus and the fund profile would contain a bar chart of annual returns over the last 10 years, a table comparing the fund's returns over three time periods with an appropriate market index and the disclosure of the fund's best and worst quarterly returns during the last 10 years.</p>
        <p>In addition, investors will see in the revised materials a clearer outline of the expenses incurred by the fund company that manages the portfolio.</p>
        <p>For example, in a table detailing a fund's expenses, the manager will be required to prominently disclose the full cost of managing the fund, before the implementation of any voluntary expense limits. Now, the expense table includes only the costs incurred by the fund after invoking expense waivers; details about the true costs can be relegated to a footnote.</p>
        <p>Barry Barbash, director of the S.E.C. 's division of investment management, which regulates mutual funds, noted that several fund companies had already sought to carry out the commission's ''plain English'' disclosure rules, adopted several weeks ago. But, he said, today's changes would require fund companies to simplify their disclosure documents further.</p>
        <p>''I don't think the fund industry has seen how good its disclosure can get,'' he said. ''We hope they will take these tools and use them to create disclosure documents that are good for investors and help them to make good decisions.''</p>
        <p>Investors have long found the current form of the prospectus daunting. In a 1996 survey sponsored by the S.E.C. and the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency, investors said the mutual fund prospectus ranked fifth in usefulness for investment decisions. More helpful, investors said, were materials provided by the sponsor of a retirement program, financial publications, advice from friends and family and broker recommendations.</p>
        <p>While protoypes of the fund profiles developed two years ago covered only two sides of a notebook-sized paper, Mr. Barbash said he expected the newly adopted profiles would run three to six pages in length. Still, that is short enough that its full contents could be included in a newspaper advertisement.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
