<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Assemblyman Sees Enough Support for Brooklyn Leader Post</title>
    <meta content="05brooklyn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/05/nyregion/05brooklyn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1707316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leaders and Leadership</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DA1130F936A35753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Assemblyman Sees Enough Support for Brooklyn Leader Post</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Assemblyman Sees Enough Support for Brooklyn Leader Post</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN P. HICKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clarence Norman Jr.'s conviction and resulting fall from power as the Democratic Party leader in Brooklyn has touched off intense political jockeying among officials who aspire to succeed him in the first scramble for a new county leader in 16 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Norman, the leader of Brooklyn's huge and fractious party, was found guilty last week of soliciting illegal campaign contributions. His conviction on various felony counts meant that Mr. Norman had to immediately vacate both his position as the borough's Democratic leader and his Assembly seat.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clarence Norman Jr.'s fall from power as the Democratic Party leader in Brooklyn has touched off intense political jockeying.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Clarence Norman Jr.'s conviction and resulting fall from power as the Democratic Party leader in Brooklyn has touched off intense political jockeying among officials who aspire to succeed him in the first scramble for a new county leader in 16 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Norman, the leader of Brooklyn's huge and fractious party, was found guilty last week of soliciting illegal campaign contributions. His conviction on various felony counts meant that Mr. Norman had to immediately vacate both his position as the borough's Democratic leader and his Assembly seat.</p>
        <p>There are several people vying for that position as party leader. Assemblyman Vito J. Lopez, from Bushwick, has moved with the greatest speed to obtain pledges of support from the 41-member Kings County Democratic Committee that will ultimately make the selection.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Mr. Lopez said that he had commitments from a majority of the committee members. ''At this point I have 25 people who have said to me personally that they are with me,'' Mr. Lopez said, ''and I believe there are another five members who see my candidacy favorably.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez is viewed by many as a formidable contender. He is not only an assemblyman with more than two decades in office, but he also is the leader of a large and influential political organization in his district. His political club has successfully campaigned for a number of officials, even outside of his district.</p>
        <p>But as Mr. Lopez has moved to gain control of the party, opposition to his candidacy has grown, with some condemning him for his endorsement of some prominent Republicans in earlier years.</p>
        <p>''This is the largest Democratic county, and he has repeatedly endorsed Republicans in significant races,'' said Alan Fleishman, a committee member. ''It's unacceptable for him to become the leader of the Democratic Party in Brooklyn.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fleishman is part of a group of so-called reform Democrats in Brooklyn who have formed an organization to stop Lopez from becoming county leader. Mr. Fleishman also suggested that Mr. Lopez, by his close association with a social service program that receives government funds, would be beholden to a Republican mayor or governor.</p>
        <p>''He is the de facto head of an organization that gets hundreds of thousands of dollars from the city and state,'' Mr. Fleishman said, ''and he is open to all kinds of pressure. If we don't have a Democratic governor or mayor, he will be serving the interests of Vito Lopez and not the Democratic party.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez said he has a long record of supporting Democratic candidates and that he has rarely endorsed Republicans.</p>
        <p>''I have backed at least 1,000 candidates for public office in my career,'' he said. ''And I might have supported three Republicans during my tenure as an assemblyman. And when I did that, some very prominent union leaders and a broad coalition of Democrats joined in those endorsements.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Lopez said that in the 1997 mayoral election, he endorsed Rudolph W. Giuliani over the Democrat Ruth W. Messinger, and in 2002, he backed Gov. George E. Pataki, the Republican incumbent, over H. Carl McCall, the Democratic challenger. But he said he had supported virtually every other Democrat, including former Mayor David N. Dinkins and Mark Green.</p>
        <p>In addition to Mr. Lopez, Assemblywoman Annette M. Robinson of Bedford-Stuyvesant said she was interested in the party leadership position, as did Freddie Hamilton, who is the acting party chairwoman. Another member of the party's committee, Joseph Bova of Bensonhurst, is also interested.</p>
        <p>Democratic politics in Brooklyn has long been characterized by intense competition based on geography, ethnicity and ideology. Those who favored change were often pitted against factions close to Mr. Norman.</p>
        <p>The timetable for electing a new party leader is not clear. Ms. Hamilton said there would be a committee meeting on Tuesday. But she said she preferred to wait until a new leader is selected. Ms. Hamilton, who lives in Bedford-Stuyvesant, said she plans to suggest to the members that the selection be postponed, perhaps until the next meeting on Oct. 20, and maybe even later.</p>
        <p>''I would like to delay the vote until we sort some things through,'' Ms. Hamilton said. ''I think we need to take a pause and talk about the future of the organization and where we're headed.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
