<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="25TRANS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1514732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DC1239F936A1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sports transactions</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Signed INF Benji Gil and assigned him to Buffalo of the IL.  DETROIT TIGERS--Recalled RHP Franklyn German and RHP Fernando Rodney from Toledo of the IL. Purchased the contract of RHP Brian Schmack from Erie of the Eastern League. Optioned C Matt Walbeck and LHP Eric Eckenstahler to Toledo. Released RHP Steve Sparks.  SEATTLE MARINERS--Activated INF Carlos Guillen from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned INF Chad Meyers to Tacoma of the PCL.  TEXAS RANGERS--Recalled RHP Rosman Garcia from Oklahoma of the PCL. Optioned RHP Juan Dominguez to Oklahoma.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Activated RHP Pete Walker from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Dan Reichert to Syracuse of the IL.</p>
        <p>National League  ST. LOUIS CARDINALS--Activated RHP Matt Morris from the 15-day disabled list. Designated RHP Esteban Yan for assignment. Placed RHP Jimmy Journell on the 15-day disabled list. Optioned LHP Jason Pearson to Memphis of the PCL.  SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS--Placed OF Barry Bonds on the bereavement list. Activated LHP Kirk Rueter from the 15-day disabled list.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  CLEVELAND INDIANS--Signed INF Benji Gil and assigned him to Buffalo of the IL.  DETROIT TIGERS--Recalled RHP Franklyn German and RHP Fernando Rodney from Toledo of the IL. Purchased the contract of RHP Brian Schmack from Erie of the Eastern League. Optioned C Matt Walbeck and LHP Eric Eckenstahler to Toledo. Released RHP Steve Sparks.  SEATTLE MARINERS--Activated INF Carlos Guillen from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned INF Chad Meyers to Tacoma of the PCL.  TEXAS RANGERS--Recalled RHP Rosman Garcia from Oklahoma of the PCL. Optioned RHP Juan Dominguez to Oklahoma.  TORONTO BLUE JAYS--Activated RHP Pete Walker from the 15-day disabled list. Optioned RHP Dan Reichert to Syracuse of the IL.</p>
        <p>National League  ST. LOUIS CARDINALS--Activated RHP Matt Morris from the 15-day disabled list. Designated RHP Esteban Yan for assignment. Placed RHP Jimmy Journell on the 15-day disabled list. Optioned LHP Jason Pearson to Memphis of the PCL.  SAN FRANCISCO GIANTS--Placed OF Barry Bonds on the bereavement list. Activated LHP Kirk Rueter from the 15-day disabled list.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association  INDIANA FEVER--Placed G Stephanie White on the injured list. Activated F Leigh Aziz from the injured list.  LOS ANGELES SPARKS--Signed F Lynn Pride.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  ATLANTA FALCONS--Placed CB Juran Bolden on the physically unable to perform reserve list. Waived T Ulish Booker, P John Huber, TE James Hugo, WR John Lewis, PK John Markham, T Michael Saffer, RB Fred Talley and DT Ryan Watson.  CHICAGO BEARS--Waived FB Casey Urlacher, DB Eric Joyce, TE Mobolaji Afariogun, P Brooks Barnard, C Carson Dach, PK Pat Dunne, T Pete Lougheed, LB Jerry Schumacher, OL Jamil Soriano, T Tim Vincent, Placed TE John Davis on the physically-unable-to-perform list.  DALLAS COWBOYS--Released QB Clint Stoerner, K Ola Kimrin, C Dustin Keith, WR Aaron Boone and DE Charles Alston.  MIAMI DOLPHINS--Released T Mark Bristol, T Morgan Pears, G Dwayne Pierce, WR Jimmy Fryzel, TE Dejhown Mandley, DT Tavares Jurineack, LB Devin Lemons, CB Cedric Donaldson and CB Terrance Leftwich.  PHILADELPHIA EAGLES--Released P Kyle Richardson, TE Brandon Davis and WR Carl Morris. Placed DE Jamaal Green and G Damian Lavergne on injured reserve.  SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS--Released RB Rashaan Salaam, CB Keith Heyward-Johnson, DE Dwight Johnson, OT Jason Jowers, WR Jermaine Lewis, WR Aaron Lockett, LB Darnell Robinson, and WR Justin Skaggs.  TAMPA BAY BUCCANEERS--Released P Andy Groom, K Rob Bironas, LB Altroy Bodrick, CB Hirchel Bolden, TE-LS Jeff Grau, OT Mitch White and TE Daniel Wilcox.</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
        <p>FLORIDA--Suspended freshman LB Channing Crowder and freshman LB Taurean Charles for the Aug. 30 season opener against San Jose State.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
