<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHAT'S DOING IN STOCKHOLM</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="155189"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRAVEL AND VACATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">STOCKHOLM (SWEDEN)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BABSKI, CINDY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/What's Doing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden/Stockholm</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Sweden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880619T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DF1130F93AA25755C0A96E948260" item-length="1787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHAT'S DOING IN STOCKHOLM</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CINDY BABSKI; CINDY BABSKI is a journalist based in Stockholm.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BABSKI, CINDY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Stockholmers feel they've earned their summers. After a harsh winter, when the sun skids across the horizon before retiring as early as 2 P.M., Swedes like to soak up any glorious sunlight with unabashed enthusiasm. Absenteeism from work rises notoriously on sunny days. Children romp at the Grona Lund amusement park.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Stockholmers feel they've earned their summers. After a harsh winter, when the sun skids across the horizon before retiring as early as 2 P.M., Swedes like to soak up any glorious sunlight with unabashed enthusiasm. Absenteeism from work rises notoriously on sunny days. Children romp at the Grona Lund amusement park.</p>
        <p>Stockholmers feel they've earned their summers. After a harsh winter, when the sun skids across the horizon before retiring as early as 2 P.M., Swedes like to soak up any glorious sunlight with unabashed enthusiasm. Absenteeism from work rises notoriously on sunny days. Children romp at the Grona Lund amusement park. Ice cream vendors are at every corner and Kungstradgarden, the King's Garden at the city's center, comes alive with people and events.</p>
        <p>On Kungsholmen, one of Stockholm's 14 islands, you can shed your threads on the shore facing the southern island of Sodermalm and join the sun-bathing Stockholmers, who also enjoy dipping into the brisk water (some women go topless).</p>
        <p>In summer the city seems unusually quiet on Friday afternoon. Stockholmers like to duck out of work early and head out to their stugas, or country homes, in the outskirts. During July, the traditional monthlong ''industrial holiday'' in Sweden, many Stockholmers head south and some restaurants close. Those left behind find the city is resplendent in summer light.  Island Hopping</p>
        <p>One of the best places to sightsee is on the city's Lake Malar. Ferries sail out into the archipelago to the islands of Vaxholm and Sandhamn. Round-trip fares are about $10 and $15 respectively (calculated at a rate of 5.8 kronor to the dollar), and the boats embark from Nybroplan in front of the Royal Dramatic Theater. For schedules and other details - indeed for information about most anything in Stockholm - it is best to to consult Sweden House, which is located on Hamngatan opposite the NK Department Store; telephone 789 20 00. (Note that the area code for Stockholm is 08. Most city numbers have six digits; some have seven.) At the dock outside the Town Hall (at 1 Hantverkargatan on Kungsholmen), you can catch a boat to Gripsholm Castle or to Drottningholm (Queen's Island), the 17th-century summer palace, now the permanent residence of Sweden's royal family. (Those sections of palace not lived in are open daily from May through August, 11 A.M. to 4:30 P.M. and noon to 4:30 P.M. on Sunday. In September the hours are from 1 to 3:30 P.M.; the palace is closed for the rest of the year. Admission is about $1.70.</p>
        <p>The Drottningholm Theater -which Ingmar Bergman copied for his film ''The Magic Flute'' - dates back to the late 18th century and still uses the original backdrops and stage machinery. Guided tours every half-hour cost $3. Hours are the same as for the palace. For more information, call Sweden House.</p>
        <p>Djurgarden, a former hunting ground for the royal family (the name means animal garden), is a scenic island covered with green forests and flower-trimmed parks. Drop by Skansen, an open-air museum of reconstructed buildings representing Sweden in miniature. There are many cafes and restaurants, as well as regular concerts, art shows, a zoo and glass blowing. Summer hours from June through August are 8 A.M. to 11:30 P.M.; shorter hours in the off-season. Admission is $3.70; telephone, 63 05 00.</p>
        <p>The Wasa Museum on Djurgarden holds what was once one of the world's largest warships. Thought to be invincible, the huge Wasa sank not far from the museum site on its maiden voyage in 1628. Raised in 1961, it is now almost completely renovated. The museum is open every day from June 6 to Aug. 16, 9:30 A.M. to 7 P.M., and from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. the rest of the year. Admission is $1.40.</p>
        <p>On Kungsholmen, Stadshuset, or Town Hall, is a 20th-century building combining several styles of architecture. Each December the Nobel Prize dinner is held at the Blue Hall inside Town Hall. Guided tours are at 10 A.M. Monday through Friday and at 10 A.M. and noon on the weekend. Climb the tower with the three crowns on top, the national symbol of Sweden. Call 785 90 00.</p>
        <p>The city has a staggering collection of museums - at least 40 of them, from the National Museum to the Army Museum to the Hologram Museum. One of the most spectacular is Millesgarden, located in the suburb of Lidingo and named after the Swedish-American sculptor Carl Milles. Many of the pieces in this outdoor sculpture garden seem to balance precariously on their pillars.</p>
        <p>From May through September, Millesgarden is open every day from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M.; 11 A.M. to 3 P.M. the rest of the year (closed Mondays). Admission is $1.70; telephone, 731 50 60.</p>
        <p>Much of Stockholm can be explored on foot.</p>
        <p>Wander around the maze of cobblestone streets on the three islands of Gamla Stan, one of Europe's most charming neighborhoods. Or cross the bridge from Gamla Stan to Slussen, a soon-to-be-gentrified area on Sodermalm, with pockets of timber-framed houses.  Events</p>
        <p>In summer Stockholm crams in as many outdoor events as it can. Something is going on nearly every day: concerts at the National Museum, the Royal Palace and the Hallwyl Museum; outdoor theater and live music at Kungstradgarden. Check schedules in the free guide called Stockholm This Week, or with Sweden House. Tourist Time, a summer radio program (103.3 FM), offers tips for tourists every day from 9 to 11 A.M. (except weekends), through Aug. 27.</p>
        <p>The annual Jazz and Blues Festival takes place on the first two weekends in July on the little island of Skeppsholmen. All-day tickets cost about $17 and are available at NK Department Store and at Svala &amp; Soderlund at the Blue Concert Hall next to Hotorget, a lively marketplace.</p>
        <p>The Drottningholm Theater takes over many of Stockholm's major performances during the summer when the Royal Opera is closed. The setting is not too different from what it was 200 years ago, including the rows of wooden benches, uncomfortable after a few hours of sitting (bring a pillow if you can). Tickets for evening performances range from $6 to about $37, and it is best to book in advance. Telephone 660 82 25 or 660 82 81. From abroad you can order by writing to Drottningholms teatermuseum, ''Forstallningar'' Box 27050 S-102 51 Stockholm. In town the post office also sells tickets.</p>
        <p>This summer, the operas will be Mozart's ''Finta Giardiniera'' (June 23, 27, 29, July 13, 15, 19, 22, Aug. 1, 3) and ''Clemenza di Tito'' (July 9, 11, 14, 18, 21, 23) and Gluck's opera ''Paride ed Elena'' (Aug. 24, 26, 30, Sept. 2, 5, 7). All three are in Italian.  Getting Around</p>
        <p>The Stockholm Card is a wise investment if you're planning on visiting several sights on the same day. Prices range from about $12 for a one-day pass to about $40 for a five-day card, available at Sweden House on Hamngatan. The card entitles the holder to free entry at more than 50 major places of interest.</p>
        <p>Public transportation is efficient and convenient. Tickets for the bus or subway are $1.20 and are good for one hour. A Rabattkuponger, or discount ticket, costs $7.75 and is good for nine trips. They're available at the yellow and blue Pressbyrans (roughly equivalent to our convenience stores).  Dining Out</p>
        <p>Swedish cuisine is relatively nondescript, save for the herring, salmon and reindeer; the better restaurants are often typically French, heavy on sauces. Nevertheless, Stockholm has several good Swedish restaurants as well.</p>
        <p>One thing to note before setting out on a dining excursion is that alcohol is heavily taxed; a glass of beer or wine can be $5 and up.</p>
        <p>In the Opera House at the end of Kungstradgarden is the ornately decorated Opera Cafe (11 00 26), one of the trendiest spots in Stockholm. After midnight a corner area converts into a dance floor. For a more proper sit-down dinner, try the Operakallaren (11 11 25) next door (closed in July). The elaborate smorgasbord ($27) is a popular splurge on Sunday.</p>
        <p>In the Old Town, Erik's (17 Osterlanggatan, 23 85 00) recently earned a star in the Michelin guide. Dinner for two in this sophisticated, country-style house is about $100 without wine. Closed from July 8 to Aug. 10.</p>
        <p>The Leijontornet in the Victory Hotel (3-5 Lilla Nygatan, 14 23 55) is popular with Stockholmers. A 14th-century ruin is incorporated into this medieval-inspired enclave. Entrees range from salmon baked in salt and fennel to breast of pheasant stuffed with goose liver. Dinner for two is about $100 without wine.</p>
        <p>At 75 Sveavagen, the Hard Rock Cafe (16 03 50), baconburgers for two are $25.</p>
        <p>For a reasonably priced vegetarian feast, try Ortagarden (31 Nybrogatan, 62 17 28). The extensive buffet of cold and hot dishes costs only $10.</p>
        <p>Stockholm has its own ''conditori culture,'' cafes serving light meals or snacks. If you have a sweet tooth, try Princess Torta, the local specialty cake of marzipan and cream.</p>
        <p>Sture-Katten (4 Riddargatan), tucked away in an 18th-century house, is one of the quaintest conditoris in Stockholm. The ''Sture-Kattan,'' a hot tomato, ham and cheese sandwich and a bottomless cup of coffee is $6.50.  Where to Stay</p>
        <p>Accommodations in Stockholm are on the expensive side, but otherwise quite acceptable. Hotel prices almost always include a buffet breakfast, and many places offer weekend rates and substantial summer rebates (from the end of June to early August) of up to half price. Be sure to inquire before booking.</p>
        <p>The Grand Hotel (8 S.Blasieholmshamnen, 22 10 20), situated on the waterfront looking out at Gamla Stan, is a popular place to stay. Rates for a double room run from $240 to $350. If you'd like to stay in the five-room suite where Nancy Reagan stayed, that will cost $2,000.</p>
        <p>The intimate Le Diplomat (663 58 00) at 7C Strandvagen, Stockholm's Park Avenue, is a favorite with frequent visitors. A double room is $215 to $230.</p>
        <p>Stockholm also has an assortment of major hotel chains. The Sheraton (14 26 00), for instance, is across from the train station and near the Town Hall. Double rooms are $240.</p>
        <p>To sample a more charming side of Stockholm, the Victory Hotel (5 Lilla Nygatan, 14 30 90) in Gamla Stan is a good choice. The hotel is decorated with nautical memorabilia and aims at business travelers. Double rooms are $250.</p>
        <p>The Eden Terrace Hotel (10 Sturegatan, 22 31 60) offers doubles for $172. The breakfast buffet on the top floor has a wonderful view of Humlegarden park, where the Royal Library is located.</p>
        <p>The centrally located Hotel Karelja (35 Birger Jarlsgatan, 24 76 60) is a Finnish hotel with nice double rooms for $146. Avoid the minuscule rooms in the underground level.</p>
        <p>Stockholm has one of Europe's most interesting youth hostels: a 100-year-old ship. The price and location can't be beaten. For only $10 (slightly more if you don't have a youth hostel card), you can have a bed in this impressive three-masted ship, just off Skeppsholmen by the Modern Art Museum. Book in advance (10 37 15), and if you can't get a reservation, 60 beds become availablle on a first- come, first-served basis at 7 A.M.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
