<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Nation; Question at the C.I.A.</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="486855"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CENTRAL INTELLIGENCE AGENCY (CIA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WICKER, TOM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GATES, ROBERT M (DIR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DD123DF937A25752C1A967958260" item-length="723" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Nation; Question at the C.I.A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TOM WICKER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WICKER, TOM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his inaugural remarks as the new Director of Central Intelligence, Robert M. Gates said that at the C.I.A. "we have always aspired to be more than a team, to be a family."</p>
        <p>The problem he faces, however, is that while the agency may be a team or a family, it's also and more prominently a giant bureaucracy -- one that got that way, moreover, with the help of a career manager named Robert M. Gates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his inaugural remarks as the new Director of Central Intelligence, Robert M. Gates said that at the C.I.A. "we have always aspired to be more than a team, to be a family."</p>
        <p>The problem he faces, however, is that while the agency may be a team or a family, it's also and more prominently a giant bureaucracy -- one that got that way, moreover, with the help of a career manager named Robert M. Gates.</p>
        <p>How does that manager now propose to lead that bureaucracy into new effectiveness in the post-cold-war era? Without the Soviet threat that has been the single dominant theme of both their lives, which way will they turn to revitalize and justify themselves in the years ahead?</p>
        <p>Mr. Gates said during his confirmation hearings that he did not intend to carry out a fundamental refashioning of the intelligence agencies he had been nominated to head.  But why not? Hasn't the collapse of Communism fundamentally refashioned the world those agencies are supposed to know and evaluate?</p>
        <p>The problem is more than the personal doubts about Mr. Gates professed by various former colleagues.  It's more nearly the difficulty of any bureaucracy in pursuing a mission -- even when that mission is clear -- rather than protecting and advancing its own internal interests.</p>
        <p>Senate consideration of Mr. Gates's nomination focused on two points -- his role in misleading Congress four years ago on the Iran-contra affair, and whether as a high-level C.I.A. executive he "slanted" intelligence reports to please William Casey, then the Director, or the White House.</p>
        <p>Senator Pat Moynihan of New York, who was formerly ranking member of the Intelligence Committee and who voted against confirming Mr. Gates, raised still another issue.  He charged that for more than a decade the C.I.A. stubbornly insisted that Soviet economic strength was far greater than it actually was, and failed dismally to detect the forthcoming collapse of the Soviet empire and breakup of the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>"For a generation," Mr. Moynihan said on the Senate floor, "the Central Intelligence Agency told successive Presidents everything there was to know about the Soviet Union except that it was about to fall apart, principally from internal failures and contradictions." Worse, the C.I.A. now denies this failure of its "single, overriding, defining mission," Mr. Moynihan charged: "It is not getting it wrong that is unforgivable, it is denying that you got it wrong."</p>
        <p>He attributed the denial to "the gradual routinization and bureaucratization" of the C.I.A. The failure itself must also be seen as part of the same process -- in which Mr. Gates, formerly a deputy to Mr. Casey, was deeply involved. The C.I.A. became part of, and helped sustain, the commitment of successive Administrations to meeting the "Soviet threat," far past the point where the actual threat posed the myriad and fearful dangers so often proclaimed.</p>
        <p>That supposed threat justified huge military expenditures -- at what ultimate cost to American society has yet to be reckoned -- and such excesses as the Reagan Administration's persistent attempts to overthrow the Nicaraguan Government.  (Mr. Moynihan quoted Mr. Gates's warnings about "a second Cuba in the Western hemisphere" less than five years before the Soviet Union withdrew from Eastern Europe, began to break up and started "begging the West for aid.")</p>
        <p>The Soviet threat also justified the C.I.A. itself -- its budget, its derring-do, the embarrassments it frequently visited on the nation, its very existence. Now that justification is gone, leaving behind the huge bureaucracy that grew to meet it -- and those, like Mr. Gates, who grew with it.</p>
        <p>Covering up C.I.A. involvement in Iran-contra, slanting intelligence reports to suit policy or please higher authority, exaggerating the Soviet threat, denying the exaggeration -- all point to the same "bureaucratization" and to its besetting sin, the maintenance, protection and growth of the organization itself. It's the common fault of all bureaucracies, government or private; but in intelligence, it's grievous.</p>
        <p>Is Robert Gates, part of the old order, the right man to define a new mission in a different world for a reborn C.I.A.? To place that mission above the agency's bureaucratic interests? It's a question the Senate seems hardly to have considered.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
