<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prices Mixed as Trading Slows</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="526088"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOND PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GILPIN, KENNETH N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920505T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DE143FF936A35756C0A964958260" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prices Mixed as Trading Slows</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">BY KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GILPIN, KENNETH N</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities were narrowly mixed in slow trading yesterday as dealers made final preparations for quarterly refunding auctions that begin today.</p>
        <p>Over the next three days the Treasury plans to sell a total of $36 billion of new 3-year and 10-year notes and 29 1/2- year bonds. Market participants were modest sellers of intermediate- to long-term securities to make room for today's auction of $15 billion worth of three-year notes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities were narrowly mixed in slow trading yesterday as dealers made final preparations for quarterly refunding auctions that begin today.</p>
        <p>Over the next three days the Treasury plans to sell a total of $36 billion of new 3-year and 10-year notes and 29 1/2- year bonds. Market participants were modest sellers of intermediate- to long-term securities to make room for today's auction of $15 billion worth of three-year notes.</p>
        <p>Traders and analysts said that demand at the three-year sale would almost certainly be stronger than for the 10-year notes and 29 1/2-year bonds to be auctioned on tomorrow and Thursday, respectively.</p>
        <p>Aside from the comparatively short maturity of the three-year notes, demand at the sale "is expected to benefit from rapidly escalating speculation that the Federal Reserve Board is about to ease monetary policy," analysts at MMS International, an economic information service company, noted in their daily market commentary.</p>
        <p>Late yesterday the three-year notes were offered on a when-issued basis at a price to yield 5.93 percent.  Timing a Factor</p>
        <p>Conversely, prospects for the more speculative 10-year note and bond auctions seem to have been dampened by a scheduling quirk. Both securities will be sold just before the Government releases April employment data on Friday.</p>
        <p>An additional unknown is how these issues, the first longer-dated coupon securities to be sold by the Treasury since racial violence erupted across the country, will be received by foreign investors.</p>
        <p>"Foreign participation in the 10-year and bond auctions is somewhat more problematic than it was before," said Brian J. Fabbri, chief economist at Midland Montagu Economics.</p>
        <p>From an investor's perspective, Mr. Fabbri added, the social unrest "either reduces the chances of the same government remaining in power after November, or increases the need for fiscal spending. In both cases I would view that as a negative from a foreign investor's point of view."</p>
        <p>Foreign participation in the Government-securities market was extremely limited yesterday because of holidays in Japan and Britain.  Thin Trading, Good Demand</p>
        <p>Even though trading in the secondary market was extremely thin, traders said demand was good at the weekly auction of three-month and six-month Treasury bills.</p>
        <p>The three-month bills were sold at an average discount rate of 3.65 percent, down from the 3.71 percent average rate at last week's sale.</p>
        <p>Bids on the new six-month bills generated an average discount rate of 3.78 percent, compared with 3.85 percent a week ago.</p>
        <p>In the secondary market for Treasury securities, the 8 percent 29 1/2-year bonds of 2021 were offered at a price of 9926/32 late yesterday, down 6/32 , to yield 8.01 percent, compared with 8 percent late Friday.</p>
        <p>Among Treasury note issues outstanding, the 7 1/2 percent 10-year notes were offered at 9921/32 , down 1/8 point, to yield 7.55 percent. And the 5 3/8 percent two-year notes were offered at 1006/32 , up 2/32 , to yield 5.27 percent.</p>
        <p>Because of the size of the Treasury auctions, few corporations or municipalities are expected to price new issues this week.  One Corporate Issuer</p>
        <p>The Bankers Trust New York Corporation was the lone investment-grade corporate issuer yesterday, as it priced $150 million worth of 10-year noncallable subordinated debentures.</p>
        <p>The 8 1/8 percent securities were priced at $99.494 to yield 8.20 percent, 65 basis points over the prevailing yield on the Treasury's 7 1/2 percent 10-year notes at the time of pricing.</p>
        <p>Lehman Brothers acted as lead manager for the underwriting. The securities are rated A-2 by Moody's Investors Service and AA- by the Standard &amp; Poor's Corporation.</p>
        <p>Activity was very slow in the secondary corporate and tax-exempt municipal bond markets. Traders said that prices of most outstanding bonds were little changed on the day.</p>
        <p>Following are the results of yesterday's auction of three-month and six-month Treasury bills: (000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>3-Mo. Bills</p>
        <p>6-Mo. Bills</p>
        <p>Average Price</p>
        <p>99.077</p>
        <p>98.089</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>3.65%</p>
        <p>3.78%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>3.74%</p>
        <p>3.91%</p>
        <p>High Price</p>
        <p>99.082</p>
        <p>98.094</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>3.63%</p>
        <p>3.77%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>3.72%</p>
        <p>3.90%</p>
        <p>Low Price</p>
        <p>99.077</p>
        <p>98.084</p>
        <p>Discounted Rate</p>
        <p>3.65%</p>
        <p>3.79%</p>
        <p>Coupon Yield</p>
        <p>3.74%</p>
        <p>3.92%</p>
        <p>Accepted at low price</p>
        <p>67%</p>
        <p>04%</p>
        <p>Total applied for</p>
        <p>$34,721,835</p>
        <p>$46,912,215</p>
        <p>Accepted</p>
        <p>$11,402,025</p>
        <p>$11,506,625</p>
        <p>N.Y. applied for</p>
        <p>$29,508,670</p>
        <p>$41,740,805</p>
        <p>N.Y. accepted</p>
        <p>$9,822,920</p>
        <p>$10,506,085</p>
        <p>Noncompetitive</p>
        <p>$1,583,505</p>
        <p>$1,096,940</p>
        <p>Both these issues are dated May 7, 1992. The three-month bills mature Aug. 6, 1992 and the six-month bills Nov. 5, 1992.  Graph: "3-Month Treasury Bills" shows the average discounted rate in percent from Jan.-May, 1992. (Source: The Bond Buyer)  CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
