<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Smorgasbord of Seawater</title>
    <meta content="2MONTE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="884309"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Les Thermes Marins de Monte Carlo Spa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Volk, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5DD1631F933A15753C1A960958260" item-length="2796" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Smorgasbord of Seawater</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA VOLK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Volk, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Volk travel article recommends visiting Les Thermes Marins de Monte Carlo spa; map; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN I was 5, I used to think heaven was a place my great-grandparents played harps above the clouds. When my kids were toddlers, I thought it must be live-in help. Now I know: Heaven is the Hydrotherapie Doyer bathtub at Les Thermes Marins de Monte Carlo.</p>
        <p>The Principality of Monaco was mainly olive groves until the Government and a group of private investors formed the Societe des Bains de Mer (S.B.M.). The Societe opened its first Casino in 1856, then built the Hotel de Paris to house high-rolling Vanderbilts and archdukes. In 1908, S.B.M.'s sea water (thalassotherapy) spa was inaugurated by Prince Albert I. Bombed during World War II, it reopened last July. The new spa was designed by Yves Treguer, a cardiologist and president of the Sea and Health Foundation, at the request of Prince Rainier III. Invisible from the fabled Place du Casino at the center of town, it is an ultramodern building wedged into the side of a cliff adjacent to the Hotel de Paris.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN I was 5, I used to think heaven was a place my great-grandparents played harps above the clouds. When my kids were toddlers, I thought it must be live-in help. Now I know: Heaven is the Hydrotherapie Doyer bathtub at Les Thermes Marins de Monte Carlo.</p>
        <p>The Principality of Monaco was mainly olive groves until the Government and a group of private investors formed the Societe des Bains de Mer (S.B.M.). The Societe opened its first Casino in 1856, then built the Hotel de Paris to house high-rolling Vanderbilts and archdukes. In 1908, S.B.M.'s sea water (thalassotherapy) spa was inaugurated by Prince Albert I. Bombed during World War II, it reopened last July. The new spa was designed by Yves Treguer, a cardiologist and president of the Sea and Health Foundation, at the request of Prince Rainier III. Invisible from the fabled Place du Casino at the center of town, it is an ultramodern building wedged into the side of a cliff adjacent to the Hotel de Paris.</p>
        <p>A word about the French and their spas. The beauty-health connection is different here from what it is in America. The French are deeply concerned with lymph and its drainage. They are obsessed with veins, bruises and something called phlebitic stimulation. Would you go to a spa for a urogenital examination? They do in Monaco. Do not go if you are seeking the Canyon Ranch cardio-yessss! experience. Do not go if you lust to feel the burn. Les Thermes Marins is about state-of-the-art informed pampering. This is not to say it can't make you feel better than you've ever felt in your whole entire life.</p>
        <p>Thalassotherapy uses everything from the sea except tides and fish for ''both curative and preventive purposes.'' Water from the Mediterranean is pumped in from 1,300 feet offshore. To ''maximize osmosis,'' it is heated, but not so hot that it will lose its ''antiviral power'' or kill the photoplankton that ''secrete antibiotic, bacteriostatic and hormonal elements.'' At Les Thermes Marins, the water is alive.</p>
        <p>Sylvie, my spa hostess, showed me around. Everything is sleek blond wood, pink marble, glass or granite with a mosaic thrown in here and there. It is the opposite of the casino's dore curlicues, but no less luxe. Now one of the largest spas in Europe, Les Thermes is 71,000 square feet spread out over four meticulous floors. There is an enormous indoor pool, a smaller one for hydrotherapy, a Turkish hamam, saunas, a diet restaurant, a juice bar, two tanning booths, warrens of cabinets or private treatment rooms, a Salle de Fitness equipped with every machine a bodybuilder could want (I never saw anyone in there), and an outdoor terrace and indoor Salon de Repos, both overlooking the Mediterranean. There is also a beauty center. To the right, Prince Rainier's palace sits high upon the Rock.</p>
        <p>Daily treatments are based on four selections from eight Azur Tonic Program seawater ''cares'': the Algae Bath, the Algae Pack, Essential Oil Bath, Hydromassage, Underwater Shower, Jet Shower, Affusion Massage and the Dead Sea Mud Pack.</p>
        <p>''Your mud comes all the way from Israel?'' I asked Sylvie.</p>
        <p>''Non,'' she said. ''We have Dead Sea in France.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the Azur Tonic, there are six treatments for specific ailments. A minimum of six days is suggested for the Business Program Stay (said to combat stress and get you refocused), Slimming (cold packs, pressotherapy and manual lymph drainage are suggested), Stop Smoking (with lots of skin treatments because ''your skin unquestionably betrays your tobacco addiction''), Heavy Legs (''specialized physicians will determine precisely the condition of your veins''), Stress Control (with individual sophrology or relaxation sessions), and Young Mothers (for postpartum blues, cellulite and ''perineal re-education'').</p>
        <p>Since I only had three days in Monte Carlo, Sylvie suggested the spa smorgasbord, a one-day initiation with ''four care products'' plus something I'd never heard of, a fasciatherapie with four hands. It cost about $200 but Sylvie swore it was worth it.</p>
        <p>The next morning I approached the spa through the labyrinthine hallways that led from our fourth-floor room in the Hotel de Paris to the reception level of the spa. This trip necessitated traversing the balcony of the 1864 Grande Baroque lobby in a terrycloth robe and mules. No one can see you but you can see them, tee-hee. Bronze arrows pointed to an elevator that opened on a sci-fi all-marble subterranean tunnel. This led to the ground floor of the spa where I had the heated saltwater pool all to myself except for a woman in her 80's with an elaborate coiffure doing leg kicks: ''sept. . .huit. . . neuf. . .et un.'' When my hand brushed my leg, I noticed my skin was covered with velvety Jell-O, like a freshly caught trout. The spa brochure says the Mediterranean has the highest concentration of ''active negative ions anywhere in the world.'' Maybe this was those.</p>
        <p>After coffee at the juice bar, I took a glass elevator to the Douches a Jet area. A woman with a name tag reading ''Annie Hydro'' motioned for me to hang my robe on a heated rack, then go to the end of a long marble room and grab a stainless steel bar. (The staff is expert at hand signals.) Annie re-entered, perched casually on a stool, and turned on the white hose that is supposed to ''decongest fat and cellulite.''</p>
        <p>You know those riot scenes in prison movies where they hose the inmates and it quiets them down? They're not scared or in pain; they're blissed out. Around and around, up and down, warm seawater massaged me body part by body part. It was deep. It was magic. I let my forehead drop against the marble wall. Whatever I'd been worried about truly seemed to fade.</p>
        <p>It was sad, 15 minutes later, when my Blitz (a k a Le Jet or Le Grand) was over. I put on my heated robe and Annie escorted me to the Applications Area, a good thing because in this condition it's easy to walk into walls. (The three times I returned to my room after treatments, I got lost each time.)</p>
        <p>In Applications, Pascale studied my print-out and asked if I wanted to change my mind about the mud pack and have seaweed instead. Since seaweed is for circulation and mud for articulation, and since I had a crick in my neck from reading old New Yorkers for seven hours straight on the plane ride over, I stuck with the mud.</p>
        <p>Pascale returned with a blue bowl. Within three minutes, I was slathered. It felt like warm Jergens lotion. I baked pleasantly on a heated table in a polyurethane cocoon. There was nothing much to do but look at the ceiling, where I noticed the chrome was starting to rust. When my 15 minutes were up, Pascale sprayed the mud off. My skin had the pleasing organic smell of dirt and the ocean.</p>
        <p>I headed for the Salon de Repos where from my chaise, I couldn't help noticing that a yacht had discharged its garbage about 200 feet offshore. I watched it bob. Nothing could disturb my reverie, not garbage, not the two ladies arguing about a Gianni Versace handbag. The ability to say ''Shhhhh'' had been hosed and mudded out of me. I felt unalert in a profound way. It occurred to me that maybe this was what relaxation was.</p>
        <p>After a while, I squooshed back to my room to get some dry slippers. Free terrycloth mules aside, Room 427 was a major disappointment. I expected Taj Mahal-like luxury from the hotel that once played host to kings, Rothschilds, Verdi and Jules Verne. Alas, the original rooms have been subdivided into three and ours was so tiny I kept bumping into my husband, who had been invited to Monte Carlo to speak at a larynx symposium. True, the walls were upholstered in yellow silk. But the lamps were lacquered brass balls and all the furniture was sprayed evenly white, as if it had come from a car factory.</p>
        <p>And I almost got killed daily in the bathroom. The shower door was a clear piece of glass hinged on one side, free on three. Getting out of the tub, I kept forgetting not to grab it. This would send me flying into the sink.</p>
        <p>But after two Azur Tonic treatments, I wouldn't have cared if our room was at the Bates Motel. I slipped my key card into the door. There was my husband.</p>
        <p>''Smell me.'' I proffered my slim, relaxed, cellulite-free arm. ''I just had a mud bath. Don't I smell wonderful?''</p>
        <p>He sniffed. ''You smell like hydrogen sulfide.''</p>
        <p>''What's that?''</p>
        <p>''Rotten eggs.''</p>
        <p>By now I was feeling pleasantly drugged. We decided on lunch at L'Hirondelle, the spa restaurant, where Philippe Girard creates haute spa food. I had the Menu Minceur for about $55. A perfect, runny poached egg with mounds of minced red and yellow peppers came in at 99 calories. My entree, roast veal with sage and endives braised to the point of caramelization, was a mere 224. Dessert was the virtuous mousse de framboise for 28 calories. This six-inch magenta disk of paradise was as good as any zillion-calorie dessert. Seven kinds of bottled water were available, targeted to liver problems, digestive ailments, cellulite, edema, calcium, bile function or the elimination of toxins. I had the house.</p>
        <p>Et voila! It was time for my Affusion. Odile told me to lie on a table. Five shower heads pelted my spine with the intensity of a tropical rain while Odile rubbed amandes douces on me from head to toe. The only thing wrong with thalassotherapy treatments is that they're over.</p>
        <p>My last ''care'' for the day was a bath in the computerized hydrotherapy tub. I was led to a cabinet in the Bain d'Algues area and told to lock my feet under a bar at the far end of a filled tub. The water began to move. Powerful jets tossed me in a deep and lovely way. They forced me up. They squashed me down. The computer seemed randomly programmed so I never knew what part of me would be hit next. Way too soon, the thing quieted down. The tub drained. Then it systematically cleaned itself. I expected it to say, ''Don't forget your watch.'' The crick in my neck was gone.</p>
        <p>The next morning, I shared the pool with a nonagenarian wearing sunglasses and a handlebar moustache. Then up to the mezzanine for la fasciatherapie.</p>
        <p>Fascia is what covers your muscles beneath your skin. It's that thin gummy layer of semi-transparent white stuff you pull off a raw chicken breast. Perhaps you've never worried about your fascia. Perhaps you didn't even know that human fascia can clump together and must be straightened out like a rumpled sheet under a bedspread. Normally the resident fascia therapist works by himself, but two or three days a month, Patrick Provost is joined by his associate Stephane Renaud. Together their four hands ''take away off your tensions, mechanical or psychological.''</p>
        <p>We introduced ourselves. It seemed odd that they were wearing shirts and ties. ''Your body is a reflection of your past and present,'' the one who looked like a Gallic Liam Neeson said. ''Our job is to erase the past in your cell's memory. We put our hands. We read the body.''</p>
        <p>Stephane left the room.</p>
        <p>''Take off your robe,'' Patrick said.</p>
        <p>''Now?''</p>
        <p>He shrugged and stood there. You will never see this man again, I told myself, then scrambled onto a table covered with butcher paper.</p>
        <p>''Does anything hurt you?'' Patrick asked.</p>
        <p>''No.''</p>
        <p>His eyes opened wide. ''Your back doesn't hurt you?''</p>
        <p>I guess I look like someone whose back should hurt.</p>
        <p>Towels were placed over my chest and pelvis. Stephane returned and started pulling my skull. Patrick focused on my stomach. He kneaded it the way you knead bread crumbs into ground round when you're making a meat loaf. It felt like he was reorganizing my intestines. Every once in a while the two of them would take my femoral, neck and arm pulse to ''monitor my vitality.'' The pulling of my head and kneading of my stomach seemed to duplicate the birth process from both the mother's and child's points of view.</p>
        <p>''So how's my fascia?'' I sat up when it was over.</p>
        <p>''You have a blocked parietal bone from emotional tension in your digestive system,'' I was told. ''Your body is the story of your life.''</p>
        <p>Non! Non! I wanted to say. Tolstoy says it's just an overcoat for the soul.</p>
        <p>''Tomorrow you will have psychological shock from the treatment,'' Patrick warned.</p>
        <p>That night, while dining in the hotel at Alain Ducasse's Michelin three-star Louis XV, the emotional tension in my stomach erupted and I missed half of the Fraises des Bois dans Leur Jus Tiede, Sorbet au Mascarpone course. The next day we left for home. I waited for my psychological shock. It never came. Instead I fell into a long, luscious sleep on the plane.</p>
        <p>Months later, I'm still explaining to people that a four-hand massage has nothing to do with tennis. The euphoria lasted two weeks.</p>
        <p>Mediterranean marinade</p>
        <p>An initiation day of four Azur Tonic ''cares'' at Les Thermes Marins de Monte-Carlo is about $130, a good deal in a town where it can cost as much to dry clean a scarf as to buy a new one. (Prices calculated at 4.95 francs to the United States dollar.) This includes use of the sauna, hamam, cardio-fitness room and swimming pool. Take two days or more, and you get a beauty and hair analysis too, plus a diet breakfast, lunch and free or reduced entry to all clubs, beaches and casinos operated by the Societe des Bains de Mer. For six or more consecutive days with four Azur Tonic treatments a day, the fee drops to $122 daily.</p>
        <p>The six-day ''cures'' include four Tonic Azur ''cares'' per day with the addition of a ''specific care product'' such as Datavein (electrodrainage that ''tones'' your veins) or Phlebotonic Exercise. Some of these are available by medical prescription only. They can also be ordered a la carte for $20 to $100. (A dietitian, doctor and ''vascular investigator'' are on staff. Medical fees are extra.) Prices range from a high of $1,340 for the Business Program Stay down to $940 for Stress Control.</p>
        <p>An ordinary fasciatherapy is about $100 an hour; the four-handed variety, offered only two or three days a month, $200.</p>
        <p>Any plan of three nights or more can be combined with a package at any of the four S.B.M. hotels -- the Hotel de Paris, the Belle Epoque Hermitage (which has much prettier rooms and also connects to the spa), the Monte Carlo (the only one with a beach) or the Mirabeau. The basic Azur Tonic Program, with a double at the Hotel de Paris for six days and nights in season (April 1 to Oct. 31), would be $2,333 for each of two people sharing the room. The same package off-season at the Mirabeau, the newest and least expensive S.B.M. hotel, costs $1,570. These rates are valid until March 31, 1997.</p>
        <p>A three-course lunch at L'Hirondelle costs $55 a person for the diet menu; a four-course dinner at Louis XV costs $158 or $180 a person, depending on which menu is chosen. Wines at Louis XV start at around $40.</p>
        <p>For reservations at the spa only, contact Les Thermes Marins de Monte-Carlo, 2 Avenue de Monte-Carlo, B.P. 215, M.C. 98004 Monaco; telephone (377) 92 16 40 40, fax (377) 92 16 49 49.</p>
        <p>Societe des Bains de Mer, which operates the hotels and the spa, has a reservations office at 712 Fifth Avenue, Seventh Floor, New York, N.Y. 10019; (212) 586-1300 or (800) 221-4708. Reservations for spa-hotel packages can also be made through individual hotels; Hotel de Paris, (377) 92 16 30 00; fax (377) 92 16 38 59.</p>
        <p>PATRICIA VOLK is a novelist and essayist.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">PATRICIA VOLK is a novelist and essayist.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
