<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fighting The Tax Assessor</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="666891"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="YOUR HOME"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REAL ESTATE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONDOMINIUMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOPERATIVES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Your Home</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooperatives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Agriculture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E3D81039F935A35751C0A962958260" item-length="1134" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fighting The Tax Assessor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREE BROOKS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ALONG with the flu, icy sidewalks and other winter woes that afflict New Yorkers around this time of year should be added the arrival of the tentative property assessments from New York City's Department of Finance.</p>
        <p>Mailed out near the end of January, they act as an early warning system for property owners, informing them of their anticipated tax bill for the fiscal year that starts in July.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ALONG with the flu, icy sidewalks and other winter woes that afflict New Yorkers around this time of year should be added the arrival of the tentative property assessments from New York City's Department of Finance.</p>
        <p>Mailed out near the end of January, they act as an early warning system for property owners, informing them of their anticipated tax bill for the fiscal year that starts in July.</p>
        <p>Owners of one-family homes in the city are taxed modestly by comparison with their suburban counterparts, so they do not regularly challenge assessments. But this is not true of the city's condominium and co-op owners, whose taxes are high.</p>
        <p>Thus it has become commonplace for boards of directors to challenge this initial figure on behalf of everyone in the building. The deadline for challenges is March 1, less than a month away, so it is critical to act quickly.</p>
        <p>All too often, boards fail to go ahead for misguided reasons, said Herbert Rose, president of Herbert Rose Inc, co-op consultants in Mount Vernon, N.Y. Some people worry, he said, that lowering the assessment could depress the market value of their units or imply trouble. Actually, a lower assessment results in a lower tax bill, which lowers monthly overhead, making a unit more -- rather than less -- attractive to a buyer.</p>
        <p>Still others fear that their taxes might even go up if an error shows up in the city's favor. Once again, this is false, insisted Herbert Podell, a partner with Podell Rothman Schechter &amp; Banfield, a Manhattan law firm specializing in tax appeals.</p>
        <p>"The city doesn't have the right to increase an assessment at a hearing," he said. "It can only deny or grant a reduction."</p>
        <p>Anxiety about the potential cost is also unfounded. Tax appeals are normally handled on a contingency basis, meaning lawyers get paid only if they obtain savings for the client. Fees range from 15 to 30 percent of the savings. And even this figure is negotiable, said Mark Shernicoff, treasurer of the Council of New York Cooperatives and a partner in the accounting firm of Zucker &amp; Shernicoff. Payment terms can also be set up, he said.</p>
        <p>Many things, moreover, have conspired to make it a propitious year to challenge the city.</p>
        <p>For one, values have been falling, especially in many co-op buildings in boroughs outside Manhattan. Further, a 1993 court case based on a Long Island situation augurs well for a beneficial change in the way the city calculates its co-op and condominium assessments.</p>
        <p>Also, the city is sorely in need of new revenues. This may soon result in steeply rising taxes unless an attempt is made right now to lower the current assessment, and thus the foundation upon which future tax increases will be based.</p>
        <p>It helps to understand how the city assesses a condominium or a co-op, a tangled web of calculations that provides a great deal of opportunity for challenge.</p>
        <p>In 1981, the Legislature created different categories of buildings for taxation purposes. Co-ops and condominiums were classified as part of Class II, along with rental buildings. The assessments on these buildings are therefore based on the comparable value of rental buildings in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>And Albert Feuer, chairman of the tax subcommittee of the co-op and condominium committee of the real property section of the New York State Bar Association, noted that rental buildings -- especially outside Manhattan -- do not command the prices they did in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>"Sales for conversion to co-op have dried up," said Mr. Feuer, who has a private practice in Forest Hills, Queens. Even the rental units themselves, especially studios and one-bedrooms, are not commanding the prices they did a few years ago, he said.</p>
        <p>Financially troubled co-ops -- those with shareholder or sponsor defaults -- should do even better, said Mr. Podell. Even if they cannot prove an error in calculation they may get a rollback based on sympathy.</p>
        <p>"When you have a lot of foreclosures, it indicates financial hardship," he said. "And the city can't afford to have a lot of arrears."</p>
        <p>Under those circumstances the tax commission can often be persuaded to grant temporary tax relief. If the financial problems remain a year later, he added, the co-op has the right to request an extension of that relief.</p>
        <p>Andrew S. Goodstein, president of Goodstein Properties, won a rollback from the Tax Commission using both these arguments after taking over the Senate, a 228-unit co-op in Brooklyn that had $300,000 in tax arrears. Arguing diminution in value because of a reputation as a financially troubled property, a faltering income stream and the likelihood of tumbling further into arrears, he won a reduction in assessment, from $1.7 million to $1.4 million, in 1993, creating a tax saving of $28,000 for the current fiscal year and will result in further savings in the future.</p>
        <p>A court decision that should provide a major support for all these challenges, according to lawyers specializing in this area, is Greentree v. Board of Assessors. The case, decided by the Court of Appeals, the state's highest court, on June 8, 1993, involved a 133-unit condominium in Lynbrook, L.I.</p>
        <p>The case hinged on the method used by assessors to determine value. Although everyone agreed the value had to be based on a comparable rental building, arguments hinged on whether that figure should assume that all the units in the building would produce free-market revenues. At issue was the fact that similar rentals in Lynbrook were actually subject to controls.</p>
        <p>The court decided that if an equivalent rental building would have been subject to rent controls then the condominium had to be assessed accordingly.</p>
        <p>Its applicability to New York City has yet to be tested, said Israel Schechter, another partner with Podell Rothman Schechter &amp; Banfield. But it should have a major impact since the decision was rendered by the Court of Appeals.</p>
        <p>Moreover, he added, most co-op buildings in the city are more than 30 years old -- just the sort that would have been filled with rent-regulated apartments had they not been converted. These buildings, rather than the newer condominiums, should benefit the most, he said.</p>
        <p>The city's Tax Commission would often compromise whenever such an argument was raised in the past, he said. "But now we have it confirmed by the courts," he added, lessening the need to compromise.</p>
        <p>Finally, co-ops with 10 units or less should be aware that a change in state law, effective last July, now permits them to demand more favorable treatment than larger buildings. This means their taxes can be raised by no more than 8 percent a year and a total of 30 percent in any five years, said Paul Korngold, a partner with the Manhattan law firm of Tuchman Katz Schwartz Gelles &amp; Korngold, which specializes in small co-op issues.  YOUR HOME</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
