<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Glaciers And Poetry In the Rough</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="666846"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="A DIRECTORY OF CRUISES WORLDWIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHIPS AND SHIPPING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRUISES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ALASKA</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">ALASKA SIGHTSEEING/CRUISE WEST</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HARRIS, ANN PRINGLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alaska</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cruises</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0D81239F935A35751C0A962958260" item-length="2146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Glaciers And Poetry In the Rough</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN PRINGLE HARRIS;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HARRIS, ANN PRINGLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN my husband and I decided to travel through Alaska's Inside Passage last August, we chose the Spirit of '98 -- 192 feet long, with a passenger capacity of 101 -- for its smallness and agility. We wanted to edge near enough to glaciers to see and hear the icebergs break off, or calve; hug the shoreline tightly enough to watch the sea lions loaf and the bears forage; sail straight into the Sound where Alaska's humpback whales spend their summers. The fact that our nine-year-old ship was retrofitted to resemble a Klondike steamer, complete with ornate plaster ceilings, sculptured mahogany bar and chandeliers worthy of the Gilded Age, was simply a matter of interest. We didn't object to the theme; we just hoped they wouldn't play it to death.</p>
        <p>In the event, the ship's turn-of-the-century fittings proved to be attractive and comfortable, and evocations of the Klondike era at get-acquainted and end-of-cruise parties added spark to the informal voyage. The focus on the gold rush also prompted an awareness of Alaska's rough-and-ready mining history, reminding today's environment-conscious visitors that Americans a century ago went to Alaska for the gold, not for the scenery.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN my husband and I decided to travel through Alaska's Inside Passage last August, we chose the Spirit of '98 -- 192 feet long, with a passenger capacity of 101 -- for its smallness and agility. We wanted to edge near enough to glaciers to see and hear the icebergs break off, or calve; hug the shoreline tightly enough to watch the sea lions loaf and the bears forage; sail straight into the Sound where Alaska's humpback whales spend their summers. The fact that our nine-year-old ship was retrofitted to resemble a Klondike steamer, complete with ornate plaster ceilings, sculptured mahogany bar and chandeliers worthy of the Gilded Age, was simply a matter of interest. We didn't object to the theme; we just hoped they wouldn't play it to death.</p>
        <p>In the event, the ship's turn-of-the-century fittings proved to be attractive and comfortable, and evocations of the Klondike era at get-acquainted and end-of-cruise parties added spark to the informal voyage. The focus on the gold rush also prompted an awareness of Alaska's rough-and-ready mining history, reminding today's environment-conscious visitors that Americans a century ago went to Alaska for the gold, not for the scenery.</p>
        <p>The seven-night, eight-day trip through the Inside Passage was operated by Alaska Sightseeing/Cruise West, a 20-year-old company that has been offering such cruises of these waters since 1990; the Spirit of '98 made this trip for the first time last year. The cruise can be taken from Seattle north to Juneau or in the reverse direction; since the latter route fit our schedule, we had our first look at the Spirit of '98 on the Juneau docks, where it was berthed next to a conventional cruise ship about six times its size. It was midafternoon and we had a few hours to roam the city before the 5 P.M. boarding. The collection of native artifacts at the Alaska State Museum -- delicately woven baleen baskets, brightly painted totem poles, masks fancifully carved to resemble seagulls, otters and other indigenous animals and birds -- gave us some background for the rich stores of objects made by Southeast Alaskan Indian tribes that we were to see in Sitka and Ketchikan.</p>
        <p>At 4 P.M. the Spirit passengers -- about 76, not a full ship -- gathered in an auditorium on Juneau's Marine Pier for an orientation meeting. We received our name tags, selected dinner from that night's choices -- Italian seafood stew or Mediterranean flank steak -- and met two key members of the cruise staff: the cruise coordinator, Kelly Kelleher, who was to shepherd us through each day's scheduled events, providing informed commentary as well as efficient organization, and Allen Olson, billed as hotel manager, whose job it was to see that life aboard ship went along as smoothly as life at a well-run resort hotel. For the entertainment portion of the meeting we heard, not for the last time, a recitation of "The Shooting of Dan McGrew" and "The Cremation of Sam McGee," with accompanying gestures: elocution in the old style. The ghost of Robert W. Service, the author of these poems, haunts Alaska the way the ghost of James Joyce haunts Dublin.</p>
        <p>There is always a moment of anxiety at seeing one's assigned cabin for the first time; on the Spirit of '98 that moment was short-lived. The cabin was fairly large, about 9 by 11 feet; a bathroom ran its full width, offering plenty of space for a sink, toilet and spacious shower, all of which were new and in good working order. The cabin walls were white, as was the dresser; the twin beds had quilted headboards framed in dark wood, and an upholstered side chair (I had to request this, but it arrived promptly) was of similar Victorian style. Bed lights -- in keeping with the 1890's motif -- were brass and crystal. Sash windows in all cabins opened to the outside, and all cabins except those on the lowest passenger deck had doors that opened to the outside as well.</p>
        <p>An after-dinner gathering at which passengers introduced themselves gave us all an opportunity to meet fellow voyagers. They were from all over the United States; the age range was wide, but those under 40 were a distinct minority. There were couples and single people, and because of the ship's small size -- the main passenger lounge housed the bar, as well as card tables and sofas and chairs for lounging -- most passengers, whether traveling alone or with others, made new friends during the trip. A one-sitting, no-assigned-tables policy at meals also allowed groups to mingle or stay together.</p>
        <p>The true common denominator, though, was the terrain and the wildlife that inhabited it. No one takes an Inside Passage cruise on a small vessel to play bingo or dress up.  The real attractions are to be seen from the deck, close up -- or through binoculars, of which the ship had a plentiful supply. The wake-up call on our first morning, as on most mornings thereafter, was for a 7:30 breakfast, so that well before midmorning we would gather on deck as the ship steamed up Endicott Arm to Tracy Arm -- home to black bears, mountain goats, harbor seals, bald eagles.</p>
        <p>We didn't spot all of these, but simply seeing cliffs 2,500 feet high from a vessel sailing through water 70 fathoms deep made us feel rather small details in the landscape. Occasional chunks of ice floated by to remind us that we were in iceberg territory, and toward afternoon the ship nosed right into Ice Lake Falls, so close that the spray settled on our eyelashes.</p>
        <p>For sheer spectacle, that day could hardly be bettered. After the falls, the ship penetrated the full length of the fjord and rested at anchor near both North and South Sawyer glaciers. Here, the term "ice blue" suddenly took on meaning. Forest rangers who kayaked out to the ship -- visits from rangers are a regular feature of cruises through Alaska's National Forest regions -- explained that compression and buildup of ice, functions of a glacier's age, account for the range of colors, from bluish white to brilliant light sapphire.</p>
        <p>As the Spirit rested at anchor near the South Sawyer glacier, we could see major shiftings of the ice mass, signs that a break was imminent. Sure enough, there was a sudden rift and an earsplitting crash, and a large iceberg slipped off and into the water; the glacier had calved.</p>
        <p>THERE was more to come. Cruising in Frederick Sound that afternoon, pods of Orcinus orca, or killer whales (actually a species of dolphin), were sighted blowing, flipping their tails, nosing out of the water and back down again, singly and in twos and threes. Later on, there were humpback whales, five and six at a time to both port and starboard, near enough so that we could see white patches on the underside of their flippers. That degree of distance is perhaps ideal; edge a little closer, as we did, and you discover that whales, glorious creatures though they are, have bad breath.</p>
        <p>The crew was extremely conscientious about using the public address system to alert passengers about what was to be seen where. Late one afternoon, bird watchers rushed to the upper deck to view the Northern phalarope; by that time, eagle sightings were commonplace.</p>
        <p>The ship's captain was friendly, knowledgeable and hospitable. He welcomed passengers on the bridge, where they could observe navigational procedures and enjoy the panoramic view while sheltered from sea breezes. It was from the bridge, as I watched some sea lions lazing on the rocks, that I suddenly picked up in my binoculars a sleek sea otter poking its whiskered face above the water.</p>
        <p>Tours were available at each of the three ports of call, but it was usually possible in the several hours allotted for passengers to walk about the town on their own. In Sitka, established by the Russians as New Archangel, the principal sights were within walking distance of the docks: the Russian Orthodox Cathedral of St. Michael, a copy built after the original burned down; the Russian Bishop's House, built in 1842 and one of the few Russian colonial-style buildings in North America, and the Sheldon Jackson Museum, home to an outstanding collection of Alaskan native boats, sleds, hunting tools, masks and other cultural artifacts.</p>
        <p>In Petersburg, a fishing village with a quaint Norwegian flavor, fish canneries (which, however, could be visited only on the tour) and the Clausen Memorial Museum, which specializes in the town's maritime history, were reachable on foot. In Ketchikan, we hired a taxi to take us the three miles to Saxman Totem Village, a park in the center of the town of Saxman, where a group of magnificent totems are spaced along a pleasant walk through a forest of tall cedar, hemlock and spruce trees. Afterward there was plenty of time to stroll along the shore and back to the ship.</p>
        <p>We were intrigued by one of the optional excursions from Ketchikan, kayaking in the harbor for $60 a person, and it was not a disappointment. Both the Sky Princess and the Westerdam were in port, and there was something exhilarating about sharing the harbor with ships that from our perspective looked like floating skyscrapers.</p>
        <p>During our two-hour guided trip we saw plenty of eagles, paddled close to Pennock Island, where whisky was hidden during Prohibition years, and returned to Ketchikan via Ketchikan Creek. Along this narrow stream runs Creek Street, actually more of a boardwalk on pilings, where small shops, artists' and artisans' galleries, and the obligatory restored brothel -- Dolly's House -- gave us a chance to shop and soak up some more Klondike atmosphere.</p>
        <p>As on most cruise ships, on the Spirit of '98 passengers can eat their way through the day. At 6 A.M. a breakfast buffet was set up in the passenger lounge: fruit, juice, muffins or sweet rolls, regular and decaffeinated coffee and several kinds of tea. Between 7 and 8, depending on the day's schedule, the dining room served a full breakfast that always included hot and cold cereal and eggs, plus such daily specials as walnut pancakes, Normandy-style crepes and French toast. (There's also an espresso bar open from 7 A.M. till 11 P.M.)</p>
        <p>Lunch usually included soups and salads, sandwiches or light pasta dishes and dessert. At dinner there was always a choice between a fish or meat course, and on days when the ship was underway in the late afternoon, tea and fresh-baked cookies or cake were served at 4.</p>
        <p>A decent selection of wines, mainly from Washington State and Oregon vineyards, with a few California selections, was available at lunch and dinner. Hors d'oeuvres were served with cocktails at 6.</p>
        <p>In general, the food ranged from acceptable to very good. The best meal was a barbecue lunch on deck, at which passengers could feast on spicy chicken, Texas-style ribs, grilled halibut and salmon, linguini-and-crab salad, mountains of fruit and cookies. Desserts at most meals were rich, but they were served in portions moderate enough so that one could justify eating them.</p>
        <p>The quality of the seafood, however, was a puzzle. Halibut, Dungeness crab and salmon, native to Northern waters, should have been bright and flavorful but tended to be bland; meat choices were better. And several passengers complained about the practice of setting out the breakfast orange juice in pitchers full of ice, so that by the time it was poured it tasted like Kool-Aid.</p>
        <p>Cruising on a small ship in Alaska offers many advantages, but travelers considering the Spirit of '98 should be aware of two possible drawbacks. First, on the three days when the vessel has no port of call, exercise is hard to come by.</p>
        <p>There is no swimming pool, circling the deck takes only a few minutes, and on our trip there were only two exercise machines: a stair climber and a bicycle. Both were set up out-of-doors, and on one occasion a deckhand pedaled merrily away while passengers waited their turns. (This incident was not typical of the staff, most of which was capable and polite.)</p>
        <p>A SECOND possible disadvantage is that smoking is forbidden anywhere inside the ship, including passengers' cabins. This policy, of course, appeals to many, but it reduces recusants to snatching puffs at the deck rail while clutching their own ashtrays.</p>
        <p>Few passengers were night owls -- bar service ended at 11 P.M. -- but there were planned festivities on several occasions. For a miner's dinner, the crew and a few passengers dressed up in miner's gear.</p>
        <p>On karaoke night there was dancing, and an opportunity for those so inclined to seize the microphone. Tastes ran to country and western and laments for the Confederate dead, but following the captain's dinner the next night, a pianist in the group played songs by the Gershwins and Rodgers and Hart. By then, most of us would have sworn that there was no life left in Dan McGrew, but a deadpan reading of the poem accompanied by hilariously overdone miming -- all by the cruise staff -- showed us we were wrong.  A DIRECTORY OF CRUISES WORLDWIDE ANN PRINGLE HARRIS, a travel writer, has taken a half-dozen cruises.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">ANN PRINGLE HARRIS, a travel writer, has taken a half-dozen cruises.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
