<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Unapologetic Tartabull Lets Others Do the Worrying</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="667128"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CURRY, JACK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TARTABULL, DANNY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E7DF1638F935A35751C0A962958260" item-length="1267" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Unapologetic Tartabull Lets Others Do the Worrying</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CURRY, JACK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Danny Tartabull strolled onto the tiny Little League field at Michael Landon Park in Malibu, Calif., with a bucket of baseballs every day last week. He softly tossed one ball after another to no one until about two dozen were scattered in front of him. Then he retrieved them and duplicated the process, throwing to an invisible friend.</p>
        <p>It must have looked strange. There was Tartabull, the highest-paid player in Yankee history, collecting his 60-foot lobs over and over as he tried strengthening his controversial and still-mending right shoulder. Even Tartabull laughed when told that the notion of a major leaguer not having a partner to play catch with was bizarre. He laughed, but he had no plans to change his approach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Danny Tartabull strolled onto the tiny Little League field at Michael Landon Park in Malibu, Calif., with a bucket of baseballs every day last week. He softly tossed one ball after another to no one until about two dozen were scattered in front of him. Then he retrieved them and duplicated the process, throwing to an invisible friend.</p>
        <p>It must have looked strange. There was Tartabull, the highest-paid player in Yankee history, collecting his 60-foot lobs over and over as he tried strengthening his controversial and still-mending right shoulder. Even Tartabull laughed when told that the notion of a major leaguer not having a partner to play catch with was bizarre. He laughed, but he had no plans to change his approach.</p>
        <p>In an intriguing way, this innocuous discussion was typical Tartabull. His methods were mildly criticized, but he did not mind. He laughed, he answered questions about the topic and he moved forward. Next issue, please?</p>
        <p>Tartabull's ability to swerve around potential trouble during other serious incidents in New York has been as impressive as his ability to pound homers. Nothing unnerves him. Sometimes, the Yankees wish something would.</p>
        <p>"It's all about being a professional," said Tartabull, explaining his knack for avoiding controversy. "When you're sure of your abilities and what's going on in your life, you don't worry about what's said."</p>
        <p>Tartabull follows this theory religiously. There have been several instances since he signed a five-year, $25.5 million contract in January 1992 in which Tartabull could have reacted angrily about something uttered by the owner, George Steinbrenner, or General Manager Gene Michael or something hinted at by Manager Buck Showalter or a teammate. But he has evaded being injected into back page disputes. He never even reads the back pages. "Danny Rips George," is as unlikely a tabloid headline as "Mets Win 1994 World Series."</p>
        <p>Like hitting 31 homers and driving in 102 runs, which he did last season, his penchant for maintaining peace is a unique talent. Bobby Bonilla and Bret Saberhagen, Tartabull's friends in Flushing, might learn from him. 'I'm Just Me'</p>
        <p>"I enjoy myself," the 31-year-old Tartabull said in a telephone interview from Malibu. "I'm just me. Words are water off a duck's back."</p>
        <p>Indeed. Tartabull has the same temperament if the Yankees win or lose, if he drives in four runs or strikes out four times. Occasionally, someone like Showalter, who treats every loss as if it were the World Series, will appear irked by Tartabull's approach and his routine appearances on the disabled list. Eyeballs will roll and questions about Tartabull will elicit formulated responses. But little is said publicly because Tartabull's power numbers and paycheck amounts make him difficult to challenge.</p>
        <p>"This," Tartabull repeated, "is me."</p>
        <p>Less than two weeks from spring training, discussions about the most recent example of Tartabull trying to dodge trouble have almost vanished. It occurred when he delayed shoulder surgery in October until after he had facial surgery and had taken a three-and-a-half-week vacation to Europe. Instead of having surgery to repair a small tear in his labrum after the regular season, as the Yankees would have preferred, Tartabull waited until Nov. 30.</p>
        <p>He explained the decision by saying he needed to have a potentially cancerous cyst removed from his neck and to correct a deviated septum, and then developed high blood pressure after the operation. He also said the trip with his wife, Kellie, had been planned for months. But the timing paralyzed Michael's chances of trading him.</p>
        <p>Although he reportedly had his cheekbones, lips and eyes cosmetically enhanced during the first operation, Tartabull said, "Oh my God, that's not true." Couldn't Shed Contract</p>
        <p>Because Michael could not trade Tartabull, who started on defense in only 3 of New York's last 72 games, he could not dispose of the $14.25 million left on Tartabull's contract over the next three years and could not seriously pursue the free agent Rafael Palmeiro or an expensive starter.</p>
        <p>Three months after his decision, Tartabull is oblivious to how it affected the Yanks. When New York's leading home run hitter for the last two seasons was asked how it felt to hear rumors about being traded, he replied: "Is that something that came out of Gene Michael's mouth? Or is that another one of those things that says we're going to get Randy Johnson, Mark Langston, Rickey Henderson and Rafael Palmeiro? I don't think he said it. I think it was another one of those that were dreamed up."</p>
        <p>As he prepares for his third season in New York, Tartabull is thrilled about the progress his shoulder has made and contended that Dr. Frank Jobe said he would be ready by opening day. Tartabull longs to play in a World Series and store the videotape of it beside the 1967 World Series tape he has, when his father, Jose, played for Boston. Polonia Fills the Outfield</p>
        <p>He said he wants to play the outfield every day, but that will not happen. Once New York signed the free agent left fielder Luis Polonia, Tartabull basically became a full-time designated hitter. Still, he has a response for those who castigate him for delaying shoulder surgery.</p>
        <p>"If someone criticizes me, it means you're a moron and you're embarrassing yourself for not having a full comprehension of the events," Tartabull reasoned. "Whether I had surgery in January or in October, it's irrelevant now."</p>
        <p>That is about as animated as Tartabull gets. The Yankees know that. Steinbrenner has occasionally needled him without results. Five days before returning from a 30-month suspension from baseball last March, Steinbrenner stressed the importance of Tartabull's being mentally and physically prepared. It was obvious Steinbrenner was trying to tweak Tartabull, who had missed 39 games with back and hamstring injuries in 1992. But the slugger responded: "If I'm doing my best, I don't let those things bother me. I don't let words bother me."</p>
        <p>Six months and 144 regular season games later, Steinbrenner issued a challenge to the entire team to overtake Toronto's two-game lead in the final 18 games. But it was revealed that Steinbrenner was targeting Tartabull when he complained about players being "hurt in direct relation to character," for not playing the field with a shoulder injury. Once again, Tartabull was calm.</p>
        <p>"Anything he had to say is his opinion," Tartabull said. "I have no comment on those things." Criticism From Farr</p>
        <p>In September 1992, his teammate Steve Farr said that Tartabull could not be relied on as a power hitter because he is too injury-prone and that he probably needed a new exercise program to prevent injuries. In March 1993, it was Farr, the critic, not Tartabull, the criticized, who complained about one version of the article and stopped speaking with one reporter.</p>
        <p>Not Tartabull. He speaks with everyone. He knows at least the first names of the majority of the eight reporters who cover the team regularly. He has little idea which newspapers they work for and probably never will. That is one reason why he has survived in New York and why he talks about signing another Yankee contract after the 1996 season and pursuing 400 homers.</p>
        <p>"I like New York," Tartabull said. "I go back there when I don't have to. I truly enjoy it. I have no qualms or quarrels with it. It doesn't bother me. You hear all the time that it takes a special person to play in New York and deal with everything that goes on. It's true. It's really true."</p>
        <p>Believe him. He could teach the course.  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
