<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Williamses Test a Life Without Any Games</title>
    <meta content="28WILLIAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/28/sports/tennis/28williams.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1515362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clarey, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Venus</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Serena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Open (Tennis)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Williams, Venus</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030828T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE4DC1E39F93BA1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="1255" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Williamses Test a Life Without Any Games</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Williamses Test a Life Without Any Games</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER CLAREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Clarey, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Venus and Serena Williams, both absent from US Open because of injuries, generate more buzz than US Open participants, with some of media questioning their motivation; Williams sisters answer by insisting they will play for at least 10 more years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Missing the Williams sisters at this year's United States Open? No need to worry. You should still have ample time to enjoy the free-swinging spectacle provided by tennis's first family.</p>
        <p>Dismissing concerns about motivation, physical ailments and the potential lure of outside interests, Venus Williams said yesterday that she planned to play for 10 more years. Her younger sister, Serena, later indicated that 10 years sounded like a nice, round and accurate expiration date for her own career, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Venus and Serena Williams are recovering from injuries while their customary foils and rivals go about their sweaty business at the U.S. Open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Missing the Williams sisters at this year's United States Open? No need to worry. You should still have ample time to enjoy the free-swinging spectacle provided by tennis's first family.</p>
        <p>Dismissing concerns about motivation, physical ailments and the potential lure of outside interests, Venus Williams said yesterday that she planned to play for 10 more years. Her younger sister, Serena, later indicated that 10 years sounded like a nice, round and accurate expiration date for her own career, too.</p>
        <p>''Oh, definitely, I'm not going away,'' said Venus, who turned 23 in June. ''I'm not retiring before 33. I've thought about it already. I'm not giving up my great job. I like it. I'm fortunate. I'm blessed, and I love being out there.''</p>
        <p>For now and perhaps quite a few weeks more, she and Serena are on forced vacations, recovering from injuries as their customary foils and rivals go about their sweaty business in Flushing Meadows. While top-seeded Kim Clijsters was preparing for her second-round match yesterday, which she won, 6-1, 6-1, and while Roger Federer and Lindsay Davenport were preparing for matches later in the day, which they won, the Williams sisters were in Midtown, making the rounds of television programs and giving separate interviews to a small group of reporters in a 22nd-floor hotel suite.</p>
        <p>The Williamses have talked little in public of late, and there was much to talk about, which meant that once again at this through-the-looking-glass Open, the nonparticipants generated more buzz than the participants. If it was not the retiring Pete Sampras on Monday, it was the recuperating Williamses on Wednesday, and it was not lost on the sisters, who have grown accustomed to complaints that their string of all-in-the-family Grand Slam finals was hurting the game. Now that they are not playing at all, they hear that it's hurting the game, too.</p>
        <p>''You can't win either way with us,'' Serena said. ''I think, obviously, Venus and I bring a huge aspect to tennis, but I still think there's a lot left in it as well without us. But without us, it is a little dry. I would be dishonest if I said it wasn't, but at the same time it would be dishonest to say there is no fun watching the tennis. Not everyone loves me. People like other people.''</p>
        <p>Venus, who withdrew from the Open on Friday, is still recovering from a badly strained stomach muscle that first forced her to retire from the final of a tournament in Warsaw in early May and then slowed her progress at the French Open and at Wimbledon. ''Maybe I shouldn't have played the French Open and just taken more time to rest,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Serena, who has won five of the last six Grand Slam singles titles, had left knee surgery in Los Angeles on Aug. 1 to repair a partial tear in the quadriceps tendon, but she arrived in the lobby of the hotel in high heels and walking with only a slight limp.</p>
        <p>Asked if her doctor would approve of such footwear less than a month after surgery, she said, ''I don't know if he'd approve, but I only walked a few blocks, and they are not that high: only three inches.''</p>
        <p>Serena has been playing with occasional knee pain for several seasons, but she said she reached a crisis point in July while preparing to leave home for a tournament in San Diego. ''It was a sudden action that made it go out,'' she said.</p>
        <p>It was not the sort of sudden movement that typically gets a tennis star in trouble. Instead of reaching for a wide forehand or an overhead, she was reaching down for a pair of earrings. ''I was bending down,'' she said. ''And I was like, 'O.K., something is not right.'''</p>
        <p>Serena, who said she had stopped practice earlier that day because of discomfort in the knee, made every attempt to avoid surgery.</p>
        <p>But she said that the six physicians she consulted all gave her the same answer. There is less certainty about when she will return to the Tour. It might not be until next season, and though she declined to give a specific date, she also made it clear that her nontennis schedule is well booked with acting and other engagements this fall.</p>
        <p>''I love tennis,'' she said. ''It's always my first love, and I really, really miss it, but in a way it is kind of a relief to see that, wow, this actually gives me a chance to do some other stuff, some acting especially.''</p>
        <p>Serena might be the defending champion, but for now, Venus, a former champion, sounds as if she misses the game and the United States Open more. ''I was coming in last night, and I was passing by the stadium, and I could see the big screen,'' Venus said. ''It was just: 'I want to be out there. I want to play the night match. Sign me up.' I was hoping they would move the Open back a few weeks so that way maybe I could be ready, but nobody liked that idea.''</p>
        <p>Venus said she had served only lightly in practice since wincing through her three-set defeat to Serena in the Wimbledon final, but though she is entered in the Moscow tournament that begins Sept. 29, she does not plan to rush back this time.</p>
        <p>Serena, who has also not competed since the Wimbledon final, proudly said she did not cry before or after surgery. But she has been practicing her crying during her layoff, preparing for a scene in an episode of the Showtime series ''Street Time.'' She will play a reformed gang member, and the role has been expanded because she, for now, no longer needs to juggle tennis with acting.</p>
        <p>She is also no longer No. 1 in the computer ranking, having been passed by Clijsters earlier this month. Though Clijsters has not won a Grand Slam singles title, Serena said she deserved the No. 1 spot.</p>
        <p>''She's playing every week,'' Serena said. ''And she's winning almost every week she plays. It's hard not to be No. 1 when you play that much.''</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, Serena, who has played only 11 events in the past year, would like to see reform of the ranking system, which counts a player's best 17 results over 52 weeks. But even if the system remained untouched, Serena said she was confident that she would regain her former dominance. ''And I'm going to be a much better player because I'm going to be mentally relaxed; I'm going to be stronger, and I'm going to be angry,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Angry? ''I'm just going to take a different attitude: take the Mike Tyson approach,'' she said.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
