<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>State Plans to Raise Fees Paid to Court-Hired Lawyers for the Poor</title>
    <meta content="13FEES$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/13/nyregion/13FEES.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1262405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legal Aid for the Poor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mansnerus, Laura</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legal Aid for the Poor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1DB143DF930A25752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="592" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>State Plans to Raise Fees Paid to Court-Hired Lawyers for the Poor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA MANSNERUS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mansnerus, Laura</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State will increase fees for private lawyers appointed by courts to represent poor in criminal and family courts; lawyers working in family court system had stopped accepting new cases two weeks prior to annoucement (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki and legislative leaders announced yesterday that they planned to increase fees this session for private lawyers appointed by the courts to represent the poor.</p>
        <p>The lawyers, who work in the state's criminal and family courts, have not had a raise for 15 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki and legislative leaders announced yesterday that they planned to increase fees this session for private lawyers appointed by the courts to represent the poor.</p>
        <p>The lawyers, who work in the state's criminal and family courts, have not had a raise for 15 years.</p>
        <p>The announcement came two weeks after lawyers working in New York City's Family Court system stopped accepting new cases, forcing judges to turn away people entitled to counsel in cases concerning child abuse and neglect or delinquency.</p>
        <p>While criminal defense lawyers  still accept new cases, their ranks have been depleted over the last decade, declining by more than half in New York City.</p>
        <p>The governor, the Senate majority leader, Joseph L. Bruno, and Sheldon Silver, the Assembly speaker, said they were creating a task force to devise a legislative proposal. The announcement was made in a statement from the governor's office.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki had previously turned aside calls to raise the lawyers' current rates of $25 an hour for out-of-court work and $40 an hour in court. The rates are the lowest of any state except New Jersey, which has a widely used public defender system and makes relatively few court appointments of private lawyers.</p>
        <p>Proposals for increases have died regularly in the Legislature, too, in deadlocks over whether the extra cost would be borne by the state or by local governments.</p>
        <p>In frustration, the associations representing court-appointed lawyers in who work in the city's Family Court decided last month to refuse new cases after Jan. 1. While the lawyers continue to represent current clients, only a handful of about 200 Family Court lawyers have taken new assignments in two weeks.</p>
        <p>Pressure has also built as judges and bar associations have called for pay increases. This week, in her annual address on the state's judiciary, the state's chief judge, Judith S. Kaye, again spoke of her ''abiding frustration'' with the state's failure to raise rates that she said ''were barely adequate 15 years ago.''</p>
        <p>Judge Kaye has proposed an increase to $75 an hour for both in-court and out-of-court work, and she has identified uncollected court fees as a possible source of money.</p>
        <p>State Senator James J. Lack, chairman of the Senate Judiciary Committee, said yesterday that a raise was in desperate need and pledged to work to adopt one this year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki was cautious in his announcement, saying he and legislative leaders were committed to increasing the current rates, but ''without an undue burden being placed on local governments and the state.''</p>
        <p>Lawyers who have lobbied for increases said last night that they remained skeptical.</p>
        <p>''I'm not thrilled,'' said Robert Jay Greenfield, who heads an association of court-appointed counsel in Brooklyn Family Court. ''Who's going to accept responsibility? Whose budget does it come out of? ''</p>
        <p>Harvey Fishbein, the chairman of the committee that certifies lawyers for criminal defense cases in Manhattan and the Bronx, said: ''We're past the point where we need a task force. I hope this isn't just a means for more delay.''</p>
        <p>In a report last May, the State Administrative Office of the Courts found that a lawyer with average overhead costs would actually lose money on court-assigned cases. As private practitioners, the lawyers are basically freelance workers, without contracts or benefits.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
