<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Faust Learns the Painful Truth: Perfection Is Not for the Having</title>
    <meta content="13CONN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/13/arts/13CONN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1262320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="CONNECTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rothstein, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Busoni, Ferruccio Benvenuto (1866-1924)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Doktor Faust (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Connections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E4DB173DF930A25752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1022" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Faust Learns the Painful Truth: Perfection Is Not for the Having</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Edward Rothstein</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rothstein, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward Rothstein Connections column considers Faust tale as interpreted by Ferruccio Busoni in his opera Doktor Faust, premiering at Metropolitan Opera in New York; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Toward the end of Busoni's opera ''Doktor Faust,'' which is now receiving its premiere performances at the Metropolitan Opera, the famous Wittenberg magus who made a pact with the devil is looking a bit shopworn. Faust has done his share of murders; he has seduced a bride on her wedding day and later abandoned her and their newborn child; he has caroused to his heart's content. But the novelty of novelty has started to wear thin. So Mephistopheles, the consummate puppeteer, pulls another trick out of the flames. He offers Faust the pleasures of Helen of Troy.</p>
        <p>He knows his customer. ''The might of perfection sends shudders through me,'' Faust sings, in anticipatory awe. And in Peter Mussbach's production at the Metropolitan Opera, we can understand how he feels. Faust stands alone on the stage, as a backdrop of the nocturnal heavens splits apart, leaving a stage-high segment of Helen's face, an intriguing image of a classically beautiful eye and nose and cheek.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Toward the end of Busoni's opera ''Doktor Faust,'' which is now receiving its premiere performances at the Metropolitan Opera, the famous Wittenberg magus who made a pact with the devil is looking a bit shopworn. Faust has done his share of murders; he has seduced a bride on her wedding day and later abandoned her and their newborn child; he has caroused to his heart's content. But the novelty of novelty has started to wear thin. So Mephistopheles, the consummate puppeteer, pulls another trick out of the flames. He offers Faust the pleasures of Helen of Troy.</p>
        <p>He knows his customer. ''The might of perfection sends shudders through me,'' Faust sings, in anticipatory awe. And in Peter Mussbach's production at the Metropolitan Opera, we can understand how he feels. Faust stands alone on the stage, as a backdrop of the nocturnal heavens splits apart, leaving a stage-high segment of Helen's face, an intriguing image of a classically beautiful eye and nose and cheek.</p>
        <p>''Perfect image of purest beauty,'' Faust ecstatically proclaims. But as he watches, the perfect image fades; he reaches for it in vain. This retreat is not a taunt by Mephistopheles; it seems, instead, that there are limits to the devil's powers. ''Purest beauty'' seems to fall outside his realm. It also lies beyond Faust's. ''Thou unknowable, unattainable,'' Faust cries at the departing vision. He sees in it a ''perfect form,'' an aesthetic ideal, an idea neatly caught by the design of this production.</p>
        <p>Of course this straining for something beyond the limits of the human has always been part of the Faust tale. The story thrived during the 16th and 17th centuries (with Marlowe, puppet shows, and legends) when modern science was beginning its own form of alchemy and the key to all mythologies seemed at hand. And it thrived again during the late 18th and 19th centuries (in Goethe, Gounod, Berlioz, Liszt and Schumann) when the longing for knowledge and experience helped define Romanticism. By the time Ferruccio Busoni took Faust on in this 1924 opera, writing the libretto along with the music, Faust was not just a magician; he was an embodiment of the artist, embarking on a dangerous quest.</p>
        <p>Given contemporary skepticism about aesthetic idealism, the ground has shifted in recent years; it is now unclear what Faust might represent. So it might be worth considering the issues raised by Busoni, who was a bit of a Faustian figure himself. He was one of the last high priests of the Romantic religion of art. His pianistic virtuosity was so imposing, one critic found listening to him a ''terrifying experience.'' Busoni's performing editions of Bach keyboard music are annotated as if they were Scripture; one fugue, he suggested, bears us upward, ''out of the crypt of a mighty cathedral, through the broad nave and onward to the extreme height of the vaulted dome.'' As for opera, Busoni wrote: ''Taking its cue from the old mystery plays, opera should be cast in the form of a ceremony: unconventional, half religious, uplifting but also stimulating and entertaining.''</p>
        <p>''Doktor Faust,'' which Busoni composed over the course of nearly two decades and left incomplete at his death, is his final testament in this now aging religion. What does Faust himself want in this operatic ceremony, aside from the usual varieties of pleasure and power? ''Give me genius,'' he demands of Mephistopheles, ''and give me too its sorrows.'' He wants to be the suffering visionary artist who knows all, sees all and can recreate all. When he lures the Duchess away from her marital bed, he does not promise sensuous bliss; he promises her ''all of Western art.'' And when he sees a consummate example of such art in the face of Helen, and it eludes his grasp, he is forced to confront human limits. ''Mankind is not yet ripe enough for perfection,'' he sings. ''Man should not strive to exceed his own measure.''</p>
        <p>This notion that ideals also create boundaries -- painfully learned by Faust -- was also knit into Busoni's artistic religion. There were aesthetic models, like Helen herself (and like Bach for Busoni), that were neither possible nor desirable to abandon. This theme actually frames the opera, which begins with a spoken prologue -- omitted in this production -- in which a Busonian poet playfully describes his quest for an appropriate operatic subject. How original can he be, given the weight of past achievements? Mozart has already brought Don Giovanni to life and Goethe has already defined Faust. While gazing higher, the poet would have to aim lower.</p>
        <p>I'm not sure how low the aim eventually was (the result is right in the middle), but the opera ends up becoming a tribute to the burdens and benefits of that artistic past. It is constructed using classical forms and techniques: a theme and variations, Lutheran chorales, Bachian counterpoint, rondos and minuets. In a final spoken epilogue, the poet returns, comparing the opera to a work of alchemy whose magic is as yet incomplete until it works on future generations. Then, ''rising on the shoulders of the past,'' the poet suggests, the ''soul of man'' shall reach his heaven.</p>
        <p>This is the artistic lesson Faust ends up learning as he watches Helen fade from view. He begins the opera by wishing for novelty rather than tradition, celebrating the present moment rather than the past or future. He demands genius and expects beauty. Busoni's opera is a solemn rebuke, a declaration that the ideal can only be approached, not reached, and that a tradition provides the foundation for future innovation. This might seem a stodgy, old-fashioned response to the avant-gardist demands of artistic revolution. But it remains as vital as the forces opposing it. These rival temptations still trouble contemporary Faustian souls.</p>
        <p>CONNECTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
