<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arbitrator Given Bids By Oilers, Rangers</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="472989"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">EDMONTON OILERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAVES, ADAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BONDY, FILIP</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Edmonton Oilers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D6143FF932A2575AC0A967958260" item-length="821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arbitrator Given Bids By Oilers, Rangers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FILIP BONDY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BONDY, FILIP</byline>
      <dateline>GLENS FALLS, N.Y., Sept. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The great chess match over seven-goal scorer Adam Graves moved one square ahead today as rival general managers Neil Smith and Glen Sather sent very different compensation bids to an Ottawa arbitrator.</p>
        <p>Sather, of the Oilers, bid for two promising young players. A person familiar with the Oilers' position confirmed tonight that Sather had asked for both Steven Rice, one of the Rangers' top offensive prospects, and Louie DeBrusk, a 225-pound banger who earned 230 penalty minutes last season in the minors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The great chess match over seven-goal scorer Adam Graves moved one square ahead today as rival general managers Neil Smith and Glen Sather sent very different compensation bids to an Ottawa arbitrator.</p>
        <p>Sather, of the Oilers, bid for two promising young players. A person familiar with the Oilers' position confirmed tonight that Sather had asked for both Steven Rice, one of the Rangers' top offensive prospects, and Louie DeBrusk, a 225-pound banger who earned 230 penalty minutes last season in the minors.</p>
        <p>Smith, the Rangers' general manager, would not divulge his compensation offer for Graves, the free agent who was a forward for Edmonton's last Stanley Cup champions in 1989. But Troy Mallette, a 21-year-old forward, appeared to be the Rangers' only viable candidate.</p>
        <p>One team official familiar with the club's stance pointed out that Mallette had similar statistics as Graves last season (Graves had 7 goals and 18 assists; Mallette, 12 goals and 10 assists), was drafted in the same position as Graves (both were first picks in the second round, one year apart), and played the same sort of rugged style on the wing. Oilers Reportedly Look to Youth</p>
        <p>The only two other equitable one-for-one possibilities, Kris King and Mark Janssens, were reportedly dismissed by Smith. King was one of the team's most improved players last season. Janssens will miss the first two or three weeks of the regular season with a left-shoulder injury, so the Rangers would risk losing the arbitration if he were Smith's selection.</p>
        <p>"I don't even want to know about it," Mallette said today when asked if he would demand to find out his status from Smith. "Why would I, if I don't end up going? What's three more days?"</p>
        <p>Sather said today that even his own bid would not be enough compensation for Graves. "What I really want for Adam Graves is Adam Graves," Sather said today.</p>
        <p>Smith and Sather are scheduled to appear Wednesday to argue their cases in Ottawa before the arbitrator, Edward Houston, who will then choose between the two bids Thursday if no deal is struck.</p>
        <p>"I can't see any way for us working it out before arbitration," said Smith, who planned to speak with Sather late tonight anyway. "I'm very confident our proposal is the one with proper equalization."</p>
        <p>"I'm sure it will come down to an argument about intangibles," Smith said. "But the question should be: 'What has Edmonton lost. How does New York make them whole again?' "</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Smith was choosing his words carefully. He would not even comment on Graves's play at camp for fear that Sather could use his printed words in arguments before Houston.</p>
        <p>Graves scored a breakaway goal Monday during a scrimmage at the Glens Falls Civic Center and has shown his usual zeal for backchecking. The son of a Toronto policeman, he is a polite 23-year-old who plays mean, two-way hockey. Graves is known around the league as "a character player," a former member of a world junior league championship team who will raise the game of others around him.</p>
        <p>In the arbitration hearing Wednesday, Sather is likely to argue that Graves was in line for the team captaincy at Edmonton, that he was a team leader, that he came on strong at the end of last season and that he was valuable enough to command a five-year, $2.2 million contract from the Rangers. Smith, who has had his arguments prepared since last Friday, probably will counter with Graves's disappointing overall statistics last year and with the notion that Sather offered him only $180,000 to re-sign.</p>
        <p>The situation in the Rangers' training camp has been a bit awkward for Graves, whose bags are now sitting in the Rye, N.Y., home of King, a former minor league teammate and friend. Players like Mallette and some of the other young Rangers could become part of the Graves compensation or a bigger deal involving Mark Messier.</p>
        <p>"They've been great, really supportive," said Graves, who has been in only one training-camp scrap, with the pugnacious Tie Domi. SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>The three leading goal-scorers in the Rangers' training-camp tournament are all new faces, of sorts: TONY AMONTE, the Boston University star who debuted during last year's playoffs, has seven goals; the agile SERGEI NEMCHINOV, formerly of the Soviet Wings, and the veteran TIM KERR both have six goals. . . . For TROY MALLETTE, this uncertain training-camp experience has reinforced an earlier decision. "No matter where I am, I'm going to get involved with the Players Association," he said. "The rules involve your future."  Word Due on Fitzpatrick</p>
        <p>MARK FITZPATRICK, the Islanders' goalie, visited a specialist yesterday for further treatment of eosinophilia myalgia syndrome, a blood disorder that forced him to miss most of last season.</p>
        <p>"The Islanders have told me not to say anything," Fitzpatrick said Tuesday night. "They will make an announcement on Wednesday. Maybe then I can say more."  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
