<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Orioles Refuse to Panic Over Midseason Series</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="860717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK YANKEES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BALTIMORE ORIOLES BALTIMORE ORIOLES</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORKYANKEES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, CLAIRE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIPKEN, CAL JR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALOMAR, ROBERTO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E4D81239F93BA15755C0A960958260" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Orioles Refuse to Panic Over Midseason Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, CLAIRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Baltimore Orioles are either blessed or cursed with great patience and a  belief in the sanctity of a 162-game season.</p>
        <p>That is why two of their most seasoned players -- Cal Ripken Jr. and Roberto  Alomar -- came to town last night and refused to put a lot of emphasis on the four-game showdown with the first-place Yankees.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Baltimore Orioles are either blessed or cursed with great patience and a  belief in the sanctity of a 162-game season.</p>
        <p>That is why two of their most seasoned players -- Cal Ripken Jr. and Roberto  Alomar -- came to town last night and refused to put a lot of emphasis on the four-game showdown with the first-place Yankees.</p>
        <p>Even though the Yankees held a four-and-one-half-game lead in the American League East. Even though the Yankees, with a timely sweep, could come close to a double-figure lead. Still, Ripken cautioned those prone to alarm: "I'm someone who thinks that it's too early in the schedule. We have a lot of baseball left.  We're not halfway there yet.</p>
        <p>"If you really sit down and think about it, if you end up losing four games against the Yankees and four games in the standings, what if we go on and win four games after that and they go on and lose four games? Then we're right back  where we started."</p>
        <p>Alomar, the Orioles' second baseman who has been in more pennant races than most any current Yankee, agreed. "We just have to try to stay consistent, worry  about us, not about the Yankees. It's still early."</p>
        <p>Yet the Orioles were in the Yankees' house, where Yogi Berra once astutely observed "it gets late early around here." The Orioles may well begin to agree.  For they now trail the Yankees by five and one-half games games, thanks to a 3-2 loss to Kenny Rogers last night.</p>
        <p>Afterward, the Orioles' tone was understandably less laconic, reflecting not  a desperation but the acknowledgment that a winnable game had slipped away.</p>
        <p>"We didn't get any clutch hits till late," said Manager Davey Johnson, who watched his team score its second and final run in the eighth, then strand the tying run on second and winning run on first in the ninth when Mike Devereaux (three hits) ended the game by striking out against John Wetteland.</p>
        <p>"We had opportunities," Johnson said. "The good ones exploit it. We didn't."</p>
        <p>That has been the story of the Orioles' season -- too inconsistent to beat the Yankees, a smooth-running machine by comparison. Last night they stranded nine runners, five in the final three innings.</p>
        <p>"A lot of things have gone right for the Yankees and they have played well,"  said Johnson, whose team is now only five games over .500. "But we have not played as well as we're capable of playing. There's no question in my mind. But  there's a long way to go and I don't worry about other ball clubs. I worry about my club. And my club just needs to get squared away."</p>
        <p>Still, losing can take a toll. It did last night. "It's tough for us right now," Devereaux said after the Orioles' third consecutive loss. "We were just one hit away from winning the ball game. And unfortunately, we need to win these games against New York and division leaders."</p>
        <p>They have not beaten the Yankees this season (0-3) and finished the season 3-10 against the A.L. West-leading Texas Rangers. The Rangers, in fact, had handed Baltimore its first two defeats in the Orioles' current losing streak.</p>
        <p>Devereaux doesn't believe the team can afford to let that losing continue in  New York, no matter what the month or the schedule.</p>
        <p>"You always take it one game at a time, but it's obvious we know the standings and it's key to win the series.</p>
        <p>To do that, the Orioles will probably have to be in a more comfortable mode.  Ripken and Alomar don't see that yet because Baltimore -- a collection of high-priced veterans, many of them free agent newcomers -- has yet to gel. Given that, given the Yankees' cohesiveness, Ripken did acknowledge this much: "We feel thankful it's a very long season."</p>
        <p>"We need to pick it up a notch," Johnson said after the long season got one game shorter. "There is a long way to go. But we do need to beat the Yankees. We need to beat the other teams above .500 and we haven't."</p>
        <p>Tonight, the Orioles get another chance. Should they lose, they would fall six and one-half games behind. If that happened, even the most laconic of Orioles would wonder if they could catch a Yankee team that appears ready to run away with the East.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
