<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Stuntman Is Ready For a Leap to Stardom</title>
    <meta content="23ANGE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1041247"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Popular Entertainers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Chuck Zito</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zito, Chuck</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4DE1F3DF930A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="817" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Stuntman Is Ready For a Leap to Stardom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>NEW ROCHELLE, N.Y.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Chuck Zito, a longtime Hell's Angel, bodyguard and movie stuntman, hopes to make leap to movie actor at age 45; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In his 45 years, Chuck Zito has been many things: outlaw biker, convict, bodyguard to the stars and stuntman.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Zito, president of the New York Nomads chapter of the Hell's Angels motorcycle club, is trying to engineer a leap from macho man to movie star.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In his 45 years, Chuck Zito has been many things: outlaw biker, convict, bodyguard to the stars and stuntman.</p>
        <p>Now Mr. Zito, president of the New York Nomads chapter of the Hell's Angels motorcycle club, is trying to engineer a leap from macho man to movie star.</p>
        <p>''As a bodyguard, I met the celebrities and progressed from there into stunt work,'' he said. ''Now I'm ready to progress into bigger and better parts. I'm just waiting for that leading role, to become the next Rocky or Rambo.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Zito had his first taste of the movies in 1979, when he appeared onscreen with his custom-painted Harley-Davidson. The following year, he used his Hollywood connections to start a bodyguard service that attracted celebrity clients like Sylvester Stallone, Mickey Rourke and Sean Penn.</p>
        <p>Since then he has worked on more than 50 films, mostly as a stuntman. But last winter, Mr. Zito won his best role yet, a part in ''Oz,'' a prison drama series on HBO in which he plays Chuckie Pancamo, the enforcer for a group of Italian inmates.</p>
        <p>His desire to act, he said, arose in part from the frustration of watching movie stars do imitations of the man he is in daily life.</p>
        <p>''I watch a lot of these actors and say to myself, 'I could do it better.' '' he said. ''They're trying to look like what I really am, but they're not living it day to day.''</p>
        <p>From 1985 to 1991, Mr. Zito was in prison serving a sentence for drug conspiracy, an experience that informs his work on ''Oz.''</p>
        <p>''He brings so much authority and credibility to the role,'' said Tom Fontana, the show's executive producer. ''But I really think that comes from his whole life, as opposed to just his time in prison.''</p>
        <p>Thanks to people like Mr. Fontana, Mr. Zito's life, which once revolved around parole boards, motorcycles and trips to the gym, has broadened to include screen tests and casting calls. He is also trying to sell a movie treatment he has written, titled ''The American Way,'' which documents his progress from the Hell's Angels to Hollywood.</p>
        <p>It was Hollywood, of all things, that first drew him to the motorcycle club.</p>
        <p>''I used to watch their movies like 'Hell's Angels On Wheels' and 'Hell's Angels '69' as a kid,'' he said. ''They were the elite of the elite, the No. 1. They were the ones who actually inspired me to ride a bike.''</p>
        <p>In his early 20's, Mr. Zito bought a 1969 Harley-Davidson Sportster, which he rode to boxing practice at the former Gramercy Gym on East 14th Street. It was there, he said, that he met Sandy Alexander, a professional boxer, who was president of the Hell's Angels' New York City chapter.</p>
        <p>''I introduced myself and told him I'd built and hand-painted my own bike,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Soon enough, I was painting all the Angels' bikes,'' he said. ''And after doing the 'hang-around' process for a while, they took a vote, and I was in.''</p>
        <p>Unlike the city chapter, which has a clubhouse in the East Village, Mr. Zito's Nomads group roams the open highway from Syracuse to the northern border of the five boroughs. While he refused to disclose the number of members in the group (''That's for the cops to figure out,'' he says), he said he has led the chapter almost from the day he helped found it in 1984.</p>
        <p>Though he became a Hell's Angel nearly 20 years ago, boxed as an amateur for several years and caused a stir in February by knocking out Jean-Claude Van Damme, the martial artist turned movie star, in a fracas in the East Side strip club Scores, Mr. Zito has a remarkably strong domestic side. Although he is divorced, he said he frequently sees his former wife, Kathy, and his daughter, Lisa, a Manhattan entertainment lawyer.</p>
        <p>''I say to myself, with the people I know, the people I've bodyguarded for, I should be retired today,'' he said. ''Done. Rich. Over with. But I've never taken anything from anybody. So I just plug along.''</p>
        <p>Over a lunch of tuna salad and potato chips, he spoke about turning 50 in five years.</p>
        <p>''I started late in the acting business,'' he said. ''The Leonardo DiCaprios and Brad Pitts, they're young guys. That's why I always say I've got to make it now, because I'm not getting any younger.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
