<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Florida 'Scarlet Letter' Law Is Repealed by Gov. Bush</title>
    <meta content="31FLOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1493093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Florida</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Canedy, Dana</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, Jeb (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privacy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Adoptions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030531T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DE1430F932A05756C0A9659C8B63" item-length="882" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Florida 'Scarlet Letter' Law Is Repealed by Gov. Bush</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DANA CANEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Canedy, Dana</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, May 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Florida Gov Jeb Bush signs law repealing state's 'Scarlet Letter' law requiring women planning to put infants up for adoption to first publish their sexual histories if they do not know father's identity; law, passed in 2001, was intended to notify fathers who might want to exercise paternal rights before adoption; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. Jeb Bush signed a bill today repealing the state's ''Scarlet Letter'' law that required single women planning to put their infants up for adoption to first publish their sexual histories in a newspaper if they did not know the identity of the father.</p>
        <p>A 2001 bill including a series of adoption-law revisions passed by large margins in the Florida House and Senate and became law when Mr. Bush declined to veto it, with the understanding that lawmakers would revise the publication section.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. Jeb Bush signed a bill today repealing the state's ''Scarlet Letter'' law that required single women planning to put their infants up for adoption to first publish their sexual histories in a newspaper if they did not know the identity of the father.</p>
        <p>A 2001 bill including a series of adoption-law revisions passed by large margins in the Florida House and Senate and became law when Mr. Bush declined to veto it, with the understanding that lawmakers would revise the publication section.</p>
        <p>That provision was intended to notify fathers who might want to exercise their parental rights before an adoption occurred to reduce the likelihood of a custody challenge later.</p>
        <p>In place of the publication requirement, the new law establishes a ''father registry'' through which men who believe they may be fathers must provide the name, address and physical description of the mother and the date and place where conception took place to protect their parental rights.</p>
        <p>After state courts had ruled that the Scarlet Letter law was unconstitutional, even the lawmakers who supported it originally said they favored its repeal. Indeed, the new bill passed both houses unanimously before Mr. Bush signed it today.</p>
        <p>Senator Walter G. Campbell Jr., a sponsor of the original legislation, said the law had produced unintended consequences for unwed mothers that needed to be addressed.</p>
        <p>''I think it had to be done; we did it and now it's fixed,'' Senator Campbell, a Democrat, said.</p>
        <p>Governor Bush's office had urged the Legislature to repeal the publication provision. ''This was an important bill to sign and it has been two years in coming,'' Jill Bratina, a spokeswoman for Governor Bush said of the repeal bill. ''It not only streamlines the adoption process by outlining specific steps for the unwed biological father but it also balances and protects the privacy rights of the mother and child.''</p>
        <p>The repeal received limited praise from the law's opponents, because the action came only after the law had been successfully challenged in court.</p>
        <p>''Only a male-dominated legislature could possibly pass a law that facilitates adoptions by requiring public humiliation of women,'' Howard Simon, executive director of the American Civil Liberties Union of Florida, said.</p>
        <p>''You've got to have a real narrow vision to congratulate the governor for signing a repeal of a statute that, as a result of a lawsuit we were involved in, the courts struck down as unconstitutional,'' he said. ''The legislature shouldn't have passed it in the first place.''</p>
        <p>A judge in Palm Beach County Circuit Court ruled last year that requiring rape victims to publicize their names and sexual histories was an unconstitutional violation of privacy. And last month, a state appeals court ruled that it was also unconstitutional for the state to require women and under-age girls to disclose their sexual histories even in cases of consensual sex.</p>
        <p>The Scarlet Letter law required women to run advertisements disclosing their names, ages, height, hair and eye color, race and weight as well as the child's name and birthplace and a description of the possible father.</p>
        <p>It also required the women to provide details of the dates and places of sexual encounters that might have produced the child. Women were required to run the advertisements once a week for a month in the community where the child may have been conceived.</p>
        <p>The publication requirement, which took effect in October 2001, was criticized by women's groups in Florida and nationally as draconian and humiliating.</p>
        <p>''I had a woman come to me who had a child 10 years ago while in college and now her husband of five years wants to adopt her child and in order to do that she had to put her name, her daughter's name and all the men she slept with in college in her college newspaper,'' said Charlotte Danciu, a Boca Raton lawyer who represented four women and two minors in a suit against the law.</p>
        <p>Though officials could not say precisely how many women placed such ads, women's advocates and lawmakers estimated that a couple of hundred had.</p>
        <p>One woman represented by Ms. Danciu called the repeal long overdue. The South Florida woman, who was raped and gave birth to a baby girl in June, said she decided to challenge the law to protect her privacy.</p>
        <p>The woman, who would not give her name, is a single mother of two other children who is in her 30's. She said she was relieved to know that other women would not be subjected to public humiliation when considering adoption.</p>
        <p>''They don't have to put their names in the paper in this barbaric gesture,'' the woman said. ''They don't have to be afraid anymore.''</p>
        <p>In the confidential father registry, men must file before the mother begins adoption proceedings. The registry, which will be kept by the state Department of Health's Office of Vital Statistics, is similar to paternity databases in about 30 other states, lawmakers said.</p>
        <p>When the original bill was approved, many lawmakers who passed it said they did not read it thoroughly and were unaware that it contained the publication provision.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
