<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Surrounded by Stuff? Call a Clutter Buddy!</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="523310"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME FURNISHINGS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DULLEA, GEORGIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920423T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4D91539F930A15757C0A964958260" item-length="1060" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Surrounded by Stuff? Call a Clutter Buddy!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGIA DULLEA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DULLEA, GEORGIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AFTER a three-hour workshop on "Letting Go of Clutter," Marilyn Vondra, an opera singer, returned to her Manhattan apartment vowing to "de-clutter." She telephoned her clutter-support person a week later to say that, for the first time in some years, she had glimpsed the top of the coffee table. "It's glass," she said.</p>
        <p>The bookcase, buried under sheet music and concert programs, came into view the next week. Again, she phoned her clutter buddy to report progress. This week finds Ms. Vondra under the dining room table, winnowing through hundreds of yellowing newspaper clippings -- recipes, mostly -- stashed in shopping bags.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AFTER a three-hour workshop on "Letting Go of Clutter," Marilyn Vondra, an opera singer, returned to her Manhattan apartment vowing to "de-clutter." She telephoned her clutter-support person a week later to say that, for the first time in some years, she had glimpsed the top of the coffee table. "It's glass," she said.</p>
        <p>The bookcase, buried under sheet music and concert programs, came into view the next week. Again, she phoned her clutter buddy to report progress. This week finds Ms. Vondra under the dining room table, winnowing through hundreds of yellowing newspaper clippings -- recipes, mostly -- stashed in shopping bags.</p>
        <p>"Today, I have hope," she declared. "Tomorrow, dinner parties."</p>
        <p>Clutter-control classes are piling up faster than junk mail on the hall table. Experts in stress and time management have branched out to become clutter consultants. Clutter hot lines are humming.</p>
        <p>Who's calling? People who keep prom dresses from the 50's, empty mayonnaise jars, instruction manuals for appliances they no longer have, single socks and gloves waiting for mates that never turn up, broken buttons, out-of-town and out-of-date phone books, keys to houses they lived in 20 years ago, fuzzy photographs of people they cannot identify but may be related to in some way.</p>
        <p>At the Learning Annex, a chain of adult-education schools around the country, the most popular course last year dealt with clutter management. The schools claim to have more than 200,000 "clutter graduates."</p>
        <p>In bookstores, shelves are sagging with works on how to keep from drowning in a sea of possessions. Even so, "The Learning Annex Guide to Eliminating Clutter From Your Life" by Susan Wright (Carol Publishing; $7.95) will be weighing in on May 1.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wright thinks the anti-clutter movement may be a backlash to the collecting craze of the 80's. "Hopefully, we're moving away from that," she said, adding that her husband delights in collecting furniture from the street. "The word he uses is 'rescuing.' "</p>
        <p>Writing the book has given her insight into the psychology of clutter, as well as techniques for dealing with it. "Now," she said, "I just tell him, 'Brian, you're doing it again. You've got too much stuff. Too much stuff. I mean it, Brian.' "</p>
        <p>Another book coming out next month is "Clutter Control: Putting Your Home on a Diet" by Jeff Campbell (Dell Publishing; $6.99). Mr. Campbell, who founded a San Francisco housecleaning service called the Clean Team, believes in tackling clutter with logic. When you realize the cost of storing the stuff, he theorizes, you will get rid of it.</p>
        <p>Say you have a 1,500-square-foot house and a monthly rent or mortgage payment of $1,500 a month. That's $1 a square foot. Your guest room (say it's 100 square feet) has evolved into a junk room. "You're paying $100 a month for storing items you don't even look at," Mr. Campbell said. "And where would you put a guest?"</p>
        <p>Yet, as experts will tell you, attachments to objects are emotional, never logical. "With some people it's about not letting go of the past," said Charlene Richter, president of Getting Organized in San Francisco. "With other people it's about resentment or anger at parents."</p>
        <p>Ms. Richter gives clutter courses and also makes house calls. So does Daralee Schulman, who presided over the "Letting Go of Clutter" workshop that Marilyn Vondra and 29 others attended at the Y.W.C.A. of the City of New York on Lexington Avenue in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>"How many of you are ready to let go of clutter?" Ms. Schulman began, glancing at the students seated in a circle, notebooks on laps.</p>
        <p>Nervous laughter.</p>
        <p>Ms. Schulman, a recovering clutterer, said that when she became a clutter consultant five years ago, she assumed she would be working mostly with people living in studio apartments, as she does. It hasn't turned out that way.</p>
        <p>A show of hands indicated that the majority of the class had larger apartments and that a few students had houses. And, while the question was not broached, one woman confided, "I rent storage."</p>
        <p>For chronic clutterers, Ms. Schulman said, "there is no here and now." Some live in the future ("I may need this someday") and some in the past ("This reminds me of someone or someplace I love"). Those whose parents grew up in the Depression cling to possessions because they might be worth money. Other clutterers are psychologically depressed. "Unlike neatniks, who clean when they're depressed, clutterers bomb out on the couch," Ms. Schulman said.</p>
        <p>Most clutterers are not stay-at-homes. "They're busy and interesting people," she said. "They'd rather go to restaurants, movies and workshops at the Y than stay home and deal with all that stuff."</p>
        <p>A woman by the window raised her hand and said: "I heard Picasso was a clutterer. Every seven years he had to move to a new studio because the old one was so cluttered."</p>
        <p>Ms. Schulman nodded. Clutterers can be creative.</p>
        <p>Leading the students through a series of written exercises and visualizations, with breaks for deep breathing, Ms. Schulman instructed them in the early phases of de-cluttering:</p>
        <p>Start with one small area -- "Say, the left side of the coffee table." Work for a minimum of 15 minutes a day and a maximum of two hours. Once an area is de-cluttered, maintain purity while moving on to the next area. Record progress on a calendar and check in with a clutter buddy. Reward yourself with flowers.</p>
        <p>"I suggest flowers because in three days they die and you have to get rid of them, " Ms. Schulman said.</p>
        <p>One of the students pointed out that you could dry the flowers. Ms. Schulman gave her a withering look.</p>
        <p>Since the students would be breaking strong behavorial patterns during the de-cluttering process, Ms. Schulman said, feelings of anxiety and occasional setbacks were to be expected. She warned that the final cleansing moment would not come in a matter of weeks or months. "For many people, the process of letting go of clutter takes about three years."</p>
        <p>Then the students closed their eyes for one last visualization. It was April 1995. They were walking through their own clutter-free homes. Opening closets and medicine cabinets, peeking under beds. They were smiling.</p>
        <p>Ms. Schulman then announced that a photographer from House Beautiful magazine was arriving any minute. Three students opened three eyes. "I'm hyperventilating," said one.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
