<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critics Say 'Star Wars' Test May Be a Treaty Violation</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="352685"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SPACE WEAPONS (STAR WARS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREATIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTI-BALLISTIC MISSILE TREATY OF 1972</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TESTS AND TESTING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADAR</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROAD, WILLIAM J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Treaties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radar</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DC1130F931A25756C0A966958260" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critics Say 'Star Wars' Test May Be a Treaty Violation</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM J. BROAD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROAD, WILLIAM J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Pentagon yesterday began a ''Star Wars'' test that critics say comes the closest to violating the 1972 Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty out of all the experiments conducted so far in the seven-year $20 billion program of research on the anti-missile system.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Pentagon yesterday began a ''Star Wars'' test that critics say comes the closest to violating the 1972 Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty out of all the experiments conducted so far in the seven-year $20 billion program of research on the anti-missile system.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon yesterday began a ''Star Wars'' test that critics say comes the closest to violating the 1972 Anti-Ballistic Missile Treaty out of all the experiments conducted so far in the seven-year $20 billion program of research on the anti-missile system.</p>
        <p>The test involves the first flight of a Boeing 767 aircraft equipped with a giant sensor meant to track warheads in space as part of the ''Star Wars'' plan to intercept missiles launched by an enemy. The plane took off from Boeing Field in Seattle, Wash., yesterday at 11:10 A.M. Pacific daylight time for a six-hour test flight.</p>
        <p>So far, more than $600 million has been spent on the airborne sensor program, which is behind schedule and over budget. The overall ''Star Wars'' budget is $3.8 billion, down slightly from last year.</p>
        <p>Pentagon Denies Violation</p>
        <p>A key issue is whether the plane could do the work of an anti-missile radar. Article 5 of the A.B.M. treaty bans mobile radars and has strict rules for nonmobile radars on the ground.</p>
        <p>Pentagon experts deny the sensor violates the treaty, saying it is highly experimental and not a prototype anti-missile sensor system.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon also says that unlike a radar, the sensor cannot rapidly scan a broad area of the sky to find fast-moving targets; It has to be told where to look. In addition, the Pentagon says the sensor, while powerful, is not so strong that it has a clear anti-missile role.</p>
        <p>The Pentagon calls the sensor plane a radar ''adjunct,'' which would be an aid to the radar but not replace it and would thus be permitted under the treaty. The Pentagon emphasized the point by putting the word in the name of the plane, the Airborne Optical Adjunct aircraft.</p>
        <p>''The aircraft has gone through a treaty review and does not violate it in any way,'' said William J. Congo, a spokesman for the Army Strategic Defense Command in Washington, which runs the program.</p>
        <p>But critics disagree, saying the plane's sensor capabilities make the program suspect.</p>
        <p>''It's moving in a direction that many, many would say is a violation if it's successful,'' said Spurgeon M. Keeny Jr., president of the Washington-based Arms Control Association, a private group. Mr. Keeny is a former Federal official who participated in the A.B.M. treaty negotiations.</p>
        <p>John E. Pike, head of space policy for the Federation of American Scientists, a private group based in Washington, agreed. ''It's the first test that raises serious questions about treaty compliance,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The plane has an 86-foot-long cupola welded to its top to house the giant sensor assembly. A seven-foot door in the cupola moves back to allow the sensor to view objects outside the plane. While Boeing is the project's main contractor, the 5.5-ton sensor was built by the Hughes Aircraft Company. Packed with 38,000 super-cooled detectors, it is to pinpoint faint infrared rays emitted by relatively warm objects like warheads and missiles in the cold vacuum of space.</p>
        <p>Advanced Tests Are Planned</p>
        <p>The first flights are to observe stars and satellites, according to the Strategic Defense Command. Late this year and early next year, flights are planned that would observe mock warheads launched from Vandenberg Air Force Base in California to the Kwajalein Atoll in the South Pacific.</p>
        <p>A key question that the Pentagon hopes to answer is whether the plane's sensor can sort out warheads from decoys and bits of debris scattered by an attacker in an effort to fool any anti-missile system.</p>
        <p>In war, such a sensor system would fly around the edge of the continental United States, helping track enemy warheads so interceptors could try to knock them out. Its advantages over ground-based systems are seen as greater flexibility and better protection from enemy attack.</p>
        <p>Most important, the airplane's high altitude places it above the atmosphere's clouds and water vapor, allowing the use of infrared sensors. These do not send out any active signals, unlike radar, and their operation is therefore impossible for an enemy to detect.</p>
        <p>In 1988, the Pentagon wrote Representative Les Aspin, chairman of the House Armed Services Committee, saying the plane ''cannot perform the basic radar functions.''</p>
        <p>Critics reject such explanations as disingenuous, saying the American Government has often questioned similar activity by the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>''Unless you went inside the plane and disassembled its parts, you'd have no way of knowing if the Pentagon is telling the truth,'' said Mr. Pike of the Federation of American Scientists.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
