<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOUSE TO GIVE UP RECORDS ON CHECKS TO A PROSECUTOR</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="524837"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCLOSURE OF INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHECKS AND CHECKING ACCOUNTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONGRESS (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FOLEY, THOMAS S (SPEAKER)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDB163DF933A05757C0A964958260" item-length="1350" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOUSE TO GIVE UP RECORDS ON CHECKS TO A PROSECUTOR</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD KRAUSS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KRAUSS, CLIFFORD</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a resounding defeat for the Democratic leadership, the House tonight voted to comply with a Justice Department subpoena for House bank records.</p>
        <p>The Democratic leaders who control the chamber had tried to construct a strategy that would have resisted what they called a politically inspired investigation without appearing to cover up a scandal that has enraged many voters. But in two separate votes tonight, they failed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a resounding defeat for the Democratic leadership, the House tonight voted to comply with a Justice Department subpoena for House bank records.</p>
        <p>The Democratic leaders who control the chamber had tried to construct a strategy that would have resisted what they called a politically inspired investigation without appearing to cover up a scandal that has enraged many voters. But in two separate votes tonight, they failed.</p>
        <p>In the first vote, a Democratic proposal to challenge the subpoena in Federal Court was defeated 284 to 131. A total of 123 Democrats broke ranks, many abandoning their pledges to the leadership as roll-call was taken, to join a unanimous Republican vote.</p>
        <p>That was followed by a vote on a resolution favored by Republicans that was intended to do exactly the opposite: give the Justice Department records of every check written on the now closed House bank from July 1988 to October 1991. The resolution was overwhelmingly approved by a vote of 347 to 64, with all the opposing votes cast by Democrats. 'A Solemn Moment'</p>
        <p>Democratic members said the defeat was particularly damaging for Speaker Thomas S. Foley, who has consistently appeared to be slow in responding to the scandal since late last year when the first public disclosures were made about scores of members systematically overdrawing their accounts.</p>
        <p>The debate over the two competing resolutions mixed emotional political diatribes with reasoned constitutional arguments about due process, privacy and separation of powers.</p>
        <p>"This is a solemn moment for the House and its solemn rights and privileges," Mr. Foley said before the votes.</p>
        <p>He added that lawmakers had "no lesser right than any other citizen" in appealing to a judge to decide what evidence was relevant and what was not in a criminal investigation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Foley and other Democrats contended that lawmakers who did not overdraw their accounts or otherwise abuse banking privileges should not be forced to turn over their records. Lawsuit Is Filed</p>
        <p>Speaking with uncharacteristic abandon, Representative David R. Nagle, Democrat of Iowa, said "public opinion be damned" if it conflicted with the constitutional rights of members to defend themselves against unreasonable search and seizure.</p>
        <p>But most members agreed with Representative James V. Hansen, a Utah Republican who is the ranking minority member of the ethics committee. "We don't want a cover-up," he said. "We want to get this behind us. We're a different breed of cat when we take this oath of office."</p>
        <p>Few Democrats wanted to open themselves to the scrutiny of the Bush Administration in an election year, but the demands of constituents for full disclosure of the bank scandal forced many to swallow institutional pride.</p>
        <p>The fear of political isolation was reinforced by the reversal on Tuesday of Representative Robert H. Michel of Illinois, the Republican minority leader, who had previously backed the Democratic position of resisting a sweeping subpoena that includes the records of members who never overdrew their accounts. Mr. Michel became the sponsor of the second resolution, which demanded full compliance.</p>
        <p>Representative Fred Grandy, an Iowa Republican who is also a member of the ethics committee, said: "It's not a question of fairness anymore. This is some nightmare out Franz Kakfa, but that's what we have to deal with."</p>
        <p>At a midday Democratic caucus, several Democrats told Mr. Foley that he needed to resist the subpoena as a matter of constitutional principle, even if he lost. They argued that if the House succumbed, it would create a precedent by which the Justice Department might one day subpoena documents to stymie Congressional investigations into the executive branch.</p>
        <p>"There was broad agreement with the Speaker on the merits," said Representative Matthew F. McHugh, a New York Democrat who is acting chairman of the ethics committee. "But the question was, where are the votes?"</p>
        <p>In the end, the Democrats chose a creative parliamentary maneuver by which they could make a symbolic stand for separation of powers and their privacy on the one hand before facing a second, superseding vote that they feared they might lose. The Democrats did not oppose introducing the second resolution because they realized that the Republicans would overwhelm them if they tried.  Fear of Public Perception</p>
        <p>Through much of the day, Democratic leaders lobbied members for a resolution committing the House to ask a Federal district judge to decide which bank records were relevant to the criminal investigation by the special counsel, Malcolm R. Wilkey, into the financial practices of members. By early evening, they found that most of their members were willing to go along with the court test, but they feared a major embarrassment if as many as 50 of the 286 House Democrats defected.</p>
        <p>As it was, dozens more voted against the challenge, reflecting fear that it would drag out the scandal and be perceived as an attempt to conceal it.</p>
        <p>Although no Republicans voted to challenge the subpoena, Democrats said several Republicans had privately told them that they opposed capitulation.</p>
        <p>Democrats said Mr. Foley risked major political damage whether he backed compliance with the subpoena or decided to resist and ended up losing on the floor. As the majority party, the Democrats expect to control the administration of the House, but they have already been forced by Republican pressure to release banking data and the names of members who repeatedly overdrew their accounts.</p>
        <p>The subpoena served last week by Mr. Wilkey, a retired Federal judge, called on the House to deliver 39 months of microfilm records of all House bank accounts originally gathered by the General Accounting Office, an auditing and investigative arm of Congress, and reviewed by the ethics committee. Mr. Wilkey declared there might be evidence of "a classic check-kiting scheme," although he did not say what the evidence was.</p>
        <p>The deadline of the subpoena is Thursday, and it would include checks written by members who had no overdrafts. In a lawsuit filed tonight, two Democratic Representatives, Henry B. Gonzalez of Texas and Sidney R. Yates of Illinois, asked a Federal District Court to invalidate the subpoena, arguing that it violated the House's powers as an independent branch of Government.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gonzalez did not write any overdrafts; Mr. Yates had four. 'Just Gone Too Far'</p>
        <p>Several other Democrats reacted angrily to the subpoena today, saying they were tired of being pushed around by the Republicans. They said canceled checks could disclose embarrassing personal information like payments for a child's drug rehabilitation or for marital counseling.</p>
        <p>"In the wrong hands, such information may become mischievous," said Representative Robert G. Torricelli, Democrat of New Jersey. "This has just gone too far."</p>
        <p>Representative Charlie Rose, Democrat of North Carolina, called the subpoena "an unconscionable invasion of one separate branch of Government on another." He added, "I think the Administration wants to keep the American people focused on Congress as a problem."</p>
        <p>Several Democrats expressed fear that by moving to resist the subpoena they could fall into a trap laid by Republicans who were waving the banner of reform by advocating disclosure of all bank documents to the Justice Department.</p>
        <p>"I am concerned about any of these votes being used politically when you have the Newt Gingriches of this world," said Representative Nita M. Lowey, Democrat of Westchester County. Mr. Gingrich of Georgia, the Republican whip, has led the charge to characterize the scandal as a symbol of Democratic mismanagement of Congress and not as a matter of personal malfeasance. He wrote 22 overdrafts himself.</p>
        <p>Some Democrats said they thought voters were beginning to understand that public funds were not at risk at the bank and that the institution's sloppy paperwork was at fault for many of the overdrafts. They said that realization led to them to believe that it was worth putting up a fight, even a symbolic one.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
