<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOME IMPROVEMENT</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="524817"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D9123BF933A05757C0A964958260" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOME IMPROVEMENT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By John Warde</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WARDE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOST wooden-door problems crop up suddenly in humid spring and summer weather; they should be let alone to see if they go away when drier conditions return. But if a wooden door has squeaked or rattled for months, or has been hard to open or close, there is probably an easy remedy for the complaint.</p>
        <p>To quiet a squeaking door, clean and lubricate the hinge pins. Remove, service and replace them one at a time to keep the door from falling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOST wooden-door problems crop up suddenly in humid spring and summer weather; they should be let alone to see if they go away when drier conditions return. But if a wooden door has squeaked or rattled for months, or has been hard to open or close, there is probably an easy remedy for the complaint.</p>
        <p>To quiet a squeaking door, clean and lubricate the hinge pins. Remove, service and replace them one at a time to keep the door from falling.</p>
        <p>To remove a hinge pin, open the door about four inches and wedge it securely by placing scraps of wood or a doorstop underneath. Hold a nail set (a metal punch used for driving nails) vertically against the bottom of the pin and strike the nail set with a hammer to raise the pin about a quarter of an inch at the top. Then hold the nail set at an angle against the underside of the pin's head and strike it to raise the pin completely.</p>
        <p>Clean pins by rubbing them with steel wool dipped in mineral spirits. Lubricate them with a few drops of lightweight household oil. To reinstall a pin, insert it into the hinge from the top and tap the head with a hammer.</p>
        <p>Rattles can be caused by loose latch hardware. If a doorknob wobbles, look for a set screw on the shaft of one or both knobs. Loosen the screw with a screwdriver if necessary; push the knobs toward each other to tighten them against the door, and tighten the screw firmly.</p>
        <p>If the latch plate is loose, tighten the screws holding it. If drafts cause the door to rattle when it is closed, attach self-sticking foam weatherstripping to the stop molding -- the part of the frame that the door presses against when shut -- on the latch side.</p>
        <p>If a door rubs against a jamb, close the door and inspect it, facing the side with the hinges. If the latch edge of the door touches the adjacent jamb near the top corner, open the door and try tightening the screws in the upper hinge. If the door touches near the bottom corner, try tightening the bottom hinge screws.</p>
        <p>Tightening the screws even a fraction of a turn can make a difference. If the screw slots are clogged, clean them with paint remover and by scraping. To tighten them, use the longest screwdriver you can find with a blade that matches the length and width of the slots.</p>
        <p>If the holes for the hinge screws have become enlarged and the screws cannot be tightened, you may be able to replace the existing screws with new ones of a larger diameter. But if the hinges will not accept larger screws or if the wood surrounding the holes is cracked, you will have to plug and redrill the holes.</p>
        <p>First, remove the door by withdrawing the hinge pins, removing the bottom pin first to keep the door from toppling. Next, remove the screws from the hinges and carefully push each leaf sideways to free it without chipping its mortise, or notch.</p>
        <p>With a quarter-inch bit, drill into the holes about as far as the old screws penetrated. Saw lengths of quarter-inch-diameter dowel (a wooden rod, available at hardware stores) to this length, and glue them in the holes with woodworking glue. Work glue into any cracks around the holes.</p>
        <p>When the glue is dry, slide the hinge leaves into their original positions and drill carefully centered holes into the ends of the dowels to accept screws. Then install the original screws or replacements. The diameter of the drilled holes should equal the average thickness of the screw shaft minus the threads.</p>
        <p>If tightening the hinges doesn't stop the rubbing, try shimming the hinge diagonally opposite the rubbing corner. To do this, cut a piece of cardboard about the thickness of a credit card to the same shape as the hinge leaf fastened to the doorjamb. Wedge the door from beneath to support it; then remove the screws holding the leaf to the jamb, slide the leaf out of its mortise, fit the cardboard shim into the notch and refasten the leaf. Install additional shims if necessary.</p>
        <p>If a door swings open by itself when not latched, make a shim only half as wide as a hinge leaf. Loosen the jamb leaf of the upper hinge and install the shim behind the part of the leaf closest to the hinge pin. Retighten the leaf. If a door swings shut by itself, install a half-size shim behind the jamb leaf of the lower hinge instead.</p>
        <p>If a door rubs along the top or if you can't close it completely without pressing hard against it, look for caked paint along the door edges and stop molding, especially at the corners. Remove the paint by applying paint remover with a brush. When applying remover overhead, stand on a stepladder so it won't drip on you.</p>
        <p>Give the remover time to work according to the manufacturer's directions; then scrape the areas down to the bare wood with a putty knife. Test the door. If it no longer rubs, apply a thin coat of fresh paint over the bare wood to prevent warping.</p>
        <p>If a door will not latch and caked paint is not the problem, check the alignment of the latch and the strike plate. If misalignment up or down is less than an eighth of an inch, remove the plate, clamp it in a vise and file the latch opening to enlarge it.</p>
        <p>If misalignment is more severe, the plate can be repositioned lower or higher on the doorjamb after lengthening its mortise with a sharp chisel. If the door does not close far enough for the latch to enter the opening in the strike plate, you can either move the strike plate horizontally, after filling the original screw holes with doweling, as above, or reposition the stop molding.</p>
        <p>To remove the molding, pry it carefully out with a putty knife and pull the nails out through the back of the molding with pliers. Close the door so it latches; then refasten the molding just far enough from it to allow a credit card to slide between the molding and the door's outside surface.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
