<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gary Condit's Bad Night</title>
    <meta content="25SAT2$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/25/opinion/25SAT2.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1319816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chung, Connie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Chandra Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Condit, Gary A (Rep)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Primetime Thursday (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missing Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">America</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Condit, Gary</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Chung, Connie</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010825T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E3DB1031F936A1575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="675" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gary Condit's Bad Night</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Gary Condit's Bad Night</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on Connie Chung's intervie</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Gary Condit obviously regards himself as one of the unluckiest men in America. The media are hounding him. The police misrepresented him. Chandra Levy's parents misunderstood him, her aunt is making up stories about him, an airline flight attendant is defaming him, and his lawyer is sending unauthorized letters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Condit's interview on ABC on Thursday night added another layer to his victimhood. If anyone had assured him that the public would be sympathetic to his request for a zone of privacy, he has been getting terrible advice.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Representative Gary Condit's interview on ABC on Thursday added another layer to his victimhood</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Representative Gary Condit obviously regards himself as one of the unluckiest men in America. The media are hounding him. The police misrepresented him. Chandra Levy's parents misunderstood him, her aunt is making up stories about him, an airline flight attendant is defaming him, and his lawyer is sending unauthorized letters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Condit's interview on ABC on Thursday night added another layer to his victimhood. If anyone had assured him that the public would be sympathetic to his request for a zone of privacy, he has been getting terrible advice.</p>
        <p>Ever since Richard Nixon's ''Checkers'' speech, elected officials who have found themselves in hot water have taken to the airwaves to explain or apologize. Mr. Condit's appearance was one of the least successful efforts along this line since the invention of television. When it was over, Richard Gephardt, the House Democratic leader, announced that Mr. Condit had made politicians look bad.</p>
        <p>Pale, edgy and evasive, the congressman responded to questions about his relationship with Ms. Levy by declaring, over and over, that he had been ''married for 34 years and I've not been a perfect man.'' He appeared to be taking a leaf from Bill Clinton's book. Mr. Clinton salvaged his first presidential campaign by acknowledging -- indirectly,  without actually admitting it -- that he had had an  affair with Gennifer Flowers. He was skillful at playing on the public's willingness to divide a politician's private and public behavior, until the Monica Lewinsky episode surfaced and people began to wonder if they had compartmentalized too well.</p>
        <p>But this situation involves a tragedy, not a sex scandal. A young woman is missing, very possibly dead. Mr. Condit's goal was obviously to establish that he had done everything he could to help the police and the Levy family, while avoiding any specific description of his relationship with Ms. Levy. But he did a better job of demonstrating how the fear of exposing an adulterous affair might have made him less than forthcoming. The police have said that it took several interviews before the congressman gave them all the information they needed about his relationship with Ms. Levy, and her parents insist that he denied having an affair when they asked him. On ABC, Mr. Condit said that the police and the Levys were both wrong.</p>
        <p>During the half-hour interview, he accused virtually everyone else involved in the case of either being confused or lying. The flight attendant who says she had a long affair with Mr. Condit was making up stories, the congressman said. The woman was asked to sign a statement disavowing any sexual relationship with Mr. Condit, but that, he said, was done by his lawyers without his knowledge. When Connie Chung pointed out that he had called for ''the public airing of every detail'' of the  Lewinsky affair during the impeachment hearings,  Mr. Condit said that statement had been taken out of context.</p>
        <p>Ms. Chung was nothing if not persistent in trying to get Mr. Condit to acknowledge that he had had an affair. But the congressman stuck to a very narrow, legalistic set of answers. ''I think the American people understand that people are entitled to some privacy,'' he said. ''I'm entitled to try to retain as much privacy as I can.'' A large segment of the American public believes that the media are devoting too much attention to the Levy case. But if Mr. Condit thinks that translates into support for his stonewalling, he is going to be disappointed. Americans are sometimes too ready to demand that elected officials speak from the heart, but in this terrible and unique case, Mr. Condit's heart was what people needed to see.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
