<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Game Maker Misses Earnings Target and Cuts 2004 Forecast</title>
    <meta content="09GAME$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/09/technology/09game.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1588056"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Take-Two Interactive Software Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richtel, Matt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roedel, Richard W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Securities and Exchange Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040609T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5D81630F93AA35755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="638" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Game Maker Misses Earnings Target and Cuts 2004 Forecast</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Game Maker Misses Earnings Target and Cuts 2004 Forecast</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MATT RICHTEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Richtel, Matt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Take-Two Interactive Software says earnings were far below its own estimates and those of industry analysts in second fiscal quarter ended April 30; says sales were $153 million, down from $170 million year earlier; posts loss of 33 cents per share, compared wiht projections of loss of 15 cents; cuts 2004 forecast; announces interim chief executive Richard W Roedel has been named permanent chief executive (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Financial disappointments continue to take a toll on Take-Two Interactive Software, the maker of the hit video game Grand Theft Auto. The company announced second-quarter earnings yesterday that were far below its own estimates and those of industry analysts.</p>
        <p>Blaming a variety of factors, including poor catalog sales and weak results in its publishing business, Take-Two also cut its full-year earnings forecast 20 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Financial disappointments continue to take a toll on Take-Two Interactive, maker of the hit video game Grand Theft Auto.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Financial disappointments continue to take a toll on Take-Two Interactive Software, the maker of the hit video game Grand Theft Auto. The company announced second-quarter earnings yesterday that were far below its own estimates and those of industry analysts.</p>
        <p>Blaming a variety of factors, including poor catalog sales and weak results in its publishing business, Take-Two also cut its full-year earnings forecast 20 percent.</p>
        <p>For the second fiscal quarter, which ended April 30, Take-Two reported sales of $153 million, down from the $170 million projection the company made in April. It posted a loss of 33 cents a share, compared with projections of a loss of 15 cents a share.</p>
        <p>The company also announced that Richard W. Roedel, its interim chief executive, had been named permanent chief executive. He is the third chief executive since 2000. Mr. Roedel became interim chief executive on April 14, after Jeffrey A. Lapin resigned.</p>
        <p>Shares of Take-Two closed at $28.65, down $1.62.</p>
        <p>The quarterly results continue the roller coaster ride for Take-Two and its investors. The Securities and Exchange Commission has been investigating the company for possible accounting irregularities for more than two years; Take-Two has had a revolving door of management, including four chief financial officers in three years.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the Grand Theft Auto franchise has been an extraordinary success, accounting for 39 percent of the company's $1 billion sales in 2003, said Stewart A. Halpern, an analyst with RBC Capital Markets. The company has said it plans to release the series' next incarnation, Grand Theft Auto: San Andreas, in October, and industry analysts said it could be one of the best-selling games of all time.</p>
        <p>Heath Terry, an analyst with Credit Suisse First Boston, wrote to investors in a note about Take-Two that ''while it would be the easy thing to do, we are not ready to throw in the towel.''</p>
        <p>''While this is the latest in a painfully long string of management missteps, financial disappointments and product delays,'' he wrote, ''we believe the new management team is putting the right structure in place to prevent reoccurrences of these problems.''</p>
        <p>But Marc Cahodes, a partner with Rocker Partners, which has shorted the stock and will profit if the share price falls, said many Wall Street analysts are guilty of forgiving consistent lack of performance by the company.</p>
        <p>Take-Two said yesterday that for fiscal 2004, it would have sales of $1.13 billion to $1.15 billion and earnings of $1.60 to $1.65 a share. In April, it projected that its full-year sales would be $1.17 billion and that earnings would be $2. The company estimated in December 2003 that it would earn $2.60 a share.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roedel, who joined the company's board in 2002 as an independent director, said in an interview that the company had been ''a bit ambitious with our expectations for ourselves for 2004, and then we had a disappointing year in terms of sales execution.''</p>
        <p>He said that in particular there was ''really weak'' performance in the catalog business, which sells back titles. He said he hoped the company's latest guidance would give investors a reliable outlook.</p>
        <p>''We've put some of these execution issues behind us,'' he said. ''We've reset our expectations to the point where we can deliver.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
