<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Schwab Set To Underwrite Stock Issues</title>
    <meta content="Y09FUND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="956276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Schwab, Charles, &amp; Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Credit Suisse Group</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hambrecht &amp; Quist Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Morgan, J P, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Brokers and Brokerage Firms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E7DF1739F93AA3575AC0A961958260" item-length="953" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Schwab Set To Underwrite Stock Issues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Charles Schwab &amp; Co, country's largest discount brokerage firm, will sign deal with Wall Street firms Credit Suisse Group, Hambrecht &amp; Quist and J P Morgan to help them underwrite public stock offerings, move that thrusts Schwab into part of financial markets that it has avoided; customers of Schwab's retail brokerage service will get opportunity to invest directly in public stock offering led by three brokerage firms (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charles Schwab &amp; Company, the country's largest discount brokerage firm, said yesterday that it had signed a deal with three Wall Street firms to help them underwrite public stock offerings, a move that thrusts Schwab into a part of the financial markets that it had avoided.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, customers of Schwab's retail brokerage service will get an opportunity to invest directly in public stock offerings led by either the Credit Suisse First Boston unit of the Credit Suisse Group, Hambrecht &amp; Quist or J. P. Morgan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Charles Schwab &amp; Company, the country's largest discount brokerage firm, said yesterday that it had signed a deal with three Wall Street firms to help them underwrite public stock offerings, a move that thrusts Schwab into a part of the financial markets that it had avoided.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, customers of Schwab's retail brokerage service will get an opportunity to invest directly in public stock offerings led by either the Credit Suisse First Boston unit of the Credit Suisse Group, Hambrecht &amp; Quist or J. P. Morgan.</p>
        <p>The agreement is a huge departure from Schwab's traditional business of matching customer orders to buy and sell stocks and bonds. As an underwriter, Schwab will be putting its own capital at risk, at least theoretically, and will be taking a direct role in helping corporations raise money.</p>
        <p>Schwab's arrangement is therefore broader -- and riskier -- than a similar deal announced in January by Fidelity Investments and Salomon Brothers, in which Fidelity agreed to act as a distributor of up to 10 percent of all Salomon-managed equity offerings.</p>
        <p>Both deals serve to give retail investors greater access to initial public offerings, in which companies raise money by selling an ownership stake to the general public. Traditionally, those offerings are sold exclusively to institutional investors, which can reap great profits by reselling shares of hot offerings once formal trading of the shares begins on a stock exchange.</p>
        <p>The agreement by Fidelity, which is a unit of the FMR Corporation and the operator of the country's second-largest discount brokerage business, makes it a sales agent in offerings in which Salomon serves as the lead manager. Fidelity will take orders from its retail customers for shares of an offering, earning sales commissions, but it is not required to first buy the shares itself, which would put its own capital at risk.</p>
        <p>In contrast, an underwriter buys, at a discount, and then resells, at the stock's offering price, shares of a company's stock -- a potentially more profitable role for the firm. Underwriting does, however, put a firm's capital at risk, although usually for only a short time, such as overnight. Still, there is always the possibility that a sudden change in market or economic conditions, or a miscalculation of demand for the shares among investors, will leave the underwriter with more shares of a company's stock than it can quickly resell.</p>
        <p>Lon Gorman, president of Charles Schwab Capital Markets and Trading, said in an interview that the deal ''expands the universe of investment opportunities available to our base of customers.''</p>
        <p>Schwab does not intend, he said, to move further toward becoming a full-service brokerage firm, like Merrill Lynch or Smith Barney, which underwrite stock issues, provide brokerage services and offer a broad array of other services, including investment banking advice to corporations.</p>
        <p>''I would say if we had wanted to be a full-service brokerage firm we would have bought an investment banking firm,'' Mr. Gorman said. ''This is consistent with our philosophy of offering a supermarket of investment products.''</p>
        <p>Schwab has tested its new operation in recent weeks, acting as an underwriter of five stock offerings, four of which were managed by one of the three partner firms, according to Mr. Gorman.</p>
        <p>For example, Schwab was part of the group of underwriters, known as a syndicate, led by J. P. Morgan in the public offering of the Hertz Corporation, the rental car company.</p>
        <p>All of the test deals performed fairly well in public trading after the offering, presenting little risk to Schwab. ''As an underwriter, we do assume risk until we redistribute'' shares to the public, Mr. Gorman said. But he characterized the potential for trouble as slight. ''That is why we spent as much time as we did evaluating the track record of the three partners'' in the arrangement, he said.</p>
        <p>For the investment banks, the Schwab deal offers access to a wide group of individual investors, in some cases significantly expanding the number of potential customers for an offering of securities.</p>
        <p>Ernesto Cruz, who oversees equity capital markets in the Americas for Credit Suisse First Boston, said Schwab's distribution capability should be especially helpful in offerings of real estate investment trusts and master limited partnerships, products traditionally aimed at individual investors.</p>
        <p>Schwab's announcement was clearly intended to differentiate its arrangement from that of Fidelity, which responded yesterday by making an early announcement of its plan to provide investors with the daily equity research done by the analysts at Salomon Brothers.</p>
        <p>Beginning in October, Fidelity's retail brokerage customers will get access to the Salomon research material, including investment recommendations, earnings estimates and details from meetings with corporate executives. The material will be distributed by fax or electronic mail each day after 5 P.M., a Fidelity spokeswoman said.</p>
        <p>As for underwriting, the Schwab and Fidelity arrangements differ in several details; for example, Schwab is not guaranteed a percentage of the shares of any of the offerings led by one of its three Wall Street partners. Fidelity, however, is guaranteed access to up to 10 percent of any Salomon equity offering; if demand from its customers is less than that, however, Fidelity is not required to buy the unsold shares.</p>
        <p>The board of Schwab was also active yesterday, authorizing the repurchase of up to 2.5 million more shares of the company's common stock. Schwab has repurchased 500,000 shares so far in 1997 and is now authorized to repurchase 3.37 million shares. Schwab shares will split 3 for 2 after the close of trading next Monday. The shares rose $2.125, to $46.25, yesterday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
