<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Cyberspace, and Talking to Strangers</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="696624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="PARENT &amp; CHILD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRONIC INFORMATION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRINGER, FELICITY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D8153CF933A05755C0A962958260" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Cyberspace, and Talking to Strangers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARRINGER, FELICITY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MY neighbors' children, who were born before mine, were loping around the neighborhood when my oldest son, Michael, was still learning to walk. Thus my husband and I had voices of experience to reassure us when we worried about Michael's falling off a two-inch ledge.</p>
        <p>That was then. This spring, some dozen years later, Michael took his first steps into the brusque, banal but intoxicating world of cyberspace, and I wished for neighbors whose children had been there, who could tell me what was worth worrying about and what wasn't.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MY neighbors' children, who were born before mine, were loping around the neighborhood when my oldest son, Michael, was still learning to walk. Thus my husband and I had voices of experience to reassure us when we worried about Michael's falling off a two-inch ledge.</p>
        <p>That was then. This spring, some dozen years later, Michael took his first steps into the brusque, banal but intoxicating world of cyberspace, and I wished for neighbors whose children had been there, who could tell me what was worth worrying about and what wasn't.</p>
        <p>For instance: Should it be a cause for alarm that the first person Michael met in America Online's "chat room," where people use keyboards and modems to talk with strangers, called herself Angel and said she was a stripper? Or that the next person to join the conversation -- his sign-on was Kurt -- asked Angel her chest measurements?</p>
        <p>Cybernetically speaking, my 13-year-old had wandered into a singles bar -- and had interrupted a pickup.</p>
        <p>I wish someone could have warned me -- or him. But there are precious few people who have been parents in the computer age. In matters electronic, the children rule.</p>
        <p>Michael and his brother, Gregory, have used a Macintosh LC computer for three years, and I have now discovered the electronic equivalent to the seasons of childhood. There was the Mystery Season, when Michael read Sherlock Holmes and chased thieves around the world with the computer program "Where in the World Is Carmen Sandiego?" There was the Space Age, during which he read Douglas Adams ("A Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy") and spent hours on the computer adopting the persona of the intrepid, punkish Roger Wilco in Space Quest games.</p>
        <p>Then, two months ago, a cousin sent us the software for the America Online service, we hooked up the modem and the boys embarked on their Internet Period.</p>
        <p>America Online is one of many services that provide varying degrees of access to the Internet, the web of computers and data bases.  The Internet itself is daunting to the uninitiated. Less daunting -- a placid suburban mall to the Internet's teeming metropolis -- are the chat rooms offered by America Online, where browsers move in and out of "lobbies" and send greetings ("Hi!" "Hello!" "Hello?") out into a silent void. Some messages are answered; others, ignored.</p>
        <p>While some lobbies are divided by interest group (teen-agers, sports fans, those over 40, gay men and lesbians), most are free-form: adolescents spouting locker-room crudities, retired teachers sounding solicitous, truck drivers sounding anything but solicitous, rabid sports fans, who knows who else. Its denizens have "screen names" (Wolf, Dawn, Sigma) that sound like vanity license plates and serve as masks at an electronic costume party.</p>
        <p>But do you let your son hobnob with strangers?</p>
        <p>If you think of this as an issue of electronic pen pals, it sounds uptight to even ask the question. If you think of the reality of pedophiles on the Internet, it seems irresponsible not to. The questions were similar to those we asked ourselves when we moved to Manhattan a year ago: How much can a junior high school student handle by himself? What does he need to know? In the case of the Internet, we gave him one rule: Don't give out your name, address or telephone number to anyone without checking with us first. Also implied was the same request we make to him on his travels around our neighborhood: stay close to home.</p>
        <p>In his first foray into the electronic mall, Michael showed that he could handle it.</p>
        <p>In his conversation with Angel, the stripper, he confided his ambitions about college to the assembled multitude. She told him he should work hard for his dreams -- and avoid drugs, which had gotten her sister into jail. Is Angel the kind of pen pal a parent dreams of? Maybe she is.</p>
        <p>Their cozy back-and-forth was interrupted when Kurt wanted to know Angel's chest size.</p>
        <p>Angel objected with a series of exclamation points, and Michael jumped to her defense.</p>
        <p>"That's not the kind of question you ask a woman," he said.</p>
        <p>Kurt was not pleased. His displeasure only became more pronounced as Angel praised Michael's you-can't-talk-that-way-to-a-lady stance.</p>
        <p>"You are a REAL gentalman  [ sic ] ," Angel cooed.</p>
        <p>"How old are you?" Kurt typed, brusquely.</p>
        <p>"Thirteen," Michael replied.</p>
        <p>"Why don't you go to Teenchat?" Kurt responded.</p>
        <p>When Michael stood his ground, Kurt let loose with two crudely dismissive words. (They, by the way, are what America Online calls a "Terms of Service Violation.")</p>
        <p>This encounter, however, was more exciting than most of those that followed. After a few days, the thrill of knowing how to get places and meet people in this strange world wore off, and the essential banality of the conversation sank in. It may, in fact, not be that much more banal than most casual encounters. But most casual encounters are not recorded word-for-word.</p>
        <p>It is humbling to wonder what any conversation, particularly one at a mall or in a bar, would look like if every word were written down. As in normal discussion, there are boors, like the person signed on as Ben, who typed the word "sex" over and over.</p>
        <p>Then again, maybe Ben wasn't doing the typing. The most unsettling experience came last week, when Michael and a visiting friend were using a new screen name, BobJr123. As they exchanged instant messages with someone named Ryan, some clever hacker (Ryan? Someone else?) started posting a crude message in the lobby with that name. The boys could neither stop the message nor post any message of their own.</p>
        <p>As it was 8:30 in the morning, no Internet guides were on call. When I was summoned to view this theft of the boys' identity, I called the service's "800" number and sent two complaints electronically. Two identical form-letter replies arrived in the electronic mailbox a few days later, but they offered little explanation. Then a guide in one of the lobbies explained that the service was aware of the problem and that it was being fixed.</p>
        <p>Michael took the lead in following up the query and discussing the issue with her. While I looked over his shoulder, I realized he needed no help.</p>
        <p>And when he starts exploring the "real" Internet, the hundreds of bulletin boards that offer commentaries on everything from nuclear physics to mountain bikes, what he has learned about handling himself in the rough-and-tumble of the chat rooms will serve him well.</p>
        <p>At his age, I spent a summer with relatives in London learning everything I could about the London subway system. My uncle gave my cousins and me a few safety pointers and then let us go. We weren't going anyplace in particular when we traveled from Piccadilly Circus to King's Cross and back, but there was great pleasure in knowing how to do it.</p>
        <p>I've given my son his electronic safety pointers. It's time to let him go.  PARENT &amp; CHILD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
