<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Job Hunters Hit the Jackpot</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="696611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNEMPLOYMENT AND JOB MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WAGES AND SALARIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHORTAGES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SIOUX FALLS (SD)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403E0D9153CF933A05755C0A962958260" item-length="1633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Job Hunters Hit the Jackpot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>SIOUX FALLS, S.D.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With pay bounding ever higher and jobs so plentiful that the local employment benefits office is often deserted, this Plains-hugging city of 105,000 is the closest thing in America to a place where it's the job seeker who says "Don't call me, I'll call you."</p>
        <p>With unemployment in Sioux Falls the lowest in the nation -- 1.9 percent in May, according to the latest figures from the Labor Department, and possibly less, compared with 6 percent nationwide -- Karen White, personnel officer at Hutchinson Technology Inc., has had to get used to interviewing prospects for the company's computer-parts assembly line at 6 A.M., before they go off to work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With pay bounding ever higher and jobs so plentiful that the local employment benefits office is often deserted, this Plains-hugging city of 105,000 is the closest thing in America to a place where it's the job seeker who says "Don't call me, I'll call you."</p>
        <p>With unemployment in Sioux Falls the lowest in the nation -- 1.9 percent in May, according to the latest figures from the Labor Department, and possibly less, compared with 6 percent nationwide -- Karen White, personnel officer at Hutchinson Technology Inc., has had to get used to interviewing prospects for the company's computer-parts assembly line at 6 A.M., before they go off to work.</p>
        <p>And Scott Simpson, owner of Sun Masters, which tints glass in cars and homes, says he has more business than he can handle and would open another shop if he could find people to work in it.</p>
        <p>"I've got to go all over the place to get people -- and then I've got to give them an arm and a leg," Mr. Simpson complained. "They're very demanding."</p>
        <p>At a time when policy makers as well as professors -- to say nothing of the Federal Reserve -- are looking warily at the possible negatives of economic strength, South Dakota's biggest city provides a laboratory of sorts in which to test what economic theory predicts of tight labor markets.</p>
        <p>Foremost is the traditional trade-off between joblessness and inflation. Workers account for about 70 percent of the typical company's costs, and estimates of how low the nation's unemployment rate can go without stoking inflation range between 5 percent and 7 percent.</p>
        <p>But a two-day visit this month showed clearly that pay is not the only thing getting more costly here. The main effect, not surprisingly, is on prices that are locally set, from real estate to haircuts. The leading complaint involves rents, which average about $370 to $750 a month for a two-bedroom apartment, the most popular size; last August, such units went for $350 to $600 a month. "I'd say rents are up about 7 percent over all from last year," said Jeffrey Iverson at the Rental Connection, a locating and property management service. This is triple the national rate of consumer price inflation.</p>
        <p>According to Jim Honermann, owner of Barber Harbor, a large emporium on the 41st Street shopping strip, "Everything is going pretty fast and furious here." The basic men's haircut at Barber Harbor rose $1 last year, to $12, and may soon rise again, he said, to "at least $13."</p>
        <p>With its its jobless rate down to the so-called frictional pool, composed mainly of people between jobs or new to the labor force, Sioux Falls also fulfills numerous other predictions about the effects of labor shortages. Among these are less qualified job applicants, high turnover, vacancies that on occasion cause work to be contracted out to other areas and intense competition that requires frequent sweetening of pay and benefits.</p>
        <p>Business and government people here say employers would be finding things even tougher if the city were unable to draw workers from a region of small towns and farms that is in economic decline.</p>
        <p>While blue-collar workers are among the hardest to find, service-sector operations like Citibank's huge credit-card processing complex are also pinched, providing academics and policy makers with another situation with test tube potential. Both are newly interested in the wage relationships of people with different skill levels and in ways of gauging the increased mobility and flexibility of the American work force. 'One Occupation at a Time'</p>
        <p>"Increasingly, wage levels are set with an eye to the competitive rates found in the local labor market, one occupation at a time," Audrey Freedman, a New York consultant, recently told a House panel examining the distribution of incomes.</p>
        <p>In Sioux Falls, though welders and skilled construction workers are in particularly short supply, the fiercest local job battles tend to be fought over the relatively unskilled.</p>
        <p>"We have raised our entry-level wage three times in the last year and a half," said Sandy Stoltz, personnel director for Carlisle Plastics, a producer of food and yard bags for Sears and other major retailers. Most recent was the May jump of 50 cents an hour that lifted starting pay to $6.60, with an extra 40 cents for the night shift.</p>
        <p>At Bell Paper Box Inc., the larger of only two suppliers of priority-mail envelopes to the United States Postal Service, Mark S. Graham, the president, says that 80 percent to 90 percent of new hires leave before working three months. 'I'm Out of Here'</p>
        <p>"We need to bring in three or four people because you're only going to have one of them left," Mr. Graham said. When something displeases them, he added, "they just say 'I'm out of here' because they can go down the street" and do better.</p>
        <p>Sioux Falls, named for a series of red-rock cascades on the Big Sioux River and boasting the nation's biggest livestock market -- more than 1.1 million hogs, cattle and sheep are expected to be auctioned this year -- is not alone in finding labor an increasingly scarce commodity. To varying degrees, the same pressures are showing up in other metropolitan areas with exceptionally low unemployment rates, a group heavily concentrated in the Midwest, in many cases cities with major universities. "These places historically have had low rates," partly because of a broad mix of recession-resistant business and industry, David Smith, an economist at the Bureau of Labor Statistics, said.</p>
        <p>And then there are places like Sheboygan, Wis. -- a city whose 3.1 percent unemployment rate places it below the top 10 -- where strong demand for production workers has inspired efforts to import them. A current target is the 2,000 Briggs &amp; Stratton Corporation employees in the Milwaukee area, 50 miles to the south, who were recently told they would be laid off over the next few years as the company shifts some production to lower-cost areas. Hospitable to Enterprise</p>
        <p>Sioux Falls, which like much of the central United States, suffered from the agricultural and energy recession of the 1980's but was largely unaffected by the 1990-91 downturn, is a virtual boom town. It is one of the relatively few places in United States where the factory work force is actually growing. But the a boom is based not on oil or entertainment projects or mega-dollar government projects but mainly on being hospitable to enterprise -- no corporate or personal income tax -- and its manageable size.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the city's tiny minority population -- Sioux Falls is 96.8 percent white, mainly of Scandinavian and German extraction -- has benefited from the intense demand for workers, pulling American Indians and blacks, some with checkered employment histories, into relatively well-paying jobs.</p>
        <p>Among its other advantages are low-cost electricity and a midcontinent location that saves money for telecommunications businesses.</p>
        <p>Virtually everyone here cites the effect of glowing articles in Money magazine, which in 1992 ranked Sioux Falls first on its list of livable locales. Though losing this honor last year, to Rochester, Minn., Sioux Falls still boasted the top-ranked economy.</p>
        <p>But as fast as newcomers arrive, many from neighboring Minnesota, where the tax burden is significantly higher, the Sioux Falls job market bids for them -- whether in financial or medical services or at such manufacturers as Hutchinson, which makes suspension assemblies for disk drives, or Aerostar International Inc., a maker of various types of balloons, including nearly all new balloons over the last 10 years for Macy's Thanksgiving Day parade in New York. Minimum Wage</p>
        <p>At John Morrell &amp; Company, whose 2,800-worker packing plant has been a pillar of the Sioux Falls economy for 85 years, even $9 an hour to start is not enough to keep the ranks full. Hutchinson's $1-an-hour raise, a 16 percent increase in starting pay, for all its production workers last October forced many other employers to follow. Greg Peterson, manager of the local Job Service office, said that not even high school students could be hired here for the minimum wage of $4.25 an hour; they get at least $4.75.</p>
        <p>Another effect of the tight labor market is to force employers to recruit more imaginatively and over ever-greater distances, luring many workers into daily treks of 100 miles or more and threatening the city's 12-minute average commute. Many applicants are already employed, leading to off-hours interviews as people "take a shot," as Mr. Peterson put it, at the most desirable jobs with such regional or national employers as Federal Express, Northern States Power or Burlington Northern.</p>
        <p>South Dakotans who had decided to move to Sioux Falls had produced "an uneasy marriage," said Lieut. Gov. Steve Kirby, who, like many officials in smaller states with part-time legislatures, remains active in business -- in his case a venture capital company. He said depopulated rural areas consoled themselves with the "spring of money" that taxes from Sioux Falls provided for the programs of state and local governments. National Job Bank</p>
        <p>Robert G. Stanek, president of the SMC Corporation, said that despite raising wages twice so far this year,his machinery company was short 20 hands, workers he said he would be willing to train free and who could make it unnecessary to contract out some production to nearby parts of Minnesota, Iowa and Nebraska.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the best thing policy makers could do, Mr. Stanek suggested, would be to create a national job bank that could link employers here with the legions of motivated but marginally skilled unemployed in other parts of the country, particularly in urban centers.</p>
        <p>"These people," Mr. Stanek said, "are not finding their way to Sioux Falls."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
