<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Predators Get More Than They Bargained For: Tuberculosis</title>
    <meta content="15KRUG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="922992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wildlife Sanctuaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Livestock Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Buffaloes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kruger National Park (South Africa)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Africa</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcneil, Donald G Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa/Kruger National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wildlife Sanctuaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tuberculosis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE2DB163FF936A25757C0A961958260" item-length="1646" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Predators Get More Than They Bargained For: Tuberculosis</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DONALD G. McNEIL Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mcneil, Donald G Jr</byline>
      <dateline>KRUGER NATIONAL PARK, South Africa</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Bovine tuberculosis spreads from domestic cattle to wild buffalo in South Africa's Kruger National Park and goes on to infect predator species, including lions; park weighs eradication plan that would involve killing 10,000 buffaloes; maps; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE age-old story of the hunter and the hunted -- the lion and the buffalo -- seems so predictable. But in a twist with overtones of poetic justice, the latest chapter in the great struggle of nature is being rewritten here: the prey are bringing down the predators by infecting them with tuberculosis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE age-old story of the hunter and the hunted -- the lion and the buffalo -- seems so predictable. But in a twist with overtones of poetic justice, the latest chapter in the great struggle of nature is being rewritten here: the prey are bringing down the predators by infecting them with tuberculosis.</p>
        <p>The bovine version of the disease, spreading from domestic cattle to wild buffalo, has become a serious threat in Kruger National Park, the jewel of South Africa's park system.  In the last two years, it has spread to lions, cheetahs, kudus and baboons.</p>
        <p>''It's quite a problem,'' said Dr. Dewald F. Keet, the park's senior veterinarian. ''Virtually half of the buffalo herds in the park are considered infected. Every time we do a post-mortem now, one of the first things we look for is tuberculosis.''</p>
        <p>Tuberculosis has been found in the past in other parks, from Queen Elizabeth Park in Uganda to Wood Buffalo National Park in Canada. But because Kruger is one of the world's most famous and undoubtedly the continent's best-organized, it breeds and exports many species around Africa, from elephants to hippopotamuses, zebras and white and black rhinoceroses. If the tuberculosis spreads to those species, Kruger could be cut off from that income, and efforts to rebuild the continent's animal populations could suffer.</p>
        <p>Kruger also has many desperately poor cattle-raising people on its western border. As buffalo nuzzle their domestic sweethearts through the fence, they can pass on the infection and, since the cows' owners drink unpasteurized milk, it could reach humans.</p>
        <p>The park is proposing a far-reaching eradication plan that would involve killing 10,000 buffaloes. Park officials feel they have no choice.</p>
        <p>''We'll have to be very careful in how we market the strategy,'' said Bruce Bryden, the park's head ranger. ''These measures may not go over very well with the public. It's like an ostrich, though. You can put your head in the sand and take it out later, but the problem won't have gone away.''</p>
        <p>Tuberculosis is an age-old killer, and forms of the mycobacterium can strike any mammal or bird on earth.  South Africa has the highest known human tuberculosis infection rate in the world, according to the World Health Organization. About 350 of every 100,000 people are infected, and a campaign is now under way here to eradicate the disease.</p>
        <p>Doctors have long known how the disease is transmitted and cured in humans. Some research has been done on its effects in dairy herds and in zoos. But in the wild, where dozens of species live together and eat each other, it remains largely a mystery.</p>
        <p>And even when it is suspected, one cannot easily get chest X-rays from a rhinoceros or sputum samples from a leopard. A skin test exists for buffaloes, and kudus betray tuberculosis infection by facial swelling, but the only way to diagnose the disease in other animals is through autopsy.</p>
        <p>Bovine tuberculosis is European in origin, and for decades, Dr. Keet said, veterinarians were taught that it simply would not survive in Africa's bright sunshine and arid climate. Moreover, since it does not kill whole herds as anthrax and rinderpest do, it was assumed that predators would suppress any chance outbreak -- in Africa, an animal that weakens is soon pulled down and devoured.</p>
        <p>In fact, that may be what happened for three decades. The disease is believed to have first entered the park in 1959 or 1960. A cattle ranch near Crocodile Bridge, at the park's southeastern corner, had an outbreak of bovine tuberculosis so virulent that its entire herd of mixed European and Asian stock had to be destroyed. In those days the park was unfenced. ''Cattle and buffalo mixed and no one thought anything of it,'' Dr. Keet said.</p>
        <p>In 1966, 100 buffaloes killed as part of normal ''culling'' to keep the park's buffalo population at about 28,500 were tested, and no tuberculosis was found.</p>
        <p>Then in 1990, a very sick two-year-old male buffalo was found at the park's western edge. He was killed, and tissue samples showed that he had bovine tuberculosis.</p>
        <p>Park officials moved to survey the disease's spread. By 1992, about 30 buffaloes in each herd of 150 to 600 had been shot and tested. The pattern was clear: the closer a herd's territory to Crocodile Bridge, the higher the incidence of tuberculosis -- up to 85 percent in some herds.</p>
        <p>The disease was unknown north of the Olifants River, which roughly divides the park in half.</p>
        <p>Then, while scientists were debating what to do, events took a turn for the worse. A dead lion, badly emaciated, was found near N'waswitshaka in September 1995. His internal organs, including his lungs, were full of tuberculosis lesions. In October, a kudu with swollen facial glands was spotted near Vervoer Dam, but got away. It was not until March 1996 that an infected kudu was shot and autopsied, but by that time, two more lions had been found, and an infected baboon so sick that it did not run from a man with a dart gun was shot near the the Skukuza headquarters car wash, practically at Dr. Keet's backdoor. In total, at present, the disease has been found in 6 kudus, the 3 lions, 2 cheetahs and 34 baboons. DNA testing has shown it to be the same bovine strain found in the buffalo.</p>
        <p>Also, in 1996, infected buffaloes were found in two herds north of the Olifants. Suddenly, time was running out.</p>
        <p>It is not clear why the infection suddenly spread so rapidly. Dairy herds show a ''snowball effect'' once a certain percentage of animals get infected, said Dr. Cobus Raath, a wildlife veterinarian and consultant to Kruger. Also, by 1995, the park had suffered 13 years of drought. Just as tuberculosis is suppressed in healthy humans but overwhelms those with immune systems compromised by AIDS or drug addiction, it overwhelms undernourished animals.  Also, drought pushes normally scattered herds together in the hunt for fresh grass, spreading the disease.</p>
        <p>Veterinarians assume the kudus got it from leaves or ponds onto which buffaloes had coughed or drooled, or from a habit peculiar to kudus: scratching their ears with their hind legs. Their hooves tread in buffalo excrement, and the skin behind their ears is broken by ticks, flies and thorns.</p>
        <p>The lions presumably got it from killing buffaloes. All the lions autopsied had lung lesions, which suggests that their method of killing -- clamping their jaws over the mouth or windpipe -- had been the death of them as well. ''It's after a chase, the animal is breathing fast and hard -- it's the ideal situation for aerosol transmission,'' Dr. Raath said.</p>
        <p>Alternatively, some lions could have caught it from each other. As social animals, they wrestle, sleep close together and growl in each other's faces, fighting over kills.</p>
        <p>Cheetahs, on the other hand, are fairly solitary and far too frail to kill buffaloes. Like all predators, they sometimes scavenge, and could have picked it up from the organs of dead buffaloes or kudus. ''Or,'' Dr. Keet said, ''there may be a smaller species on the cheetah menu that we don't know is infected yet.''</p>
        <p>Thus far, the disease has not spread to the park's export species.  Dr. Keet has dissected 800 culled elephants and found no evidence of tuberculosis. They may be protected by their long trunks. Hippopotamuses may be protected by living in water and rhinoceroses by their anti-social habits. It is not clear what protects zebras.</p>
        <p>But something clearly has to be done, and the park's study group of outside and local experts has a plan.  Their most radical notion, fencing off the southern half of the park and killing every buffalo in it, was rejected for a host of ecological and political reasons. The current proposal, still awaiting approval, is to create a 25-mile wide ''dynamic corridor'' across the park well north of the infected herds. It would not be fenced, but it would be patrolled daily by helicopter and on foot. Every buffalo inside and entering from the south would be shot. Once a year, the corridor would be moved about 12 miles south. Within 10 to 15 years, all the southern buffalo would be dead and the park would be repopulated with ''clean'' northern buffalo.</p>
        <p>There are still some worries about whether infected animals could slip through. Herds normally do not wander more than two and a half miles a day, but under stress they could conceivably cross the corridor in one night. ''Fortunately,'' Mr. Bryden said, ''even a blind man can follow a buffalo herd.''</p>
        <p>And interaction with other species remains a threat.</p>
        <p>Bovine tuberculosis has never been eradicated when it is shared between a domestic species and a wild one; domestic cattle have shared it with badgers in England, opossums in New Zealand and feral pigs and Asian buffaloes in Australia.</p>
        <p>''If people in intensive farming in Europe struggle to get rid of this disease, can you imagine how we'll battle to get rid of it?'' Dr. Keet said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
