<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Legal Experts Divided on New Antiterror Policy That Scuttles Lawyer-Client Confidentiality</title>
    <meta content="13LEGA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/13/national/13LEGA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1342585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: SECURITY AND CIVIL LIBERTIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Bar Assn</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Assn of Criminal Defense Lawyers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Speech</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom of Speech and Expression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ashcroft, John</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E4D81038F930A25752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Legal Experts Divided on New Antiterror Policy That Scuttles Lawyer-Client Confidentiality</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Experts Divided on New Antiterror Policy That Scuttles Lawyer-Client Confidentiality</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Legal experts differ sharply on new Justice Dept policy of monitoring communications between terror suspects and their lawyers; people on both sides of issue say policy is clear example of how government's expansive terrorism investigation is restricting long-recognized rights, like right to confidential communications between lawyer and client; civil liberties and lawyers' groups, including American Bar Assn and National Assn of Criminal Defense Lawyers, criticize new policy, but it has won support from some legal experts and former prosecutors, who say it is carefully designed to protect public while impinging as little as possible on rights of people to confer with their lawyers (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Legal experts differ sharply on the new Justice Department policy of monitoring communications between people the government says have been involved in terrorism and their lawyers.</p>
        <p>But people on both sides of the issue said the policy was one of the clearest examples of how the government's expansive terrorism investigation is restricting long-recognized rights, like the right to confidential communications between lawyer and client.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Legal experts differ on the Justice Department policy of monitoring communications between people suspected of terrorism and their lawyers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Legal experts differ sharply on the new Justice Department policy of monitoring communications between people the government says have been involved in terrorism and their lawyers.</p>
        <p>But people on both sides of the issue said the policy was one of the clearest examples of how the government's expansive terrorism investigation is restricting long-recognized rights, like the right to confidential communications between lawyer and client.</p>
        <p>Attorney General John Ashcroft said the policy was intended to stop inmates who had been involved in terrorism from passing messages to confederates through lawyers, their assistants or translators ''for the purpose of continuing terrorist activities.''</p>
        <p>The policy, which drew public attention last week, has become a central issue in the debate over the expansion of the government's law enforcement powers, said Benito Romano, a New York lawyer and a former United States attorney in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>''How far do you want to go in sacrificing civil liberties for the purpose of furthering an investigation?'' Mr. Romano asked.</p>
        <p>Civil liberties and lawyers' groups, including the American Bar Association and the National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers, have criticized the policy. Mr. Romano was one of many lawyers who said the policy was an unnecessary limitation on the right guaranteed by the Constitution to legal representation.</p>
        <p>But the Justice Department measure also won support from some legal experts and former prosecutors who said it was carefully designed to protect the public while impinging as little as possible on the rights of people to confer with their lawyers.</p>
        <p>Charles Fried, a Harvard law professor who was solicitor general in the Reagan administration, said the Justice Department policy was a reasonable way for officials to try to prevent attacks.</p>
        <p>''Under certain circumstances,'' Mr. Fried said, ''the lawyer is part of the conspiracy and, wittingly or unwittingly, the conversation is a means of furthering the conspiracy.''</p>
        <p>The policy was instituted on Oct. 30 with little public notice. In an announcement published the next day, the Justice Department said communications between inmates and their lawyers would be monitored when ''reasonable suspicion exists to believe that a particular inmate may use communications with attorneys or their agents to further or facilitate acts of terrorism.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ashcroft has said only a small number of inmates and their lawyers would be monitored.</p>
        <p>Critics of the policy said it would violate the Constitution by inhibiting free communication with lawyers and by taking information learned in the monitoring. The Sixth Amendment grants a criminal defendant the right ''to have the assistance of counsel for his defense,'' and the Fourth Amendment gives citizens a right to be free of ''unreasonable searches and seizures.''</p>
        <p>Irwin H. Schwartz, a Seattle lawyer and president of the National Association of Criminal Defense Lawyers, said the measure would most likely be challenged in court.</p>
        <p>''We call ourselves a nation of laws,'' Mr. Schwartz said, ''and the test of a nation of laws is whether it adheres to them in times of stress.''</p>
        <p>He said that by threatening lawyer-client confidentiality, the Justice Department was ''sliding toward being what we condemn other countries for.''</p>
        <p>Some critics said they were most troubled by the fact that the policy permits officials to monitor communications without getting prior approval from a judge.</p>
        <p>''You are concentrating an enormous amount of power in the hands of a very few government officials,'' said Gregory J. Wallance, a New York lawyer who is a former federal prosecutor.</p>
        <p>Lewis R. Katz, an expert on criminal law at Case Western Reserve University, said that since Sept. 11 he had changed many of his views about how expansive investigators' powers ought to be. But he said monitoring lawyer-client communications went over the line of what should be permitted by the Constitution.</p>
        <p>''I don't think there's any valid reason for not going to court'' for permission to intrude on the lawyer-client relationship, Mr. Katz said.</p>
        <p>George Rutherglen, a legal ethics specialist at the University of Virginia, said the monitoring was unnecessary because ''there are ways to get this information now.'' Agents could get a court-approved wiretap, he said, if they had probable cause to believe that a lawyer was involved in furthering a crime.</p>
        <p>But some experts said the critics were relying on legal concepts that have become outmoded by the deaths of so many civilians. Otto G. Obermaier, another former United States attorney in Manhattan, said the government could now make a far stronger case for monitoring lawyer-client conversations than would have been possible before Sept. 11.</p>
        <p>''It gives the government significant justification for conduct that in other circumstances might not be totally in accordance with longstanding practices,'' Mr. Obermaier said. ''Sept. 11 changed a whole lot.''</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: SECURITY AND CIVIL LIBERTIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
