<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hobbled Martin Practices And Is Probable for Patriots</title>
    <meta content="14JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/14/sports/football/14JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1423540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Patriots</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskenazi, Gerald</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Martin, Curtis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New England Patriots</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Martin, Curtis</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E4D81E31F937A2575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="815" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hobbled Martin Practices And Is Probable for Patriots</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jets' Martin Probable to Play</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALD ESKENAZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskenazi, Gerald</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Sept. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets running back Curtis Martin will likely play in game against New England Patriots, recovering well from ankle injury (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Just as his coach, his teammates and, most important, Curtis Martin himself expected, he picked up a helmet on the sideline today, strode into the huddle and ran with the Jets' first team for the first time all week.</p>
        <p>The practice left little doubt that Martin, perhaps the Jets' greatest player since Joe Namath, would start his 61st straight game Sunday in the big division matchup against the New England Patriots. Indeed, the Jets officially upgraded him to probable to play on his sprained right ankle.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Curtis Martin, perhaps the Jets' greatest player since Joe Namath, will likely start his 61st straight game Sunday against New England.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Just as his coach, his teammates and, most important, Curtis Martin himself expected, he picked up a helmet on the sideline today, strode into the huddle and ran with the Jets' first team for the first time all week.</p>
        <p>The practice left little doubt that Martin, perhaps the Jets' greatest player since Joe Namath, would start his 61st straight game Sunday in the big division matchup against the New England Patriots. Indeed, the Jets officially upgraded him to probable to play on his sprained right ankle.</p>
        <p>And just how important is this versatile runner, who spent the first three years of his career with the Patriots and the last four with the Jets?</p>
        <p>This important: The team that had Curtis Martin at running back won 11 of the 14 games between the clubs during that time.</p>
        <p>In Martin's Patriots career, New England was 5-1 against the Jets. Since switching teams, Martin has helped the Jets compile a 6-2 record against the Patriots.</p>
        <p>That is why Coach Herman Edwards was in the Jets' practice bubble this morning taking a peek at Martin working out. Edwards did not stare at Martin -- he merely took darting glances at the ankle. He watched how Martin walked. He watched Martin take a few handoffs from Chad Pennington -- the starting quarterback, Vinny Testaverde, rests on Fridays -- and then, satisfied, left.</p>
        <p>As a player, Edwards understood, and coped with, pain. It is something Martin has often done. He has been inspired, he said, by reading a book called ''As a Man Thinketh,'' by James Allen. It is filled with mind-over-matter anecdotes about refusing to yield to injury.</p>
        <p>''What Curtis does,'' Edwards said, ''is master the pain, as he did today. I didn't take it easy with him today. That was the whole point. We wanted to see how he'd come out of it on Saturday.''</p>
        <p>So the Jets are still not officially saying Martin will play. If the ankle unexpectedly swells up Saturday, plans could be altered. But the way Edwards used the player he calls ''the best Jet'' left little room for questioning. Martin went out for passes, he sprinted carrying the ball wide, and he cut to his right or his left through the tackles. And anyway, the Jets' No. 2 ball carrier, the inexperienced LaMont Jordan, has a sprained left wrist protected by a cast.</p>
        <p>Martin not only wills away his pain, he revels in overcoming it.</p>
        <p>Asked how he felt about performing today, after he had been sidelined since Sunday's game against the Bills, Martin said, ''It was inspiring to myself.''</p>
        <p>He admitted to being apprehensive at first. ''I didn't know what to expect,'' he said.</p>
        <p>After his workout, while the offense rested on the sideline and watched the defense take over against a simulated Patriots attack, Martin kept walking. It was as if he were trying to walk away the injury.</p>
        <p>''He wants to play,'' Edwards said. ''But it won't be his decision. It will be mine.''</p>
        <p>It is a little surprising that Martin has turned into an iron man; his last days as a Patriot were filled with speculation about his durability. He missed the last three games of the 1997 season with a shoulder injury. Then he failed to appear in two playoff games because of the shoulder as well as abdominal and groin injuries. When the Patriots declined to match the Jets' offer to Martin in 1998, when he had become a free agent, whispers out of Foxboro were that he was not durable and not worth the millions it would cost to keep him.</p>
        <p>But since becoming a Jet, Martin has missed only one game, at St. Louis in 1998, because of a thigh injury. He has become somewhat of a medical legend around the Jets because he played the last two years despite ligament damage in his knee.</p>
        <p>The incentive for Martin to play has now gone far beyond the emotion of performing well against a former team. The Jets and Patriots are contenders for division honors, and the theatrics of recent years surrounding their games has given way to that football imperative.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>The Jets are not superstitious. But they have decided to dress all in white Sunday. It is their traditional road garb. They are 8-1 going back to last season while wearing white. . . . The Patriots lead the league with the highest number of players from another team -- seven once played for the Jets. Patriots Coach BILL BELICHICK likes his players to have experience -- 14 of them are 30 years or older. Only eight Jets are 30 or older.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
