<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dole Looking to 'Well-Known' Running Mate</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="862599"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VICE PRESIDENTS AND VICE PRESIDENCY (US)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOLE, BOB</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NAGOURNEY, ADAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELLSWORTH, ROBERT F ROBERT DOLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vice Presidents and Vice Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 1996</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960706T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E6DA1039F935A35754C0A960958260" item-length="735" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dole Looking to 'Well-Known' Running Mate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NAGOURNEY, ADAM;</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, July 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bob Dole will choose a "well-known figure" as his running mate and, though he expects to make his choice within a month, he has yet to begin contacting potential candidates for the job, the head of his Vice-Presidential search committee said today.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Ellsworth, who is heading Mr. Dole's search, said after a 90-minute meeting with the all-but-certain Republican Presidential nominee and his aides that the committee and Mr. Dole had begun to consider names rather than just discussing process.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bob Dole will choose a "well-known figure" as his running mate and, though he expects to make his choice within a month, he has yet to begin contacting potential candidates for the job, the head of his Vice-Presidential search committee said today.</p>
        <p>Robert F. Ellsworth, who is heading Mr. Dole's search, said after a 90-minute meeting with the all-but-certain Republican Presidential nominee and his aides that the committee and Mr. Dole had begun to consider names rather than just discussing process.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ellsworth, who was the chairman of Mr. Dole's 1988 Presidential campaign, would not name anyone under consideration and responded elliptically when asked to discuss details of the selection process.</p>
        <p>"It's a non-linear process," Mr. Ellsworth said. "Most of the process is going on inside Mr. Dole's head and Mr. Dole's heart."</p>
        <p>When a reporter asked whether that process had produced an actual list of names, Mr. Ellsworth replied: "Don't ask me about a list. It's a non-linear process. It's not a list. It's a pool -- sometimes expanding, sometimes contracting."</p>
        <p>At that point Nelson Warfield, the campaign spokesman, who had been standing  quietly at Mr. Ellsworth's side, whispered, "Mondale."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellsworth looked at the press secretary, puzzled, and asked, "Pardon?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Warfield responded, "Mondale model," a reminder of what was supposed to be Mr. Ellsworth's principal point, that Mr. Dole was not going to repeat the public process that Walter F. Mondale, the 1984 Democratic Presidential nominee, staged before selecting Geraldine A. Ferraro, then a Congresswoman from Queens,  as his running mate.</p>
        <p>"Oh, thank you," Mr. Ellsworth said. "The important point -- this is going to be a private process. It's not going to be an open cattle-call process. We're going to do this not in public, out of consideration of the dignity of the potential candidate."</p>
        <p>Mr. Ellsworth said the Vice-Presidential candidate would almost certainly be  someone who is a well-known public figure, and probably someone in government. He said that was why he was not concerned that the campaign had not begun the preliminary questioning of people who might be asked to serve, the first step of a background check.</p>
        <p>Asked how long the vetting process would take, Mr. Ellsworth replied, "Not long, because they're all so well-known."</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole's efforts to organize his selection of a running mate came a day after the chairman of the Republican platform committee appeared to complicate Mr. Dole's effort to deal with a second major issue before next month's convention, the party's stand on abortion. The chairman, Representative Henry J. Hyde of Illinois, differed with two suggestions Mr. Dole has made on how to deal with the abortion plank.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hyde, who appeared at the candidate's side at a campaign rally in Mr. Hyde's Congressional district on Thursday, took issue with what the platform should say on the subject and where it should say it. Nevertheless, he agreed with Mr. Dole that the Republicans were close to resolving the issue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole has proposed that the platform incorporate a "declaration of tolerance" that would affirm Republican opposition to abortion while saying the  party accepted dissenting views. But Mr. Hyde, who is one of the most prominent  opponents of abortion rights in his party and whose agreement is virtually essential to any compromise, said he would prefer an "expression of diversity."</p>
        <p>"I think 'tolerance' is kind of a weak word," he said. "You know tolerance, that implies disapproval. I don't want to do that. I want to welcome everyone. You win by inclusion and addition, so tolerance is not my favorite word."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hyde also seemed uncomfortable with Mr. Dole's proposal that the modifying language go into the abortion plank itself. Opponents of abortion rights want the declaration of tolerance in the platform's preamble, so that it  applies to all planks equally.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dole is leaning to a proposal that the tolerance clause be included in several disputed planks. But Mr. Hyde said he preferred to see it in the preamble. "Otherwise," he said, "we'd have to have a disclaimer in every plank in the platform."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
