<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Helping or Confusing, TV Labels Are Widening</title>
    <meta content="30RATI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="961487"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mifflin, Lawrie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labeling and Labels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970930T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E1DA133AF933A0575AC0A961958260" item-length="915" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Helping or Confusing, TV Labels Are Widening</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRIE MIFFLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mifflin, Lawrie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Most television networks are set to begin adding labels D, L, S and V--for suggestive dialogue, coarse language, sex and violence--to existing labels of TV-G, TV-PG, TV-14 and TV-MA; although many family-advocacy groups argue that parents need more detailed labels to indicate exactly what made a show deserve a parental-discretion warning, others say that parents may find new system bewildering (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Starting tomorrow, most television networks will add the labels D, L, S and V -- for suggestive dialogue, coarse language, sex and violence -- to the existing labels of TV-G, TV-PG, TV-14 and TV-MA.</p>
        <p>Although many family-advocacy groups argue that parents need more detailed labels to indicate exactly what made a show deserve a parental-discretion warning, others say that parents may find the new system bewildering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Starting tomorrow, most television networks will add the labels D, L, S and V -- for suggestive dialogue, coarse language, sex and violence -- to the existing labels of TV-G, TV-PG, TV-14 and TV-MA.</p>
        <p>Although many family-advocacy groups argue that parents need more detailed labels to indicate exactly what made a show deserve a parental-discretion warning, others say that parents may find the new system bewildering.</p>
        <p>''I call it 'L.S./M.F.T.,' '' said Peggy Charren, a longtime advocate of better television for children who calls herself an equally staunch advocate of freedom of speech. (People over 50 may recall the advertising slogan ''Lucky Strike Means Fine Tobacco.) ''I think it's very, very confusing.''</p>
        <p>NBC, alone among the major networks, has refused to add the extra letters, sticking to the age-based categories adopted by the broadcast and cable networks last year and in use since January. But NBC has begun adding its own parental advisories to shows, such as ''This program has some violent scenes'' or ''This episode has a level of violence unusual for the series.''</p>
        <p>Some networks began using the new labels when the new television season began this month, and already some labels have provoked questions. For example, on Sunday night the pay-cable network Showtime presented a made-for-television movie, ''Elmore Leonard's Gold Coast,'' that contained frontal nudity, simulated sexual intercourse and frequent coarse language. Yet the movie had a TV-14 rating, not TV-MA.</p>
        <p>The TV-14 rating is supposed to indicate material that parents might find unsuitable for children under 14. The TV-MA is supposed to suggest that a show is ''for mature audiences only.'' (TV-PG means ''parental guidance suggested,'' and TV-G means suitable for all audiences.)</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Showtime said the movie had been preceded by parental advisories from its own three-year-old system, used also by HBO. She said ''Gold Coast'' had carried these labels: brief nudity, violence, adult language and adult content.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, some competitors were surprised that CBS put a TV-MA rating as well as the letters V, S, L on the premiere episode of ''Brooklyn South,'' the new police drama from Steven Bochco. They said only the violence in the opening sequence (which showed a policeman bleeding profusely after being shot in the back of the head) was strong enough to get a TV-MA, while the bulk of the episode deserved a TV-14. Some viewers praised CBS for using the TV-MA label, while others suggested that stronger labels would encourage producers to put even more violent and sexually graphic scenes on the air. And some said the labels would frighten advertisers away from shows, making it more difficult to finance them.</p>
        <p>But Jack Myers, publisher of The Myers Report, an advertising newsletter, said most advertisers screened each episode of a show beforehand anyway, and those who object to an ''N.Y.P.D. Blue'' or a ''Brooklyn South'' episode would avoid it regardless of its rating.</p>
        <p>''From the advertisers' side or the viewers' side, there's no discernible impact,'' he said. ''I don't think it will be an issue until the V-chip rolls out and viewers have a filtration device to use, and that starts showing up in the Nielsen ratings.''</p>
        <p>The ratings system was designed to work with a computer chip that will enable viewers to block programs with certain rating labels. Under Federal law, the chips must be installed on new television sets starting in 1998.</p>
        <p>After seven months of using the age-based system and under pressure from the family-advocacy groups and many Congressional leaders, the television industry agreed to the more detailed labels in July in exchange for a pledge from several key Congressmen not to legislate on television content. An oversight board has been established to monitor the labels' use and determine whether the networks are labeling shows consistently. It has not met yet.</p>
        <p>Chris Hikawa, vice president for broadcast standards and practices at ABC, said her department's toughest discussions revolved around the intensity of violence. And she said some shows would get an age-group label without a V, S, L or D, because of their overall theme. ''There could be a story about AIDS, for example, with no violence, foul language or sex,'' she said. ''But the nature of the topic means we'd call it TV-14.''</p>
        <p>At Fox, Roland McFarland, vice president for broadcast standards and practices, said the process had become much more time-consuming now that D, L, S and V had to be considered.</p>
        <p>''Is it a punch? A gunshot? A gunshot plus killing?'' he said. ''These are all subjective interpretations. The classic discussion here is around shows where there's heavy jeopardy involved, but no real on-screen violence. You might see a body, the aftermath of violence, but you're not dealing with an active piece of violence. Where's the tilt factor, as far as giving it a V?''</p>
        <p>Ms. Hikawa said the new system was bound to be confusing at first.</p>
        <p>''I hope people give it a chance,'' she said. ''In the beginning of the last one, it was all 'PG,' nobody was using 'TV-14' at all, but within a few months, there were more 'TV-14's.'' She added, ''It will evolve.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
