<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pop Life</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="702477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CD-ROM (COMPACT DISK-READ ONLY MEMORY)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SERIOUS FUN FESTIVAL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOWIE, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALLEN, TERRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STRAUSS, NEIL</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CHIPPY: DIARIES OF A WEST TEXAS HOOKER (PLAY)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/The Pop Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Memory</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">CD-ROM (Compact Disk-Read Only Memory)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3D61E3EF93BA15754C0A962958260" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pop Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Neil Strauss</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STRAUSS, NEIL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Far Out Into Interactivity</p>
        <p>David Bowie has been exploring strange new worlds, and they're light years away from those of "Space Oddity" and "Starman." "I'm totally in this alien area and it's great," he said by telephone on Tuesday in his first interview since last spring, when his CD-ROM "Jump" was released. Mr. Bowie's alien land is interactive multimedia, in which manipulatable pictures, sound, video, animation and text turn users into participants. His means of travel is the recording studio, where technology and the creative process meet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Far Out Into Interactivity</p>
        <p>David Bowie has been exploring strange new worlds, and they're light years away from those of "Space Oddity" and "Starman." "I'm totally in this alien area and it's great," he said by telephone on Tuesday in his first interview since last spring, when his CD-ROM "Jump" was released. Mr. Bowie's alien land is interactive multimedia, in which manipulatable pictures, sound, video, animation and text turn users into participants. His means of travel is the recording studio, where technology and the creative process meet.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bowie said he'd been immersed in four new projects with Brian Eno, with whom he recorded pioneering electronic pop albums in the late 1970's: "Heroes," "Low" and "Lodger." The two are working on a new CD-ROM, music for the La La La Human Steps dance company, a music theater piece and, he said, "an album of so-called songs."</p>
        <p>"We don't feel part of what's going on at all now," the 47-year-old singer said. "We feel totally distanced from everything, and that's kind of exciting. It kind of feels a bit dangerous because you're not sure if anybody's going to relate to what you're doing. People might dismiss it, which is fine, because we're used to being dismissed. The stuff that we did in the late 70's was pretty much 80 percent dismissed all around. But I think that they've proved to be three of the most important albums of that particular period because they defined so many areas of where music was going to go."</p>
        <p>The recently released "Jump" is just a hint of the things to come. That CD-ROM, which allows users to create their own videos for Mr. Bowie's 1993 single "Jump They Say" by maneuvering through a bank of preselected images, was created by the Los Angeles multimedia company Ion, with Mr. Bowie's permission and resources but without much of his creative influence.</p>
        <p>"What spurred me on," Mr. Bowie said, "is that I looked at the thing they did for me, and then I started looking at everybody else's CD-ROM's, and I thought, 'Well, is this as far as it goes?' and I think that really made me want to get involved, just to see what I could do with it."</p>
        <p>"The other major decision which helped me a lot was not having to do my old hits anymore," he added, referring to his decision in 1990 never to perform his early songs in concert. "It made a kind of barrier for me and really pushed me into saying, 'Well, do I want to stay in music, and if so, why?' Because it certainly wasn't to just keep doing the cabaret rounds for the rest of my life singing 'Ground Control to Major Tom.' "</p>
        <p>Mr. Bowie continued to make music, recording with the band Tin Machine and releasing a solo album in 1993, "Black Tie White Noise," which is no longer available because its record label, Savage, went out of business. Mr. Bowie is still trying to find a new record label (he says he has plenty of offers), and hopes to release his new CD-ROM in January and his album with Mr. Eno shortly afterward.</p>
        <p>He said the ideas for his planned projects would be difficult to put into words. Unlike most other music-oriented CD-ROMs, he said, his will not be archival, biographical, or based on an album release. It will be fully interactive, he explained, and have a nonlinear storyline, allowing the listener to "approach the thing again and again and never go through the same experience."</p>
        <p>"Everything seems to have crossed through the mediums a lot more," he said, "and I'm not quite sure what it is we're doing, but it's not just making records anymore. It's got a lot further than that, and we keep translating everything to be interactive. The medium that we are working in is not actually CD-ROM. The medium is interactive multimedia, and I think that the CD-ROM is only the best delivery system currently available." Texan at Lincoln Center</p>
        <p>Terry Allen is a Texas-born artist with too many outlets for his creativity. He has recorded eight albums of his own songs and had one-man exhibitions of his sculpture and art in dozens of galleries. He has also written screenplays, scored dance pieces, designed books, created theater pieces, erected art installations, written novels and recorded radio plays. Unlike Mr. Bowie, he works on one canvas at a time.</p>
        <p>"Whatever I happen to be working on or interested in at the time dictates how it gets done and what I choose to use," Mr. Allen said by telephone this week.</p>
        <p>The newest child of his productivity is the music-theater piece "Chippie: Diaries of a West Texas Hooker," which he wrote with his wife Jo Harvey Allen, who has been in the films "The Client," "Fried Green Tomatoes" and "True Stories." "Chippie" opened last night in the John Jay Theater at Lincoln Center and runs through Saturday as part of the Serious Fun festival. "Songs From Chippie" (Hollywood), a CD released last week, compiles music from the piece, including new songs by Mr. Allen and two of Texas's most distinct songwriters, Joe Ely and Butch Hancock. It also features the first commercially available recordings of Wayne Hancock and Jo Carol Pierce. Ms. Pierce is a cynical, extremely talented musician who was recently the subject of a tribute album called "Across the Great Divide" (Dejadisc).</p>
        <p>All of these songwriters sing and act in "Chippie," the story of a woman they know only through her diaries, which were divided into two packages: one reading "bundles from heaven," the other "parcels from hell."</p>
        <p>"She stormed around the part of West Texas where we all grew up," Mr. Ely said. "I guess we kind of felt that we knew that character. Our grandparents told us all about that time in the 30's when, because of the Depression, Texas was pretty well dried up and about to blow away, and the only thing keeping people here was the oil boom."</p>
        <p>Ms. Harvey, who plays the role of Chippie, continued: "Chippie hitchhiked in high heels on those roads and followed the oil boomers, and went from tent city to tent city, wherever the action was. She was actually apologetic for having had only 6,000 lovers." (She also had syphilis.)</p>
        <p>Said Mr. Allen: "Her life was a real parade of names and faces and characters, and the piece is structured that way. I think the acts work like tracks on a record. They relate to one another, but they have these gaps in them that the diaries had in them, gaps that that part of the country has in it, too."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
