<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Foreign Affairs; A Crippled Policy</title>
    <meta content="24FRIE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Columnists/Thomas L Friedman</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E6DF153BF937A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="753" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Foreign Affairs; A Crippled Policy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel and President Clinton sat down in the Oval Office on Tuesday, Mr. Clinton began by clearing the air. The President, according to U.S. and Israeli officials, basically said to Mr. Netanyahu: ''I know you're upset about reports that we're stiffing you, and that we're not doing a lunch for you, and that you're not staying at Blair House. But before you came in here today you met with my sworn political enemies [the Christian far right] who have put out tapes accusing me of having people murdered. So, Prime Minister, we're even.''</p>
        <p>The two pols then had a laugh over their mutual attempts to stick it to each other, and it broke the ice. More important, Mr. Clinton followed it up with the first concrete U.S. blueprint for breaking the Mideast deadlock. It was probably Mr. Clinton's last laugh, though, because the latest sordid White House scandal hit a few hours later. By week's end, when Yasir Arafat arrived, that all-too-rare, blunt, put-your-cards-on-the-table approach to foreign policy evinced by the President earlier in the week seemed to peter out. Mr. Arafat left muttering about his bad luck; Bibi went home speaking warmly of a President now too wounded to be a threat to him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel and President Clinton sat down in the Oval Office on Tuesday, Mr. Clinton began by clearing the air. The President, according to U.S. and Israeli officials, basically said to Mr. Netanyahu: ''I know you're upset about reports that we're stiffing you, and that we're not doing a lunch for you, and that you're not staying at Blair House. But before you came in here today you met with my sworn political enemies [the Christian far right] who have put out tapes accusing me of having people murdered. So, Prime Minister, we're even.''</p>
        <p>The two pols then had a laugh over their mutual attempts to stick it to each other, and it broke the ice. More important, Mr. Clinton followed it up with the first concrete U.S. blueprint for breaking the Mideast deadlock. It was probably Mr. Clinton's last laugh, though, because the latest sordid White House scandal hit a few hours later. By week's end, when Yasir Arafat arrived, that all-too-rare, blunt, put-your-cards-on-the-table approach to foreign policy evinced by the President earlier in the week seemed to peter out. Mr. Arafat left muttering about his bad luck; Bibi went home speaking warmly of a President now too wounded to be a threat to him.</p>
        <p>Yasir, you're not alone. At a moment when a host of major foreign issues are about to surface as Congress returns from recess, Mr. Clinton is going to be distracted at best and indicted at worst. Farewell Madeleine, hello Monica, goodbye foreign policy.</p>
        <p>Yes, I know the President is adept at compartmentalizing his scandals and isolating them from his duties. But however this latest scandal ends, it is going to diminish the President's stature, make him more vulnerable to Congressional pressures (his jury in any impeachment proceeding) and cast every foreign-policy decision he makes in a jaded light. Get ready for: ''Do we really have to bomb Saddam, or is the President just doing that to change the subject?''</p>
        <p>The good news here is that the cold war is over and America is the world's only superpower. That is, this scandal may turn out to be Watergate, but thankfully it's not 1973. We are not in the midst of a global cold-war struggle with the Soviet Union, with both sides pointing cocked nuclear weapons at each other. In that cold-war era, global stability depended on the credibility of nuclear deterrence, and the credibility of that deterrence depended in large part on the credibility of each nation's leader. That was one reason Americans felt they could afford to discard a George Bush and indulge a Bill Clinton, even knowing he had a few Gennifers in the closet.</p>
        <p>But the bad news is that while there's no rival to American power in the world, there's also no substitute for American leadership. The immediate foreign-policy challenges, while not as lethal as the cold war, nevertheless involve fundamental U.S. interests. If collectively left to fester, they will affect global stability. But to defuse them will require strong Presidential leadership.</p>
        <p>Think about it. The U.S. is very likely going to have to bomb Saddam Hussein again, and probably without allies. Nurturing Iran's overture to the U.S. for a dialogue can only be done with Presidential cover. Getting an isolationist, skeptical Congress to support an I.M.F. Asian bailout will require the President's most persuasive powers. The only way you are going to break the deadlock in the Middle East is if Secretary of State Albright holds both Mr. Netanyahu's and Mr. Arafat's feet to the fire and is willing to tell the truth when the peace process becomes a fraud. Is she up to that without strong Presidential backing?</p>
        <p>This situation reminds us again ''that the end of the cold war is both an advantage and a disadvantage,'' remarked the Johns Hopkins University foreign-affairs specialist Michael Mandelbaum. ''It is an advantage because a hobbled President doesn't imperil the nation by making us more vulnerable to powerful enemies. We have no powerful enemies today. On the other hand, precisely because there is no threat, there is no consensus on foreign policy, and no presumption in favor of following the President's lead. The President has to put together a consensus on every issue from scratch. That is a difficult, time-consuming and essentially political task, and the weaker Mr. Clinton is politically, the less able he is to do it.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
