<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Streaking Storm Has First Place in Sight</title>
    <meta content="24STOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St John's University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Villanova University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fraschilla, Fran</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Timothy W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE7DE153BF937A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="582" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Streaking Storm Has First Place in Sight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Timothy W</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St John's basketball coach Fran Fraschilla prepares for game against Villanova at Madison Square Garden (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>St. John's Coach Fran Fraschilla is not deluding himself. Yes, his team whipped Pittsburgh in double overtime Thursday night to extend its winning streak to five games, all in the Big East. And, sure, the team is playing its best basketball since he took over last season.</p>
        <p>But Fraschilla does not expect a large, enthusiastic crowd when St. John's opens a three-game homestand with a game against Villanova tomorrow at Madison Square Garden.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>St. John's Coach Fran Fraschilla is not deluding himself. Yes, his team whipped Pittsburgh in double overtime Thursday night to extend its winning streak to five games, all in the Big East. And, sure, the team is playing its best basketball since he took over last season.</p>
        <p>But Fraschilla does not expect a large, enthusiastic crowd when St. John's opens a three-game homestand with a game against Villanova tomorrow at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''That's a tough game for us,'' Fraschilla said. ''Although we're in the midst of this streak, there won't be a lot of people there. It's Super Bowl Sunday; people will be making their guacamole dip. I told the team that this has got to be one of those schoolyard battles.''</p>
        <p>The Red Storm (14-6, 6-3) has a chance to claim a share of first place in the Big East 6. It must defeat Villanova (7-9, 4-4), and Syracuse (15-3, 5-2) must beat Connecticut (16-3, 6-2) today at the Carrier Dome.</p>
        <p>That is not far-fetched. The Red Storm beat the Huskies on Monday night, and that victory gave it a level of confidence heading into the Pittsburgh game. The Red Storm's Tarik Turner, the senior guard whose two free throws at the end of regulation sent the game into overtime, said it would have been devastating if St. John's had lost to the Panthers.</p>
        <p>''Everyone was saying that St. John's would let down after our big win against UConn,'' Turner said. ''We felt we had a lot to prove. We wanted to prove to ourselves and to everyone else that we're a team that comes out every night playing like it's our last game.''</p>
        <p>Turner seemed surprised when informed that the victory over Pittsburgh had given the team more victories than it had last season. ''We're not really trying to compare this season to last season,'' Turner said. ''We're just trying to take it one game at a time and just go out intense and try to win every game.''</p>
        <p>That is the way Fraschilla likes it. He does not want the team to look too far ahead. The Red Storm managed to win the Pittsburgh game without its top scorer, Felipe Lopez, who fouled out with 1 minute 23 seconds left in regulation and missed both overtime periods. The Panthers took Lopez (2 of 10, 7 points) out of the flow of the game, and the offensive burden shifted to center Zendon Hamilton and forward Tyrone Grant. Hamilton had 26 points and 16 rebounds. Grant, who has strep throat, had 11 points and 15 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Fraschilla decided to allow his freshman forward Ron Artest to defend Pittsburgh's most dangerous offensive threat, guard Vonteego Cummings, who scored 27 points but missed 2 crucial free throws in overtime and threw a pass out of bounds in the second overtime. Fraschilla said the double-overtime victory is all part of the team's learning how to win.</p>
        <p>''You go back to last year and you look at those four straight buzzer beaters that we lost and I think we've taken something from those experiences, especially the upperclassmen,'' Fraschilla said. ''Felipe, Tarik, Zendon and Tyrone, they're willing themselves on the younger guys. They're explaining that we're not going to lose these games. They're really developing a great chemistry and a great mental toughness.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
