<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Merged Hospitals Gain Both Power and Critics</title>
    <meta content="Y26HOS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/09/26/business/26HOSP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1426771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Trade Commission</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Evanston Northwestern Healthcare</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Massachusetts General Hospital</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bringham and Women's Mass General Hospital</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Partners HealthCare</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abelson, Reed</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mongan, James J (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020926T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E6DD1139F935A1575AC0A9649C8B63" item-length="1806" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Merged Hospitals Gain Both Power and Critics</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Merged Hospitals Gain Both Power and Critics</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By REED ABELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abelson, Reed</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Merged hospitals are gaining power and critics; discontent with managed care and creation of large networks have given hospitals tremendous leverage; in seeking better prices, they are ones threatening to drop health plans, risking disruption of medical care for thousands of patients; Federal Trade Commission, which has little success blocking mergers, is going back to look at some merged hospitals; regulators are examining merger in Illinois that took place two years ago at Evanston Northwestern Healthcare; state attorneys general are also re-examining some mergers; Massachusetts General Hospital's merger with Brigham and Women's Mass General resulted in about $250 million in cost savings; employers are increasingly worried about power of Mass General and its parent system Partners HealthCare, created in 1994; Mass General's president Dr James J Mongan will become chief executive of Partners next year; graphs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For years, Massachusetts General Hospital was barely able to increase prices. Payments from the area's three major health plans rose an average of just 1.5 percent a year from 1996 through 2000, according to the hospital.</p>
        <p>But all that has changed. After merging with another of Boston's leading hospitals, Brigham and Women's, Mass General is the crown jewel in a system with 10 hospitals and 5,000 doctors that commands a fifth of the health care market in this city, the nation's foremost medical center. During its most recent negotiations with health plans, the hospital won price increases of about 6 percent a year through 2004.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Employers and regulators are asking whether hospitals are abusing the market power they have gained through consolidation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For years, Massachusetts General Hospital was barely able to increase prices. Payments from the area's three major health plans rose an average of just 1.5 percent a year from 1996 through 2000, according to the hospital.</p>
        <p>But all that has changed. After merging with another of Boston's leading hospitals, Brigham and Women's, Mass General is the crown jewel in a system with 10 hospitals and 5,000 doctors that commands a fifth of the health care market in this city, the nation's foremost medical center. During its most recent negotiations with health plans, the hospital won price increases of about 6 percent a year through 2004.</p>
        <p>The merger -- like hundreds around the country in the 1990's -- promised to help stem the rise in health care costs by eliminating expensive duplication of services and squeezing overhead. But with hospital prices rising sharply, both the employers who pay most of the bills and the regulators who oversee the nation's health care system are asking whether hospitals are abusing the market power they have gained through consolidation.</p>
        <p>''Provider consolidation, hospital consolidation, is strongly aggravating these costs,'' said Helen Darling, president of the Washington Business Group on Health, which represents large employers.</p>
        <p>The situation in Boston illustrates this remarkable shift in the dynamics of health care. A few years ago, hospitals cowered before health plans, which threatened to exclude them from managed care networks. Now, the discontent with managed care and the creation of large hospital networks have given the hospitals tremendous leverage. In seeking better prices, they are the ones threatening to drop plans, risking the disruption of medical care for thousands of patients.</p>
        <p>''What we're seeing in these markets is this game of health care chicken,'' said Cara S. Lesser, a senior researcher for the Center for Studying Health System Change in Washington, who points to the recent bargaining between Mass General and the Boston area's health plans as a prime example.</p>
        <p>Given these concerns, the Federal Trade Commission -- which has had little success blocking mergers -- is now going back to look at some merged hospitals.</p>
        <p>Regulators, for example, are now examining a merger in Illinois that took place two years ago at Evanston Northwestern Healthcare, according to a spokesman for that system.</p>
        <p>State attorneys general, whose purview includes the not-for-profit hospitals that make up most of the industry, are also scrutinizing the competitive landscape. Regulators in New York broke up a merger in Poughkeepsie; Florida officials, with the help of federal regulators, took action against two hospitals for violating the consent decree that allowed them to be partners.</p>
        <p>After years in which hospital costs were largely dormant, they are now the main source of higher health care costs, responsible for half of the 10 percent increase experienced by private insurers last year, according to Paul B. Ginsburg, president of the Center for Studying Health System Change. Although prescription drug costs are rising more quickly, hospital costs represent a much larger share of overall costs.</p>
        <p>Here, employers are increasingly worried about the power of Mass General and its parent system, Partners HealthCare, created in 1994.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, Partners emerged the clear winner after tense negotiations with the big Tufts Health Plan, according to employers and others involved in the Boston market. At one point, the talks broke off, with Partners said to be demanding a 30 percent increase in prices over three years. But people panicked at the idea of not being able to go to Mass General, and Tufts was also faced with the loss of many of Partners' doctors.</p>
        <p>Some big purchasers of health care voiced anxiety about Partners' power to Tom Reilly, the state attorney general. ''The purchasers were concerned and expressed their concern,'' said Dolores L. Mitchell, the executive director of the state's Group Insurance Commission, which provides health coverage to 250,000 state employees and their families.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reilly declined to comment on his inquiry.</p>
        <p>Just what health plans pay hospitals is hard to know, but Mass General appears to be among the most aggressive here in seeking higher prices. The hospital's average bill per discharge rose about 72 percent from 1996 through 2000, compared with 40 percent for other academic medical centers in Boston, according to data provided by the Massachusetts Division of Health Care Finance and Policy. While hardly anyone pays those prices, just as few buyers pay the list price for a car, the bill indicates what the hospital is demanding.</p>
        <p>Another measure is the hospital's revenue from inpatient services, adjusted for the kinds of cases it handles and including fixed payments from government programs. According to state data, that figure jumped 26 percent for Mass General from 1996 through 2001, versus 16 percent for its peers.</p>
        <p>Partners dismisses the idea that it has any special influence in the marketplace. ''We weren't able to get a blank check from the payors,'' said Dr. James J. Mongan, the president of Mass General, who will become the chief executive of Partners next year.</p>
        <p>And some say that Partners, like other hospitals, is simply making up for years in which the health plans were the ones driving brutal bargains. ''I do think the pendulum has swung, but I think it needed to swing,'' said William C. Van Faasen, the chairman and chief executive of Blue Cross and Blue Shield of Massachusetts, the area's largest insurer.</p>
        <p>The market power of Partners has allowed the system to ''climb out much faster'' from the overly low reimbursement hospitals received, said Stuart Altman, a Brandeis University professor who was co-chairman of a state task force on health care costs.</p>
        <p>Employers and others are also concerned about Partners' impact on its closest competitor, Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center, which is part of the CareGroup Healthcare System. While Partners and Beth Israel share a medical school, Harvard, they vie directly with one another for patients and doctors, according to Paul F. Levy, Beth Israel's chief executive.</p>
        <p>Like Partners, CareGroup was created by a merger, but the results have been radically different. Though the system suffered from years of mismanagement, it also tried to do what Partners did not: combine the medical departments of its leading hospitals, Beth Israel and Deaconess, to form a clinically integrated institution. As doctors fled, upset by the changes, Partners capitalized on the disruption.</p>
        <p>Beth Israel, which is struggling financially and has lost market share over the last five years, is now trying to persuade patients to return. Mr. Levy, who appears to be having some success in turning the hospital around, is rebuilding essential departments like surgery.</p>
        <p>The decision by Partners to keep its hospitals distinct also prompts questions from critics about the rationale for the merger. Some argue that it simply created a negotiating powerhouse. ''It made health care here more expensive and weakened the local institutions,'' said David Mulligan, a former state public health commissioner who now teaches health care policy at Stonehill College.</p>
        <p>Partners defends the merger, saying that combining the two hospitals never made sense, given their locations and other factors. The merger also resulted in roughly $250 million in cost savings, according to Dr. Mongan, who points to some attempts to integrate services, such as sharing the best practices.</p>
        <p>Across the country, there is a growing debate about whether hospital mergers have benefited the public.</p>
        <p>In Grand Rapids, Mich., for example, the merger of the Butterworth and Blodgett Hospitals, which the F.T.C. unsuccessfully sought to block, was examined by two former regulators who published their findings last year. The hospitals, now part of the Spectrum Health System, agreed to limit their price increases to many of the area's plans. The regulators, David Balto and Meleah Geertsma, say the hospitals did not merge the bulk of their clinical operations and that cost savings are much less than estimated.</p>
        <p>The merged entity, which commands well over half of the local market, is also proving a formidable negotiator. The two hospitals recently threatened to pull out of some plans offered by Blue Cross Blue Shield of Michigan that were not covered by the pricing agreement after demanding double-digit increases. The two parties recently settled their differences, according to Richard T. Cole, a Blue Cross spokesman.</p>
        <p>Spectrum said completely integrating the facilities would take another 5 to 10 years, given the complexity and cost of the undertaking. The system argues that its costs have remained basically flat, compared with annual increases of about 7 percent before.</p>
        <p>Here in Massachusetts, Mr. Reilly, the attorney general, has voiced his concern about the narrowing of competition in Springfield, where there are two big hospital systems, Baystate Health System and the Sisters of Providence. Because Baystate owns a popular health plan and is much stronger financially, there are concerns about the viability of its competitor. Baystate's plan does not contract with Sisters' major hospital, Mercy Medical Center, for most services.</p>
        <p>The possibility of Baystate's becoming the only large hospital system in Springfield poses a big problem, according to the attorney general, including the potential for significant increases in health care costs.</p>
        <p>''What we found in Springfield was that kind of roughshod competition was hurting access,'' said Mr. Reilly, who issued a report on the situation a year ago. While he did not recommend any action to the state legislature, which requested the review, he is monitoring the market and looking at other hospital systems in the state.</p>
        <p>''I think they know we're on the field, and we have seen the impact,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
