<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Markets Shaken as Economic Statistics Fan Inflation Fears</title>
    <meta content="Y29ECON" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1172187"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hershey, Robert D Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Savings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gross Domestic Product</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EFD8113CF93AA15752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Markets Shaken as Economic Statistics Fan Inflation Fears</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hershey, Robert D Jr</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commerce Department reports gross domestic product grew at blistering 5.8 percent annual rate in 1999 fourth quarter; reports personal savings as percentage of disposable income fell to 1.9 percent from 2.1 percent in preceding quarter; puts rate for all of 1999 at 2.4 percent; analysts, concerned about faster-than-expected economic growth, are also upset by inflation number, so-called GDP deflator, which jumped to 2 percent pace in autumn from 1.1 percent in summer; expect Federal Reserve to respond by raising interest rates; reports spur sharp drop in stock prices and roil bond market, which ends mostly higher (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The American economy grew at a blistering rate of 5.8 percent in the final quarter of last year as it closed in on the record for the longest expansion in United States history.</p>
        <p>But inflation also jumped during the quarter and this, along with more evidence of accelerating health costs, make it more certain that the Federal Reserve will raise short-term interest rates by at least a quarter of a percentage point when it meets next week, analysts said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The American economy grew at a blistering rate of 5.8 percent in the final quarter of last year as it closed in on the record for the longest expansion in United States history.</p>
        <p>But inflation also jumped during the quarter and this, along with more evidence of accelerating health costs, make it more certain that the Federal Reserve will raise short-term interest rates by at least a quarter of a percentage point when it meets next week, analysts said.</p>
        <p>The two government reports published today ''amount to the 'smoking gun' that the Fed has been warning would eventually appear,'' said David Orr, chief economist at First Union Bank. ''The key story is the uptick in inflation.''</p>
        <p>Stocks, which have been retreating for most of the year, were pummeled heavily throughout the day while the bond market gyrated wildly and finished mostly higher, pushing rates lower.</p>
        <p>Gross domestic product, the Commerce Department reported, grew at a blistering 5.8 percent annual pace during the quarter, just slightly higher than the summer's 5.7 percent but well ahead of the 5.2 percent that economists expected.</p>
        <p>Consumers, many of them holding large stock gains, spent freely; military and other federal outlays rose sharply; and there was a huge buildup in inventories that apparently reflected precautions against computer failure at the turn of the year.</p>
        <p>Spending on food, in fact, climbed 9.3 percent -- representing about one-quarter of the rise in consumer outlays -- as many households stocked up, fearing Year 2000 computer problems that proved largely unfounded.</p>
        <p>Business spending on equipment and software, on the other hand, grew more slowly as some companies took a breather after preparing for potential Year 2000 problems, while others deferred such spending until the new year, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Since many of the factors affecting the fourth quarter, including exceptionally favorable weather, are unlikely to be repeated, analysts say the economy is certain to cool off in the January-March period.</p>
        <p>But it is not at all clear that it will cool enough for the Fed to be able to avoid a series of rate increases as the economy in February sets a record for uninterrupted expansion, 107 months. This would surpass the 106 months of Vietnam-era prosperity from 1961 to 1969.</p>
        <p>Stan Shipley, senior economist at Merrill Lynch, said Alan Greenspan, the Fed's chairman, ''wants it south of 4 percent,'' referring to growth of the gross domestic product, on the assumption that inflation will break out if the economy keeps exceeding its speed limit. This is set by the sum of population growth, about 1 percent a year, and productivity growth, traditionally thought to be about 1 1/2 percent but now perhaps 2 1/2 percent to as much as 3 1/2 percent.</p>
        <p>This report also showed that the savings rate -- personal savings as a percentage of disposable income -- shriveled to 1.9 percent from 2.1 percent in the preceding quarter. The rate was 4.5 percent for 1997, 3.7 percent for 1998 and 2.4 percent for all of 1999.</p>
        <p>The inflation number that seemed to upset analysts the most today was the so-called G.D.P. deflator, which jumped to a 2 percent pace in the autumn from 1.1 percent in the summer. But others also advanced, including the price index for gross domestic purchases, up to 2.3 percent from 1.7 percent; without counting food and energy, this index accelerated to 2 percent from 1.2 percent.</p>
        <p>But economists also cited the Labor Department's Employment Cost Index, which showed today that while wages and salaries for civilian workers rose the same in the autumn as in the summer, 0.9 percent, the cost of fringe benefits accelerated to 1.3 percent from 0.8 percent.</p>
        <p>''The pickup in benefits apparently reflected increased retention bonuses as well as a continued uptrend in health insurance costs,'' said James F. O'Sullivan, an economist at J. P. Morgan. Wall Street's year-end bonuses, especially hefty for 1999, are expected to have their main impact in the next report.</p>
        <p>Pay and benefits of civilian workers advanced 3.4 percent last year, the same as in 1998, as consumer prices advanced 2.7 percent. Benefits include vacations, holidays, sick leave, overtime pay, shift differentials and bonuses, as well as health and life insurance, savings and pension payments and severance pay.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
