<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Film Financed by a Religious Group</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUNDANCE FILM FESTIVAL (PARK CITY, UTAH)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FESTIVALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GREGORY PRODUCTIONS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">PRIESTS OF THE SACRED HEART</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, CARYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BURSTYN, ELLEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">CARE OF THE SPITFIRE GRILL (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals/Sundance Film Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Film Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sundance Film Festival (Park City, Utah)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3D91739F930A35751C0A960958260" item-length="1432" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Film Financed by a Religious Group</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, CARYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Care of the Spitfire Grill" was the Cinderella story of this year's Sundance Film Festival in Park City, Utah. The tale of a young woman who brings spiritual redemption to a Maine town, the film won the festival's Audience Award for drama, making it the most popular movie at the festival.  It was bought by Castle Rock Entertainment, a major distributor, for $10 million, more than four  times as much as any previous film shown at Sundance.</p>
        <p>Only a handful of people at the festival, most of them executives who acquire films, were aware that this $6.1 million movie came from a most unusual source:  it was financed, produced and marketed by a new company, Gregory Productions, which is owned by a Roman Catholic order of priests, the Priests of the Sacred Heart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Care of the Spitfire Grill" was the Cinderella story of this year's Sundance Film Festival in Park City, Utah. The tale of a young woman who brings spiritual redemption to a Maine town, the film won the festival's Audience Award for drama, making it the most popular movie at the festival.  It was bought by Castle Rock Entertainment, a major distributor, for $10 million, more than four  times as much as any previous film shown at Sundance.</p>
        <p>Only a handful of people at the festival, most of them executives who acquire films, were aware that this $6.1 million movie came from a most unusual source:  it was financed, produced and marketed by a new company, Gregory Productions, which is owned by a Roman Catholic order of priests, the Priests of the Sacred Heart.</p>
        <p>Gregory is the for-profit arm of a nonprofit group based in Mississippi called the Sacred Heart League, which publishes religious books and videos. Roger Courts, the executive director of Gregory and director of the Sacred Heart League, said the new company had been founded to promote "Judeo-Christian values" and to "increase the outreach of the ministry" through movies.</p>
        <p>"Spitfire" is the company's first completed project, and Mr. Courts said proceeds from the movie would go to the Sacred Heart League's charitable works (which include AIDS counseling and health care for children) and to creating similar entertainment in the future.</p>
        <p>Some executives in Hollywood are uneasy about the church's connection with the film and what they see as Gregory's religious agenda, but because many companies bid on the film, even those who were troubled by the backers would not speak on the record.</p>
        <p>Martin Shafer, the president of Castle Rock (which was recently bought by Turner Broadcasting), said he had no problem with the acquisition. He said he had been unaware of Gregory's existence before he bought "Spitfire," after brief negotiations with Jonathan Dana, a consultant who was selling the film.</p>
        <p>"The whole thing happened in about six hours," Mr. Shafer said. "We saw the film at 2 in Los Angeles, and started negotiating. Before we closed the negotiations that evening, I asked Jonathan Dana, 'By the way, who are they?' He basically told me it was an organization that was an offshoot of the Sacred Heart League, a Catholic group that publishes Bibles and whose proceeds were intended to go to building schools and things like that. That didn't sound too bad to me."</p>
        <p>He added: "We are not affiliating ourselves with the company in any way on an ongoing basis. We are not going to make films that send any messages. If there were any clause in the contract, any suggestion by Gregory Productions that we promote their organization, we wouldn't have signed it. We're not promoting the  Sacred Heart League. We bought a movie and our job is to sell it as entertainment. We love the movie.  We're proud of it."</p>
        <p>It is extremely rare, though not unprecedented, for a religious group to have totally financed and produced a film that on the strength of the Castle Rock sale appears to have the potential for mainstream success. Paulist Pictures, which is owned by the Paulist order of priests, produced the small Raul Julia film "Romero," about the bishop of El Salvador, and the forthcoming biography "Dorothy Day," about the Catholic social reformer. But "Care of the Spitfire Grill" is in a different league. Castle Rock would have to make about $30 million at the box office to break even on its investment.</p>
        <p>Its makers say that the film, with Catholic backers, Protestant characters and a Jewish director, is not meant to promote any denomination. The movie stars Ellen Burstyn and Marcia Gay Harden.</p>
        <p>At Sundance, Gregory Productions neither hid its association with "Spitfire"  nor advertised it. Gregory's name was included in the film's press material and  mentioned in question-and-answer sessions after the screenings, but no mention was made of the company's ownership or spiritual purpose.</p>
        <p>Geoffrey Gilmore, the program director of the Sundance Film Festival, said he had not been aware of Gregory's religious affiliation before inviting the movie  to the festival. "I don't think anyone feels there's a hidden message behind the screen," he said. If Gregory had been more vocal about its background, he added, "That would have created preconceptions. Once you do that you marginalize the film."</p>
        <p>At least two potential buyers, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said they were uncomfortable because it appeared that Gregory had a religious agenda. Another executive who insisted on anonymity said that though Gregory's mission would not have prevented his company from acquiring the film, he saw a difference between the commercial and moral issues involved.</p>
        <p>"The origins of the financing are reflected in the ideology of the film," he  said. "If you know the context of the financing, an agenda does emerge in the film."</p>
        <p>Mr. Shafer of Castle Rock said, "If people say they were uncomfortable with this film, maybe it's an excuse because they didn't think it was commercial."</p>
        <p>In an interview at Sundance, the film's director, Lee David Zlotoff, said a friend had put him in touch with Mr. Courts, who was looking for projects for Gregory to produce. Mr. Zlotoff, a television director who created the action series "MacGyver," is Jewish, but said he agreed with the company's spiritual mission. He said he and his wife of 25 years and their four children were deeply religious.</p>
        <p>He was asked to come up with three concepts for Gregory, and the first one turned into "Care of the Spitfire Grill." Mr. Zlotoff said: "I told them if you  have any religious agenda, don't hire me. This was never intended to be a religious movie. There are biblical references, but there are also literary and  mythical references."</p>
        <p>Among the film's religious references is a scene in which a young woman just  released from prison is taken to meditate in an abandoned church. Another character laments, "If you want to go to church, you have to go all the way to Bethel."</p>
        <p>In October, three months before Sundance, Gregory invited major film distributors to Memphis, just over the state border from Gregory's Mississippi offices, to see the film. "As an enticement," Mr. Dana said, "we offered them a  trip to Graceland and a party." Representatives from 40 companies, including representatives from Miramax, Fine Line, Trimark and October, attended, Mr. Dana said. There was a screening for the distributors and Memphis residents at an old 2,500-seat theater.</p>
        <p>Those at the screening were given a brochure about the film, and in the back  was Gregory Productions' "mission statement," which explains the company's intentions to "persuasively move audiences" to appreciate "the values of the Judeo-Christian tradition, in particular, love of and reverence for God."</p>
        <p>"I was sitting in the theater when I read this statement of purpose and my jaw dropped," said Bingham Ray, a partner in October Films. "It sent a slight chill; that was the collective reaction."</p>
        <p>In the end, Mr. Ray said that he had decided "film financing is film financing" and that the movie's spiritual content could be a marketing asset.</p>
        <p>"If I were marketing it, I'd start in the middle of the country and create a  groundswell, using church groups," Mr. Ray said. His partners were not as enthusiastic about the film's commercial possibilities, he added, so October did not pursue it.</p>
        <p>Gregory had two offers for the film after the Memphis screening, from Fine Line Features and Trimark Pictures, but delayed making any deal until the soundtrack was changed. Gregory hired James Horner, a well-known Hollywood composer, to create a new score in time for Sundance. At screenings of the film in Park City and in nearby Provo, audiences wept, and bidding for the film  heated up.</p>
        <p>Trimark now insists it had a deal with Gregory for "Spitfire," and is suing the production company, Mr. Courts, Mr. Dana, Castle Rock and Turner Broadcasting for $20 million. If there are no legal obstacles, Castle Rock plans to release the film in the fall.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
