<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Parts Were Denied, Satellite Developer Charges</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="601974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECONNAISSANCE SATELLITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEFENSE CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">APPLIED MAGNETICS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NAKAMICHI CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MOUNTAIN OPTECH INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMPSON, BRUCE E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Defense Contracts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDE1439F937A25757C0A965958260" item-length="512" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Parts Were Denied, Satellite Developer Charges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER,</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Developers of the next generation of military reconnaissance satellites were denied access to computer parts they wanted to use because the manufacturer feared a military contract would jeopardize the company's chances of being sold to Japan, a Government contractor said today.</p>
        <p>Bruce E. Thompson, the chairman of Mountain Optech Inc., said his company had sought the components from a unit of the Applied Magnetics Corporation. The subsidiary, the Optical Products Division, was sold in late January to the Nakamichi Corporation of Tokyo.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Developers of the next generation of military reconnaissance satellites were denied access to computer parts they wanted to use because the manufacturer feared a military contract would jeopardize the company's chances of being sold to Japan, a Government contractor said today.</p>
        <p>Bruce E. Thompson, the chairman of Mountain Optech Inc., said his company had sought the components from a unit of the Applied Magnetics Corporation. The subsidiary, the Optical Products Division, was sold in late January to the Nakamichi Corporation of Tokyo.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for Applied Magnetics said the company had never had a policy of avoiding sales to the military. Optical Products makes top-of-the-line laser readers for laser disk drives, which resemble compact disk players and are used to store computer data. The Latest Twist in Saga</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson's comments are the latest odd twist in the sale to a Japanese company of the only United States producer of the disk-drive components that designers wanted for the satellites. The Defense Department also uses the laser disk-drive parts in Trident missiles and is testing them for inclusion in an upgraded version of the Patriot missile.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration approved the sale on Jan. 19 and it was completed later that month for an undisclosed price. But the Clinton Administration has been investigating the transaction to determine whether national security issues were overlooked or possibly misrepresented in the original decision. If so, the Administration can cancel the sale.</p>
        <p>American and foreign companies have been watching the case closely as a bellwether of the Clinton Administration's attitudes toward foreign investment.</p>
        <p>Companies with military contracts are hard to sell to foreign concerns, because the necessary reviews by the Federal Government are much more extensive. Mr. Thompson today accused the Applied Magnetics Corporation of refusing to discuss any military contract because Applied Magnetics was trying to sell its laser disk-drive division. No 'Glimmer' of a Buyer</p>
        <p>Raymond P. LeBlanc, the general counsel of Applied Magnetics, based in Goleta, Calif., said that the company had decided then to sell the division. But he denied that the company had instituted any policy to avoid defense contracts so as to permit a sale to a foreign company.</p>
        <p>"We didn't have a glimmer of a prospective buyer" at the time, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson said in an interview today that Applied Magnetics had refused to supply basic information about its laser disk-drive parts, after Mountain Optech revealed that it needed the information to determine whether the parts met certain military standards. As a result, Mountain Optech was forced to buy lower-quality Japanese components for a reconnaissance satellite development project.</p>
        <p>The Japanese components are not quite as fast and durable as the Applied Magnetics components, Mr. Thompson said. The laser disk drives would go aboard reconnaissance satellites and store images for transmittal later when the satellite passed over the United States.</p>
        <p>BUSINESS TECHNOLOGY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
