<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An auction at a fallen agency is a reminder of the industry's modern perils</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="602052"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUCTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEER DUBOIS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ELLIOTT, STUART</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ADVERTISING (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DB153AF937A25757C0A965958260" item-length="749" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An auction at a fallen agency is a reminder of the industry's modern perils</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ELLIOTT, STUART</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>GEER, DUBOIS died in February, but the funeral, such as it is, is being held this morning. The agency's office in the Flatiron neighborhood of lower Manhattan will reopen a final time to sell its few tangible assets.</p>
        <p>A public auction will offer computers, a telephone system and what a newspaper classified advertisement tersely called a "tremendous quantity very fine office furniture and equipment."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>GEER, DUBOIS died in February, but the funeral, such as it is, is being held this morning. The agency's office in the Flatiron neighborhood of lower Manhattan will reopen a final time to sell its few tangible assets.</p>
        <p>A public auction will offer computers, a telephone system and what a newspaper classified advertisement tersely called a "tremendous quantity very fine office furniture and equipment."</p>
        <p>The sale is expected to raise only a couple hundred thousand dollars toward the estimated $4 million to $5 million in debts left when the agency, known for stylishly creative campaigns for products including Baileys Original Irish Cream liqueur and Jaguar cars, abruptly collapsed two months ago, throwing 55 people out of work.</p>
        <p>The shop traced its history to a public relations agency founded by the owner Peter Geer's parents in 1935. But its sudden end more than half a century later offers a cautionary tale at a perilous time in the advertising industry.</p>
        <p>"It isn't just another agency that failed to make it," said Doria Steedman, an 18-year employee who left before top executives decided on liquidation. "It was special; we walked taller and were prouder."</p>
        <p>What crippled the agency, asserted Ms. Steedman, now an executive vice president at the Partnership for a Drug-Free America in New York, was that it "never moved from the 70's into the 90's" and failed to adapt to advertising's new realities. For instance, as Adweek noted in an article, "Death of an Agency," at a time when most agencies had cut back to staffing levels of one person for each $1 million in billings, Geer, DuBois at one point had 250 employees for its $120 million in billings.</p>
        <p>Stephen G. Bowen Jr., who joined the agency in March 1992 as president and chief executive, said that agencies can no longer fool themselves into believing "that if the numbers don't look strong, next year will be better than this year."</p>
        <p>"Frankly, the agency business in the last 30 years has been a go-go business," added Mr. Bowen, who is still thinking about what to do next in the wake of Geer, DuBois's closing. Given the industry's current "significant prolonged downturn," he continued, "if you have major account losses, you're dead -- and that's precisely what happened to Geer, DuBois."</p>
        <p>Two months before Mr. Bowen arrived at the agency, its second-largest client, Brown &amp; Williamson Tobacco, withdrew its estimated $30 million in billings. And not long after, Jaguar Cars Inc. took its estimated $20 million account to Ogilvy &amp; Mather New York. The final blow was struck by the Paddington Corporation, which markets Baileys and other spirits brands; its decision to consolidate accounts at two other agencies meant Geer, DuBois would lose its largest remaining client and $13 million to $15 million in billings.</p>
        <p>"The problems there were worse than I realized," Mr. Bowen said. "To keep the doors open without Paddington, I would have had to risk $2 million of personal money." So Mr. Geer and his lawyers decided to cease operations under a provision of New York State law known as an assignment for the benefit of creditors.</p>
        <p>"I never believed it would go under," said Rodney Underwood, chairman and creative director, adding that after he turned down "three separate opportunities" to join other agencies during the final year, a friend told him " 'You're either a saint or an idiot.' "</p>
        <p>"I don't think I was either one," Mr. Underwood continued, "but in the end I think I did the right thing." He and about 6 to 12 former Geer, DuBois colleagues are working out of an office at TBWA Advertising, completing work on campaigns for Geer, DuBois's last clients, which include the New York Zoological Society, the Northrop Corporation and Meridien Hotels.</p>
        <p>Jerold R. Ruderman, a lawyer in White Plains who was assigned by the New York State Supreme Court to handle the Geer, DuBois liquidation, said that the 750 to 1,000 claims that he expected creditors to file were "massively in excess of the amount of money we will be taking in."</p>
        <p>"It's kind of sad when you go down there," he added, referring to his visits to confer with Jackson Hecht Associates, the auctioneers preparing the former agency quarters on the 16th and 17th floors of 114 Fifth Avenue, between 16th and 17th Streets, for today's sale, which begins at 10:30 A.M.</p>
        <p>Ms. Steedman said that she was "toying with attending the auction."</p>
        <p>"Half of me wants to go and say goodbye," she added. "The other half says 'What the hell for?' "</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
