<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Jersey's Brain Drain</title>
    <meta content="lucent" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region; Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1753168"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lucent Technologies Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Alcatel Sa</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Corzine, Jon S (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DF1130F93AA35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="457" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Jersey's Brain Drain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial on plan by Lucent Technologies to merge with Paris-based Alcatel and expected loss of jobs; calls on New Jersey Gov Jon Corzine and his economic advisers to devise plan to develop new businesses and create new private-sector jobs</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With so much focus on Gov. Jon Corzine's bad-news budget and the state's perilous public finances, it is easy to forget that the private sector is not ordering much in the way of wine and roses these days, either.</p>
        <p>A recent survey by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation found that the state's economy remains in a rut, with job growth checking in at a measly 1 percent or so during the last quarter of 2005. Last week's announcement that Lucent Technologies, the maker of telecommunications equipment, will merge with Paris-based Alcatel will do nothing to rouse the state from its economic stupor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With so much focus on Gov. Jon Corzine's bad-news budget and the state's perilous public finances, it is easy to forget that the private sector is not ordering much in the way of wine and roses these days, either.</p>
        <p>A recent survey by the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation found that the state's economy remains in a rut, with job growth checking in at a measly 1 percent or so during the last quarter of 2005. Last week's announcement that Lucent Technologies, the maker of telecommunications equipment, will merge with Paris-based Alcatel will do nothing to rouse the state from its economic stupor.</p>
        <p>Lucent, based in the Union County community of Murray Hill, currently employs about 6,000 workers in New Jersey and about 30,000 worldwide. Alcatel has 58,000 workers around the world. The merged company, to be based in Paris, expects to shed nearly 9,000 jobs over the next two years.</p>
        <p>Nobody knows how many New Jerseyans will lose their jobs at Lucent, but the process will seem painfully familiar. Since spinning off from AT&amp;T in 1996, Lucent has eliminated thousands of local jobs. Corporate prosperity has not followed the cost-cutting: the company's stock price has fallen from $84 in 1999 to just over $3 today.</p>
        <p>A decade ago, New Jersey was quite literally the center of the nation's telecommunications industry. The state's largest private-sector employer was AT&amp;T. But times changed quickly and drastically, and AT&amp;T sold off its sprawling Basking Ridge campus in 2002. Its iconic bee's nest building became an empty, grim monument to the effects of corporate restructuring.</p>
        <p>There is little question that Lucent needed help to survive, and the merger may wind up saving jobs that would have been lost if Lucent had continued on its own. But still, the shock value of Lucent's fall from grace should not be lost on state policy makers. New Jersey might well brag about its affluence, median household income, high property values and educated work force, but only a fool would take any of this for granted.</p>
        <p>The state's much-abused treasury is hardly the only economic problem Mr. Corzine has inherited. He will have to deal with the state's vulnerabilities in industries like telecommunications and technology, once thought to be embedded in New Jersey's DNA. It is imperative that Mr. Corzine's new economic advisers come up with a plan to develop new businesses and create new private-sector jobs. Local communities, heavily dependent on property taxes, inevitably bear the brunt of corporate relocations. A smart statewide strategy will take this into consideration.</p>
        <p>Politicians once held out the promise that white-collar jobs were the ticket to economic stability. Thousands of New Jerseyans have found out otherwise, a trend that may be exacerbated by the latest news from Murray Hill.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
