<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HABITATS/West Village; Where Summer Arrives in a Single Day</title>
    <meta content="09habi" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/04/09/realestate/09habi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1753184"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="Habitats | West Village"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Habitats</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Furniture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E7DE1130F93AA35757C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HABITATS/West Village; Where Summer Arrives in a Single Day</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Summer Arrives in a Single Day</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELIA BARBOUR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE seasons change gradually in New York City, except in the home of Mitchell Motsinger and John Friedman. Here, summer arrives in a day, with celery and pink floral slipcovers for the living room banquette and a dozen contrasting covers for the throw pillows; a shower curtain in orange, turquoise and white stripes in the bath; and a change of linens in the kitchen and bedroom, too.</p>
        <p>Winter's appearance is equally abrupt, and there's a less extensive wardrobe change to mark the transitional months. Ms. Motsinger is a seamstress specializing in home décor (her business is called Sew and Sew), and she really cannot help herself. Even when she's under deadline to make, say, covers for 400 banquet chairs for the Sheraton, or a complete set of curtains for a weekend house, she can find herself tormented by a new vision for the 600-square-foot two-bedroom apartment in a West Village tenement that she shares with her husband, a dog, two cats and a bird.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Friedman, a lawyer, and Mitchell Motsinger, a seamstress, live and work in a West Village apartment. She also bakes, and they love to entertain, all in 600 square feet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE seasons change gradually in New York City, except in the home of Mitchell Motsinger and John Friedman. Here, summer arrives in a day, with celery and pink floral slipcovers for the living room banquette and a dozen contrasting covers for the throw pillows; a shower curtain in orange, turquoise and white stripes in the bath; and a change of linens in the kitchen and bedroom, too.</p>
        <p>Winter's appearance is equally abrupt, and there's a less extensive wardrobe change to mark the transitional months. Ms. Motsinger is a seamstress specializing in home décor (her business is called Sew and Sew), and she really cannot help herself. Even when she's under deadline to make, say, covers for 400 banquet chairs for the Sheraton, or a complete set of curtains for a weekend house, she can find herself tormented by a new vision for the 600-square-foot two-bedroom apartment in a West Village tenement that she shares with her husband, a dog, two cats and a bird.</p>
        <p>She doesn't always manage to shelve her impulses until there's a lull in her workload. ''It all depends on how many nights I lie awake,'' she said. ''When a vision gets in your head like that, you've got to purge it.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Motsinger, who is 49, grew up in Kansas City, Mo. She was, by her own account, something of a misfit. ''I wore grandma dresses -- you know the kind with those great buttons -- and old beaded sweaters,'' she said. ''Maybe that's why I didn't date anyone in high school.''</p>
        <p>''That's what's great about moving here,'' she said. ''You feel like, ahh, you finally fit in; you're not an oddity.'' She may have felt at home in New York, but the home she created for herself after she arrived hardly reflected the city's hip urban sensibilities. It was instead a relic from her childhood landscape, a Midwestern farmhouse shrunk to a tenth its normal size.</p>
        <p>She met Mr. Friedman in 1993, and he moved in shortly thereafter, despite some initial aesthetic misgivings. ''The apartment was very pink at the time,'' he said. Even the floors were painted pink, and the living room was paneled with lattice below the chair rail, giving it a kind of Mother Goose's garden feeling.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Friedman, who grew up in suburban Westchester, was sufficiently intrigued to stick around. ''Mitchell has this kind of 'Home, Sweet Home' core to her,'' he said. ''She amazes me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman had gravitated to this particular corner of the Village, where Cornelia Street meets West Fourth, since he was a child, as if he'd always known he'd live here. ''When I was 7 or 8, I remember lying in the back of my parents' station wagon and looking up at this building as we drove by,'' he said. ''I looked in through some windows and saw people talking and drinking. I thought it was so sophisticated and liberated.''</p>
        <p>Six hundred square feet isn't exactly a dream come true of liberated living space for a couple and their menagerie. And for Ms. Motsinger and Mr. Friedman, who married in 1996, the tiny apartment also doubles as office space.</p>
        <p>Ms. Motsinger has worked from home since the beginning, hauling bolts of fabric up the five flights of stairs and rolling it out on her worktable, which nearly fills the second bedroom.</p>
        <p>Four years ago, Mr. Friedman, a telecommunications lawyer and an adjunct professor at Hofstra University, also began working from home. His desk fits into one corner of the living room and his files, which are arranged in bright yellow accordion folders that he chose to match the bright yellow paint of the walls, line ceiling-high bookshelves.</p>
        <p>Despite the close quarters, Mr. Friedman likes the situation. ''I couldn't stand to go to an office in Midtown every day,'' he said. And given the high-tech nature of his field, it's not as if he needs a conference room. ''I'm on the phone a lot, and I do a lot of teleconferencing and videoconferencing,'' he said. ''And I'm I.M.-ing'' -- instant messaging -- ''all the time. My biggest client is in Arizona.''</p>
        <p>Unwritten rules keep the couple out of each other's hair. ''We're both pretty disciplined,'' Mr. Friedman said. ''We don't bother each other or listen in on each other's phone calls.'' Until midday, that is, when they set aside their work and meet for lunch at the painted-metal table in the kitchen.</p>
        <p>''I like having lunch with my wife,'' Mr. Friedman said. His coffee breaks are equally small-townish. ''I put the collar on the dog, go down to a cafe and hang out for a while,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Motsinger's farmhouse sensibility isn't confined to decorating. She's a committed gardener, with a window box on every sill. She also bakes on weekends: pies, tarts, cupcakes, cakes, cookies. ''Last weekend, I made a coconut cream pie,'' she said.</p>
        <p>And since there was too much for the two of them -- there always is -- she delivered a slice to a bachelor friend around the corner whose girlfriend can't cook, and the rest to the staff of a nearby restaurant. She embroiders ducks on towels for friends who have babies and sets of napkins at Christmastime for friends and family.</p>
        <p>And then there are the parties.</p>
        <p>Every Thanksgiving for more than a decade, Ms. Motsinger and Mr. Friedman gave parties that often included more than a dozen guests and lasted all day.</p>
        <p>''And then we started doing Easter brunch,'' Ms. Motsinger said. ''We'd do Jewish appetizers, gefilte fish, and we have a Seder plate. One year we did poached eggs for 15 people. Then we have egg decorating in my workroom. All the Jews are back there decorating eggs because they didn't get to do it. And I have little baskets to give people, with tulips in them.''</p>
        <p>''I'm an idiot,'' Ms. Motsinger said. ''I used to send 'Happy Spring' cards to my friends.''</p>
        <p>Her work, too, has an old-fashioned attentiveness to it. Rather than trucking a client's furniture off to a workroom, Ms. Motsinger comes by with tape measure and muslin, and sketches a pattern on the spot, as if she's fitting a dress.</p>
        <p>Over the years, she has visited some 400 houses and apartments in the New York City area in this fashion, from modernist lofts to town houses done up like chateaus.</p>
        <p>''I've seen the gamut,'' she said. ''Every apartment I see is different.''</p>
        <p>But few of them give her apartment envy. ''Some places you go into, and you have no idea who would live there. It doesn't say anything about the people.''</p>
        <p>A person walking into the apartment of Ms. Motsinger and Mr. Friedman, no matter the season, would not have that problem.</p>
        <p>Habitats | West Village</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
