<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. and Mexico Reach Accord Over Satellite TV Transmission</title>
    <meta content="09BIRD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="888567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mexico</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Communications Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hundt, Reed E (Chmn)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lozano Alarcon, Javier</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Satellites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1D7173BF93AA35752C1A960958260" item-length="494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. and Mexico Reach Accord Over Satellite TV Transmission</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mexico and United States jointly agree that two countries' 2,000-mile border should not be barrier to satellite tv transmission; FCC Chmn Reed E Hundt and Javier Lozano Alarcon, subsec of Mexican communications ministry, sign agreement that gives both countries broad access to each other's rapidly growing direct-to-home television markets (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mexico and the United States jointly agreed yesterday that at least when it comes to satellite television transmission, the 2,000-mile border between the two countries should not be a barrier. Yesterday afternoon in Washington, Reed E. Hundt, chairman of the Federal Communications Commission, and Javier Lozano Alarcon, subsecretary of the Mexican communications ministry, signed an agreement that gives both countries broad access to each other's rapidly growing direct-to-home television markets.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, Mexican satellite transmission companies will be able to send programs and advertising into the United States, signing up Spanish-speaking customers from California to Florida. At the same time, companies based in the United States will be allowed to legally service Mexican subscribers with English-language programming and commercials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mexico and the United States jointly agreed yesterday that at least when it comes to satellite television transmission, the 2,000-mile border between the two countries should not be a barrier. Yesterday afternoon in Washington, Reed E. Hundt, chairman of the Federal Communications Commission, and Javier Lozano Alarcon, subsecretary of the Mexican communications ministry, signed an agreement that gives both countries broad access to each other's rapidly growing direct-to-home television markets.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, Mexican satellite transmission companies will be able to send programs and advertising into the United States, signing up Spanish-speaking customers from California to Florida. At the same time, companies based in the United States will be allowed to legally service Mexican subscribers with English-language programming and commercials.</p>
        <p>Two multinational companies are already in place awaiting the cross-over agreement. They are Galaxy Latin America, which includes DirecTV in Los Angeles and Multivision in Mexico, and Sky Entertainment Services Latin America, in which Rupert Murdoch's News Corporation and the Mexican broadcasting giant Televisa participate.</p>
        <p>By the terms of the agreement signed yesterday, both the United States and Mexico will be able to place some restrictions on the content of what is beamed down from the satellites. But both countries agreed to limit the restrictions to ''a modicum,'' which one United States Government official explained as ''allowing some flexibility but not enough of a loophole to drive a truck through.'' In Washington, the satellite agreement with Mexico was presented as a model of how the United States is willing to give access to its market when such actions are matched by other countries.</p>
        <p>''This is consistent with the spirit of Nafta,'' Mr. Hundt said in a telephone interview from Washington. He referred to the North American Free Trade Agreement, a broad trade pact among the United States, Canada and Mexico.</p>
        <p>''It is a sign and symbol of our willingness to open our market when we see a corresponding country open its market,'' Mr. Hundt said.</p>
        <p>So far, the United States has been unable to reach a similar agreement on satellite television with Canada.</p>
        <p>Before yesterday's signing, Mexico debated the opening of its market in the Mexican Senate, with some legislators expressing old fears that giving the United States unhindered access would destroy any domestic competitors.</p>
        <p>''We understand that the agreement seeks to establish a level playing field but we have our doubts,'' the head of the Mexican National Cable Television Association told the Senate. ''The superiority of the United States will encourage the use of American technology much more than Mexican technology.''</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
