<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Elections in Britain Reveal A Scottish Line in the Sand</title>
    <meta content="02scotland" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/02/world/europe/02scotland.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1844478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Scotland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Wales</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cowell, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Macdonald, Iona</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Blair, Tony (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brown, Gordon (Chancellor of the Exchequer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Scotland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Wales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Referendums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Scotland</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Gordon</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F01E2DC103EF931A35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1116" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Elections in Britain Reveal A Scottish Line in the Sand</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Elections in Britain Reveal a Scottish Line in the Sand</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN COWELL; Iona Macdonald contributed reporting.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cowell, Alan; Macdonald, Iona</byline>
      <dateline>KIRKCALDY, Scotland, April 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Regional voting in Great Britain on May 3 will choose who dominates Scottish Parliament and Welsh Assembly, but is portrayed by contenders as referendum on Prime Min Tony Blair's tenure and prologue to Gordon Brown's expected ascendency as well as beginning of Scottish independence move; critics say Scotland move toward independence would inspire economic chaos and constitutional crisis, but advocates say it would propel Scotland to bright future, as viable as any other small European state; photos, map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gordon Brown, Britain's presumed prime minister-to-be, is usually associated with a somewhat dour manner and a mastery of statistics. But here, he displays other skills -- a bolt-on smile and a ready handshake to work sparse crowds between the discount stores on the High Street, asking parents with strollers whether their new babies are keeping them awake at night, and inquiring whether the men support the local Raith Rovers soccer team.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown was raised in Kirkcaldy, but not everyone is persuaded by his chummy display, coming, as it does, just days before an election.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Scottish Nationalist Party, which is poised to become the biggest party in the Scottish Assembly, has promised a referendum on seeking independence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gordon Brown, Britain's presumed prime minister-to-be, is usually associated with a somewhat dour manner and a mastery of statistics. But here, he displays other skills -- a bolt-on smile and a ready handshake to work sparse crowds between the discount stores on the High Street, asking parents with strollers whether their new babies are keeping them awake at night, and inquiring whether the men support the local Raith Rovers soccer team.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown was raised in Kirkcaldy, but not everyone is persuaded by his chummy display, coming, as it does, just days before an election.</p>
        <p>''Mr. Brown is taking all the money for his taxes,'' said Samuel Watters, a 71-year-old retired scaffolder. Mr. Watters met Mr. Brown, smiled and shook hands with him, then told a reporter that he would never vote for him.</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Watters' wife, Janet, 69, who said she would vote for Mr. Brown's Labor party, said the party has become complacent after 50 years of dominance in Scottish politics and ''needs a fright.''</p>
        <p>It might be about to get one.</p>
        <p>The voting on Thursday is a tangle of regional ballots across Britain that on one level will simply choose who dominates the Scottish Parliament and Welsh Assembly, along with many local councils in England.</p>
        <p>But it is portrayed by its contenders as much more -- a final verdict on Prime Minister Tony Blair's decade in office, a prologue to Mr. Brown's expected ascendancy to the premiership and the beginnings of moves to prise Scotland away from the 300-year-old union with the United Kingdom.</p>
        <p>''This is a big choice on Thursday, between those who want to break up Britain and those who want to build up Scotland,'' Mr. Brown, currently Britain's chancellor of the exchequer, told students at Adam Smith College, named for the 18th-century economist who was born here.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the contest is a battle between the Scottish Labor Party and the Scottish Nationalist Party, once seen as a fringe party but now tipped by many political analysts and pollsters to become the biggest single party in the 129-seat Scottish Assembly. The Scottish Nationalists have promised a referendum among Scotland's five million people on seeking independence -- a move that critics say would inspire economic chaos and constitutional crisis.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, who is not standing in these elections, came to town, alongside the choppy waters of the Firth of Forth, to support the Scottish Labor campaign and resist the nationalists.</p>
        <p>''I do not think the Scottish people want to see the breakup of the union'' that makes up Britain, he said here in Kirkcaldy (pronounced kerr-CUDDY).</p>
        <p>But advocates of independence say it would propel Scotland to a bright future, as viable as any other small European state.</p>
        <p>''I think we can stand on our own two feet quite willingly,'' said Fay Massey, a 57-year-old baker who plans to vote Scottish Nationalist. ''I think we'd do quite well by ourselves.''</p>
        <p>The debate draws on deep tribal passions and a history of mutual animosity and suspicion that date from even before May 1, 1707, the day Scotland and England were formally united. Indeed, Mr. Brown's own heritage as a Scot who rose to high office in Britain has left him vulnerable to both English taunts that he represents narrow Scottish interests and Scottish taunts that he does not represent the land of his birth.</p>
        <p>''He's for England and nobody else,'' said Morven Woods, 38, a pet shop worker on the High Street, who has voted Labor in the past but is now considering not voting at all. ''It's just disappointing; everybody promises the earth and then they don't deliver.'' Under a longstanding and oft-postponed deal with Mr. Blair, Mr. Brown is set to become Britain's prime minister when Mr. Blair steps down in the next few weeks. (The regional and local vote on Thursday does not affect this arrangement, because it will not alter the lineup in the British Parliament in London.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown has sought to overcome the distinctions of identity by advocating a notion of Britishness that embraces values that he learned as the son of a Presbyterian pastor, and which he defines to include fairness, honesty and decency.</p>
        <p>It does not persuade all the people on the High Street. ''I think there should be somebody else,'' Brian Brown, a 42-year-old window cleaner and Labor supporter, said of Mr. Brown. ''I don't think he'll make a very good prime minister. I just feel he wouldn't be right for Scotland.''</p>
        <p>Most pollsters, political analysts and politicians themselves seem to be expecting the same result from the complicated voting system on Thursday: the Nationalists dominating, Labor coming in second, and the Liberal Democrats emerging as the kingmaker.</p>
        <p>The outlook is for a Nationalist coalition with Liberal Democrats who are opposed to the idea of Scotland separating from Britain. According to many opinion surveys cited by political analysts, only about one-quarter of Scots favor out-right independence, but a much higher percentage of the population favors greater autonomy.</p>
        <p>At present, Scotland receives roughly $22 billion more from the central coffers in London than it contributes, but that calculation does not include revenue going to London from Scotland's large share of North Sea oil. Nationalists want that money to go to Scotland.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown argues that Scottish independence would create a huge tax burden for Scots, amounting to $10,000 extra every year for every taxpayer; the Nationalist leader, Alex Salmond, says the deficit would be offset by oil money.</p>
        <p>Setbacks for Labor in the Scottish vote are likely to be compounded elsewhere -- unless there are upsets -- by poor showings for Labor in the voting for the Welsh Assembly for local councils in England. If that is the case, Mr. Blair's 10 years in office, starting with a landslide election victory on May 1, 1997, will end with a broad protest vote against the way he has run the country.</p>
        <p>That could give a boost to the Conservative opposition, led by David Cameron, who also campaigned in Scotland on Monday. The Times of London reported that he paused before a bronze relief map of Glasgow, where Conservatives have long been unpopular, and proclaimed, ''All this can be ours.''</p>
        <p>If Labor does poorly, Mr. Brown would take office as prime minister against an embarrassing backdrop of electoral setbacks, possibly alleviated by a surge in Labor's popularity when Mr. Blair steps down.</p>
        <p>But some politicians argue that the blame for Labor's expected decline should not be placed exclusively at Mr. Blair's door.</p>
        <p>''We took the accolades together,'' John Reid, the home secretary, said in a television interview on Sunday. ''We now must take responsibility together if we are declining at the polls.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
