<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crime</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="764025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">EDGE OF THE CRAZIES, THE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">THIN AIR (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GRAVE MUSIC (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PREJUDICIAL ERROR (BOOK)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SHORT MONEY (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950521T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE6D7103FF932A15756C0A963958260" item-length="1138" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crime</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marilyn Stasio</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Big town, small town, crime taints them both. But in a little twerp of a town like Blue Deer, Mont. -- population 3,872, altitude 4,500 feet, hunkered down between the Crazy Mountains and the Absaroka Range of the Rockies -- every felony is a blot on the landscape. Or, as Jamie Harrison would have it in her sparkling, caustic first novel, THE EDGE OF THE CRAZIES (Hyperion, $20.95), crime is "made crueler by a pastoral setting, by the violent who were oblivious to beauty."</p>
        <p>It's lucky for the local populace that Jules Clement, native son and county sheriff, is tolerant of barmy people and lunatic behavior, because "Blue Deer had always boasted a high ratio of insanity." Someone carries out that boast by taking potshots at George Blackwater, a successful screenwriter and shameless philanderer who is married to a rabid tirebiter named Mona. ("A tirebiter is a large, usually unfriendly female.") George survives to write again; but before Jules can narrow down the suspect list, someone knocks off nutty Mona.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Big town, small town, crime taints them both. But in a little twerp of a town like Blue Deer, Mont. -- population 3,872, altitude 4,500 feet, hunkered down between the Crazy Mountains and the Absaroka Range of the Rockies -- every felony is a blot on the landscape. Or, as Jamie Harrison would have it in her sparkling, caustic first novel, THE EDGE OF THE CRAZIES (Hyperion, $20.95), crime is "made crueler by a pastoral setting, by the violent who were oblivious to beauty."</p>
        <p>It's lucky for the local populace that Jules Clement, native son and county sheriff, is tolerant of barmy people and lunatic behavior, because "Blue Deer had always boasted a high ratio of insanity." Someone carries out that boast by taking potshots at George Blackwater, a successful screenwriter and shameless philanderer who is married to a rabid tirebiter named Mona. ("A tirebiter is a large, usually unfriendly female.") George survives to write again; but before Jules can narrow down the suspect list, someone knocks off nutty Mona.</p>
        <p>In this madly original debut, Ms. Harrison speaks up in a fresh, animated voice to say something worth saying about the festering animosities of small minds cooped up in small towns. Her humor may be off the wall -- more at home in Twin Peaks than Cicely, Alaska -- but anything less weird wouldn't do justice to a hell-raising place like Blue Deer.</p>
        <p>She picks at her food; he teases her about it. He drops literary allusions; she calls him on them. They have frequent, playful sex, and they call the dog "the baby." He's Spenser, Robert B. Parker's perdurable Boston private eye; she's Susan the shrink, lady fair to his knight-errant; and we, we're just hanging around waiting for THIN AIR (Putnam, $21.95) to get off the ground.</p>
        <p>Lost it? Not Mr. Parker. When he forgets to be cute, he can still create characters who live and dialogue that talks. This honest style surfaces in a veteran police detective's description of his young wife, who he fears has been kidnapped. "She wasn't, isn't, like anyone else," he says. "She was all there in the right-now, you know? She was everything she was, all the time." Spenser finds the lady, who turns out to be shady, in a depressed mill town abandoned to packs of feral dogs and vicious gangs. And in this Godforsaken place he meets a sad, defeated priest whose struggle to perform a brave deed is an act of heroism and another example of honorable writing.</p>
        <p>The action gets going when Spenser acquires Chollo, a Mexican bone crusher whose lethal grace and acid humor peg him as a Hawk clone. But there's not much flesh on the story, and a gratuitous trip to California deflects Spenser from digging into the town and its troubles. Instead, he takes the easier route of kicking a few bricks and walking away from the rubble.</p>
        <p>Inspector Bill Slider's wife has left him, his own true love is playing coy, and he's in Dutch with the brass at the Shepherd's Bush police station. When GRAVE MUSIC (Scribner, $20) opens, Cynthia Harrod-Eagles's beleaguered English copper could not be in a better mood for a Mahler concert. But before Slider can lose himself in wild torrents of music, the conductor is gunned down at the podium.</p>
        <p>In the course of grilling the maestro's kin, the inspector discovers that the publicly revered genius was in private a "rude, unpleasant, arrogant" tyrant whose dirty habits drew him to places like the Ootsy Tootsy Club. Given his revolting character, it's a real effort to give a fig who killed the old goat, especially when the prime candidates, a shifty son-in-law and a parasitic grandson among them, are almost as unlovable as the unlamented victim.</p>
        <p>Having written herself into a corner, Ms. Harrod-Eagles redeems herself with her methodical plot construction and sympathetic hero. Although Slider's estrangement from his beloved Joanna (fourth violinist in the accursed orchestra) seems contrived, it gives him a good excuse to examine his conscience. Rattling around in his empty house, missing his children and thinking brown thoughts, he makes you want to steer him away from sharp cutlery and Mahler.</p>
        <p>"Of all the legal controversies decided in American courts of law," Bill Blum writes in his first novel, PREJUDICIAL ERROR (Dutton, $21.95), "none compared with a death penalty trial for procedural complexity, cutthroat advocacy and sheer emotional wallop." Too true -- which is why one is advised to turn to page 91 of this courtroom drama and commence reading.</p>
        <p>While not quite so thrilling as Mr. Blum, a Los Angeles administrative law judge, would like to think, the courtroom procedures have a nice, nasty snap to them. "Deciding where to stand while examining a witness is an art in itself," says John Phillip Solomon, a disgraced lawyer who gets a new lease on his career when he defends a cop killer. Although the down-at-the-heels attorney proves he has not forgotten where to stand, there is a problem with his case: it's dull. There is also a problem with the characters: they're dull too. But Solomon knows his onions, and it's a treat to watch him baiting witnesses, baring his teeth at colleagues he loathes, laying traps during cross-examination and generally having himself a high old time.</p>
        <p>But what, then, of those first 90 pages? (The count goes up if you skip all the other sections that mull over Solomon's past history and current angst.) Keep your seat in the courtroom and you'll never miss them.</p>
        <p>Pete Hautman has written 27 children's books, which seems logical because SHORT MONEY (Simon &amp; Schuster, $21) is a comic bedtime story for grown-up kids with perverse tastes in crime fiction. A prequel to the author's inspired debut novel, "Drawing Dead," this new caper finds Joe Crow tossed out by his wife, booted off the Big River police force and trying to get through a Minnesota winter without booze or cocaine. The humbled hero is reduced to playing bodyguard for Dr. Nelson Bellweather, possible child molester and known practitioner of liposuction, who is being stalked by the redneck clan that runs a hunting preserve. Zebras, elk, bison, 600-pound Bengal tigers -- if you want to mow it down, these boys will lead you right up to the barrel and hand you the MAC-10.</p>
        <p>The plot makes more sense than it has a right to, once you accept its screwy conventions. (Everybody is related to everybody else, and outsiders are poker buddies.) But why read for sense when you can read for fun? There's plenty of that in the loony-bird characters and in their backcountry dialogue, which reads as if the speakers were scratching themselves during discourse. Crow picks up one choice specimen at a Cocaine Anonymous meeting, where the habitues are a lot "darker, funnier, faster and more colorful" than the "gloomy and sluggish" folks at A.A. A day on the hunt will do them all a world of good.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
