<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Teen-Ager Accused of Killing 8-Month-Old Cousin in Queens</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="779624"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, RENDELL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHIELDS, KEHIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950802T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2D6143BF931A3575BC0A963958260" item-length="658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Teen-Ager Accused of Killing 8-Month-Old Cousin in Queens</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Far Rockaway teen-ager who the authorities said had a history of psychiatric problems was charged yesterday with killing his 8-month-old cousin while baby-sitting the child.</p>
        <p>The teen-ager, Rendell Williams, used the handle of a bullwhip to beat the baby, Kehia Shields, because she would not stop screaming, and then tried to stifle her cries by placing his hands, then a pillow, over her tiny face, the authorities said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Far Rockaway teen-ager who the authorities said had a history of psychiatric problems was charged yesterday with killing his 8-month-old cousin while baby-sitting the child.</p>
        <p>The teen-ager, Rendell Williams, used the handle of a bullwhip to beat the baby, Kehia Shields, because she would not stop screaming, and then tried to stifle her cries by placing his hands, then a pillow, over her tiny face, the authorities said.</p>
        <p>The badly bruised child was later found unconscious in her crib by Mr. Williams's mother, Beverly Williams, when she returned from work, the police said. The infant was taken to St. John's Hospital, where she was pronounced dead.</p>
        <p>The teen-ager, according to law-enforcement officials who spoke on the condition of anonymity, has a history of mental illness, for which he had been taking medication until recently, and had tried more than once to commit suicide. They said he was arrested and charged with the killing after he told the police he had hit the child to quiet her.</p>
        <p>Richard A. Brown, the Queens District Attorney, said Mr. Williams was charged as a juvenile with second-degree murder, first- and second-degree manslaughter and criminal possession of a weapon. He could face nine years to life in prison if convicted, Mr. Brown said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams was arraigned last night in Queens Criminal Court in Kew Gardens.</p>
        <p>When Mrs. Williams went from the apartment to work on Monday morning, the police said, she left her two sons, Rendell, 15, and Carlen, 18, to watch Kehia. The police said Mr. Williams told them that he was playing with the infant at about 2 P.M. when she started to cry. To quiet her, they said, he began to hit the child -- with a nail file, the handle of a bullwhip and his fists. The child continued to cry over the next three hours, the police said, and Mr. Williams finally placed his hands over the infant's mouth and then reached for a pillow.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Williams noticed the child was unconscious, he tried briefly to revive her but failed, the police said. He then left her in the crib and waited for his mother to return. The police said that he made no attempt to call for help and that it was his mother who called 911 when she came home two hours later.</p>
        <p>Lieut. Robert W. Schruhl of the 101st Detective Squad said two police officers from the 101st Precinct and emergency workers who arrived at the apartment also tried unsuccessfully to revive the child.</p>
        <p>Kehia Shields's death is the third in recent days in New York City to be linked to child abuse or neglect. A Brooklyn woman, Sara Munoz, was charged last Wednesday with murder in the beating death of her 3-year-old daughter, Gabriella. Her husband, Gilberto Vasquez, was charged with endangering the welfare of a child, the police said, because Gabriella had been abused for some time and he had known about it.</p>
        <p>And a 1-year-old boy in Brownsville, Brooklyn, Dy'kqim Edmundson, died on July 24 from burns on his legs, arms and back, suffered when he was dipped into scalding bath water. His mother, her boyfriend and her boyfriend's mother were questioned in the death, which has been ruled a homicide.</p>
        <p>In Queens, the police said there was no evidence that Kehia had been abused before.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Williams, who spoke from behind the door of her sixth-floor apartment at the Wavecrest Gardens complex on Seagirt Boulevard, said she did not want to speak to reporters.</p>
        <p>The police said Mrs. Williams had just won custody of Kehia, her sister's child, a month ago but had cared for the infant almost since her birth. The police said the child's mother was in jail. Mrs. Williams lived in the home with Kehia and her two sons.</p>
        <p>Rendell's brother, Carlen, who the authorities said was in an adjoining bedroom playing video games during the time of the beating, is being questioned by the police as a witness.</p>
        <p>Of Mrs. Williams, Lieutenant Schruhl said: "She's lost a baby and now her son's in jail. It's a double tragedy."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
