<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cornmeal's Felicitous Knack for Adding Texture and Flavor</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="804883"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE6DF123AF93AA15753C1A963958260" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cornmeal's Felicitous Knack for Adding Texture and Flavor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LOCAL sweet corn is now a memory. Nonetheless, corn continues to offer culinary pleasures. But until next July, cornmeal prevails.</p>
        <p>In the form of polenta or grits, golden or white, cornmeal can be the sustaining starch of a meal, a sumptuous underpinning for a good gravy or counterpoint to spicy sausages. And given its felicitous knack for adding a touch of texture and flavor, it can improve an array of treats, from pie crust to pancakes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LOCAL sweet corn is now a memory. Nonetheless, corn continues to offer culinary pleasures. But until next July, cornmeal prevails.</p>
        <p>In the form of polenta or grits, golden or white, cornmeal can be the sustaining starch of a meal, a sumptuous underpinning for a good gravy or counterpoint to spicy sausages. And given its felicitous knack for adding a touch of texture and flavor, it can improve an array of treats, from pie crust to pancakes.</p>
        <p>Here are several such preparations in which a portion of cornmeal enhances character and savor. For best results, use stone-ground cornmeal. Sweet Cornmeal Cranberry Scones Total time: 35 minutes  1 1/3cups all-purpose flour, plus flour for work surface  1/2cup yellow cornmeal, preferably stone ground  4teaspoons baking powder  Pinch of salt  3tablespoons granulated sugar  1/2cup cold unsalted butter, in pieces  1/2cup chopped dried cranberries  1large egg, lightly beaten  1/2cup buttermilk  Preserves and creme fraiche (optional).</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 450 degrees. Adjust rack to upper third of the oven.</p>
        <p>2. Mix the flour, cornmeal, baking powder, salt and sugar in a food processor and process to blend. Add the butter and pulse until you have a uniformly crumbly mixture. Transfer it to a bowl. Lightly toss in the dried cranberries.</p>
        <p>3. Lightly stir in the egg and buttermilk, using a fork or your fingertips. The ingredients should be moistened just enough so they come together to form a ball of soft dough.</p>
        <p>4. Pat the dough on a lightly floured board to a thickness of half an inch. Cut it in two-and-a-half-inch rounds. Gently reform any scraps and cut a few additional rounds.</p>
        <p>5. Put rounds on foil-covered baking sheets and bake until the biscuits are beginning to brown on top, about 15 minutes. Remove from the oven, allow to cool briefly, then serve, or cool completely and warm just before serving. If desired, serve with good preserves and creme fraiche.</p>
        <p>Yield: about 16 scones. Cornmeal Pancakes Total time: 1 hour  1cup all-purpose flour  1/2cup white cornmeal, preferably stone ground  1/2teaspoon baking powder  1tablespoon sugar  Pinch of salt  1egg  2tablespoons melted butter  1cup milk  Soft butter for greasing skillet or griddle and for serving  Warm maple syrup.</p>
        <p>1. Mix flour, cornmeal, baking powder, sugar and salt in a bowl.</p>
        <p>2. Beat the egg with the melted butter and milk. Stir into the dry ingredients. The batter should not be perfectly smooth.</p>
        <p>3. Heat a griddle or skillet and brush with butter. Drop a generous tablespoon of the batter into the pan, cook over medium heat until lightly browned, turn and brown the other side. If this first pancake turns out well, put it on a warm serving platter. But often, the first pancake serves to season the pan and does not brown evenly. It is best discarded before getting on with cooking the rest. Brush more butter on the griddle or skillet as needed.</p>
        <p>4. Serve the pancakes with butter and maple syrup.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings. Cornmeal Brioche Total time: 5 hours, plus cooling  1package active dry yeast  1/3cup heavy cream, warmed  1/3cup yellow corn meal, preferably stone ground  1/2cup sugar  2 1/2sticks soft unsalted butter, plus butter for bowl and pans  6large eggs  2teaspoons salt  5cups all-purpose flour (approximately).</p>
        <p>1. Dissolve the yeast in the warm cream in a bowl. Set aside until it becomes frothy, about 10 minutes, then stir in the cornmeal. Cover and set aside for 30 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. Beat the sugar and butter until fluffy, then beat in the eggs one at a time. Stir in the cornmeal mixture and salt.</p>
        <p>3. Beat in the flour half a cup at a time to form a soft, elastic dough. Knead the dough about eight minutes by hand on a floured board or by machine. Transfer the dough to a clean, lightly buttered bowl, cover and set aside to rise until doubled, about two hours.</p>
        <p>4. Punch the dough down, divide it in half and form each half into a rectangle about 9 by 12 inches. Roll and shape into two oblong loaves 9 inches long.</p>
        <p>5. Butter two 9-by-5-by-3-inch loaf pans, put the rolls of dough in each pan, seam side down. Allow to rise until doubled, about an hour and a half.</p>
        <p>6. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Bake the loaves about 40 minutes, until browned. Cool completely before slicing.</p>
        <p>Yield: 2 loaves.  FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
