<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Medical Centers May Lease City Hospitals</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="804688"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MEDICINE AND HEALTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOSPITALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK UNIVERSITY MEDICAL CENTER</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MAIMONIDES MEDICAL CENTER(NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MOUNT SINAI MEDICAL CENTER (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CONEY ISLAND HOSPITAL</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ELMHURST HOSPITAL CENTER</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">QUEENS HOSPITAL CENTER</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TOY, VIVIAN S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD71F39F93AA15753C1A963958260" item-length="703" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Medical Centers May Lease City Hospitals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIVIAN S. TOY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TOY, VIVIAN S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At least three area hospitals seeking to expand their health-care networks are expressing interest in plans to lease three city hospitals, lured by their locations, the mix of patients and the kinds of services each provides.</p>
        <p>Officials at New York University Medical Center and Maimonides Medical Center both say they are exploring a lease of Coney Island Hospital in Brooklyn, while  officials at Mount Sinai Medical Center say they plan to consider leases with Elmhurst Hospital Center and Queens Hospital Center in Jamaica.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At least three area hospitals seeking to expand their health-care networks are expressing interest in plans to lease three city hospitals, lured by their locations, the mix of patients and the kinds of services each provides.</p>
        <p>Officials at New York University Medical Center and Maimonides Medical Center both say they are exploring a lease of Coney Island Hospital in Brooklyn, while  officials at Mount Sinai Medical Center say they plan to consider leases with Elmhurst Hospital Center and Queens Hospital Center in Jamaica.</p>
        <p>While threatened cuts in Medicare and Medicaid could make each hospital less attractive financially, hospital officials said the city hospitals could give access to new territories and new revenues.</p>
        <p>The Giuliani administration released two detailed plans last week, one for Coney Island Hospital and one for both Elmhurst Hospital and Queens Hospital, offering long-term leases on the hospitals to nonprofit companies, provided they meet the city's requirements for delivering health care to the poor.</p>
        <p>James R. Tallon, the president of the United Hospital Fund, a research and philanthropic group, said a number of New York hospitals seeking to build their  networks across borough boundaries, specifically in Brooklyn or Queens, were sure to test the leasing waters.</p>
        <p>"By definition, networks need to operate on a city or regionwide basis," he said.</p>
        <p>Kenneth E. Raske, the president of the Greater New York Hospital Association, agreed. "There have been rumors that a number of institutions have been interested," he said. "And there'll be at least a couple of candidates for both  deals."</p>
        <p>Given the Federal and local push to make the hospital industry a more market-driven system, hospital administrators have been exploring opportunities  to expand, said Frederick D. Alley, the president of the Brooklyn Hospital Center.</p>
        <p>"Conceptually, a hospital would have to be crazy not to consider coming into  the market," he said. "The Mayor's offer to allow those hospitals to go into nonprofit systems is right on target."</p>
        <p>Mr. Alley said his hospital would be extremely interested in leasing Coney Island Hospital, but it lacked the capital to make a serious bid.</p>
        <p>"Therefore, we have to look to our partners to demonstrate an interest," he said, noting that Brooklyn Hospital is affiliated with the New York University Medical Center. "As we build a system together, we would logically be interested in studying municipal facilities."</p>
        <p>Martin S. Begun, a vice president at New York University Medical Center, said a lease of Coney Island Hospital, recognized as the most appealing of the three  hospitals on the block, would be carefully considered. "That's a natural arena for Brooklyn Hospital and for us," he said. "We have a history of attracting a lot of patients from that geography."</p>
        <p>Officials at Maimonides Medical Center in Brooklyn also said they planned to  explore the possibility of leasing Coney Island Hospital. "It's our neck of the  woods," said Stanley Brezenoff, the president of Maimonides. "And we are not foreclosing any options at this point."</p>
        <p>He added, however, that meeting the city's requirements for providing care to the uninsured, as well as dealing with labor contracts, would complicate the deals.</p>
        <p>In addition to those broad issues, the Queens hospitals face additional hurdles because of their combined lease offering and because the city has required that a new Queens Hospital Center be built to replace the aging facility.</p>
        <p>Officials at Mount Sinai Medical Center, a natural candidate for the Queens lease because it is already affiliated with both hospitals, remained noncommittal, but said they would consider the offer.</p>
        <p>A statement from Mount Sinai noted that it has worked with Elmhurst Hospital  Center for more than 30 years and began a similar relationship with Queens Hospital Center at the city's request in 1992. In its statement, Mount Sinai took credit for recent improvements in quality and efficiency at Queens Hospital Center, "despite the constraints imposed by the hospital's inadequate, antiquated physical plant."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
