<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONNECTICUT GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="805089"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0DA143EF93AA15753C1A963958260" item-length="1379" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONNECTICUT GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONNECTICUT FORUM</p>
        <p>The Connecticut Forum season starts off on Thursday at 8 P.M. with "90 Minutes With '60 Minutes,' " presenting Lesley Stahl, Andy Rooney and Morley Safer under the moderation of Colin McEnroe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONNECTICUT FORUM</p>
        <p>The Connecticut Forum season starts off on Thursday at 8 P.M. with "90 Minutes With '60 Minutes,' " presenting Lesley Stahl, Andy Rooney and Morley Safer under the moderation of Colin McEnroe.</p>
        <p>The forum's format allows the audience to get up close and personal with the panelists -- "to peel away the layers of personage that make celebrity personalities seem omniscient, in order to intersect their personal stories with those of the audience members," according to forum publicity.</p>
        <p>Three additional forums will be held at The Bushnell in Hartford through May. Tickets cost $25 to $45 per program and subscriptions are $80 to $160. The number for more information is 241-2090.  GUITARS AND ALL</p>
        <p>A Guitar Extravaganza at Yale on Saturday will cover guitar playing, teaching, composing and history, geared toward everyone from professionals to teachers and students from high school to adult level.</p>
        <p>At the event, organized by Benjamin Verdery, professor of guitar at the Yale School of Music, there will be sessions on pedagogy, arranging, amplifying, choosing an instrument, composing for the classical guitar and a master class with Aldo Parisot on interpreting Villa-Lobos. Among the experts who will be conducting the panels and workshops are Roberto Sierra, Douglas Ching, Chris Carrington, Lars Frandsen, Michael Lorimer and Nathanial Guno.</p>
        <p>A related exhibition of Segovia manuscripts, a 1590's lute manuscript from England, original manuscripts of Yale composers and various guitar and lute treatises from 17th- and 18th-century France will be on display at the Yale Music Library in Sprague Memorial Hall, 470 College Street. In addition, the Yale Collection of Musical Instruments will be open for viewing of its guitars, lutes and similar instruments. The collection is housed at 15 Hillhouse Avenue.</p>
        <p>Included in the $30 registration fee ($25 for students and members of the Connecticut Classical Guitar Society) are concerts by Ignacio Rhodes at 5:15 P.M. and the Gray/Pearl Duo at 8 P.M., in Sprague Hall. Admission to each concert for non-registrants will be $10, students $5.</p>
        <p>Free concerts for extravaganza participants will be presented by the Staten Island Suzuki Student Ensemble and the New World Trio, plus several individual artists under the New Music from Yale banner.</p>
        <p>For more information or ticket reservations, call 432-4158. DICKENS CHRISTMAS</p>
        <p>Farmington's 12th annual Dickens of a Christmas, sponsored by the Friends of the Farmington Library and the Stanley-Whitman House Museum, will usher in the holiday season from Friday through next Sunday, 11 A.M. to 3 P.M., with house tours, a gift boutique and a Teddy Bear Tea.</p>
        <p>Three historic houses on Main Street, dating from 1740 to 1815, may be seen daily from 11 A.M. to 3 P.M for an admission charge of $10 in advance, $12 on tour days. Visitors are requested to wear low heels to avoid gouging the antique floor boards.</p>
        <p>A preview party on Thursday from 7 P.M. to 9:30 P.M. at the Village Branch Library, 71 Main Street, costs $20 and includes a house tour, first dibs on the contents of the boutique, and an array of hors d'oeuvres and wine.</p>
        <p>Box lunches will be available daily from 11 A.M. to 2:30 P.M. at the Art Guild on Church Street, at $8 with or without a tour ticket. The boutique, also in the Art Guild, is open to the public without tour tickets.</p>
        <p>Children from 4 to 7 (with a parent) are most likely to enjoy the Teddy Bear Tea and entertainment next Sunday at the library. One-hour sittings are scheduled at 1 and 3 P.M. and cost $5. For more information, call 673-6791 or 677-9222. PRESERVATION MEETING</p>
        <p>Those interested in historic preservation will be welcome at the annual meeting of the Commissioners of Local Historic Districts and Local Historic Properties to be be held on Saturday from 8:30 A.M. to noon at the Old Town Hall, 5 Mountain Road, at the corner of Main Street and Route 6, in Woodbury.</p>
        <p>Laura Clarke, executive director of the Connecticut Trust for Historic Preservation, will make the welcoming address, followed by John W. Shannahan, director of the Connecticut Historical Commission, who will present a rundown of recent preservation efforts around the state.</p>
        <p>Marilyn Ackerman, a historic architect, will talk about Colonial Connecticut in terms of construction and rehabilitation, while the grounds around historic homes will be the subject for W. Phillips Barlow, landscape architect.</p>
        <p>Three other architects will be on hand to discuss windows and what is available in the marketplace for historic buildings. The audience is encouraged to bring slides or photos of windows in need of help.</p>
        <p>At noon the group will tour the Hurd House and the 1867 District School House, properties of the Woodbury Historical Society. For more information, call one of the sponsors -- the Connecticut Historical Commission at 566-3005 or the Connecticut Trust for Historic Preservation at 562-6312. ANTIQUES AHEAD</p>
        <p>Visitors to the 26th annual Simsbury Antique Show on Saturday or next Sunday may tour the Massacoh Plantation, headquarters and showplace of the Simsbury Historical Society, sponsors of the antiques show.</p>
        <p>Situated in the center of town, the complex of buildings includes a 1740 schoolhouse, a Victorian carriage house, a 1795 cottage and herb garden, Captain Elisha Phelps's 1771 residence, a replica of the 1683 meetinghouse and an exhibition of Simsbury's industrial past.</p>
        <p>The Phelps house was an inn during the early 1800's, serving passengers on the Farmington canal boats. It has been preserved as it was then, with a tavern room, a separate parlor for women, an upstairs ballroom and an unusual barrel ceiling.</p>
        <p>Massacoh, with nine buildings on a 2 1/2-acre site amid 18 acres of wetlands, is one of the largest museum complexes in the state.</p>
        <p>The antique show, at Henry James Junior High School, 155 Firetown Road, will feature a selection of high quality furniture, china, jewelry, glass, silver, pewter, paintings, toys and country accessories. Hours on Saturday are 10 A.M. to 5 P.M., Sunday 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Admission is $4. Call 658-2500 for more information. JUST BOOKS</p>
        <p>"The Write Stuff: From Inspiration to Publication" is the title of the daylong second annual Just Books Writers Conference on Saturday, beginning at 8 A.M., at the Indian Harbor Yacht Club in Greenwich.</p>
        <p>Leading off the program will be an "Overview of the Publishing Process," by Brenda Marsh, executive vice president of trade sales at HarperCollins. The day will end with a roundtable discussion of "From Ordinary to Visionary: How to Ignite Your Muse" led by the author Lucy Hendrick. In between there will be six panels before lunch and three more after lunch, headed by such authors including Anne Raver and Billie Letts; two editors, Victoria Wilson of Random House and Jamie Raab, of Warner Books; two literary agents, Anita Diamant and Ted Chichak, plus publishers, publicists and experts on grants and other financing. Participants will be able to meet with one of the literary agents for 10 minutes, one on one. Tickets for the 150-seat event cost $100 in advance. Call 869-5023 for reservations or more information. ANTIQUING WEEKEND</p>
        <p>The northeastern corner of the state has long been a treasury of antiques, mined by savvy collectors, dealers and interior decorators. During the region's Antiquing Weekend on Saturday and next Sunday, shoppers will receive up to a 20 percent discount in some 30 shops found in barns, village centers, on farms and country roads.</p>
        <p>New England furniture from 1680 to 1840 is featured at Bartizek's Antiques on Bush Hill Road in Windham, while Coventry's Indoor-Outdoor Flea Market on Lake Street has 45 booths selling collectibles.</p>
        <p>Everything relative to chickens is the specialty of Cackleberry Farm Antiques on Lisbon Road in Canterbury, including a profusion of egg cups and utensils for cooking fowl.</p>
        <p>Floorcloth demonstrations on Saturday from 10 A.M. to 5 P.M. at Stone House Antiques in Dayville, and a glass and bottle auction at the same hours in West Woodstock by Norman C. Heckler and Company, are some of the special events. For a complete list of shops, events, lodgings and restaurants, call 860-928-1228. ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
