<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Suburbs, Famous for Being Normal, Aren't</title>
    <meta content="23MEMO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1327410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="ESSAY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9907EED7103BF930A1575AC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Suburbs, Famous for Being Normal, Aren't</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINERIP</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF you strolled down the main street of the tidy little upscale suburban village of Manhasset, N.Y. last week, everything looked normal, though it was not normal.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Rail Road parking lots were full again, the suits were rushing off to make appointments, the regulars were eating breakfast and lunch at Louie's and drinking whiskey at Leo's. Olive Duntley Florist, which had been deserted during the terrorist horror, was in full flower again, doing a brisk business, and Bob's One-Hour Photo was keeping its 60-minute promises.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF you strolled down the main street of the tidy little upscale suburban village of Manhasset, N.Y. last week, everything looked normal, though it was not normal.</p>
        <p>The Long Island Rail Road parking lots were full again, the suits were rushing off to make appointments, the regulars were eating breakfast and lunch at Louie's and drinking whiskey at Leo's. Olive Duntley Florist, which had been deserted during the terrorist horror, was in full flower again, doing a brisk business, and Bob's One-Hour Photo was keeping its 60-minute promises.</p>
        <p>But normal? ''No, not normal,'' said Bob Lickel, the Bob in One-Hour Photo. ''I'm trying to be careful about not saying the wrong thing.''</p>
        <p>As if on cue, two women wearing no makeup walked into his shop on Plandome Road carrying an old snapshot that they needed enlarged for the next day. The counter worker was saying it wouldn't be easy, but then Mr. Lickel, the owner, leaned over and said, ''Can I ask what it's for?''</p>
        <p>''Funeral,'' one woman said.</p>
        <p>''We'll have it by the end of the day,'' Mr. Lickel said.</p>
        <p>Manhasset looked normal, but it was not normal. Ground Zero might have been downtown Manhattan, but the aftershock rushed outward, carrying death, if not the dead, back to most every suburb in the metropolitan area.</p>
        <p>It was the quietness of the breakfast crowd at Louie's that was haunting Lillian Orofino. ''I keep looking around, trying to figure out who's missing,'' she said. She owns Olive Duntley Florist and said that last week it seemed people weren't sure if it was too soon, maybe too morbid, to send flowers for the missing. Monday morning, it was as if the starting bell at the New York Stock Exchange also went off in everyone's head. ''We're deluged,'' she said, as she raced to assemble bouquets. ''I've got orders going to 10 families who've lost someone.''</p>
        <p>Brian Hull of Merrill Lynch; Kevin McAleer of Morgan Stanley; Al Poto, a municipal bond broker; Kelly Quinn, a stockbroker; Scott Wysota, an executive recruiter; and Boomer Esiason, the former Jets star, were all dressed in suits and hurrying out of their suburban houses last week, looking ready for a normal business day. But it wasn't normal. They were going to the Church of St. Mary's in Manhasset, just at the end of the village's main street, to a memorial service for their dear friend Michael Seaman, 40, last seen alive on the 104th floor, north tower.</p>
        <p>In hitting the World Trade Center, the terrorists were apparently looking to strike at American capitalism, and in Michael H. Seaman, a senior vice president of Cantor Fitzgerald Securities, they seemed to have hit their target.</p>
        <p>But as you sat there at that memorial service in that packed church listening to the priest, the Rev. Peter Dugandzic, repeatedly calling him Mikey and talking about the joy Mikey Seaman got from coaching his daughter Michaella's C.Y.O. basketball team, and how he drove to work at 6 a.m. and would sit in the dark saying the rosary while waiting for his carpool buddy Brendan Lavelle to come out of the house, it was hard to think of Mikey Seaman as a symbol of anything besides Dara Seaman's husband and the daddy of Michaella, 13, Mary, 9, and Eddie, 8.</p>
        <p>Like a lot of those finance people lost, Mr. Seaman was the first in his blue-collar family to have a Manhasset address. He grew up in working-class South Ozone Park, Queens. His father was a carpenter, his brother is a conductor on the Long Island Rail Road.</p>
        <p>Mr. Seaman was no Harvard Business School whiz. He graduated from Adelphi, and he paid for that Manhasset address, friends say, by working 12-hour days, a phone in each ear, a speaker phone on his desk, convincing some trader a lot like him on the other end of the line that Mikey Seaman was the one who should get the trade on the $200 million in bonds Morgan Stanley was looking to sell.</p>
        <p>Like most of the dead and missing commuter capitalists, he was a man who had never done anything important enough in the business world to have his name in The New York Times or Newsday. And yet every one of the 852 spots in St. Mary's pews was taken, and mourners lined the church walls, were backed up all the way out onto the sidewalk and even stood down the center aisle. The priests in their white robes set up two extra stations by the altar to accommodate all the mourners who wanted to take communion.</p>
        <p>It may look normal, but it is not normal, far from it. The memorial services are just beginning to fill the suburban churches and temples and funeral homes. Msgr. Jim Lisante, pastor of St. Thomas the Apostle Church in West Hempstead, N.Y. lost 26 parishioners and as of midweek last week not a service -- not a single one -- had been scheduled.</p>
        <p>Gregory Hoffman, whose twin brother Stephen is missing, called looking for guidance. ''Shall we have the service now,'' he asked Monsignor Lisante. ''Shall we wait? What do we do?''</p>
        <p>Maureen Fanning, whose husband Jack, a New York City fire chief, is missing, won't even talk to Monsignor Lisante about a funeral or memorial service. ''She's been going to the site and watching from a distance,'' Monsignor Lisante said. ''She takes it literally that he's lost. She's not accepted that he's gone.''</p>
        <p>She can't afford to have him dead. They have two sons, Sean, 13, and Patrick, 5, both autistic.</p>
        <p>There are three priests at St. Thomas, and they divided among them the 26 grieving families, each priest taking a share of home visits.</p>
        <p>But as they made their calls, they found that many did not want a visit. ''There's a lot of them,'' Monsignor  Lisante said. ''They say, 'We don't need you to come yet, father, not yet.' ''</p>
        <p>Msgr. James P. Kelly, the rector of St. Agnes Cathedral in Rockville Centre, N.Y. has 20 parishioners lost, but only four services scheduled as of the end of last week. At one home he visited to console a woman about her husband, the family's two oldest sons talked with the priest, but the youngest, a boy of 8 or 9, would not come out of his bedroom. He thought Monsignor Kelly was the man from the valley of the shadow of death.</p>
        <p>Everyday in the suburbs, you see people -- on the commuter train, on the Little League field, at a P.T.A. meeting -- and they become part of your landscape, part of your daily routine, even though you may not know their names or what they do.</p>
        <p>Daya Brandon works the newsstand at the train station in Long Beach, N.Y.. One of her regulars for 10 years suddenly disappeared in the days after the attacks. She knew him as a kind face who always ordered a coffee (milk, no sugar), a buttered roll, a bottled water and a copy of The Times. At the end of the first week she finally saw him again, and was so relieved, she bungled his order. ''He said, 'Give me my coffee, I have to go.' I said, 'I'm so happy to see you.' ''</p>
        <p>The flow of patients at the Great Neck dental office of Dr. Harvey Passes has been busy as usual, but not normal. A few days after the attacks, Dr. Passes got a calm call from the wife of a patient of 20 years, saying she needed his dental records. Dr. Passes had just fixed a tooth for the man and made sure she had the most recent x-rays for identification purposes.</p>
        <p>Michael Mazza, the chef at Classico in Roslyn, N.Y., was asking one of his regulars how her salmon was when she burst into tears, saying she'd lost a nephew. DeFranco Spagnola salon in Great Neck usually calls people who miss an appointment, but not last week. ''We were afraid to,'' said the manager, Michelle Badakhshan.</p>
        <p>Each suburb spread the word in its own way. In Manhasset, salespeople from all 22 real estate companies regularly go out together each day to look over new houses being listed in the area. On a typical day, 80 salespeople will travel together to four or five new listings. ''They all filled each other in on who lost someone,'' said Jerry DiFede, publisher of a real estate listings magazine.</p>
        <p>People improvised mourning rituals. Long after Leah Dann, who grew up in Stonington, knew her childhood friend Joshua Piver, 23, was dead, she kept calling his cellphone, to get the voice mail. ''I just called it to hear his voice,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Eugene Murray, the 76-year-old mayor of Rockville Centre, has visited 20 homes of people in his village of 25,000 who've lost family.</p>
        <p>Ms. Orofino, the florist, was at St. Mary's that Tuesday night, saying prayers of thanks that her son, who worked on the 68th floor of tower 2 for Morgan Stanley, had not gone to the office that day, when a woman she knew came over. ''It was Kevin Cosgrove's mother, Mary,'' said Ms. Orofino. She said, 'He's missing.' ''</p>
        <p>In the center aisle at St. Mary's on a plain wooden stand, the Book of Intentions is kept. Church members write in requests for prayers of support from the priests and fellow parishioners.</p>
        <p>The days before the disaster are full of prayer requests for happy marriages, healthy babies and safe trips.</p>
        <p>Since the disaster, the entries -- more than 40 pages -- trace the sadness of one church that lost a dozen people:</p>
        <p>Pray for today's tragedy . . .</p>
        <p>God rest the souls of WTC</p>
        <p>Pray for the failing human race.</p>
        <p>To my brother Kevin on the 105 floor of WTC. You are probably closer to God and Dad, love Chris</p>
        <p>Pray for the people missing in the WTC expxlosion including our son Tim</p>
        <p>Pray for the Cascio and Dickey families</p>
        <p>Thanks for my husband's safe arrival at last</p>
        <p>Thanks for the safe return of Andrew Butcher</p>
        <p>God forgive me for any sins and any anger felt toward my husband's former employers who perished in this disaster</p>
        <p>Pray for my brother Tim Kelly, 37, feared dead on the 104th floor of WTC working for Cantor Fitzgerald. Tim graduated frorm St. Mary elementary and high school. Lives in Port Washington, N.Y. with wife Julie, 3 kids under 6, Kevin 5, Mary Kate, 3, Caroline 1 week. Thank you, Shawn P. Kelly</p>
        <p>Please pray for Eddie's Dad, Love, his friends in the third grade</p>
        <p>For the repair of psychic horror of my son who witnessed it</p>
        <p>The Seerys brought their 6-year-old, Richie, in to talk to Monsignor  Lisante about dealing with the loss of his uncle, Farrell Lynch. Father Lisante recalled, ''Richie says to me, 'You know who my favorite uncle is? Uncle Farrell. He'd always pick me up and flip me over. Do you thinking he's flipping angels?' ''</p>
        <p>At Mr. Seaman's service, his carpool mate, Brendan Lavelle, predicted that their friend was up in heaven, ''on one of his 30-mile bike rides, exhausting the angels.''</p>
        <p>It is not normal, all this talk of death and psychic horror among people from these quiet, safe suburbs. And it is just beginning. Tomorrow morning Monsignor Kelly, a former high school principal, drives to Huntingon to memorialize John Wallace, one of his former students. At St. Mary's on Monday there is a service for Paul Cascio. And at St. Thomas the Apostle, Monsignor Lisante has added a daily 7:30 p.m. mass, in part, so when his 26 families decide it's time, ''we'll have a little scheduling wiggle room.''</p>
        <p>ESSAY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
