<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>High Court Bars States From Energy Trust Suit</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="362916"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTITRUST ACTIONS AND LAWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KANSAS</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MISSOURI</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Kansas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Missouri</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DF1F38F931A15755C0A966958260" item-length="587" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>High Court Bars States From Energy Trust Suit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The Supreme Court ruled today that states cannot bring Federal antitrust suits on behalf of consumers charging energy producers with illegal price-fixing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The Supreme Court ruled today that states cannot bring Federal antitrust suits on behalf of consumers charging energy producers with illegal price-fixing.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court ruled today that states cannot bring Federal antitrust suits on behalf of consumers charging energy producers with illegal price-fixing.</p>
        <p>The 5-to-4 decision reaffirmed the Court's longstanding bar against antitrust suits by anyone other than direct purchasers. In this case, the direct purchasers were neither the consumers nor the states, but a Kansas utility, which had filed an antitrust suit charging that a natural gas pipeline and five gas production companies had conspired to fix prices.</p>
        <p>Two states, Kansas and Missouri, argued that the Court should make an exception from its direct-purchaser rule in the case of regulated utilities, which are frequently required by states to pass higher prices on to their customers.</p>
        <p>The two states' appeal was supported by the attorneys general of 32 other states and by organizations including the National Conference of State Legislatures and the U.S. Conference of Mayors.</p>
        <p>Sought to Resolve Conflict</p>
        <p>The United States Court of Appeals for the 10th Circuit, in Denver, dismissed the Kansas and Missouri suits last year on the ground that the Supreme Court's antitrust precedents did not support the exception the states were seeking. The Supreme Court took the case to resolve a conflict among the Federal courts. The United States Court of Appeals for the Seventh Circuit, in Chicago, had permitted Illinois to bring a similar suit in 1988.</p>
        <p>Writing for the majority today, Justice Anthony M. Kennedy said it would be ''imprudent'' to create an exception from the direct purchaser rule for antitrust cases involving regulated public utilities. The Court's rule was announced in two cases, Hanover Shoe v. United Shoe Machinery in 1968 and Illinois Brick v. Illinois in 1977.</p>
        <p>Justice Kennedy said that suits by consumers, or by states on consumers' behalf, would involve the same difficult problems of proof and apportionment of damages that led the Court to establish the direct-purchaser rule in the first place. He noted that utilities could suffer damages, like lost business, from price-fixing by their suppliers even if they pass on the overcharges to their customers. Justice Kennedy said it would be difficult for courts to ascertain whether the business was lost because of the higher prices or because of other market conditions.</p>
        <p>In addition, he said, utilities themselves ''have an established record of diligent antitrust enforcement'' in bringing their own lawsuits. ''This history makes us quite hesitant to take from the utilities the responsibility for enforcing the antitrust laws,'' he said. The utility that initiated the antitrust suit in this case was Utilicorp United Inc., based in Kansas and western Missouri.</p>
        <p>The majority opinion, Kansas and Missouri v. Utilicorp, No. 88-2109, was joined by Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and Justices John Paul Stevens, Sandra Day O'Connor and Antonin Scalia.</p>
        <p>Justice Byron R. White filed a dissenting opinion joined by Justices William J. Brennan Jr., Thurgood Marshall, and Harry A. Blackmun. They said that this case appeared to involve a ''perfect and provable pass-on'' of the overcharges that would make it easy to determine damages. ''None of the concerns that caused us to bar the indirect purchaser's suit in Illinois Brick exist in this case,'' the dissenting Justices said.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration, which told the Court late last year that it had not yet formulated a position on the question, filed a brief arguing that the states' suits should not be permitted.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
