<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Job Cuts Take Heavy Toll on Telecom Industry</title>
    <meta content="Y29JOB$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/06/29/technology/29JOBS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20020702T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1404353"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TURMOIL AT WORLDCOM: THE WORK FORCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recession and Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">WorldCom Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E7DB113EF93AA15755C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1504" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Job Cuts Take Heavy Toll on Telecom Industry</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Job Cuts Take Heavy Toll on Telecom Industry</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Exodus of workers from telecommunications industry swells as companies cut labor force by laying off or buying out workers and forcing retirements; industry accounts for 167,000 jobs cuts, over ten percent of lost jobs in nation since recession began in Mar 2001; industry analysts believe that elimination of another ten percent of industry's employees is required and that no rehiring will be necessary when economy rebounds; graphs; photographs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WorldCom's downfall is swelling the exodus of workers from the telecommunications industry, which alone has accounted for more than one out of every 10 jobs lost in the United States since the recession began in March last year.</p>
        <p>Most of this rapid job shrinkage in telecommunications has come through layoffs, buyouts and forced retirements. Indeed, telecommunications companies have exceeded any other industry in the number of publicly announced job cuts over the last 18 months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>WorldCom's downfall is swelling the already substantial exodus of workers from the telecommunications industry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WorldCom's downfall is swelling the exodus of workers from the telecommunications industry, which alone has accounted for more than one out of every 10 jobs lost in the United States since the recession began in March last year.</p>
        <p>Most of this rapid job shrinkage in telecommunications has come through layoffs, buyouts and forced retirements. Indeed, telecommunications companies have exceeded any other industry in the number of publicly announced job cuts over the last 18 months.</p>
        <p>The cuts have come from the dozens of companies that build and operate the nation's networks for telephone service, cable television, the Internet, e-mail and data transmission. Having wildly overexpanded in the 1990's, the companies have been rushing to shrink ever since, serving as a drag on the economic recovery.</p>
        <p>''They have to cut another 10 percent of their employees to get down to where they should be,'' said Kenneth McGee, a telecommunications expert at Gartner, the research firm. ''And in the next economic expansion they won't need those people back.''</p>
        <p>Not all job losses are prominently announced, of course. In total, the nation has lost 1.5 million jobs since the recession began in March of last year, with the telecommunications industry contributing 167,000 to that loss through April, according to the latest industry breakdown from the Bureau of Labor Statistics. Employment is so important to well-being that some economists are reluctant to declare a new expansion firmly under way until a revival in the job market is clearly happening.</p>
        <p>While telecommunications companies continue to eliminate jobs, many other industries appear to have stopped doing so. Since April, national employment has even begun to grow a bit, although so far adding back only 40,000 jobs.</p>
        <p>''I have not heard the phrase jobless recovery applied yet to our current experience but it is very much to the point,'' said Robert Hall, a Stanford economist and the chairman of the committee of economists that designates when recessions and recoveries begin and end. ''We have regained almost none of the lost jobs; we are still very stalled.''</p>
        <p>This time the rehiring and job creation must take place without help from telecommunications companies, industry executives insist. The jobs that are being eliminated in the industry will not have to be recreated, they say. Once the downsizing is over, the industry may level off at fewer than 1.2 million employees. Some of the lost jobs represented overstaffing, even in good times, to build more capacity into wireless and fiber optic networks than the nation will be able to use for a long time, said Scott Cleland, a telecommunications expert and chief executive of the Precursor Group, an investment research firm.</p>
        <p>''Everyone overbuilt,'' he said, ''and telecom companies will not be spending appreciably for expansion for years to come.''</p>
        <p>Other jobs are being lost to labor- saving technology, many in the industry argue, and to changes in the way the companies now operate, given that cellphones are cutting into the more labor-intensive regular phone service. Moreover, the Telecommunications Act of 1996 has forced the Baby Bells to share their local phone monopolies with ''resellers'' that lease circuits at wholesale prices from the Bells and resell them to households and companies.</p>
        <p>''In some small markets, we have lost 50 percent of our customers,'' Jeff Battcher, a BellSouth executive, said.</p>
        <p>If past recoveries are a guide, the men and women who have lost their jobs in telecommunications will eventually find work in other industries. But that is not happening quickly for Roy Abrahamsen, a technician at an AT&amp;T maintenance center at 33 Thomas Street in Manhattan -- until that center was closed in March.</p>
        <p>Told to choose between a buyout package or a transfer to an office in White Plains, Mr. Abrahamsen, 56 and a Brooklyn resident, took the buyout.</p>
        <p>That was partly to avoid the two-hour commute versus his previous 35 minutes, Mr. Abrahamsen said, and partly out of fear that AT&amp;T would soon close the White Plains office, laying him off without a buyout. Now he is looking for a job at places like Home Depot, hoping that a skill in carpentry will help him recover some of the $57,000 in salary that he lost. As part of the buyout, AT&amp;T is continuing his health insurance and is paying him the $22,000-a-year pension that he normally would have received in his 60's.</p>
        <p>''I miss the routines of work very much,'' he said. ''I wake up at the same time every morning, and I cannot always fill my days. It sounds strange but I enjoyed working and I enjoyed my job.''</p>
        <p>Until WorldCom came along with its announcement this week that it would eliminate 17,000 jobs on top of the 6,000 it cut last year -- drastically shrinking a work force that totaled 85,000 in January -- few companies in the telecommunications industry had drawn more attention for job shedding than AT&amp;T. Since the beginning of 2001, it has announced more than 20,000 cuts, or roughly 16 percent of its job slots.</p>
        <p>But while AT&amp;T cites efficiency gains through technology as a main reason for its actions, Mr. Abrahamsen says that technology is only part of the explanation for consolidating the Thomas Street maintenance center, where he worked, with a similar operation in White Plains.</p>
        <p>Using a computer, he performed remote repairs on telephone lines and data circuits leased to business customers -- American Express and Avis, for example -- or he pinpointed the trouble so others could make the repair. The staff doing this maintenance by computer had dwindled since early last year from 70 to 60. Fifty of the 60 made the transfer.</p>
        <p>''With fewer people, the time needed to make a repair grew longer,'' Mr. Abrahamsen said. ''There was not a specific moment when this happened or a directive, but little by little it happened. Customer service declined.''</p>
        <p>From January through May, job- cut announcements in the telecommunications industry reached 135,385, or nearly 29 percent of all such announcements, according to Challenger, Gray &amp; Christmas, a consulting firm that tracks this data. That was up from 102,366 in the same period last year.</p>
        <p>The downsizing varies. Faced with a sharp dropoff in orders, Lucent Technologies, the manufacturer of switches and other communications equipment, has in effect sold three major factories to independent ''contract manufacturers,'' transferring many of its factory workers in the bargain. Lucent now buys from the contractors only the amount of equipment that it can sell. The Lucent payroll has shrunk to 56,000 from 62,000 on Jan. 1.</p>
        <p>''We anticipate that by the end of September, it will be close to 50,000,'' said Mary Ward, a Lucent spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>BellSouth has announced that 4,000 to 5,000 jobs will be eliminated this year from its payroll of 85,740, which in turn has declined from 97,000 a year ago. ''We feel we will then be at the right number of people to handle a quick and fast economic recovery,'' Mr. Battcher said.</p>
        <p>Beyond the competition from resellers, he lists some other reasons the cutbacks are likely to be long term. Cellphones, for example, are less labor intensive than standard telephones and rather than order another phone line for a teenager's bedroom, many parents are giving their children cellphones. And while demand is huge for high-speed Internet D.S.L. service, the labor requirement is small.</p>
        <p>''We have self-install,'' Mr. Battcher said. ''A customer asks for D.S.L. and we can mail them out a do-it-yourself disc. It is simple for them and simple for us, and it saves us money.''</p>
        <p>TURMOIL AT WORLDCOM: THE WORK FORCE  Correction:  July 2, 2002, Tuesday  A picture caption in Business Day on Saturday with an article about the loss of jobs in the telecommunications industry referred imprecisely to a protest by employees at Verizon Communications in late May. They were demonstrating against the company's declaration that it could lay off employees as a last resort, not an announcement of actual layoffs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: July 2, 2002, Tuesday</p>
        <p>A picture caption in Business Day on Saturday with an article about the loss of jobs in the telecommunications industry referred imprecisely to a protest by employees at Verizon Communications in late May. They were demonstrating against the company's declaration that it could lay off employees as a last resort, not an announcement of actual layoffs.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
