<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Anti-Poverty Program Under Fire in Mexico</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="772712"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALINAS DE GORTARI, CARLOS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DEPALMA, ANTHONY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZEDILLO PONCE DE LEON, ERNESTO (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950703T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DE1E38F930A35754C0A963958260" item-length="1440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Anti-Poverty Program Under Fire in Mexico</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DEPALMA, ANTHONY</byline>
      <dateline>ANGOSTURA, Mexico</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every Sunday, no matter how hot it gets in this fiery land between the desert and the sea, Joel Incunza Contreras and the Campo Plata Harvesters play at least nine innings of baseball at a new stadium, which they built with $30,000 from the anti-poverty program that was a trademark of the former President, Carlos Salinas.</p>
        <p>Critics have asserted that such spending by the program, known as Solidarity, has done nothing to ease Mexico's grinding poverty. Nor, they say, have the millions of Solidarity dollars spent all over Mexico in the last six years to build more than 2,000 basketball courts, dozens of gymnasiums and enough baseball stadiums to support a league.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every Sunday, no matter how hot it gets in this fiery land between the desert and the sea, Joel Incunza Contreras and the Campo Plata Harvesters play at least nine innings of baseball at a new stadium, which they built with $30,000 from the anti-poverty program that was a trademark of the former President, Carlos Salinas.</p>
        <p>Critics have asserted that such spending by the program, known as Solidarity, has done nothing to ease Mexico's grinding poverty. Nor, they say, have the millions of Solidarity dollars spent all over Mexico in the last six years to build more than 2,000 basketball courts, dozens of gymnasiums and enough baseball stadiums to support a league.</p>
        <p>But what these projects and 500,000 other more traditional public works have done is to link the name Solidarity with the name Salinas and the party he headed, the Institutional Revolutionary Party, or PRI. When elections come, many voters remember Solidarity, and that has helped keep the party in power.</p>
        <p>Those positive links have now turned into big problems for the Government. Since his term ended, Mr. Salinas and nearly everything he accomplished in six years in office, including Solidarity, have been rejected or ridiculed. Critics have demanded Solidarity's demise, and the new President, Ernesto Zedillo, who has his own problems, has been intent on distancing himself from his predecessor.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Zedillo contends there is something in Solidarity worth saving, and that is already making his critics suspicious.</p>
        <p>He has indicated that he intends to retain the basic structure of Solidarity while limiting its propaganda potential and radically changing the way it works. The annual budget, at $1.6 billion this year, is to focus more on fighting extreme poverty, which affects nearly 15 million Mexicans, and less on building political support. But critics say the potential for abuse would still exist.</p>
        <p>Mr. Zedillo is expected to announce the formation of the new program -- the Alliance for Well-Being -- in the next few weeks. Mr. Salinas had structured the program using thousands of small local committees waiting for a nod from the President. He brought some committee leaders to Mexico City for training every week and spoke to the graduating class before sending them back to the countryside. In this way he created a network of support that offset the harshest aspects of his economic policies.</p>
        <p>The heart of the program would continue to be the local committees, ordinary people in a community who decide what they most need -- even if that turns out to be a baseball stadium, as here in the northern state of Sinaloa.</p>
        <p>But under Mr. Zedillo's proposal, the Alliance for Well-Being, states and local communities and not the federal Government would decide what gets money and what has to wait.</p>
        <p>Some of Mr. Zedillo's critics contend that the 31 state governors and the thousands of local mayors could exploit the program for their own political purposes. Moreover, they see in the new name, which echoes the "Well-Being for Your Family" theme of Mr. Zedillo's 1994 campaign, the potential for more presidential image-building.</p>
        <p>"Before, you had just the President of Mexico who decided where the money would go," said Rosario Robles, a congresswoman from the leftist Democratic Revolutionary Party, who is president of the multiparty Committee on Social Development. "Now you have to multiply that by the 2,000 or so mayors because there is still no control on how the money is used."</p>
        <p>Along with the passage of the North American Free Trade Agreement in 1993, Solidarity was what Mr. Salinas most wanted to be remembered for. During his term he devoted more than $15 billion of federal money to the program and spent untold amounts of time wrapped in its symbol: a red, white and green braid that represented Mexicans working together.</p>
        <p>"Solidarity was instrumental for maintaining social peace during the Salinas years," said Denise Dresser, a political scientist at the Autonomous Technological Institute of Mexico who has written extensively about Solidarity. "It was a way of governing expectations and delivering public goods in every dinky, dusty corner of the country."</p>
        <p>Outside the Angostura baseball stadium where the Harvesters play, there is a ceramic plaque with the Solidarity name and symbol. In the Salinas years, Government road maps were adorned with the Solidarity symbol. Solidarity commercials ran endlessly on television. President Salinas often jogged in a Solidarity sweatshirt.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Salinas opened the economy, there were widespread layoffs as older, noncompetitive businesses closed. Peasants who barely survived before could not compete when the Mexican market for farm products was opened to farmers in the United States and Canada. Solidarity's stadiums and small public works compensated the poorest Mexicans temporarily and kept them loyal to the Government.</p>
        <p>Over the long run, the program did not do much to reduce the number of Mexicans living in poverty, its critics point out. Rather than focus on creating permanent jobs, which would have raised people out of poverty, it instead provided temporary employment on public works. In some rural communities, though, projects like water filtration plants were thought to have improved the overall quality of life.</p>
        <p>Solidarity served well to attract votes, though. A study by Juan Molinar Horcasitas, a political scientist at Colegio de Mexico, showed that after Mr. Salinas squeaked by his opponents in a contested 1988 election, Solidarity money poured into the communities where he had his poorest showing. After the 1991 midterm elections, in which Mr. Salinas's party regained much of the ground it had lost in 1988, Mr. Molinar checked Solidarity spending in swing districts. He found that for every percentage point increase in voting for the PRI, about $2.50 more per voter had been spent on Solidarity projects.</p>
        <p>In Sinaloa, for example, several of the congressional districts where baseball stadiums have been built showed strong PRI recoveries between 1988 and 1991.</p>
        <p>Carlos Rojas Gutierrez, the current Secretary of the Department of Social Development, who has been an integral part of Solidarity since 1988, denies that its resources were ever used to influence an election. He says Solidarity money goes to all 31 states, including 4 now run by the opposition, and to more than 250 communities governed by opposition parties.</p>
        <p>He said that in only one community, a Salinas showcase called Chalco in Mexico State, have local politicians blatantly tried to use Solidarity for their own political gains. A local PRI boss tried to put up election propaganda saying "Solidarity brought the lights," which in Spanish also carries the connotation that "Solidarity brought the dough."</p>
        <p>Many of his critics say that when Mr. Salinas went on a hunger strike last March in a desperate attempt to clear his name, he doomed the Solidarity program by taking refuge in the house of the president of a local Solidarity committee in Monterrey.</p>
        <p>But while the name is being changed, it will not be easy to wipe out its memory. The Solidarity symbol, which the Government legally registered in 1992, has been painted or carved on most flat surfaces in Mexico, and even the harshest critics say the program did some good. Millions of poor people touched directly by the program's bounty do not want to see it disappear.</p>
        <p>Incunza Contreras, of the Harvesters, worked on the committee that decided a baseball stadium was most needed in his poor farming community, even if the roads are not paved and some houses have neither indoor plumbing nor electricity. He dug holes and helped level the ground. Others did masonry work or painted.</p>
        <p>"Building the stadium proved we could work together," Mr. Incunza Contreras said. "It shouldn't stop."</p>
        <p>Eugenia Raquel Arguelles of Guamuchil, in Sinaloa, where Solidarity money helped pay for a soccer field covered in artificial turf, also thought the program should survive. "Whether Salinas was a good President or a bad one, Solidarity was one of the good things that he left us," she said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rojas, of the Department of Social Development, said the new program would concentrate on the basic needs of the poor. But if a local committee insists on using the money to build a basketball court or a baseball stadium, or even to repair an old church, he said he would support it.</p>
        <p>"That is the risk of decentralization, and we have to take it," he said. "And if we are going to place a political bet on a new kind of federalism that respects the decisions of the people, we have to respect the people."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
