<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>You Say Anything Goes In Politics? Only if It Works</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="649658"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE NATION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLYMER, ADAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITMAN, CHRISTINE TODD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROLLINS, ED</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE6D61F39F937A25752C1A965958260" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>You Say Anything Goes In Politics? Only if It Works</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM CLYMER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLYMER, ADAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>POLITICAL consultants are not as widely trusted as, for example, television diet pitchwomen. But when Ed Rollins told two dozen reporters that he had paid off ministers in New Jersey to hold down the black vote, everyone believed him. (The next day, when the Republican operative said he had been fibbing, he fell back to the confidence level his trade usually inspires.)</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mr. Rollins attributed the upset victory of Christine Todd Whitman in New Jersey's gubernatorial race one week earlier to his brilliance in offering money to black preachers so they would forgo their usual pre-election appeals to their flocks to go out and vote. On Wednesday, Mrs. Whitman and Mr. Rollins said that never happened.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>POLITICAL consultants are not as widely trusted as, for example, television diet pitchwomen. But when Ed Rollins told two dozen reporters that he had paid off ministers in New Jersey to hold down the black vote, everyone believed him. (The next day, when the Republican operative said he had been fibbing, he fell back to the confidence level his trade usually inspires.)</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, Mr. Rollins attributed the upset victory of Christine Todd Whitman in New Jersey's gubernatorial race one week earlier to his brilliance in offering money to black preachers so they would forgo their usual pre-election appeals to their flocks to go out and vote. On Wednesday, Mrs. Whitman and Mr. Rollins said that never happened.</p>
        <p>Two decades ago, most people did not believe what they first heard of the sabotage Republicans were carrying out against Democratic Presidential candidates in the 1972 campaign, not just burglarizing the headquarters of the Democratic National Committee but staging disruptive demonstrations, sending phony letters and stealing documents.</p>
        <p>By 1980 the public barely noticed that Ronald Reagan's campaign had obtained and used President Jimmy Carter's briefing book before their only televised debate.</p>
        <p>Now the country seems inured to the idea that anything goes in politics. The questions Mr. Rollins got the other day over coffee, cold cereal and eggs were about how he had pulled off an original stunt.</p>
        <p>"Did we stand up in moral outrage, condemn him, and throw our food at him?" one reporter asked rhetorically. "No, we asked for details on how it was done."</p>
        <p>And politicians hardly lined up to condemn him. Representative Maxine Waters, a black Democrat from Los Angeles, did demand a Federal investigation, saying, "We didn't fight and beat Klan intimidation of black voters in the South only to tolerate G.O.P. vote suppression in New Jersey."</p>
        <p>But spokesmen for the House Republican leader, Robert H. Michel of Illinois, and his deputy, Newt Gingrich of Georgia, said their bosses did not want to discuss the matter. Bob Dole of Kansas, the Republican leader in the Senate, said bluntly, "This never should happen, but if it did, I deplore that kind of conduct."</p>
        <p>The more typical Republican response was to argue that what Mr. Rollins said was, as Senator John C. Danforth of Missouri put it, "the next extension of what is a long-standing and generally bad practice, but not an unusual one, the idea of sort of paying people to crank out the vote."</p>
        <p>That use of "walking-around money," he and others observed, is usually a Democratic habit. It is an efficient descendant of paying voters directly, in cash or booze, a practice so ancient that it was done even when some big-city machines were controlled by Republicans.</p>
        <p>Indeed, most of the reaction in Washington focused on how stupid it was of Mr. Rollins to admit doing something like this, and how embarrassing it must be for his client, Governor-elect Whitman, still basking in her defeat of Gov. Jim Florio.</p>
        <p>One Republican Congressional aide, who insisted on not being named, argued that morality was not relevant to campaign methods, unless a particular tactic was actually against the law. (Mr. Rollins, before he decided he had not done it, maintained that the scheme was legal, but the NAACP Legal Defense and Educational Fund Inc. argued that his efforts to depress the black vote may have violated the Voting Rights Act. On Friday, the Justice Department said it would investigate to find out what happened and whether any Federal laws were broken.)</p>
        <p>Certainly, nothing in the open campaigning of the last 20 years or so contradicts the aide's view. In fund raising, the history of the Federal Election Campaign Act of 1974 is the history of an industrious search for ways to evade the law. In television advertising, the old theory that people expected more than negative campaigning from a Presidential candidate, whatever they would accept for lesser offices, no longer applies. And appeals to racial prejudice are more open than they used to be.</p>
        <p>Indeed, there are hardly any documented cases of a politician of either party saying that, while a particular fund-raising device might be legal, it would be wrong to take the money, or that while a television spot looked effective it was too divisive or sleazy to use. If they avoid nasty approaches, it is almost always for fear that they will lose votes from disapproving voters.</p>
        <p>Campaign managers do everything they can to energize their potential voters and lull the other side. Lulling the opposition usually means not saying things to make people angry. But the Ku Klux Klan simply scared blacks from voting, and Republicans in New Jersey followed their example in 1981, stationing armed off-duty police officers near urban voting precincts, where signs warned that voter fraud could lead to prison. (After a lawsuit, the Republican National Committee pledged not to engage in intimidating tactics.)</p>
        <p>Still, it may just be that no one ever thought of paying black ministers not to urge their flocks to vote before Ed Rollins did, if he did.</p>
        <p>But whether he did or did not, why was he talking about it? One theory was that Mr. Rollins was taking out an advertisement whose not-so-secret text read: "Afraid that blacks will vote against you next year in (fill in name of state)? Then hire Ed Rollins! He knows how to solve that problem for you."</p>
        <p>The ad may have been too badly placed. It probably needed to be sent in a plain brown wrapper before candidates would sign up. On front pages, it was so obvious that would-be officeholders would look like racists if they hired him. They certainly don't want to look like racists.</p>
        <p>THE NATION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
