<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>3 Ways to Stand Tall While the Accusations Fly</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="649708"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="POLITICAL NOTES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSITION BETWEEN ADMINISTRATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CONNECTICUT</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FAIRFIELD (CONN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HARTFORD COURANT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, KIRK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LARSON, JOHN B (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WACHNER, LINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LANGONE, KENNETH G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIEDERMEIER, CHRISTINE M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">AUDLEY, PAUL M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFD81F3BF937A25752C1A965958260" item-length="1009" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>3 Ways to Stand Tall While the Accusations Fly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, KIRK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>State Senator John B. Larson's campaign for governor of Connecticut got off to a textbook rocky start last week: On the very day he was starting his effort with a bus tour around the state, The Hartford Courant, quoting documents and unnamed sources, said that the Democratic candidate's financial records had been subpoenaed by a Federal grand jury. The newspaper said the grand jury was looking into possible connections between a legislative vote on interstate banking in 1989 and bank loans to lawmakers.</p>
        <p>What has commenced now is perhaps another chapter from that same textbook: How does a candidate who has professed absolute innocence get beyond what is, for the moment at least, nothing more than an anonymous, if toxic, cloud that somehow leaked from a supposedly confidential jury room? What tools do you use, and what tools do you avoid using, in trying to put it behind you? How do you recover your balance?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>State Senator John B. Larson's campaign for governor of Connecticut got off to a textbook rocky start last week: On the very day he was starting his effort with a bus tour around the state, The Hartford Courant, quoting documents and unnamed sources, said that the Democratic candidate's financial records had been subpoenaed by a Federal grand jury. The newspaper said the grand jury was looking into possible connections between a legislative vote on interstate banking in 1989 and bank loans to lawmakers.</p>
        <p>What has commenced now is perhaps another chapter from that same textbook: How does a candidate who has professed absolute innocence get beyond what is, for the moment at least, nothing more than an anonymous, if toxic, cloud that somehow leaked from a supposedly confidential jury room? What tools do you use, and what tools do you avoid using, in trying to put it behind you? How do you recover your balance?</p>
        <p>So, herewith, an update from Mr. Larson's book so far:</p>
        <p>*Throw open all the records to the public and press.</p>
        <p>*Avoid the temptation to hire a lawyer, because like it or not, many voters believe that only guilty people need lawyers.</p>
        <p>*Cast the grand jury investigation as a threat to the image of the entire State Senate as an institution and put Senate staffers, not your own campaign, in charge of answering the questions.</p>
        <p>"It's a very gray area," said David J. McQuade, the chief of staff for the majority Democrats in the State Senate, who has been assigned the delicate task of pushing the United States Attorney's office for a resolution of the Larson investigation, but without making new headlines about it. "My role is gathering a lot of advice about how to pursue this -- with all the sensitivities, it's very difficult."</p>
        <p>Mr. Larson has said he believes that the material about the investigation was leaked by his political opponents, and that a loan his insurance company received from a unit of Fleet Bank a year after the 1989 vote, which benefited Fleet, was simply an ordinary business loan, in which he had to put up his home as collateral.</p>
        <p>The state's Republican Party Chairman, John A. Mastropietro, said the propriety of Mr. Larson's use of Senate staff to deal with the Federal investigation is a new question of its own, but one that will have to await the resolution of the inquiry.</p>
        <p>If the subpoena involves Mr. Larson's acts as a Senator, Mr. Mastropietro said, then using Senate staff is appropriate. But if the matter involves only Mr. Larson's actions as a private citizen, then using Senate staff would be an abuse, Mr. Mastropietro said, and future fodder for the gubernatorial campaign. Money in Transition</p>
        <p>Sometimes there's more to a transition council than meets the eye.</p>
        <p>When New York's Mayor-elect, Rudolph W. Giuliani, named the appointees to his transition council last week, there were obvious bows to supporters: Republicans, crossover Democrats, Hispanic and black backers, and his defeated running mates, Herman Badillo and Susan D. Alter.</p>
        <p>But money was a factor as well. Two appointees, Linda J. Wachner and Kenneth G. Langone, both identified as business executives, were also big donors to Mr. Giuliani's campaign, according to campaign finance filings.</p>
        <p>Ms. Wachner, who is chairwoman and chief executive of Warnaco Group Inc., a Fortune 500 clothing company, gave the campaign $6,500, the legal limit. Mr. Langone, who is founder and managing director of Invemed Associates, and his wife each gave $6,500.</p>
        <p>And Ms. Wachner and Mr. Langone each gave $25,000 to a registration and poll-watching operation run by the State Republican Committee. Another member of the transition council, Herbert Rubin, identified as a senior partner at the law firm of Herzfeld &amp; Rubin, is the longtime counsel to the Liberal Party, which gave Mr. Giuliani its ballot line. Three-Time Loser</p>
        <p>Three strikes, you're out?</p>
        <p>Christine M. Niedermeier, a Fairfield, Conn., Democrat who seemed just a few years ago to be the party's great young hope in a section of the state dominated by Republicans, has now lost three elections in a row -- most recently a race for top local official of her own hometown. While giving her high marks for effort, party leaders are suggesting that perhaps her future is in party work beyond the ballot box.</p>
        <p>Ms. Niedermeier, a 42-year-old former state legislator, left the Capitol in Hartford in 1986 to run for Congress, losing narrowly to Stewart B. McKinney. Mr. McKinney died in office a year later, and Ms. Niedermeier ran again, but lost heavily to Christopher Shays, who still holds the seat. Last week, having lowered her sights, she lost an election for Fairfield's First Selectman to Paul M. Audley, a Republican, in what Ms. Niedermeier said was the closest town election in 10 years.</p>
        <p>She said in an interview that in her overall political career, she had won seven elections and lost three. Unfortunately for her, the three have been prominent and recent.</p>
        <p>"It gives one pause," she said.</p>
        <p>The Democratic state party chairman, Edward L. Marcus, said Ms. Niedermeier has been a slugger in her every contest, but "she just hasn't been able to win."</p>
        <p>"Christine still has a political future, but pragmatically, it is within the party structure as opposed to being a candidate at this point," Mr. Marcus said. 3 Fewer Black Mayors</p>
        <p>Connecticut had three prominent black mayors at the beginning of 1993, and now it has none in its top-tier cities. Mayor Carrie Saxon Perry lost in her bid for re-election in Hartford. John C. Daniels of New Haven declined to seek a third term. And Joseph M. Suggs Jr., the former Mayor of Bloomfield, a Hartford suburb, resigned to become State Treasurer.</p>
        <p>Officials at the N.A.A.C.P. said that they were still analyzing the election results. But so far, they said, the only discernible trend is that local offices are becoming more of a revolving door, related to race in some instances and unrelated in others. For instance, Mayor-elect Michael P. Peters of Hartford, who is white, drew many black votes.</p>
        <p>POLITICAL NOTES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
