<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stern's Complaint</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="649749"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STERN, HOWARD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">PRIVATE PARTS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D8173DF937A25752C1A965958260" item-length="1092" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stern's Complaint</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Walter Goodman;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>PRIVATE PARTS By Howard Stern. Illustrated. 446 pp. New York:  Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>PRIVATE PARTS By Howard Stern. Illustrated. 446 pp. New York:  Simon &amp; Schuster. $23.</p>
        <p>TO lead off the thank-you's with which he begins this assemblage of his greatest moments, Howard Stern acknowledges the efforts of Larry (Ratso) Sloman, who "helped me find my 'voice' on paper -- whatever that means." Voice-finding is a common assignment for the writers who turn out books by show-biz personalities, but what can it mean for somebody who is all voice?</p>
        <p>For "Private Parts," Mr. Sloman seems to have gone through his client's radio and television shows, selected the most scabrous passages and patched them together with autobiographical confessions or inventions, cracks about minorities (Rodney King "should be beaten every time he reaches for his car keys") and send-ups of "self-indulgent, narcissistic, self-important celebrities," especially talk show stars like Oprah Winfrey ("a big dolt with an empty, oversized head and $250 million"); Arsenio Hall ("triangle-headed moron"); Kathie Lee Gifford ("Hah! A Jew!") and Regis Philbin ("despicable"); Rush Limbaugh ("fat pig"); Phil Donahue ("hypocrite"); Johnny Carson ("just another Hollywood phony"); Jay Leno ("a puppy"), and Howard Stern ("the nicest, sweetest, most sentimental radio personality on the planet"). Here as elsewhere, insults do the work of punch lines.</p>
        <p>There are also plenty of pictures, many from the Stern family album, along with plugs and knocks in assorted typefaces. The resultant commotion catches the voice that has won a big audience and agitated the F.C.C.</p>
        <p>Sorry, but I am not able to do that voice justice in this newspaper's closely policed pages. Mr. Stern is heavily devoted to breasts (36 D and vicinity), behinds (including his own) and penises (he makes no great claims in that neighborhood), and is drawn to discussions of masturbation, defecation and the expulsion of intestinal gas. His language is more pungent than most newspaper style manuals encourage, which doubtless accounts for some of his appeal. Since the evidence is unquotable, those who haven't heard Mr. Stern will just have to take my word that juvenilia -- amusing, disgusting and at times both at once -- is the man's stock in trade.</p>
        <p>"Private Parts" may remind old-timers of the raunchy parodies of comic strips in which favorites like Maggie and Jiggs, possessed of the enormous appendages that fill Mr. Stern's imaginings, went at each other with the help of words that were not yet utterable on radio. They were fine, filthy fun that helped several generations get through their teens. (Somebody should put out an anthology of that pubescent porn.) The thousands of people seen lining up to buy copies of "Private Parts" were, for the most part, well beyond adolescence; maybe they have another excuse.</p>
        <p>In the tradition of Jewish memoirists, Mr. Stern does a lot of kvetching about what he calls his dysfunctional family (Stern's Complaint), some of it funny. Mrs. Stern, a principled liberal, is credited with having refused to move from a changing Long Island neighborhood, where young Howard found himself being beaten up daily by the tough black newcomers. The son takes his revenge by doing riffs on his parents' sex practices, mild though they are. But, in fairness, he does not spare himself or his wife either. (The news here is that she does not care for bondage but enjoys the vibrator.) Only his three young daughters escape such reportage. Well, maybe in the next book.</p>
        <p>The Stern range is not as broad or as deep as the organs that fascinate him, but he is out ahead in the Beavis and Butt-head nastyspeak stakes. He owes a lot to feminists and mainstream multiculturalists, who serve as plump objects for spanking. Mr. Stern treats his female guests like you-know-what (they seem to enjoy it, even the spanking part), and he says in public the sorts of things about minorities that many of his fans would doubtless say in private if they had the wit for it.</p>
        <p>An instructive if typically intemperate chapter has to do with Mr. Stern's troubles with WNBC in the 1980's. That New York radio station evidently wanted to retain the Stern audience while trying to restrain the man himself. He was suspended for doing a skit about the Virgin Mary and finally fired for "conceptual differences."</p>
        <p>Elsewhere in his book, he says, "I did anything to get noticed," but that sounds more programmed than his programs actually are. My hunch is that Mr. Stern is doing what comes naturally, cruel though that may sound. Don't believe his promise that if the people who want him off the air would send him enough money, he'd leave voluntarily. There isn't that much money.</p>
        <p>The memos he received from the WNBC management are almost enough to arouse sympathy even for Howard Stern. Here is one: "I'd appreciate it if you'd discontinue making deprecating remarks regarding the other Talents' capabilities, styles and performances." Depriving a shock jock of deprecation is an outrage against his human rights. Mr. Stern's is a comedy of the put-down, only instead of picking on the polyester and blue-hair crowd, he socks it to currently protected species.</p>
        <p>OF Los Angeles looters, whose excuse is that they cannot find jobs: "Who's going to hire you? You've got 37 earrings in your ear, you look as if you stepped off the set of a rap video, your hat is on backwards and you've got your girlfriend's initials carved into your hair."</p>
        <p>Of Indian immigrants: The men (all of them doctors who don't go back to India to help their own people) "make their wives wear those saris with their bellies flopping out all over the place. . . . And what is it with the dots on their heads?" (The habits of white ethnics seem to escape his notice.)</p>
        <p>Of Oprah Winfrey and the uses of sexual abuse: "She's always testifying before some committee in Washington on child abuse and telling about how she was molested by everybody in her family -- uncles, cousins, guys coming in the door, you name it. No wonder she had to go to Capitol Hill, she had to get out of that house."</p>
        <p>Well, that's the best of Howard Stern. For the worst, buy the book. Along the way, Mr. Stern mentions Lenny Bruce. Although the talents are of different dimensions, there are resemblances: two on-the-edge, over-the-top, in-your-face trashers of the proprieties. But Bruce, a true radical, seemed to be driven by a passion against hypocrisy; he was on a mission. Mr. Stern, powered by the pleasures of exhibition, is just on a kick. Where Lenny Bruce could be cathartic, Howard Stern is strictly laxative.  Walter Goodman is a television critic for The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Walter Goodman is a television critic for The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
