<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children Who Live in Boxes</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="649726"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="CHILDREN'S BOOKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALDERSON, BRIAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SENDAK, MAURICE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">WE ARE ALL IN THE DUMPS WITH JACK AND GUY (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D6123AF937A25752C1A965958260" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children Who Live in Boxes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Brian Alderson;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ALDERSON, BRIAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WE ARE ALL IN THE DUMPS WITH JACK AND GUY Written and illustrated  by Maurice Sendak. Unpaged. New York:  Michael di Capua Books/HarperCollins Publishers. $20. (All ages)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WE ARE ALL IN THE DUMPS WITH JACK AND GUY Written and illustrated  by Maurice Sendak. Unpaged. New York:  Michael di Capua Books/HarperCollins Publishers. $20. (All ages)</p>
        <p>PUT it all down to Randolph Caldecott. As you may know, Maurice Sendak is a devotee of that Victorian picture-book artist, and indeed he designated an early book, "Hector Protector" (1965), "an intentionally contrived homage to this beloved teacher."</p>
        <p>Like "We Are All in the Dumps With Jack and Guy," it was assembled from two English nursery rhymes: "Hector Protector" (who makes an unproductive visit to see the queen) and "As I Went Over the Water" (a nonsense rigmarole). Mr. Sendak transformed those rhymes into small epics by introducing a pictorial narrative that was inspired, but not called for, by the rhymes' slender texts. Caldecott loved to play with such visual counterpointing (the tragic demise of the dish eloping with the spoon; the decrepit beggar man fiddling while bonny lasses and lads dance around the maypole). The exercise probably helped to keep up his interest in his rudimentary copy.</p>
        <p>Such Caldecottian fancies, so playfully presented in "Hector Protector," are now being applied to an altogether darker purpose. This can't really be discussed without an awareness of the two rhymes that are involved:  We are all in the dumps</p>
        <p>For diamonds are trumps</p>
        <p>The kittens are gone to St Paul's!</p>
        <p>The baby is bit</p>
        <p>The moon's in a fit</p>
        <p>And the houses are built without walls.</p>
        <p>Unlike "Hector," Mr. Sendak's newest picture book continues the pictorial narrative into the second rhyme:  Jack and Guy went out in the rye</p>
        <p>And they found a little boy with one black eye.</p>
        <p>Come says Jack let's knock him on the head.</p>
        <p>No says Guy let's buy him some bread.</p>
        <p>You buy one loaf and I'll buy two</p>
        <p>And we'll bring him up as other folk do.</p>
        <p>The interpretation that Mr. Sendak has imposed on these rhymes is not one you might immediately see as sanctioned by the text. The scene is set in a cardboard city more or less beneath the Brooklyn Bridge. Down-and-out kids (some bald, presumably from treatment of AIDS-related cancers) are in tenuous residence there until their little community is disrupted by a pair of rats who steal a small boy and a load of kittens. Jack and Guy give chase, are defeated in a rigged game of bridge and must watch while boy and kittens are carted off to the St. Paul's Bakery and Orphanage.</p>
        <p>The moon, which has been observing these goings-on with dismay, now intervenes to collect Jack and Guy, dressed in old newspapers, and dump them into their own rhyme in a field outside a very sinister St. Paul's Bakery and Orphanage (catchers in the rye). The stolen boy is found, along with two kittens; the angry moon turns into a white cat and demolishes the rats, and everyone returns through the ether to the cardboard city. A winged Mozart is to be seen on the way, conducting the music of the spheres.</p>
        <p>It would be idle to condemn this strange farrago as self-indulgence; that has been a Maurice Sendak prerogative ever since the days of the Wild Things. He knows that he has only to string a few images together for psychologists and semiologists from the West Side to Winnipeg to go on their way rejoicing. But there must have been a more urgent compulsion to direct him to these little-known rhymes and to inspire a parade of packed, claustrophobic images, executed with wondrous powers of color and design.</p>
        <p>Pain and deprivation would seem to be the source. Mr. Sendak apprehends more sharply than many of us how easy has became the descent to limbo, and these Dumps are a cry from wastes. (Surprising not to find T. S. Eliot as epigraph: "I think we are in rats' alley / Where the dead men lost their bones.") The trouble is that we no longer know how to articulate such a cry.</p>
        <p>Things were bad in Caldecott's time too. Victorian writers like Hesba Stretton still strike to the heart in books like "Little Meg's Children," but they do so through direct observation and lucid storytelling -- qualities no longer good enough for semiologists and post-Chagallian man. Only by indirection now do we find directions out. The forced coupling of those nursery rhymes makes very little narrative sense; the wandering moon has to be brought in to weld the disparate elements together; readers must do the best they can with a row of pregnant images and Mr. Sendak's customary esoteric references. A glass tower following the word "trumps" is obvious enough, as are such ironic newspaper ads as "Mortgage Money Available," but you have to be in the know to catch up with yells of "Rascal" and "Thief" (from "Hector Protector") and memorials like "Oct. 17, 1992. Jim Goes Home." (How are children to know that James Marshall, the American author and illustrator, was buried that day, although an angel appears later holding his book "George and Martha"?)</p>
        <p>Certainly, children are as quick at do-it-yourself deconstruction as the rest of us, and they will find their own stories to tell and their own visions in Mr. Sendak's somber picture show -- especially, I hope, in the beautiful Mozartian dona eis requiem of the final page. But I would not force them to it. Guilt, pain and deprivation will be their lot soon enough, and I am not one with John Calvin (or the television news) for giving them an eyeful before their time. Call me escapist, but I would sooner they were dancing round the maypole with the real Randolph Caldecott, or sitting on the stoop outside Rosie's door with such fine Sendak figures as Magic Man and Alinda the lovely lady singer.  CHILDREN'S BOOKS Brian Alderson, the children's books editor for The Times of London, has completed a two-volume study of the American illustrator Ezra Jack Keats.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Brian Alderson, the children's books editor for The Times of London, has completed a two-volume study of the American illustrator Ezra Jack Keats.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
