<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BOLDFACE NAMES</title>
    <meta content="19BOLD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/03/19/nyregion/19BOLD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1377024"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Boldface Names"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Symphony Orchestra</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Minnelli, Liza</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gest, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Daschle, Tom (Sen)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sweet Smell of Success, the (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Boldface Names</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Regent Wall Street</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E3DE1538F93AA25750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BOLDFACE NAMES</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Witness at the Reception</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Barron</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Boldface Names column reports on wedding of Liza Minnelli and David Gest, Sen Tom Daschle's performance as narrator of Aaron Copland's Lincoln Portrait with National Symphony in Rapid City, SD, and party for opening of Sweet Smell of Success on Broadway; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Witness at the Reception</p>
        <p>These are scenes from a wedding, not to be confused with the Ingmar Bergman film ''Scenes From a Marriage.'' Actually, these are scenes from the reception that followed the wedding of LIZA MINNELLI and DAVID GEST, as described by a guest who saw JANET LEIGH arriving at the Regent Wall Street Hotel on the arm of TITO JACKSON. They had ridden to the hotel from the Marble Collegiate Church in a limousine with almost enough Jacksons inside for a family reunion.</p>
        <p>But MICHAEL JACKSON, who had been a best man at the wedding, was not with Miss Leigh or his brothers. Of the 1,150 guests, he was the only one who went in by a back entrance, a spokeswoman for the hotel said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The reception following Liza Minnelli's wedding resulted in some great publicity for the Regent Wall Street Hotel.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Witness at the Reception</p>
        <p>These are scenes from a wedding, not to be confused with the Ingmar Bergman film ''Scenes From a Marriage.'' Actually, these are scenes from the reception that followed the wedding of LIZA MINNELLI and DAVID GEST, as described by a guest who saw JANET LEIGH arriving at the Regent Wall Street Hotel on the arm of TITO JACKSON. They had ridden to the hotel from the Marble Collegiate Church in a limousine with almost enough Jacksons inside for a family reunion.</p>
        <p>But MICHAEL JACKSON, who had been a best man at the wedding, was not with Miss Leigh or his brothers. Of the 1,150 guests, he was the only one who went in by a back entrance, a spokeswoman for the hotel said.</p>
        <p>Then there was ALLAN J. LAZARE, a holder of patent No. 4,657,758 and one of the ushers, talking with GINA LOLLOBRIGIDA, above, who starred in ''When Love Calls'' and ''The Bride Can't Wait.'' This was around the time Miss Lollobrigida stumbled and almost fell.</p>
        <p>''The wig was moving,'' said another woman who watched the fast footwork that kept her from ''wiping out'' on the red carpet. ''She sort of had to catch herself, and then she had to adjust the wig. It was, like, bouffant style.'' (By the way, patent No. 4,657,758 was for Plax, the predental rinse.)</p>
        <p>The guest who saw Miss Lollobrigida stumble also described an encounter between JOE BOLOGNA (who is rather tall) and MICKEY ROONEY (who is not). It began with Mr. Bologna picking up Mr. Rooney just to give him a hug and continued with a lengthy, four-feet-on-the-floor conversation.</p>
        <p>What with the deal that sold the right to cover the wedding to the British magazine OK!, some wedding-watchers wondered whether the hotel had opened its doors for free, in return for the publicity. Not so, said CHRISTOPHER KNABLE, the hotel's president and managing director. ''They paid, and paid handsomely,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Stand-In for Mr. Lincoln</p>
        <p>This is what he said. This is what TOM DASCHLE said.</p>
        <p>The only difference between those two sentences and what Mr. Daschle said on Sunday night in Rapid City, S.D., is that he said ''Abraham Lincoln'' instead of his own name. As the narrator in a performance of Aaron Copland's ''Lincoln Portrait,'' Mr. Daschle was just following the script, which Copland created using Abraham Lincoln's writings and biographical information.</p>
        <p>Mr. Daschle appeared with the National Symphony, whose music director, LEONARD SLATKIN, above, gave him a good review. ''I think he was a little nervous, but once he got out there, he didn't show it,'' said Mr. Slatkin, who has conducted the piece with narrators like GEN. H. NORMAN SCHWARZKOPF; SENATOR EDWARD M. KENNEDY; and J. DENNIS HASTERT, the speaker of the House. ''I never think of him so much as an orator, but a kind of plain-spoken-type person, and at the concert, he really let go. It was quite astonishing.''</p>
        <p>Taking Fashion Notes</p>
        <p>The producer MARTIN RICHARDS, who has some rather spectacular ruby cuff links and shirt studs that were given to him by his late wife, wore aquamarine cuff links and studs to the opening of the musical ''Sweet Smell of Success.'' ''They're my birthstone,'' he said before the post-performance dinner at the Waldorf-Astoria Hotel.</p>
        <p>At his table were PATRICIA NEAL (who also attended the Minnelli-Gest wedding on Saturday) and MICHELLE HERBERT, who was wearing a black spangled BOB MACKIE dress with a spider-web back. Mr. Mackie is the designer who did Ms. Minnelli's wedding gown.</p>
        <p>HELEN GURLEY BROWN, above, whose husband, DAVID, was also a producer of ''Sweet Smell,'' said she had not done any special shopping in anticipation of the opening. ''This is a 102-year-old Calvin Klein sheath,'' she said of the black spaghetti-strap number she was wearing under what she described as ''an Adolfo jacket nearly as old.''</p>
        <p>''I feel fashion is to play with,'' said Mrs. Brown, who set trends for the fashion-conscious when she was editor of Cosmopolitan, ''and if you don't like what's shown this year, don't buy it.''</p>
        <p>Boldface Names</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
