<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Islanders Are No Doormats As Rangers Come Visiting</title>
    <meta content="27ISLE$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="976147"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Rangers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Bashir, Tarik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E0DF123AF934A15752C1A961958260" item-length="833" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Islanders Are No Doormats As Rangers Come Visiting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARIK EL-BASHIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Bashir, Tarik</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., Nov. 26</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Islanders defeat New York Rangers at Nassau Coliseum, 4-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has been difficult to gauge these Islanders. One game they are pulling off the unlikeliest of upsets. Then, a few days later, they are struggling against one of the Eastern Conference's worst teams.</p>
        <p>It had been a week since the Islanders beat the defending champion Red Wings in Detroit, a few days since they lost to the lowly Buffalo Sabres.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has been difficult to gauge these Islanders. One game they are pulling off the unlikeliest of upsets. Then, a few days later, they are struggling against one of the Eastern Conference's worst teams.</p>
        <p>It had been a week since the Islanders beat the defending champion Red Wings in Detroit, a few days since they lost to the lowly Buffalo Sabres.</p>
        <p>But as they have done so often this season, the Islanders rebounded from a miserable loss with one of their better overall performances of the season, getting three goals from Robert Reichel as they beat the Rangers, 4-1, before a crowd of 16,297 at a sold-out Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>It was the Islanders' second defeat of the Rangers at the Coliseum this season.</p>
        <p>''We are trying to figure ourselves out,'' said Islanders defenseman Kenny Jonsson, who scored a goal and assisted on another tonight. ''We've talked about it, we need to have some consistency. We need to put the same effort every night. We need to stay disciplined.''</p>
        <p>With tonight's victory, the Islanders, at 10-10-4, are back at .500 and have a 1-point lead on the Rangers in the Atlantic Division. ''This was one of our best games all year,'' Islanders Coach Rick Bowness said.</p>
        <p>Tonight's game was the third of six meetings between the teams this season. The Islanders won by 5-3 at the Coliseum last month and the teams tied, 2-2, in the season opener at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>Aleksei Kovalev scored late in the game for the Rangers, who were 0-5 on the power play and struggled again tonight to get any sustained pressure in the offensive zone.</p>
        <p>The Islanders, who were buoyed by Tommy Salo's 17 saves and got back the defensemen Bryan Berard and Rich Pilon from injuries, had appeared to be finally playing up to their potential when they beat the Red Wings. But then came successive road losses to the streaking Devils, 5-1, followed by the 6-1 loss to the Sabres, the Islanders' worst defeats of the season.</p>
        <p>The Rangers (8-11-7) weren't in much better shape coming into tonight's game. It had been 24 hours since the emotional return of Mark Messier to the Garden. Messier, the former Rangers captain who led the team to the Stanley Cup championship in 1994 and was signed by Vancouver as a free agent this summer, scored a goal to help beat the Rangers, 4-2.</p>
        <p>As is the case with all Islander-Ranger games, emotions ran high on the ice and in the stands. In the span of 10 minutes in the second period, there were four minor skirmishes. Fourteen penalties in all were called in the second period, one of which led to an Islanders' second goal.</p>
        <p>Reichel, who has 12 goals and 27 points this season, opened the scoring less than two minutes into the game. The score was set up by a couple of precise passes. The first was a break-out pass from Zigmund Palffy, who found Sergei Nemchinov streaking down the right boards. Nemchinov skated the puck into the Rangers' end, stopped to let Jeff Beukeboom overskate the play and delivered a pass squarely onto the stick of Reichel, who beat Mike Richter over the shoulder.</p>
        <p>Jonsson gave the Islanders what proved to be the winning goal on the power play at 15 minutes 4 seconds of the second period. The puck deflected off the stick of the Rangers' Mike Keane, who was attempting to block Jonsson's pass from the point but instead steered it past Richter.</p>
        <p>Reichel scored the Islanders' third goal at 11:20 of the third period. He executed the give-and-go perfectly with Bryan Smolinski, who returned the puck to Reichel as he streaked to the net.</p>
        <p>Reichel's third goal, at 14:46, brought the hats onto the ice. He sneaked behind the Rangers net to redirect Jonnson's slap shot from the point.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Islander defenseman DENNIS VASKE, who is sidelined with a mild concussion, his third in three seasons, met with General Manager MIKE MILBURY and the team's physician, Dr. ELLIOT PELLMAN, before Wednesday night's game to discuss his future with the team, and perhaps his future in hockey. Vaske has missed 115 games during the past three seasons with the concussions. Milbury said that Vaske will seek the opinion of doctors outside the organization. ''The concussions aren't the issue,'' Milbury said. ''The issue is that Dennis suffers from post-concussion syndrome.''</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
