<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>When Strawberry Speaks About Drugs, Kids Listen</title>
    <meta content="22YANK$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="917293"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curry, Jack</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Strawberry, Darryl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807EEDE153BF931A15750C0A961958260" item-length="617" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>When Strawberry Speaks About Drugs, Kids Listen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Curry, Jack</byline>
      <dateline>TAMPA, Fla., March 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seventh-graders at Oak Grove Junior High School in Tampa, Fla, listen in rapt attention as Darryl Strawberry talks to them about drugs and how they almost ruined his life (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Everywhere Darryl Strawberry turned, another seventh-grader pointed at him or posed a question. He could not budge an inch after completing a speech denouncing drugs, alcohol, guns and gangs to three dozen students inside the cozy library at Oak Grove Junior High School.</p>
        <p>Eventually, the students who are part of an alternative learning program escorted their guest to an auditorium, where 350 classmates with perfect attendance were waiting to hear more inspirational words from Strawberry. They watched a student introduce him, watched him rise from one of the folding chairs on the stage and then listened for the next 30 minutes as the Yankee outfielder lectured them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Everywhere Darryl Strawberry turned, another seventh-grader pointed at him or posed a question. He could not budge an inch after completing a speech denouncing drugs, alcohol, guns and gangs to three dozen students inside the cozy library at Oak Grove Junior High School.</p>
        <p>Eventually, the students who are part of an alternative learning program escorted their guest to an auditorium, where 350 classmates with perfect attendance were waiting to hear more inspirational words from Strawberry. They watched a student introduce him, watched him rise from one of the folding chairs on the stage and then listened for the next 30 minutes as the Yankee outfielder lectured them.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to die because of drugs,'' said Strawberry, looking more statuesque than 6 feet 6 inches with some of the 12- and 13-year-olds sitting behind him. ''I wanted to give up on life because of drugs. Somewhere, there was a little hope that kept me encouraged that I could make a change. I did.''</p>
        <p>Strawberry switched from speaker to slugger when he doubled in a run and Kenny Rogers pitched six more snazzy innings -- decreasing his earned run average to 0.90 -- in the Yankees' 4-3 exhibition victory over the Detroit Tigers tonight. But Rogers admitted he must be careful throwing breaking pitches after surgery on his elbow and shoulder during the off season.</p>
        <p>''I still have to be cautious,'' Rogers said. ''It tells me, at times, that I'm not ready to do some things.''</p>
        <p>Earlier, in the auditorium, an overhead fan hummed as Strawberry spoke, but the same noisy kids who had jostled to snag a good seat were silent. Their eyes bulged when Strawberry talked about how drugs almost ruined his life, about how they should turn their backs when someone offers drugs and about how speaking with them is a significant part of his recovery.</p>
        <p>''I'm content with never hitting another home run as long as I put myself with God and am a good person and a good speaker,'' Strawberry said. ''It's about giving back.''</p>
        <p>Brenda Kearse, the school principal, said the main problems for her students are family issues, poor reading scores and more family issues, shaking her head as she revealed how one seventh-grade girl in the Hillsborough County school district committed suicide after getting a shoddy report card.</p>
        <p>''These kids are dealing with death and things like AIDS at such a young age,'' Kearse said. ''It's not the 'Ozzie and Harriet' days anymore.''</p>
        <p>Of Strawberry's appearance, Kearse said: ''I know he got through to them. This was the best assembly I've ever seen.''</p>
        <p>One boy asked Strawberry of what it felt like to want to die.</p>
        <p>''You go into a deep depression and you don't want to go forward any more,'' Strawberry said. ''That's what happens to people when they get involved with drugs. It makes you depressed and makes you want to just give up.''</p>
        <p>But Strawberry did not give up. That was his message.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DWIGHT GOODEN was relieved after a Yankee doctor told him that the result of his 24-hour blood-pressure and heart-rate test had come back normal and that the pitcher would not need to take medication or adjust his diet. The Yankees would not disclose Gooden's blood-pressure reading, which was found to be high in a February physical and which doctors told him was probably related to stress from his father's death earlier this year. . . . DON MATTINGLY's No. 23 will be retired on Aug. 31 before an interleague game against the Montreal Expos at Yankee Stadium. Mattingly will become the 15th Yankee to have his number retired.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
