<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arts Briefing</title>
    <meta content="24ARTS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Education; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1483381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Visas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kissing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iran</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bard College</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Symphony Orchestra</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Philharmonic</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">mobile symphony</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metropolitan Museum of Art (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orquesta Aragon (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kheirandish, gowhar</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zamani, Ali</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Gelder, Lawrence</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gehry, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Botstein, Leon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Racine, Jean (1639-99)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Masur, Kurt</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beethoven, Ludwig Van (1770-1827)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shankar, Anoushka</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Phedre (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iran</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kissing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07E6DE1F3AF937A15757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1762" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arts Briefing</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Lawrence Van Gelder</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Gelder, Lawrence</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iranian actress Gowhar Kheirandish gets suspended sentence of 74 lashes after apologizing for kissing director Ali Zamani, young student of her late husband, at film festival awards ceremony; both were arrested for allegedly trying to harm Islam; Bard College's new $62 million performing arts center, Annandale-on-Hudson, NY, designed by Frank Gehry, will open with American Symphony Orchestra concert led by Leon Botstein, Bard's president, and performance of Racine's play Phedre; Kurt Masur, New York Philharmonic's director emeritus, to lead orchestra in series of concerts; Mobile Symphony to perform United States premiere of recently reconstructed short fragment of Beethoven concerto, Mobile, Ala; sitar player Anoushka Shankar to perform at Metropolitan Museum of Art; Cuba's Orquesta Aragon gets visas in time to perform in New York; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HIGHLIGHTS</p>
        <p>IRAN: THE FORBIDDEN KISS -- A well-known Iranian actress has received a suspended sentence of 74 lashes for kissing a director at an awards ceremony. The actress, Gowhar Kheirandish, who is in her late 40's, attracted arrest and religious condemnation when she kissed the director, Ali Zamani, in his 20's, who had been a student of her late husband. Immediately after the kiss, Mr. Zamani apologized, saying the gesture at a film festival last October in the city of Yazd was spontaneous. ''She kissed me like a mother kisses her child,'' Mr. Zamani said, the BBC reported. Nevertheless the local justice department ordered the arrest of Ms. Kheirandish and Mr. Zamani, and religious leaders depicted their act as an attempt to harm Islam. Physical contact between unmarried and unrelated men and women is forbidden. Mr. Zamani was released on bail of $2,500, and the lashing sentence imposed on Ms. Kheirandish was suspended after she apologized.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HIGHLIGHTS</p>
        <p>IRAN: THE FORBIDDEN KISS -- A well-known Iranian actress has received a suspended sentence of 74 lashes for kissing a director at an awards ceremony. The actress, Gowhar Kheirandish, who is in her late 40's, attracted arrest and religious condemnation when she kissed the director, Ali Zamani, in his 20's, who had been a student of her late husband. Immediately after the kiss, Mr. Zamani apologized, saying the gesture at a film festival last October in the city of Yazd was spontaneous. ''She kissed me like a mother kisses her child,'' Mr. Zamani said, the BBC reported. Nevertheless the local justice department ordered the arrest of Ms. Kheirandish and Mr. Zamani, and religious leaders depicted their act as an attempt to harm Islam. Physical contact between unmarried and unrelated men and women is forbidden. Mr. Zamani was released on bail of $2,500, and the lashing sentence imposed on Ms. Kheirandish was suspended after she apologized.</p>
        <p>OPENING FESTIVITIES AT BARD -- Now comes opening night. The scene is Frank Gehry's new Richard B. Fisher Center for the Performing Arts at Bard College in Annandale-on-Hudson, N.Y. This $62 million, 107,612-square-foot complex, with two theaters, rehearsal studios and classrooms, will open with two weekends of celebration intended to showcase its 900-seat Sosnoff Theater and 200-seat Theater Two. The official opening night performance takes place tomorrow at 8 in the Sosnoff, when Leon Botstein, Bard's president and the music director of the American Symphony Orchestra, will lead that ensemble in Mahler's Symphony No. 3. At noon Saturday in the Sosnoff Theater Mr. Botstein, Mr. Gehry and the director JoAnne Akalaitis, among others, will take part in a discussion of the creation of the center. At 5 p.m. the scene will shift to Theater Two for a performance of Racine's ''Phèdre,'' directed by Ms. Akalaitis. At 2 p.m. Sunday, selections from 13 years of the Bard Music Festival will be played by various artists in the Sosnoff. When the opening celebration continues from May 1 to May 3, highlights will include performances by the Merce Cunningham Dance Company and the Kronos Quartet, the Ballet Hispanico, and the Charles Mingus Orchestra with Elvis Costello as special guest.</p>
        <p>KURT MASUR'S RETURN -- It's homecoming time for Kurt Masur, right. Now the music director emeritus of the New York Philharmonic, Mr. Masur will return to Avery Fisher Hall for a series of concerts from 7:30 tonight through May 10 that feature world and New York premieres and the first Philharmonic appearance since 1994 of the pianist Maurizio Pollini. The first program, to be repeated at 11 a.m. tomorrow, 8 p.m. Saturday and 7:30 p.m. Tuesday, includes works by Brahms and Dvorak and the New York premiere of André Previn's Violin Concerto. Concerts on May 1, 2 and 3 bring the world premiere of Lukas Foss's Concertino, ''Passacaglia, Bachanalia, Passacaglia.'' Also dedicated to Mr. Masur is another Philharmonic commission, Siegfried Matthus's ''Concerto for Two'' (trumpet and trombone), to be heard in its world premiere on May 7 and 8. Mr. Pollini will perform on May 9 and 10, when the program includes Beethoven's ''Emperor'' Concerto.</p>
        <p>MOBILE, ALA.: A BEETHOVEN PREMIERE -- When it comes to frequency of appearance in the 21st century, hen's teeth and Beethoven (1770-1827) premieres might run a good race. Nevertheless, what is billed as the United States premiere of some Beethoven music is on the schedule for 8 p.m. Saturday at the Saenger Theater in Mobile, Ala., where the Mobile Symphony, under Scott Speck, will end its season. The piece in question is an eight-minute fragment of a Concerto for Oboe and Orchestra, written by Beethoven when he was in his early 20's. Dutch musicologists, working from a discovery in the British Library of the opening bars of each movement, reconstructed the slow, melodic largo movement. The reconstituted music was given its world premiere by the Rotterdam Chamber Orchestra in the Netherlands in March.</p>
        <p>RAGAS IN THE TEMPLE OF DENDUR -- When it comes to sitar virtuosity, it's all in the family, if the family happens to be the family of Ravi Shankar. For evidence look no further than Anoushka Shankar, who will perform at 7 p.m. Saturday in the Temple of Dendur at the Metropolitan Museum of Art. Ms. Shankar, above right, began to study and  perform with her father when she was 9, playing a baby sitar built specially for her. At 13 she made her public debut and her first recording. Now 20, Ms. Shankar, a veteran of world tours and recording studios and now also a conductor, will perform ragas composed by her father with musicians, like the tabla player Tanmoy Bose, who have worked with him.</p>
        <p>FOOTNOTES</p>
        <p>With two days to go before its concert at 8 p.m. tomorrow in Town Hall, the renowned Cuban charanga band Orquesta Aragón received its visas. So under the auspices of the World Music Institute, the show, by the orchestra that has been performing all over the world for 60 years, will go on. The band, founded in 1939 in the central Cuban port of Cienfuegos by the double bass player Orestes Aragón Cantero, specializes in what Jon Pareles of The New York Times described in a 2001 review as ''the elegant, lighter-than-air swing of old Cuban styles, particularly its specialty, the cha-cha.'' . . . Hudson Shad, the sextet that specializes in the music of the Comedian Harmonists, whose vast popularity in pre-World War II Germany was undone by the Nazis, will perform at 9 p.m. tomorrow in the spring cabaret series at Café Sabarsky in the Neue Galerie at 1048 Fifth Avenue, at 86th Street.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
