<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yale Clerical Workers Strike as Talks Stall</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="828501"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRIKES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">YALE UNIVERSITY YALE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HONAN, WILLIAM H</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Strikes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0D71439F93BA35751C0A960958260" item-length="528" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yale Clerical Workers Strike as Talks Stall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM H. HONAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HONAN, WILLIAM H</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN, Feb. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Clerical workers at Yale University went on strike this morning, setting up picket lines that led many professors to hold classes off campus in churches, movie theaters and private homes.</p>
        <p>The walkout came less than a month after graduate teaching assistants abandoned a job action involving the withholding of students' grades. They had begun the action in an attempt to win recognition for their union, but they did  not succeed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Clerical workers at Yale University went on strike this morning, setting up picket lines that led many professors to hold classes off campus in churches, movie theaters and private homes.</p>
        <p>The walkout came less than a month after graduate teaching assistants abandoned a job action involving the withholding of students' grades. They had begun the action in an attempt to win recognition for their union, but they did  not succeed.</p>
        <p>Union leaders said that nearly 2,000 workers, who handle much of the paperwork on campus, had set a one-month deadline for the first phase of the strike. If the contract dispute is not resolved in that time, they said, maintenance, dining hall and custodial workers will follow. All belong to locals of the Federation of University Employees. The average salary of the clerical workers is $25,000 a year; the other workers are paid an average of $30,000.</p>
        <p>The unions are seeking raises, better pension benefits and an end to subcontracting with nonunion labor, but their major concern is job security.</p>
        <p>"People don't go on strike for a quarter-an-hour raise," Deborah Chernoff, a  union spokeswoman, said. "They feel their livelihood is being threatened."</p>
        <p>The unions today offered to submit the dispute to binding arbitration, but university negotiators refused.</p>
        <p>For its part, the university, which has been running an operating deficit for five years, is seeking changes in the contract to help hold down costs by means  of what a spokesman, Gary Fryer, calls "greater freedom to manage its work force." That might entail the hiring of outside workers and the creation of a two-tier pay scale so that new employees would earn less and have less costly benefits than present staff members.</p>
        <p>Student opinion about the strike was mixed. Ramzi Zein, a fifth-year economics student, said: "I fully sympathize with the strikers. What they're doing is necessary to keep the administration in check."</p>
        <p>Other students seemed indifferent. Kevin Shertzer, a junior majoring in history, said: "It's like the O. J. Simpson trial. You hear so much about it, you turn your ears off."</p>
        <p>Craig Yacks, a sophomore majoring in American Studies, spoke for many students when he said, "As long as it doesn't affect me, I'm not interested."</p>
        <p>Yale has a long history of labor disputes. Although the last two contracts were settled amicably, in 1984 a 10-week strike closed campus dining halls, and  in 1977, the university endured a 13-week labor dispute. There were also walkouts in 1971 and 1974.</p>
        <p>Ms. Chernoff charged that Yale was "more interested in the bottom line than in living up to its lofty ideals."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Fryer contended that union demands for improved benefits were farfetched since Yale already provides "the most generous benefits package" of any competing university in the country, including free health insurance and up  to $8,400 a year in scholarship aid per child for the children of workers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
