<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greenpoint Residents See Change, but Not All Object</title>
    <meta content="03NABE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/05/03/nyregion/03nabe.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1669585"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Brooklyn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E1D71F31F930A35756C0A9639C8B63" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greenpoint Residents See Change, but Not All Object</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Greenpoint Residents See Change, but Not All Object</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREEM FAHIM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Verity Liljedahl's face fell yesterday when she spotted the drilling machines extracting soil samples from the earth underneath an abandoned loading dock on the waterfront in Greenpoint, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''They're going to put buildings here,'' she said, her voice working against the loud, pneumatic cadence of the machines as two land surveyors measured the loading dock. ''It would be a big pain to live across the street from a construction site.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Verity Liljedahl's face fell yesterday when she spotted the drilling machines extracting soil samples from the earth underneath an abandoned loading dock on the waterfront in Greenpoint, Brooklyn.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Verity Liljedahl's face fell yesterday when she spotted the drilling machines extracting soil samples from the earth underneath an abandoned loading dock on the waterfront in Greenpoint, Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>''They're going to put buildings here,'' she said, her voice working against the loud, pneumatic cadence of the machines as two land surveyors measured the loading dock. ''It would be a big pain to live across the street from a construction site.''</p>
        <p>There will be many more surveyors, and loud machinery, around the waterfront in coming months. City officials agreed yesterday to let developers make over a 175-block area of Greenpoint and Williamsburg, changing it from a graveyard of abandoned industrial sites to a green promenade buffeted by new buildings.</p>
        <p>And behind West Street, in the neighborhood's row houses, bars, Colonials and butcher shops, residents and business owners were bracing for change.</p>
        <p>Ms. Liljedahl, 36, a freelance writer who has lived for three years with her male companion in a loft on West Street, 100 yards or so from the East River, said she welcomed development of the waterfront and especially the proposed restoration of a nearby park with swimming pools and volleyball courts, part of New York City's Olympic bid. But she cringes at the thought of the new residential towers, and the people who will live in them.</p>
        <p>''We can see the tippity-top of the Empire State Building,'' she said. ''As soon as the development begins, the secret is gone.''</p>
        <p>As far as Doris Niles is concerned, Greenpoint's secrets were out long ago. Ms. Niles, who moved to Franklin Street from Bedford-Stuyvesant with her family more than 30 years ago, pointed from her doorway to a new bar that had opened down the street. ''I don't object to people having fun,'' she said, ''but they're out here making noise at 3, 4 in the morning.''</p>
        <p>She said she did not oppose the idea of development, especially if someone can figure out a way to make the Newtown Creek stop smelling so foul.</p>
        <p>But the newcomers would be the ''upper classes'' from places like SoHo, Ms. Niles said, and the character of the area would change. ''It was all hard-working people when we moved here,'' she said. ''Plumbers, electricians, guys who worked for the Sanitation Department.''</p>
        <p>Like Ms. Liljedahl, Ms. Niles said she would miss her view of Manhattan if residential towers rise on the waterfront. Every year, on the Fourth of July, she and her daughter, Carolyn Davis, watch the fireworks, unobstructed, on the East River. ''We sit out there, and get hit with elderberries from our tree,'' Ms. Davis said.</p>
        <p>A few blocks from Ms. Niles's house, the three owners of a bar called the Pencil Factory -- which is across the street from an old pencil factory -- cautiously welcomed the city's plan.</p>
        <p>''I accept that change is part of the aging process of any neighborhood,'' said Louise Favier, 41, an owner. ''The concern, of course, is affordable housing, access to the park and the effect on the neighborhood. The lovely thing here is the village feeling. You've got your butcher, your baker, your candlestick maker.''</p>
        <p>But with good urban planning, she said, residents and visitors will eventually be able to enjoy the waterfront, which is currently off limits. And of course, new residents would mean more business for the bar.</p>
        <p>''It's like Hoboken,'' Ms. Favier said. ''It looks at the city, and people love it.''</p>
        <p>Anna Mierzwinski, who has owned Staropolski Meat Market and Deli on Manhattan Avenue in Greenpoint for 15 years, unapologetically embraces the development plans. ''It will be great,'' she said, various dried meats dangling in front of her. ''It will be more people. It will be more fun. It will be more business.''</p>
        <p>Staropolski, which she said meant ''old-style Poland,'' mainly caters to Greenpoint's large Polish population, but she has customers from all over. Many of her fellow Polish immigrants -- like herself -- have made enough money to move away from Greenpoint, to the suburbs.</p>
        <p>''We need more restaurants here,'' she said. ''We need galleries. I have children, so I know what they like. Parks are O.K. But we need something.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday was Irene Wahlberg's 58th birthday, and as she walked along Calyer Street during her lunch break, she recalled the old days when there was always a seat from Greenpoint on the subway to Manhattan.</p>
        <p>She said she looks out at the water every day from her desk at Penguin Air Conditioning, where she works as the receptionist. She has lived her whole life in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''Everyone who lived here, worked here,'' she said. ''Everyone knows everyone's business.''</p>
        <p>Now, she said, all that will change.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
