<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Down East</title>
    <meta content="26REEDLT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034680"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reid, Van</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Reed, Kit</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Cordelia Underwood (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E7DB1530F935A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="738" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Down East</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Kit Reed</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Reed, Kit</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kit Reed reviews book Cordelia Underwood. Or the Marvelous Beginnings of the Moosepath League by Van Reid (M)2</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cordelia Underwood</p>
        <p>Or the Marvelous Beginnings</p>
        <p>of the Moosepath League.</p>
        <p>By Van Reid.</p>
        <p>400 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cordelia Underwood</p>
        <p>Or the Marvelous Beginnings</p>
        <p>of the Moosepath League.</p>
        <p>By Van Reid.</p>
        <p>400 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Viking. $24.95.</p>
        <p>THE more savage and risky the future, the more we fall in love with the past -- with those sweet, safe summer nights in some small town where adults murmured on wide porches and children collected fireflies. It was never quite like that, but nostalgia seduces us. Tensed for the millennium, who isn't tempted?</p>
        <p>In his amiable, richly populated first novel, a bookseller from Maine named Van Reid draws a past that should soothe even the twitchiest reader. His re-creation of the summer of 1896 has its mishaps and villains, but it's so sunny that even the violence isn't too scary. Part of a projected trilogy, ''Cordelia Underwood'' first appeared in installments in a regional newspaper, The Lincoln Weekly. Diffuse and leisurely, the novel seems designed for long afternoons in a hammock.</p>
        <p>Dozens of characters amble in. Every one of them has a story and is spoiling to tell it. There's the mysterious seaman who visits the Underwoods and their spirited daughter, Cordelia. Next come the crusty denizens of Portland's harbor, who sometimes speak in verse. They are closely followed by courtly Tobias Walton, assorted Underwood relatives and a pair of love interests for Cordelia. Then there are the founders of the Moosepath League, followed by brigands, rustics and the mysterious Sir Eustace Pembleton and his child lieutenant, who chug up and down the coast in a miniature steamboat. Oops. Let's not forget Sundry Moss and Ducky Planke.</p>
        <p>The narrative waters off this carefully researched patch of Maine are thick with red herrings, and the story is so laced with outside events -- the balloon ascension, the ghost ship, the escaped bear -- that it takes time to get moving, but the sheer geniality of it all keeps the reader in the tent. The mysterious seaman stirs things up with big news: It seems that Cordelia's late uncle, Basil, has left her some property in northern Maine. Oh yes, and a cryptic note.</p>
        <p>When the family goes to the wharf to collect Basil's sea chest, Cordelia saves Tobias Walton from falling into the harbor. Topping herself, Cordelia is saved from the drink by the dashing John Benning. Meanwhile (and there are a lot of meanwhiles), three silly charmers named Ephram, Eagleton and Thump converge on Portland for their 14th annual Fourth of July celebration -- and the glamorous Mrs. Roberto's jaunt in her balloon. Inspired by a news item, the three decide to form a club. What shall they call it? Without telling Tobias, they make him chairman of the Moosepath League.</p>
        <p>Complications abound. Tobias rides a runaway wagon and is at the deathbed of the last survivor of a drowned ship when its phantom crew comes for him; he also goes with the sheriff to hunt smugglers. He catches that escaped bear (whose name, by the way, is Maude) and is so delighted when she stands on her head that he refuses to shoot her. In the realm of plentiful meanwhiles, the Underwoods have joined forces with Cordelia's great-aunt Delia, aunt Grace and cousins to inspect her land. They puzzle over Basil's mystifying note: ''Our Minmaneth is a young goatt.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps because it's gentler than the future, the imagined American past seems to encourage stylistic liberties and excesses. (''It is fortunate that human ears do not independently cock toward interesting sounds, or those people in the immediate vicinity would have looked much like a kennel when the fox horn is blown.'') And there's a liberal sprinkling of cliches. Never mind. Reid's gazillion characters sparkle. Their collective adventures are engaging and (especially when talking in concert or at cross-purposes) they can be funny.</p>
        <p>In a society populated by sterling types and delightful ninnies, even the villains are decent sorts. Escapists will be charmed by what the author, in an endnote, describes as a ''world of decency and kindness, goodness and laughter,'' in which there's plenty going on and nothing too terrible ever happens.</p>
        <p>Kit Reed's latest book is a collection of stories, ''Weird Women, Wired Women.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Kit Reed's latest book is a collection of stories, ''Weird Women, Wired Women.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
