<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Disease Detector at White Plains Center</title>
    <meta content="26SCAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Heart</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nerves and Nervous System</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Positron Emission Tomography (Pet)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">White Plains Hospital Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wetzler, Cynthia Magriel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nerves and Nervous System</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cancer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Anatomy and Physiology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE0DE1439F935A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="1065" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Disease Detector at White Plains Center</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA MAGRIEL WETZLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wetzler, Cynthia Magriel</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>White Plains Hospital Center in White Plains, NY, acquires Positron Emission Tomography (PET) scanner, only one in Westchester County, that detects and diagnoses cancer, heart disease and neurological disorders; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE patient lies on a comfortable table. He or she has fasted and has been given a radioactive sugar solution through an IV.</p>
        <p>After waiting 60 minutes for the radioactive sugar to become distributed in the organs, the patient is moved slowly through a large ring-like scanner to a position where the scanner can detect high-energy gamma rays emitted from the radioactive sugar. Because most tumors metabolize sugar at higher rates than normal tissue, the resulting images, which are 95 percent accurate, can reveal ''hot spots'' or areas of brighter intensity that most often signal disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE patient lies on a comfortable table. He or she has fasted and has been given a radioactive sugar solution through an IV.</p>
        <p>After waiting 60 minutes for the radioactive sugar to become distributed in the organs, the patient is moved slowly through a large ring-like scanner to a position where the scanner can detect high-energy gamma rays emitted from the radioactive sugar. Because most tumors metabolize sugar at higher rates than normal tissue, the resulting images, which are 95 percent accurate, can reveal ''hot spots'' or areas of brighter intensity that most often signal disease.</p>
        <p>This highly sophisticated imaging technology is called Positron Emission Tomography or PET.</p>
        <p>The White Plains Hospital Center in White Plains has recently acquired a PET. scanner, one of 75 scanners in the United States, 13 in New York and the only one in Westchester. It is the most advanced detector available for diagnosing cancer, heart disease and neurological disorders.</p>
        <p>The PET scanner has the ability to delve deeper than ever before into the mysteries of disease. It can produce images of biological failure of an organ undetectable in other imaging techniques such as CAT (Computerized Axial Tomography) or M.R.I. (Magnetic Resonance Imaging.)</p>
        <p>''PET can determine metabolic change or functional change in an organ,'' said Dr. Andrew De Rogatis, chief of nuclear medicine at the White Plains Hospital Center. ''Other imaging techniques just show us anatomical enlargement or gross anatomical changes in a structure.''</p>
        <p>Since metabolic change occurs before anatomic change, earlier detection of disease is possible. ''Differentiating, for example, post-operative scars or scars from old infections in the lung from tumors is really PET in a nutshell,'' Dr. De Rogatis said. ''If you see a blob of gray on a CAT scan you don't know if it's a scar or a tumor. Before PET, we would do perhaps several procedures to find out what was benign or not.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Arthur Lerner, medical director of the cancer program at the White Plains Hospital Center and director of surgery, said: ''PET is going to eliminate what is done conventionally to determine malignancy. We're high, for example, on M.R.I. of the breast, but those tests can produce difficult interpretations.  Now here comes the PET scan to clarify things. You don't have to biopsy if something abnormal is seen on an M.R.I. It has saved me a lot of sleepless nights. If I take one step back and think about it, it's astounding. What you see for the near and far future in the utilization of PET has no bounds.'' PET is not a screening device, Dr. De Rogatis explained.  ''The scanner cost $2 million, and the procedure costs the patient $2,000,'' he said. ''Most insurance companies do not cover this procedure. We're fighting this.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Lerner added: ''We conference with colleagues in radiology so as not to abuse or misuse it. When used properly it enlarges the team of people involved with patients. Imaging is inseparable from what we do clinically and has become very sophisticated, very complicated and very important.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Lerner continued: ''A nurse in the hospital had a breast M.R.I., which showed a little blip. Could this be cancer? The PET scan came out negative. This gave us confidence to put her in a follow-up group.''</p>
        <p>An M.R.I. can be abnormal with hormone therapy or birth control pills, Dr. Lerner added. ''We take the patient off these, wait four to six months, then do a PET scan,'' he said. ''If it's normal, we do nothing.''</p>
        <p>In the case of another woman with a big breast cancer there was concern that the cancer might have spread to other parts of the body. ''If an upcoming PET scan is negative for other parts of the body, then we may do aggressive surgery on the breast,'' Dr. Lerner said. ''If it is positive and has spread to the bones or lungs, for example, then we take a palliative approach and give her some kind of therapy that will make her feel better.''</p>
        <p>The PET scan can also show the effectiveness of a particular treatment and whether there is a need to go to a different regimen.</p>
        <p>''In pinpointing heart disease with a PET scan, we look for areas that appear to be scar tissue,'' Dr. De Rogatis said. ''Scar tissue is not recoverable. Metabolism indicates that the tissue is still alive, so if it's muscle on its way out it can be fixed. With brain tumors, again you can't tell the difference between scar tissue and a tumor in conventional imaging. With PET the tumor metabolizes with the sugar showing brighter in the image and the scar doesn't.''</p>
        <p>It is a beautifully simple concept, Dr. Lerner said, although the technology is very complex. ''A rapidly growing malignancy has greater demand for nutrients than the surrounding tissues,'' he said. ''PET takes a sugar and tags it with a radioactive isotope so we can trace it. The sugar goes to the cancer, and we can detect it. What it is doing is using the metabolic needs of a tumor to let us detect that tumor when other forms of screening haven't found it.''</p>
        <p>The isotope, fluorodeoxyglucose or F.D.G., is fully active only for 110 minutes. Manufactured in Manhattan, it needs to get to the hospital center just at the time the patient will receive his injection.</p>
        <p>The levels of radiation are very safe, Dr. De Rogatis said, because the radioactive sugar leaves the body through decay and urination.</p>
        <p>Dr. Lerner added: ''With PET we can avoid extensive, tedious testing. Teeth-gnashing kinds of discussions are gone. And not all PET scans are positive. A negative PET scan is a positive for the patient.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
