<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fighting Highway Aggression With a Phone Number</title>
    <meta content="26RAGE$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034414"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ROAD AND RAIL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hot Lines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Traffic Violations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kent, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drunken and Reckless Driving</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Traffic Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EEDE1239F935A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="979" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fighting Highway Aggression With a Phone Number</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KENT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kent, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Transportation Division reports decline in number of 'road rage' incidents since January 1997, when federal funds were allocated for public education, toll-free reporting hotline and increased police presence in trouble spots; cartoon (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's no secret that the automotive belligerence known as road rage is endemic among the state's drivers.</p>
        <p>In 1996, the state had its first highway death conclusively attributed to road rage when an object hurled from a car by an angry driver on the New Jersey Turnpike hit another driver's windshield, leading to a fatal collision. This year, an anonymous survey conducted by the Automobile Association of America in the northern half of the state indicated that almost half of all drivers did not merely get mad at real or imagined slights by other motorists, but also tried to get even.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's no secret that the automotive belligerence known as road rage is endemic among the state's drivers.</p>
        <p>In 1996, the state had its first highway death conclusively attributed to road rage when an object hurled from a car by an angry driver on the New Jersey Turnpike hit another driver's windshield, leading to a fatal collision. This year, an anonymous survey conducted by the Automobile Association of America in the northern half of the state indicated that almost half of all drivers did not merely get mad at real or imagined slights by other motorists, but also tried to get even.</p>
        <p>Since January 1997, about $500,000 in Federal and state money has been spent in New Jersey to reduce road rage. The money, which has paid for public education programs, a toll-free reporting line and an increased police presence at known trouble spots in selected counties, is beginning to show results.</p>
        <p>This year, the police have issued 53,000 more traffic citations than in the first six months of 1997 for aggressive driving, including speeding, unsafe lane changes and tailgating. The toll-free line to report aggressive driving, (888) 732-7623 or #77 on a cellular phone, receives 65 calls a day. State Police Sgt. William Wade, who coordinates anti-aggressive driving programs with the Division of Transportation, said statewide traffic fatalities were down 19 percent from the same period last year. ''That's the most important yardstick we have for determining if we're making a difference,'' Sgt. Wade said, ''and it appears as if we are.''</p>
        <p>He said he and other law enforcement officials in the state began to look seriously at aggressive driving in 1995, when they noticed a decline in driving while intoxicated but an increase in collision fatalities. ''We were reducing the number of drunk drivers, but people were still getting killed,'' he said. ''We took a look at what tends to cause these collisions, and many of them seemed to stem from the kind of aggressive driving that also tends to makes people get mad -- the guy who decides you're driving too slow and tailgates you, or the person who cuts you off in an unsafe lane change, or who maybe runs a red light because he thinks he shouldn't have to wait. All of these things are against the law, but a lot of drivers may not have remembered it from their driver ed classes, or didn't know what to do about it if they saw it.''</p>
        <p>The initiative focused on accident-prone places in Atlantic, Bergen, Burlington, Essex, Middlesex and Monmouth Counties, as well as portions of the Route 1 corridor in Mercer County, where traffic fatalities have traditionally been the highest in the state.</p>
        <p>To remind drivers that aggressive driving was illegal and could be punished with fines, suspension and even loss of license, police officers gave talks to community groups. The State Police established the toll-free line, which routes complaints through State Police headquarters in West Trenton to local police departments.</p>
        <p>Sgt. Wade said the toll-free number also tended to prevent tempers from rising. ''A driver might get mad, but instead of trying to get even by responding aggressively, he calls the cops,'' he said. ''That way, he has an outlet for his frustration, and a potentially dangerous situation defuses itself.''</p>
        <p>For Sgt. Vincent DeRienzo, Bergen County's traffic safety supervisor, the single greatest benefit of the program to fight aggressive driving has been money for police overtime, putting more officers on the road. ''When we're out there and drivers see us, they're less apt to do something that would get them in trouble,'' he said, noting that Bergen County had had only 33 collision fatalities this year, compared to 37 in the same period of 1997,</p>
        <p>Sgt. DeRienzo has also specifically targeted trouble spots. In eight hours on July 15, officers from 13 police departments along Route 46 gave 399 drivers 405 tickets for speeding and other moving violations, driving unsafe vehicles and failing to wear seat belts. One driver was found to be wanted for aggravated assault. Another was a carjacker.</p>
        <p>''When we go out looking for aggressive-driving violations, it's pretty much like shooting fish in a barrel,'' said Officer Arnold Anderson of the Irvington Police, who recently targeted a portion of Western Parkway where a child was hit and killed by a car. Irvington's officers gave 73 tickets to 50 drivers in two hours.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, he added, citations for aggressive driving citations yielded an unexpected result. ''Just by stopping cars, we uncovered a major scam involving forged insurance documents, not to mention arrests of violent criminals,'' he said. ''In a high-crime area like ours, it's usually the bad guys who are driving badly or operating unsafe vehicles, sometimes going to or from a rape or robbery. The more stops we do, the more bad guys we get off the street.''</p>
        <p>Although not originally part of state's program, Pennsauken Township in Camden County has been permitted to bill the state for local police overtime during anti-aggressive driving patrols. As a result, Pennsauken's traffic safety supervisor, Sgt. Thomas Connor, said he had ''noticed a shifting of serious accidents off the highways and onto the county and secondary roads.''</p>
        <p>Sgt. Connor said the department would soon target residential areas. Aggressive driving ''is a plain lack of regard for the other people on the road,'' he said. ''At least we're making them aware that we're out there.''</p>
        <p>ROAD AND RAIL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
