<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beach Reads and Pool Books: Long Island in Hardcover; Visiting the Pollocks In a House of Squalor</title>
    <meta content="26GAIN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034339"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gaines, Steven</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Philistines At the Hedgerow (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFD71739F935A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="720" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beach Reads and Pool Books: Long Island in Hardcover; Visiting the Pollocks In a House of Squalor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpt of summer reading suggestion recommends Philistines at the Hedgerow, compendium of Hamptons lore written by Steven Gaines; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Philistines at the Hedgerow'' is Steven Gaines's compendium of four centuries of Hamptons lore. Here he writes about a 1949 visit paid by the artist Alfonso Ossorio and his dancer companion, Ted Dragon, to the home shared by a pair of struggling artists named Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner.</p>
        <p>OSSORIO and Dragon stopped at the Bohack Supermarket on Main Street and bought bags of groceries and a turkey to take to the Pollocks. They found the artist and his wife not south of the highway with the Summer Colony but in a ramshackle farmhouse a few miles north of the town in a place called Springs -- population then, 360 -- a section literally and figuratively on the other side of the railroad tracks, or ''below the bridge,'' as townsfolk would say. Springs (cognoscenti never use the article) was the backwoods of town, deep country, undisturbed fields, thick woods, gorgeous ponds with green saltwater meadows. It was a closed community, culturally and socially isolated from East Hampton, with bloodlines so intertwined that natives even had their own derisive nickname, Bonackers (after the Accabonac Creek), East Hampton's equivalent of hillbillies. In present-day East Hampton they are known as ''Bubs.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Philistines at the Hedgerow'' is Steven Gaines's compendium of four centuries of Hamptons lore. Here he writes about a 1949 visit paid by the artist Alfonso Ossorio and his dancer companion, Ted Dragon, to the home shared by a pair of struggling artists named Jackson Pollock and Lee Krasner.</p>
        <p>OSSORIO and Dragon stopped at the Bohack Supermarket on Main Street and bought bags of groceries and a turkey to take to the Pollocks. They found the artist and his wife not south of the highway with the Summer Colony but in a ramshackle farmhouse a few miles north of the town in a place called Springs -- population then, 360 -- a section literally and figuratively on the other side of the railroad tracks, or ''below the bridge,'' as townsfolk would say. Springs (cognoscenti never use the article) was the backwoods of town, deep country, undisturbed fields, thick woods, gorgeous ponds with green saltwater meadows. It was a closed community, culturally and socially isolated from East Hampton, with bloodlines so intertwined that natives even had their own derisive nickname, Bonackers (after the Accabonac Creek), East Hampton's equivalent of hillbillies. In present-day East Hampton they are known as ''Bubs.''</p>
        <p>Bubs were mostly descendants of Lion Gardiner's less-well-to-do employees, the Bennets and Kings and Lesters, who unlike Goody Garlick and her husband couldn't afford to build houses in town when they moved to the mainland 400 years ago. They wound up in a patch of rich land about three miles square between Accabonac ''Crik'' and Louse Point. Fifteen generations of Bonackers had lived on this land, untouched by the good fortune and spoils brought by the Summer Colony. They subsisted as dirt-poor, small-time farmers and fishermen. The most financially productive Springs had ever been was during Prohibition, when the nooks and crannies of its waterfront made it a favorite rumrunners' drop. It had one saloon, Jungle Pete's, and one grocery, Springs General Store. It didn't even have its own fire department until 1965; when one newcomer asked what to do in case of a fire, the Bubs' solution was ''Don't have a fire.''</p>
        <p>You can still tell true Bonackers in East Hampton because of their distinctive Bonac dialect, an accent and speech pattern whose roots can be traced back to Dorset, England. It's an exaggerated Yankee twang, such as saying ''yit'' for ''yet'' and repeating words twice, ''Yes, yes,'' or adding syllables, like ''hay-at'' for ''hat.'' Bonackers were not apt to be ''long in the mouth'' with summer strangers, whose presence sometimes turned their little neck of the woods ''catty-wumper'' instead of ''finest kind,'' the way they liked things. Strangers were ''from away,'' especially guys like Pollock who they thought didn't work for a living -- they were called ''drifts'' because they appeared for a season or two and then faded from memory.</p>
        <p>''We were shocked when we got to where Jackson and Lee were living,'' Dragon said. ''It was squalor.'' Ossorio called it ''lamentable borderline existence.'' They lived in a 200-year-old house with no heat or hot water and only a coal stove in the kitchen to keep warm. Pollock told them that it got so cold in the winter that the water froze in the toilets, and they still used the outhouse. ''Jackson was so poor,'' Dragon said, ''that he held his pants up with a string. They couldn't even afford a car -- he rode around on a bicycle.'' Lee said they lived off the clams Jackson dug himself out of Accabonac Crick and vegetables she grew in the garden. The previous winter the owner of Springs General Store finally took pity on them and accepted a small painting from Pollock to pay off his sixty-dollar bill. The grocer hung the painting in the store and told customers it was an ''aerial view of Siberia.'' Ten years later he sold it for $17,000, and it's likely worth a million today.</p>
        <p>From ''Philistines at the Hedgerow.'' Copyright $; 1998 by Steven Gaines. Published by Little, Brown and Company.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
