<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Beside Balanchine, Other American Pioneers</title>
    <meta content="26ANDE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1034753"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jenkins, Nicholas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Balanchine, George (1904-83)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kirstein, Lincoln</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Anderson, Jack</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980726T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01EEDD1F30F935A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="1212" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Beside Balanchine, Other American Pioneers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Anderson, Jack</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article disputes contention by Nicholas Jenkins, in April 13 issue of New Yorker, that George Balanchine and Lincoln Kirstein were founders of American ballet; focuses on others who pioneered ballet across US; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE New York City Ballet is 50 years old this year. So let's rejoice. The company and its affiliated School of American Ballet are remarkable institutions, and George Balanchine and Lincoln Kirstein, their founders, are heroic figures. Nevertheless, justifiable euphoria should not lead to myth making.</p>
        <p>Some dancegoers with hazy notions of history now seem to assume that when Kirstein brought Balanchine to New York in 1933, America was a balletic wilderness. Such a view was expressed by Nicholas Jenkins in ''The Great Impresario,'' a tribute to Kirstein in the April 13 issue of the New Yorker. Mr. Jenkins declares, ''Kirstein and Balanchine labored to create and then perpetuate a basis for classical dance in a country where none had really existed before they arrived on the scene.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE New York City Ballet is 50 years old this year. So let's rejoice. The company and its affiliated School of American Ballet are remarkable institutions, and George Balanchine and Lincoln Kirstein, their founders, are heroic figures. Nevertheless, justifiable euphoria should not lead to myth making.</p>
        <p>Some dancegoers with hazy notions of history now seem to assume that when Kirstein brought Balanchine to New York in 1933, America was a balletic wilderness. Such a view was expressed by Nicholas Jenkins in ''The Great Impresario,'' a tribute to Kirstein in the April 13 issue of the New Yorker. Mr. Jenkins declares, ''Kirstein and Balanchine labored to create and then perpetuate a basis for classical dance in a country where none had really existed before they arrived on the scene.''</p>
        <p>That's nonsense. And calling it so does not belittle either man. A basis for American ballet did indeed exist in the 1930's, and Balanchine and Kirstein built upon it, as did other architects of balletic visions.</p>
        <p>Several opera companies, the Metropolitan among them, had ballet troupes with schools, often headed by Italian ballet masters. There were also teachers from other backgrounds, including American-born and Russian teachers.</p>
        <p>Two famous Russians opened successful New York schools in the early 20's: Michel Fokine, the choreographic reformer who created masterpieces like ''Les Sylphides'' and ''Petrouchka,'' and Mikhail Mordkin, a dancer noted for his magnetic presence. Both formed companies. But financial difficulties prevented their groups from becoming permanent. (Balanchine and Kirstein would experience comparable problems.) In 1937, however, Mordkin made a fresh attempt to start a company, organizing the Mordkin Ballet, whose dancers three years later became the nucleus for the first season of Ballet Theater (now American Ballet Theater).</p>
        <p>Anyone surveying American dance may find surprises. Chicago was a balletic boom town in the 20's and 30's. The Chicago Opera employed dancers, and there were ambitious, if short-lived, independent troupes, some of them headed by Adolph Bolm, a former member of Sergei Diaghilev's innovative Ballets Russes. Because of his labors as choreographer, teacher and director in Chicago and California, Bolm was a real pioneer. His Chicago creations ranged from ''The Birthday of the Infanta,'' based on an Oscar Wilde fairy tale, to ''Krazy Kat,'' inspired by the comic strip.</p>
        <p>For a special Washington performance in 1928, Bolm choreographed the world premiere of Stravinsky's ''Apollo,'' more than a month before Diaghilev presented Balanchine's version of that work in Paris. The three Muses in Bolm's production made their own contributions to American ballet. Elise Reiman taught for many years at the School of American Ballet. Berenice Holmes stayed on in Chicago as a prominent teacher. Chicago also remained the home of Ruth Page, who organized several companies there, sometimes in association with the American dancers and teachers Bentley Stone and Walter Camryn.</p>
        <p>Bolm went west in the 30's, becoming the San Francisco Ballet's first director in 1933. His productions included ''Ballet Mecanique,'' an Expressionist evocation of a factory, and ''Lament'' and ''Consecration,'' two heroic pieces to Bach.</p>
        <p>Later, after Bolm had settled in Los Angeles, the San Francisco Ballet began its long and happy association with Willam, Harold and Lew Christensen, brothers from Utah whose early training was largely Italian. Harold and Lew then studied at the School of American Ballet, and Lew danced with the American Ballet, Balanchine's first American company. But, although benefiting immeasurably from Balanchine's guidance, he was already a trained dancer at the time. Willam directed the San Francisco Ballet from 1938 until 1951, when he was succeeded by Lew. Both Willam and Lew were versatile choreographers, and Harold supervised the San Francisco Ballet School.</p>
        <p>Ballet flourished in unexpected places. Our oldest surviving regional company is the Atlanta Ballet, which Dorothy Alexander founded in 1929. Another hardy perennial is the Dayton Ballet, established in 1937 by Josephine and Hermene Schwarz, two determined sisters. Both studied with many teachers, and Josephine had danced with Bolm in Chicago. A video documentary tracing their remarkable careers, ''How Can We Know the Dancer From the Dance?,'' has just been released by Global Village Communications of Bellbrook, Ohio.</p>
        <p>And what was the first American ballet company to tour Europe? Not one from New York. The Philadelphia Ballet existed from 1935 to 1941 and went abroad in 1937. It was founded by another pair of sisters, Catherine and Dorothie Littlefield, whose mother had opened a ballet school in Philadelphia back in 1908. Dorothie, a respected teacher, was among the first faculty members of the School of American Ballet, but she soon returned to Philadelphia. Catherine choreographed such works as ''Terminal,'' which depicted a busy railroad station; ''Ladies Better Dresses,'' a satire on the fashion industry, and the rousing ''Barn Dance.''</p>
        <p>The Philadelphia Ballet, like most early balletic ventures (except for those in Atlanta, Dayton and San Francisco), did not last long. But neither did the Kirstein-Balanchine companies. The American Ballet, founded in 1934, collapsed in 1938, then was briefly revived for Latin American performances in 1941. Ballet Caravan, a touring group organized in 1936, disbanded in 1940. One constant in this unsettled time was the School of American Ballet, which continued to produce dancers. But, as a glance at dance publications of the time will reveal, it was never New York's only important ballet school. Then, in 1946, Balanchine and Kirstein established Ballet Society, which initially presented works for subscription-only audiences. After opening its performances to the general public, it became the New York City Ballet in 1948.</p>
        <p>By then ballet was successful in America. Balanchine and Kirstein were major factors in bringing this about. And there were other important influences from abroad: Col. W. de Basil's Ballets Russes, which embarked on its first American tour in 1933, spurred great interest in ballet, as did that company's rival, the Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, which arrived here in 1938.</p>
        <p>THE incessant coast-to-coast touring of the Ballet Russe and Ballet Theater made Americans ballet conscious during the 40's. Balanchine, among others, choreographed for these groups. Yet, at the time, he and Kirstein probably did more to train dancers at their school than to promote their choreographic conceptions, for the simple reason that they did not have their own company for much of that decade. However, thanks to various choreographic and directorial forces, a ballet audience was formed, one that came to support the City Ballet.</p>
        <p>Many people, then, served as architects of American ballet. Some of their schemes were castles in the air; some proved sturdy. But even the evanescent projects may have contributed to the art. Balanchine and Kirstein were among the idealists whose dreams eventually became realities.</p>
        <p>DANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
