<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Skinner Urges Service Roles For Graduates</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="527797"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="COMMENCEMENTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEGREES, ACADEMIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GRADUATE SCHOOLS AND STUDENTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEORGE WASHINGTON UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SYRACUSE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF NORTH CAROLINA</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Graduate Schools and Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920511T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DB1531F932A25756C0A964958260" item-length="691" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Skinner Urges Service Roles For Graduates</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>George Washington University conferred 1,290 undergraduate degrees and 1,159 advanced degrees yesterday on the Ellipse in Washington at its 167th commencement exercises.</p>
        <p>The White House chief of staff, Samuel K. Skinner, who received an honorary degree, gave the commencement address. Mr. Skinner encouraged the students to "cast off the politics of division" so the United States could "build a society in which people respect each other, work with -- not against -- each other."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>George Washington University conferred 1,290 undergraduate degrees and 1,159 advanced degrees yesterday on the Ellipse in Washington at its 167th commencement exercises.</p>
        <p>The White House chief of staff, Samuel K. Skinner, who received an honorary degree, gave the commencement address. Mr. Skinner encouraged the students to "cast off the politics of division" so the United States could "build a society in which people respect each other, work with -- not against -- each other."</p>
        <p>Emphasizing that "the power of one individual" can make a difference, Mr. Skinner cited examples of individual bravery during the riots in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Mr. Skinner said that "perhaps the most dramatic story was the rescue of Reginald Denny, a white man who was pulled from his truck and then beaten with a fire extinguisher." One woman who saw that Mr. Denny's eyes were swollen fought her way through the crowd and, Mr. Skinner said, asked if Mr. Denny could see. "When he shook his head, she said, 'Then I will be your eyes.' Along with three other blacks, she helped Denny inch away from the rioters and to the hospital," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Skinner told the students that the most important thing in life is the "call to serve" because it is through self-sacrifice that "our finest discipline and best traits" are developed.</p>
        <p>Also receiving honorary degrees were Christopher F. Edley, president emeritus of the United Negro College Fund; the artist Helen Frankenthaler, and Robert C. Maynard, publisher and editor of The Oakland Tribune. American University</p>
        <p>The American University awarded 1,000 undergraduate degrees and 395 advanced degrees at the 90th commencement exercises, held yesterday at the Bender Arena on the campus in Washington.</p>
        <p>Elie Wiesel, the Nobel Peace Prize winner, and Adele Smith Simmons, president of the MacArthur Foundation, addressed the graduates of the college of Arts and Sciences.</p>
        <p>Mr. Wiesel was awarded an honorary doctor of humane letters degree.</p>
        <p>Ms. Simmons, an educator and author, was awarded an honorary doctor of laws degree.</p>
        <p>Maurice Strong, an environmentalist and the Secretary General for the United Nations' conference on the environment in Rio de Janeiro, addressed the graduates of the School of International Service and the School of Public Affairs. He was awarded an honorary doctor of philosophy in international relations degree.</p>
        <p>Other speakers were Sir Ralph Dahrendorf, an economist and social policy scholar, and Allan D. Gilmour, executive vice president of the Ford Motor Company. Syracuse University</p>
        <p>Syracuse University presented 4,885 degrees at its commencement ceremony yesterday. Wendy Kopp, the 24-year-old founder of Teach for America, delivered the address.</p>
        <p>Teach for America was founded in 1989 to train recent graduates to teach in underserved urban and rural schools.</p>
        <p>An honorary degree was presented to Charles Vert Willie, a sociologist and long time faculty member of the college since 1950.</p>
        <p>Betty Jane Myers, a 70-year-old student who began her studies in 1974, received a doctorate in counselor education.  University of North Carolina</p>
        <p>David Brinkley, host of the ABC news program, "This Week," addressed the 4,263 graduates of the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill yesterday at the university's 190th commencement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brinkley told the graduates, "The end of the Soviet Union, the end of Communism and the end of the cold war has left the world unprepared."</p>
        <p>He said this country had become "so accustomed to war and cold war it came to seem normal."</p>
        <p>He added: "If we can fix our primary weakness, our politics, and we can fix it, ours will remain one of the great countries of history -- the most productive, the most respected."</p>
        <p>Mr. Brinkley was awarded an honorary doctor of letters degree.</p>
        <p>Other honorary degrees were awarded to Shelby Foote, the historian and novelist; T. Franklin Williams, former director of the National Institute on Aging; Sherman E. Lee, oriental art scholar and former director of the Cleveland Museum, and Anne Queen, former director of the university's Young Men and Women's Christian Associations.</p>
        <p>COMMENCEMENTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
