<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Complete Urban Angler</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="707408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISH AND OTHER MARINE LIFE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FISHING, SPORT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, IAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Fishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fishing, Sport</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fish and Other Marine Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE7D81639F932A1575BC0A962958260" item-length="2704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Complete Urban Angler</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IAN FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISHER, IAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A BIG green turtle surfaced to the left of Glenn Brown's fishing line, which he had plunked below a half-toppled pier on Staten Island. He mumbled something about chasing it, then worried about keeping his fingers. Mr. Brown has had enough pain recently. Pain, in fact, inspired him to fish in New York Harbor, a few hundred yards south of a rusted ferryboat named Verrazano.</p>
        <p>"I started fishing because of this," said the 41-year-old Mr. Brown, lifting his round sunglasses to reveal two purplish swollen eyes. "I was mugged in my neighborhood, and I bought a fishing pole. Back to the outdoors."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A BIG green turtle surfaced to the left of Glenn Brown's fishing line, which he had plunked below a half-toppled pier on Staten Island. He mumbled something about chasing it, then worried about keeping his fingers. Mr. Brown has had enough pain recently. Pain, in fact, inspired him to fish in New York Harbor, a few hundred yards south of a rusted ferryboat named Verrazano.</p>
        <p>"I started fishing because of this," said the 41-year-old Mr. Brown, lifting his round sunglasses to reveal two purplish swollen eyes. "I was mugged in my neighborhood, and I bought a fishing pole. Back to the outdoors."</p>
        <p>Believe it or not, most people need less of an excuse to fish on the 576 miles of shoreline that encircle the city's five boroughs -- to the ever-optimistic angler, a theoretical fishing ground that runs from here to South Carolina. And despite what most people think about the sewage, the PCB's, the heavy metals, the oozing trash barges, the sunken cars, the rats, the corpses and all that, New York can be a magnificent place to fish. Or to sit, hook in water, gazing at the skyline, and catch nothing at all.</p>
        <p>You can even eat what you catch, mostly (as long as you are not a child or a woman of child-bearing age and you don't do it too often, the state advises).</p>
        <p>"It's just a great place," said Ian Frazier, a writer for The New Yorker who has fished often in the city. "When you see the fish and the birds and the volume of fish that come up those rivers, it's amazing. There are guys catching 70 stripers a day and throwing them back."</p>
        <p>For snob value, trolling for dinner in New York does not have the cachet of, say, casting flies into the Bighorn River in Montana. Most people in this city, where four boroughs are either islands or on islands, have forgotten the water. But there are devoted and resourceful urbanites (waterfront guerrillas, perhaps?) who cast from broken piers in upper Manhattan and the Bronx, heave their lines from the foot of the Brooklyn Bridge, dangle hooks fat with chunked bunker from the bridges and overpasses of Far Rockaway, drop nightcrawlers into the Harlem Meer in Central Park. Fishermen board party boats off Coney Island for fluke, and some test the triple swirls of Hell Gate for ferocious bluefish and striped bass.</p>
        <p>Though much of the waterfront is fenced off or impossible to reach, many places are accessible by subway, bus or bike. And because of strict environmental laws and new sewage treatment plants, the water is cleaner than it has been in decades.</p>
        <p>Algae blooms on rocks once slick with goop. Worms bore tubular homes into wooden piers. A fisherman in Brooklyn recently found a sea horse off Greenpoint, a sign that something is going well.</p>
        <p>"You throw your sinker down and you can actually see for a foot, a foot and a half," said Tony Evangelista, president of the Hudson River Fishermen's Association, as he fished from a friend's small boat near the Robin's Reef lighthouse, not far from the Statue of Liberty. "This is a nursing area for the coast. The fish people eat in restaurants may have started their lives here."</p>
        <p>(To be on the safe side, though, he did feel bound to allow that "some days are better than others.")</p>
        <p>While fishermen normally swear by the harbor, the problem this year is that the fishing has not been great, which many fishermen blame on the especially cold winter and late spring. But as the water begins to cool now through October or later, the two most popular sport fish, bluefish and striped bass, should run in good numbers. Anglers can also take flounder, porgies, an occasional sheepshead (the striped porgie after which Sheepshead Bay in Brooklyn is named), weakfish, blackfish, herring, red hake or ling, eels, menhaden or bunker, blue crabs and perhaps a Spanish mackerel, flecked in pale yellow.</p>
        <p>Everett Hill, a 50-year-old salesman at Herman's World of Sports on 42d Street in Manhattan, has been fishing in the city since he was a teen-ager (and swears he once caught a 23-pound German carp in Prospect Park, but that's another story). These days he sells fishing rods and keeps a board of photos of trophies caught by customers around the city. A centerpiece is the 37-inch striped bass hauled in right over the railings on Roosevelt Island.</p>
        <p>"One thing I have said and noticed is that fishing in the five boroughs -- it's very good fishing," Mr. Hill said. "But people don't know where to do it because there is so much concrete and bricks."</p>
        <p>He is glad, however, to offer a few hints, like the pier at 44th Street on the Hudson, or off 14th Street on the East River, or on Brighton Beach or Manhattan Beach in Brooklyn. He himself is eyeing a spot at the end of Avenue C on the Lower East Side for his first adventure in city fly fishing.</p>
        <p>"Once the tide goes down, there is a little rock you can go out and walk on," he said. "I may try it from there." A CHANGE OF PACE</p>
        <p>There does not appear to be a trend here. People are not flooding to the water's edge the way newly minted fly fishermen have taken to the Catskills or to the clear gravel-bottom rivers out West. Many people who fish in New York do not earn a lot of money: They fish for a cheap meal, as well as for a few hours of relaxation by the water, where surprisingly few other people go.</p>
        <p>No matter how murky the water might be, it still reflects the diversity, strifes and strengths of New York On piers in Brooklyn, long established Irish and Italian residents fish next to the neighborhood's newer arrivals -- Polish, black, Asian and Hispanic -- sometimes sharing tackle, other times blaming one group or another for killing off the schools by taking too many small fish.</p>
        <p>But there is room for any sort of fisherman. Witness the unlikely sight of Bill Pruitt, a 31-year-old film maker, whizzing to the East River Park in an oddly apt symbol for fishing in New York: in-line skates. It was his first time fishing in Manhattan, and he seemed to have everything he needed. He had a 9-foot graphite rod, red, which he had bought at a K-Mart in New Jersey for about $45. He had bait, a pale pink sliver of squid twisted around his hook. And he had a perfect spot, just south of the Williamsburg Bridge on a brilliant Saturday.</p>
        <p>"I've been warned by the locals that if I catch anything I should prepare to go waterskiing," said Mr. Pruitt, who grew up in Utah, fishing streams in waders rather than in-line skates. "They are tough fighting, and I won't stay stationary."</p>
        <p>He had decided to fish there, he said, because it was close to his home in the East Village and he was curious. In only a little time, though, he lost his rig -- the bait, hook and sinker -- not to a fish, but to a boat that cruised past under the railing. All he had to do was ask, and Jose Cordero, 40 years old and a long-time fisherman at the park, set him up again, a new piece of squid included.</p>
        <p>Samuel Edwards, 57, a darkroom technician and a friend of Mr. Cordero, comes to the park with his wife, Jo Anne, his dog, Pooch, and his fishing pole. He likes to eat the fish he catches -- striped bass, bluefish, flounder, eels and porgies -- but he hasn't caught a whole lot this year. On the other hand, that's not entirely the point.</p>
        <p>"I come here to relax after work," said Mr. Edwards, who in his heart prefers fishing in Antigua, where he grew up and caught big grouper and snapper. "And in the meantime I get a little fight."</p>
        <p>This day was not the best: no one had a thing. Mr. Pruitt, though, was working hard, leaning over the iron railings with an intense patience.</p>
        <p>"I got a bite, yeah," he said. "It played around, stole my bait and ran. Enough to keep me hopeful anyway." A HOLE IN THE FENCE</p>
        <p>The exact location of the pier where Mr. Brown was fishing with a friend, Peter Gilardi Jr., a congenial funeral director, will go unnamed here: this is partly out of respect to a fisherman who considers it his secret spot, and partly because, like many places to fish in New York City, this one appeared to be on private property, accessible only through a hole in a chain-link fence.</p>
        <p>But anyone who gets off the Staten Island ferry and walks south will find it and other piers like it swarming with life. Mr. Brown, using an empty Tic Tac box as a bobber, was crouched over the water, dark but rich with flashing minnows. The turtle, if it liked fish, was swimming through a feast.</p>
        <p>Closer to shore, Donald Lewis, 32, a construction site supervisor, had thrown out six crab baskets, baited with a turkey neck or a chunk of bunker, with the help of his two children, Dezmond, 8, and Mechsha, 7, and his nephew Illidge, also 8. The catch after two hours was one enormous blue crab, missing its right claw but six inches wide from point to point. Dezmond held it up with pride, framed from his back with a broad view of Manhattan's skyline.</p>
        <p>"It really gives a chance for kids who live in an urban area to be more outdoors -- to get back in touch with nature, you could say," Mr. Lewis said. "They get a thrill out of it, keeping the baskets straight, going to the bait store. Then going home and actually cooking what you caught."</p>
        <p>Despite the state warnings for children, he has few fears about the harbor, which he considers untainted enough to provide healthy food. His view is shared by many fisherman around the harbor. (One exception is Mr. Frazier, the writer, who said: "This is an incredibly rich ecosystem, and the fish are poisonous.")</p>
        <p>"The water's clean now, the fish taste delicious," said Jim Engel, a 26-year-old welder. "The meat is pink. It's a big misconception, the harbor is beautiful."</p>
        <p>Mr. Engel was visiting from the Bronx, fishing with his brother-in-law, Agustin Agront, 21. The two said they spent a lot of time on this pier, catching bluefish, striped bass, porgies and an occasional sand shark. Seated on a black car seat, Mr. Agront worked his rod against the current.</p>
        <p>"As long as people stop littering, the harbor will clean itself up," Mr. Engel said. "I wish you would put that in your paper." PRAYING FOR FISH</p>
        <p>"Catch anything?" Barbara Deats asked.</p>
        <p>"A nice sunburn," said her husband, Dennis.</p>
        <p>It was slow, too, at the pier at 69th Street in Bay Ridge, Brooklyn, sometimes called Owl's Head Pier. Though many spots along the water seem seedy, a bit removed, this is what might be called a family pier. Children ride mountain bikes to the water with their poles. People of all colors and ages and sizes fish side by side, with only a little bad feeling. Fish-cleaning stations, flecked with dried scales, are welded to the metal rails. You can get there by subway, the 69th Street station on the R train.</p>
        <p>"I hooked a nice one," said Tippy Lund, 52, pulling out a small silver fish that glinted like a knife blade. "He's a herring."</p>
        <p>A limousine pulled onto the pier and people looked to see if it was a celebrity. No one came out of the limo. People fished or crabbed about how bad the fishing was this year. They prayed it would pick up. Mr. Deats, who has won fishing contests here, drank a few beers with his friends, Joe Stemberger and Stan Ferraiolo. When he was about 7 years old, Mr. Stemberger found a dead man at a ferry slip on the pier.</p>
        <p>A few feet away sat Mildred Smith, 79, once of North Carolina and now of East Flatbush, and her granddaughter, Khalilah Barron, 17. Mrs. Smith knows about fishing in the five boroughs of New York City: Armed with a box of blood worms, two rods and enough tackle to empty the harbor, she had fished that day on Far Rockaway. Then she went to Jacob Riis Park, where she caught eight porgies but also lost eight hooks and sinkers.</p>
        <p>She ended up at Owl's Head pier by mid-afternoon. She likes it because the people are nice and she does not lose a lot of gear.</p>
        <p>"You want to see what I caught?" she asked.</p>
        <p>"We caught," her granddaughter reminded her. Ms. Barron opened a cooler and picked up a small porgy, about the size of a slice of bread.</p>
        <p>"I'd throw that back," Mrs. Smith said, though it was too late. "I wonder what's wrong with fish today."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Smith has caught many fish here over the years, some to eat and others just because, like any angler in New York or anywhere else, she loves to fish.</p>
        <p>"If I could only catch some nice-sized porgies," Mrs. Smith said.  Talking Tackle: What to Buy</p>
        <p>In outfitting the novice, the most important consideration is location: river or harbor and beach. Here are some tips from George Gifford, manager of Capital Fish and Tackle on West 23d Street in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>ROD AND REEL For river fishing, the strong currents demand a strong, thick pole, 7 to 8 feet long and about an inch in diameter, with a tip hole about the size of a pinkie. At the beaches or in the harbor, where the water is less volatile, a thinner pole is fine. A simple spinning reel is the best choice for beginners at any location.</p>
        <p>LINE AND SINKER River fishermen should use 20- to 25-pound test line (which means it can withstand that much pull without breaking), beach anglers, 12- to 14-pound test. In either case, start with 250 yards of line. In the rivers, sinkers weighing 4 to 6 ounces are needed to keep the bait from flowing back to shore. At the beach, use a 1- to 2-ounce sinker.</p>
        <p>BAIT, HOOK AND LURE The river angler will use worms or chunks of fish, preferably bunker (also called menhaden). Different hooks are better for different fish. For porgies, a good bet to be biting now, use a No. 6 beak hook, for stripers or fluke, 2/0 or 3/0 beak hooks, and for bluefish, notorious line breakers, a 5/0 or 6/0 beak hook with a wire leader. If you just want to fish off a pier, use a 2- or 3-ounce sinker with a 4/0 or 6/0 beak hook.</p>
        <p>At the beach, lures usually replace hook and bait. For weakfish, which should be running soon, try rubber shrimp or buck tails tipped with a sand worm. For stripers, swimming plugs or popping plugs will work. But as with any lure, if it doesn't work, try something else. JESSE McKINLEY Good Enough To Eat? Yes, in Moderation.</p>
        <p>Fish caught in the waters around the city are generally safe to eat, within limits, according to health officials.</p>
        <p>Due to continued contamination of local waters by PCB's, mercury and other industrial by-products, the State Health Department suggests that people limit their consumption to one meal (about half a pound) of city-caught fish a week. It also urges women of child-bearing age and children under the age of 15 to avoid the fish altogether, because contaminants have a greater impact on developing organs in a fetus or a young child. The warnings are "erring on the side of caution," says Jim Gilmore of the State Department of Environmental Conservation.</p>
        <p>Here are some additional safety tips:</p>
        <p>* The once-a-week rule applies to all fish caught in the New York Harbor, Upper and Lower Bays, the Arthur Kill, the Kill Van Kull and the Hudson, East and Harlem Rivers. Beyond Rockaway Point and in Jamaica Bay, the rule applies only to bluefish and American eel.</p>
        <p>* Striped bass, whose young spawn in the Hudson and ingest higher levels of contaminants, should only be eaten once a month. In crabs and lobsters, the tomalley should be discarded. A complete listing of advisories for freshwater fishing is available by calling the environmental agency at (718) 482-6464 or 482-4922.</p>
        <p>* Since the highest levels of contaminants are usually found in the skin and fat of fish, the warnings advise skinning and trimming away the darker, fatty tissue along the midsection, back and belly. Broiling or grilling also helps eliminate fat. Drippings shouldn't be used for gravies or sauces.</p>
        <p>Here is one local fisherman's recipe for grilling your catch:</p>
        <p>Jim Engel's Grilled Bluefish or Striped Bass Fillets of bluefish or striped bass Vinegar Bottled lemon juice Flour</p>
        <p>1. Cut fillets thin, removing all skin and fatty areas, where contaminants tend to concentrate</p>
        <p>2. Marinate the fillets for a while in a sauce that is half vinegar and half lemon juice.</p>
        <p>3. "Just put some flour on it and slap it on the grill, get a nice cup of beer and you're good to go," says Mr. Engel. Grill the fillets for a few minutes on each side.</p>
        <p>Serve with fried green plantain, garden salad and baked potato.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
