<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Chretien Says He Wants Changes in Trade Accord</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="645289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NORTH AMERICAN FREE TRADE AGREEMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CANADA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MEXICO</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHRETIEN, JEAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALINAS DE GORTARI, CARLOS (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">North American Free Trade Agreement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D71E3BF93BA15753C1A965958260" item-length="677" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Chretien Says He Wants Changes in Trade Accord</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLYDE H. FARNSWORTH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FARNSWORTH, CLYDE H</byline>
      <dateline>TORONTO, Oct. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fresh from the stunning triumph of his Liberal party in Canada's general elections, Prime Minister-designate Jean Chretien said today that he wants changes in the North American Free Trade Agreement and may not implement the pact without them.</p>
        <p>Although he insisted at a news conference in Ottawa that Canada did not want to intervene in the debate over trade legislation in the United States, his comments complicated the task of passage and appeared to put him into conflict with President Clinton.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fresh from the stunning triumph of his Liberal party in Canada's general elections, Prime Minister-designate Jean Chretien said today that he wants changes in the North American Free Trade Agreement and may not implement the pact without them.</p>
        <p>Although he insisted at a news conference in Ottawa that Canada did not want to intervene in the debate over trade legislation in the United States, his comments complicated the task of passage and appeared to put him into conflict with President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton told reporters in Washington on Tuesday that he saw "no reason to renegotiate the agreement." President Carlos Salinas de Gortari of Mexico also opposes renegotiation.</p>
        <p>Over 15 years, Nafta is intended to create a single $7 trillion-a-year market covering 360 million consumers in Canada, the United States and Mexico.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chretien's remarks created consternation in Washington, with officials saying some members of Congress would refuse to vote for the agreement if there were a possibility it might be changed later. "We get the sense that many Congressmen will use Chretien's comments as an excuse" to oppose the pact, one official said.</p>
        <p>But Representative Bill Richardson, a New Mexico Democrat who favors the pact and is a chief deputy majority whip, said Mr. Chretien's position "has not affected our vote count -- that's the truth."</p>
        <p>He added that if Mr. Chretien revived talks on the pact before Congress votes in mid-November, "that will hurt us." Noting that Mr. Chretien had said he would not take any action until he had appointed his Cabinet, Mr. Richardson said, "My hope is he will wait in appointing his ministers."</p>
        <p>Still uncertain is whether Canadian demands can be dealt with as side issues or whether they will lead to counterdemands in Mexico and the United States that would reopen the entire agreement.</p>
        <p>Elaborating on the Liberal position for the first time, Mr. Chretien said he would press for changes to protect Canadian energy reserves and to define rules on unfair subsidies and unfairly low prices for exports.</p>
        <p>Canadians have asked for such definitions because, they say, American charges that Canada unfairly subsidizes exports of steel, pork, lumber and other products are arbitrary.</p>
        <p>Washington has demands of its own, including abandonment of provisions in the four-year-old Canada-United States trade accord that protect Canadian books, films and other cultural industries from full competition.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chretien made his comments in response to reporters' questions; they were not part of a formal declaration by the new Government, which will not be installed for 9 or 10 days.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chretien and Mr. Clinton, who spoke by telephone on Tuesday, have scheduled a meeting to discuss the problem on Nov. 19 in Seattle, during an Asian-Pacific Economic Cooperation conference.</p>
        <p>Although the Liberal Party platform had called for renegotiation, there has always been a question how hard the case would be pressed once the party was in power.</p>
        <p>Liberals had fought free trade in the 1988 elections and are divided over Nafta today. The left wing wants to scrap the deal. Moderates fear that if it does not go forward, Canada will find itself isolated and economically impaired. Mr. Chretien is in the camp of the moderates, but he is anxious to prevent any ruptures within the party.</p>
        <p>He also emphasized today: "I will do my best to have very good relations with the United States and Mexico."</p>
        <p>The Canadian legislation to put Nafta into force was passed by Parliament under the Progressive Conservative Government, which was soundly beaten at the polls Monday. But Mr. Chretien said it would not become law until he proclaimed it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chretien said his first task as Canada's 20th Prime Minister would be to create jobs -- as was also promised in the Liberal platform. "My first priority will be definitely to work on the economy," he said. "That is the reason why we won the election."</p>
        <p>He is expected to announce shortly a $6 billion public-works program to create up to 120,000 jobs over two years.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
