<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Celebrating a 20's Bandleader With an Ear for the Symphonic</title>
    <meta content="18JAZZ1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/02/18/arts/music/18jazz.1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1650926"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="JAZZ REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jazz at Lincoln Center</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Whiteman, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Whiteman, Paul</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E1DE113AF93BA25751C0A9639C8B63" item-length="591" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Celebrating a 20's Bandleader With an Ear for the Symphonic</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Celebrating a 20's Bandleader With an Ear for the Symphonic</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff reviews Jazz at Lincoln Center performance of music of Paul Whiteman (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul Whiteman has really taken it on the chin over the years: dismissed as a popularizer who loaded his dance band with seven violins, as a deflator of Bix Beiderbecke's creative spirit, as an unswinging slickster who was being hailed as ''the King of Jazz''when Louis Armstrong was practically inventing the then-and-future style of jazz improvisation.</p>
        <p>And you wouldn't expect to find his defenders in the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra simply because so much of the Whiteman band's music sits apart from the rest of jazz. Its top-level musicians could play jazz to a degree -- and a few were great -- but many were by necessity based in classical music so that they could play what was then called Whiteman's ''symphonic jazz.'' Some of the Whiteman band's work is distinguished by the great arrangers, musicians and singers he hired, including Bill Challis, Don Redman, Beiderbecke and Bing Crosby; some of it is conceptually ambitious. But the swing feeling that Armstrong and others pioneered was, by and large, another animal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Paul Whiteman has really taken it on the chin over the years: dismissed as a popularizer who loaded his dance band with seven violins, as a deflator of Bix Beiderbecke's creative spirit, as an unswinging slickster who was being hailed as</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Paul Whiteman has really taken it on the chin over the years: dismissed as a popularizer who loaded his dance band with seven violins, as a deflator of Bix Beiderbecke's creative spirit, as an unswinging slickster who was being hailed as ''the King of Jazz''when Louis Armstrong was practically inventing the then-and-future style of jazz improvisation.</p>
        <p>And you wouldn't expect to find his defenders in the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra simply because so much of the Whiteman band's music sits apart from the rest of jazz. Its top-level musicians could play jazz to a degree -- and a few were great -- but many were by necessity based in classical music so that they could play what was then called Whiteman's ''symphonic jazz.'' Some of the Whiteman band's work is distinguished by the great arrangers, musicians and singers he hired, including Bill Challis, Don Redman, Beiderbecke and Bing Crosby; some of it is conceptually ambitious. But the swing feeling that Armstrong and others pioneered was, by and large, another animal.</p>
        <p>It is true, though, that Whiteman's vision to merge jazz with long-form classical music and areas in between (like Gershwin), is the first prototype for the cross-discipline, high-visibility work that Wynton Marsalis and Jazz at Lincoln Center have accomplished. Armstrong might have done immeasurably more for the sound, but when a major newspaper in the mid-1920's wanted to call on someone to defend jazz as a music of complexity and seriousness, it contacted the charismatic Whiteman, as it would call Mr. Marsalis now.</p>
        <p>''The Jazz Age: Music of Paul Whiteman,'' which opened last night, is about Whiteman in his context. Nearly half the program consisted of songs from contemporaneous black bands of the 20's, including Duke Ellington's, Jelly Roll Morton's and Fletcher Henderson's -- music in which the Lincoln Center band could show its ensemble tightness, and the soloists could let rip. The Whiteman-band music that the Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra did play, mostly arranged by Challis, came from the hotter end of its enormous output. There was no ''symphonic jazz,'' and Vince Giordano's crooning on songs like ''Louisiana'' was as close as the concert got to the goopy geniality of the era's ''sweet'' music.</p>
        <p>''What Are You Waiting For, Mary?'' contained context within itself: its trick was to pit the sweet and hot styles against each other. The action flipped back and forth between the violinist Andy Stein and the guitarist James Chirillo, trilling sweetly, and the New Orleans-style jazz coming from the other side of the stage, recreating parts once played by a version of the Whiteman orchestra that included Beiderbecke and Frank Trumbauer.</p>
        <p>And in one of the concert's best moments, Mr. Marsalis sang Hoagy Carmichael's ''Washboard Blues'' -- the only recording Carmichael made with Whiteman -- in a quiet, raspy voice, with an arrangement for six clarinets, violin and piano. It wasn't typical Whiteman, typical Lincoln Center Jazz Orchestra or typical anything. But it was very nicely done.</p>
        <p>The program repeats tonight and tomorrow night at the Rose Theater, Frederick P. Rose Hall, Broadway at 60th Street, (212)721-6500.</p>
        <p>JAZZ REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
