<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Clinton Draws Line on Vetoes On 2 Subjects</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="764669"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="GRAMM PROPOSAL FOR DEEP TAX CUT KILLED BY SENATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOD STAMPS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WELFARE (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN AID</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITCHELL, ALISON</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Stamps</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Welfare (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFD61331F937A15756C0A963958260" item-length="1029" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Clinton Draws Line on Vetoes On 2 Subjects</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITCHELL, ALISON</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 23</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Confronting the Republican Congress on several major fronts, a combative Clinton Administration today threatened to veto foreign aid legislation the President denounced as "isolationist," as well as any welfare bill that would turn the Federal food stamp program over to the states.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the President backed away from his remarks to New Hampshire radio stations on Friday, suggesting that he was preparing his own counterproposal to Republican plans to balance the budget over seven years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Confronting the Republican Congress on several major fronts, a combative Clinton Administration today threatened to veto foreign aid legislation the President denounced as "isolationist," as well as any welfare bill that would turn the Federal food stamp program over to the states.</p>
        <p>At the same time, the President backed away from his remarks to New Hampshire radio stations on Friday, suggesting that he was preparing his own counterproposal to Republican plans to balance the budget over seven years.</p>
        <p>After saying that he believed such a goal was achievable, Mr. Clinton returned instead today to themes sounded by his own advisers, calling the seven-year goal "an arbitrary period" that would require "massive tax increases or massive budget cuts," which would hurt the nation's standard of living.</p>
        <p>The veto threats, delivered personally by Mr. Clinton and by the Agriculture Secretary, Dan Glickman, continued White House efforts to put the Republicans on the defensive and draw sharp distinctions between the President and the Congress.</p>
        <p>And while the White House has insisted that Mr. Clinton's comments in New Hampshire reflected only a marginal shift in his tone and thinking, it was clear from his remarks today that he and his top aides were concerned that the remarks would be interpreted as a significant shift in strategy and draw him into negotiations before he is ready.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Senate Republican leaders leapt to deride Mr. Clinton for what they called his "secret plan" to balance the budget, noting that he had endorsed the balanced budget in a key primary state known for its anti-tax mood. "It's strange that only people in New Hampshire have heard about this plan," said the Senate majority leader, Bob Dole, who is the front-runner for the Republican nomination to challenge Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>For the first time today, Mr. Clinton said he would veto legislation under consideration in the Republican Congress that would cut foreign aid and eliminate the Agency for International Development, the United States Information Agency and the Arms Control and Disarmament Agency.</p>
        <p>As the House began debating a measure to cut foreign aid by 15 percent over the next two years and the Senate Foreign Relations Committee worked on its own bill, Mr. Clinton spoke at a news conference in the Rose Garden and assailed the legislation as "the most isolationist proposals to come before the United States Congress in the last 50 years."</p>
        <p>Singling out the House proposal, Mr. Clinton said it would compromise efforts to stop North Korea's nuclear program, endanger the Administration's policy toward Russia and restrict the President's ability to fight illegal immigration. "Taken together, these constraints represent nothing less than a frontal assault on the authority of the President to conduct the foreign policy of the United States and on our nation's ability to respond rapidly and effectively to threats to our security."</p>
        <p>It was at a hearing of the Senate Agriculture Committee today that Mr. Glickman made it clear that Mr. Clinton would veto any attempt to turn the food stamp program over to the states.</p>
        <p>Mr. Glickman said that wrapping food stamps into block grants for the states would do away with a valuable feature of the food stamp and school lunch programs, which as entitlement programs automatically expand to meet increased need in a recession.</p>
        <p>But the chairman of the committee, Senator Richard G. Lugar, said that despite the veto threat he was considering suggestions by Republican governors to give each state a lump sum of Federal money to run its own food assistance program.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lugar, an Indiana Republican, said he had not decided whether to recommend such changes and added that he had heard nothing on the question from Mr. Dole.</p>
        <p>On the question of balancing the budget, when Mr. Clinton was asked if he was prepared to set a target date, he said: "No, but I can say this, I think it can be done -- well, it can -- first of all, it can be done in seven years. The question is what is the penalty and what are the tradeoffs. I think it clearly can be done in less than 10 years."</p>
        <p>Today Mr. Clinton emphasized the pain involved in balancing the budget by the year 2002, saying "that would require massive tax increases or massive budget cuts, which would be unfair to our long-term objective to stabilize the incomes and the way of living of the American people."</p>
        <p>Seeking to explain the change in emphasis, White House officials later said that since Friday Mr. Clinton had asked for detailed figures on the kinds of cuts needed to balance the budget in seven years and had rejected them as untenable. They also said he was irritated that news accounts of his New Hampshire remarks had interpreted them as signaling a shift in policy.</p>
        <p>The White House spokesman, Michael D. McCurry, also suggested that the President had signaled a willingness to negotiate too early, because House and Senate negotiators have not agreed on their own outline for balancing the budget by 2002 and have not indicated if they are willing to compromise with the White House.</p>
        <p>Asked if the President's change in tone was designed to keep the emphasis on the Republicans, Mr. McCurry said, "Bingo!"</p>
        <p>"The Republicans are still wrestling with their own resolution, and there's a huge internal contradiction in their two versions of a budget resolution," he said. "And the President has made it clear that they've got to reconcile that."</p>
        <p>Asked if the President would offer specific full-scale budget alternative, Mr. McCurry said: "It depends. And it depends on what type of posture the Congress will be in at that point.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton repeated his three longstanding conditions for negotiations with the Republicans: that they drop tax cuts for the wealthy, protect education programs and curtail the growth in Medicare only in the context of overhauling the health care system. He also added a fourth, that Republicans back off from their plan to repeal the scheduled expansion of tax credits for low-income working families with children, which were enacted after Mr. Clinton made them a central feature of his 1993 economic plan.</p>
        <p>GRAMM PROPOSAL FOR DEEP TAX CUT KILLED BY SENATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
