<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Nomo Breathes Life Into America's Game</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="764663"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES DODGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, CLAIRE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOMO, HIDEO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950524T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D8143EF937A15756C0A963958260" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Nomo Breathes Life Into America's Game</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Claire Smith</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, CLAIRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hideo Nomo of the Los Angeles Dodgers is known as the Tornado because of a unique pitching delivery in which he twists his body so much it looks like an unsprung piece of licorice.</p>
        <p>The nickname, it turns out, could also apply to the breath of fresh air brought to baseball by Nomo, the major league's first import from Japan in three decades.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hideo Nomo of the Los Angeles Dodgers is known as the Tornado because of a unique pitching delivery in which he twists his body so much it looks like an unsprung piece of licorice.</p>
        <p>The nickname, it turns out, could also apply to the breath of fresh air brought to baseball by Nomo, the major league's first import from Japan in three decades.</p>
        <p>True, Nomo has yet to earn a decision in five starts. And yes, he squandered a three-run lead against the Mets last night at Shea Stadium in his first start on the East Coast.</p>
        <p>Still, the 26-year-old contortionist from Osaka who was spared a defeat when the Dodgers rallied for a 6-4 victory is causing a refreshing flutter of genuine interest in baseball. That is a welcome occurrence in a troubled sport too long preoccupied with depressing news about drugs, spousal abuse, strikes and lockouts.</p>
        <p>What Nomo is creating is similar to the ground swell of curiosity that built up around another Dodger rookie pitcher, Fernando Valenzuela, 14 years ago. Valenzuela, whose instant stardom is still unequaled, came from another land (Mexico), too. And he applied a salve to a strike-torn game, something all of baseball has to hope Nomo can duplicate.</p>
        <p>The excitement Nomo created here last night wasn't quite Fernandomania. Baseball fans are still staying away in droves and only 19,107 people showed up at Shea. And there were a few xenophobic moments, faint cheers of "U-S-A." But there were also many people of Asian descent in the crowd, decked out in Dodgers gear and waving Japanese flags or signs in both English and Japanese. The cheers and support for the pitcher were obvious, and not lost on him or on his sport.</p>
        <p>"It's funny, but we've never had many Asian fans," said Joe McIlvaine, the Mets' general manager. "We had a lot tonight. And it's great for baseball."</p>
        <p>And Nomo is turning heads not only on both coasts but across the Pacific, as the presence of more than 100 Japanese reporters at last night's game shows.</p>
        <p>Nomo is appreciative of the support as he makes his first tour of the United States, he said through Michael Okumura, an interpreter hired by the Dodgers.</p>
        <p>"The cheering from the stands does encourage me," Nomo said at a news conference after the game. "I want to throw hard and throw good pitches for the fans who follow me."</p>
        <p>But Nomo, who won 78 games in five years in the Japanese professional leagues, is also a realist. He's happy to provide cheer for his countrymen, he says, but, he added last night, "I'd like to pick up the win."</p>
        <p>Though Nomo allowed four runs last night, he struck out seven Mets in six innings, bringing his season total to 40 strikeouts in 26 2/3 innings. "He has a good fastball," the Mets' first baseman, Rico Brogna, said. "It's hard to pick up the ball out of his delivery. His motion makes him seem that much quicker."</p>
        <p>Just listening to people talk about Nomo in that fashion was refreshing. It was baseball. Deliveries, not dollars and cents, balls and strikes, not strikes and lockouts.</p>
        <p>And make no mistake: If Nomo is becoming quite the phenomenon here, he is all that and more across the Pacific. The NHK public television network, the BBC of Japan, broadcasts his games live. Therefore, last night's game was to start at 11:40 this morning in Tokyo. Some games broadcast from the West Coast begin at 3 or 4 in the morning on Tokyo television. And people watch.</p>
        <p>"Most people think it's a dream come true," said Kikuto Muromachi, an NHK reporter. "They watch the live program full of excitement and anticipation, because he's in the major leagues."</p>
        <p>Nomo hasn't had to overcome the sorts of obstacles that a Jackie Robinson did. But there has been an element of culture shock. He is the first Japanese-born major leaguer to play in the United States in 30 years and only the second in major league history after Masanori Murakami, who played for the Giants in 1964-65.</p>
        <p>"This is a stereotype in Japan -- no one wants to hurt," Okumura said. "No one wants to be the pioneer. They can make the money in Japan. They don't have to get out to America."</p>
        <p>And Japanese players traditionally have not, content to stay, not swayed by agents pushing or pulling them across the great divide. Until now. Nomo has an agent, all but unheard of in Japan. And the agent made a great effort to get him to the Dodgers, thanks in part to a $2 million signing bonus.</p>
        <p>The way Okumura describes it, though, the money alone didn't make Nomo's decision easier. He was earning more than a million dollars a year playing professionally in Japan and is now just another minimum-wage rookie many, many miles away from home.</p>
        <p>"Many things he has sacrificed," said the interpreter. "Money. Family. Also himself. It was a big decision for him."</p>
        <p>Now, Okumura surmises, "everyone wants to follow," reversing a trade imbalance that has favored the Americas when it comes to exporting professional ballplayers.</p>
        <p>Indeed, other Japanese players may well be on the way. Already, says NHK's Yumi Ouchi, the Giants have sent inquiries to Japan about another pitcher, Masumi Kuwata.</p>
        <p>If and when Nomo's peers come, maybe they, too, can help a game and its disgruntled fans remember what once made them think major league baseball here is special. Just the way Fernando Valenzuela reminded them a decade and a half ago.  ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
