<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Borough-Power Plan Generates Heat With the Cheers</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="661042"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOROUGH PRESIDENTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUECK, THOMAS J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E0D61731F93AA35752C0A962958260" item-length="1011" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Borough-Power Plan Generates Heat With the Cheers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LUECK, THOMAS J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By suggesting that New York City's five borough presidents be given greater control over road repairs, garbage collection and other municipal services, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani may have opened a Pandora's box for a city where political power has progressively grown more centralized.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's offer to share power, which he made publicly on Dec. 30, has been warmly received by the borough presidents, and for good reason. The five officials, all political veterans, lost much of their clout with the recent elimination of the city's Board of Estimate, a powerful legislative body in which the borough presidents controlled 5 of the 11 votes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By suggesting that New York City's five borough presidents be given greater control over road repairs, garbage collection and other municipal services, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani may have opened a Pandora's box for a city where political power has progressively grown more centralized.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's offer to share power, which he made publicly on Dec. 30, has been warmly received by the borough presidents, and for good reason. The five officials, all political veterans, lost much of their clout with the recent elimination of the city's Board of Estimate, a powerful legislative body in which the borough presidents controlled 5 of the 11 votes.</p>
        <p>The officials say that Mr. Giuliani's election -- and his stated commitment to more localized government -- may reverse the long-term trend of the eroding political power of the boroughs, which have struggled to retain their identity since their consolidation into a single city in 1898.</p>
        <p>"We are now in a very advantageous position," said Guy V. Molinari, the borough president of Staten Island, who finds himself in the unlikely position of meeting with his fellow borough presidents to discuss power-sharing with City Hall less than two months after his borough voted to secede from the city.  Neighborhood Priorities</p>
        <p>In arguing for power-sharing, Mr. Molinari said the borough presidents "are in a much better position to determine priorities for their neighborhoods than a centralized government." The five officials will present City Hall with a power-sharing plan by mid-February, he added.</p>
        <p>But reversing the trend toward a centralization will not be easy, and even the suggestion has touched raw nerves on the City Council.</p>
        <p>"We know better than anyone the needs and aspirations of every segment of the city," Peter F. Vallone, the City Council Speaker, said in his annual State of the City Address on Thursday. While Mr. Vallone, who represents Queens, has sided with the new Mayor on many issues, he used the speech to draw a political line in the sand over the limits of municipal decentralization.</p>
        <p>Although the City Council would support some decentralization of control over street cleaning and other services, he said, it would fight any attempt by the borough presidents to reclaim the control over city spending that they had as members of the Board of Estimate. A Warning Note</p>
        <p>Government monitoring groups said that decentralization of the city bureaucracy should not simply mean transferring power to the borough presidents, who traditionally have been more closely allied to political organizations -- and subjected more often to charges of patronage -- than citywide officials.</p>
        <p>"The problem is accountability," said Gene Russianoff, senior attorney for the New York Public Interest Research Group. "We live in a town where everyone knows the Mayor's name and holds him accountable. How many know the name of their borough president, or even how to get to their borough hall?"</p>
        <p>While Mr. Guiliani's offer to decentralize services appeared at first to mean that he would entrust the borough presidents with power over matters like which roads should be repaired first and which parks deserve upgrading, it was clear last week that the borough presidents want more.</p>
        <p>"What good is it to decentralize if you don't have sufficient resources to do the job," said Claire Shulman, the Queens borough president, who has complained for years that her borough is short-changed, particularly compared with Manhattan. Bigger Share Sought</p>
        <p>"The issue is equity," she said.</p>
        <p>Although the Mayor did not join the increasingly rancorous debate over decentralization last week, his spokeswoman, Cristyne Lategano, said he was anxiously awaiting proposals from the borough presidents.</p>
        <p>"What he has opened is a healthy discussion of the issues," she said, adding that Mr. Giuliani was simply following through on his campaign promises.</p>
        <p>In his past statements, the Mayor has also appeared willing to allocate more city money and personnel to the boroughs outside Manhattan. The Political Side</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani's courting of the boroughs may stem in part from political realism. In November's election, he won overwhelmingly on Staten Island, and should that borough secede from the city, it could seriously damage any hopes for re-election in 1997.</p>
        <p>Perhaps mindful of his wide support in Staten Island and Queens, Mr. Giuliani plans to hold cabinet meetings of his deputies and commissioners in all the boroughs. At Mr. Molinari's inauguration last night, Mr. Giuliani said the first meeting would be on Staten Island, on or about Jan. 20.</p>
        <p>"I want the commissioners to be very involved, present and involved, wih all five boroughs," the Mayor said. "There is a perception that City Hall is too focused on lower Manhattan, which may have been a problem in the past."</p>
        <p>The borough meetings will be held every other month and in each of the boroughs at least once a year, Ms. Lategano said.</p>
        <p>In interviews, the borough presidents said that Mr. Giuliani's offer to share more power sprang from conversations he had with them the day after his election. In an initial meeting to draft their plan, senior staff members of the borough presidents met in Mr. Molinari's Staten Island offices in early December, and have set another meeting there this week.</p>
        <p>Already, according to Marilyn Gelber, executive assistant to Howard Golden, Brooklyn's borough president, representatives of the borough presidents have singled out five city agencies for decentralization: . the Parks Department, the Department of Transportation, the Department of Environmental Protection, the Sanitation Department and the Department of City Planning.</p>
        <p>Although they mainly want to decentralize routine services to streets, sewers and parks, the preliminary plan for the Department of City Planning is more complex. Ms. Gelber said the borough presidents hope to wrest control of the early phases of the process that leads to zoning changes and variances from the city's centralized planning department.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
