<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding Nature, and Inspiration, at a Summer Camp</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="820533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THE NEEDIEST CASES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW YORK TIMES NEEDIEST CASES FUND</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CAMPS AND CAMPING</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GIRLS VACATION FUND</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUENSTER, MAUREEN C</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/The Neediest Cases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Camps and Camping</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E3D91239F935A35752C0A960958260" item-length="965" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding Nature, and Inspiration, at a Summer Camp</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MAUREEN MUENSTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MUENSTER, MAUREEN C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kharisma Gray, 13, was just 5 when the police took her from her abusive mother.</p>
        <p>As one of the nearly 50,000 children who struggle to weave their way through  New York City's foster care program, Kharisma was placed in a foster home in Mount Vernon by the Children's Aid Society. After only a few years, an aunt took Kharisma into her home and, in time, the aunt and her husband adopted her.  Until the beginning of 1995, Kharisma had been living with them in the Bronx.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kharisma Gray, 13, was just 5 when the police took her from her abusive mother.</p>
        <p>As one of the nearly 50,000 children who struggle to weave their way through  New York City's foster care program, Kharisma was placed in a foster home in Mount Vernon by the Children's Aid Society. After only a few years, an aunt took Kharisma into her home and, in time, the aunt and her husband adopted her.  Until the beginning of 1995, Kharisma had been living with them in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Everything was fine, but then we started to not get along," said Kharisma,  now 14. "My aunt is in her 60's, so there is a big age gap. Naturally, we don't  see eye to eye on a lot of things."</p>
        <p>It was during this turmoil in 1994 that Kharisma joined a counseling program  at her school and was given the opportunity to attend summer camp.</p>
        <p>"They asked me, 'Where do you want to go to camp?' " Kharisma said. "At first, I didn't want to go because they told me I would have to use an outhouse  instead of a regular bathroom. But I went for two weeks and loved it."</p>
        <p>She attended Camp Oh-ne-tah in Windham, N.Y., one of the camps sponsored by the Girls Vacation Fund.</p>
        <p>Because of the age gap and continuing disagreements at home, her aunt could no longer take care of Kharisma. The Child Welfare Administration placed Kharisma with the Anthony family in Manhattan. December marked Kharisma's eighth month with the Anthony family. "I like them a lot," she said. "Mrs. Anthony is really nice."</p>
        <p>Along with adjusting to life with a new family, Kharisma had to settle in at  a new school, Public School 175 in upper Manhattan. But camp had become a constant in Kharisma's life. Receiving a scholarship from the Girls Vacation Fund again and encouragement from her new mentor at P.S. 175, Kharisma was lucky enough to attend Camp Oh-ne-tah for the second summer in a row. Because she had  such a good time the year before, Kharisma decided to go for one month instead of two weeks.</p>
        <p>"I did drama sketches, archery and swimming," she said. "I received hiking awards, a swimming award, and I received a 'Good Camper' award."</p>
        <p>One highlight of her camp experience was her relationship with her counselors, Kandace Thomas, now a freshman at Wesleyan University in Middletown, Conn., and Pam Sharlin, a graduate student at New York University School of Social Work.</p>
        <p>Ms. Thomas said Kharisma flourished at Camp Oh-ne-tah. "It is a very supportive environment, one in which you feel free to explore who you are through drama, swimming or arts and crafts," she said. Ms. Thomas also attended camp in previous years courtesy of Girls Vacation Fund.</p>
        <p>The fund receives help from the Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, one of seven organizations supported by The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.  Because The Times pays for the overhead, contributions to the campaign go directly to the organizations. The fund's 84th annual appeal for donations runs  through Feb. 29.</p>
        <p>"Right from the start, Kharisma was very outgoing, very sociable and showed good leadership skills," Ms. Thomas said. "For example, when there was competition going on between two girls in the cabin, Kharisma would usually be the mediator. She probably did the same thing for her girlfriends outside of camp."</p>
        <p>Ms. Sharlin agreed. "Kharisma was warm and affectionate and good with other campers, especially those who were having problems adjusting," she said.</p>
        <p>Thanks to encouragement from the two counselors, Kharisma is looking into attending private school through programs that place inner-city youths. "I want  to be a lawyer," she said. "My aunt always told me that I would be a great lawyer, since I love to argue so much."</p>
        <p>In the meantime, Kharisma continues to enjoy the welcoming embrace of her new foster family. "Whatever your situation, there will be people who will help you  make it through life," she said.</p>
        <p>HOW TO HELP</p>
        <p>Checks payable to The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund should be sent to P.O.  Box 5193, General Post Office, New York, N.Y. 10087, or any of these organizations:</p>
        <p>BROOKLYN BUREAU OF COMMUNITY SERVICE 285 Schermerhorn Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11217.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES OF THE ARCHDIOCESE OF NEW YORK 1011 First Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>CATHOLIC CHARITIES, DIOCESE OF BROOKLYN AND QUEENS 191 Joralemon Street, Brooklyn, N.Y. 11201.</p>
        <p>CHILDREN'S AID SOCIETY 105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>COMMUNITY SERVICE SOCIETY OF NEW YORK 105 East 22d Street, New York, N.Y. 10010.</p>
        <p>FEDERATION OF PROTESTANT WELFARE AGENCIES 281 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y.  10010.</p>
        <p>UJA-FEDERATION OF NEW YORK 130 East 59th Street, Room 427, New York, N.Y. 10022.</p>
        <p>No agents or solicitors are authorized to seek contributions for The New York Times Neediest Cases Fund.</p>
        <p>The Times pays the fund's expenses, so all contributions go directly to the charities, which use them to provide services and cash assistance to the poor.</p>
        <p>Contributions to the fund are deductible on Federal, state and city income taxes to the extent permitted by law.</p>
        <p>To delay may mean to forget.</p>
        <p>Previously recorded $3,067,802.59 Recorded yesterday $259,079.16 Total $3,326,881.75</p>
        <p>THE NEEDIEST CASES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
