<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Collages in Color and Black and White</title>
    <meta content="30ART.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="ART" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="861634"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="ART"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRAFF, PHYLLIS</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BIANCHI, BEN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARCA-RELLI, CONRAD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960630T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05EEDA123FF933A05755C0A960958260" item-length="1039" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Collages in Color and Black and White</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHYLLIS BRAFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRAFF, PHYLLIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ben Bianchi</p>
        <p>Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center, 830 Fireplace Road, East Hampton. To July 28. By appointment, 324-4929.</p>
        <p>IN a departure from presentations of art related to the Pollock years, this historic site features 1995 collages by Ben Bianchi, a friend and one-time neighbor of Lee Krasner. Over the years, visitors have noted an intriguing, surreal assemblage by Mr. Bianchi that Ms. Krasner had placed rather centrally in her parlor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ben Bianchi</p>
        <p>Pollock-Krasner House and Study Center, 830 Fireplace Road, East Hampton. To July 28. By appointment, 324-4929.</p>
        <p>IN a departure from presentations of art related to the Pollock years, this historic site features 1995 collages by Ben Bianchi, a friend and one-time neighbor of Lee Krasner. Over the years, visitors have noted an intriguing, surreal assemblage by Mr. Bianchi that Ms. Krasner had placed rather centrally in her parlor.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bianchi tried to infuse the collages with visual and mental energy by layering torn fragments of his watercolors, drawings and prints with a miscellany of commercial and periodical papers. Original gestural markings in his recycled art now appear abruptly truncated by their new, accidentally determined boundaries, and this contributes to the busy dynamics.</p>
        <p>There is a reminder here of Ms. Krasner's tearing and re-using of her earlier work, but Mr. Bianchi chooses a broader palette, bringing in lettering from printed matter and images conjuring sight and sound impressions, particularly of New York's Chinatown, the location of his last studio. A scrap of medical chart in one collage serves as a reminder that this is, in a sense, a memorial exhibition. Mr. Bianchi died in March at age 62 after a long illness. He had worked on the collages while recuperating from surgery.</p>
        <p>A concurrent presentation calls attention to a single painting, a collaborative work by Jackson Pollock, William Baziotes and Gerome Kamrowski, that resonates with historical significance. It brings visitors back to an evening in 1941 when Mr. Baziotes brought Pollock to Mr. Kamrowski's studio and the three decided to experiment with some quick-drying paint developed for commercial purposes. A principal interest was finding a freer way of applying paint to go further with the psychic automatism that they had been recently discussing with the Surrealist painter Matta. They tried dripping, pouring and flinging the loosely flowing material. The result is a dark surface bearing bold biomorphic shapes activated by overlapping lines of varying widths. Lines alternately strike a course, then swirl and loop unpredictibly, inviting the eye through a maze of visual discovery. Where these energetic strands loop into the canvas's black areas, they eliminate the separation between image and background and suggest the shifting ambiguities that were so important to subsequent phases of abstraction. This is the one surviving work from that evening. It is on loan from Mr. Kamrowski's daughter.</p>
        <p>Coenties Slip Artists: Now and Then</p>
        <p>Elise Goodheart Fine Arts, 61 Island View Drive, Sag Harbor. To July 14. 725-5764.</p>
        <p>More than 30 years ago, Charles Hinman physically altered the picture plane with concave/convex canvases, and Agnes Martin turned rhythmic gestures into a mesmerizing repetitive order. Both were among a group renting studios on Coenties Slip, at that time an inexpensive and forgotten part of old New York's commercial waterfront. Their work, along with that of their neighbors Joe Cali, Robert Indiana, Ellsworth Kelly, Fred Mitchell, Lenore Tawney and Jack Youngerman, is the subject of this modest but historically sound overview.</p>
        <p>Comparisions between that period and recent work suggest that most have continued to grow within the formal areas they defined while at Coenties Slip, although this is not the comprehensive show that would be necessary to examine the question fully.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the greatest shift appears in the remarkable pieces by Ms. Tawney. Her 1967 ''Shield'' is a part-firm, part-pliable form of feathers and fiber that emphasizes the expressive handling of materials. The 1996 assemblage ''Shrine XV'' uses a puffy, toylike animal anchored in a grid of blue wires to deliver a conceptual message about a high-technology world.</p>
        <p>There are obvious shifts, too, in some fine pieces by Mr. Kelly, who has continued to research Minimalist dynamics, and by Mr. Mitchell, who now softens edges and tones, infusing them with light to add a shimmering quality to a rich, densely painted surface.</p>
        <p>Mr. Indiana's six-foot sculpture ''Love'' now seems like an icon of its day. This and the artist's several other examples make strong additions to the presentation.</p>
        <p>Conrad Marca-Relli</p>
        <p>Vered Gallery, 68 Park Place Passage, East Hampton. To July 11. 324-3303.</p>
        <p>In this wonderful selection of primarily black and white collages, 1956 -- 1996, Mr. Marca-Relli looks his best. As good, perhaps, as he did in his Whitney Museum show in 1967. It may be significant that just 6 of the 15 pieces here are dated after that show, and it is undoubtedly significant that the gallery has hung none of the late-60's collages with strap motifs, which, in retrospect, seem to have slowed the surface interactions.</p>
        <p>It should be noted, however, that two works from the 70's make substantial contributions to the show. ''Windmill,'' a smashing 11-foot burst of diagonal energy, functions in the area between worldly image and abstract emblem. ''Figures'' provides a sense of texture, unravelling material and handcrafting. Its adaptation of grommets as a visual motif also encourages a play between a factual reading and pure abstraction.</p>
        <p>A complex inventory of ideas runs throughout the exhibition. Most impressive is the use of perceptual forces as a subject. In the best example, ''October,'' dots of differing sizes behave like stains, blurring and spreading as if they were seeking their own boundaries. While all relate, each is held within its own unit.</p>
        <p>It is the variety of approaches to creating units, or fragments, that also makes an impact. These segments establish order, but at the same time the torn edges introduce a sense of the accidentally determined shape. Other works stand out for the way they consider questions of weight, movement and the layering of seemingly flat forms in different planes. Most of the work has held its force, urgency and power well over the years. The bolder examples that are close to the interests of younger artists may even have gained in stature.</p>
        <p>ART</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
