<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Economic Scene; Radio Waves Can Be Solid Gold</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="491438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RADIO</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PASSELL, PETER</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ECONOMIC SCENE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Economic Scene</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Radio</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DF1F3BF937A35751C1A967958260" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Economic Scene; Radio Waves Can Be Solid Gold</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter Passell</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PASSELL, PETER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WANT to earn big money in your spare time? You might take a flier on a sure-fire cold fusion stock recommended by that nice young broker on the telephone from Fort Lauderdale. Or you could really strike it rich by doing what hundreds of lucky millionaires have done: enter one of Washington's bizarre lotteries for licenses to use the airwaves.</p>
        <p>For years, economists have gnashed their teeth over the policy of giving away stunningly valuable rights to use the radio spectrum. And for years, those who already control commercial licenses have successfully defended their sinecures by fending off attempts to end the giveaway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WANT to earn big money in your spare time? You might take a flier on a sure-fire cold fusion stock recommended by that nice young broker on the telephone from Fort Lauderdale. Or you could really strike it rich by doing what hundreds of lucky millionaires have done: enter one of Washington's bizarre lotteries for licenses to use the airwaves.</p>
        <p>For years, economists have gnashed their teeth over the policy of giving away stunningly valuable rights to use the radio spectrum. And for years, those who already control commercial licenses have successfully defended their sinecures by fending off attempts to end the giveaway.</p>
        <p>But the stalemate is apparently on the verge of being broken. Thanks to the persistence of the revenue-hungry Bush Administration and a growing realization among Congressional Democrats that assignment by any other means has become an administrative nightmare, there's an excellent chance Uncle Sam will auction off some new licenses. The public payoff, estimates Peter Pitsch, a former Federal Communications Commission staff member who is a communications consultant in Washington, could amount to "billions and billions."</p>
        <p>Room on the spectrum, needed for everything from broadcasting television to paging the dishwasher repairman, has generally been parceled out to the applicants who can show how they are uniquely qualified to revitalize the economy or brighten the dreary lives of their fellow Americans. But once assigned, licenses effectively became private property, to be freely sold to anyone without a felony conviction.</p>
        <p>That makes the award equivalent to a visit from John Beresford Tipton. And as the value of the licenses has grown, so has the legion of lawyers employed to argue over their initial disposition. Polite elbowing for the juicier slices of the spectrum in the 1960's and 70's turned to outright frenzy in the 80's, once the commission started dispensing licenses for cellular phone systems in big cities, worth hundreds of millions of dollars each. In an attempt to cut through the time-consuming sham of searching for the most qualified licensees, the commission decided in the late 1980's to distribute licenses by lottery.</p>
        <p>But the lotteries have not reduced the agency's workload. Consultants armed with laser printers and faxes now stand poised to fire off lottery entries at the first glimpse of license green. Earlier this year, a lottery for relatively low-value spectrum to be used for data transfer services drew 60,000 applications in just two days.</p>
        <p>Nor have the lotteries satisfied critics like the former F.C.C. chairman, Mark Fowler, who asks why the Government gives away the spectrum when it sells rights to extract oil, harvest timber and graze cattle on public land. The Commerce Department estimates that the total market value of cellular phone licenses alone exceeds $50 billion. It is, in fact, the lure of this revenue that is changing the politics of spectrum policy. The Bush Administration is eager for any new source of cash that does not begin with the letter T. And it has refused to go along with a Congressional initiative to transfer a fat slab of underused spectrum from government to civilian use unless the licenses are sold to the highest bidder.</p>
        <p>A year ago Congress would almost certainly have defended license applicants' rights to something for nothing. But a combination of disgust with the lottery follies and pressure to make room for new mobile communications technologies has weakened the opposition. "There's open-mindedness on the part of Democrats," reports Janice Obuchowski, the Assistant Secretary of Commerce in charge of telecommunications policy.</p>
        <p>In the Senate, an auction bill is expected to breeze through next session, after broadcasters and perhaps rural telephone companies have carved exemptions in stone. It will have a tougher time in the House, where John D. Dingell, the Michigan Democrat who is the powerful chairman of the Commerce Committee and a longstanding skeptic on auctions, is sure to demand his pound of flesh. But aides to Mr. Dingell say that he will try to square the auction idea with sound public policy, not kill it altogether.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dingell will, for example, seek to prevent the Government from enriching the Treasury at the expense of consumers who must buy services from license holders. Such ploys are not unthinkable: Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher, sometime champion of free markets, worked to shore up British Airways' privileged landing rights and routes before selling the airline on the stock market.</p>
        <p>Even with Congressionally mandated restrictions, the pot of gold at the end of the auction rainbow could be enormous. A dazzling array of new technologies, ranging from low-cost pocket phones to compact-disk quality digital radio to satellite-based worldwide communications systems, lack only room on the spectrum to become a commercial reality. And this time around, Uncle Sam could share in the bounty.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
