<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ROWLAND SEEKING TAX AND JOB CUTS</title>
    <meta content="14CONN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="908820"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Excise Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Metro-North Commuter Railroad</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rabinovitz, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowland, John G (Gov)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Excise Taxes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Railroads</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7D8143FF937A25751C0A961958260" item-length="1089" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ROWLAND SEEKING TAX AND JOB CUTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN RABINOVITZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rabinovitz, Jonathan</byline>
      <dateline>HARTFORD, Feb. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Connecticut Gov John G Rowland, continuing his drive to shrink state government, proposes two-year $20.5 billion budget that will substantially cut state income tax and reduce work force by about 10 percent; calls for reducing state gasoline excise tax, at 39 cents nation's highest, by nickel this year; reduction will be paid in part by ending railroad service on Metro-North branch lines to Danbury and Waterbury as well as Shoreline East railroad service in southeastern Connecticut; Rowland calls for cutting income tax by about $380 million in 1998; graph (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Continuing his drive to shrink state government, Gov. John G. Rowland today proposed a two-year $20.5 billion budget that would substantially cut the state income tax and reduce the work force by about 10 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland also called for reducing the state gasoline excise tax, at 39 cents the nation's highest, by a nickel this year. The reduction would be paid for in part by ending railroad service on the Metro-North branch lines to Danbury and Waterbury as well as the Shoreline East railroad service in southeastern Connecticut, replacing it with bus service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Continuing his drive to shrink state government, Gov. John G. Rowland today proposed a two-year $20.5 billion budget that would substantially cut the state income tax and reduce the work force by about 10 percent.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland also called for reducing the state gasoline excise tax, at 39 cents the nation's highest, by a nickel this year. The reduction would be paid for in part by ending railroad service on the Metro-North branch lines to Danbury and Waterbury as well as the Shoreline East railroad service in southeastern Connecticut, replacing it with bus service.</p>
        <p>The plan will likely be the blueprint for Mr. Rowland's re-election bid next year, and it stayed close to the themes that were at the heart of his 1994 campaign: cutting spending and eliminating the state income tax by the year 2000.</p>
        <p>While today's proposal appeared to concede that Mr. Rowland's goal of phasing out the income tax would not be achieved, legislators said the proposed cut would still make a sizable dent in the state budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland, a Republican, called for cutting income tax by about $380 million in 1998, beyond the $200 million cut enacted two years ago. If the proposal is accepted in its entirety -- an unlikely prospect given that Democrats control both houses of the legislature -- it will mean that he will have reduced the income tax by one-fifth during his tenure.</p>
        <p>In a 21-minute speech today, Mr. Rowland offered no bold new programs or any major increases in state spending. Instead, he vowed that total spending next year would be slightly less than this year, the first decrease in more than 35 years.</p>
        <p>''I'm not here with a fistful of dollars and a long list of promises,'' Mr. Rowland said. ''That's the old way we used to do business.''</p>
        <p>But Democrats, who control the General Assembly, questioned whether Mr. Rowland's budget truly delivered the cuts he promised. They noted that two years ago, he said his budget reduced spending when it actually included a small increase.</p>
        <p>The biggest sticking point appeared to be Mr. Rowland's plan to achieve about $200 million in savings in two years through an early retirement plan for state employees.</p>
        <p>''That is just not going to happen,'' said the Speaker of the House, Thomas D. Ritter, noting that the state employee unions had refused such a plan in recent negotiations. Even if it were enacted, past early retirement programs in 1989 and 1991 ended up costing the state money, not saving it, Mr. Ritter added.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ritter also complained that Mr. Rowland's income tax cut relied, in part, on repealing a property tax credit that was passed several years ago and was to take effect this year.</p>
        <p>''We're not going to accept his sense of what the bottom line is,'' Mr. Ritter said. ''We need to come up with a budget that is realistic.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland's budget officials projected that about 2,500 of the state's 46,000 employees would participate in an early retirement program and that only one in every five would be replaced.</p>
        <p>These cuts come in addition to another reduction of roughly 2,000 jobs over the next two years through program changes. This would mean that the state work force would be reduced to 42,047 in fiscal year 1999 from 46,109 this year, a decline that could involve layoffs.</p>
        <p>Union leaders said that such reductions would lead to serious deterioration in government service and that there was evidence in today's budget of some new restrictions.</p>
        <p>These are a few of the most controversial items:</p>
        <p>*A move to eliminate welfare for about 12,000 single adults who are deemed employable, an idea that the Legislature has rejected in the past.</p>
        <p>*A projection that the total cost of the state's family welfare program would fall by almost one-half, or $$150 million, by 1999, as the state's 21-month time limit is finally phased in, ending state benefits for thousands of women and children.</p>
        <p>*A 12 percent cut -- about $20 million -- in the University of Connecticut's budget, which is likely to be unpopular among the many UConn alumni in the Legislature.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland did propose new funds to comply with last summer's State Supreme Court order that the state must desegregate and improve the Hartford schools. That decision, Sheff v. O'Neill, has been seen by many as a mandate to improve the racial balance of schools throughout the state, as well as to enhance education in urban school systems.</p>
        <p>But many Democratic lawmakers felt that the $63 million Mr. Rowland offered over the two-year budget period to address the Sheff case was not enough. ''The new commitments to Sheff funding are really peanuts,'' said State Representative Cameron Staples, a co-chairman of the legislature's Education Committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rowland's proposal to cut the gas tax is expected to draw widespread support, although the state's gasoline tax would remain higher than those of New York, New Jersey, Rhode Island and Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Underlying many of these budget decisions was Mr. Rowland's strong conviction that the top priority continues to be reducing the income tax, a stark contrast with the Democratic focus on relieving the property tax burden, one of the nation's heaviest.</p>
        <p>While recent surveys suggest that the public is roughly divided between these two choices, Mr. Rowland argued today that reducing the income tax was the most equitable way of providing a tax break.</p>
        <p>''Everyone pays income tax,'' Mr. Rowland said. ''We didn't ask whether people owned property when we took money away from them; we shouldn't be asking if they own property when we give it back.''</p>
        <p>Under this proposal, a typical family filing a joint return could save $820 in 1998, when it would take effect. The plan would reduce the income tax rate to 3 percent from 4.5 percent on the first $48,000 of taxable income for joint filers.</p>
        <p>At present, joint filers get the lower rate only on the first $9,000 of taxable income. Taxable income is determined for joint filers by deducting $24,000 from the family's gross income.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
