<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kerry Returns Check to Donor Facing Tax Evasion Charges</title>
    <meta content="22FINA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/22/politics/campaign/22finance.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1591374"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN FINANCE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">South Korea</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Worth, Robert F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chun Jae Yong</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chun Doo Hwan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yi, Rick</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Campaign Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Asian-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Korea</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerry, John F</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E3DA1339F931A15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kerry Returns Check to Donor Facing Tax Evasion Charges</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kerry Returns Check to Donor Facing Tax Evasion Charges</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT F. WORTH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Worth, Robert F</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John Kerry's presidential campaign returns $2,000 check after discovering that it came from former South Korean Pres Chun Doo Hwan's son Chun Jae Yong, who has been arrested by South Korean authorities and charged with evading taxes on millions of dollars in inheritance money; elder Chun was convicted of bribery in 1997 and pardoned next year; Kerry campaign officials say donation was solicited by Rick Yi, high-level Kerry fund-raiser who has raised more than $100,000 for Kerry, mostly from Asian-Americans; Kerry campaign officials say they have confidence in their screening procedures (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John Kerry's presidential campaign has returned a $2,000 check after discovering that it came from a former South Korean president's son who has been arrested and charged with tax evasion.</p>
        <p>The campaign gave back the check last week after learning from The Associated Press that it came from Chun Jae Yong, who was arrested by South Korean authorities in February -- six months after his donation -- and charged with evading taxes on millions of dollars in inheritance money. Mr. Chun's father, Chun Doo Hwan, the former South Korean president, was convicted of bribery in 1997 and pardoned the next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John Kerry's campaign has returned a $2,000 check after discovering that it came from a former South Korean president's son who has been charged with tax evasion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator John Kerry's presidential campaign has returned a $2,000 check after discovering that it came from a former South Korean president's son who has been arrested and charged with tax evasion.</p>
        <p>The campaign gave back the check last week after learning from The Associated Press that it came from Chun Jae Yong, who was arrested by South Korean authorities in February -- six months after his donation -- and charged with evading taxes on millions of dollars in inheritance money. Mr. Chun's father, Chun Doo Hwan, the former South Korean president, was convicted of bribery in 1997 and pardoned the next year.</p>
        <p>Campaign officials said that the donation was solicited by Rick Yi, a high-level Kerry fund-raiser who is based in Georgia. Mr. Yi has raised more than $100,000 for Mr. Kerry and $400,000 more for Democrats, mostly from Asian-Americans.</p>
        <p>Separately, campaign officials and the South Korean consulate in Los Angeles said, Mr. Yi met with a South Korean consular official in Los Angeles seeking to set up a Korean-American political group to exert influence on issues relevant to South Korean immigrants.</p>
        <p>Mr. Yi, a businessman and former military attaché in the Clinton White House, did not return repeated calls for comment on Monday. He told The A.P. that he did not think at the time there was any problem with the donation from Mr. Chun, a business partner of his for about six months, and that Mr. Chun had said he was a legal resident of the United States who could make donations.</p>
        <p>A Democratic Party official, who spoke on condition of anonymity, said Monday that the other contributions Mr. Yi solicited had been checked and that none appeared to be problems.</p>
        <p>Kerry campaign officials said they had confidence in their screening procedures and had no plans to change them. ''We have a vetting process where we work with fund-raisers to make sure all donations are legal and proper,'' said Michael Meehan, a campaign spokesman.</p>
        <p>The consular official, Chung Byung Man, returned to South Korea in May on a routine rotation, said Min Ryu, a consul at the Los Angeles office. ''He was never directly involved in political donation activities,'' Mr. Ryu said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ryu added that Mr. Chung was initially approached by Mr. Yi, who had asked him for introductions to some Korean-Americans in Los Angeles. Mr. Chung made the introductions, Mr. Ryu said.</p>
        <p>''He only introduced them personally,'' Mr. Ryu added, saying there was no intent to be involved in partisan activities.</p>
        <p>The Bush campaign on Monday jumped on the returned donation.</p>
        <p>''These revelations raise serious and troubling questions about the fund-raising practices of the Kerry campaign that the Kerry campaign has failed to answer,'' said Steve Schmidt, a Bush campaign spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Schmidt said he saw a shadow of the Democratic campaign finance scandal of the 1996 campaign, which became a serious embarrassment for the party and raised the specter of foreign interests seeking to buy political influence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry was touched by those scandals in 1997 when he acknowledged receiving campaign contributions arranged by Johnny Chung, a California businessman and Democratic fund-raiser who eventually pleaded guilty to bank fraud, tax evasion and conspiracy in connection with $20,000 in illegal contributions to the Clinton-Gore re-election campaign and to making $8,000 in illegal donations to Mr. Kerry's Senate campaign.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry, who also helped arrange a visit to the Securities and Exchange Commission for Johnny Chung and some foreign business associates, returned the donations after questions were raised about Mr. Chung's fund-raising in 1997.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meehan disputed the comparison with the fund-raising excesses of the 1996 campaign. Mr. Chun made his donation last August and was not arrested until February, Mr. Meehan noted. The campaign returned the money as soon as it learned of the arrest last week, he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meehan added that there was no indication that Chung Byung Man, the consulate official, tried to raise money or did anything improper. He said Mr. Yi, the Kerry fund-raiser, declined Mr. Chung's offer to help create the Korean-American political group.</p>
        <p>THE 2004 CAMPAIGN: CAMPAIGN FINANCE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
