<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An annual survey finds relations deteriorating between clients and their agencies.</title>
    <meta content="Y21ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1040551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Salz, Nancy L, Consulting</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E6D6133DF932A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An annual survey finds relations deteriorating between clients and their agencies.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Salz Survey of Advertiser-Agency Relations conducted by Nancy L Salz Consulting finds relationship between agencies and advertisers is deteriorating; surveys for 1996 and 1997 had brought surprisingly better responses from executives at agencies and client companies when asked about nature of their relations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE relationship between agencies and advertisers is deteriorating, according to an annual survey, after two years of results that had begun to narrow a yawning chasm between the two sides.</p>
        <p>''We had seen some real improvements, but this year the advertisers and agencies are starting to fall out again,'' said Nancy L. Salz, president of Nancy L. Salz Consulting in New York, who offered a preview of the findings of the 1998 Salz Survey of Advertiser-Agency Relations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE relationship between agencies and advertisers is deteriorating, according to an annual survey, after two years of results that had begun to narrow a yawning chasm between the two sides.</p>
        <p>''We had seen some real improvements, but this year the advertisers and agencies are starting to fall out again,'' said Nancy L. Salz, president of Nancy L. Salz Consulting in New York, who offered a preview of the findings of the 1998 Salz Survey of Advertiser-Agency Relations.</p>
        <p>The surveys for 1996 and 1997 had brought surprisingly better responses from executives at agencies and client companies when asked about the nature of their relations. But that era of good feelings proved brief, much to Ms. Salz's dismay.</p>
        <p>''I wasn't expecting that,'' Ms. Salz said, referring to the conclusions of the 1998 survey.</p>
        <p>The survey, which has been conducted for the last 13 years, is significant because what advertisers and agencies think and feel about each other strongly influences their ability to work together. That in turn can profoundly affect the quality and effectiveness of the campaigns that are aimed at consumers.</p>
        <p>''People have to stay focused on the advertising,'' Ms. Salz said, ''but it's very, very easy to lose that focus.'' Indeed, advertisers responding to the survey said that if they could consistently obtain the best work from their agencies, their sales would increase by 25 percent.</p>
        <p>Half the agency executives who replied to the survey said that there was increased tension in the relationship with major clients. That figure was at its highest level since 1994. At the same time, 30 percent of the executives at client companies said that there was increased tension in the relationship with their agencies.</p>
        <p>Both agencies and advertisers also told of frustrations with the process by which ads are produced. Asked if in the last year there were more or fewer hassles (to use the wording of the question) than previously, 45 percent of agencies, and 25 percent of advertisers, answered by saying there were more.</p>
        <p>And there were sharp differences in the responses to a question about whether there was more or less teamwork in the agency-client relationship. Sixty-four percent of advertisers said that there was more teamwork, a record figure for that response; 5 percent said that there was less teamwork.</p>
        <p>When agencies were asked the same question, only 36 percent said that there was more teamwork. Thirty-two percent said that there was less teamwork, a record figure for that response.</p>
        <p>The primary reason for the reversal of fortune in the survey, Ms. Salz said, was ''the extraordinary pressure on advertisers to increase earnings to justify stock value.''</p>
        <p>''As the bull market goes on, those pressures are even greater,'' she added. ''So what clients demand of their agencies causes the tensions.''</p>
        <p>''Both advertisers and agencies agree that the agencies have responded well to the pressure,'' Ms. Salz said, ''and are more focused on their clients' needs. However, they do not agree how well their relationship is going.''</p>
        <p>Generally, Ms. Salz said, survey responses from advertisers were more optimistic than those from their agencies. That's an interesting twist to the widespread perception that Madison Avenue is replete with preternatural Pollyannas.</p>
        <p>Ms. Salz said she did not believe that the continuing turmoil in agency account assignments, as marketers frenetically hire and fire shops, contributed to the souring of client-agency relations.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that's an issue any more so than in the past,'' she said, citing the fact that account turnover had been particularly pronounced in 1996 and 1997 as the relationship between advertisers and agencies was deemed to be improving.</p>
        <p>Asked what clients and agencies can do, Ms. Salz suggested that they ''set the highest possible standards and insist up front on only the best,'' because they ''agree that's the most important thing you can do to create or get terrific work.''</p>
        <p>''It is easier said than done,'' Ms. Salz acknowledged, especially in such fields as telecommunications, which ''change so fast, there is no time'' to ''want great advertising.''</p>
        <p>And quality is frequently a runner-up to productivity, Ms. Salz said, particularly now that technology enables work to be produced faster.</p>
        <p>Advertisers and agencies must remember, she added, that ''ideas are still created the old-fashioned way, in people's minds and emotions.''</p>
        <p>The survey was conducted in April for Salz Consulting by Thurm Marketing and Consulting Inc. in Princeton, N.J. Salz Consulting sponsors training seminars in agency relations and advertising development for marketers like the Clorox Company and the I.B.M. Corporation.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
