<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Insurers Set $17.8 Billion Stock Deal</title>
    <meta content="Y21INS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1040572"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">American International Group Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sunamerica Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Treaster, Joseph B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenberg, Maurice R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, Eli</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E0DE103DF932A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1177" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Insurers Set $17.8 Billion Stock Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH B. TREASTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Treaster, Joseph B</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>American International Group, world leader in corporate insurance, agrees to buy SunAmerica Inc, pioneer in selling investments for retirement, for stock valued at $17.8 billion; deal brings together a pair of chief executives--Maurice R (Hank) Greenberg of American International and Eli Broad of SunAmerica, with Greenberg continuing as chairman and chief executive and Broad becoming member of the board of merged company; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a merger of insurance giants, American International Group, a world leader in corporate insurance, agreed yesterday to buy SunAmerica Inc., a pioneer in selling investments for retirement, for stock valued at $17.8 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal, one of the largest in the financial services industry, vaults American International Group into the rapidly growing business of variable annuities -- mutual funds with insurance that protects against market dips -- and gives SunAmerica a springboard to worldwide expansion through American International Group's offices in 130 countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a merger of insurance giants, American International Group, a world leader in corporate insurance, agreed yesterday to buy SunAmerica Inc., a pioneer in selling investments for retirement, for stock valued at $17.8 billion.</p>
        <p>The deal, one of the largest in the financial services industry, vaults American International Group into the rapidly growing business of variable annuities -- mutual funds with insurance that protects against market dips -- and gives SunAmerica a springboard to worldwide expansion through American International Group's offices in 130 countries.</p>
        <p>The deal also brings together a pair of chief executives -- Maurice R. (Hank)  Greenberg of American International Group and Eli Broad of SunAmerica -- who are among the most respected and admired in the insurance business. Both hold large stakes in their companies and are among the world's wealthiest people, with fortunes exceeding $1 billion each.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg is to continue as chairman and chief executive and Mr. Broad will become a member of the board of the merged company. Mr. Broad, whose personal wealth would jump more than $250 million in the transaction, will continue to direct SunAmerica from its headquarters in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''It's a terrific fit,'' Alice D. Schroeder, an analyst at Paine Webber, said. ''It fills the biggest hole in A.I.G.'s product lineup and offers a platform that SunAmerica can instantly plug into its globalization strategy.''</p>
        <p>Under the terms, SunAmerica shareholders will get 0.855 of one A.I.G. share for each SunAmerica share. Based on A.I.G.'s closing price of $94.625 Wednesday before the announcement, the deal is worth $17.8 billion.</p>
        <p>The purchase price comes to more than five times SunAmerica's book value of $2.966 billion at a time when shares of leading competitors are trading at about four times their book value.</p>
        <p>A.I.G.'s stock dropped 7.5 percent, to close at $87.50, yesterday, while shares of SunAmerica rose 11.1 percent, to close at $71.375.</p>
        <p>''Investors are sort of giving a thumbs down to the price,'' said Eric N. Berg, an analyst at CIBC Oppenheimer.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Berg and others described SunAmerica as ''an exceptional company,'' worthy of an exceptional price. ''You can't buy a good franchise at a bargain price,'' Ms. Schroeder said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg said he felt confident the price was not excessive. There is an enormous market for SunAmerica's variable annuities and other retirement investments around the world, he said, and the combined company will go after that. ''The need is global,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The promise of huge new overseas markets has been a driving force in several recent financial services megamergers, notably the combination of Citicorp and Travelers Group. Like A.I.G. and SunAmerica, partners in the Citicorp-Travelers deal hope to exploit each other's strengths to sell products around the world.</p>
        <p>Some analysts said the A.I.G.-SunAmerica deal, reported yesterday in The Wall Street Journal, could look less promising if the stock markets fell and investors began to shy away from variable annuities, which have been SunAmerica's main engine for growth. ''That's maybe a near-term implication,'' said Jay A. Cohen, an analyst at Merrill Lynch. ''But long term, I don't see a lot of downside.''</p>
        <p>Other analysts cautioned that the merged company might find it difficult to introduce American-style retirement products in some countries. Introducing new products to each other's sales forces for so-called cross-selling, the analysts noted, has proved daunting to some companies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg and Mr. Broad, who have been friends for nearly a decade, said they believed that their personal styles and their corporate cultures would integrate well.</p>
        <p>''Both Hank and I and our people are Type A people,'' Mr. Broad said. ''We like to win. We're very competitive. We believe in doing things in a quality way and we're owner-operators.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, while the two companies are publicly owned, Mr. Greenberg, 73, and Mr. Broad, 65, have run them rather like entrepreneurs, avoiding layers of committees and leaving no doubt where power resides.</p>
        <p>Mr. Broad literally built SunAmerica from the ground up. While running a successful construction business, he bought the Sun Life Insurance Company of America, an old-line life insurance company in Baltimore, as a hedge against a downturn in housing. But in 1989 he spun off the construction business. Perceiving great demand for investments aimed at providing money for retirement as the American population grayed, Mr. Broad abandoned the sale of traditional life insurance and began to sell insurance only in connection with mutual funds and other investments. He took the company public in 1989 and owns nearly 42 percent of it.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg was not a founder of A.I.G. but is responsible for the company's extraordinary growth by taking it public in 1969, nine years after he joined the company and one year after he became chief executive.</p>
        <p>Back then it had a market value of about $300 million. Today it operates 300 subsidiaries, in businesses ranging from its signature corporate coverage to automobile and life insurance, and has a market value of about $92 billion.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenberg's son, Evan G. Greenberg, is president and chief operating officer.</p>
        <p>Last year, A.I.G., with assets of $164 billion, reported net income of $3.3 billion on revenues of $30.6 billion. Net income for SunAmerica, with assets of $35.6 billion, was $379 million on revenues of $5.3 billion.  For the last decade, SunAmerica's stock has been one of the best-performing issues on the New York Stock Exchange, rising an average of 42 percent a year. In the last five years, A.I.G.'s stock value has more than doubled.</p>
        <p>A.I.G. plans to use the pooling method of accounting in the merger, which shields the merged company from some one-time charges that would reduce future earnings. The swap of stock for stock also means SunAmerica shareholders will not be liable for taxes from an increase in the value of their investment until they decide to sell their new A.I.G. stock.</p>
        <p>Domestically, Mr. Broad said, the merger would give SunAmerica entree to scores of blue-chip corporate clients of A.I.G. Larry Mayewski, a senior vice president and analyst at A. M. Best &amp; Company, the rating agency, said SunAmerica's nationwide network of broker-dealers would become an outlet for such A.I.G. products as auto and life insurance.</p>
        <p>Analysts were generally effusive about the merger. ''This is a great deal in every way,'' said Michael A. Frinquelli, a principal in Renaissance Fund Advisers, a hedge fund specializing in insurance. ''Most importantly you're marrying the two smartest guys in their respective businesses. Ask anybody in property and casualty who their idol is and it's Hank Greenberg. Ask anybody in the annuities business and it's Eli Broad.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
