<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Klansman Testifies at Leader's Murder Trial That Klan Was Benevolent</title>
    <meta content="21KLAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1040603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mississippi</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ku Klux Klan</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bragg, Rick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nix, Deavours</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bowers, Samuel H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dahmer, Vernon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Mississippi</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hate Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E6DA103DF932A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Klansman Testifies at Leader's Murder Trial That Klan Was Benevolent</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICK BRAGG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bragg, Rick</byline>
      <dateline>HATTIESBURG, Miss., Aug. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Klansman Deavours Nix testifies at trial of Samuel Bowers, former Imperial Wizard of White Knights of the Ku Klux Klan of Mississippi; Bowers is accused of ordering murder of respected civil rights leader Vernon Dahmer; Nix describes White Knights as benevolent organization and says he never even heard Bowers use a racial slur (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Spectators at the trial of a former Klansman accused of ordering the murder of a respected civil rights leader were surprised, to say the least, when another former Klansman described the White Knights of the Ku Klux Klan of Mississippi as a benevolent organization that only existed to give money to the rural poor and pass out fruit baskets at Christmas.</p>
        <p>Many of the older black people in the courtroom especially shook their heads, some of them snickered, and a few laughed out loud when Deavours Nix, a defense witness and former Klansman, testified that he never even heard the defendant, Samuel F. Bowers, use a racial slur.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Spectators at the trial of a former Klansman accused of ordering the murder of a respected civil rights leader were surprised, to say the least, when another former Klansman described the White Knights of the Ku Klux Klan of Mississippi as a benevolent organization that only existed to give money to the rural poor and pass out fruit baskets at Christmas.</p>
        <p>Many of the older black people in the courtroom especially shook their heads, some of them snickered, and a few laughed out loud when Deavours Nix, a defense witness and former Klansman, testified that he never even heard the defendant, Samuel F. Bowers, use a racial slur.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bowers, the Imperial Wizard who led the Mississippi White Knights when the violent organization was linked to murders, church burnings and beatings in the 1960's, stands accused for the fifth time of ordering the murder of Vernon Dahmer, a black grocer who was killed when his home was firebombed by Klansmen on Jan. 10, 1966. Both the prosecution and the defense wrapped up their cases today, with closing arguments scheduled for Friday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nix, who held the Klan title of ''state investigator'' though he said he did not know what that title really meant and only attended three or so Klan meetings in his life, described Mr. Bowers, now 73, as a ''patriot'' who was respectful to ladies.</p>
        <p>''He did not use profane language and I never heard him use a racial slur,'' said Mr. Nix, who himself stands accused of taking part in the firebombing that killed Mr. Dahmer, an N.A.A.C.P. leader who was helping blacks register to vote.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nix suffers from cancer and heart and lung ailments and testified from a wheelchair rigged with an oxygen bottle. He and another former Klansman, Charles Noble, are expected to go on trial later this year.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Nix testified that to his knowledge, Mr. Bowers was never the leader of the Mississippi Klan, that the Klan did not stand for violence and that he, himself, was never that much involved in it, anyway.</p>
        <p>He only joined, he said, because he heard that the Klan ''did some benevolent work, such as delivering baskets of fruit at Christmastime to people that was needy.''</p>
        <p>He never had a robe, he said. He did not hear racial slurs at the Klan meetings.</p>
        <p>But three former Klansmen who became Government informers have testified that Mr. Bowers planned and ordered Mr. Dahmer's murder at Klan meetings in 1965. He walked free, three decades ago, after four previous juries deadlocked.</p>
        <p>This trial has boiled down to the word of two factions: those former Klansmen who said Mr. Bowers was a coldly racist leader who masterminded the execution of Mr. Dahmer against those who were either members of the Klan or had Klan ties who said he was not.</p>
        <p>Based on the testimony, it was not a good day in court for Mr. Bowers, or for Mr. Nix.</p>
        <p>The lead prosecutor, Robert Helfrich, picked apart Mr. Nix's testimony one statement at a time, showing gaps in the truth that had the courtroom laughing out loud.</p>
        <p>For example, there was this exchange:</p>
        <p>''What color was your robe,'' Mr. Helfrich asked him.</p>
        <p>''I didn't have no robe,'' Mr. Nix said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Helfrich handed him a picture, from an F.B.I. file, that showed a man identified as Mr. Nix wearing a robe.</p>
        <p>''Look like that might be a robe?'' Mr. Helfrich asked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nix said it was.</p>
        <p>''Got a hood on it?'' Mr. Helfrich asked.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nix acknowledged that it did.</p>
        <p>''Holding a gun?'' Mr. Helfrich said, referring to the man in the picture.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nix did not deny any of it. Instead, he just said of the man in the picture:</p>
        <p>''That ain't me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Helfrich asked Mr. Nix whether he remembered something his wife had said when F.B.I. agents seized the picture in the spring of 1966. According to court documents, Mr. Helfrich said, Mr. Nix's wife walked up to him and said: ''They found that silly picture of you with the pointed hood on.''</p>
        <p>Much of courtroom guffawed at that.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nix's credibility has already been questioned. After he was arrested in May when state officials decided they had enough evidence for one more trial, he told the presiding judge that his health was bad and that he needed regular treatment. Several days later, a news photographer took a picture of ''his backswing'' at a golf course, said Mr. Helfrich.</p>
        <p>When he was ordered back before the judge, he had five golf tees in his pocket.</p>
        <p>''How many fruit baskets did you deliver for the Klan?'' asked Mr. Helfrich here today, sounding disgusted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nix said none.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
