<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Fluff to 'Eternity': The Many Faces of Sinatra on Screen</title>
    <meta content="21SINA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1040521"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Film Society of Lincoln Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Holden, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sinatra, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Day, Doris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEEDB133DF932A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Fluff to 'Eternity': The Many Faces of Sinatra on Screen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Holden, Stephen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Lincoln Center to show 1954 movie Young at Heart, starring Frank Sinatra and Doris Day as part of Film Society's Salute to Sinatra; photo from scene in movie; chart listing movies to be shown in series (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of the more unlikely romantic couplings to be found in a 1950's Hollywood movie was the pairing of Frank Sinatra as a gaunt, impoverished young composer from New York City and Doris Day as his indefatigably chipper apple-cheeked Connecticut dream girl. Ms. Day's character, who is engaged to another man throughout much of the film, is the singer with a family orchestra whose perky togetherness and taste for kitsch vaguely suggests a tacky Connecticut equivalent of the Von Trapps.</p>
        <p>The Sinatra character, an Italian-American who has changed his name to disguise his origin, moans on and on about how the fates have conspired against him in both his career and his love life. When he sings ''One For My Baby'' near the end of the  film, the song becomes a summation of all the self-pitying complaints that have gone before. Throughout the movie, Ms. Day's goody-goody, who finds herself strangely drawn to him, is tireless (to the point of obnoxiousness) in her efforts to cheer up this self-proclaimed loser who, unbeknownst to her, has been nursing a case of unrequited love.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of the more unlikely romantic couplings to be found in a 1950's Hollywood movie was the pairing of Frank Sinatra as a gaunt, impoverished young composer from New York City and Doris Day as his indefatigably chipper apple-cheeked Connecticut dream girl. Ms. Day's character, who is engaged to another man throughout much of the film, is the singer with a family orchestra whose perky togetherness and taste for kitsch vaguely suggests a tacky Connecticut equivalent of the Von Trapps.</p>
        <p>The Sinatra character, an Italian-American who has changed his name to disguise his origin, moans on and on about how the fates have conspired against him in both his career and his love life. When he sings ''One For My Baby'' near the end of the  film, the song becomes a summation of all the self-pitying complaints that have gone before. Throughout the movie, Ms. Day's goody-goody, who finds herself strangely drawn to him, is tireless (to the point of obnoxiousness) in her efforts to cheer up this self-proclaimed loser who, unbeknownst to her, has been nursing a case of unrequited love.</p>
        <p>''Young at Heart,'' which will be shown Sept. 4 to 6 at the Walter Reade Theater as part of the Film Society of Lincoln Center's ''Salute to Sinatra,'' is a musically enhanced remake of ''Four Daughters,'' the 1938 movie in which John Garfield made his screen debut. In the remake Sinatra fills Garfield's shoes,  playing the same vulnerable ''ethnic'' outsider pressing his nose to the glass and peering with longing at a preposterously idealized vision of WASP gentility.</p>
        <p>The 1954 movie, whose title was taken from the hit song that commercially revitalized Sinatra's recording career after a long slide, is miles away from the best film he made. But what it captures, perhaps more purely than any of his other movies, is the essence of his screen charisma and the mannerisms that embellished it.</p>
        <p>There is the raised left eyebrow arched to the point of no return, expressing a deep quizzical sadness that in later films shaded into a combative cynicism. There is the tilted fedora that seemed to float on the side of his head like a more grown-up rakish version of the askew sailor hat he sported in 40's movie musicals. There is the cigarette dangling so precariously from one side of his upper lip that you begin to wonder if the butt hasn't been glued on.</p>
        <p>Finally there are the eyes that seem to spin like blue pinwheels, alternately searchingly lonely and penetratingly observant. As Sinatra aged, that aura of loneliness and wonder steadily gave way to a harder glare seething with a tough, often accusatory carnal knowledge.</p>
        <p>One thing that ''A Salute to Frank Sinatra'' forcefully demonstrates is that Sinatra didn't have to sing to be a movie star. Singing may have gotten him into the movies. But after his 1953 comeback in ''From Here to Eternity,'' he wouldn't have had to sing another note to continue on screen as long as he cared. As the series also shows, after ''From Here to Eternity,'' the period in which Sinatra cared didn't last too long.</p>
        <p>At his most convincing, he embodied and carried forward his own version of Garfield's up-from-the-streets outsider tradition, mixing it with some of Humphrey Bogart's hard-as-nails-but-still-vulnerable tough guy. To these archetypes he brought an extra dimension of waifish vulnerability. More than any other male movie star, with the possible exception of Montgomery Clift, Sinatra wore his nerve endings on his sleeve. But where Clift's characters seemed terminally neurotic, Sinatra's were scrappy outsiders fighting their way in.</p>
        <p>Sinatra's physique had a lot to do with it. In an era of fleshy male stars, he was skinny and as a bobby-socks idol had been ridiculed for it. Thinness, of course, has always been equated with hypersensitivity (think of the expression thin-skinned), and Sinatra's tender imploring ballad style of those early years was nothing if not sensitive.</p>
        <p>With Maggio, the Academy Award-winning role in ''From Here to Eternity'' that turned his career around in 1953 (and for which he was paid a measly $8,000), all the chemical ingredients of Sinatra's screen and vocal persona came together. The wiry, high-strung outsider whose self-martyring refusal to buckle to authority costs him his life is a version of the same personality who could prostrate himself totally to a self-destructive passion in a song like ''I'm a Fool to Want You.'' But that scrappy outsider could also swing out with a feisty aggression that on a good night could best an opponent twice his size.</p>
        <p>But could Sinatra really act? It depends on what you mean by acting. Even in his most ''serious'' performances, you are never less than 100 percent aware that what you're watching is Sinatra giving a performance. And when the shoe fits, that performance can be impressive.</p>
        <p>Perhaps his finest moment after his triumph as Maggio came in ''The Man With the Golden Arm,'' Otto Preminger's black-and-white 1955 adaptation of Nelson Algren's novel in which Sinatra plays a heroin-addicted cardsharp and aspiring drummer fighting to survive on Chicago's mean streets. The scenes in which his character goes cold turkey with the help of Kim Novak (as a sympathetic bar girl) are still harrowing to watch.</p>
        <p>As his character goes through the shakes and cold chills, his nerve endings aren't just on his sleeve, they're emitting stinging lightning flashes from all over his body.</p>
        <p>''A Salute to Sinatra,'' which begins today and runs through Sept. 8, features 19 of the 57 films he made. All phases of his career are represented, from the 40's musicals to the 50's dramas (excluding ''Suddenly,'' the well-regarded film in which he played a Presidential assassin) to his Rat Pack capers (only one, ''Ocean's 11'') and beyond.</p>
        <p>Through it all, Sinatra maintained a certain stubborn integrity. If his taste in songs began to waver in the 1960's, his taste in movie roles more than wavered, it plummeted. But even if Sinatra walked through a role or riffed crudely on a pop song (''How's your bird, Mrs. Robinson?'' he once interpolated), he was always nothing more or less than himself.</p>
        <p>Through the Good or Lean Years</p>
        <p>''A Salute to Frank Sinatra,'' a film series sponsored by the Film Society of Lincoln Center, will run through Sept. 8 at the Walter Reade Theater, 165 West 65th Street. Each program consists of a double feature. Admission to each program: $8.50; $5 for Film Society members, and $4.50 for the elderly at weekday matinees. Information: (212) 875-5600. Here a schedule of screenings:</p>
        <p>Today  ''HIGH SOCIETY'' (1956), directed by Charles Walters, 2 and 6:30 P.M.  ''SOME CAME RUNNING'' (1958), directed by Vincente Minnelli, 4 and 8:35 P.M.</p>
        <p>Tomorrow  ''SOME CAME RUNNING,'' 4 and 8:35 P.M.  ''HIGH SOCIETY,'' 6:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>Sunday  ''SOME CAME RUNNING,'' 4 and 8:35 P.M.  ''HIGH SOCIETY,'' 6:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>Monday  ''FROM HERE TO ETERNITY'' (1953), directed by Fred Zinneman, 2 and 6:40 P.M.  ''THE JOKER IS WILD'' (1957), directed by Charles Vidor, 4:15 and 9 P.M.</p>
        <p>Tuesday  ''FROM HERE TO ETERNITY,'' 2 and 9 P.M.  ''THE JOKER IS WILD,'' 4:15 P.M.</p>
        <p>Wednesday  ''HIGHER AND HIGHER'' (1944), directed by Tim Whelan, 2, 5:30 and 9:15 P.M.  ''TAKE ME OUT TO THE BALL GAME'' (1949), directed by Busby Berkeley, 3:45 and 7:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>Thursday  ''TAKE ME OUT TO THE BALL GAME,'' 4 and 7:50 P.M.  ''IT HAPPENED IN BROOKLYN'' (1947), directed by Richard Whorf, 2 and 5:50 P.M.</p>
        <p>Aug. 28  ''PAL JOEY'' (1957), directed by George Sidney, 2 and 6:45 P.M.  ''ANCHORS AWEIGH'' (1945), directed by George Sidney, 4:10 and 9 P.M</p>
        <p>Aug. 29  ''PAL JOEY,'' 4 and 9 P.M.  ''ANCHORS AWEIGH,'' 6:15 P.M.</p>
        <p>Aug. 30  ''PAL JOEY,'' 4 and 9 P.M.  ''ANCHORS AWEIGH,'' 6:15 P.M.</p>
        <p>Aug. 31  ''ON THE TOWN'' (1949), directed by Gene Kelly and Stanley Donen, 2 and 6:15 P.M.  ''THE TENDER TRAP'' (1955), directed by Charles Walters, 4 and 8:10 P.M</p>
        <p>Sept. 2  ''THE MANCHURIAN CANDIDATE'' (1962), directed by John Frankenheimer, 2 and 6:35 P.M.  ''VON RYAN'S EXPRESS'' (1965), directed by Mark Robson, 4:20 and 9 P.M.</p>
        <p>Sept. 3  ''THE MANCHURIAN CANDIDATE,'' 2 and 6:35 P.M.  ''VON RYAN'S EXPRESS,'' 4:20 and 9 P.M.</p>
        <p>Sept. 4  ''YOUNG AT HEART'' (1954), directed by Gordon Douglas, with ''THE HOUSE I LIVE IN,'' 2 and 6:45 P.M.  ''THE MAN WITH THE GOLDEN ARM'' (1955), directed by Otto Preminger, 4:30 and 9:10 P.M.</p>
        <p>Sept. 5  ''THE MAN WITH THE GOLDEN ARM,'' 4:30 and 9:10 P.M.  ''YOUNG AT HEART,'' with ''THE HOUSE I LIVE IN,'' 6:45 P.M.</p>
        <p>Sept. 6  ''THE MAN WITH THE GOLDEN ARM,'' 4:30 and 9:10 P.M.  ''YOUNG AT HEART'' with ''THE HOUSE I LIVE IN,'' 6:45 P.M.</p>
        <p>Sept. 7  ''LADY IN CEMENT'' (1968), directed by Gordon M. Douglas, 2 and 6 P.M.  ''THE DETECTIVE'' (1968), directed by Gordon M. Douglas, 3:50 and 7:50 P.M.</p>
        <p>Sept. 8  ''COME BLOW YOUR HORN'' (1963), directed by Bud Yorkin, 2 and 6:30 P.M.  ''OCEAN'S 11'' (1968), directed by Lewis Milestone, 4:10 and 8:40 P.M.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
