<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giuliani Goes to the Top; Gets 40 Minutes in Meeting With Clinton</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="654648"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURDUM, TODD S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RANGEL, CHARLES B (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURDUM, TODD S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RANGEL, CHARLES B (REPR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DF1E3CF93BA35751C1A965958260" item-length="1019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giuliani Goes to the Top; Gets 40 Minutes in Meeting With Clinton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURDUM, TODD S</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 7</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Unlike Mayor David N. Dinkins, who had to spend nearly two years in office before George Bush let him sneak into the Oval Office on Thanksgiving eve with no witnesses, Mayor-elect Rudolph W. Giuliani sailed through the front door today for a 40-minute, bipartisian chat on gun control, welfare reform, Medicaid and politics with President Clinton, who was interested enough to ask for a second cup of coffee just when the New Yorkers thought the meeting was ready to break up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, who will be New York's first Republican Mayor since Mr. Clinton was in college -- came to make peace overtures to this Democratic President and this Democratic town, where he once cut a wide swath in the Reagan years, and to make common cause with Republican Congressional friends. He left with no promises, some White House M &amp; M's and a bit of a lecture on political politesse from Representative Charles B. Rangel of Harlem, who is not generally known for his own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Unlike Mayor David N. Dinkins, who had to spend nearly two years in office before George Bush let him sneak into the Oval Office on Thanksgiving eve with no witnesses, Mayor-elect Rudolph W. Giuliani sailed through the front door today for a 40-minute, bipartisian chat on gun control, welfare reform, Medicaid and politics with President Clinton, who was interested enough to ask for a second cup of coffee just when the New Yorkers thought the meeting was ready to break up.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani, who will be New York's first Republican Mayor since Mr. Clinton was in college -- came to make peace overtures to this Democratic President and this Democratic town, where he once cut a wide swath in the Reagan years, and to make common cause with Republican Congressional friends. He left with no promises, some White House M &amp; M's and a bit of a lecture on political politesse from Representative Charles B. Rangel of Harlem, who is not generally known for his own.</p>
        <p>"He has a great interest in New York City," Mr. Giuliani said of the President as he left the West Wing at midday. "New York to a large extent defines America to a lot of people all around the world. So we have a mutual interest in its success."</p>
        <p>It was that kind of conversation, said Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, New York's Democratic senior Senator, who escorted Mr. Giuliani like a benevolent uncle and helped lead a session that ranged from a discussion of Mr. Giuliani's interest in a Federal gun-registration law to the New York Congressional delegation's unwillingness to back Mr. Clinton's health-care proposals unless they relieve New York of the disproportionate share of Medicaid benefits it must now pay compared with other states. 'Exchanging Ideas'</p>
        <p>"They weren't negotiating," Mr. Moynihan said. "They were exchanging ideas."</p>
        <p>Even so, the President did not roll out the red carpet completely. The White House released an official photograph of the visit after Mr. Giuliani left, instead of inviting reporters and photographers into the Oval Office to record the scene. Asked why, the White House press secretary, Dee Dee Myers, said there was no particular reason.</p>
        <p>"He's the Mayor of one of the largest cities in the country," she said, correcting herself to say, "It is the largest city." She added: "There are a lot of problems I think the President wants to work with the Mayor of the city of New York to resolve, whoever the Mayor is."</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Giuliani said he pledged that New York would streamline its operations and be more efficient so as to deserve Federal help. He said that he and the President had discussed an article today in The New York Post that the Dinkins administration had forfeited $50 million in potential Federal housing funds because it failed to apply for them in a timely way and that Mr. Clinton promised to have his staff look into whether the money could be recouped.</p>
        <p>At their morning meeting, Mr. Rangel, ranking member of the House Ways and Means Committee, said he hoped that with his law-and-order reputation, Mr. Giuliani could press the President to focus not only on police and prisons but also on the underlying causes of crime and programs like drug treatment.  Note of Public Courtesy</p>
        <p>Mr. Rangel, one of Mayor Dinkins's best friends, often gave the Mayor free use of his Washington office and he struck a note of public courtesy with Mr. Giuliani today, saying: "It's not hospitality. It's professionals working together for the job that we have run to do and I cannot think of any political issue that could break this, even though I'll be looking for one."</p>
        <p>The elevator doors had no sooner closed on Mr. Giuliani, who rushed off to his next meeting, than Mr. Rangel found one. He chided Mr. Giuliani for chomping at the bit to get into City Hall and then complaining about Mr. Dinkins's decisions to press forward with municipal labor negotiations and a new contract for the United States Tennis Center in Queens and to start the time clock ticking on the developer Mortimer B. Zuckerman's proposal to build a skyscraper at Columbus Circle.</p>
        <p>"We've only got a precious few weeks before he's sworn in," Mr. Rangel told reporters. "If he can't hold back until then, then that's an impatience that lacks professionalism.</p>
        <p>"Hell, the law is clear, the charter is clear. Mayors-elect don't have the authority to do anything but make the transition as smooth as possible."</p>
        <p>The Mayor-elect inspired healthy curiosity from the blase inside-the-beltway locals, with his artificial suntan drawing special attention.</p>
        <p>"Is that guy wearing makeup?" asked Brit Hume, the ABC News correspondent, who knows a TV facial foundation when he sees it. And, indeed, as he usually does to lessen his pallor, Mr. Giuliani came prepared for the photo "opportunity" wearing foundation in the White House driveway. To Fulfill a Promise</p>
        <p>While the Mayor-elect was meeting with the President, Senator Moynihan and the President's adviser, David Gergen, Mr. Giuliani's wife, Donna; his campaign manager, Peter Powers, and Ninfa Segarra, his newly named deputy mayor for education, met with George Stephanopoulos, the senior Clinton adviser, who gave them some (undisclosed) advice on how to handle their first days in power -- and the press. Mrs. Giuliani took some official White House M &amp; M's to fulfill a promise to her cable-television colleagues at the Food Channel, who asked her to bring back "some food from the White House."</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani began his day with a brief courtesy call on Mayor Sharon Pratt Kelly of the District of Columbia and he also stopped in on Representative Robert H. Michel of Illinois, the House minority leader, and Dan Rostenkowski, chairman of the Ways and Means Committee.</p>
        <p>But the emotional highlight of the day was a harrowing 90-minute visit to the United State Holocaust Museum, where Mr. Giuliani looked soberly at a replica of bunks from Auschwitz and piles of shoes from victims of the gas chamber.</p>
        <p>"It's a shattering experience," he said. "It may be the most traumatic and important museum experience a person can ever have."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
