<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For a Less Restrained Era, a Restored 'Streetcar'</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="634920"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CENSORSHIP</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KAZAN, ELIA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAMS, TENNESSEE (1911-83)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">STREETCAR NAMED DESIRE, A (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Tennessee Williams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930916T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D9113EF935A2575AC0A965958260" item-length="763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For a Less Restrained Era, a Restored 'Streetcar'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</byline>
      <dateline>HOLLYWOOD, Sept. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>More than 40 years after the release of the classic film "A Streetcar Named Desire," the movie is being quietly rereleased with dialogue and sections that had been cut because of their sexual content.</p>
        <p>Four minutes of the 1951 film, which was directed by Elia Kazan and starred Vivien Leigh, Marlon Brando and Kim Hunter, has been restored. The full original version will be released for the first time, executives at Warner Brothers said, at the Nuart Theater in West Los Angeles on Oct. 1. The studio plans to release this version in New York and possibly other major cities if the revival succeeds in Los Angeles. The film is to be shown on Oct. 23 at the Hamptons International Film Festival in East Hampton, L.I.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>More than 40 years after the release of the classic film "A Streetcar Named Desire," the movie is being quietly rereleased with dialogue and sections that had been cut because of their sexual content.</p>
        <p>Four minutes of the 1951 film, which was directed by Elia Kazan and starred Vivien Leigh, Marlon Brando and Kim Hunter, has been restored. The full original version will be released for the first time, executives at Warner Brothers said, at the Nuart Theater in West Los Angeles on Oct. 1. The studio plans to release this version in New York and possibly other major cities if the revival succeeds in Los Angeles. The film is to be shown on Oct. 23 at the Hamptons International Film Festival in East Hampton, L.I.</p>
        <p>Adapted by Tennessee Williams from his Pulitzer Prize-winning play, the movie starred Leigh as Blanche DuBois, a tormented Southern belle struggling to endure; Mr. Brando as the brutal, childlike Stanley Kowalski, and Ms. Hunter as Stella, Stanley's sensual wife and Blanche's sister. "Streetcar" was named best picture of 1951 by the New York Film Critics, was nominated for 12 Academy Awards and received 4 Oscars, for best actress (Leigh), supporting actress (Ms. Hunter), supporting actor (Karl Malden) as well as its art direction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brando, whose performance left an indelible mark on generations of actors, lost out that year to Humphrey Bogart, who won for his performance in "The African Queen." Sharpened Tension</p>
        <p>Peter Gardiner, a vice president of Warner Brothers' film and video services, said the new version of "Streetcar" sharpens the sexual tension between Stanley and Blanche, and underscores Stella's hunger for Stanley, even after he abuses her. Moreover, Blanche's sexual history is made more vivid. And the harrowing finale, Stanley's rape of Blanche, is intensified.</p>
        <p>The restoration does not involve whole scenes, but adds dialogue, shots of the actors reacting to one another and even a portion of Alex North's score that the censors found too steamy in the context of one sexual scene.</p>
        <p>Although it was critically applauded in 1951, "A Streetcar Named Desire" had been heavily edited and toned down before its release, over the objections of Mr. Williams and Mr. Kazan. The editing was designed to meet the standards of the Motion Picture Production Code, which was created in 1929 to monitor the content of movies, in addition to the powerful Legion of Decency, a Roman Catholic Church group that rated films for parishioners.</p>
        <p>Before the film was edited, Joseph Breen, who oversaw the production code, called portions of the script "unacceptable" and filled with "perversity." The Legion of Decency called the movie "immoral," and objected heavily to the depiction of Stella's passion for her husband. Demand on Rape Scene</p>
        <p>Officials at the production-code offices at first demanded that the studio remove the crucial rape scene, according to a Warner Brothers statement just released in connection with the revised film. At that point, Mr. Kazan and Mr. Williams almost dissociated themselves from the picture.</p>
        <p>Mr. Williams wrote an impassioned letter to Mr. Breen. In it, he said: " 'Streetcar' is an extremely and peculiarly moral play, in the deepest and truest sense of the term. The rape of Blanche by Stanley is a pivotal, integral truth in the play, without which the play loses its meaning, which is the ravishment of the tender, the sensitive, the delicate, by the savage and brutal forces in modern society. It is a poetic plea for comprehension."</p>
        <p>A scaled-down rape scene was used in the 1951 version of the film. A 1988 Discovery</p>
        <p>Mr. Gardiner said that the unused clips were found during a routine inventory after Warner Brothers acquired Lorimar Telepictures in 1988. Although the movie was produced by Warner Brothers, the negative wound up at Lorimar after the film's release. "We discovered the fact that all this extra material came with the negative," said Mr. Gardiner. "We were thrilled."</p>
        <p>Editors re-inserting the material consulted several literary sources to reconstruct the movie as it had been intended. These included Mr. Kazan's autobiography, "A Life," which discussed the movie's omissions. Another book, "Inside Warner Bros." by Rudy Behlmer, reprinted many memos and letters about the production of the film.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kazan has not seen the revised version and was not involved directly in the restoration, Warners executives said. Floria Lasky, his longtime agent in New York, said that the director and writer was too busy to discuss the film.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
