<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Critic's Notebook; Cool Performance in a Heated Legal Melodrama</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="493143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SEX CRIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PALM BEACH (FLA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LASCH, MOIRA K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, WILLIAM KENNEDY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODMAN, WALTER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BOWMAN, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida/Palm Beach</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D81E3BF932A25751C1A967958260" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Critic's Notebook; Cool Performance in a Heated Legal Melodrama</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOODMAN, WALTER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For people watching on television, the first big difference between the testimony of William K. Smith and his accuser was that you could see his face.</p>
        <p>Boyish, open, it turned the memory of CNN's blob or Court Television's sci-fi masks into something almost sinister. No fault of the accuser, but however winning her features or persuasive her expressions, they were lost outside the courtroom.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For people watching on television, the first big difference between the testimony of William K. Smith and his accuser was that you could see his face.</p>
        <p>Boyish, open, it turned the memory of CNN's blob or Court Television's sci-fi masks into something almost sinister. No fault of the accuser, but however winning her features or persuasive her expressions, they were lost outside the courtroom.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith's description of who undid whose pants and removed whose panties qualified for an X rating, but the manner of the telling was not even PG. Wearing a sober blue blazer instead of his customary jacket of tiny brown check, he offered an account that could astound no one who had ever visited a singles bar or ever just enjoyed the scene on the tube. The astounding element was the prosecutor's response.</p>
        <p>Whatever coaching Mr. Smith may have received from his formidable defense team had taken. He looked straight at his questioner, paused earnestly to recall or reflect now and then, glanced frequently and deferentially at the jury and gave only a sign of exasperation as the prosecutor, Moira K. Lasch, pressed on with questions whose importance it was not always easy to fathom.</p>
        <p>There was nothing about Mr. Smith's appearance or demeanor, or his answers, to signal that this man was not telling the truth. No shifty look, no hunched shoulders, no display of antagonism. Only minor memory lapses. Again viewers could find a contrast to the gap-riddled testimony of his accuser. Greta Van Susteren, CNN's legal analyst, called Mr. Smith's time on the stand "a brilliant job."</p>
        <p>The contest between prosecutor and defendant, the climactic scene of so many courtroom dramas, took a peculiarly contemporary form. As the questioning went on, Mrs. Lasch seemed to be spinning out a primitive feminist parable. Whether it was a courtroom tactic or an admission of her own limited experience in such matters, she took the position that there was something inherently incredible about the notion of a young couple meeting at a bar and an hour or so later engaging in sex acts.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Mrs. Lasch had her legal problems. Before Mr. Smith took the stand, the television audience witnessed an encounter between the prosecutor and the judge that jurors did not. Judge Mary E. Lupo turned down the prosecution's arguments for admission of testimony by three other women who assert that they have been sexually assaulted by Mr. Smith. More, she chided Mrs. Lasch for trying to "appeal to the media" and warned her in strong terms against inviting a mistrial by impermissible questions.</p>
        <p>Thus constrained, Mrs. Lasch went this way and that like someone lost in unknown country. What about the accuser's bruises? What about this or that expert's testimony? What about Kennedy influence and power? What about the possibility that William Barry, a family friend, had misled the police? There seemed to be little purpose to the exercise but to cast some sort of generalized doubt on the defendant, in lieu of being able to shake the overall plausibility of his account. And he never seemed shaken.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith repeatedly one-upped Mrs. Lasch. After a long string of questions on exactly what time he had dinner and went to the nightspot Au Bar, Mr. Smith said with a glance at the jury: "I just didn't know what time it was." He was appealing to common sense. His glance said: Does anyone but an uptight prosecutor know the exact hour that she does every inconsequential thing on a vacation night out?</p>
        <p>He conceded his fault, granting readily that having intercourse without contraception was a "foolish and irresponsible thing to do." All right, he was telling the world, I'm no paragon, but that does not make me a rapist.</p>
        <p>In this duel Mr. Smith was hardly touched, but Mrs. Lasch managed to damage herself. Toward the end of the morning session she resorted to lines that might have seemed comical but clearly were not intended as such.</p>
        <p>Referring to the couple's decision to go from the bar to the Kennedy home at about 3 A.M., she asked: "You could have gone to a hotel, couldn't you?" Go to a hotel rather than a moonlit beach on a balmy night?</p>
        <p>When Mr. Smith said that he and his accuser had engaged in sex acts twice within a few minutes, Mrs. Lasch asked: "What are you, some kind of sex machine here?" Would a sexual prowess expert be brought on?</p>
        <p>To his testimony that the accuser had massaged his penis and helped him to enter her, Mrs. Lasch asked: "What are you saying, that she raped you, Mr. Smith?" As though in relations between men and women somebody has to rape somebody.</p>
        <p>And when he told of going for a swim after the act, she said, "It doesn't sound as though you were in the throes of passion, Mr. Smith." Can it be news to Mrs. Lasch that after a one-night stand, one or both partners are sometimes glad to get away? None of this is news to people who watch talk shows.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Mrs. Lasch knows something about the attitudes of her jurors toward casual sex that is not often reflected on the tube these days. But it must have seemed odd to even the least sophisticated television watcher to hear someone arguing the constricted proposition that there is passionate love and there is rape, and between men and women there is nothing else.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
