<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Free Trade at the Movies Puts U.S. in New Role</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="657849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL AGREEMENT ON TARIFFS AND TRADE (GATT)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL AGREEMENT ON TARIFFS AND TRADE (GATT)</org>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">GENERAL AGREEMENT ON TARIFFS AND TRADE (GATT)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DD1539F937A15751C1A965958260" item-length="398" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Free Trade at the Movies Puts U.S. in New Role</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In "High Noon at Uruguay Gulch" (Editorial Notebook, Dec. 13), Karl E. Meyer defends French foot-dragging on the demands in the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade concerning United States access to Europe's audiovisual market and France's insistence on a cultural exception. The question has, at any rate, now been deferred (front page, Dec. 15).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>In "High Noon at Uruguay Gulch" (Editorial Notebook, Dec. 13), Karl E. Meyer defends French foot-dragging on the demands in the General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade concerning United States access to Europe's audiovisual market and France's insistence on a cultural exception. The question has, at any rate, now been deferred (front page, Dec. 15).</p>
        <p>Mr. Meyer is right that France is "not alone in fearing for the survival of its national culture." Even the United States does not leave culture entirely to markets. At year end, the rich remember tax writeoffs for gifts to museums. The real question is: How do we best protect national culture? The answer appears to be: Subsidize your movies, but permit free access (without quotas) to ours.</p>
        <p>But the French-American dispute has other ironies that only economists will recognize. Jack Valenti, head of the motion picture association, and Mickey Kantor, the United States trade representative, have claimed that, since 57 percent of the movies shown in French theaters are American, the 11 percent surcharge levied on all movies (and spent on subsidizing French film production) must be shared with Hollywood.</p>
        <p>I suggest that this remarkable new principle of taxation be adopted symmetrically by the United States. Our toll receipts (often earmarked for our highway spending) should be shared with Japan pro rata to the number of Japanese cars that pay road and bridge tolls in this country.</p>
        <p>For those who have tracked and fought the Clinton Administration's shift to a tough, managed-trade, "results-oriented" trade policy toward Japan, based mainly on industry complaints that our shares in Japan's markets are low while Japan's shares in our markets are high, the irony is that the French are accusing us in the same way on movies.</p>
        <p>Since Hollywood takes 80 percent of the European market, while European films take only 2 percent of ours, France accuses us of invisible protectionism, of structural impediments, much like those of which our industries accuse Japan!</p>
        <p>Perhaps this role reversal might help to restore sanity to a Japan-fixated Administration that has allowed itself to become a handmaiden of Japan-bashers and special interests. JAGDISH BHAGWATI  New York, Dec. 15, 1993 The writer, professor of economics at Columbia University, was an adviser to the director general of GATT.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
