<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Texas Jail Wing Just for Christians</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="589631"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRISONS AND PRISONERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTIANS AND CHRISTIANITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FORTH WORTH (TEX)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TARRANT COUNTY (TEX)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED7143FF932A25751C0A965958260" item-length="1137" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Texas Jail Wing Just for Christians</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM HOWE VERHOVEK,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VERHOVEK, SAM HOWE</byline>
      <dateline>FORT WORTH, Feb. 6</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Inmates call it the God Pod.</p>
        <p>They're talking about a Christians-only wing at the county jail that features religious videos, hymn sings, Bible instruction and what one nonbelieving convict complained to his lawyer recently is "a cushier life style" than other inmates lead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Inmates call it the God Pod.</p>
        <p>They're talking about a Christians-only wing at the county jail that features religious videos, hymn sings, Bible instruction and what one nonbelieving convict complained to his lawyer recently is "a cushier life style" than other inmates lead.</p>
        <p>Tarrant County officials praise the unit, which they prefer to call the Christian Rehabilitation Pod or the Chaplain's Education Pod. They insist inmates have no greater privileges there than elsewhere in the jail, aside from being allowed to play a secondhand organ donated by a local church.</p>
        <p>But some former prisoners at the 13-story jail, which normally houses up to 4,400 inmates charged with crimes ranging from shop-lifting to murder, have protested. The protesters include a Jewish inmate who objected to the concept and a Methodist who contended he was removed from the 48-cell unit and transferred to a dingier wing after his brand of Christianity failed to mesh with the fundamentalist strain encouraged in the unit.</p>
        <p>Civil liberties groups have joined their side, and now the matter may be headed for the Texas courts.  One of a Kind?</p>
        <p>While many jails and prisons around the country encourage inmates to practice their faiths, the Christian pod here appears to be unique. Spokesmen for three national organizations of corrections officials, as well as the not-for-profit Prison Fellowship Ministries, said the Fort Worth jail was the only one they knew that reserved separate living quarters for Christians.</p>
        <p>Don Jackson, board president of the Fort Worth chapter of the American Civil Liberties Union, said he believed the unit was "a clear-cut violation" of the First Amendment guarantees of the separation of church and state. "You have a jail segregated by religion," he said. "It's exclusionary."</p>
        <p>But Van Thompson Jr., an assistant district attorney who handles civil rights matters, said that residence in the Christian cellblock was voluntary and that it simply accommodated inmates' right to free exercise of their religion. "I feel like we're doing some good," Mr. Thompson said. Asked about legal challenges to the unit, he said, "I sure hope it's constitutional."</p>
        <p>A certain amount of mystery surrounds the pod. Built on North Lamar Street near the downtown here, the beige-brick jail opened in 1990. It is divided into several dozen cellblocks, each one of about 50 cells surrounding a two-story recreation area. The Christian pod is one of these cellblocks. The exterior is a sort of neo-Art Deco with green trim around the narrow windows.</p>
        <p>Sheriff David Williams has refused requests from journalists to examine the cellblock. "It's nix-nix," said his spokeswoman, Lieut. Sue Maddock. "It's off limits."  Snapshot Is Provided</p>
        <p>The chief deputy jail administrator, Pat Howell, did provide a snapshot of one cellblock in the jail and said the Christian Rehabilitation Pod looked just like that.</p>
        <p>Even the lawyers objecting to the Christian cellblock have never seen it. "The Sheriff's office will not let anybody in," said Scott M. Kline, a Dallas lawyer representing the American Jewish Congress. "No one can go in and see it."</p>
        <p>Both inmates who filed legal complaints were, like most people in the jail, short-term prisoners who are no longer there. Jail officials declined to make public a list of inmates now in the Christian pod.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, in response to questions from reporters about the former prisoners' assertions, the sheriff's office released a statement saying it was "conducting a wide-based and intensive investigation into the alleged special jail unit, in order to establish the exact nature of complaints as to reported special privileges.</p>
        <p>"Investigation findings will be formalized in the form of a report which will be submitted through governmental and legal challenges to receive an opinion on the findings," the statement said. Until then, the statement concluded, no other action would be taken and the Christian unit would remain in operation.  Former Sheriff Defeated</p>
        <p>County officials said the Christian pod was the idea of the county's former Sheriff, Don Carpenter, a fundamentalist who was defeated for re-election last year after he was indicted on charges of giving away confiscated handguns to his friends rather than destroying them, as a judge had ordered. The case is still pending.</p>
        <p>But the cellblock has continued under Sheriff Williams, who is also active in local fundamentalist circles. One minute after his swearing-in at 12:01 A.M. Jan. 1, the Sheriff issued an order forbidding employees from talking to the news media without his approval.  Mr. Williams has since declined requests for an interview.</p>
        <p>Jail officials said they could not understand the interest in the cellblock. "It's really not a big thing," said the chief deputy jail administrator, Mr. Howell. "Nobody's being forced into it. It's voluntary."</p>
        <p>Asked if inmates in the unit enjoyed anything that could be construed as a special privilege or a practice giving them an easier time of it, he responded: "Yeah, they've got an organ. Big deal."  No Smokers Allowed</p>
        <p>Some officials at the jail insisted that inmates in the unit had to surrender certain privileges, like smoking.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson, the assistant district attorney, acknowledged that only Christians lived in the pod. But he said county officials would probably have no philosophical objection if someone proposed a separate pod for people of other religious beliefs, like Muslims or Jews.</p>
        <p>"Half the black guys in there are Muslims," he said. "Nobody's come forward to do it, though. Certainly there would be a good case for accommodating it." He also said he doubted there would ever be a need for a Jewish pod: "Quite frankly, we rarely see a Jewish inmate in our jail. They either get bailed out right away, or they just don't come in to begin with."</p>
        <p>Mr. Jackson and Mr. Kline, a lawyer with the Dallas firm of Carrington, Coleman, Sloman &amp; Blumenthal, said they had been negotiating separately with county officials for the last several months to close the unit. Mr. Jackson threatened to file a lawsuit because there had been no or little progress, but Mr. Kline said, "We're still optimistic that it can be resolved without litigation."</p>
        <p>Jail officials said they had no intention of closing the pod before the investigation, which is expected to take at least a few weeks. Because it is only a few months old, they said they had no way to measure whether it is a success.</p>
        <p>The chief deputy administrator, Mr. Howell, apologized for not showing a reporter the cellblock, explaining that he had been told to keep the public away while lawyers studied its constitutionality. "After we get a legal opinion on whether it's right or wrong, I'm very receptive to showing it," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
