<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Democrats Complain of Exclusion From Talks on Energy Bill</title>
    <meta content="Y12ENE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/09/12/politics/12ENER.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1518970"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulse, Carl</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Blackouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blackouts and Brownouts (Electrical)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Lobbying and Lobbyists</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Congress</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Democratic Party</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE6DB103BF931A2575AC0A9659C8B63" item-length="910" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Democrats Complain of Exclusion From Talks on Energy Bill</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Democrats Complain of Exclusion From Talks on Energy Bill</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARL HULSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulse, Carl</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Congressional Democrats say Republicans are excluding them from talks to write new national energy policy; Rep Henry A Waxman, Democratic member of conference committee that is supposed to reconcile House and Senate energy bills, says Democrats have not been consulted at all; Democrats and interest groups say that given significance of legislation, more work should be done in public view, and that process should not be solely Republican exercise; some Republicans say those calling for greater Democratic participation are actually intent on stalling measure (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>They had hoped in the wake of the biggest power failure in the nation's history to work as partners with Congressional Republicans to write a new national energy policy. Instead, Democrats say they are being relegated to spectators.</p>
        <p>''It is an optical illusion that Democrats are involved,'' said Bill Wicker, a spokesman for Democrats on the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Democrats say they are being relegated to spectators as Congress tries to complete its first major energy bill in a decade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>They had hoped in the wake of the biggest power failure in the nation's history to work as partners with Congressional Republicans to write a new national energy policy. Instead, Democrats say they are being relegated to spectators.</p>
        <p>''It is an optical illusion that Democrats are involved,'' said Bill Wicker, a spokesman for Democrats on the Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee.</p>
        <p>As Congress tries to complete its first major energy bill in a decade, Democratic lawmakers and others say they fear that the bill is being too tightly controlled by the Republican chairmen of the House and Senate energy panels, sidelining most members of the special 58-member conference considering the bill.</p>
        <p>''To this point, they have not sought involvement of Democrats at all,'' said Representative Henry A. Waxman, Democrat of California and a member of the conference committee that is supposed to reconcile the House and Senate energy bills. ''The Republicans are talking among themselves.''</p>
        <p>The dispute intensified today as Senator Pete V. Domenici of New Mexico, the Republican who is chairman of the conference, said he and Representative Billy Tauzin of Louisiana, the Republican who heads the House Energy and Commerce Committee, would hammer out preliminary agreements on various elements of the voluminous and contentious measure. They intend to begin releasing those agreements for review and comment on Monday.</p>
        <p>''Frankly, I don't know what to do short of just taking all day long every day for the next month with all kinds of squabbles and spending three or four days on a single item,'' said Mr. Domenici, who added that he would like to complete a measure by the end of the month.</p>
        <p>His approach drew objections from Senator Jeff Bingaman of New Mexico, the senior Democrat on the energy panel, who called it ''deeply flawed'' in a letter sent today to Mr. Domenici.</p>
        <p>''A process in which the duly appointed conferees for 49 senators get only to react to legislative text that has been negotiated without their input would not seem to constitute a real effort to find common ground on crucial and complex issues that are not inherently partisan,'' Mr. Bingaman wrote.</p>
        <p>Party exclusivity is not unheard of in conference committees, a crucial but often overlooked element of the legislative process. Much of the work typically goes on behind the scenes and did so when Democrats controlled the Congress as well.</p>
        <p>But Democrats and interest groups say that given the significance of the legislation, more work should be done in public view, and that the process should not be solely a Republican exercise.</p>
        <p>''There are some huge issues in this bill,'' said Joan Claybrook, the president of Public Citizen, which today sent a letter to lawmakers asking that meetings between two or more members of the energy conference be held in a public forum.</p>
        <p>The Republican leaders of the conference say they want to be as ''inclusive'' as possible in assembling the bill but not at the expense of the bill itself. Some Republicans say that those calling for greater Democratic participation are actually intent on stalling the measure.</p>
        <p>''What they are really saying is unless you do it their way, they don't want to play,'' Mr. Tauzin said. ''Well, I am tired of hearing harping by people who don't want to play.''</p>
        <p>Democrats in both the House and Senate say they understand that Republicans, with majorities in both chambers, can force through a measure if they choose. But they contend that action can lead to flawed policy.</p>
        <p>''Everybody understands that there is power to say, 'This is the way it is going to be,' '' said Senator Ron Wyden, Democrat of Oregon and a member of the conference committee who is trying to inject ideas about rising gasoline prices into the mix. ''But the evidence shows that is not a good way to make policy and build a consensus to carry it out.''</p>
        <p>Representative Nick J. Rahall II of West Virginia, the senior Democrat on the House Resources Committee and a conference member, put it more plainly: ''I think this does a disservice to the country if they try to jam it down our throats.''</p>
        <p>Republicans said the negotiations were following typical conference procedures, procedures with which Democrats were well acquainted.</p>
        <p>''Every conference I have been on, the bulk of the work gets done between the House and Senate staffs,'' said Representative Richard W. Pombo, the California Republican who heads the Resources Committee. ''That's how it always works.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Domenici and his aides said the route they intended to follow would be more open than the usual conference, giving lawmakers and the public a chance to review proposals well before they were presented for formal conference votes.</p>
        <p>But that did not satisfy Democrats. Some are planning to try to add their electricity initiatives to a separate energy spending measure to be considered by the Senate next week because they fear they might not get an opportunity to shape the broader energy policy.</p>
        <p>''There is some frustration,'' said Robert M. Simon, the top staff member for Democrats on the Senate energy panel, especially since major energy legislation is so seldom addressed. ''We are probably not likely to do one again for a very long time. Obviously, conferees and their staffs would like to have as much opportunity as you can to make a positive contribution.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
