<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Hit From the 70's Is Fading in the 90's; ABC's 'Good Morning America' Has Seen Better Days</title>
    <meta content="21SHOW$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1048248"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mifflin, Lawrie</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Good Morning America (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Today (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DE1330F932A1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="2209" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Hit From the 70's Is Fading in the 90's; ABC's 'Good Morning America' Has Seen Better Days</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRIE MIFFLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mifflin, Lawrie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>ABC-TV's Good Morning America, most-watched show in 7-to-9 AM weekday time slot from 1985 to 1995, has slipped substantially in the ratings, being overtaken by NBC's Today Show; in May 1998, Today had average of 5.26 million homes tuned in, while second-place Good Morning Ammerica slipped to 3.12 million; for fist half of year, Today earned about $117 million for NBC, while estimates show Good Morning America earned about $77 million for ABC; news division takeover is widely blamed for Good Morning America decline, but even die-hard devotees of old show admit changes are needed; graph; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In early-morning television, Katie and Matt don't need surnames. As co-hosts of the enormously popular ''Today'' show on NBC, Katie Couric and Matt Lauer are not only familiar companions in more than five million American homes each morning, they are also well known to movers and shakers from Washington to New York to Hollywood.</p>
        <p>But when it comes to ''Good Morning America'' on ABC, many people think of the co-hosts primarily as that smiling blond woman and that nice young man who wears glasses.</p>
        <p>True, Lisa McRee has been in the job for just one year, and Kevin Newman took over from Charles Gibson only this May. But their valiant, visibly difficult struggles to stay smiling and sharp-witted in the competitive arena of morning television are the surface signs of turbulence at a show in very deep trouble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In early-morning television, Katie and Matt don't need surnames. As co-hosts of the enormously popular ''Today'' show on NBC, Katie Couric and Matt Lauer are not only familiar companions in more than five million American homes each morning, they are also well known to movers and shakers from Washington to New York to Hollywood.</p>
        <p>But when it comes to ''Good Morning America'' on ABC, many people think of the co-hosts primarily as that smiling blond woman and that nice young man who wears glasses.</p>
        <p>True, Lisa McRee has been in the job for just one year, and Kevin Newman took over from Charles Gibson only this May. But their valiant, visibly difficult struggles to stay smiling and sharp-witted in the competitive arena of morning television are the surface signs of turbulence at a show in very deep trouble.</p>
        <p>For the better part of a decade, from 1985 to 1995, ''Good Morning America'' was the most-watched show in the 7-to-9-A.M. weekday slot. But in the last two years, it has seen its Nielsen ratings plummet, losing more than 25 percent of its viewers. In May 1996, the average number of households watching the show each day was 4.17 million, just a bit behind the ''Today'' show's 4.43 million. By May 1998, ''Today'' had an average of 5.26 million homes tuned in, while second-place ''Good Morning America'' had slipped to 3.12 million.</p>
        <p>That drop hurts the prestige of ABC, a subsidiary of the Walt Disney Company, but the financial pain is far worse. Not only are the breakfast shows the most profitable news programs on NBC and ABC, but those networks split the advertising time 50-50 with their owned and affiliated local stations -- for whom it is almost pure profit since they contribute little to the shows' costs.</p>
        <p>''Good Morning America'' had been run by ABC Entertainment since its debut in 1975. But because all the morning shows were becoming newsier and more sophisticated in keeping with changing American habits and tastes, and because the show's ratings had begun to stagnate, ABC in 1995 moved the program to the news division. Oddly, that is when the downturn began.</p>
        <p>And it has been costly. For the first half of this year, ''Today'' earned about $117 million for NBC, a unit of the General Electric Company, more than the other two morning shows combined, according to estimates reported by the networks themselves and by advertising agencies, and compiled by Nielsen. Those estimates show ''Good Morning America'' earned about $77 million.</p>
        <p>Five years ago, ''Today'' and ''Good Morning America'' were ''dead even'' in revenue, said a network executive with direct knowledge of the revenue picture, who spoke on condition of anonymity. ''CBS This Morning,'' usually a distant third but improving recently, earned about $35 million.</p>
        <p>The news division takeover is widely blamed for the ''Good Morning America'' decline, but even die-hard devotees of the old show admit changes were needed. Its audience was growing older, and ''Today'' was growing stronger and more competitive in snapping up the important first interview with the news maker of the day. But most of the changes backfired, either because they were too precipitous, were not well thought out, or were poorly communicated to the staff producing the show, according to interviews with two dozen people including some who work on the show now, some who have left it and executives at all three networks. Many, especially those still employed at ABC, insisted on anonymity.</p>
        <p>Since Phil Beuth, the president of ''Good Morning America'' under the entertainment division, and Jack Reilly, its executive producer for seven years, departed in early 1994, the program has had four executive producers in four years.</p>
        <p>At other levels, too, that has helped foster high turnover, especially among producers and bookers, who are the people who get guests to commit themselves to appear on the show.</p>
        <p>For viewers, the change is most visible in the co-anchors. Mr. Newman, a well-regarded reporter, and Ms. McRee, a former anchor of ABC's overnight news, of magazine shows and of local news at KABC in Los Angeles, may be competent, but they were almost unknown when they arrived.</p>
        <p>The tension seen on the set began when the news division took over in 1995, and even some news staffers acknowledge that change may have been too blunt and too fast, according to accounts from people on both sides. Many longtime staff members of the show use the same word -- ''disdain'' -- to describe the attitude they sensed from the news division.</p>
        <p>''There was a sense when news took over that anyone who worked there before that was an idiot,'' said Kevin Magee, a former senior producer who now works at CNBC, the cable business-news channel. ''It was very sad, very hurtful, especially when people were killing themselves with the work level they gave to that show.''</p>
        <p>Originally created to be an alternative to ''Today,'' deliberately less newsy and more folksy, ''Good Morning America'' grew popular with little help from the news division. It built its own news gathering team and its own slate of experts, like doctors, lawyers and consumer advocates. ''We had to find Tim Johnson, Geraldo Rivera, Joel Siegel,'' said Bob Reichblum, the executive producer through all of 1995 and now the vice president for prime time at CNBC, ''but that became the signature of the show, its own family of contributors. That concept started with 'G.M.A.' out of necessity, because the show had no support from ABC News.''</p>
        <p>The ''Today'' show even copied that ''family'' concept in the early 1990's, trying to mend its own rifts of 1989 and 1990 after Jane Pauley quit, Bryant Gumbel criticized colleagues in a memo leaked to the press and Deborah Norville proved a disastrous replacement for Ms. Pauley.</p>
        <p>In 1994, ''Today'' got viewers' attention by moving to a new studio on Rockefeller Center's plaza, where a live audience could participate, and by 1995, ''Today'' had pulled even in the Nielsen ratings.</p>
        <p>That is when ABC News took over, with a history of scant mutual respect between the news division and the program. By contrast, ''Today'' had the advantage of having always been an integral part of NBC News, going back to its debut on Jan. 14, 1952, with Dave Garroway as host.</p>
        <p>Many longtime ''Good Morning America'' producers and correspondents were pushed aside, and the number and quality of their assignments diminished. With producers' roles frequently changing, and the program's top executives tending to rule by committee, according to most accounts, the show began to appear chaotic on the air, too.</p>
        <p>Rumors circulated that Joan Lunden and Mr. Gibson would be replaced, yet the ABC News executives never chose regular substitute anchors to groom them to fit comfortably into the morning's mix, as ''Today'' had done with Ms. Couric and Mr. Lauer. (Mr. Lauer co-anchored almost one-third of the ''Today'' shows in the year before he took over permanently from Mr. Gumbel, according to NBC News.)</p>
        <p>In an effort to attract younger viewers, young contributors were hired, often not staying long. Cindy Adams, a brassy New York Post gossip columnist, was added. Many loyal viewers of the show began to feel they scarcely recognized it.</p>
        <p>When Elizabeth Vargas replaced Morton Dean as the show's news reader, in May 1996, audience research showed that many viewers were upset, said one ABC executive, who insisted on anonymity. It was yet another goodbye to a familiar face, and Ms. Vargas was perceived as openly seeking to replace Joan Lunden as the show's co-anchor.</p>
        <p>Executives did not stick with her either, however; she left a year later to become a correspondent for the news magazines ''20/20'' and ''Prime Time Live.''</p>
        <p>''The people I reported to had no vision whatsoever,'' Mr. Reichblum said. ''It's one thing to say, 'You're stale, you have dead wood, you're not coming up with new ideas.' Nothing's wrong with that, if you have a plan for how to fix things.</p>
        <p>''No one at 'G.M.A.' was opposed to change,'' he said. ''They recognized that, like any television show, it needed to evolve. But it did not need a revolution.''</p>
        <p>Some of those responsible for making the changes say complaints about ''revolution'' are naive. They say the ''family'' so cherished by longtime ''Good Morning America'' staff members blocked the integration of new talent into that clan, and did little to recruit a new generation of viewers. And the ''Today'' ratings were getting stronger, especially in the 18-to-49-year-old age group that advertisers covet.</p>
        <p>But even these people acknowledge there may have been too much change, too fast. ''It has lurched back and forth,'' one said. ''For six months this year it tended toward fluffier, lighter segments, more spontaneity, and then for the last two, three months it has been trying to get newsy again.''</p>
        <p>Indecision like that causes bookers to be less certain about what sort of guests to pursue, and if they wait to get approval from a high-level producer, the guest will often already be booked by ''Today.'' Or, a booker will snare a guest, only to have to call back and undo the commitment.</p>
        <p>Indecision can also give the anchors less time to prepare for interview segments, or make them appear uncomfortable and jittery shifting between segments.</p>
        <p>A nadir mentioned with chagrin by a number of people connected with the show was the coverage of the crash of T.W.A. flight 800 into the sea off Long Island in 1996. ''Good Morning America'' executives decided not to risk sending Mr. Gibson to the scene because technical problems made it questionable as to whether he could get on the air. NBC flew Mr. Gumbel back from the Atlanta Olympics to anchor the coverage from the beach.</p>
        <p>That will not happen again, said Shelley Lewis, the show's current executive producer.</p>
        <p>''Our mantra now is substance,'' she said. ''We're trying to be the most substantive news and information program on television. The show just has to get a lot better, and then the ratings will follow.''</p>
        <p>But the climb back toward No. 1 is much steeper now than it has ever been for either show, and there is more competition in the morning than ever -- from local morning shows, like Fox's ''Good Day New York,'' to cable networks, like ESPN for the sports fan or CNBC for the business person.</p>
        <p>''When I took over 'Today,' they told me I had two years to fix that show,'' said Steve Friedman, a former executive producer of ''Today'' who is now vice president and station manager of WCBS/Channel 2 in New York. ''I did it a lot differently knowing I had two years than if I'd had to worry about every week, every month, every quarter.''</p>
        <p>How long does he think it will take to revitalize ''Good Morning America''?</p>
        <p>''At least two years,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Lewis said bravely, ''Nobody has given me a deadline or a time frame.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
