<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Industry View; The stock market's gyrations are causing anxiety among Silicon Alley start-ups that are planning to go public.</title>
    <meta content="21TECH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1048239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stites, Janet</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Startup</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E1DF1330F932A1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Industry View; The stock market's gyrations are causing anxiety among Silicon Alley start-ups that are planning to go public.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Janet Stites</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stites, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stock market's gyrations are causing problems among Silicon Valley start-up companies that are planning to go public; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN contrast to politics, in the world of entrepreneurs, going public has fabulously positive connotations. Many founders of start-ups set their sights on taking their companies public before even filing their incorporation papers.</p>
        <p>Going public is how their investors make back their money -- and, hopefully, then some. It is how entrepreneurs achieve real wealth, if only on paper. It is how they will be judged for years to come. It is the consummate measure of business success or failure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN contrast to politics, in the world of entrepreneurs, going public has fabulously positive connotations. Many founders of start-ups set their sights on taking their companies public before even filing their incorporation papers.</p>
        <p>Going public is how their investors make back their money -- and, hopefully, then some. It is how entrepreneurs achieve real wealth, if only on paper. It is how they will be judged for years to come. It is the consummate measure of business success or failure.</p>
        <p>So consider the anxiety of Silicon Alley entrepreneurs like Jack Hidary, Todd Krizelman, Stephan Paternot and Alan Andreini. All four run high-profile Internet companies that filed papers in the summer with the Securities and Exchange Commission to go public. All have, to this point, capitalized on the innovation and excitement of the Internet and helped to define the amorphous New York new-media industry that has come to be known as Silicon Alley.</p>
        <p>But as the stock market continues to vacillate, all these men face a quandary: to go or not to go. They have arrived at the dance only to find that the band is taking a break.</p>
        <p>In all, six new-media companies in the New York area have filed for public offerings, including Mr. Hidary's Earthweb, Mr.  Krizelman's and Mr. Paternot's theglobe.com and Mr. Andreini's Interworld, plus two New York companies, Multex and Net Grocer, and All-Tech Investment Group of Montvale, N.J.</p>
        <p>Under the S.E.C.'s quiet-period rules, the executives of those companies are prohibited from discussing their situations, but speculation in the Alley has been rampant.</p>
        <p>''Those that are in registration now will wait if they can do so,'' predicted John Siracuse, vice president and head of East Coast Internet banking for Nationsbanc Montgomery Securities. ''They don't want to be the first to test the market.''</p>
        <p>Further complicating the go/no-go question, Mr. Siracuse observes, is that the window of opportunity is diminishing as the holiday season approaches.</p>
        <p>''It's difficult for small-cap companies to get the investors' attention between Thanksgiving and Christmas,'' he said. If companies wait until the new year to go public, he continued, they will have logistical issues, like having to update their prospectuses, but more important, they will have to wrangle with the perception that they were not ready to go public.</p>
        <p>''Perception is reality,'' he said. ''And there will be the perception they couldn't get the deal done.''</p>
        <p>Jonathan Cohen, head of Internet research at Merrill Lynch, believes many companies will turn to mergers and acquisitions. He notes that mergers and acquisitions have been increasing in the last 6 to 12 months anyway.</p>
        <p>And while there have been virtually no technology offerings in the last few weeks, Mr. Cohen said, ''The landscape for Internet I.P.O.'s has shifted, but the window is still open for high-quality companies with compelling business models -- models such as community and E-commerce.''</p>
        <p>''Investors want to see properties with components of high functionality and high intellectual property,'' he said, saying that theglobe.com is an example of a community site where users create a wealth of intellectual property.</p>
        <p>Venture capitalists see the recent correction in technology stocks as a much-needed dose of reality.</p>
        <p>Tom Hirschfeld, a principal at Patricof &amp; Company Ventures Inc., which has interests in Alley-based Medscape Inc. and New Jersey-based Audible Inc., says that the current market has not diminished his firm's interest in the Internet and new-media start-ups. But, he added, ''It does have an impact on price negotiations.''</p>
        <p>The drop in the market, Mr. Hirschfeld says, brings a sense of sanity to private market valuation.</p>
        <p>But it also leaves pre-public Silicon Alley companies in a precarious position. If they are hard-pressed for cash, they may have to turn to their original investors or go for a private placement. They may have to pull their public offerings altogether.</p>
        <p>Mr. Siracuse adds that delayed public offerings can cause another problem. ''Employees who have other opportunities may decide to leave the company,'' he said.</p>
        <p>A big issue for Silicon Alley is the fact that it is still being judged by the number of successful public offerings. Each one is tallied as younger companies continue to try to lure venture capital from the West Coast, and to garner the respect of Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Mr. Siracuse agrees with Mr. Cohen that while the outlook may not be peaches and cream, neither is it liver and onions. ''There is still an appetite for Internet stocks,'' he said. ''What the market needs is a high-profile Internet stock to go out and do well.''</p>
        <p>The stock needs to sell out at its offering, Mr. Siracuse said, and then continue to sell well in the after market.</p>
        <p>As for those companies that had already gone public, many star-struck entrepreneurs and their option-holding employees found out what their investors already knew: what goes up must come down. Double Click Inc., an Internet advertising network and an Alley favorite, watched its stock drop from more than $50 a share in July to $23 last week. It closed Friday at $19.69.</p>
        <p>Double Click's chief competitor, 24/7 Media Inc., went public in mid-August, opening at $18.50 and closing at $20.25. Last week, its stock was selling below $12. It closed Friday at $11.56.</p>
        <p>Among other Alley stocks that saw their share prices drop into single digits were N2K Inc., the owner of Music Boulevard, and Cyber Shop Inc., an on-line mall.</p>
        <p>Even so, Mr. Cohen, who has been following Silicon Alley companies for the last three years, first as an analyst at Salomon Smith Barney, then at the Union Bank of Switzerland, remains optimistic.</p>
        <p>''Silicon Alley has come to be populated with good companies and intelligent people and will continue to be a source of investment ideas going forward,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Music to the ears of New York's high-technology entrepreneurs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
