<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tiny Objects, Grandiose Statements</title>
    <meta content="24SMIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="967375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedman, Tom (Sculptor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Roberta</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971024T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07E7D7133EF937A15753C1A961958260" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tiny Objects, Grandiose Statements</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERTA SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Roberta</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roberta Smith reviews sculptures by Tom Friedman, at Feature Gallery; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Friedman, sculptor extraordinaire, continues to endanger his eyesight by making objects of mind-boggling refinement and tininess. His fourth exhibition at the Feature gallery in SoHo contains a dozen sculptures and three works on paper -- the most pieces this 32-year-old artist, who lives in Conway, Mass., has exhibited at one time. It represents several years of his eccentrically herculean labors, often expended on the most ephemeral of materials.</p>
        <p>These include a gnarled, translucent strand that hangs from ceiling to floor in the first room of the show. In actuality, it is a very, very long piece of nylon monofilament, which the artist laboriously knotted thousands of times until it resembled a string of tiny glass beads. Like many of Mr. Friedman's efforts, it takes the relaxed modesty of 70's Process Art to Faberge heights of obsession.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Friedman, sculptor extraordinaire, continues to endanger his eyesight by making objects of mind-boggling refinement and tininess. His fourth exhibition at the Feature gallery in SoHo contains a dozen sculptures and three works on paper -- the most pieces this 32-year-old artist, who lives in Conway, Mass., has exhibited at one time. It represents several years of his eccentrically herculean labors, often expended on the most ephemeral of materials.</p>
        <p>These include a gnarled, translucent strand that hangs from ceiling to floor in the first room of the show. In actuality, it is a very, very long piece of nylon monofilament, which the artist laboriously knotted thousands of times until it resembled a string of tiny glass beads. Like many of Mr. Friedman's efforts, it takes the relaxed modesty of 70's Process Art to Faberge heights of obsession.</p>
        <p>At once whimsical and uncannily devotional, Mr. Friedman's work continually circles art's first principles, poking at them, exalting them, isolating them, drawing them out in the open for better viewing. The main principle, of course, is that art usually involves the transformation of inert, everyday materials into something that can feed the spirit, if you pay enough attention to it. To insure our attention, Mr. Friedman  flirts with different kinds of invisibility, executing enticing disappearing acts that pull us into his game.</p>
        <p>Mr. Friedman's materials are resoundingly mundane, including typing paper, plastic straws and Play-Doh. And his transformational processes, as it were, can be as low-tech as his materials: the knotting, for example. Or they can be masterly, as in the trompe l'oeil sculptures of a daddy longlegs spider and a dragonfly, which are hard to distinguish from the real thing. Or his techniques can be nonexistent. One work in this show consists of a large blank piece of paper that the artist has purposefully stared at during the last five years. It is, according to its title, the repository of ''1,000 Hours of Staring.''</p>
        <p>This can seem, at first, like a Conceptual Art hoax, but it could be said to honor, in glorious isolation, the intense visual scrutiny that all successful artists expend on their work, the long hours of looking, looking, looking in order to figure out how to make it better. And the stared-at paper is not all that different from the dragonfly, which is so perfect that the hours spent making it are all but invisible.</p>
        <p>Another piece defines a middle ground between the extremes of the insect replicas and the stared-at paper. It is a construction made entirely of little bits of household trash -- bottle caps, paper clips, you name it -- that has been sprayed white and carefully suspended from the ceiling. It looks like the world's most complicated model spacecraft, but in fact it is merely an imitation, an approximation of precise replication.</p>
        <p>One of Mr. Friedman's main themes is the accumulation of tiny, hard-to-see gestures into something that is surprisingly grandiose, especially when viewed up close. For example, approach the large drawing that from across the room looks like a chaotic firestorm of fine, randomly crisscrossing lines. Suddenly, you see that each line is in fact an arrow pointing at a tiny dot without touching it. The drawing is covered with thousands of these pinging points of light. It is as if some dedicated stargazer had decided that the usual constellations -- the Big Dipper, the Great Bear and so on -- were too simple, and set out to plot all the stars in the Milky Way instead.</p>
        <p>Similarly intergalactic is an environmental piece that covers the gallery's entire north wall, evoking a white-on-white version of deep space with nothing more substantial than hundreds of tiny, widely spaced balls of Styrofoam stuck in paint.</p>
        <p>Other pieces blend Mr. Friedman's trompe l'oeil and Process Art tendencies. Working in Play-Doh, he recreates every pill in ''The Physician's Desk Reference,'' scattering them about in a kind of medicinal color spectrum. Similarly encyclopedic, and also in Play-Doh, is a work subtitled ''Small World.'' In the somewhat naive manner of a small child, it recreates 500 things, among them a ladder, a clipboard, a space missile and a 12-inch stick. But as each item is about a half-inch high, the piece is a tour de force display of patience, focus and skill, like everything else in this terrific show.</p>
        <p>Tom Friedman's work is on view at Feature Inc., 76 Greene Street, near Spring Street, SoHo, through Nov. 14.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
