<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Shiite Leader Criticizes Plan for Stronger U.S. Role in Iraq's Security</title>
    <meta content="29iraq" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/29/world/middleeast/29iraq.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1779132"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Semple, Kirk</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hakim, Abdul Aziz Al-</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Hakim, Abdul Aziz al-</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E5D6123FF93AA15754C0A9609C8B63" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Shiite Leader Criticizes Plan for Stronger U.S. Role in Iraq's Security</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shiite Leader Criticizes Plan for Stronger U.S. Role in Iraq’s Security</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK SEMPLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Semple, Kirk</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, July 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Abdul Aziz al-Hakim, leader of largest Shiite bloc in Iraqi Parliament, criticizes current security strategy; says that Iraq's forces, rather than those of US, should be in charge of stabilizing country; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of Iraq's most powerful Shiite leaders criticized the current security strategy on Friday and said that Iraq's forces, rather than those of the United States, should be in charge of stabilizing the country.</p>
        <p>During a rally in the southern Shiite holy city of Najaf, Abdul Aziz al-Hakim, leader of the largest Shiite bloc, said that the worsening security situation was caused by ''carelessness'' and ''wrong policies.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Abdul Aziz al-Hakeem, leader of the largest Shiite bloc, called for handing over security to Iraqi forces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of Iraq's most powerful Shiite leaders criticized the current security strategy on Friday and said that Iraq's forces, rather than those of the United States, should be in charge of stabilizing the country.</p>
        <p>During a rally in the southern Shiite holy city of Najaf, Abdul Aziz al-Hakim, leader of the largest Shiite bloc, said that the worsening security situation was caused by ''carelessness'' and ''wrong policies.''</p>
        <p>He called for ''handing over the security dossier to the Iraqi apparatus and stopping the interference in its work.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hakim, who leads the Supreme Council for the Islamic Revolution in Iraq, has said that Iraqi forces should have more responsibility for the country's security. But his criticisms on Friday were particularly acute because they came only three days after President Bush and Prime Minister Nuri Kamal al-Maliki announced an agreement to significantly strengthen the American military presence in the capital.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hakim's remarks also seemed intended to put pressure on Mr. Maliki, a fellow Shiite but a fierce political rival.</p>
        <p>American and Iraqi leaders have struggled to break the cycle of sectarian bloodshed that has steadily worsened in recent months, particularly in Baghdad. Mr. Bush's announcement on Tuesday was a tacit acknowledgment that a new security strategy for Baghdad, initiated by Mr. Maliki last month, had failed.</p>
        <p>American officials have tried to shift much of Baghdad's policing to Iraqi forces. But while publicly praising the maturation of the Iraqi military and police, American officials have privately acknowledged that progress has been much slower than anticipated.</p>
        <p>Much of the recent violence has been driven by sectarian death squads, some operating within Shiite-controlled security forces and Shiite militias tied to political parties. Mr. Maliki has pledged to disband the militias and clean the ranks of the police and the military of militia influence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hakim has said in the past that he wanted established militias, including his own Iranian-trained Badr Organization, to have more authority in securing the country. But on Friday he appeared to back away from that stance, saying he supported Mr. Maliki's vow to disband them.</p>
        <p>The American military command, seemingly eager to demonstrate success in its fight against insurgents, issued an unusually long statement on Friday describing what it called a ''daylong battle'' last Sunday in a town south of Baghdad. The statement said American and Iraqi forces killed 33 ''terrorists'' in the firefight.</p>
        <p>According to the statement, the clash began when gunmen attacked an Iraqi police post in Musayyib and seized police vehicles and weapons. American troops responded and came under fire from around a small mosque, including by rocket-propelled grenades fired from inside the mosque, the statement said.</p>
        <p>An American AH-64 Apache helicopter blew up a fuel truck that American officers believed was carrying explosives, the statement said, and an Abrams tank destroyed a building being used as a bunker by at least six gunmen. American and Iraqi troops traded small-arms fire with the insurgents for several hours, the military reported.</p>
        <p>Lt. Col. Patrick Donahoe, commander of the First Battalion, 67th Armor, described the insurgent attack as ''coordinated, sustained and complex.''</p>
        <p>In scattered violence on Friday, a mortar shell exploded near a Sunni Arab mosque on the southern outskirts of Baghdad, killing at least four people and wounding six, government officials said. The attack occurred despite a four-hour driving ban intended to curb violence in the city. Mortar crews often use vehicles for easy escape.</p>
        <p>The attack was among several that concentrated on civilians and security forces, though violence appeared to be sharply lower than on most other days this month.</p>
        <p>Four marines were killed in Anbar Province on Thursday in two separate attacks, according to the American military command. One of the marines was assigned to Regimental Combat Team 5, and the other three were with the First Brigade, First Armored Division.</p>
        <p>The bodies of three Sunni Arab men who disappeared several days ago were found in a boat on Friday, each with a bullet in the head, according to a police official in Baquba, north of Baghdad.</p>
        <p>The bodies of five men kidnapped Thursday in Baquba were found Friday on a farm in that city, according to the police official, who requested anonymity because he was not authorized to speak for attribution.</p>
        <p>The United Nations and the Iraqi government formally began a campaign on Friday to attract more countries and international organizations to help rebuild Iraq.</p>
        <p>The campaign, the International Compact With Iraq, aims to draw a coalition of countries to help develop economic, political and security reforms that will, in five years, establish Iraq as a ''united, federal and democratic country'' that is ''well on its way to sustainable economic self-sufficiency and prosperity,'' according to a statement issued by the Iraqi government and the United Nations.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
