<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Yeltsin's Ban on Communists Upheld</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="573740"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COMMONWEALTH OF INDEPENDENT STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">RUSSIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">YELTSIN, BORIS N (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD9163CF932A35751C1A964958260" item-length="1080" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Yeltsin's Ban on Communists Upheld</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SCHMEMANN, SERGE</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Nov. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After five months of intense and sometimes emotional testimony, Russia's highest court today upheld President Boris N. Yeltsin's ban on the Communist Party but sidestepped any broad condemnation of the still potent legacy of Soviet Communism.</p>
        <p>The 13-member Constitutional Court found that Mr. Yeltsin's decrees banning the Soviet and Russian Communist parties after the aborted putsch of August 1991 were basically sound. But it ruled that the issue of property was for civil courts to decide, and that low-level party units were legitimate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After five months of intense and sometimes emotional testimony, Russia's highest court today upheld President Boris N. Yeltsin's ban on the Communist Party but sidestepped any broad condemnation of the still potent legacy of Soviet Communism.</p>
        <p>The 13-member Constitutional Court found that Mr. Yeltsin's decrees banning the Soviet and Russian Communist parties after the aborted putsch of August 1991 were basically sound. But it ruled that the issue of property was for civil courts to decide, and that low-level party units were legitimate.</p>
        <p>The narrow legal decision was a far cry from the sweeping ban that Mr. Yeltsin's supporters had sought in what they saw as the "trial of Communism" or the "Russian Nuremberg." It was also far from the vindication of the party's tarnished ideals and history sought by the Communists. Who Really Won?</p>
        <p>In the end, the court chose a judicial compromise that did not fully satisfy either side, but left both grumpily claiming victory.</p>
        <p>It also declared that since the Soviet party was essentially defunct by the time of the decrees, and the Russian party not yet legally registered, there was no need to rule on the separate issue of whether the party was constitutional with or without Mr. Yeltsin's ban.</p>
        <p>Contributing to the dryness of the decision was the fact that the court announced its it with no explanation. The chief justice, Valery D. Zorkin, said the full opinion would be issued in two weeks.</p>
        <p>But already it was evident that the muted decision would not have a major immediate impact on the political upheavals of the state. Eight Heirs to Party Legacy</p>
        <p>Mr. Yeltsin never banned Communism, only the official Communist Party, and in the 15 months since the coup and the suspension of the party, die-hard Communists have already formed at least eight new parties, none with anywhere near the clout of old.</p>
        <p>Lawyers acknowledged that the ruling on property could prompt a welter of legal claims. But they noted that since no one could legally claim to be a successor to a banned party, it was unlikely any of the countless properties seized from the party, ranging from the vast headquarters in Moscow to innumerable resorts and rest homes, would ever be given back.</p>
        <p>The decision came on the eve of what is expected to be a tempestuous session of Parliament, and all sides had been anxious that an unfavorable ruling could bolster the other. But in the absence of a strong verdict, the decision seemed to give no one much solace.</p>
        <p>That may well have been what the court sought. Formed only six weeks before the coup attempt, the Constitutional Court was intended to give the new democracy something Russia had never had -- an independent judiciary. Throughout the proceeding, Justice Zorkin struggled to enforce the unfamiliar concept, curtailing the constant political and ideological harangues. Independence of Court</p>
        <p>At a news conference, Mr. Zorkin admitted that the court was still far from a true "third power" to the executive and legislative, and not yet truly independent of the forces raging in the country.</p>
        <p>But the decision today, he insisted, was not a political compromise. "There is, if you understand me correctly, a constitutional compromise," he said, adding: "In my view, we must live within the framework of the law. There is a legal platform, and on either side is dictatorship or anarchy."</p>
        <p>The hearing was actually a merger of two petitions. The first was filed by Communists seeking to overrule Mr. Yeltsin's ban on the party. The President's supporters countered with a suit seeking to declare the Communist party unconstitutional and criminal. Rebuilding From Below</p>
        <p>After the ruling, Communists declared that they would start rebuilding the Russian party from the newly legal primary cells. Mr. Yeltsin's supporters said they were satisfied that the party had in fact been declared unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>"The court displayed a very interesting methodology," said Sergei Baburin, one of the most vocal pro-Communist members of Parliament and himself a legal expert. "It's as if a doctor is asked whether a patient is dead or alive. 'The right hand is warm,' the doctor says, 'the left is cold, the heart is ripped out but seems to be beating, the kidneys are gone -- but you decide yourself if he's dead.' "</p>
        <p>Mikhail A. Fedotov, a lawyer on Mr. Yeltsin's side, declared it a "half-decision" that could pose problems for the Government. But he also acknowledged that it was probably the only position the court could take.  'Concrete Composition' of Court</p>
        <p>"I am satisfied with it, given the concrete political situation and the concrete composition of the court," he said. "After decades of regimentation, it's very difficult, psychologically difficult, for them to declare the party unconstitutional. They understand it's unconstitutional, but they're not able to pronounce it."</p>
        <p>Mr. Fedotov was alluding on one level to the fact that all but one of the justices -- just as most of the lawyers, and for that matter Mr. Yeltsin and virtually all his administration -- had been Communists. Not many were prepared to declare that everything they once believed in and worked for was utterly wrong.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Fedotov's thought also applied more broadly to the entire process, which began last May 26. By sheer volume, it was a monumental case -- 52 sessions were held, 46 witnesses were called, 16 experts were heard and a mountain of documents, many culled from the most secret files of the Communist party, were submitted.</p>
        <p>The witnesses included some of the most powerful men of the former regime -- Nikolai I. Ryzhkov, Vladimir I. Dolgikh, Yegor K. Ligachev. But the most prominent of all, Mikhail S. Gorbachev, raised the one notable controversy when he refused to participate in what he dubbed a political show. The last Soviet president was briefly barred from going abroad, but in the end the court canceled its summons.</p>
        <p>Yet the process never captured any public interest. On most days the courtroom was all but empty, and none of the commentaries in the press ever treated it as the great trial of Communism that Mr. Yeltsin's side wanted.</p>
        <p>To underscore its new role as a disinterested referee, the court moved immediately after upholding Mr. Yeltsin's ban of the Communist Party to a hearing on his recent ban of the National Salvation Front, a newly formed coalition of Communists and nationalists. The court is widely expected to overturn this ban.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
