<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ABC Bets That (Hollywood) Ugly Is the New Pretty</title>
    <meta content="10heff" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="98" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/10/arts/television/10heff.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1788715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THE NEW SEASON -- TELEVISION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heffernan, Virginia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ferrera, America</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Ugly Betty (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Betty La Fea (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">ABC Inc</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ferrera, America</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060910T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EEDF1F3EF933A2575AC0A9609C8B63" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ABC Bets That (Hollywood) Ugly Is the New Pretty</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">ABC Bets on ‘Ugly Betty’</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VIRGINIA HEFFERNAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Heffernan, Virginia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Virginia Heffernan article describes new ABC show Ugly Betty, based on Colombian telenovela Betty la Fea; features Honduran-American actress America Ferrera as unattractive woman working for fashion magazine; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HOPING to claim a piece of the telenovela phenomenon, ABC may have inadvertently tapped into an even bigger trend this fall: ugliness.</p>
        <p>Not real ugliness of course. Hollywood ugliness. But Hollywood's standards of ugliness, like Hollywood's standards of beauty, change. Remember Eliza Doolittle, with her ratty hair, tar-colored dress, smudged cheeks? Messy stood in for ugly in those days.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hoping to claim a piece of the telenovela phenomenon, ABC may have inadvertently tapped into an even bigger trend this fall: ugliness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HOPING to claim a piece of the telenovela phenomenon, ABC may have inadvertently tapped into an even bigger trend this fall: ugliness.</p>
        <p>Not real ugliness of course. Hollywood ugliness. But Hollywood's standards of ugliness, like Hollywood's standards of beauty, change. Remember Eliza Doolittle, with her ratty hair, tar-colored dress, smudged cheeks? Messy stood in for ugly in those days.</p>
        <p>More recently movie actresses who have played women we're told are ugly -- Toni Collette (''Muriel's Wedding''), Minnie Driver (''Circle of Friends''), Lili Taylor (''Dogfight'') -- have gone on to play objects of desire. To pass as ugly, a woman is now typically about a size 10 among zeroes, with slightly smaller eyes and a bigger nose, proportionally, than a Hummel figurine. Thus, ''ugly.''</p>
        <p>And consider America Ferrera, the 22-year-old Honduran-American star of ''Ugly Betty,'' ABC's charming and irrepressible mash-up of ''The Devil Wears Prada'' and the Colombian telenovela ''Betty la Fea.'' So lovely is Ms. Ferrera that she requires glasses, heavy bangs and bulky braces to suggest she's homely. Even with all this, it's going to be hard not to see her as a romantic lead, as she was in ''Real Women Have Curves,'' for which she won a best actress award at Sundance.</p>
        <p>But Betty's would-be ugliness has an incalculable upside for this actress. Think of it: she won't have to devote vast reserves of psychic and physical energy to being pretty all the time, which means she'll be at liberty to act. What a concept. She won't be preoccupied with wardrobe, makeup, angles or lighting.</p>
        <p>Better yet, she won't be required to submit to the famous and ill-understood prime-time wasting disease that, in a single season, turned beautiful Ellen Pompeo of ''Gray's Anatomy'' into a shadow. Sufficient nourishment can't hurt an actress's work, after all, and might even help.</p>
        <p>''Ugly Betty'' chronicles the life and times of a smart, sweet girl from Queens who goes to work as the assistant to the dashing editor in chief of a fashion magazine. A very real paradox of the Manhattan culture industry informs Betty's situation: namely, English majors who dream of New Yorker-style literary lives often end up working at glossy magazines whose interests have become (or always were) debased, commercial and far from literary.</p>
        <p>Why should Betty, a scholarly nerd who cares about Darfur and art photography, have to concern herself so urgently with the trivial lives of rich, vain couture people who haven't read a book in years? Because the monthly magazines that still represent American letters to college kids are now run by many such people.</p>
        <p>This on-screen fish-out-of-water story will, with any luck, work symbiotically with the equally sweet off-screen one: the story of America Ferrera getting a starring role in ABC prime time, where she'll perpetually get to dominate the scenes she shares with slimmer, cuter girls. (In the pilot the sex bombs Vanessa Williams, Gina Gershon and Salma Hayek, who is the show's canny executive producer, all play gross caricatures of glamour.)</p>
        <p>Though she doesn't starve herself or endure highlights and Restalyne injections, Ms. Ferrera will get all the close-ups, attention and praise. And more amazing still, no one will be able to begrudge her her success, all because she's willing and able to star on a show called ''Ugly Betty.'' That's a girl with a good head on her shoulders.</p>
        <p>THE NEW SEASON -- TELEVISION</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
