<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cowboys Are Back To Their Old Ways</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="555375"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="ON FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DALLAS COWBOYS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON REDSKINS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GEORGE, THOMAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Dallas Cowboys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920909T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DF1331F93AA3575AC0A964958260" item-length="648" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cowboys Are Back To Their Old Ways</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas George</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GEORGE, THOMAS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is amazing what one victory during prime time on national television can do for a team's reputation and psyche.</p>
        <p>That is what happened with the Dallas Cowboys on Monday night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is amazing what one victory during prime time on national television can do for a team's reputation and psyche.</p>
        <p>That is what happened with the Dallas Cowboys on Monday night.</p>
        <p>They throttled the Washington Redskins, 23-10, in the season opener for both teams and the next day the talk runs rampant. Doesn't Dallas look like a lock in the National Football Conference Eastern Division? Weren't the Cowboys so much faster and stronger than the Redskins? How about that Dallas "D"?</p>
        <p>Get those Super Bowl tickets, the ones with bright blue stars, printed.</p>
        <p>Let's catch our breath here.</p>
        <p>Sure, there is plenty to marvel when you look at what Dallas accomplished against Washington. Their victory was so complete in every phase of the game. The most impressive aspects were: holding Washington's vaunted rushing attack to 75 yards, with only 24 of those coming in the second half; their ability to create and maintain pass rushing lanes on quarterback Mark Rypien and the excellent preparation by the Dallas staff, led by Coach Jimmy Johnson.</p>
        <p>But the real key with the Cowboys at this stage of their impressive resurgence is not how they handle the Washingtons but how they respond to the Seattles.</p>
        <p>They are a very young team acquiring a taste for supremacy in the N.F.L. The Cowboys do not enter a game emotionally charged because of the their opponent, but rather they enter each contest insistent on establishing their own standard of excellence.</p>
        <p>This will be the true measuring test for Dallas.</p>
        <p>It is something not attained in one night.</p>
        <p>For the Cowboys. this is something they appear to have at least pondered.</p>
        <p>Listen to Cowboys' receiver Michael Irvin following Monday night's game: "Hey, guys, it's one win, a big win, but one win. The encouraging thing is that we've taken room to grow, but we've got to keep growing. We've got 15 more games. It's a long way from now till December."</p>
        <p>And just as long a way from Dallas to Pasadena, Calif., and the Super Bowl in January.</p>
        <p>Dallas was 11-5 last year and made the playoffs, so the team has already established some consistency. What makes Super Bowl champions is a level of consistency that does not waver. School is still very much in session for the Cowboys in that respect.</p>
        <p>Everybody talks about how shoddy the Redskins looked, how out of sync their offense was, but the crowd noise in Texas Stadium was so severe that Washington's timing was noticeably off.</p>
        <p>Redskins tackle Jim Lachey said: "You couldn't hear a thing. So, you watched the defensive guy and when he made his move, you made yours. In our system, where timing is everything, that's a tough way to play football. They've got too many talented guys to have that much of an edge on you at the snap."</p>
        <p>It is something the Redskins have enjoyed at home for years. It is usually something they handle on the road much better, but not on Monday night.</p>
        <p>Charles Haley, the new Dallas defensive end acquired late in the preseason from San Francisco, had plenty to do with Washington's confusion. He was a magnificent addition for the Dallas defense. But this Dallas secondary still features many of the faces who were ripped by run-and-shoot teams last season, especially by the Detroit Lions in the playoffs. There are still many questions about that bunch.</p>
        <p>Over all, there aren't any questions about Dallas' big-play people and their concepts on both sides of the line of scrimmage. When you have outcoached the Redskins, you have outcoached the N.F.L.'s best, and that is what Dallas did on Monday night. There were simply too many plays where Washington was in the wrong defense on the Dallas play called and too many times where Rypien rolled left and right and smack into Dallas' defense. This was accomplished by Dallas without defensive tackle Russell Maryland, who missed the game due to a dislocated toe.</p>
        <p>Johnson had all the nuances on his side.</p>
        <p>ON FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
