<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ready, Set, Grammy!</title>
    <meta content="01GRAM$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="998975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grammy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kuczynski, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grammy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grammy Awards</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DA1E3EF932A35750C0A96E958260" item-length="1454" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ready, Set, Grammy!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX KUCZYNSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kuczynski, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Grammy award week parties in New York described; photos (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''I USUALLY go to four or five Grammy parties,'' the calm, composed and collected rock star Sting said as he sat at a table with Luciano Pavarotti at the Waldorf-Astoria two nights before the 40th annual Grammy Awards ceremony. ''Until I get too drunk and have to be taken home.''</p>
        <p>It was hard to think of Sting looking drunk or frazzled; every perfectly blond hair was in place, his face was as smooth and dewy as a baby's bottom and his smile was so beatific he resembled the Pope. But it is important to remember that the endless round of Grammy parties, both before and after the ceremonies, is a sporting event, a virtual Ironman triathlon of night life. Only the toughest survive. Could Sting go the distance?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''I USUALLY go to four or five Grammy parties,'' the calm, composed and collected rock star Sting said as he sat at a table with Luciano Pavarotti at the Waldorf-Astoria two nights before the 40th annual Grammy Awards ceremony. ''Until I get too drunk and have to be taken home.''</p>
        <p>It was hard to think of Sting looking drunk or frazzled; every perfectly blond hair was in place, his face was as smooth and dewy as a baby's bottom and his smile was so beatific he resembled the Pope. But it is important to remember that the endless round of Grammy parties, both before and after the ceremonies, is a sporting event, a virtual Ironman triathlon of night life. Only the toughest survive. Could Sting go the distance?</p>
        <p>''I hope so,'' he said, with an eager gleam in his eye.</p>
        <p>The Grammys, you see, aren't just one piddling awards ceremony. Besides the categories relating to their day jobs, the music-world denizens can compete in numerous extracurricular events: pre-Grammy parties, pre-rehearsal parties, post-rehearsal parties, the parties for new Grammy categories, the general industry schmoozing parties, the perennial parties, the post-Grammy parties, and post-post-Grammy parties.</p>
        <p>''I don't go to those,'' Sting said, referring to the last group, those mysterious gatherings that inevitably end up in a $3,000-a-night hotel suite with strangers sometime around dawn. ''I'm a happily married man.''</p>
        <p>And now, a trumpet fanfare for those brave individuals who trained longer and harder than Tara Lipinski, for Grammy week! The festivities unofficially began last Saturday night at the songwriter Denise Rich's Fifth Avenue penthouse apartment and ended on Thursday morning with the actor Vincent Gallo pronouncing the end of glamour in the music industry outside the China Club at about 4 A.M.</p>
        <p>Somewhere along the way, Grammy nominees, music executives and hangers-on were expected to attend the Music Cares benefit at the Plaza; an MTV party at the Supper Club; Webster Hall's all-night dance party for Grammy-nominated deejays; a dinner at Sean (Puffy) Comb's restaurant, Justin's, for the rap crooner Usher; a cocktail party at the home of Clive Davis, the president of Arista Records, followed by a dinner and concert Mr. Davis gave at the Plaza, and at least 10 parties on Wednesday night -- all of which started after 11 P.M.</p>
        <p>After giving a dinner for 400 on Saturday night at which ice-skating waitresses in gold lame bodysuits served cocktails from her ice-sheathed wraparound balcony, Ms. Rich went to the Music Cares benefit on Monday, to Clive Davis's home on Tuesday, and to at least four parties on Wednesday, Grammy night. A producer and songwriter, Ms. Rich trains for the week with the discipline of a yogi. She avoids salt on awards day, she said, doesn't leave her apartment before nightfall and meditates. ''I visualize everything wonderful,'' she said. ''I always go to about five or six parties on Grammy night. By the end I'm carrying my shoes in my hand.''</p>
        <p>Fortunately for Ms. Rich, she keeps an extra pair of Manolo Blahniks in her limousine.</p>
        <p>The Grammy games are open to more than just music-industry types. In an unlikely pairing, Martha Stewart, in a tan suit, mingled with Puffy Combs, in a white dinner jacket and Mongolian fur overcoat, at Clive Davis's Plaza party. The actress Arlene Dahl and her husband, Marc Rosen, a cosmetics executive, dished about Bobbi Brown and Whitney Houston. (''He had on more jewelry than she did,'' Mr. Rosen marveled.) The former Mets first baseman Keith Hernandez put his tuxedo to good use and showed up at Denise Rich's on Saturday and at Clive Davis's dinner on Tuesday, as did Star Jones, a host of ''The View,'' in a leopard-print Marc Bouwer dress.</p>
        <p>''Oh, you'll see me everywhere,'' Ms. Jones predicted as she mingled at Mr. Davis's Plaza soiree. ''But this is the most important party. It's like the Swifty party of the Grammys,'' she added, referring to the agent Swifty Lazar's legendary post-Oscars party in Los Angeles, which he held for three decades.</p>
        <p>On Grammy night, Ms. Jones stayed out until 3 A.M., at parties given by BMG and Time-Warner. Her secret for partying all night and still turning up fresh, fully made-up and rested-looking for a taping by 10 A.M. the next morning? Power napping. ''Before the party I took a bath and a nap,'' Ms. Jones said. ''An hour-and-half power nap and, baby, I can go all night!''</p>
        <p>But Courtney Love apparently hadn't been napping. At the party for MCA Universal at the Four Seasons in the early hours of Thursday morning, she and her boyfriend, Edward Norton, an actor, were in serious wardrobe dysjunction. She wore a dazzling white sequined floor-length dress with strategically skin-baring cut-outs, and Mr. Norton wore a blue oxford shirt and khakis; they scored poorly on the Famous Couples' Outfit Coordination tandem event.</p>
        <p>Mr. Norton skulked behind Ms. Love, while she pasted on a brave smile as a woman in a black lace dress grasped her shoulders and exclaimed: ''I am being serious. Really. I am so full of love for you. Well, I'm drunk, too, but I am so full of love!'' So, Ms. Love won points in the How to Deal Graciously With Excessive Adoration by a Fan category, but she eventually lost in the General Fatigue category; Mr. Norton carried her -- playfully, a China Club spokesman noted -- out of that club later in the evening.</p>
        <p>Gwen Stefani of No Doubt and Gavin Rossdale of Bush, another cute couple, won medals for Best Hair. Outside Clive Davis's Plaza party on Tuesday, Ms. Stefani stopped before photographers and tilted her head, covered in tiny blond knots, and Mr. Rossdale tossed his black and blond mane.</p>
        <p>The two of them stopped into Barneys a couple of times a day during Grammy week for supplies. They wound their way through at least three parties on Grammy night, when Ms. Stefanie's head sprouted several randomly placed blond braids and Mr. Rossdale tossed his hair around some more. Mr. Rossdale even wore a black vestlike garment that had dangling straps and D-rings and looked something like a full-body athletic supporter.</p>
        <p>Kelsey Grammer, this year's Grammy host, showed the deep-down flint of an endurance athlete. After a grueling week of rehearsals and parties in his honor, on Grammy night at the Four Seasons' party Mr. Grammer looked pale despite the residual streaks of makeup clinging to his cheeks. Yet, he had pressed on through the BMG party at Barneys and the Sony party at the Hammerstein Ballroom.</p>
        <p>''I'm just exhausted,'' he sighed. A woman who said she was a producer for the Wu-Tang Clan came up and introduced herself.</p>
        <p>''Hi, Frasier!'' she said, batting suspiciously long eyelashes. ''Were you at the Grammys?'' she asked Mr. Grammer, who didn't bat an eye and said he had enjoyed himself very much, thank you. For that alone, Mr. Grammer won a Grammy gold medal as the most gracious, polite television star on the planet.</p>
        <p>''Can I get a picture with you?'' she asked, and handed a camera to her companion. The flash didn't work. Mr. Grammer and his family stood by, helpless captives with frozen smiles. After several excruciating minutes, the flash finally popped.</p>
        <p>''I'm so tired I could shoot myself,'' Mr. Grammer said, as he turned away and surveyed the room, eyeing the 200-meter dash to the front door.</p>
        <p>Later, at Polygram's post-Grammy party at the Racquet and Tennis Club, Sting and his wife, Trudie Styler, sat behind a wall of bodyguards, half-eaten plates of pasta before them. When asked if they were going to go to parties until they got drunk and had to be taken home, Ms. Styler said: ''I have a 2-year-old and a 7-year-old at home. I think we're just going to this and EMI.''</p>
        <p>Then she added: ''Five parties? Really? He said that? I don't think so.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
