<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Culture Zone; Portrait of the Artist As a Focus Group</title>
    <meta content="301KAKUTT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="998776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04EED8143EF932A35750C0A96E958260" item-length="1019" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Culture Zone; Portrait of the Artist As a Focus Group</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michiko Kakutani</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani article deplores pressure in arts to be popular and accessible that results in art created by consensus; sees abdication by creative types of their artistic freedom and judgment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you took a poll, what would America's best-loved painting look like? In their playful new book, ''Painting by Numbers,'' two Russian emigre conceptual artists decided to find out. With a little help from some polling experts, Vitaly Komar and Alexander Melamid queried 1,001 Americans about their tastes in color, form and style, and concluded that the most wanted painting in the country is a bluish landscape painting, populated by George Washington, a family of tourists and a pair of frolicking deer. The canvas is the size of a dishwasher and looks like something that might adorn the walls of a third-rate motel. It is the apotheosis of art created by consensus.</p>
        <p>Komar and Melamid's exercise, of course, is a sly comment on the democratization of creativity and America's mania for polls. What is more disturbing is that their satiric project unwittingly underscores another trend at work in American culture: our eagerness to substitute public opinion for personal belief, market demands for authentic artistic and political vision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you took a poll, what would America's best-loved painting look like? In their playful new book, ''Painting by Numbers,'' two Russian emigre conceptual artists decided to find out. With a little help from some polling experts, Vitaly Komar and Alexander Melamid queried 1,001 Americans about their tastes in color, form and style, and concluded that the most wanted painting in the country is a bluish landscape painting, populated by George Washington, a family of tourists and a pair of frolicking deer. The canvas is the size of a dishwasher and looks like something that might adorn the walls of a third-rate motel. It is the apotheosis of art created by consensus.</p>
        <p>Komar and Melamid's exercise, of course, is a sly comment on the democratization of creativity and America's mania for polls. What is more disturbing is that their satiric project unwittingly underscores another trend at work in American culture: our eagerness to substitute public opinion for personal belief, market demands for authentic artistic and political vision.</p>
        <p>From the world of advertising, consumer research has already spread to Washington, where President Clinton has rarely made a move without checking with his pollsters, and to Hollywood, where test audiences can affect the content, pacing and tone of big-budget pictures and determine which TV pilots get scheduled. From Hollywood, it is now spreading into music, theater, novels and journalism. The result is a new brand of carefully positioned art and a culture-wide embrace of that old advertising slogan ''The customer is always right'' -- even if that customer has no expertise, no knowledge and no taste.</p>
        <p>MTV's new show ''12 Angry Viewers'' gives audience members a chance to add a video to the station's playlist, and focus groups similarly determine what songs many radio stations will or will not play. In his insightful new book, ''Dreaming Out Loud,'' Bruce Feiler points out that a growing number of country-music stations now employ market-research companies to tell them exactly what their audiences want. The process, he suggests, systematically excludes tracks that provoke the strongest reaction, positive as well as negative -- and the resulting picks tend to be predictable, homogenized and cheerfully upbeat.</p>
        <p>The sales imperative -- be popular, be accessible, be liked -- is also threatening to turn writing into another capitalist tool. In an effort to raise circulation, newspapers like The Miami Herald and The Boca Raton News have used reader-preference surveys to determine their ''coverage priorities,'' and some novelists are adopting the literary equivalent of the applause-o-meter as well. The best-selling author Andrew Greeley has used focus groups to shape his marketing campaigns, and the novelist James Patterson has conscripted groups of test readers to analyze his books before publication. Patterson recently changed the ending of his new thriller, ''Cat &amp; Mouse,'' in response to reader feedback; the novel reached No. 2 on the Times best-seller list.</p>
        <p>This shameless second-guessing is not simply a money-grubbing attempt to give audiences what they think they want. It also represents the abdication by creative types of their artistic freedom and judgment. Just as today's poll-driven politicians have elected to become mirrors of the national Zeitgeist rather than leaders, so have poll-driven ''artists'' elected to become assembly-line manufacturers, in thrall to the opinions of mall rats deemed demographically correct.</p>
        <p>No one has tried harder to turn the messy process of artistic creation into a systematic, risk-free proposition than Garth Drabinsky, the producer of the Broadway musical ''Ragtime.'' A 20-year veteran of the movie business, Drabinsky is methodically transferring Hollywood practices to the stage. He insists that a show's prospective book writer submit an initial treatment to insure that the writer is not ''going off on a tangent and doing something that is incongruous to the philosophy or ideas of the producer.'' For ''Ragtime,'' he hired a polling firm to help calibrate audience reactions. The show's book eventually went through some 20 drafts.</p>
        <p>''We want to hear what audiences have to say about what they're seeing,'' Drabinsky says, ''and most importantly, we want to find out if the work is coherent -- if it's making sense emotionally and dramatically.'' The ''Ragtime'' focus groups, he argues, helped his creative team ''learn about the response of audiences to what characters we've chosen to put in the show,'' as well as ''whether they feel the show is too long.''</p>
        <p>So what if critics complained that ''Ragtime'' lacked a distinctive voice? So what if they thought it had the feel of a corporate committee? ''Ragtime'' has already racked up a $17.5 million advance, and other producers and theater owners are being encouraged to use surveys and exit polls as a means of boosting business. In an article in the theatrical magazine Back Stage, George A. Wachtel, president of a firm called Audience Research &amp; Analysis, writes: ''Response cards distributed during previews can produce objective feedback from which the creative team can learn what is working and what isn't.'' In five years, Wachtel says, ''when you open the Playbill for a show and it says, advertising by ..., publicity by ..., it will also say market research by ..., because it's going to become part of what happens on Broadway. In five years, I predict that most shows will be doing audience surveys and will be better understanding their audience from the get-go, and that the majority of new shows will have some kind of preview research.''</p>
        <p>Such predictions eerily limn a future in which Pop Art gives way to Poll Art -- a future in which reproductions of Komar and Melamid's cloying painting will hang on every museum's walls.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
