<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WHITE HOUSE SAYS INTEREST RATE RISE MAY SLOW GROWTH</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="678444"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTEREST RATES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL RESERVE SYSTEM</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYSON, LAURA D'ANDREA (CHMN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940404T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E6D6103FF937A35757C0A962958260" item-length="1318" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WHITE HOUSE SAYS INTEREST RATE RISE MAY SLOW GROWTH</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With long-term interest rates now above 7 percent, President Clinton's top economic advisers expressed concern over the weekend that further rate increases could damage the economy and slow growth to an unacceptable level.</p>
        <p>The Administration argues that the economy is going through a transition from very strong growth in last year's fourth quarter to less growth now. But no one can tell where the leveling-off point will be. The concern is that if interest rates rise another notch, economic growth could decline too much -- slowing the creation of new jobs.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With long-term interest rates now above 7 percent, President Clinton's top economic advisers expressed concern over the weekend that further rate increases could damage the economy and slow growth to an unacceptable level.</p>
        <p>The Administration argues that the economy is going through a transition from very strong growth in last year's fourth quarter to less growth now. But no one can tell where the leveling-off point will be. The concern is that if interest rates rise another notch, economic growth could decline too much -- slowing the creation of new jobs.</p>
        <p>"Based on what we know, our view of how strongly the economy will grow this year is not changed by an interest rate in the neighborhood of 7 percent," said Laura D'Andrea Tyson, the chairwoman of the President's Council of Economic Advisers. "But if the level goes much above 7 percent, then that would exercise a contractionary effect on the economy."</p>
        <p>Long-term interest rates rose nearly three-quarters of a percentage point during the last month, reaching 7.26 percent on Friday in a bond-trading session shortened in observance of Good Friday. Not since the early 1980's have rates increased so much in a single month, and the comments by Ms. Tyson and other Administration officials seemed clearly aimed at calming the markets.</p>
        <p>The Administration's new concerns could put it in open conflict for the first time with the Federal Reserve Board, whose chief priority has been to control inflation even at the cost of economic growth. The Administration's priority has been creation of jobs through economic expansion, even at the possible cost of an inflation rate that is mildly higher than what the Fed might accept.</p>
        <p>While Fed officials have expressed surprise at the rapid run-up in interest rates, they have not indicated whether they agree with Ms. Tyson and other Administration officials that 7 percent is as high as rates can go without choking economic growth.</p>
        <p>Treasury Secretary Lloyd Bentsen, in an interview yesterday, also expressed concern about rates rising any farther. Mr. Bentsen and, separately, Robert Rubin, the President's chief economic adviser, in a television appearance on "This Week," said they expected interest rates to fall back once the bond markets settle down.</p>
        <p>"I think the underlying economic fundamentals will in the end have their influence," Mr. Bentsen said. When that happens, Ms. Tyson expects interest rates to come back into line with the economy's true strength.</p>
        <p>"Based on history, the normal level today for long-term interest rates should be about a percentage point below what they are now," she said.</p>
        <p>Their views were clearly a signal to Wall Street and its traders to end what might come to be known as the great interest rate "crash" of 1994.</p>
        <p>What has crashed, in fact, is bond prices, particularly the price for the Treasury's 30-year bond. As they have gone down, so has the stock market. The Dow Jones industrial average has lost nearly 9 percent of its value since the end of January.</p>
        <p>On Wall Street, when bond prices fall, that perversely makes interest rates rise. When a $1,000 bond paying $60 annually, or 6 percent in interest, falls to a price of $825, because bondholders are selling in a panic, then the rate, in effect, rises for the person acquiring a $1,000 bond for only $825.</p>
        <p>For the new buyer, the $60 annual interest payment continues unchanged, but now it represents a 7.26 percent return on his $825 investment. And that is how much rates have jumped in recent months, with much of the rise coming in March.</p>
        <p>The 30-year Treasury bond in particular is a benchmark for home construction loans, mortgages and car loans, the industries that made the economy boom in the fourth quarter, mainly because rates had fallen so low. Now rates are rising, largely because speculators had bought bonds with borrowed money, gambling that the weak economy that had prevailed since 1989 would keep bond prices high and interest rates low.</p>
        <p>But those buyers changed their minds and started dumping bonds to repay debts after the Federal Reserve, for the first time in five years, raised rates on Feb. 4. The Fed acted out of concern that the unexpectedly strong economic growth in recent months might raise the inflation rate later this year. But the bond market took the Fed's action as a signal that the long boom in bond prices was over, that higher inflation was on the way back and that bondholders had better get out. Braking a Swift Selloff</p>
        <p>Their rapid exodus gave the bond market a momentum of its own, and as bond prices fell, rates rose far more than what either the Fed or the Administration had anticipated. It is this momentum that the Administration is trying to arrest, but in doing so it raises the potential for disagreement with the Fed.</p>
        <p>While the Administration endorsed the Fed's rate increase on Feb. 4 and another small one on March 22, the subsequent run-up in rates is forcing the administration to be more insistent that inflation is mild, indeed milder than the Fed might believe.</p>
        <p>Still, the White House avoids criticism of the Fed or its chairman, Alan Greenspan.</p>
        <p>"There is a feeling in the Administration that we respect the guy and he is trying to do the right thing," a senior economic adviser in the Administration said. "He may be wrong; he may be right. But he is trying to achieve the same goals we are."</p>
        <p>The main goal is mild inflation. Ms. Tyson and Mr. Rubin say inflation is mild now and seems very likely to stay mild -- a declaration that no one at the Federal Reserve has publicly matched in recent weeks. Despite the increase in interest rates, the Council of Economic Advisers, which Ms. Tyson heads, sticks to its forecast: the annual inflation rate, as measured by the Consumer Price Index, might rise to 3.5 percent in the months ahead from 3 percent today, an acceptable increase brought on by a gradually strengthening economy.</p>
        <p>If the economy grows gradually, then the normal 30-year bond rate should be between 6 percent and 6.5 percent, Ms. Tyson said, or roughly a percentage point less than the level reached last week.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubin yesterday also predicted that the inflation rate was most likely to remain at a moderate 3 percent to 3.5 percent in the months ahead. That is in line with an economy that the Administration says will settle down this year and early next year to an annual growth rate of between 2.5 percent and 3 percent -- enough growth to continue to create new jobs. Two Causes Suggested</p>
        <p>Given this projection, there are two explanations for the unexpected jump in interest rates, Ms. Tyson said. "One is that the economy is stronger than we have been predicting," she said, "and the other is that the market is going through an adjustment that has to do with loans and losses that needed to be covered in a period of time."</p>
        <p>Ms. Tyson said that bond prices might be responding both to the speculation and to an economy that is momentarily growing more strongly than anticipated. "There is agreement in the Administration that it is both factors," she said. "But no one knows yet how much weight to ascribe to each one."</p>
        <p>The uncertainty made the surge in employment in March, reported by the Labor Department on Friday, particularly difficult to read. The Labor Department said that while the unemployment rate remained at 6.5 percent, the same as in February, the economy had created 456,000 jobs, the biggest one-month increase in years.</p>
        <p>Such job gains suggest stronger growth than the Administration's estimate. But Ms. Tyson and other Administration officials, among them Alicia Munnell, the Treasury Department's assistant secretary for economic policy, said that the proper way to interpret March's job figures was to average the 456,000 figure with job growth in January and February -- a process that produces an average monthly gain of slightly more than 200,000 jobs.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
