<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Bad Day for Cubs, Sosa Ties McGwire at 65</title>
    <meta content="24CUBS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1048897"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chicago Cubs</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Milwaukee Brewers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dedman, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sosa, Sammy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcgwire, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Milwaukee Brewers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980924T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE5D81639F937A1575AC0A96E958260" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Bad Day for Cubs, Sosa Ties McGwire at 65</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL DEDMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dedman, Bill</byline>
      <dateline>MILWAUKEE, Sept. 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sammy Sosa hits 64th and 65th home runs, again tying Mark McGwire for single-season record, in Chicago Cubs' 8-7 loss to Milwaukee Brewers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The summer of the home run headed toward a final glorious chapter today after Sammy Sosa hit home runs No. 64 and No. 65 against the Milwaukee Brewers and once again tied Mark McGwire in a battle that may go down to the last swing.</p>
        <p>The race, which has captivated fans and nonfans alike, had seemed to be over. Even Sosa conceded yesterday that McGwire was likely to win. Sosa had gone five days without a hit, much less a home run.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The summer of the home run headed toward a final glorious chapter today after Sammy Sosa hit home runs No. 64 and No. 65 against the Milwaukee Brewers and once again tied Mark McGwire in a battle that may go down to the last swing.</p>
        <p>The race, which has captivated fans and nonfans alike, had seemed to be over. Even Sosa conceded yesterday that McGwire was likely to win. Sosa had gone five days without a hit, much less a home run.</p>
        <p>But as he has done several times before, Sosa pulled even with McGwire, who failed to hit a home run tonight. The players were tied at 55 home runs after 138 games, tied at 62, tied at 63 and now they are even at 65. Both are well past Roger Maris's record of 61 home runs in a season, a mark they broke six days apart earlier this month.</p>
        <p>A screenwriter planning the Hollywood version of the home-run race of 1998 will need a travel agent to witness the magical ending. Fly to Houston? Sosa's Chicago Cubs will play three games against the Astros, Friday through Sunday. Fly to St. Louis? McGwire's Cardinals play four against the Montreal Expos, Thursday through Sunday.</p>
        <p>For Sosa, and his Cub teammates, today's blasts before a crowd of 45,338 at County Stadium were ultimately overshadowed by a loss to the Brewers that set a new level of frustration for a franchise well known for its decades of disappointment. Leading, 7-0, the Cubs lost, 8-7, when a young left fielder, Brant Brown, dropped a fly ball that would have been the last out of the game. Instead, three Brewers runners scored, the game was lost and the Cubs were suddenly a half-game behind the Mets in their neck-and-neck National League wild-card race. But the Cubs were soon back in a tie with the Mets after Montreal beat New York, 3-0.</p>
        <p>''For me, it makes no difference if I finish first in home runs, or if I finish last,'' Sosa said after the painful ending. ''I have another thing to think about: the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>For the second day in a row, it was a Cubs crowd cheering Sosa on in Milwaukee. At least half of those in attendance wore Cubs caps, shirts or entire pinstriped uniforms. Until the last play of the game, they had a great time.</p>
        <p>One Cubs fan, Roger Moore, drove all night from Indianapolis to see Sosa and his team. At age 57, he has yet to see the Cubs win a World Series. One of their chances came in 1969, when they collapsed and lost out to the Mets in a divisional race. Moore spent the afternoon wandering the bleachers, erasing the bitterness of a lifetime as a Cubs fan. ''And I'll hate the Mets until I die,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Moore nearly died in the fifth inning, when Sosa hit No. 64 into the right-field corner off of Rafael Roque, the left-handed Brewer pitcher, also from the Dominican Republic. And Moore couldn't stop yelling in the sixth, when Sosa hit No. 65, a line drive to center off of Rod Henderson, a relief pitcher. Both were fastballs, on the way in and out.</p>
        <p>Sosa celebrated each home run with his ritual clap of the hands and was called out for a bow after returning to the dugout by a crowd that stood for each of his at-bats.</p>
        <p>But then a century of failure for Cubs fans intruded into the late-afternoon shadows in the ninth inning. With two outs in the bottom of the ninth, with the bases loaded in what was now a 7-5 game, three runners were circling the bases as a fly ball sliced toward the line in left and Brown tracked it down.</p>
        <p>Jim Riggleman saw the ball. The manager of the Cubs was on the top step of the dugout, ready to celebrate a victory that would keep the Cubs at least even with the Mets for the last seat in the National League playoffs. ''I don't take anything for granted,'' he said.</p>
        <p>And Brown saw the ball. He glided back and over to the line, ready to squeeze the last out of the game. Originally a first baseman, he had worked for six years in the minor leagues to learn the outfield. Today, he entered the game in the eighth inning, as a defensive replacement.</p>
        <p>''It was a routine fly ball,'' Brown said.</p>
        <p>As Cubs fans will remember until they die, the ball bounced off the heel of Brown's glove. It rolled away as three Brewers crossed the plate and Brewers fans in the stadium and Mets fans in New York exulted. ''I hope it doesn't cost us,'' Brown said, shaken and quiet in a funereal Cubs clubhouse.</p>
        <p>Now the Cubs go to Houston for their last three games against the Astros on Friday, Saturday and Sunday. The Mets, losers of two straight to Montreal, will be in Atlanta against the Braves.</p>
        <p>Sosa went home with one of his two home-run balls. No. 65 hit the empty center-field area and bounced back onto the field. Marquis Grissom, the Brewers' center fielder, put the ball in his back pocket. Then he threw it to first baseman Mark Loretta, who put it in his pocket. After a while, he threw it to the Cubs dugout.</p>
        <p>No. 64 had been caught in the second row of the right-field bleachers by Vernon Kuhlemeier, a 33-year-old Cubs fan from Dakota, Ill. He said he intended to keep it, not sell it, after many years without catching a ball at Wrigley Field. The Cubs offered him tickets to a game next year and a chance to meet Sosa. He countered with a request that Sosa sign the ball for him. It was a standoff.</p>
        <p>''I've got 65,'' Sosa said, not too concerned about 64. For his part, Sosa will be sorry that he can't take the Milwaukee Brewers pitchers with him. In all, he hit 12 home runs in 12 games against the Brewers.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
