<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At the United Nations, One Seat for Korea;   Seoul's Sea Change</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="391924"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH KOREA</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/South Korea</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD9153BF936A25753C1A966958260" item-length="457" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At the United Nations, One Seat for Korea;   Seoul's Sea Change</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: To the Editor:</p>
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Jong Keun You's criticisms of the South Korean Government (letter, Sept. 27) are familiar ones to me. I was once an outspoken critic of Korean authoritarianism whose writings were considered troublesome by past Seoul governments. But Mr. You's complaints struck me as out of date considering the hopeful changes taking place on the peninsula.</p>
        <p>His contention that President Roh Tae Woo of South Korea ''has rapidly moved away from democratization'' is plainly untrue. While the previousregimes of Park Chung Hee and Chun Doo Hwan did use authoritarian tactics to crack down on their critics, President Roh Tae Woo, who was elected in 1987, has done much to democratize the Korean political system. From the expanded civil liberties of the average citizen to the strengthened political clout of the labor unions, the media, dissident groups and the national legislature, it is clear to even the casual observer of Korean affairs that a political sea change for the better has occurred in recent years and continues today.</p>
        <p>Although I have lived in the United States for more than 20 years, I have traveled to South Korea regularly since 1987 and have contributed articles to publications there of all stripes, radical and conservative. My perception is that freedom of press and expression in South Korea has reached new heights.</p>
        <p>Mr. You's charge that the Seoul Government aims to use the threat from Communist North Korea to quell its domestic opponents and thus resists improved relations with the North doesn't ring true either. His criticism comes at a time when the highest level inter-Korean talks ever are taking place between the prime ministers of North and South. And it was policy initiatives advanced by Seoul that brought the North to the bargaining table.</p>
        <p>Since 1988 President Roh has boldly sought to translate easing cold-war tensions into better North-South relations by improving ties with the North's allies in the Communist bloc. In a stunning breakthrough, Seoul has managed to establish first-ever official ties with a number of socialist countries and is making significant progress in improved ties even with China and the Soviet Union. These moves have had the desired effect: the hard-line North Korean regime, which for decades denied Seoul's legitimacy, has been pressured to resume negotiations toward tension reduction and eventual reunification.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. You, I have long supported Korean democracy and reunification. The fact is, though, that significant progress is being made in both areas, and credit should be given where it is due.</p>
        <p>YEARN HONG CHOI</p>
        <p>Washington, Sept. 28, 1990</p>
        <p>The writer is Distinguished Professor of Management, University of the District of Columbia.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
