<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Question Box</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392178"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Baltimore Orioles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Chicago Cubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901015T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DE103CF936A25753C1A966958260" item-length="905" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Question Box</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ray Corio</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Never Behind in Series</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>Never Behind in Series</p>
        <p>Never Behind in Series</p>
        <p>Q. When Oakland swept San Francisco in the earthquake-interrupted World Series last season, the Athletics never trailed in any of the four games. Was that a first?</p>
        <p>A. It was a third, but the feat was not as earth-shattering as the one achieved by Baltimore almost a quarter-century earlier. The Orioles not only were never behind in any of the four games of the 1966 World Series against Los Angeles, but they were never even tied by the Dodgers. In the top of the first of game 1, Baltimore, with home runs from Frank Robinson and Brooks Robinson, took a 3-0 lead, and the Dodgers were behind for good before they even batted. Baltimore went on to win the opener, 5-2, then got shutouts from Jim Palmer (6-0), Wally Bunker (1-0) and Dave McNally (1-0) in completing the four-game sweep. In their 36 times at bat, the Dodgers were scoreless over the last 33. Three years earlier, the Dodgers had scored a Series sweep in which they never trailed in any game. Better yet, they did it against their long-time rivals, the Yankees, and they did it in this fashion: a 5-2 victory in the opener as Sandy Koufax struck out 15; a 4-1 second-game victory by Johnny Podres; a 1-0 decision in which Don Drysdale outdueled Jim Bouton, and a Series-clinching 2-1 game that saw Koufax outpitch Whitey Ford despite a game-tying home run by Mickey Mantle. The seventh-inning homer was the only time the Yankees caught the Dodgers in that Series, but when the Dodgers responded with a run in the bottom of the seventh, that was that.</p>
        <p>Last season, Oakland matched the 1963 Dodgers in being tied but never trailing during a Series as the A's were caught for one spell by the Giants in game 2. The 1-1 tie lasted one inning before Oakland rang up four runs in the fourth inning and pulled away for good. But the brief tie prevented Oakland from permanently tying the 1966 Orioles, the only team in 86 World Series to lead from the first inning to the last.</p>
        <p>The Fewest Pitchers</p>
        <p>Q. In Oakland's World Series sweep in 1989, the Athletics used six members of their pitching staff: Dave Stewart, Mike Moore, Gene Nelson, Rick Honeycutt, Dennis Eckersley and Todd Burns. What's the fewest pitchers used by a Series winner?</p>
        <p>A. Although several teams during the dead-ball days of the first dozen World Series got by with three pitchers for an entire Series, no team has ever won a Series with just one pitcher carrying the load. But 80 years ago, the Philadelphia Athletics, the root of the franchise now in Oakland, came mighty close.</p>
        <p>In the 1910 Series, the Athletics of Connie Mack were winners in five games over the Chicago Cubs. Three of those four complete-game victories went to Jack Coombs by scores of 9-3, 12-5 and 7-2. The other went to Chief Bender, who won the opener, 4-1, but was a loser in 10 innings, 4-3, in game 4. Coombs won his three games in a span of six days, starting one of them on only one day's rest. Was he tired? Apparently not, for he also managed 5 hits in 13 times up for a .385 batting average and drove in 3 runs.</p>
        <p>Since the death of the dead-ball era, the 1928 Yankees rank as the team that has gotten by with the skimpiest staff in winning a World Series. In sweeping St. Louis, the Yankees needed just three pitchers: Waite Hoyt, who won the first game and the last one; and George Pipgras and Tom Zachary, who won the games in between.</p>
        <p>Sweeping the Series</p>
        <p>Q. How many times has the World Series ended in a sweep?</p>
        <p>A. It's happened 12 times in 86 World Series, an average of roughly every seven years, and oddly it's been roughest on the Yankees, the most successful Series team in the game. Twice the Yankees have been swept in four games: by the Los Angeles Dodgers in 1963 and the Cincinnati Reds in 1976, and once they've been swept in five games: by the New York Giants in 1922, when game 2 ended in a 3-3 tie after 10 innings.</p>
        <p>Only one other team, the Chicago Cubs, has been swept more than once in Series play. It happened to the Cubs in 1932 and 1938, and both times the sweeper was the Yankees, who also have 4-0 records against the Pirates (1927), Cardinals (1928), Reds (1939) and Phillies (1950) to their credit for a total of six four-game sweeps, or half the entire Series amount.</p>
        <p>Mets' Pitching Feat</p>
        <p>Q. When Nolan Ryan won his 300th game this season, it meant that the 1969 World Series champion Mets had on their staff two future 300-game winners in Ryan (302 and counting) and Tom Seaver (311 and retired). Is this true for any other Series winner?</p>
        <p>A. Not yet, and not only that, but it's not even true for a Series loser. When the Mets beat the Baltimore Orioles in five games 21 years ago, Seaver won game 4 after losing the opener, and Ryan earned a save in game 3. The closest thing to this achievment of two future 300-game winners on the same Series staff, win or lose, occurred with the 1977-78 Los Angeles Dodgers. Those teams, which lost both Series to the Yankees in six games, had Don Sutton (who wound up with 324 career victories) and Tommy John (who retired with 288) on its starting corps.</p>
        <p>Question Box is a regular feature of SportsMonday. Readers are invited to submit questions concerning any aspect of sport: statistics or strategies, rules or records. The address is Question Box, SportsMonday, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Questions not published cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
