<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sierra Health Stock Falls on Acquisition Announcement</title>
    <meta content="05CARE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="887863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Physician Corp of America</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sierra Health Services Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gilpin, Kenneth N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5DD1238F936A35752C1A960958260" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sierra Health Stock Falls on Acquisition Announcement</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gilpin, Kenneth N</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sierra Health Services Inc says it has agreed to buy Physician Corp of America in all-stock deal valued at $509.4 million; Sierra shares fall $5 and analysts say Sierra will be paying too much for troubled company and that turnaround could take up to two years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a transaction that drew a resoundingly negative reaction from investors, Sierra Health Services Inc. said yesterday that it has agreed to buy the Physician Corporation of America in an all-stock deal initially valued at $509.4 million.</p>
        <p>The combination would create a managed care company with more than $2 billion in revenues and slightly more than one million members in 18 states, according to data from Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company. Analysts said Sierra would be paying too much for a troubled company and that a turnaround could take up to two years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a transaction that drew a resoundingly negative reaction from investors, Sierra Health Services Inc. said yesterday that it has agreed to buy the Physician Corporation of America in an all-stock deal initially valued at $509.4 million.</p>
        <p>The combination would create a managed care company with more than $2 billion in revenues and slightly more than one million members in 18 states, according to data from Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company. Analysts said Sierra would be paying too much for a troubled company and that a turnaround could take up to two years.</p>
        <p>In terms of members, that would make the combined company, which would retain Sierra's name, the nation's 12th-largest managed care company that is publicly traded, according to the Bernstein data.</p>
        <p>Sierra, which is based in Las Vegas, Nev., and dominates that market, would be acquiring a company with a strong presence in Florida, Texas and Puerto Rico. But the Miami-based Physician Corporation has been losing money for the last year and a half.</p>
        <p>The company, which has had difficulty controlling medical costs, said separately yesterday that it lost $95.44 million in the third quarter, or $2.44 a share, on revenues of $362.1 million. The results included a $100 million one-time after-tax charge for workers' compensation business.</p>
        <p>Under the agreement, each share of Physician Corporation of America will be exchanged for 0.45 share of Sierra Health.</p>
        <p>The transaction was first reported in The Wall Street Journal yesterday.</p>
        <p>Analysts and investors reacted quickly to the deal, which was also formally announced yesterday, sending Sierra's stock plunging.</p>
        <p>Shares of Sierra fell $5, to $23.875. The drop turned what had been a $509.4 million deal into a transaction worth $419 million.</p>
        <p>Shares of Physician Corporation rose 12.5 cents, to $10.75. Based on yesterday's price, the deal values each Physician share at $10.74.</p>
        <p>''This is a decision we made for more than just the short term,'' Ria Marie Carlson, Sierra's vice president for investor relations, said after the market closed. Ms. Carlson added that the steep drop in Sierra's stock price would not alter the terms of the transaction. ''There is no walk-away clause in here,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Analysts said Sierra was paying far too much for the Physician Corporation, despite the deal's potential strategic value.</p>
        <p>''The problem is that Sierra's stock will incur a lot of dilution over the next year or so,'' Lori M. Price, an analyst at Oppenheimer &amp; Company, said. ''They are almost doubling their number of shares outstanding for a company that is just approaching the break-even point for the first time in 18 months. That is a high price to pay.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Price and other analysts said that Sierra, which is regarded as a well-managed company, was gambling that it could turn the Physician Corporation's fortunes around.</p>
        <p>''Sierra is doing well, and Physician Corporation is not, and Sierra obviously thinks they can help turn it around,'' Kenneth S. Abramowitz, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, said. ''Sierra is taking a reasonable businessman's risk.''</p>
        <p>Sierra said it anticipated the merger would generate $10 million to $15 million in annual cost savings. Staff reductions are expected to be minimal, Sierra said.</p>
        <p>After the deal is completed, Dr. E. Stanley Kardatzke, chairman of Physician Corporation, will assume the same title at Sierra Health Services. Dr. Anthony M. Marlin, Sierra's chairman and chief executive, will become vice chairman and chief executive. Erin E. MacDonald, Sierra's president and chief operating officer, will retain those positions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
