<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Make Art, and Peace, Not Trouble</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="390020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL AID (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CENSORSHIP</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PORNOGRAPHY AND OBSCENITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ENDOWMENT FOR THE ARTS</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Aid (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2D81238F93AA35753C1A966958260" item-length="505" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Make Art, and Peace, Not Trouble</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the 15 months since Jesse Helms and other senators began their carrying on about ''obscene'' and ''indecent'' art, the National Endowment for the Arts has ignited hot heads and even hotter talk. This week, Congress finally gets the chance to debate the N.E.A.'s future temperately and intelligently.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the 15 months since Jesse Helms and other senators began their carrying on about ''obscene'' and ''indecent'' art, the National Endowment for the Arts has ignited hot heads and even hotter talk. This week, Congress finally gets the chance to debate the N.E.A.'s future temperately and intelligently.</p>
        <p>In the 15 months since Jesse Helms and other senators began their carrying on about ''obscene'' and ''indecent'' art, the National Endowment for the Arts has ignited hot heads and even hotter talk. This week, Congress finally gets the chance to debate the N.E.A.'s future temperately and intelligently.</p>
        <p>Negotiators in both houses have come up with bipartisan compromises on legislation to renew the agency's life. These are compromises that can deflate hysteria and permit artists who receive Federal funds to work without intimidation.</p>
        <p>Senator Helms's fevered assault on the N.E.A. followed the Endowment's partial funding of a retrospective showing of photographs by Robert Mapplethorpe and its award of $15,000 to another photographer, Andres Serrano. Mapplethorpe's documentation of a sadomasochistic male homosexual subculture can evoke disgust; Mr. Serrano's image of a crucifix submerged in urine seems calculated to offend.</p>
        <p>Until the Mapplethorpe-Serrano controversy, about the harshest words ever aimed at the Endowment during its 25 constructive years were ''too elitist'' or, conversely, ''too folksy.'' Suddenly, however, anyone unfamiliar with its remarkable record might have thought it a coven of pornographers.</p>
        <p>Suggestions for ''reform'' have ranged from restricting the contents of federally funded arts programs, a suggestion the Bush Administration commendably refused to endorse, to getting rid of the agency altogether. Last month an independent commission headed by John Brademas, a former Congressman and president of New York University, and Leonard Garment, a Washington lawyer, urged Congress not to impose restrictions on content.</p>
        <p>That recommendation has arrived in a considerably saner climate. The yearlong controversy has made the Endowment's worth evident to millions. Now Congress seems ready to be saner, too. In lieu of restrictive language, the House proposal suggests a preamble to the existing legislation declaring ''that the Government must be sensitive to the nature of public sponsorship.''</p>
        <p>The House then goes on to shift responsibility for deciding what is obscene from the Endowment to the courts, which is precisely where it belongs. In doing so, the House is both responding to those who fear that public money is funding smut and trusting to the wisdom and common sense of the Federal judiciary. Any artist found guilty of obscenity would have to return the money and be prohibited from receiving new Federal money for three years.</p>
        <p>The grant-making procedure would also be overhauled and presumably made more accountable. Whenever feasible, the artists' panels would be expanded to include knowledgeable lay people.</p>
        <p>The Senate proposal asks for a five-year, rather than a three-year, reauthorization of the Endowment; and its language on repaying grants for work judged obscene could apply to grants that have already been approved. But the bills are wholly similar in one respect. They shed welcome light on a dispute that for too long has degenerated into empty heat.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
