<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="390006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE6D61538F93AA35753C1A966958260" item-length="580" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>President Bush and Congressional leaders agreed on stopgap spending legislation that averted a suspension of most Government services. The agreement came shortly before the Senate adopted the broad outline of a budget identical to the one the House approved earlier in the day. [Page A1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>President Bush and Congressional leaders agreed on stopgap spending legislation that averted a suspension of most Government services. The agreement came shortly before the Senate adopted the broad outline of a budget identical to the one the House approved earlier in the day. [Page A1.</p>
        <p>THE ECONOMY</p>
        <p>President Bush and Congressional leaders agreed on stopgap spending legislation that averted a suspension of most Government services. The agreement came shortly before the Senate adopted the broad outline of a budget identical to the one the House approved earlier in the day. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>New York City's economic weakness and budgetary problems are starting to spill over into the financial markets, which may make it increasingly costly for the city government to issue bonds to raise funds for municipal operations. Professional investors sold more than $30 million of city bonds on Friday, traders said. [A1.]</p>
        <p>California voters will weigh steep new taxes on wine, beer and liquor to support alcohol-abuse and mental-health programs. [A23.]</p>
        <p>COMPANIES</p>
        <p>Three unions are expected to present to UAL's board an offer to buy the parent of United Airlines for about $160 a share, or a total of $3.5 billion. Of that, only about $70 a share will reportedly be in cash, while the rest will mostly be in notes secured by airplanes. [D1.]</p>
        <p>The nation's three leading long-distance carriers have sharply increased spending on advertising and other marketing this year. Recent television and print campaigns are becoming nastier. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Philips is developing a digital tape recorder that will also be able to play conventional analog cassette tapes, it announced. [D1.]</p>
        <p>Motorola and Hitachi reached a settlement in their dispute over chip patents. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Nordstrom's Paramus store appears to be off to a strong start in its first month, analysts and company executives say. [D17.]</p>
        <p>Dow Jones said its net income fell 17.5 percent in the third quarter as the acquisition of Telerate weighed on profits. [D19.]</p>
        <p>Continental Airlines ordered 25 new Boeing 757's, with an option for 25 more, in anticipation of long-term growth. [D4.]</p>
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>Although the pound jumped and London stocks soared in response to Britain's formal entry into the European Monetary System, some economists said the euphoria may be short-lived. [D1.]</p>
        <p>As Washington's diplomatic relations with Hanoi begin to thaw, the Administration is under increasing pressure to end a 15-year-old trade embargo. [D1.]</p>
        <p>A group of American experts has taken on Bulgaria's moribund economy and has drawn up a plan for transforming it. [D20.]</p>
        <p>MARKETS</p>
        <p>Oil prices moved up again on scattered military news in light trading, with crude up 96 cents, at $38.95 a barrel. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Stocks moved up in light trading after moving sharply higher at first on hopes of a break in the budget deadlock. The Dow gained 13.12, to 2,523.76. [D10.]</p>
        <p>Prices of Treasury securities dipped and interest rates rose slightly in thin trading overseas. [D20.]</p>
        <p>The British pound took center stage again in foreign exchange trading, while the dollar weakened. [D21.]</p>
        <p>Prices of soybean futures soared as much as 17 cents a bushel amid heavy speculative buying. [D21.]</p>
        <p>TODAY'S COLUMNS</p>
        <p>Support is growing for taxpayer-supported subsidies to help buy private health insurance for low-income people. Milt Freudenheim: Business and Health. [D2.]</p>
        <p>Problems at other insurers are probably less severe than at Travelers, analysts say. Market Place. [D10.]</p>
        <p>SportsChannel has found its first sponsor for high school sports broadcasts: Gatorade. Advertising. [D22.]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
