<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Behind the Asphalt Walls, Hopes and Heavy Burdens</title>
    <meta content="02pit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/02/movies/02pit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823143"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rulfo, Juan Carlos</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">In the Pit (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico/Baja California/Cabo San Lucas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Mexico</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Documentary Films and Programs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Cabo San Lucas (Mexico)</location>
        <object.title class="online_producer">In the Pit (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE1D8153FF931A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="671" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Behind the Asphalt Walls, Hopes and Heavy Burdens</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Behind the Asphalt Walls, Hopes and Heavy Burdens</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis reviews Juan Carlos Rulfo documentary film In the Pit; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Literally and existentially down and dirty, ''In the Pit'' is an absorbing documentary about work and the transformation of men into laborers. Directed and shot with sensitive attention to detail by Juan Carlos Rulfo, the film takes us into a world apart, populated by members of the construction crew building the second deck of the Periférico beltway in Mexico City. For the city's inhabitants, each of whom apparently spend an estimated 1,485 hours a year commuting, and mostly on public transportation, the construction is at once a nuisance and a possible solution. For the most part, like construction sites everywhere, it is also hidden in plain sight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rulfo takes a distinctly personal approach to his subject, eschewing issues of public policy, environmental impact or even much by way of factual information or history about the beltway. Instead he introduces us to a handful of men, most of whom work in the ground or high in the air, and one fatalistic woman, who helps move traffic through the beltway's completed areas and likes to talk about death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Literally and existentially down and dirty, “In the Pit” is an absorbing documentary about work and the transformation of men into laborers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Literally and existentially down and dirty, ''In the Pit'' is an absorbing documentary about work and the transformation of men into laborers. Directed and shot with sensitive attention to detail by Juan Carlos Rulfo, the film takes us into a world apart, populated by members of the construction crew building the second deck of the Periférico beltway in Mexico City. For the city's inhabitants, each of whom apparently spend an estimated 1,485 hours a year commuting, and mostly on public transportation, the construction is at once a nuisance and a possible solution. For the most part, like construction sites everywhere, it is also hidden in plain sight.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rulfo takes a distinctly personal approach to his subject, eschewing issues of public policy, environmental impact or even much by way of factual information or history about the beltway. Instead he introduces us to a handful of men, most of whom work in the ground or high in the air, and one fatalistic woman, who helps move traffic through the beltway's completed areas and likes to talk about death.</p>
        <p>Shooting with a digital camera, Mr. Rulfo sticks close to the workers, following them in and out of wide-yawning muddy holes, where they tease one another mercilessly as they claw through the earth. Their camaraderie feels touching and true, even if it seems at least partly predicated on communal survival.</p>
        <p>There are some singular personalities here, including the jovial Isabel Dolores Hernández, a small man with a saucy hitch in his walk who also seems on the move and, like most of the workers, has a work-site nickname, Chabelo. There's also José Guadalupe Calzada Placencia, or El Grande, who, as his moniker suggests, looms large on site and on screen. Given to bursts of harsh laughter, El Grande proves to be the film's sole shadowy figure, a man whose aggressiveness hides some uglier truths. As he does with all the workers, Mr. Rulfo fixes a cool eye on El Grande. When, during one offhand moment, he casually confesses to beating a family member, the filmmaker offers no comment; he just keeps the camera going as El Grande buries himself in words.</p>
        <p>There are other men with other words and from other worlds, most notably the impossibly romantic Vicencio Martínez Vázquez, who wears his luxurious long hair tied back when he's on the job, only to wear it loose around his shoulders when he's racing horses bareback. A single cut from the image of Mr. Vázquez in his construction clothes to a shot of him immaculately dressed in his cowboy costume speaks volumes about the private selves we keep tucked inside our workaday persona.</p>
        <p>Much like the film's knockout final image, an uninterrupted aerial shot of the beltway that seems to go on forever, a bird's-eye view of this heroically scaled project, Mr. Rulfo knows how to make images say much more than they might otherwise.</p>
        <p>Although he assumes the classic direct cinema, fly-on-the-wall approach for much of his film, Mr. Rulfo occasionally breaks with tradition and throws out a question at the men. These periodic inquiries and the intimacy of the camerawork make the film feel more personal than many documentaries, and over time you grow as aware of the man behind the camera as you become familiar with the men he's shooting (especially when both are hanging off some wincingly tall abutment). This individuated touch is also evident in Mr. Rulfo's rigorous specificity, his self-aware limitations. With ''In the Pit'' he isn't advancing any totalizing theory, a treatise on transportation or an argument about alienation; he is, rather simply and elegantly, revealing the secret human face of a seemingly inhuman world.</p>
        <p>In the Pit  Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Produced and directed by Juan Carlos Rulfo; in Spanish, with English subtitles; director of photography, Mr. Rulfo; edited by Valentina Leduc Navarro; music by Leonardo Heiblum; released by Kino International. At the Cinema Village, 22 East 12th Street, Greenwich Village. Running time: 84 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
