<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ariza Is Gone, but Trade Continues to Confound Knicks</title>
    <meta content="02ariza" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/02/sports/basketball/02ariza.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1823224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Orlando Magic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Beck, Howard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Orlando Magic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Ariza, Trevor</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Francis, Steve</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brown, Larry</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E5DF123FF931A35751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ariza Is Gone, but Trade Continues to Confound Knicks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ariza Is Gone, but Trade Continues to Confound Knicks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK; Viv Bernstein contributed reporting from Charlotte, N.C.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks prepare to face Orlando Magic; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Whatever goes wrong for the Knicks this weekend -- and something surely will, given their recent ill fate -- Coach Isiah Thomas will at least be spared one cringe. He will not have to see Trevor Ariza soaring over his team for a thunderous, momentum-altering dunk.</p>
        <p>Ariza earned his reputation as a frequent flier with the Knicks, who drafted him out of U.C.L.A. in 2004. But he was buried on the bench by Coach Larry Brown last season, then shipped to Orlando in a trade for Steve Francis, a three-time All-Star. That deal now looks like a steal for the Magic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trevor Ariza was buried on the bench by Knicks Coach Larry Brown last season, then shipped to Orlando in a trade for Steve Francis, a three-time All-Star. That deal now looks like a steal for the Magic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Whatever goes wrong for the Knicks this weekend -- and something surely will, given their recent ill fate -- Coach Isiah Thomas will at least be spared one cringe. He will not have to see Trevor Ariza soaring over his team for a thunderous, momentum-altering dunk.</p>
        <p>Ariza earned his reputation as a frequent flier with the Knicks, who drafted him out of U.C.L.A. in 2004. But he was buried on the bench by Coach Larry Brown last season, then shipped to Orlando in a trade for Steve Francis, a three-time All-Star. That deal now looks like a steal for the Magic.</p>
        <p>Ariza, 21, was blossoming into a key reserve before injuring his right knee Jan. 10. Francis has been alternately injured and ineffective. Neither player will be in uniform when the Knicks play tomorrow night in Orlando.</p>
        <p>''When I see Trevor, I'm going to give him a big hug and a kiss,'' said Thomas, who as team president drafted Ariza with the 43rd pick two and a half years ago. ''I'm happy that he's doing well.''</p>
        <p>Thomas called Ariza ''one of my favorite guys that I drafted'' and said he was ''extremely proud of him.''</p>
        <p>''I don't like that he's hurt,'' Thomas said, ''but I'm glad that he's hurt because we play them next.''</p>
        <p>Thomas has made a dizzying number of roster moves in the past three years, and most have been panned -- usually for the players the Knicks acquired, rather than the ones they gave up. But, pending the outcome of this June's draft (when Chicago can swap first-round picks with the Knicks), Ariza is probably the one player the Knicks will regret trading away.</p>
        <p>He is young and supremely athletic, the qualities Thomas touts the most. He is also a dedicated defender and a hard worker. His offense is limited but growing. Ariza spent last summer working on his jump shot, which Magic officials say is now reliable to 16 or 17 feet.</p>
        <p>''To me, Trevor has always had very good basketball instincts,'' Magic General Manager Otis Smith said. ''He's just pulling those things out of him.''</p>
        <p>Losing Ariza is only one reason why the Francis trade -- made at Brown's behest -- could be regarded as Thomas's worst deal. Consider the domino effect: After trading Ariza, the Knicks were desperate for an athletic small forward. So they drafted Renaldo Balkman with the 20th pick last June and passed on the gifted point guard Marcus Williams. The stated reason? Because they already had too many guards, a glut created when they acquired Francis. The Knicks later spent $30 million to sign small forward Jared Jeffries, who has been a bust.</p>
        <p>Thomas certainly would have made different decisions last summer if Ariza, and not Francis, were on the roster.</p>
        <p>Before spraining a knee ligament, Ariza was averaging 8.6 points with a .532 shooting percentage, 4.5 rebounds, 1.2 steals and 1.3 assists, playing only 23 minutes a game for Orlando. He scored in double figures in eight straight games from Dec. 20 to Jan. 5.</p>
        <p>A rangy 6 feet 8 inches, Ariza can defend four positions, and the Magic often assigns him to the opponent's best player. With a nose for the ball and great leaping ability, he is a superior offensive rebounder and nicely complements Dwight Howard, the Magic's gifted young center.</p>
        <p>''When he's on the floor with Dwight, their offensive rebounding is crazy,'' Smith said.</p>
        <p>Ariza has always thrived in the open court, but with a reliable jumper, ''He's going to be scary,'' Smith said.</p>
        <p>Ariza said he used visualization techniques as he worked on his jumper in the off-season, imagining himself shooting against every guard and small forward in the league.</p>
        <p>''I just kind of went back to my childhood,'' Ariza said in a recent telephone interview. ''I always imagined myself going up against Reggie Miller, Michael Jordan, guys like that, and I had to make the shot to win the game.''</p>
        <p>Ariza has adopted the number of another childhood idol, Penny Hardaway, who was traded with him in the Francis deal. (Hardaway was immediately waived.) With Hardaway's blessing, Ariza wears No. 1, Hardaway's number during his six years in Orlando. ''That brings me a lot of joy,'' Ariza said.</p>
        <p>Ariza said he should be back next month and looked forward to playing at Madison Square Garden when the Magic visits March 26. When he last played there, for the Knicks, Ariza was being assailed by Brown as ''delusional'' during a disagreement about his role.</p>
        <p>''I learned a lot from that situation,'' Ariza said. ''I learned that no matter what you do, nothing's going to be given to you, and you always have to work for everything you get.''</p>
        <p>It was Brown who pushed to acquire Francis, which led to Ariza's unplanned exit. The Knicks had offered a package of Jamal Crawford and Maurice Taylor. But Smith was leery of their big contracts and he wanted Ariza.</p>
        <p>''Isiah fought me,'' said Smith, who made re-signing Ariza a priority last summer. ''I think the kid's going to be a special basketball player.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>Quentin Richardson (sprained elbow) practiced with the team yesterday and is expected to play tomorrow in Orlando.  Jared Jeffries is listed as day to day after bruising his lower back in Wednesday's road loss against the Charlotte Bobcats.  Stephon Marbury (sore left knee) participated in noncontact drills and is expected to play tomorrow.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
