<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Handymen and -women Achieve Domestic Tranquillity</title>
    <meta content="CNCLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1259228"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DF1F38F932A05751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="795" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Handymen and -women Achieve Domestic Tranquillity</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SOUNDS that are disturbing, loud and obtrusive are not only unpleasant but can produce adverse physical and psychological side effects. Noise is as much an environmental pollutant as dust, lead powder or any other airborne contaminant.</p>
        <p>Sound waves are readily transmitted through rigid materials. Hard, solid materials, like wood, metal or wallboard, transmit and sometimes amplify sound, while soft materials like fabric or foam absorb the vibrations and stop sound from traveling.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SOUNDS that are disturbing, loud and obtrusive are not only unpleasant but can produce adverse physical and psychological side effects. Noise is as much an environmental pollutant as dust, lead powder or any other airborne contaminant.</p>
        <p>Sound waves are readily transmitted through rigid materials. Hard, solid materials, like wood, metal or wallboard, transmit and sometimes amplify sound, while soft materials like fabric or foam absorb the vibrations and stop sound from traveling.</p>
        <p>There are two basic types of sound: airborne and structure borne. Airborne sound is generated from a source, like a loud television or stereo, and transmitted through the air. In most cases it affects only the people who are in the same room with the source.</p>
        <p>Structure-borne sound is produced when airborne sound strikes a structural element, like a wall, floor, ceiling or duct. The impact of the sound waves causes the material to vibrate and transmit the sound to other areas.</p>
        <p>Not all noises in the house can be eliminated. This is just as well, because research shows that most people feel more comfortable in an environment with low-level sounds, commonly called ''"white noise.'' But many harsh or annoying sounds can be reduced or at least dampened. Most household noise is a combination of airborne and structure-borne sounds. There are two strategies for diminishing the amount of noise in the home: controlling it at the source and blocking its transmission to other areas.</p>
        <p>Appliances like washing machines, dryers, refrigerators, air-conditioners and ventilating fans produce the most noise. Usually these noises are caused by loose parts that vibrate excessively. Tightening the components so they are secure in the housing will usually eliminate the problem. A vibrating appliance, like a washing machine, can also generate structure-borne sound if it is in direct contact with a structural element like a wall.</p>
        <p>Appliances should be isolated so they are not in contact with nearby walls. You can also purchase sound-deadening kits for this purpose from an appliance dealer or manufacturer. These kits contain rubber mounting pads that absorb vibrations before they can be transmitted to the floor or walls.</p>
        <p>It is also possible to insulate the rooms in which noise is produced. This is a good strategy for rooms with entertainment systems. In these rooms, sound emanating from the speakers strikes the walls, floors and ceiling and is transmitted through the structure to other parts of the house. By placing sound-absorbing materials on these surfaces, you can contain the sound in the room.</p>
        <p>Lay a thick carpet pad and carpeting on the floor. Hang soft coverings, like tapestries, on the walls and install acoustical tile on the ceiling. You can mount the tile directly to the ceiling, but you will achieve better results if you hang the tile in a framework from the ceiling (this is commonly called a suspended ceiling). The tile panels should be a least three-quarters of an inch thick and have a noise reduction coefficient rating of .65. For extra sound-proofing, fill the space above the suspended ceiling with unfaced fiberglass insulation that is at least three inches thick.</p>
        <p>Other irritating household noises can be traced to the plumbing system. A common, and annoying, plumbing noise is called water hammer. Water hammer is a loud banging noise that occurs when you close a faucet or when an appliance, like a washing machine, shuts off. The noise is generated when the water moving under pressure through the pipes suddenly comes to a stop as the valve closes. The water then slams into the sides of the pipe and the valve. This causes the pipes to rattle against nearby framing and it produces a loud bang.</p>
        <p>You can sometimes correct the problem by anchoring the pipes to nearby framing members with metal straps. This will prevent them from rattling as the water passes through. If the hammer persists, install water-hammer arresters near the fixtures. A water-hammer arrester is a device with a closed air chamber. The air inside the chamber acts as a damper that absorbs and cushions the shock of the moving water.</p>
        <p>In cases where the noise problem is especially acute it may be necessary to modify the structures within the house to eliminate noise transmission. There is also the problem of noise that comes from the outside environment. These topics will be discussed next week.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
