<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ignoring the Smoke and Mirrors Used by Fund Managers</title>
    <meta content="31STRA$09" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/31/business/31STRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1259332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="STRATEGIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hulbert, Mark</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Strategies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001231T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E7DF173BF932A05751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="702" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ignoring the Smoke and Mirrors Used by Fund Managers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK HULBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hulbert, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mark Hulbert article warns of mutual fund managers who cite in advertisements only those market averages against which they compare most favorably; notes range between best- and worst-performing market averages is particularly wide this year; cites ways to determine most appropriate benchmarks for judging fund performance; graphs (M)t</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ONE way advertisers put a positive spin on the track records of money managers is by picking and choosing among myriad market averages until they find one against which the managers compare favorably. With so many indexes to choose from, it is little wonder that -- like all the children in Lake Woebegon -- all managers appear to be above average.</p>
        <p>While you should always be on guard against this practice, be particularly so over the next several weeks, as you study the performance of managers for 2000. The range between the returns of the best-  and the worst-performing stock market averages is wider than it has been in years. Even dismal performers can appear to have performed creditably, at the least.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ONE way advertisers put a positive spin on the track records of money managers is by picking and choosing among myriad market averages until they find one against which the managers compare favorably. With so many indexes to choose from, it is little wonder that -- like all the children in Lake Woebegon -- all managers appear to be above average.</p>
        <p>While you should always be on guard against this practice, be particularly so over the next several weeks, as you study the performance of managers for 2000. The range between the returns of the best-  and the worst-performing stock market averages is wider than it has been in years. Even dismal performers can appear to have performed creditably, at the least.</p>
        <p>Unless you are on the lookout for the practice, for example, you may not object to an advertisement that compares a manager's performance with the that of the Nasdaq composite. But it is an appropriate benchmark only if the manager focuses only on the few growth stocks -- mostly Internet issues -- that dominate the index.</p>
        <p>Consider the investment newsletters tracked by the Hulbert Financial Digest monitoring service, only a few of which focus on such stocks. Not surprisingly, more than 90 percent of them did better in 2000 than the Nasdaq, which ended the year down 39.3 percent. So either newsletter editors suddenly became geniuses in 2000, or the Nasdaq was not the appropriate benchmark to use to judge their performances.</p>
        <p>It is easier to identify which market averages are inappropriate comparisons than it is to pick the one that is best. In 2000 (through Dec. 28), especially among small-cap companies, there was an extraordinary spread between growth and value stocks.</p>
        <p>According to the Frank Russell Company, an investment adviser in Tacoma, Wash., small-cap growth companies -- as measured by the Russell 2000 Growth index -- lost 20.2 percent; small-cap value companies -- as measured by the Russell 2000 Value index -- gained 24.8 percent. That is a spread of nearly 45 percentage points.</p>
        <p>For large-cap stocks, the spread, while not quite as huge, was also big -- 28 percentage points, as measured by the Russell 1000 Value and Growth indexes.</p>
        <p>When evaluating performance, those four Russell indexes, while not the only decent benchmarks from which you can choose, are as good a place to start as any. Here is how you should go about determining which of the four is the most appropriate benchmark for judging how your equity portfolio performed during 2000:</p>
        <p>* First, determine whether your portfolio focuses more on large- or a small-cap issues, using the definitions for Russell's indexes as your guide. The median market value of the stocks in Russell's large-cap index is $3.8 billion, which means that half the stocks in that index are larger than this, with the other half smaller. The median market value of Russell's small-cap index is $428 million.</p>
        <p>* Next, determine whether your portfolio is more oriented toward growth or toward value. The indicator most commonly used to differentiate growth from value is the ratio of a company's price to its per-share book value. Among large-cap companies, the median price-to-book ratio is around 3.3. For small-caps, in contrast, it is about 2.2. If the number falls above the median, you should compare your portfolio with the growth indexes; if below, to value indexes.</p>
        <p>If you invest in mutual funds rather than individual stocks, use reference services like Morningstar, the fund research firm in Chicago. Morningstar reports the average market-cap and price-to-book ratio for each stock fund it follows.</p>
        <p>There is no need for you to be exact when following these rules of thumb. Because you are merely determining your portfolio's overall emphasis, estimates are just as helpful. But I urge you to go through the exercise. If you do not, you run the risk of concluding that an adviser beat the market in 2000 when in fact he or she lagged it badly -- and overlooking another adviser whose relative performance was quite impressive.</p>
        <p>STRATEGIES Mark Hulbert is editor of The Hulbert Financial Digest, a newsletter based in Annandale, Va. His column on investment strategies appears every other week.  E-mail: strategy@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mark Hulbert is editor of The Hulbert Financial Digest, a newsletter based in Annandale, Va. His column on investment strategies appears every other week.
&lt;br&gt;E-mail: strategy@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
