<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Why Risk Start Now, Needlessly?</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="342909"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMS CONTROL AND LIMITATION AND DISARMAMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Arms Control and Limitation and Disarmament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900412T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D91F39F931A25757C0A966958260" item-length="607" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Why Risk Start Now, Needlessly?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: At the eleventh hour, Washington and Moscow have introduced ill-timed complications into their strategic arms reduction talks. Both sides are now reaching for a lot more than they can quickly resolve. Maybe they believe they're doing the right thing, though belatedly. Maybe they're just bargaining or maneuvering for internal political reasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: At the eleventh hour, Washington and Moscow have introduced ill-timed complications into their strategic arms reduction talks. Both sides are now reaching for a lot more than they can quickly resolve. Maybe they believe they're doing the right thing, though belatedly. Maybe they're just bargaining or maneuvering for internal political reasons.</p>
        <p>At the eleventh hour, Washington and Moscow have introduced ill-timed complications into their strategic arms reduction talks. Both sides are now reaching for a lot more than they can quickly resolve. Maybe they believe they're doing the right thing, though belatedly. Maybe they're just bargaining or maneuvering for internal political reasons. Whatever the various motives, they're inviting needless risks.</p>
        <p>For his part, President Bush recently proposed banning mobile land-based missiles armed with multiple warheads. The principle of banning all multi-warhead missiles is sound. Such a ban would lessen the jitters of nuclear war planners. But Mr. Bush's specific proposal is too one-sided for the Soviets to accept. President Gorbachev, meanwhile, has backed away from recent concessions on cruise missiles. That's no way to negotiate, either.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush and Mr. Gorbachev share a powerful interest in putting the Start talks back on track to signature this year, as they previously pledged. Better to finish this treaty and then build on it in Start 2.</p>
        <p>As of now, Start 1 would reduce the existing long-range nuclear forces of both sides by about a third. Most important from an American perspective, it would require substantial cuts in some Soviet missiles with multiple warheads - the large SS-18's based in fixed silos. From Mr. Gorbachev's standpoint, the reductions required of the U.S. would make it easier for him to cut Soviet forces and transfer funds to domestic programs.</p>
        <p>Negotiations were proceeding smoothly until Mr. Bush last month proposed a ban on mobile land-based missiles with multiple warheads. This reversed a previous understanding to postpone the issue until Start 2, as well as the larger issue of banning all land-based missiles with multiple warheads. Banning multi-warhead missiles makes eminently good sense. If both sides had only single-warhead missiles that could each destroy no more than one opposing missile, there would be little to gain from shooting first.</p>
        <p>But the ban Mr. Bush proposes puts the burden almost entirely on the Soviets. They have mobile land-based missiles, which Mr. Bush would ban in Start 1. The United States does not. And if Start 2 extended the ban to missiles with multiple warheads in silos, as Mr. Bush also proposes, the impact on the Soviets would be even greater. That's because the Bush proposal makes no mention of multi-warhead missiles based at sea, where the U.S. enjoys a substantial lead.</p>
        <p>The one-sided character of President Bush's proposal may also account for the noticeable Soviet stiffening in talks last week. Regarding sea-launched cruise missiles, Moscow had agreed that both sides simply would declare the number they planned to build. Now the Soviets have renewed their insistence on legally binding limits. Moscow also stiffened its position on air-launched cruise missiles.</p>
        <p>It's not militarily necessary for either side to solve the multiple warhead or cruise missile problems in Start 1. Missiles with multiple warheads won't cause concern until reductions begin under Start 1. Neither will a few hundred cruise missiles. Then it will become extremely important to get further cuts in all multi-warhead missiles, land-based and sea-based. As to cruise missiles, both sides have to become more confident of their ability to verify tighter limits.</p>
        <p>It's forever tempting for the parties to try to correct possible shortcomings or gain marginal advantages late in a negotiation. But to do that now puts Start 1 in needless jeopardy. Mr. Bush and Mr. Gorbachev had the right idea months ago: to lock in this agreement and begin reducing forces.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
