<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reuters Buys Lipper Analytical To Expand Global Fund Reports</title>
    <meta content="Y24LIP$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1033975"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Lipper Analytical Services Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Reuters Holdings Plc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wyatt, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980724T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE4DB1239F937A15754C0A96E958260" item-length="400" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reuters Buys Lipper Analytical To Expand Global Fund Reports</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WYATT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wyatt, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Reuters Group PLC acquires Lipper Analytical Services Inc, mutual fund data company, for undisclosed amount of cash (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reuters Group P.L.C. announced yesterday that it had acquired Lipper Analytical Services Inc., the mutual fund data company, for an undisclosed cash amount.</p>
        <p>Lipper, founded in 1973, pioneered the business of providing detailed performance information on individual mutual funds and groups of funds with similar investment objectives. But more recently it has lagged behind competitors like Morningstar Inc. in marketing those data to the brokers and investment advisers who are the biggest sellers of mutual funds to individual investors.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reuters Group P.L.C. announced yesterday that it had acquired Lipper Analytical Services Inc., the mutual fund data company, for an undisclosed cash amount.</p>
        <p>Lipper, founded in 1973, pioneered the business of providing detailed performance information on individual mutual funds and groups of funds with similar investment objectives. But more recently it has lagged behind competitors like Morningstar Inc. in marketing those data to the brokers and investment advisers who are the biggest sellers of mutual funds to individual investors.</p>
        <p>In joining Reuters, Lipper will gain access to the capital required to update its technology and broaden its distribution, said Simon Thompson, currently marketing director for Reuters Europe, Middle East and Africa, who will take over as chief executive of Lipper Analytical. A. Michael Lipper, the founder and chairman of Lipper Analytical, will serve as chairman of the new Reuters unit.</p>
        <p>''We have the technological strength and financial resources to take Lipper forward in the larger global world of funds that is emerging,'' Mr. Thompson said. ''We also have ways of reaching users within the fund companies and, more importantly perhaps, private investors at home, in effective and attractive ways that simply were not possible before.''</p>
        <p>Reuters has extensive distribution capabilities, an ability absent at Lipper, whose data are available primarily in printed form or electronically over a dedicated computer terminal. Much more popular with brokers and financial advisers are products like Morningstar's Principia, a CD-ROM containing historical data and analysis on several thousand funds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lipper will devote about half his time to Lipper Analytical, which is based in Summit, N.J., and has 300 employees worldwide. The remainder of Mr. Lipper's time will go to three formerly affiliated businesses that were not purchased by Reuters.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson said that Lipper would be the cornerstone of the Reuters global fund-data business, which includes three recent European acquisitions: HSW, which provides performance data on funds and investment trusts marketed in the Britain; Bopp, which provides similar data on Swiss and German investment funds, and Citywatch, which distributes ownership information on shares of publicly traded British companies.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
