<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>States' Immunity From Suits Is Argued</title>
    <meta content="Y19SCO$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/19/national/19SCOT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1442037"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="Supreme Court Roundup"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Maryland</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenhouse, Linda</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">hason, michael j (dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">wiggins, kevin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Health Care Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Depression</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Maryland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Doctors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">States (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Depression (Mental)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Supreme Court (US)</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E5D91E30F93AA25752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>States' Immunity From Suits Is Argued</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">States' Immunity From Suits Is Argued</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Greenhouse, Linda</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supreme Court, in next step toward defining limits of Congressional power, agrees to decide whether states are immune from suits under Americans With Disabilities Act for failing to provide disabled people equal access to public services; accepts appeal by California of appeals court ruling granting trial under act to Dr Michael J Hason, who sued state medical board for refusing him license because of his mental illness; Hason argues he has been successfully treated for depression and drug dependency; court agrees to hear government appeal of ruling that lets advocacy groups organized as nonprofit corporations make direct campaign contributions in federal elections, despite federal ban on corporate contributions and independent expenditures; court accepts appeal by Maryland death-row inmate Kevin Wiggins that raises question of defense lawyer's duty to investigate and offer potentially mitigating evidence for why defendant should not be sentenced to death; Federal District Court overturned death sentence, but appeals court overturned that ruling on ground state court rulings that denied earlier appeals had been minimally adequate (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court took a long-anticipated next step today toward defining the limits of Congressional power when it agreed to decide whether states are immune from suit for failing to provide equal access to public services by people with disabilities.</p>
        <p>The justices accepted an appeal by the State of California, which had argued unsuccessfully before a federal appeals court that its state medical board was immune from suit under the Americans With Disabilities Act for refusing to give a mentally ill doctor a license to practice medicine.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court on Monday agreed to decide whether states are immune from suit for failing to provide equal access to public services by people with disabilities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court took a long-anticipated next step today toward defining the limits of Congressional power when it agreed to decide whether states are immune from suit for failing to provide equal access to public services by people with disabilities.</p>
        <p>The justices accepted an appeal by the State of California, which had argued unsuccessfully before a federal appeals court that its state medical board was immune from suit under the Americans With Disabilities Act for refusing to give a mentally ill doctor a license to practice medicine.</p>
        <p>Last year, the Supreme Court addressed a separate provision of the disabilities law in ruling that states were immune from disability discrimination suits brought by their own employees. That case, in turn, followed an earlier ruling that immunized states from age discrimination suits by their employees. The court has also shielded states from suits by their employees for violations of federal labor law. And later this term, the justices will decide whether states are immune from suits by their employees under the Family and Medical Leave Act.</p>
        <p>The new case, Medical Board of California v. Hason, No. 02-479, significantly expands the potential impact of the court's federalism revolution. The universe of those who could be affected by the decision goes beyond state employees to include the millions of Americans with disabilities, in whose behalf the law was passed with broad bipartisan support in 1990.</p>
        <p>At issue is the application to the states of the disability act's Title II, which provides that people with disabilities shall not be discriminated against or ''be excluded from participation in or be denied the benefits of the services, programs, or activities of a public entity.''</p>
        <p>The number of activities covered by Title II is vast, including voting, education, public transportation and conditions of confinement in public institutions for people with mental or physical disabilities. Congress explicitly expressed its intent to abrogate the immunity the states would otherwise enjoy under the 11th Amendment, which the court has interpreted as generally barring suits against states in federal court.</p>
        <p>The plaintiff in the new case, Michael J. Hason, is arguing that he has been successfully treated for depression and drug dependency and should not be denied a medical license on the basis of his medical history. The Federal District Court in Los Angeles dismissed his case and the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit, in San Francisco, reinstated it, with no trial yet having taken place.</p>
        <p>Beyond its practical impact, the new case is also highly significant as a matter of constitutional doctrine. It tests the full dimension of the rule the court has established in its recent federalism cases, all by a narrow 5-to-4 majority, that Congress cannot validly breach the states' 11th Amendment immunity without first compiling extensive evidence that the states have been committing constitutional violations that lie within the authority of Congress to correct.</p>
        <p>Critics of the federalism rulings have asserted that the court has set a standard that ignores the reality of life in a legislature. Given that the majority is highly unlikely to retreat from that standard, the question in this case is how the five justices -- Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist and Justices Sandra Day O'Connor, Anthony M. Kennedy, Antonin Scalia, and Clarence Thomas -- will respond to the fact that during years of hearings leading up the law's passage in 1990, Congress did document a long history of denials by the states of access to public services by individuals with disabilities.</p>
        <p>In his majority opinion last year in Board of Trustees v. Garrett, the case that barred disability suits by state employees, Chief Justice Rehnquist in fact contrasted the sparse record of employment discrimination by the states -- governed by Title I of the law -- with evidence Congress had compiled of state conduct that violated Title II, which was not at issue in that case.</p>
        <p>The chief justice said the ''overwhelming majority'' of the incidents cited by Justice Stephen G. Breyer, one of the dissenters, ''pertain to alleged discrimination by the states in the provision of public services and public accommodations.''</p>
        <p>One interesting aspect of the court's action today was the justices' treatment of the federal government's request to participate in the case. In a motion filed last month, Solicitor General Theodore B. Olson told the court that the government had not been aware of the existence of the case until California filed its appeal, and asked for a chance to formulate and express the government's views before the court acted in the case. The solicitor general's office, which has strongly defended the Americans With Disabilities Act, had successfully persuaded the court not to accept earlier cases raising the immunity issue under Title II.</p>
        <p>While the court granted Mr. Olson's motion today, it also granted the California appeal without waiting to hear from the federal government. One possible explanation is that waiting for the government's brief might have required the court to defer consideration of the case for several months, meaning that a grant of review would have come too late for the case to be scheduled for argument during the current term.</p>
        <p>The case will be argued in late March.</p>
        <p>California's appeal also raised the narrower issue of whether issuing a medical license is the kind of public service to which the law applies. However, the court denied review on that question, indicating its desire to address the broader issue.</p>
        <p>There were also the following developments at the court today:</p>
        <p>Campaign Speech</p>
        <p>The justices agreed to hear a government appeal of a ruling that permitted advocacy groups organized as nonprofit corporations to make direct campaign contributions in federal elections, despite a longstanding federal ban on corporate contributions and independent expenditures.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court ruled in 1986 that the ban on independent expenditures could not constitutionally be applied to nonprofit advocacy corporations, drawing a distinction between business corporations organized for profit and groups that exist to take political positions. The question in the new case, Federal Election Commission v. Beaumont, No. 02-403, is whether that distinction requires, as a matter of the First Amendment right to free speech, that advocacy groups also be free to make direct contributions.</p>
        <p>The United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit, in Richmond, Va., held that an anti-abortion group, North Carolina Right to Life Inc., had a First Amendment right to contribute directly to campaigns.</p>
        <p>The case will be argued in March, putting it almost certainly ahead of the anticipated argument on the constitutionality of the new McCain-Feingold campaign finance law, which a special three-judge federal court here will review next month. The two cases are not directly related, but the justices' approach to the North Carolina case could indicate the court's willingness to abide by its longstanding distinction between expenditures and contributions.</p>
        <p>Death Penalty Appeal</p>
        <p>The court accepted an appeal by a Maryland death-row inmate that raises the question of a defense lawyer's obligation to investigate and present potentially mitigating evidence for why a defendant should not be sentenced to death.</p>
        <p>Kevin Wiggins, a first-time offender convicted on circumstantial evidence of the 1988 murder of an elderly woman in her apartment, was given two defense lawyers, neither of whom presented any mitigating evidence to the jury. The Federal District Court in Baltimore found that Mr. Wiggins had been denied the effective assistance of counsel, granting a writ of habeas corpus and overturning the death sentence. But the Fourth Circuit overturned that ruling on the ground that the state court rulings that denied his earlier appeals had been minimally adequate. His appeal, Wiggins v. Corcoran, No. 02-311, now argues that the Fourth Circuit had ignored Supreme Court precedents requiring more searching scrutiny of state court rulings.</p>
        <p>Supreme Court Roundup</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
