<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="726182"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E6DE1031F93BA25752C1A962958260" item-length="925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>N.B.A.  Rockets Pound Bulls  Hakeem Olajuwon's 29 points and Kenny Smith's 3-point shooting led Houston to a 106-83 victory over the visiting Chicago Bulls last night, extending the Rockets' season-opening winning streak to eight. The Rockets also have a 22-game November winning streak over the last two seasons. They were 14-0 a year ago in November when they won their first 15 games, tying a National Basketball Association record. They are 8-0 this year. Olajuwon dominated the inside from start to finish, and Smith, who finished with 19 points, was 4 of 6 on 3-point shots, including 2 in an early fourth-quarter run when the Rockets took command. (AP) Mavericks 96, Kings 94: Mavericks forward Roy Tarpley had 16 points and 9 rebounds in his return to the N.B.A., and Lucious Harris's 8-foot bank shot with 59 seconds remaining gave Dallas a 96-94 victory over visiting Sacramento. Tarpley played in his first N.B.A. game since he was dismissed by the league for violating its anti-drug regulations Oct. 16, 1991. Tarpley was activated from the injured list on Wednesday after missing the season's first five games with bursitis in his left knee. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>N.B.A.  Rockets Pound Bulls  Hakeem Olajuwon's 29 points and Kenny Smith's 3-point shooting led Houston to a 106-83 victory over the visiting Chicago Bulls last night, extending the Rockets' season-opening winning streak to eight. The Rockets also have a 22-game November winning streak over the last two seasons. They were 14-0 a year ago in November when they won their first 15 games, tying a National Basketball Association record. They are 8-0 this year. Olajuwon dominated the inside from start to finish, and Smith, who finished with 19 points, was 4 of 6 on 3-point shots, including 2 in an early fourth-quarter run when the Rockets took command. (AP) Mavericks 96, Kings 94: Mavericks forward Roy Tarpley had 16 points and 9 rebounds in his return to the N.B.A., and Lucious Harris's 8-foot bank shot with 59 seconds remaining gave Dallas a 96-94 victory over visiting Sacramento. Tarpley played in his first N.B.A. game since he was dismissed by the league for violating its anti-drug regulations Oct. 16, 1991. Tarpley was activated from the injured list on Wednesday after missing the season's first five games with bursitis in his left knee. (AP)</p>
        <p>Hornets, 99, Clippers 83: Larry Johnson and Dell Curry had 19 points each to lead host Charlotte over Los Angeles, which equaled the worst start in club history. By losing their first seven games, the Clippers matched the 1982-83 San Diego Clippers, who also began the season 0-7 before earning a victory against San Antonio in their eighth game. (AP) Pistons 94, Nuggets 92: Terry Mills hit a 20-foot jump shot at the buzzer to lift Detroit over host Denver, snapping the Nuggets' four-game winning streak. With his 21 points, Detroit's Joe Dumars became the 124th player in N.B.A. history to score 12,000 points. Bryant Stith scored 22 points for the Nuggets. Mills finished with 20 points. The rookie Grant Hill was limited to 13 points, the first time he didn't score at least 20 points in a game for the Pistons. (AP) Cavaliers 81, Trail Blazers 80: Mark Price scored 30 points, 15 of them on 3-pointers, as Cleveland handed Portland its second straight loss at home. (AP) COLLEGE BASKETBALL  Seton Hall Women Fall  Melissa Wuschnig scored 15 of her career-high 23 points in the first half as Washington beat Seton Hall, 84-72, last night in the quarterfinals of the women's Preseason N.I.T. in Seattle. Seton Hall, ranked No. 22 by The Associated Press, cut Washington's lead to 5 with 3:35 remaining, but Wuschnig's steal and driving layup capped a 9-2 Washington run that put the game away.</p>
        <p>Rukaiyah Walker scored 15 points for Seton Hall before fouling out with 8:48 left in the game.</p>
        <p>In other women's Preseason N.I.T. games last night: Connie Robinson scored 16 points, 14 in the second half, to lead Texas Tech to a 79-51 victory over Arkansas State in Lubbock, Tex.; Vanderbilt earned a semifinal date against Texas Tech by edging Montana, 69-65; and Charitee Longstreth led three players in double figures with 13 points as Southwest Missouri State topped Virginia Tech, 61-45, in Springfield, Mo. Southwest Missouri and Washington will meet in the other semifinal, with both games scheduled Sunday. (AP) N.I.T.: Teams Advance  Gerald Walker scored 24 points and San Francisco used a 12-0 run at the start of the second half last night to beat New Mexico, 80-74, in the first round of the Preseason National Invitational Tournament at Albuquerque, N.M. The game was the season opener for the teams with San Francisco advancing to the quarterfinals at Memphis, which defeated Southwestern Louisiana, 70-66, last night on its home court. David Vaughn scored 17 points and grabbed 13 rebounds to lead the Memphis attack. San Francisco and Memphis will meet Saturday night. (AP) GYMNASTICS  Russia Enters Finals  Russia proved yesterday that its days as a men's gymnastic power aren't over by leading six teams into the finals at the World Gymnastics Team Championships in Dortmund, Germany. Russia, relying on only one 1992 Olympian gold medalist, Aleksei Voropayev, bounced back from a fourth-place finish in Tuesday's compulsories to capture yesterday's optionals. With a combined score of 560.034 points, the Russians bumped surprising Germany into second place over all at 557.986.</p>
        <p>China, silver medalist at the 1992 Olympics, also reached the final by finishing third over all, followed by the Ukraine, Belarus and Japan. The United States, with only two Olympians on the squad, ended up ninth and failed to reach the finals. (AP) HIGH SCHOOL FOOTBALL  Massapequa Romps  Jim Chase ran for one touchdown and teamed with Mike Sheridan on five pass completions for 136 yards and another touchdown as Massapequa routed Farmingdale, 26-0, in the Nassau County Conference I semifinals last night at Hofstra University. The touchdown pass, which came in the first period, was a 49-yard play off a reverse. "We've run that play a lot in practice this year but never in a game," said Chase, who also ran for another score. "The idea is to suck the defense in and then go long."</p>
        <p>Said Sheridan: "It worked perfectly. Farmingdale bit and Jimmy put it where I could catch it."</p>
        <p>Tom Santuro ran for second-half touchdowns of 22 and 6 yards for Massapequa, which shut out Farmingdale, 21-0, in the regular-season finale last Saturday. Massapequa will play Lawrence next Thursday at C. W. Post. Lawrence, led by Vaughn Sanders, who scored 4 rushing touchdowns, defeated Freeport, 31-28, in the other semifinal game.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
