<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>World Tour Steps Up To First Tee vs. PGA</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="726204"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WORLD TOUR (GOLF)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DORMAN, LARRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORMAN, GREG</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD1031F93BA25752C1A962958260" item-length="719" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>World Tour Steps Up To First Tee vs. PGA</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY DORMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DORMAN, LARRY</byline>
      <dateline>THOUSAND OAKS, Calif., Nov. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Oozing the same Aussie bravado and cocksure bearing that he brings to the golf course, Greg Norman took to the dais here today to assure the world that the proposed World Tour is no longer a proposal, but a reality.</p>
        <p>Undaunted by a cool reception to the idea from some top American players on the PGA Tour, and despite the fact that specific sponsors, sites and players have yet to be named, Norman proclaimed that the eight-tournament, $25 million series with fields of the top 30 players in the world would begin in 1995 at sites in the United States, Canada, Scotland, Spain and Japan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Oozing the same Aussie bravado and cocksure bearing that he brings to the golf course, Greg Norman took to the dais here today to assure the world that the proposed World Tour is no longer a proposal, but a reality.</p>
        <p>Undaunted by a cool reception to the idea from some top American players on the PGA Tour, and despite the fact that specific sponsors, sites and players have yet to be named, Norman proclaimed that the eight-tournament, $25 million series with fields of the top 30 players in the world would begin in 1995 at sites in the United States, Canada, Scotland, Spain and Japan.</p>
        <p>"This is fantastic," Norman said. "It's something that's been in my heart for the past seven years. All along, it's been a dream of mine, as an international player to play against the best players in the world, week in and week out. Now that's going to be possible."</p>
        <p>The new World Tour, which will be underwritten in part and televised by the Fox Television Network, will offer $600,000 to tournament winners and guarantee at least $30,000 for last place. It also will pay a $1 million bonus to the player of the year and will give a $50,000 travel allowance to each player who signs up for the series.</p>
        <p>But significant hurdles remain if the World Tour is to commence play -- at a site to be named in South Florida the week of March 30-April 2 -- directly before the Masters and directly opposite the Freeport-McMoRan Classic in New Orleans.</p>
        <p>Opposition from the PGA Tour is certain. Tim Finchem, commissioner of the PGA Tour, has said he will not grant releases to PGA Tour members to play in conflicting events, and he will attempt to block the telecasts by invoking the PGA Tour's TV release rules.</p>
        <p>"Anything we do, we want to do in cooperation with the PGA Tour," said John Montgomery Jr., who resigned his position at Executive Sports Inc., a tournament management company, to become the executive director of the World Tour. "We're not looking for a fight with anyone. That would be counterproductive."</p>
        <p>But a fight is a virtual certainty. Finchem, who won't comment further until he addresses a meeting at the 1995 Golf Summit on Saturday in Phoenix, is under pressure on two fronts, and isn't expected to back down.</p>
        <p>First, he must assuage the fears of the American Golf Sponsors, who underwrote the 41 official Tour events and seven unofficial events to the tune of $82 million in 1994. They are unnerved at the prospect of top players absenting themselves for eight tournaments and playing in events that directly compete with the PGA Tour for television exposure. Finchem is also dealing with an continuing Federal Trade Commission investigation into tour practices, specifically television releases and the conflicting-events rule that forces players to obtain releases to play in competing tournaments overseas.</p>
        <p>Then there is the matter of attracting top United States players to sign up for the World Tour. Reaction from foreign players has been extremely favorable. Norman received a fax of support from the Masters champion, Jose Maria Olazabal, and spoke at length with Seve Ballesteros, who also expressed support. Reports on player reaction in the European press from this week's tournament site at Japan have been glowing.</p>
        <p>But even Nick Price, Norman's best friend and the No. 1-ranked player in the world, issued his support with a caveat.</p>
        <p>"He has my total support as long as my position on the PGA Tour isn't challenged," Price said.</p>
        <p>And an informal survey of American players here revealed a sense of uncertainty, both about the viability of the World Tour and its potential adverse impact on the PGA Tour. The Ryder Cup captain, Lanny Wadkins, said he wasn't opposed to the concept, "but you can't just go dumping on the people who supported you all these years and put you where you are to begin with."</p>
        <p>Curtis Strange, a two-time United States Open winner and still a marquee player, agreed. "The scary part is that we could end up in court and the last thing I want to do is be suing my own organization," he said.</p>
        <p>Norman said he would play in 15 PGA tour events and 8 World Tour events in 1995. He believes that he will be joined by the best of the best, and said Jack Nicklaus and Ray Floyd and Arnold Palmer, "the icons of game" will join the fields on sponsors exemptions.  GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
