<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Is It Time For Smaller New League?</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="726221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED BASEBALL LEAGUE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7DC1031F93BA25752C1A962958260" item-length="717" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Is It Time For Smaller New League?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE rumbling comes closer together now. The world of sports is going through financial tremors unlike anything we have ever seen before -- strikes and shortfalls, power plays and dead seasons. Where will it end?</p>
        <p>Things happen on a daily basis now. Baseball will never recover from canceling its 1994 season. Hockey is destroying its once-promising future. The owners in both sports cannot convince people they just might be telling the truth about the ledgers they will not display.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE rumbling comes closer together now. The world of sports is going through financial tremors unlike anything we have ever seen before -- strikes and shortfalls, power plays and dead seasons. Where will it end?</p>
        <p>Things happen on a daily basis now. Baseball will never recover from canceling its 1994 season. Hockey is destroying its once-promising future. The owners in both sports cannot convince people they just might be telling the truth about the ledgers they will not display.</p>
        <p>"And you have the nerve to tell me, over and over and over again, you don't believe we're on the eve of destruction," rasped Barry McGuire on his apocalyptic '60's song, "Eve of Destruction."</p>
        <p>Yet in the midst of chaos, people still dare to dream. In the wake for the 1994 World Series that never happened, some people are plotting a new baseball league. A songbird chirps after the hurricane has passed through.</p>
        <p>This proposed new entity would be called the United Baseball League. A man named Bob Mrazek, a rational adult who was my congressman from Long Island for five terms, is trying to persuade us of the great and glorious day to come in 1996.</p>
        <p>"Suppose you had Howard Johnson hitting the ball over the fence for the Long Island Rough Riders," Mrazek said yesterday, talking about a population area of 2.5 million. "People have a real fondness for HoJo."</p>
        <p>I tried to envision this new league in regions unrepresented by the currently moribund major leagues. I tried to imagine a league based on modest investment, open books, revenue sharing, profit sharing, catching the middle-of-the-road players who became too expensive for the major leagues (Mrazek named Harold Reynolds and Jody Reed as examples).</p>
        <p>I tried to imagine a league ranging from Vancouver to Riverside-San Bernardino in California to Long Island to Mexico City. That stopped me right there. I love international travel as much as the next person, but I've covered baseball in Mexico City, and I have seen the dugouts fill up with rainwater.</p>
        <p>"The Aztec rain god is named Tlaloc," I said, hating to be the bearer of bad news. "Every night I was there, Tlaloc made it rain very hard, from 5 P.M. to 8 P.M. Sometimes they get the games in. Sometimes they don't." Bad drainage. I forgot to tell him the city is built on a lake.</p>
        <p>I hate to be the one to pour water on chirping songbirds, but that's my job. On the other hand, I worry about the Vince Colemans and Tom Henkes, who can't get callbacks from baseball general managers, who are operating on the blind human hope that the sport will resume.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, almost every sport seems to be shuddering at the foundation. The National Football League -- the last bastion of communism, sharing its television wealth equally -- grimly rumbles on. The National Basketball Association is on a one-year truce. The rest is anarchy.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the New York Racing Association confirmed rumors that it was tapped out. The sport of kings has become a legal stooper, bending to find a discarded winning ticket in the debris, in the state of the Belmonts and the Whitneys and the Vanderbilts. How dreary.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, officials announced that a major American soccer league would be postponed at least until 1996. Alan Rothenberg could not put together enough investors in the afterglow of the World Cup, the greatest sports event on the face of the earth. How gloomy.</p>
        <p>This week, women's tennis is holding its last Virginia Slims championship. A gracious and capable host but also a socially unacceptable sponsor -- cigarettes, bad health, bad air, bad manners, bad karma -- had to get out. Who's going to pay the next Evert, the next Navratilova? How sad.</p>
        <p>And professional golf is being riven by its own people. Some top golfers like Greg Norman are going along with the Fox television network's plans for a tour that would challenge the PGA Tour. Civil war in golf. Guys in yellow pants hitting guys in yellow pants with 4-irons. How delightful.</p>
        <p>Maybe it's all gotten too big. Maybe the baseball and hockey leagues deserve to perish from bad leadership and bad faith. Maybe we need newer, smaller, purer sports leagues. Baseball is still a great game to play and watch, when the owners and the players don't mess it up. Maybe Tlaloc wouldn't rain on the United Baseball League.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
