<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Think Globally, Listen Locally</title>
    <meta content="04WORL$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1173723"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pareles, Jon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE6DF103FF937A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="2957" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Think Globally, Listen Locally</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JON PARELES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pareles, Jon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jon Pareles Critic's Notebook offers second annual survey of world-music albums released in last year, as well as live performances of international music in Manhattan in next few months; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE world's music has never been more accessible, speeded to new ears by everything from jet travel to the Internet. And the whole world comes to New York: if not in person, then through its songs. Onstage or on CD's, music from far-flung places offers easy transport to distant lands and times. The Babel of different musical languages promises not strife but diverse pleasures, available amazingly close to home.</p>
        <p>This is the second annual survey of world-music albums released in the last year. But this weekend is also an unusually strong one for live performances of international music. A gala concert tomorrow night at Town Hall celebrates the 15th anniversary of the World Music Institute, which has combed the globe to produce concerts of worthwhile music rooted in local traditions. The gala concert includes music from India, Morocco, Uganda, Iran, China, the Middle East and New York, with a lineup featuring violinists: Kayhan Kalhor from Iran; Shankar from India; Simon Shaheen, an Arab oud and violin player; and David Harrington from the Kronos String Quartet.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE world's music has never been more accessible, speeded to new ears by everything from jet travel to the Internet. And the whole world comes to New York: if not in person, then through its songs. Onstage or on CD's, music from far-flung places offers easy transport to distant lands and times. The Babel of different musical languages promises not strife but diverse pleasures, available amazingly close to home.</p>
        <p>This is the second annual survey of world-music albums released in the last year. But this weekend is also an unusually strong one for live performances of international music. A gala concert tomorrow night at Town Hall celebrates the 15th anniversary of the World Music Institute, which has combed the globe to produce concerts of worthwhile music rooted in local traditions. The gala concert includes music from India, Morocco, Uganda, Iran, China, the Middle East and New York, with a lineup featuring violinists: Kayhan Kalhor from Iran; Shankar from India; Simon Shaheen, an Arab oud and violin player; and David Harrington from the Kronos String Quartet.</p>
        <p>An international lineup also appears tomorrow night at the annual Tibet House Benefit Concert at Carnegie Hall, where regulars like Philip Glass and Patti Smith are to share the stage with Gomang monks from Tibet, the ethereal Brazilian soprano Virginia Rodrigues, the West African pop spark plug Angelique Kidjo (from Benin) and the Canadian fiddler Ashley MacIsaac, who plays Celtic music with a punk rocker's fury.</p>
        <p>The Center for Traditional Music and Dance is recreating the traditional festivities of Jews from the Caucasus Mountains, where Russian and Persian culture met. Its third annual ''Nashi Traditsii (Our Traditions),'' a concert of music and dance along with a banquet, takes over the Atlantic Oceana Restaurant in the Russian kitsch belt of Brighton Beach, Brooklyn, on Sunday night.</p>
        <p>Argentina is sending its cultural representatives, including musicians, for a series at the World Financial Center that began this week and runs through March 26. And the annual birthday tribute to Bob Marley of Jamaica, who gave hope and direction to musicians across the third world, takes place tomorrow night at Irving Plaza.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, companies of all sizes continue to release world-music albums, in an anarchic jumble of scholarly ethnomusicology, non-Western classical styles, informed compilations, imported pop releases and hodgepodge surveys. And the musicians, who aren't exactly primitives, are also coming up with border-crossing collaborations like Ghazal, Mr. Kayhor's group with the Indian sitar player Shujaat Khan. The group reunites Persian and Indian classical styles, both based on melodic modes and rhythmic cycles.</p>
        <p>After the million-selling success of ''Buena Vista Social Club'' (whose headliners Ibrahim Ferrer and Ruben Gonzalez have sold out their concerts this weekend at the Beacon Theater), there has been a flood of releases of music from Cuba. And the last year has seen the rise of ethnomusicologists treated as auteurs. Rounder Records has been releasing a series of recordings made on excursions by Alan Lomax in the United States and abroad, as he worried that ''our barbarous centralized culture is now destroying this ancient treasury of musical traditions.''</p>
        <p>Smithsonian Folkways has just finished releasing a 20-CD series of music from Indonesia recorded by Philip Yampolsky; and Stern's Africa is importing a series of albums recorded in the 1950's by Hugh Tracey, who documented African music soon to be destroyed or transformed by political upheavals and the electric guitar.</p>
        <p>Large stores like Tower, HMV and Virgin now stock good selections of world music. The World Music Institute (www.heartheworld.org) also has an impressive catalog of traditional and traditionalist music, which it sells by mail, at concerts and from its office at 49 West 27th Street in Manhattan (212-545-7536).</p>
        <p>What follows is a selection of rewarding world-music albums from the last year: just a limited sampling from a world of song. (CD's range in price from $15 for a single disc to $25 each for some imports.)</p>
        <p>Albania</p>
        <p>Tirana is an unaccompanied choir of six men and one woman, dedicated to preserving ancient songs from Albania's minorities. Performing songs from various regions, it's a professional group that uses robust, polished harmony as a symbol of cultural survival. On its album ''Xhevhir'' (Arco Iris import), there are sustained, close-harmony songs similar to Bulgarian choral music, with Irini Qirjako's sobbing, determined voice answered by the men. There are also uptempo songs in ebullient major chords that sound something like tarantellas. Although the performances are far removed from what were probably more rough-hewn originals, they maintain a tenacious spirit.</p>
        <p>Brazil</p>
        <p>For Brazilian musicians there has never been a barrier between the traditional and the modern. They can draw at will on old parade rhythms, new harmonies and newer gadgets. Os Mutantes, pioneers in the surreal late-60's Brazilian hybrid called tropicalia, finally had an American greatest-hits collection released in 1999: ''Everything Is Possible'' (Luaka Bop), including some songs in English.</p>
        <p>Mestre Ambrosio, a band from Recife, plugged in the local music of carnivals and troubadours. On its album ''Fua na Casa de Cabral'' (Chaos/Sony Brasil), it melds the local variants of fiddle and guitar with a rock band, singing about the preservation of culture transforming it.</p>
        <p>A songwriter named Otto, on ''Samba pra Burro'' (Trama, Brazilian import), carries tropicalia's experimentation into the realm of electronica, letting samba rhythms warp into throbs and blips provided by D.J. Soul Slinger. Monica Salmaso's ''Trampolim'' (Blue Jackel) is pensive pop as only Brazilians can make it. Her breathy, melting voice is set against just a handful of instruments at a time, making the melodies seem even more cherished.</p>
        <p>Congo</p>
        <p>Soukous is the perpetual-motion machine of African pop. It carries the Afro-Cuban rumba back to Africa and transfers its rhythm to lilting, twining, endlessly inventive guitar lines. Unfortunately, soukous productions from Parisian studios, where most of the music is recorded, can grow repetitious or overly sweet. The assortment on ''Lightning Over the River: The Congolese Soukous Guitar Sound'' (Music Club), with most of the best-known soukous bands, can't entirely avoid the synthesizer overlays, but it keeps the grooves varied, buoyant and continually surprising.</p>
        <p>Hugh Tracey's ethnographic documents of Congolese music, compiled by Sharp Wood Productions and available through Stern's Africa, were recorded nearly 50 years ago and sound as if they come from another world. ''On the Edge of the Ituri Forest: Northeastern Belgian Congo'' shows the effects of the polyphonic singing of rain-forest pygmies on their neighbors; recorded in mono with a hand-held microphone, many of the pieces sound like bustling, happy crowds that suddenly coalesce into complex call and response. ''Kanyok and Luba: Southern Belgian Congo'' collects demonstrations of drum language, pieces with interlocked xylophone or thumb-piano patterns and ululating voices, and early incursions by the guitar.</p>
        <p>Another Tracey collection, ''Royal Court Music From Uganda,'' preserves music from courts that were brutally dismantled in the 60's: patterns so quick and complicated that they turn into a frenetic, articulate buzz.</p>
        <p>Cuba</p>
        <p>Everyone associated with ''Buena Vista Social Club'' put out a follow-up album last year, proving again that the club's members were superbly chosen. Among the best of the spinoffs are Eliades Ochoa's ''Sublime Illusion'' (Higher Octave), stern and propulsive songs driven by acoustic guitar picking, and Ibrahim Ferrer's album of big-band crooning, ''Buena Vista Social Club Presents Ibrahim Ferrer'' (Nonesuch).</p>
        <p>They're largely performing music of an older generation, steeped in nostalgia. Another decades-old style, the charanga -- a large ensemble featuring violins and flute -- survives with Orquesta Aragon, which was founded in 1939 and still plays danzons and cha-chas with suave sensuality.</p>
        <p>On ''La Charanga Eterna'' (Lus africa, French import), the group has guest singers, including the torchy Omara Portuondo, from ''Buena Vista Social Club,'' and Papa Wemba from Congo, whose music draws on the Afro-Cuban rumba. Cuba's current dance bands play the omnivorous updated salsa called timba, a hyperactive, quick-changing mixture that can include mambos, funk vamps and plenty of jabbing, angular horn-section parts.</p>
        <p>N.G. La Banda, one of the jazziest and most aggressive timba bands, has just released a compilation, ''The Best of N.G. La Banda'' (EMI Hemisphere), with liner notes that also explain some of the lyrics' socially charged double-entendres.</p>
        <p>Ethiopia</p>
        <p>Poverty, censorship and civil war took a severe toll on Ethiopian music. But in the decade from 1969 to 1978 it produced a homegrown pop: a tense mixture of electric guitars, imported late-60's soul and funk, modal Arab-flavored melodies and voices that veered between the tightly ornamented phrases of Arab music and the exultance of soul singing.</p>
        <p>A series of compilation albums called ''Ethiopiques'' (Buda Musique, French import) has resurrected some of this music. On Volume 1, the hybrid is tentative and a little clumsy, though it has some of the period charm of blaxploitation soundtracks. But it comes completely into its own with unleashed voices and horn-section muscle on Volumes 3 and 5, while Volume 7 is a reissue of Mahmoud Ahmed's ''Ere Mela Mela,'' where the muezzin meets the wah-wah pedal.</p>
        <p>Finland</p>
        <p>Members of Hedningarna, a Finnish folk group, decided to visit Karelia, a region on Finland's border with Russia. The songs they found fill ''Karelia Visa'' (NorthSide), and they're hearty melodies that can seem like Celtic reels at one moment, Slavic polyphony the next. The arrangements are modern ones, mixing guitars and keyboards with accordion, fiddle and jaw harp beyond Hedningarna's two female singers. While the lyrics are haunted by mortality, the songs sound square-jawed and sturdy, dug in against adversity.</p>
        <p>Indonesia</p>
        <p>The final volumes of ''Music of Indonesia'' were released last year by Smithsonian Folkways; like the rest of the series, these have thorough annotation and superb sound. While some will appeal mostly to specialists, others are so atmospheric that they deserve to be in home collections. Volume 20, ''Indonesian Guitars,'' examines local styles as they're transformed by guitars both standard and nonstandard, bringing in hints of everything from raga to Hawaiian slide guitar.</p>
        <p>Volume 18, ''Sulawesi: Funerals, Festivals and Work,'' features some of the most otherworldy music anywhere. It begins with somber funeral songs, sung in eerie near-unison with piercing double-reed shawms, followed by slow-motion music for women's voices and flute, pitched so closely they create the vibrating acoustic phenomenon called beats. Antiphonal choruses, gong pieces and a choral harvest celebration in bright major chords complete the album.</p>
        <p>Ireland</p>
        <p>Irish traditional music was thriving well before the faddish moment fueled by Riverdance and ''Titanic''; even as that craze passes, there's no shortage of young musicians to learn the subtleties of the old jigs, reels and hornpipes.</p>
        <p>They have hard acts to follow, particularly the Chieftains, who released ''The Chieftains Collection: The Very Best of the Claddagh Years'' (Atlantic), from their glory days in the 60's as Ireland's traditionalist standard-bearers, well before they became the comedy act of recent years. Lunasa, an instrumental band named after a Celtic harvest festival, isn't as traditional as the Chieftains; it includes guitar and bass (sometimes electric bass) alongside fiddle and whistle. As fingers fly, smart arrangements create shifting moods: fierce and yearning, lighthearted and melancholy.</p>
        <p>Italy</p>
        <p>On Alan Lomax's trip to Italy in the mid-50's, he recorded rural music that can sound as close to Eastern Europe or the Middle East as it does to the opera house. ''Folk Music and Song of Italy'' (Rounder) is a countrywide sampler: men, women and children, old and young, raising raw voices backed by tambourines, jaw harps, accordions and even bagpipes. It's vigorous, untutored music. One sea chantey was recorded on a boat, with the fishermen harmonizing as they haul in a squeaking net.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lomax's favorite region was Liguria, where he recorded ''The Trallaleri of Genoa'' (Rounder). It focuses on a local tradition, popular among dock workers, of male group singing that's a wild outpouring of harmony and counterpoint. A trallalero is an unaccompanied five-part song: a vibrant group drone with tenor and piercing falsetto lines crisscrossing high above. It's the missing link between Monteverdi and Frankie Valli. Percussive nonsense syllables -- the tra-la-las that give the songs their name -- percolate through the group or burst out like centuries-old scat singing.</p>
        <p>Mali</p>
        <p>When Ali Farka Toure's music first came out of Mali, in West Africa, it sounded strangely familiar. His circling, meditative one-chord guitar riffs bore a family resemblance to the deep blues of John Lee Hooker: a resemblance that Mr. Toure was cosmopolitan enough to recognize and use for ''Talking Timbuktu,'' a 1994 collaboration with Ry Cooder that won a Grammy Award. His songs have a serene austerity: just voice, guitar (acoustic or electric) and perhaps a drum, a fiddle or an answering voice.</p>
        <p>Two albums by Mr. Toure were released in the United States in 1999, both bare-bones productions with a hypnotic focus. ''Radio Mali'' (Nonesuch), recorded in the 70's, revolves around acoustic guitar and is achingly quiet. ''Niafunke'' (Hannibal) is his most recent recording, made on his farm in the village of Niafunke; with resonant, snaky electric-guitar riffs, its songs have an air of sage certainty.</p>
        <p>In a similar style Habib Koite and his band Bamada ratchet up the tempos and entwine a second guitar in their songs, fingerpicking in modal patterns that sometimes resemble Celtic rock. ''Ma Ya'' (Putumayo World Music), mostly using acoustic guitars, lets its patterns delicately insinuate themselves, but the electrified ''Muso Ko'' (Alula) is even better; its songs build up dizzying cross-rhythms.</p>
        <p>Before guitars came to Malian music, griots traditionally played the kora, a 21-stringed harp-guitar. ''New Ancient Strings'' (Hannibal) is an album of duets for two koras by Toumani Diabate and Battake Sossoko. It's a sequel to an album by their fathers, ''Ancient Strings,'' recorded in 1970, and it displays their heritage with resonant, shimmering purity.</p>
        <p>Middle East</p>
        <p>Across the Arab world, singers have been compressing the impassioned, open-ended improvisations of traditional music into pop songs with terse melodies and instrumental hooks. Cheb Mami, an Algerian who now lives in Paris, is one of the most cosmopolitan of these singers; his album ''Meli Meli'' (Ark 21/Universal) touches on reggae and flamenco without losing the sweeping passion of his voice. ''Camelspotting'' (EMI Hemisphere) is a collection of performers from Egypt, Syria, Lebanon and Morocco, among other places; in voices that quiver and slide and rasp, the singers pledge their love over backing tracks that juxtapose traditional ouds and hand drums with saxophones and synthesizers.</p>
        <p>Nigeria</p>
        <p>Femi Kuti's father, Fela Anikulapo Kuti, was a pivotal figure in African music. He invented Afro-Beat, which couched rebellious manifestos in a re-Africanized funk. Femi Kuti leads a less flamboyant life; unlike his father, he has only one wife and a mien of sobriety. But he has chosen to continue his father's approach with his own Afro-Beat band. On ''Shoki Shoki'' (MCA) Femi holds on to Fela's social concerns and brusque horn charts while using modern production techniques to clarify how precisely he builds the grooves: ticking and wah-wah-ing guitars, terse bass lines, snickering percussion. Some dance-club remixes are tacked on at the end of the American version of the album, including a rap from the Roots, but the strength of the music is in the band's own clockwork intensity.</p>
        <p>Pakistan</p>
        <p>Nusrat Fateh Ali Khan, who died in 1997, introduced much of the outside world to Pakistan's qawwali music, with its succinct refrains and driving, call-and-response improvisations. ''Land of the Sufis: Soul Music From the Indus Valley'' (Shanachie) surveys Pakistani music from lesser-known performers and local traditions. It includes qawwali along with other styles of devotional songs that share qawwali's melodic clarity and rhythmic vigor. Fiddle, accordion and a pair of penetrating, oboelike shenais share the melodies with voices that are weathered but fervent in their invocations of prophets and saints.</p>
        <p>Romania</p>
        <p>Three generations of Gypsy musicians sit in on ''Taraf de Haidouks'' (Nonesuch), which translates as ''Band of Brigands.'' Old, grizzled voices take turns with young and fervent ones; fiddles are cantankerous and then sweet. Their music has a cagy sense of timing. Sometimes it bounces easily along, with scratchy fiddle improvisations and voices that quaver and break with their urgency. And sometimes the oom-pah accelerates toward meteoric dance tunes, with accordion, fiddle and panpipes racing through impossibly fast, zigzagging lines. The music is simultaneously raw and virtuosic, implacable and giddy, hinting at history but living in a vivid present tense.</p>
        <p>Zimbabwe</p>
        <p>The steady, triple-time plinking of the mbira, or thumb piano, runs through Zimbabwean rock. Two of its masters, Thomas Mapfumo and Oliver Mutukudzi, released albums in 1999. Mr. Mapfumo's band was one of the pioneers in transferring mbira patterns to electric guitars for a style of music called chimurenga.</p>
        <p>He returned to using mbiras -- but kept the trap drums and electric bass -- on the 1995 tour that was recorded for ''Live at the El Rey'' (Chimurenga Music Company, www.anonymousweb.com).</p>
        <p>His thoughtful, troubled voice comes through the twinkling patterns like a gentle conscience. Oliver Mutukudzi's ''Tuku Music'' (Putumayo World Music) uses chimurenga's needlepoint electric guitars for music that's intricate, never pushy. In the husky baritone of a soul singer, he sings social messages about perseverance for his audience at home. But his music can easily move listeners who live half a world away.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S NOTEBOOK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
