<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>HOME VIDEO</title>
    <meta content="04VIDB$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1173707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Marius and Jeannette (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Blue Streak (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Swindle, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Astronaut's Wife, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Columns/Home Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Columns/Home Video</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE7D7133FF937A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>HOME VIDEO</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Films Marius and Jeannette, Blue Streak, The Swindle and The Astronaut's Wife released as new videos; brief excerpts from original reviews; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Marius and Jeannette</p>
        <p>As surely as romance develops between Jeannette (Ariane Ascaride, left), a supermarket cashier and single mother of two, and Marius (Gerard Meylan), a security guard, Robert Guediguian's film becomes a love affair with the working class of Marseilles. Having lost her job, the resilient Jeannette makes the best of it amid neighbors who get through hard times by sharing warm friendships and populist political ideas. One of her sons, by different men, is Catholic, while the other is Muslim, adding religious considerations to a warm, rich film with ''a strong, hearty, down-to-earth spirit throughout,'' Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times.</p>
        <p>1998. New Yorker. $89.98. 102 minutes. French with English subtitles. No rating.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Marius and Jeannette</p>
        <p>As surely as romance develops between Jeannette (Ariane Ascaride, left), a supermarket cashier and single mother of two, and Marius (Gerard Meylan), a security guard, Robert Guediguian's film becomes a love affair with the working class of Marseilles. Having lost her job, the resilient Jeannette makes the best of it amid neighbors who get through hard times by sharing warm friendships and populist political ideas. One of her sons, by different men, is Catholic, while the other is Muslim, adding religious considerations to a warm, rich film with ''a strong, hearty, down-to-earth spirit throughout,'' Janet Maslin wrote in The New York Times.</p>
        <p>1998. New Yorker. $89.98. 102 minutes. French with English subtitles. No rating.</p>
        <p>Blue Streak</p>
        <p>About to be nabbed by the law, Miles Logan (Martin Lawrence) races into a building under construction and tapes the $18 million diamond he has just stolen to the wall of an air-conditioning vent. After his prison term, he returns for the rock, only to find the building is now police headquarters, and, to have any chance of crawling into the ventilating system and retrieving the prize, he must impersonate a police officer. Using all his criminal savvy, Logan is soon running the station house, but ''among movies of its type, 'Blue Steak' may be classified among the zircons'' (Lawrence Van Gelder).</p>
        <p>1999. Columbia Tri-Star. $108.97; DVD, $24.95. 93 minutes. PG-13. Release date: Feb. 8.</p>
        <p>The Swindle</p>
        <p>A couple of con artists work so smoothly in Claude Chabrol's film that one is never sure of their identity and connection. Betty (Isabelle Huppert) dons wigs and seductive outfits to set up well-to-do business and professional people for the blandishments of her partner, Victor (Michel Serrault), who plays an officer and gentleman with panache. But then at a Swiss resort Betty latches on to a handsome businessman (Francois Cluzet), who is either a perfect target or an uninvited third partner in crime. ''Mr. Chabrol keeps curiosity piqued, the actors delightful and the outcome in sufficient question'' (Maslin).</p>
        <p>1997. New Yorker. $94.98. 105 minutes. French with English subtitles. Release date: Feb. 8.</p>
        <p>The Astronaut's Wife</p>
        <p>''They gon' be pilots, honey,'' drawls the astronaut Spencer Armacost (Johnny Depp) to his wife, Jillian (Charlize Theron), who is pregnant with twins. Back from a space mission gone wrong, Spencer isn't  his old self, and when Jillian starts wearing a hairdo straight out of ''Rosemary's Baby,'' it's better than even money that if the babies do become pilots, they'll be flying for an alien air force. With Mr. Depp carrying on suavely, Rand Ravich's film is not that bad, but it is ''ridiculously derivative'' (Maslin).</p>
        <p>1999. New Line. $107.37; DVD, $24.98. 100 minutes. R. Release date: Feb. 8.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a theater release, appeared on television or been on videocassette in earlier editions.</p>
        <p>INTRODUCING DOROTHY DANDRIDGE. When Dandridge (Halle Berry), star of Otto Preminger's ''Carmen Jones,'' arrives at the 1955 Academy Awards ceremony, she is called ''the first-ever colored nominee for best actress.'' (Her competition included Audrey Hepburn and Grace Kelly, who won for ''The Country Girl.'') Caught in many of the tired conventions of television docudrama, Martha Coolidge's film for HBO, adapted from Earl Mills's book, only partly explains the enigmatic singer and actress. Yet despite its flat-footed narrative, the production ''is worth watching for its affecting performances and for the sheer drama of Dandridge's life,'' Caryn James wrote in The New York Times in 1999. HBO. $76.12; DVD, $24.98. 115 minutes. R.  NOSFERATU and THE CABINET OF DR. CALIGARI. Unlike Ernst Lubitsch, Fritz Lang and other directors of the day who erected landscapes in the studio, F. W. Murnau shot ''Nosferatu'' (1922, 84 minutes), his unauthorized adaptation of Bram Stoker's ''Dracula,'' in the Carpathian Mountains. Robert Wiene's ''Cabinet of Dr. Caligari'' (1919, 72 minutes) stars Werner Kraus as a hypnotist who turns a death-dealing ogre (Conrad Veidt) loose on unsuspecting country folk. Both films are digitally remastered. Kino. $24.95 each.  BESHKEMPIR: THE ADOPTED SON. In the first independent feature film made in Kyrgyzstan, a young boy grows to adolescence only to be undone by the news that he is not his parents' biological child. Winstar. $89.98. 81 minutes. Kyrgyzstani with English subtitles.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
