<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Firearms Agency Intensifies Scrutiny of Suspect Dealers</title>
    <meta content="Y04GUNS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1173776"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butterfield, Fox</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDA103FF937A35751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1263" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Firearms Agency Intensifies Scrutiny of Suspect Dealers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FOX BUTTERFIELD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Butterfield, Fox</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms is embarking on most aggressive campaign in its 30-year history to crack down on corrupt gun dealers who help put firearms in the hands of criminals and juveniles; new enforcement campaign to be announced by Pres Clinton at White House (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms is embarking on the most aggressive campaign in its 30-year history to crack down on corrupt gun dealers who help put firearms in the hands of criminals and juveniles, White House and Treasury Department officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The new enforcement campaign, to be announced by President Clinton at the White House today, will use information developed by the firearms bureau in tracing guns used in crimes. As a byproduct of the tracing, the bureau discovered that just 1.2 percent of federally licensed firearms dealers, 1,020 of them, originally sold 57 percent of the guns used in crimes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The federal Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms is embarking on the most aggressive campaign in its 30-year history to crack down on corrupt gun dealers who help put firearms in the hands of criminals and juveniles, White House and Treasury Department officials said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The new enforcement campaign, to be announced by President Clinton at the White House today, will use information developed by the firearms bureau in tracing guns used in crimes. As a byproduct of the tracing, the bureau discovered that just 1.2 percent of federally licensed firearms dealers, 1,020 of them, originally sold 57 percent of the guns used in crimes.</p>
        <p>The firearms agency will now intensify its inspections of these suspect dealers, some of whom have not been checked in years. It will also require that some suspect dealers start providing records for the first time of sales of used guns, not just new guns.</p>
        <p>The bureau will also require a much fuller and prompter accounting of sales by dealers who claim that many of their guns were stolen or simply disappeared. And it will provide for revoking the licenses of the 31 percent of dealers who say they have not sold any guns in the past year, a possible sign, officials said, that those dealers are actually selling to illegal gun traffickers for a higher price.</p>
        <p>''This is a real sea change,'' said Stuart E. Eizenstat, the deputy secretary of the treasury. ''In the lifetime of the A.T.F., this is by far the most aggressive effort it has ever undertaken to deal with suspect dealers.''</p>
        <p>Under the new program, the firearms bureau will also provide a list, to any manufacturer that asks for it, of that company's guns that have been traced to a crime in the previous year, along with the name of the dealers who sold them.</p>
        <p>Gun makers have long contended that they have no way of knowing what happens to their firearms after they leave the factory and so have no way to police their distributors and retailers.</p>
        <p>''They will no longer have this little excuse,'' an administration official said.</p>
        <p>In the past, the firearms bureau has been a cautious agency, often under attack by the National Rifle Association and its supporters in Congress, and agents who demonstrated zeal in targeting corrupt dealers were often subject to internal criticism or had their careers truncated, agents say.</p>
        <p>The stepped-up enforcement program against suspect dealers presents a challenge to the rifle association and its backers in Congress. Officials of the rifle group have said repeatedly in recent months that the government should enforce existing gun laws rather than adopt new gun-control measures.</p>
        <p>And Bruce Reed, the president's adviser for domestic policy, said, ''With our actions, we are giving Congress a chance to put its money where its mouth is.''</p>
        <p>But Bill Powers, the rifle association's director of public affairs, dismissed the announcement of the new plan as a publicity stunt that would do nothing to reduce violent crime. ''There is nothing new here,'' he said, adding that ''they already have the authority'' to do all the things outlined in the plan.</p>
        <p>''It is painfully obvious that Bill Clinton and Al Gore don't like people who sell guns, or who own them either,'' Mr. Powers said. ''When you are not doing anything, hold a press conference.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's announcement today is part of a broader effort by the administration to expand its gun-control efforts, Mr. Eizenstat said. Last month, Mr. Clinton said he would ask Congress for 500 more agents for the firearms bureau, which as a result of N.R.A. pressure over the years is no larger today than it was when it was established.</p>
        <p>The president is also expected to try to win passage this year of a bill to require background checks on all handguns sold at gun shows, a bill that passed the Senate last year but died in the House.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton's announcement is to be accompanied by the release of what administration officials said would be the first in an annual series of comprehensive reports on the state of the gun industry. The report shows that about 4.5 million new guns are sold in the United States each year, but that the number of handguns has increased from only 10 percent of all firearms sales in the 1940's to more than 40 percent today. Handguns account for the vast majority of gun deaths each year.</p>
        <p>The number of federally licensed dealers surged to 284,117 in 1992 from 161,927 in 1975, largely during the Reagan and Bush administrations, making it harder for the A.T.F. to regulate the gun business, since its own number of agents did not increase, the report said.</p>
        <p>But after Mr. Clinton became president, and with tougher criteria to maintain a firearms license, the number dropped to 103,942 in 1999, of which 80,570 are actual gun stores or pawnshops and not people selling from their homes.</p>
        <p>But the report found that while 46 percent of the dealers had not sold a gun in the previous year in 1992, last year 31 percent of all gun stores and pawnshops reported they had not sold a gun in the past 12 months.</p>
        <p>''That is too high a number,'' said an administration official. ''These kinds of dealers have the opportunity to buy large numbers of guns at wholesale prices and then sell them in the illicit market at a steep mark up.''</p>
        <p>Under the new regulations, every three years, when a dealer applies to renew his license, he will have to show how many guns he has sold in the previous three years, and if he is not actively engaged in the business, his application may be denied.</p>
        <p>The report also found that in addition to the 1,020 dealers who are responsible for 57 percent of all the crime guns traced by the bureau, there are 450 dealers and pawnbrokers who sold more than 10 guns in 1998 with what the agency calls ''a short time to crime,'' guns that ended up being used in a crime in less than three years from the date of purchase. The average time to crime is six years.</p>
        <p>These dealers, who in some cases may also be in the group with a high volume of crime guns, will now be required to report information to the bureau on their sales of used guns. The agency has had great difficulty tracing secondhand guns because while it may know the name of the original dealer and purchaser, the chain is broken after the gun is resold.</p>
        <p>''I think these actions are wonderful news and smart law enforcement,'' said Dr. Garen Wintemute, director of the Violence Research Project at the University of California at Davis and an emergency-medicine physician. ''The A.T.F. is using its new information from gun tracing in a very focused way.''</p>
        <p>''From a prevention standpoint, the good news is that the number of suspect dealers is very limited, so given A.T.F.'s resources, it can concentrate on these few,'' said Dr. Wintemute, who has helped analyze some of the tracing information.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
