<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="148445"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880525T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE4DC1238F936A15756C0A96E948260" item-length="387" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:  Golf</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:  Golf</p>
        <p>Golf</p>
        <p>Glenz Shares Lead: David Glenz, last year's New Jersey P.G.A. Player of the Year, and Rick Vershure, last year's Metropolitan PGA Player of the Year, each shot a four-under-par 68 to share the first-round lead of the 25th Dodge Open yesterday in Denville, N.J. Glenz, a Morris County Golf Club player who has won every major tournament in the area except the Dodge, and Vershure, of Quaker Ridge, held a two-stroke lead. The $85,000 tournament awards Dodge automobiles to the top three finishers in the field of 67. The tournament continues with a round today and concludes with 36 holes tomorrow. Glenz, who started on the back nine of the 6,489-yard course, bogeyed the 10th hole but then strung together five straight birdies. Vershure was five-under heading into his 15th hole, but failed to save par from 30 feet after his tee shot caught a bunker.  Weight Lifting</p>
        <p>World Record Set: Israil Militosian of the Soviet Union hoisted 348.7 pounds to set a world record for both men and juniors in the snatch event of the 148.5-pound class of the World and European Weightlifting Championships yesterday. Militosian also set a world junior record in both snatch and jerk of the same class by lifting a total of 753.5 pounds.(AP)  Tennis</p>
        <p>Stanford Wins N.C.A.A. Title: Top-seeded Stanford defeated No. 2 Louisiana State, 5-2, to win the National Collegiate Athletic Association team championship after the finals were moved indoors because of rain yesterday in Athens, Ga. It was Stanford's seventh N.C.A.A. title since the team format was adopted in 1977, and the ninth over all for the Cardinal. Stanford improved its record to 25-1 for the year, while L.S.U. finished at 27-2.(AP)  Cycling</p>
        <p>Bontempi Wins Stage: Guido Bontempi of Italy sprinted ahead of the pack to win the second stage of the Tour of Italy yesterday on a hilly 143-mile course from Urbino to Ascoli Piceno. He was timed in 6 hours 20 minutes 56 seconds at an average speed of 23 miles an hour. Jean Francois Barnard, a Frenchman who finished in the same time as the winner, retained the pink jersey of the overall leader.</p>
        <p>Andrew Hampsten of the United States was delayed by a flat tire in the final miles but managed to catch the tail end of the pack in the final straight and finished in the same time as the winner.(AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
