<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Incorrigible Rogue Returns With a Wisp of Regret</title>
    <meta content="16KAKU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="980824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kakutani, Michiko</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richler, Mordecai</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Barney's Version (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E3DB143FF935A25751C1A961958260" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Incorrigible Rogue Returns With a Wisp of Regret</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHIKO KAKUTANI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kakutani, Michiko</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michiko Kakutani reviews Mordecai Richler book Barney's Version; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BARNEY'S VERSION  By Mordecai Richler  355 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>''Barney's Version,'' Mordecai Richler's entertaining new novel, purports to be the autobiography of one Barney Panofsky: entrepreneur, television producer, hockey fan, womanizer and malcontent, ''an impenitent rotter'' rewinding the spool of his wasted life, wondering how he got from there to here -- ''from the sweet teen-ager reading 'The Waste Land' aloud in bed to the misanthropic, aging purveyor of TV dreck, with only a lost love and pride in his children to sustain him.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BARNEY'S VERSION  By Mordecai Richler  355 pages. Alfred A. Knopf. $25.</p>
        <p>''Barney's Version,'' Mordecai Richler's entertaining new novel, purports to be the autobiography of one Barney Panofsky: entrepreneur, television producer, hockey fan, womanizer and malcontent, ''an impenitent rotter'' rewinding the spool of his wasted life, wondering how he got from there to here -- ''from the sweet teen-ager reading 'The Waste Land' aloud in bed to the misanthropic, aging purveyor of TV dreck, with only a lost love and pride in his children to sustain him.''</p>
        <p>Eschewing the sprawling, mythic ambitions of his last novel, ''Solomon Gursky Was Here'' (1990), ''Barney's Version'' marks something of a return by Mr. Richler to the methods and themes of such earlier books as ''The Apprenticeship of Duddy Kravitz'' (1959) and ''Joshua Then and Now'' (1980).</p>
        <p>Once again, we are introduced to a Jewish Montrealer who leaves behind his hardscrabble roots to achieve fortune and (a modicum of) fame. Once again, we are introduced to this hero's family, friends, rivals, drinking buddies and women. And once again, these introductions are made with lots of comic brio -- and not a little vulgarity and sophomoric humor.</p>
        <p>There is a melancholy undertow to Barney's story, however. Near the end of his life, Barney is filled with regrets and brokenhearted over the breakup of his last marriage, and while his self-doubts have not tamed his vituperative spirit, they have clearly tempered it. Barney is as amusing -- and often as incorrigible -- a character as earlier Richler heroes, but he's also a little older and wiser.</p>
        <p>Barney's biggest problem -- or rather, Mr. Richler's biggest problem -- is the uncanny resemblance he bears to Saul Bellow's Herzog: from his compulsive letter writing to his knee-jerk quotation of other writers; from his obsession with an ex-wife to his fixation on a former best friend. Like Herzog, Barney is preoccupied with trying to make sense of his life, with explaining, justifying and clarifying. And like Herzog, he conducts his self-inventory in great, looping strides that take him back and forth between the past and present -- in his case, between his modest childhood and his lucrative middle age, between his bohemian youth as an expatriate in Paris in the 50's and his dotage in Montreal in the 90's.</p>
        <p>The reader quickly realizes that Barney is a highly unreliable narrator: his memory's none too good these days, and as he points out himself, he's a ''natural-born burnisher,'' intent on polishing the comic anecdote and embellishing the dramatic moment. He's also the first to admit that he's an unreconstructed curmudgeon, nostalgic for the ''olden times'' when ''doctors made house calls. Rabbis were guys. Kids were raised by their moms instead of in child-care pens like piglets.''</p>
        <p>Barney makes no attempt to hide his contempt for political correctness, and he infuses his portraits of feminists, Quebec separatists, Zionists, academics and artists with lots of satiric bile. His first wife, Clara, emerges as a hysterical self-hating Jew, who was later sanctified as a feminist saint; his second wife, referred to only as the Second Mrs. Panofsky, was a long-winded princess, obsessed with gourmet treats and designer clothes. Barney's nemesis, Terry McIver, comes across as a self-serving, sanctimonious idiot who has undeservedly won a reputation as a distinguished writer, while his onetime buddy, Leo Bishinsky, is portrayed as con artist masquerading as a painter.</p>
        <p>The two people spared Barney's wrath are his third wife, the beauteous and long-suffering Miriam; and his best friend, the charismatic Boogie, whom he idolized in his youth. It is these two people who dominate Barney's daydreams, and it is these two characters who supply the plot in this otherwise messy, discursive novel. What destroyed Barney's happy marriage to Miriam? What happened between Barney and Boogie so many years ago at the lake? Did Barney really kill his best friend, as the Second Mrs. Panofsky alleges? Or did Boogie use their quarrel as an excuse to disappear, to escape his creditors and begin a new life abroad?</p>
        <p>As he did in ''Joshua,'' Mr. Richler coyly withholds the answers to such pivotal questions until the final pages of the novel. In the end, though, we don't really mind this shameless tactic of building suspense. We don't even mind all the rip-offs of ''Herzog,'' for Barney eventually emerges as a distinctive and wonderfully vivid character all his own. As usual, Mr. Richler's writing is boisterous, street-smart and allusive -- pitched just this side of manic, but equally capable, this time, of capturing both Barney's absurd comic high jinks and his sadder forays into regret and grief.</p>
        <p>''Barney's Version'' turns out to be a fine, funny novel, often derivative, but deft, irreverent and affecting all the same.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
