<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>International Effort Is Pledged to Curb Demand for Illegal Drugs</title>
    <meta content="T11DRUG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Assembly (Un)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wren, Christopher S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402EFDB103AF932A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>International Effort Is Pledged to Curb Demand for Illegal Drugs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wren, Christopher S</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, June 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>United Nations General Assembly concludes special session on world drug problem with 150 participating nations promising to work to reduce their appetites for illegal drugs within next five years (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The General Assembly concluded a special session on the world drug problem today with the 150 participating nations promising to work to reduce their appetites for illegal drugs within the next five years.</p>
        <p>The effect was to place reduction of demand on par with reduction of supply as an ''indispensable pillar'' in combating the spread of illegal drugs. Until recently, the drug-fighting strategies of the United States and many other consumer countries focused on intercepting drugs from producing countries.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The General Assembly concluded a special session on the world drug problem today with the 150 participating nations promising to work to reduce their appetites for illegal drugs within the next five years.</p>
        <p>The effect was to place reduction of demand on par with reduction of supply as an ''indispensable pillar'' in combating the spread of illegal drugs. Until recently, the drug-fighting strategies of the United States and many other consumer countries focused on intercepting drugs from producing countries.</p>
        <p>The participants also shifted from a purely law enforcement approach toward reducing drug supply to an approach of alternative development, including inducing farmers who grow coca leaf and opium to switch to less lucrative crops in return for roads, hospitals, schools and other means to a better life.</p>
        <p>On the recommendation of the United Nations International Drug Control Program, the delegates endorsed an ambitious proposal by its director, Pino Arlacchi, to phase out cultivation of opium and coca leaf in 10 years. The countries also agreed to do more to expose money laundering, to tighten up on chemicals used to process illegal drugs and to cooperate on extraditing traffickers.</p>
        <p>''We are not starting a new 'war on drugs,' '' Mr. Arlacchi told the delegates. ''In fact, there never was one. Instead, the better analogy for the international community is that of a doctor facing a deadly disease. Drugs quite simply kill people. And it is our responsibility to help find the cure.''</p>
        <p>The three-day session was filled with speeches that described the damage done by drugs as well as calls for concerted action against the traffickers. The session has been more useful in bringing delegates together offstage to compare how their respective countries deal with the problems and to discuss a coordinated response.</p>
        <p>Today, the Netherlands, which has the most liberal drug policies, took the session into the uncharted waters of ''harm reduction,'' a public health concept for reducing the damage drug users cause themselves and others.</p>
        <p>''Our primary aim is to protect health and social well-being and to reduce the harm and risks associated with drug abuse,'' the Dutch Deputy Prime Minister and Foreign Minister, H.A.F.M.O van Mierlo, said. ''Within this context, we believe that drug users should not be criminalized for their habits, but on the contrary, should be provided the help they need.''</p>
        <p>He said his country tried to make drug use less glamorous by bringing it into the open. ''For young people in the Netherlands now, heroin is for losers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Some other speakers appeared unsympathetic. Wong Kan Seng, the Home Affairs Minister of Singapore, which hangs drug traffickers, said that the situation is under control in his country because ''drug offenders are treated with the same gravity, regardless of whether they are Singaporean or foreign nationals.''</p>
        <p>The United States has been less than enthusiastic about alternative development, in part because it would mean working with repressive Governments like those of Myanmar and Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>''We would love to be able to deal with advanced Western democracies, but that's not where drugs are produced,'' Sandro Tucci, a spokesman for the United Nations drug control program, said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
