<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Showtime for the Sisters of the N.B.A.</title>
    <meta content="11WNBA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1023705"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Women's National Basketball Assn</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litsky, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980611T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04E1D9103AF932A25755C0A96E958260" item-length="612" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Showtime for the Sisters of the N.B.A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Women's National Basketball Association begins its second season (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Women's National Basketball Association, a sister of the N.B.A. and a beneficiary of the N.B.A.'s marketing clout, begins its second season with four games tonight. One of those games -- the New York Liberty at the Cleveland Rockers -- will be televised nationally by the Lifetime cable network.</p>
        <p>In fact, 30 games in the 10-week regular season will be televised nationally -- 10 each by NBC, ESPN and Lifetime. And those networks, one or two at a time, will televise every playoff game.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Women's National Basketball Association, a sister of the N.B.A. and a beneficiary of the N.B.A.'s marketing clout, begins its second season with four games tonight. One of those games -- the New York Liberty at the Cleveland Rockers -- will be televised nationally by the Lifetime cable network.</p>
        <p>In fact, 30 games in the 10-week regular season will be televised nationally -- 10 each by NBC, ESPN and Lifetime. And those networks, one or two at a time, will televise every playoff game.</p>
        <p>That extensive television coverage of the 10 teams (up from eight) is part of the war between the W.N.B.A. and the equally young American Basketball League for the public's heart and ultimately its dollars. The A.B.L. plays in the traditional winter-spring basketball season. The W.N.B.A. plays in the summer, when N.B.A. arenas have more open dates. In their first seasons, the A.B.L. had better players and a higher level of competition, but fewer marketing dollars and smaller crowds. The W.N.B.A. averaged 9,669 fans a game, to the A.B.L.'s 3,536.</p>
        <p>The W.N.B.A. scored a major signing coup this year. First, it picked up Nikki McCray, the A.B.L.'s most valuable player last season. Then it signed most of the best college seniors, including such all-Americans as Ticha Penicheiro, the flashy point guard from Old Dominion, Nykesha Sales of Connecticut and Kristin Folkl of Stanford.</p>
        <p>Penicheiro will play for the Sacramento Monarchs. Sales and Folkl are injured and will not play this season, but at least the W.N.B.A. has them in the fold. Their presence has cheered such W.N.B.A. players as Rebecca Lobo of the Liberty.</p>
        <p>''I'm excited,'' she said, ''because it's important to us to get the best players, and we sure did this year.''</p>
        <p>The W.N.B.A.'s biggest score may have been the signing of Malgorzata (''call me Margo'') Dydek of Poland, who has played in Europe for six years. When she reported to the W.N.B.A.'s combine camp, she was listed at 6 feet 6 inches. She turned out to be 7-2 and graceful, with a 7-foot wingspan that forces opponents to alter shots. The Utah Starzz made her the first choice in the draft, which should get the team out of the cellar. But the Detroit Shock and the Washington Mystics, the expansion teams, may not be buried there, either. Washington, coached by Jim Lewis, formerly of George Mason, has McCray. Detroit, coached by Nancy Lieberman-Cline, has six foreign players.</p>
        <p>The A.B.L. will start its season in November with 10 teams, including new ones in Chicago and Nashville. Like the W.N.B.A., it is a single-entity league, which means the league owns all the teams and signs all the players. Its season is longer than the W.N.B.A.'s, its salaries are higher and the players get part ownership of the league. But the A.B.L. does not allow its players to play in another league. The W.N.B.A. does, and most of its players play overseas during the traditional basketball months. The A.B.L. is privately owned, and it lacks the financial clout of the W.N.B.A., whose 12 sponsors include Nike, Coca-Cola, McDonald's, General Motors and American Express, and its national television package pales next to the W.N.B.A.'s.</p>
        <p>The A.B.L. teams are mostly in middle-sized cities. The W.N.B.A. teams are in N.B.A. cities, including New York, where the Liberty reached last year's playoff title game before losing to the Houston Comets.</p>
        <p>While Val Ackerman, the W.N.B.A. president, did not call this a make-or-break season, she said much was at stake.</p>
        <p>''This year is the test,'' she said, ''because the curiosity is lessened and the novelty is gone.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
