<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Some Sioux, Costner Now Dances With Devil</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="745131"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAMBLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CASINOS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SIOUX INDIANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDIANS, AMERICAN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">DEADWOOD (SD)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOUTH DAKOTA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">COSTNER, KEVIN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, DIRK</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">DANCES WITH WOLVES (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/South Dakota</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DD123CF937A15751C0A963958260" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Some Sioux, Costner Now Dances With Devil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, DIRK</byline>
      <dateline>DEADWOOD, S.D.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kevin Costner became a hero among American Indians five years ago for his movie "Dances With Wolves," a tribute to the Lakota Sioux culture before whites swarmed the Black Hills in the 1870's to snatch the land and search for gold.</p>
        <p>In fact, the actor was presented by tribal leaders with a hand-woven quilt and honored with a ceremony in which a sacred eagle feather was tied in his hair, a gesture of appreciation for his sensitivity to Sioux traditions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Kevin Costner became a hero among American Indians five years ago for his movie "Dances With Wolves," a tribute to the Lakota Sioux culture before whites swarmed the Black Hills in the 1870's to snatch the land and search for gold.</p>
        <p>In fact, the actor was presented by tribal leaders with a hand-woven quilt and honored with a ceremony in which a sacred eagle feather was tied in his hair, a gesture of appreciation for his sensitivity to Sioux traditions.</p>
        <p>But now that Mr. Costner wants to build a huge new casino and resort here, some Sioux feel betrayed. The resort would be partly built on National Forest land that tribal leaders believe belongs to the Indians.</p>
        <p>"After the movie, I thought he was pretty cool," said Joe Pulliam, a 26-year-old Sioux artist who lives on the Pine Ridge reservation in Shannon County, the poorest county in America. "But now, it seems like he's just another white guy coming here to take what he can get."</p>
        <p>The complicated dispute over the land sought by Mr. Costner and his business partner and brother, Dan Costner, dates to the Fort Laramie Treaty of 1868. Under that agreement, the Sioux were granted land from the Missouri River in South Dakota west to the Bighorn Mountains in Wyoming, in exchange for a promise from the tribe to vacate vast sections of the Great Plains.</p>
        <p>When gold was discovered in the Black Hills in the 1870's, however, settlers from the East began to swarm into Deadwood's famous gulch and other areas. And in 1877, Congress passed a law that took back the land, an act that many historians believe was intended to punish Indians for the defeat of General George Armstrong Custer and the Seventh Cavalry in the Battle of Little Bighorn a year earlier.</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court ruled in 1980 on behalf of the tribes, ordering the Federal Government to compensate the Indians for the property loss. But the tribes have refused to accept the money, insisting that they be given National Forest lands in the Black Hills, which they consider sacred. The monetary compensation has been held in escrow, drawing interest, and is now about $380 million.</p>
        <p>The Costners, who also own the Midnight Star casino in Deadwood, which is on private land, want to use about 600 acres of National Forest land for an 18-hole golf course for their new project. The proposed $100 million resort, to open in 1997, would also include a 350-room lodge and an outdoor amphitheater built on adjacent private land.</p>
        <p>In exchange for the Federal land, the Costners would swap a 600-acre parcel they own in Spearfish Canyon, about 10 miles from Deadwood. The National Forest Service says it will probably approve the trade because the private land being offered is pristine and spectacular.</p>
        <p>But the tribes contend that no National Forest land in the Black Hills should be traded, since they consider the compensation issue unresolved. Over the years, tribal leaders have tried, unsuccessfully, to persuade members of Congress to sponsor legislation that would return the Black Hills to the Indians.</p>
        <p>Among whites in South Dakota, any talk of returning the Black Hills to Indians is overwhelmingly opposed. And they welcome the proposed Costner project, especially since jobs are scarce in this remote section of the Dakotas and could become even more scarce if Ellsworth Air Force Base in Rapid City, the largest employer in the area, is shut down in the Pentagon's effort to save money.</p>
        <p>Some Sioux express concerns that a huge new casino would hurt business on eight Indian-run gambling halls in South Dakota. But others believe the huge Costner project would increase business for the tribal halls by attracting tourists who could then be lured into making the three-hour drive to the closest reservations.</p>
        <p>"We've got plenty of history in Indian country, and we can compete with the casinos in Deadwood for tourism," said Wayne Barber, the general manager for the new Prairie Wind casino on Pine Ridge reservation. "They've got Wild Bill Hickok and we've got Crazy Horse. They've got Potato Creek Johnny and we've got Chief Red Cloud. We've got a herd of bison, an elk refuge, the grasslands, the Badlands."</p>
        <p>Kevin Costner, who is working on a movie in Hawaii, could not be reached. Publicists for the actor have declined to comment. Dan Costner did not return telephone calls requesting an interview, but he released a statement earlier contending that their resort would not hurt tribal casinos and that it would have a "strong, positive, measurable impact on Deadwood and the surrounding communities' economies."</p>
        <p>Sioux leaders have also expressed resentment over the $14 million in Federal, state and local tax breaks and incentives that have been promised for the Costner project.</p>
        <p>"When the tribes wanted gambling, the state fought them every step of the way," said Tim Wapato, the executive director of the National Indian Gaming Association in Washington. "Along come the Costners, who don't even need the money, and they get subsidies. It seems racist to me."</p>
        <p>The Costner resort would be named Dunbar, after the United States Army officer played by the actor in "Dances With Wolves." Mr. Costner earned an estimated $60 million from the movie. At the time, some tribal officials suggested that the actor invest some of his profits in Indian casinos. But he has not done so.</p>
        <p>Tim Giago, the publisher of the Indian Country Today newspaper in Rapid City, said many of the Sioux people who revered "Dances With Wolves" wanted to give Mr. Costner the benefit of the doubt, speculating that he was "so busy with his movies" that he had not kept track of the dispute in South Dakota.</p>
        <p>Doris Leader Charge, a Sioux who taught Mr. Costner some of the Lakota language and had a role in the film, remembers as a small child going to the store and interpreting for her grandmother, who spoke no English. Invariably, the girl would ask for candy. "When I get my Black Hills back," her grandmother would answer.</p>
        <p>"Now I'm a woman of 70 myself," said Ms. Leader Charge. "And we're not any closer to getting back our Black Hills than we were then."</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Costner, Ms. Leader Charge said that by "making a movie that told people all over the world that the Lakota people still live -- will always live," he has already given American Indians a gift more valuable than money.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
