<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Misguided Attempt at Fatherhood</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="745034"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LAMB (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews/By Stephen Holden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950224T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7DF123BF937A15751C0A963958260" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Misguided Attempt at Fatherhood</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN HOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLDEN, STEPHEN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From its opening scenes in a modern Dickensian home for throwaway children to its agonizing final sequence on a deserted beach, Colin Gregg's fine and disturbing film "Lamb" conveys a sinking feeling of dread. As this story of a man who recklessly sacrifices himself trying to save an emotionally damaged child unwinds, that dread steadily mounts.</p>
        <p>"Lamb" focuses on the relationship between Brother Michael Lamb (Liam Neeson), a teacher in a Roman Catholic-run institution for troubled boys in Ireland, and 10-year-old Owen Kane (Hugh O'Conor), the school's most unruly pupil. Dumped into the institution by his abusive mother, Owen is an incorrigible mess who smokes cigarettes, curses, wets his bed, picks fights and has epileptic seizures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From its opening scenes in a modern Dickensian home for throwaway children to its agonizing final sequence on a deserted beach, Colin Gregg's fine and disturbing film "Lamb" conveys a sinking feeling of dread. As this story of a man who recklessly sacrifices himself trying to save an emotionally damaged child unwinds, that dread steadily mounts.</p>
        <p>"Lamb" focuses on the relationship between Brother Michael Lamb (Liam Neeson), a teacher in a Roman Catholic-run institution for troubled boys in Ireland, and 10-year-old Owen Kane (Hugh O'Conor), the school's most unruly pupil. Dumped into the institution by his abusive mother, Owen is an incorrigible mess who smokes cigarettes, curses, wets his bed, picks fights and has epileptic seizures.</p>
        <p>Michael becomes fiercely protective of Owen after the boy is severely punished for an act of vandalism he insists he didn't commit. But the school's sadistic headmaster, Brother Benedict (Ian Bannen), doesn't care whether Owen is guilty or not. "We'll never find the real culprit," he admits before reiterating his motto, "Discipline is love in disguise."</p>
        <p>Michael's witnessing of Brother Benedict's systematic cruelty erodes his already shaky faith. And when Michael's father dies, something inside him snaps. With part of the money from his meager inheritance, he flees the institution, taking Owen with him. Although Owen is glad to be away from the place, he utterly fails to comprehend that he has in effect been kidnapped.</p>
        <p>Michael's deed may be noble in spirit (he only wants to be a good father to the boy and is not a molester), but it is also criminal. The pair have no choice but to travel under assumed names as father and son. Since Owen is too young to grasp the reality of the situation, there are many excruciating moments when he almost gives them away. Although the boy eventually comes to trust his rescuer and would-be father, much of the time he is a nagging, whining troublemaker who would try the patience of the most devoted parent.</p>
        <p>Arriving in London, they stay in a series of hotels and rooming houses, each dingier and more depressing than the last. In these scenes, in which Michael has to cope with nosy landladies and worse, "Lamb" has the feel of an Anglo-Irish "Lolita," minus the sex. Their final stop in London is a ghastly slum owned by a sleazy con man who introduces Owen to marijuana while Michael is away on a construction job.</p>
        <p>As it grinds along at a very leisurely pace, "Lamb" rubs your face in the seediness of modern Britain. It also uses its nearly two-hour running time to let the fear and the hopelessness of the situation sink in as deeply as possible.</p>
        <p>"Lamb" was filmed in 1985, several years before "Schindler's List" made Mr. Neeson a major international star. Although the lanky actor gives a touching portrayal of Brother Michael, he also conveys a reserve of inner strength that doesn't really fit the personality of an impetuous fugitive. Mr. Neeson's performance is impressively understated and anti-heroic, yet he still seems morally towering.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. O'Conor's Owen has occasional flashes of sweetness, the performance totally avoids teary-eyed, little-boy-lost cuteness. The character is a tough little handful. "Lamb" forces you emotionally into the role of surrogate parent to an angry, defensive child too wounded to love back. LAMB  Directed by Colin Gregg; written by Bernard Maclaverty, based on his novel; director of photography, Mike Garfath; edited by Peter Delfgou; music by Van Morrison; production designer, Austen Spriggs; produced by Neil Zeiger; released by Capitol Entertainment. Running time: 110 minutes. This film is not rated. WITH: Liam Neeson (Michael Lamb), Hugh O'Conor (Owen Kane), Ian Bannen (Brother Benedict), Ronan Wilmot (Brother Fintan) and Frances Tomelty (Mrs. Kane).  FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
