<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sprewell Holds On To Playoff Dreams</title>
    <meta content="07KNICKS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1470467"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="N.B.A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sprewell, Latrell</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE3DA103FF934A35750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="513" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sprewell Holds On To Playoff Dreams</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Chris Broussard</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Knicks player Latrell Sprewell says Knicks have good chance of making playoffs and going to NBA finals, despite being four games out of final Eastern Conference playoff spot (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is little reason to believe the Knicks will make the Eastern Conference playoffs and almost no reason to believe they would win a series if they did reach the postseason.</p>
        <p>They are four games out of the eighth and final Eastern Conference playoff spot with 21 games remaining, 12 on the road, where they have lost seven straight games and are 8-21 this season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is little reason to believe the Knicks will make the Eastern Conference playoffs and almost no reason to believe they would win a series if they did reach the postseason.</p>
        <p>They are four games out of the eighth and final Eastern Conference playoff spot with 21 games remaining, 12 on the road, where they have lost seven straight games and are 8-21 this season.</p>
        <p>Still, Latrell Sprewell believes in magic.</p>
        <p>Sprewell says the Knicks (26-35) have a chance to go not just to the first round, the second round and the conference championship series, but all the way to the N.B.A. finals.</p>
        <p>''In the East? Yeah,'' Sprewell said before the Knicks' 97-95 loss in Boston on Wednesday. ''I think we could go with this team if we can get in the playoffs. The East is not like the West at all. When you go out there, those teams are good. They're very talented guys. They've got great players. They've got size. It just seems like the teams in the East are so evenly matched, you never know who's going to win on any given night. So, yeah, I feel like anything can happen, especially after being in the East and being the eighth seed and playing Miami. You always know that anything is possible.''</p>
        <p>Sprewell, of course, was referring to the Knicks' 1998-99 season, when they barely reached the playoffs as the eighth-seeded team, upset Miami in the first round and rolled all the way to the finals before losing to San Antonio. But that Knicks team had underachieved during the regular season.</p>
        <p>Sprewell's statement was essentially unsolicited. He was asked if he thought the Knicks could have fought for homecourt advantage in the playoffs or even reached the finals if Antonio McDyess (fractured left kneecap) had been healthy this season. Sprewell said yes, and then added that they could win the East even without McDyess.</p>
        <p>In the past, Sprewell has not been one to make unreasonable comments. But Sprewell is basing his faith on some evidence. The Knicks have beaten six of the top seven teams in the East -- all but Boston -- and most of their losses to those teams have been close, some even going down to the last possession.</p>
        <p>Plus, the top teams in the conference have fallen into a funk since the All-Star Game break. Indiana has lost 8 of its last 9 games. After last night's 92-78 loss at San Antonio, the Nets are 4-9 since the break, and Detroit just ended a seven-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Chris Broussard</p>
        <p>N.B.A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
