<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Consorting With the Snake</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="851551"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="RECORDINGS VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOUNDGARDEN (MUSIC GROUP)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STRAUSS, NEIL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E4D91339F93AA25756C0A960958260" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Consorting With the Snake</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL STRAUSS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STRAUSS, NEIL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SINCE ITS INCEPTION, rock music has had the snake as its escort. The snake is slimy, sinuous and lowly. It can be the agent of a fall from grace, an all-purpose phallic symbol, a cheater and back stabber or the losing combination in a roll of the dice. Whatever form it takes, the snake is always very masculine and very wicked. And it is all over "Down on the Upside," the latest album from Soundgarden, the leaders of grunge's hard-rock school.</p>
        <p>The album is not the first recording on which Soundgarden has walked with the snake -- "Get on the Snake" is one of the centerpieces of 1989's "Louder Than Love." Nor does "Down on the Upside" (A&amp;M) represent the best use to which Soundgarden has put the snake; that honor goes to the line about the snake being in the singer Chris Cornell's eyes in "Black Hole Sun," the hit from last year's No. 1 album "Superunknown." But never before has Soundgarden relied on snake imagery more than it does on "Down on the Upside," the band's rawer, looser follow-up to "Superunknown."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SINCE ITS INCEPTION, rock music has had the snake as its escort. The snake is slimy, sinuous and lowly. It can be the agent of a fall from grace, an all-purpose phallic symbol, a cheater and back stabber or the losing combination in a roll of the dice. Whatever form it takes, the snake is always very masculine and very wicked. And it is all over "Down on the Upside," the latest album from Soundgarden, the leaders of grunge's hard-rock school.</p>
        <p>The album is not the first recording on which Soundgarden has walked with the snake -- "Get on the Snake" is one of the centerpieces of 1989's "Louder Than Love." Nor does "Down on the Upside" (A&amp;M) represent the best use to which Soundgarden has put the snake; that honor goes to the line about the snake being in the singer Chris Cornell's eyes in "Black Hole Sun," the hit from last year's No. 1 album "Superunknown." But never before has Soundgarden relied on snake imagery more than it does on "Down on the Upside," the band's rawer, looser follow-up to "Superunknown."</p>
        <p>Eat the fruit, and kiss the snake good night," Mr. Cornell sings in his high-pitched voice in the album's first song, "Pretty Noose." In "Tighter and Tighter," he softly moans, "Fell too far to start again/ A sudden snake found my shape and tells the world." And in "Unkind," the bassist Ben Shepherd pitches in, "We see the vipers of distance/ Crawl into our lives every day/ Breeding our Edens of hatred." Even when there is no mention of the snake, it is still present. He (the snake is always a he) lurks in titles like "Applebite" and in the references to primal sin and falls from Paradise in other songs.</p>
        <p>The snake belongs to a particular tradition in rock music. Its roots are Soundgarden's roots, buried in the blues, the blues-based rock of the late 60's  (Led Zeppelin and the Doors) and the heavy metal of the 70's and 80's. From the beginning, the snake was mean. John Lee Hooker flaunts his "crawlin' " (or infidelity) to a lover in his version of "Crawlin' King Snake;" in "Who Do You Love," Bo Diddley uses a cobra as a necktie, builds a house of rattlesnake hide  and brandishes a rattlesnake whip.</p>
        <p>Though women have started singing about the reptile recently, it has remained male and vulgar; think of the hand trying to work its way up a woman's blouse in the Throwing Muses' "Snakeface," or the coarse lover that P. J. Harvey dominates in "Long Snake Moan." In its songs, Soundgarden does not represent the snake but rather is possessed by it and is led into sin by it ("the snakes . . . crawl into our lives"). Thus the victimizers are the victims, able to sin without repenting and to escape responsibility for their actions. In this way the band can harness grunge's self-absorption to heavy metal's destructive energy and come up with a song like "Blow Up the Outside World."</p>
        <p>Rock musicians don't like to confine the snake exclusively to lyrics. Flashing a big snake to an audience is a quick way for a rocker to convey potency and fearlessness. So the reptile appears in band names like Whitesnake,  on the cover of the 1991 album "Metallica," wrapped around Alice Cooper's torso  during concerts, in the tattoos of Henry Rollins and in the home of Slash from Guns 'n' Roses (he owns more than 200 snakes). More important, the goal of most hard-rock guitarists is to play a solo that conjures up images of the snake twisting and undulating.</p>
        <p>Soundgarden's guitarist, Kim Thayil, is the master of the serpentine, playing Jimmy Page to Mr. Cornell's Robert Plant. Or, on "Down on the Upside" 's weaker  tracks -- about a third of the 16-song album -- he plays Eddie Van Halen to Mr.  Cornell's Sammy Hagar. He slowly wraps his guitar lines around Mr. Cornell's voice in "Tighter and Tighter," increasing in intensity until he overwhelms the  singer.</p>
        <p>The snake isn't the only animal invoked on "Down on the Upside." There are some mice, a dog, an ant and one fictional "rhinosaur."</p>
        <p>Generally, identifying with animals in song lyrics is a sign of low self-esteem, and Soundgarden is no exception. For all the virility and macho power that rock singers have tried to wring from the sanke, Soundgarden remains  more interested in the fact that it is the only animal cursed to spend its days  slithering on the ground.  As Mr. Cornell sings in "Rhinosaur," "Only healthy in the dirt."</p>
        <p>RECORDINGS VIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
