<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Early Birds on the Trail of Value</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="851488"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DOLCE VITA (DANBURY, CONN, RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E1DA1339F93AA25756C0A960958260" item-length="750" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Early Birds on the Trail of Value</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, PATRICIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT may be possible to find a fresh-cooked, high-quality prix-fixe dinner with three courses and coffee for less than $14.95 in an attractive restaurant in Fairfield County, but we don't know where such a place might be. That's the price of the early dinner special at Dolce Vita in Danbury, and we consider it one of the best dining values around.</p>
        <p>Of course you must arrive between 5 and 6:30 P.M. to avail yourself of such a value. At some places, when there's a dinner special, the choices are limited. Such isn't the case at Dolce Vita, where at least four appealing choices are offered in each category: appetizer, entree and dessert.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT may be possible to find a fresh-cooked, high-quality prix-fixe dinner with three courses and coffee for less than $14.95 in an attractive restaurant in Fairfield County, but we don't know where such a place might be. That's the price of the early dinner special at Dolce Vita in Danbury, and we consider it one of the best dining values around.</p>
        <p>Of course you must arrive between 5 and 6:30 P.M. to avail yourself of such a value. At some places, when there's a dinner special, the choices are limited. Such isn't the case at Dolce Vita, where at least four appealing choices are offered in each category: appetizer, entree and dessert.</p>
        <p>For our $14.95 special, we began with eggplant rollatini (thin slices of grilled eggplant stuffed with ricotta and mascarpone, covered with melted mozzarella); it was luscious. Four entree choices included loin of lamb grilled  with mushrooms, scallops with zucchini, grilled swordfish in a white wine-and-caper sauce and chicken with prosciutto and white wine. We opted for penne with Italian sausage, broccoli rape and a profusion of garlic slices, a lusty dish. Our finale was zuppa inglese, a monster-large portion that jumbled raspberry mousse and sponge cake with subtle lacings of rum and port wine.</p>
        <p>Before the starters arrived, a basket of excellent, crusty bread was served with butter as well as a cruet of flavorful olive oil. For those responding to quantity alone, this prix-fixe meal more than sufficed. What made it special was its made-to-order high quality.</p>
        <p>The regular menu has its own pleasures, including well-prepared calamari fritti, with lots of legs lightly battered and crisply fried, served with a small boat of fresh tomato sauce gently spiked with red pepper.</p>
        <p>Of two versions of salmon, one was simply, expertly grilled, the other, called salmon reale, was grilled, then covered with a gloppy pink sauce the consistency of Thousand Island dressing, that contained brandy, capers, tomato and Dijon mustard. We preferred the salmon merely grilled, which highlighted the perfection of the lightly cooked fish.</p>
        <p>Other worthy entrees were shrimp Gabriella (jumbos in a lightly spiced garlic-fresh tomato sauce) and pollo inferno (chicken in a piquant garlic-white  wine sauce). With each a la carte entree came a house salad with tomatoes and green beans (barely cooked, to the al dente stage) and a minute potato croquette.</p>
        <p>Most desserts are premises-made and provided tasty finishes to the meal. Zuppa inglese, chocolate roll (light and springy) and fresh oranges in Grand Marnier -- all were delicious. Adding to the pleasant dining experience is the place itself (which formerly housed a French restaurant, Duo's): three cozy rooms with pale yellow stucco walls, wood floors and punctuations of fresh greenery.</p>
        <p>Our one complaint: on a busy weekend evening the staff consisted of one waitress, a bus person and a waiter/busman who seemed to be playing back-up to the waitress, yet was not knowledgeable about the menu. A guest who cannot tolerate white chocolate inquired if the chocolate roll contained white chocolate. "No" was the quick reply. The first taste revealed, to the diner's dismay, the error of that uninformed response. Requests for water and for a second glass of wine were taken with good grace, but there was no follow-through. An extra staffer or manager would correct most of the service problems.</p>
        <p>That may be quibbling, considering the reasonable prices, both prix-fixe and  in general. A three-course dinner for two, off the a la carte menu, came to $38, before tax, tip and drinks. A limited wine list of 15 Italian and Californian vintages runs between $18 and $32 a bottle.</p>
        <p>Dolce Vita Very Good</p>
        <p>52 1/2 Pembroke Road, Danbury. 746-0037.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: Coziness of a private house.</p>
        <p>Service: A good-humored but imperfectly informed and insufficient staff, especially on weekends.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Eggplant rollatini, calamari fritti, zucchini fritti, penne with sausage and broccoli rape, grilled salmon, pollo inferno, shrimp Gabriella, zuppa inglese, chocolate roll.</p>
        <p>Price range: Lunch $9.50-$14.50, dinner $10.50-$18.50,prix-fixe early dinner  $14.95, Sunday brunch $12.50.</p>
        <p>Credit cards: Most major cards.</p>
        <p>Hours: Noon-4 P.M. Tuesday-Sunday, 4-10 P.M. Tuesday-Thursday, 4-11 P.M. Friday-Saturday, 4-9 P.M. Sunday.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Accepted.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: Three steps at entrance.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
