<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CONNECTICUT GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="851574"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">AKIRA KUROSAWA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E1D91339F93AA25756C0A960958260" item-length="1202" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CONNECTICUT GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ASIAN FILMS</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ASIAN FILMS</p>
        <p>Rashomon," the classic 1950 Japanese film that is considered to be Akira Kurosawa's masterpiece, is the first of five Asian films to be shown at the Stratford Library Monday through Friday at 1 P.M.</p>
        <p>His 1990 film, "Akira Kurosawa's Dreams" is Tuesday's offering, with the director Martin Scorsese as van Gogh in one of the dream vignettes. Ang Lee's "Eat Drink Man Women" (an Academy Award nominee for best foreign film in 1994) will be screened on Wednesday. "Tokyo Story," the 1953 foreign film winner is scheduled on Thursday, and "Ju Dou," the first Chinese Academy Award nominee (1989), will be seen on Friday.</p>
        <p>The library is at 2203 Main Street and admission is free. Call 385-4162 for more information.</p>
        <p>TEAPOTS, TEAPOTS</p>
        <p>One hundred teapots on view at the Wilton Historical Society through Aug. 25 are the basis for a symposium titled "Tea in America: A Social History from the  18th to the 20th Century." It will be held on Wednesday at the society's headquarters, 249 Danbury Road, and will cost $50, including morning refreshments, a box lunch and tour of the exhibition.</p>
        <p>All the teapots are from the Norwich Castle Museum in England, where some 3,000 teapots have been collected for the Twining Teapot Gallery. Tea, coffee, chocolate and sugar were introduced into England in the mid-1600's, but it was tea that the British fancied most, generating an avalanche of teapots, teacups,  tea cozies, tea services, teaspoons, tea towels and the the dansants (tea dances) of the 20's and 30's.</p>
        <p>Russell Bastedo, curator, author and historian, will give a talk at the symposium titled "A World Government Founded on Tea: The British East India Company, 1600-1834." Ulysses Grant Dietz, curator of decorative arts at the Newark Museum, will deliver a slide-presentation, "Symbol of Gentility: The Rise of Tea and Coffee Drinking in America." Robert Mehlman, decorative arts expert,  will address "The Arts of Tea: Silver, Ceramic and Furniture Design for 300 Years of Tea and Coffee Drinking in the West."</p>
        <p>The final speaker, Jeanne Watson, executive director of the Morristown Historical Society, will present an illustrated talk on "Ladies Who Do Tea: Life in a Doll's House."</p>
        <p>On June 8, a tea seminar and tasting will be presided over by Samuel Twining, ninth-generation director of R. Twining &amp; Company Ltd. Later in the month a the  dansant will take place at the Historical Society, replete with palms, a band, cakes and sandwiches. The number for for reservations or more information is 762-7257.</p>
        <p>HORSE SHOW</p>
        <p>The annual 4-H Spring Horse Show will be in progress today from 8:30 A.M. to  about 5 P.M. at the University of Connecticut Cooperative Extension System grounds on Route 6 (Stony Hill Road) in Bethel. Admission is free; there will be food and drink and equine-oriented merchandise for sale.</p>
        <p>The competitive divisions include a traditional Kentucky Hunter Classic, a new Baby Green Hunter division for riders under 18 years of age, Adult Western,  Western Walk/Jog, Adult Walk/Jog and a Color Horse Division judged on high horse-rider points.</p>
        <p>KENT FAIR</p>
        <p>Kent is fun to visit at any time, given its profusion of galleries, boutiques, pretty old houses and scenery, but the May Fair next Saturday from 10 to 5 and Sunday from 11 to 3 is an added incentive.</p>
        <p>Almost everything will take place in and around the Library on Main Street (Route 7) in booths and under tents: a book sale, antiques and collectibles, book and antique appraisals, lots of strawberry shortcake and other home-baked items, a drawing for a surprise May basket, silent and live auctions, and discounts at restaurants.</p>
        <p>Carrying out the theme, "Recollections of Kent," old photographs of the town  have been copied for sale, some suitable for framing, others transferred onto note paper, and a series of oral histories will be presented by long-time residents at the Swift House on Route 341 at 4 P.M. on Sunday, followed by a Victorian tea.</p>
        <p>SEWING GROUP</p>
        <p>From 1 to 4 P.M. on Thursday at the Carriage Barn in Waveny Park, New Canaan, a selection of handmade items by 50 women who are members of the New Canaan Sewing Group will be for sale. Each year buyers line up at the door an hour or so beforehand to have first pick of the merchandise.</p>
        <p>Founded in 1931 and with a current membership of 163 women, the group has raised almost $820,000 for distribution to 25 agencies that serve the sick, disabled, homeless, children and families in need, historical institutions and women in domestic crises. Last year's take was $45,000.</p>
        <p>The quality of work that the women produce is rarely available in today's marketplace. Embroidered and lace-appliqued bed and table linens, doll clothes and furniture, children's knitwear, decoupage trays, boxes and bowls, needlepoint footstools and pillows. The number for more information is 966-1171.</p>
        <p>FAIRFIELD TOURS The Fairfield Historical Society has engaged four historians and lecturers to lead tours through various areas. The first is a bus tour of old trolley routes; the tour departing from the society's headquarters, 636 Old Post Road, today at  1 and 3 P.M. and is led by Charles Brilvitch. The fee is $7.50 (259-1598). On May 27, June 2, 9, 15, 23 and 30, July 14 and August 11 at 2 P.M., additional districts of the Old Post Road, Stratfield, Tunxis Hill, Black Rock and Southport will be covered in tours by Mr. Brilvitch, Bill Stansfield, Michelle Generous or Barbara Moroson. Fees are $5 for Old Post Road tours, $3 for the others. CHILDREN'S CHOIR</p>
        <p>A reception and concert by the 90-member Fairfield County Children's Choir today marks the close of the group's first year of operation. The program will segue from Renaissance chants to Bach, Schubert and a little scat singing during a rendition of "In the Mood."</p>
        <p>Curtain time at the Fairfield High School is 2 P.M. and tickets at the door are $5, or $3 for children under 10 and adults over 65. The reception, at 1 P.M., will be a mixer for the audience, the conductors and the board of directors, at which a piano will be raffled off. Admission is by donation.</p>
        <p>The choir is actually two choirs -- one open to any child with a treble voice in grades 4 through 8; the other is limited to auditioned applicants who become  members of the Chamber Singers. Rehearsals are held on Wednesdays from 6:30 to 8 P.M. at the Ludlowe Community Center in Fairfield.</p>
        <p>For those interested in trying out, auditions are scheduled for May 28 and 29 and June 4 and 5. More information is available at 576-6528.</p>
        <p>ELEANOR CHARLES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
