<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLINTON ENDORSES THE MOST RADICAL OF WELFARE TRIALS</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="851850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">1186 WORDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WISCONSIN, USA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WILLIAM JEFFERSON 'BILL' CLINTON</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Wisconsin</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Wisconsin</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E2D61339F93AA25756C0A960958260" item-length="1255" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLINTON ENDORSES THE MOST RADICAL OF WELFARE TRIALS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT PEAR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 18</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Under attack by Senator Bob Dole for having twice vetoed welfare legislation, President Clinton today gave his blessing to the most radical of all state welfare experiments, which would abolish the Federal guarantee of cash assistance for poor children in Wisconsin and replace it with wage subsidies for single mothers who work.</p>
        <p>The program, devised mainly by Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin, a Republican often mentioned as a possible running mate for Mr. Dole in this year's Presidential election, has been hailed as an innovative way to move people from welfare to work.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Under attack by Senator Bob Dole for having twice vetoed welfare legislation, President Clinton today gave his blessing to the most radical of all state welfare experiments, which would abolish the Federal guarantee of cash assistance for poor children in Wisconsin and replace it with wage subsidies for single mothers who work.</p>
        <p>The program, devised mainly by Gov. Tommy G. Thompson of Wisconsin, a Republican often mentioned as a possible running mate for Mr. Dole in this year's Presidential election, has been hailed as an innovative way to move people from welfare to work.</p>
        <p>But child-welfare advocates have strongly criticized it, saying it would harm the most vulnerable children.</p>
        <p>And a new nonpartisan study says a welfare experiment already under way in Wisconsin, the Learnfare project, which trims benefits for families with children who quit or skip school, has failed to improve school participation. [Page 20.]</p>
        <p>In his weekly radio address today, Mr. Clinton said of the proposed experiment, "Wisconsin submitted to me for approval the outlines of a sweeping welfare reform plan, one of the boldest yet attempted in America, and I'm encouraged by what I've seen so far."</p>
        <p>Under the Wisconsin plan, Mr. Clinton said, poor people would "have the dignity of earning a paycheck, not a welfare check," and "people on welfare who  can work must work immediately."</p>
        <p>The Wisconsin plan needs a Government waiver because it would abrogate many Federal guarantees to the poor. Officials at the Department of Health and Human  Services have just begun reviewing it. And Michael D. McCurry, the White House press secretary, said, "We have some legal and technical issues we will have to  work through with the state."</p>
        <p>But Rahm I. Emanuel, a White House aide who coordinates welfare policy for the President, said the state's application would win the Administration's consent. "They'll work out the details," Mr. Emanuel said, "and it will be approved."</p>
        <p>Kevin W. Keane, a spokesman for Governor Thompson, welcomed Mr. Clinton's remarks but said: "We need action by the President. We don't need more political grandstanding."</p>
        <p>Mr. Keane said he feared that Administration officials would stall by haggling with the state over details of its waiver request. "We've been experimenting for 10 years," Mr. Keane said. "We hope the President will approve 100 percent of our requests. Anything less is unacceptable. If he had not twice  vetoed welfare legislation, Wisconsin and other states would not have to go through this waiver process."</p>
        <p>And Representative John A. Boehner of Ohio, chairman of the House Republican  Conference, said he was entirely unimpressed with the President's remarks.</p>
        <p>"For Bill Clinton to take credit for the welfare reform efforts of Republican governors is a cynical deception," Mr. Boehner said. "For three years, Bill Clinton has been a noncombatant in the battle for welfare reform. He has preserved welfare as we know it with his two vetoes and has never allowed a single state to impose a real time limit on welfare recipients."</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton and Mr. Dole will each visit Wisconsin next week. Senator Dole will use his visit for a speech on welfare, just as Republicans in Congress begin work on another welfare bill that seems likely to be vetoed.</p>
        <p>As Governor of Arkansas, Mr. Clinton worked with Congress on the last major revision of Federal welfare policy, in 1988. And although he has been unable to  reach agreement with Congress on another welfare overhaul since entering the White House, he has rarely balked at any state's request for permission to experiment with welfare or Medicaid on its own.</p>
        <p>If he promptly approves the Wisconsin plan, he will have immunized himself to a large degree against Republican criticism of his welfare record and will be able to claim some political credit for the plan, as he has for the experiments  of other states that have been granted waivers.</p>
        <p>Over the last four years, the emphasis of Mr. Clinton's welfare policy has often changed, and his positions on specific proposals have been consistently unpredictable, confusing his friends and angering his foes.</p>
        <p>In the 1992 Presidential campaign, he promised to "end welfare as we know it." But he was preoccupied with health care policy in the first two years of his Administration, and Republicans seized the initiative on welfare when they took control of Congress last year. To reclaim the issue, Mr. Clinton now asserts that he has presided over "a quiet revolution" in welfare policy by allowing governors of both parties to innovate.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton endorsed an early version of Federal welfare legislation, passed  by the Senate with bipartisan support in September, even though a study by his Administration had predicted that the bill would push more than one million children into poverty. He then rejected the final version of the legislation after Marian Wright Edelman, president of the Children's Defense Fund, had told  him that the bill was an obscene violation of "God's mandate to protect the poor and the weak and the young."</p>
        <p>The President's comments today were remarkable in part for their haste: they  came little more than a week after Wisconsin had formally requested Federal approval.</p>
        <p>In signing the plan into state law on April 25, Governor Thompson criticized  the President, saying, "The only person standing in the way of welfare's demise  in Wisconsin is Bill Clinton, the man who promised America he would devote his Presidency to ending welfare."</p>
        <p>But child-welfare advocates and religious groups, some of which played a role in persuading Mr. Clinton to cast his two welfare vetoes, both in the last six months, have criticized the Wisconsin plan and say the President's approval of it would be evidence that he will approve almost any state proposal.</p>
        <p>Deborah V. Weinstein, director of the family income division at the Children's Defense Fund, said today: "We oppose the Wisconsin plan. The most disturbing element is that it would strip income away from families with children. Some will not be able to comply with the work requirements and will lose assistance. That will hurt children. Many of those who do comply will, out  of their very meager incomes, have to pay more for child care and health coverage."</p>
        <p>The Interfaith Conference of Greater Milwaukee, which represents 11 denominations, had asked the Clinton Administration to hold a hearing on the Wisconsin plan before approving it.</p>
        <p>The Rev. Quentin Meracle, chairman of the interfaith conference, said the Wisconsin plan, while helping some people, "will lead many families to live in deeper poverty" than they experience today. "Wisconsin's plan will pay many families a flat grant that no longer considers family size," said Mr. Meracle, the Milwaukee district superintendent of the United Methodist Church.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thompson, the chairman of the National Governors' Association, said the Wisconsin program was "the most dramatic change in social policy in this country in 50 years." In signing the bill, he said: "The welfare check is history. From  now on, the only check someone in Wisconsin is entitled to is the one they earn  through hard work."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
