<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Look at the Reconstruction Era</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="851484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="TRAVEL ADVISORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E2DA1339F93AA25756C0A960958260" item-length="355" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Look at the Reconstruction Era</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN A. HOLMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Perhaps no period in American history is less known or less understood than Reconstruction, the turbulent period following the Civil War when, briefly, Southern blacks gained near equality with whites. Now in Richmond, the capital of the Confederacy, the Virginia Historical Society has opened a major exhibition on Reconstruction.</p>
        <p>Called "America's Reconstruction: People and Politics After the Civil War," the exhibition contains more than 250 photographs, artifacts and other memorabilia from that era. Some are momentous, such as a copy of the 14th Amendment, which made the Federal Government the guarantor of civil rights for all Americans. Some are poignant: a ticket to the Senate impeachment trial of President Andrew Johnson, who was nearly forced from office after he clashed with Republicans over the goals and strategies of Reconstruction, and a roster from one class at a school established for newly freed slaves in which the ages  of the students range from 4 to 29.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Perhaps no period in American history is less known or less understood than Reconstruction, the turbulent period following the Civil War when, briefly, Southern blacks gained near equality with whites. Now in Richmond, the capital of the Confederacy, the Virginia Historical Society has opened a major exhibition on Reconstruction.</p>
        <p>Called "America's Reconstruction: People and Politics After the Civil War," the exhibition contains more than 250 photographs, artifacts and other memorabilia from that era. Some are momentous, such as a copy of the 14th Amendment, which made the Federal Government the guarantor of civil rights for all Americans. Some are poignant: a ticket to the Senate impeachment trial of President Andrew Johnson, who was nearly forced from office after he clashed with Republicans over the goals and strategies of Reconstruction, and a roster from one class at a school established for newly freed slaves in which the ages  of the students range from 4 to 29.</p>
        <p>The overall effect of the 3,000-square-foot exhibition is to highlight the eerie parallels between Reconstruction and the modern-day civil rights movements. There is a lithograph of blacks celebrating passage of the 15th Amendment which -- as the Voting Rights Act was to do 100 years later -- guaranteed them access to the ballot box. Also on display are a drawing of the South Carolina Constitutional Convention, where black and white delegates drew up a document that prohibited discrimination in public facilities, and an 1872 Currier &amp; Ives print of the six black Representatives and one black United States Senator who served in the 41st Congress.</p>
        <p>Some items indicate the retreat from the civil rights struggle of Reconstruction: narration explaining how Northern liberals grew tired of the battle for black rights; a broadside from the 1866 Pennsylvania campaign that charged the Freedman's Bureau with being an inefficient, corrupt antipoverty agency that was wasting taxpayers' money.</p>
        <p>The exhibition is on view daily to Oct. 1. It will then travel to several Southern cities including Columbia, S.C., Atlanta, and Charlotte, N.C. Admission is $4. Information: (804) 358-4901.</p>
        <p>TRAVEL ADVISORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
