<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Artist's Restless Search for Love, and a Place in the World</title>
    <meta content="02CTART" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1461678"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wadsworth Atheneum (Hartford, Conn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genocchio, Benjamin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hartley, Marsden (1877-1943)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906EFDB1238F931A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Artist's Restless Search for Love, and a Place in the World</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BENJAMIN GENOCCHIO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genocchio, Benjamin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Benjamin Genocchio reviews works by Marsden Hartley at Wadsworth Atheneum Museum, Hartford, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TIMING is everything, or so they say. It was certainly the case for Marsden Hartley (1877-1943), who was so confident of his paintings celebrating pre-war Berlin and the pageantry of the German military that he expected to be showered with praise after his return to New York from Berlin in 1915 to escape the war. But he failed to realize that anti-German feeling had swept the country. Hartley's paintings were condemned as pro-German, and shunned.</p>
        <p>The sad part of this is that those paintings were among the most advanced modernist works done, up to then, by an American. Had his timing been better, the avant garde, still bleary-eyed over the innovations of the 1913 Armory Show, when European modern art was first introduced to Americans, might have greeted Hartley as a hero. But it was not to be. The frosty reception crushed his confidence. Despondent, he retreated to more conventional landscape and still-life painting in what critics have long regarded as a fatal stylistic regression.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TIMING is everything, or so they say. It was certainly the case for Marsden Hartley (1877-1943), who was so confident of his paintings celebrating pre-war Berlin and the pageantry of the German military that he expected to be showered with praise after his return to New York from Berlin in 1915 to escape the war. But he failed to realize that anti-German feeling had swept the country. Hartley's paintings were condemned as pro-German, and shunned.</p>
        <p>The sad part of this is that those paintings were among the most advanced modernist works done, up to then, by an American. Had his timing been better, the avant garde, still bleary-eyed over the innovations of the 1913 Armory Show, when European modern art was first introduced to Americans, might have greeted Hartley as a hero. But it was not to be. The frosty reception crushed his confidence. Despondent, he retreated to more conventional landscape and still-life painting in what critics have long regarded as a fatal stylistic regression.</p>
        <p>Is there more to Hartley's career than his early German paintings? That's the gambit of this exhaustive and, in the end, exhausting retrospective at the Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art in Hartford. Organized by Elizabeth Mankin Kornhauser, the Wadsworth's chief curator, it is the first exhibition in over 20 years to explore the full range of his work, including previously neglected paintings of France, his paeans to Mount Katahdin in Maine, where he was born, and works from his travels in New Mexico and Mexico. The exhibition also comes with some worthwhile new scholarship.</p>
        <p>Hung chronologically, the exhibition begins with a series of early Maine landscapes, like ''Storm Clouds, Maine'' (1906-07) and ''Carnival of Autumn'' (1908). These are views of mountains with overhanging cloud forms, mostly, painted with short, broken strokes showing the influence of Cézanne and Albert Pinkham Ryder. They are crudely composed, but convey a haunting love of the landscape and mystical bent, qualities that recur throughout Hartley's later paintings.</p>
        <p>Hartley's Maine landscapes did not sell well. In a fit of depression, he packed his bags and headed for Europe in 1912. He gravitated to Paris, where he hung out with Gertrude Stein and fell under the spell of Picasso and Cubism. He was also introduced to the paintings and writings of the Russian émigré Wassily Kandinsky, whose book, ''On the Spiritual in Art'' (1910), resonated with his own spiritual yearnings. Hartley's favorite author was Walt Whitman.</p>
        <p>But most important, Hartley met a young German military officer, Karl von Freyburg, with whom he fell in love. Little is known about von Freyburg, or his relationship with Hartley, although what is certain is that Hartley followed von Freyburg to Berlin in 1913, where he began to paint distinctive semi-abstract and brilliantly colorful paintings that combine a fascination for the jarring modernity of Berlin and its pre-war military pageantry with mystical motifs. They look like zany wrapping paper.</p>
        <p>It is wonderful to see Hartley's major paintings from this period together in one room, including ''The Warriors'' (1913), ''Military'' (1913), ''Berlin Ante-War'' (1914), ''The Aero'' (circa 1914) and ''Himmel'' (circa 1914-15). Their formal inventiveness and imaginative brilliance is undeniable, the artist abandoning representational realism for personal and symbolic abstractions of imagery drawn from the agitated modernist city around him. Hartley, you get the feeling, is punch-drunk on the pomp, power and pageantry of the German imperial capitol.</p>
        <p>The outbreak of war changed everything. Hartley's celebration of military pageantry with handsome soldiers in bright uniforms and feathered helmets gave way to the bitter reality of dead bodies in ditches. One of those who fell was von Freyburg. Hartley was devastated, although channeled his grief into a series of tightly structured, symbolic paintings known as the War Motifs. The first in the series, and an unmitigated masterpiece, is ''Portrait of a German Officer'' (1914). Painted with passion and vibrancy, it is a stirring elegy to his lost lover.</p>
        <p>In low spirits over the death of von Fryburg, Hartley returned to New York. But his home country was not ready for him, and in some ways never would be. He was a restless innovator and internationalist, as well as a gay man, living in an era of xenophobic resentment and crushing conservatism. For the next 20 years, he sought solace in travel, to New Mexico, Paris, Berlin, Mexico, Bermuda, Nova Scotia, and many other places.</p>
        <p>Hartley's most innovative paintings during this time were elemental, expressionist studies of the boulder-strewn Dogtown Common landscape near Gloucester, Mass., done in 1931-36. A challenge to the placid pastoral scenes of the Regionalist painters, then enjoying widespread acclaim, these rough, direct, boldly colored and emotionally gripping pictures prefigure the archaic landscapes and primitive figure studies Hartley produced during the last 10 years of his life. They also announce a re-connection to his native soil.</p>
        <p>But it was loss, once again, that was to be a catalyst for Hartley's best work. In 1935 the artist traveled to Nova Scotia where he found lodgings with a local fishing family on East Point Island. He had been living with the family about a year when their two sons and a cousin were drowned after their boat capsized and sunk in a storm. Hartley had fallen in love with one of the boys, and sought to memorialize their death in a series of seascapes and naïve portraits like ''Adelard the Drowned, Master of the 'Phantom''' (circa 1938-39). One of his first paintings on the theme was ''Northern Seascape, Off the Banks'' (1936), a dark and sorrowful picture that ranks among his best works.</p>
        <p>Hartley was the most gifted of the early American modernists, as the paintings in this panoramic exhibition attest. But I also get the sense that he was deeply conflicted, haunted by loss and intense feelings of estrangement from others. He found a kind of peace toward the end of his life in Maine, the landscape of his youth, where he became captivated by the stormy coast and bleak hinterland around Mount Katahdin. Here, if anywhere, he might have called home.</p>
        <p>''Marsden Hartley'' is at the Wadsworth Atheneum Museum of Art, 600 Main Street, Hartford, through April 20. Information: (860)278-2670. The show will be at the Phillips Collection, Washington, from June 7 through Sept. 7, and the Nelson-Atkins Museum of Art, Kansas City, Mo., from Oct. 11 through Jan. 11.</p>
        <p>ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
