<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ambiguous Light</title>
    <meta content="02UNSWORT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/02/books/review/02UNSWORT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1461820"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Unsworth, Barry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kalfus, Ken</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Commissariat of Enlightenment, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Kalfus, Ken</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980CE0D81E30F931A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1248" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ambiguous Light</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'The Commissariat of Enlightenment': The Power to Reconstitute History</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Barry Unsworth</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Unsworth, Barry</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barry Unsworth reviews book The Commissariat of Enlightenment by Ken Kalfus; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE COMMISSARIAT</p>
        <p>OF ENLIGHTENMENT</p>
        <p>By Ken Kalfus.</p>
        <p>295 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Ecco/HarperCollins Publishers. $24.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ken Kalfus's novel is about images -- religious icons, posters, films -- in postrevolutionary Russia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE COMMISSARIAT</p>
        <p>OF ENLIGHTENMENT</p>
        <p>By Ken Kalfus.</p>
        <p>295 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Ecco/HarperCollins Publishers. $24.95.</p>
        <p>IT is 1910. Leo Tolstoy lies dying in the stationmaster's house at the railway station of Astapovo, a remote village in provincial Russia. Journalists from all over the world have gathered at this unlikely place, along with a motley crowd of eccentrics and opportunists, all hoping to derive some personal advantage from the celebrated novelist's last hours. Among this waiting throng are Gribshin, a young cinematographer with Pathé Frères, who intends to get some shots of the count on his deathbed, and so perpetuate him on celluloid, and the ghoulish Vorobev, who wants to perpetuate him in the flesh by injecting him with embalming fluids. Vorobev was later to use his skills on Lenin, but he was not actually present at Astapovo, nor was Lenin himself, nor Stalin, both of whom, however, make brief appearances. It doesn't matter, in the impeccable logic of the novel, whether they were actually there or not: they were there in spirit, both masters in the burgeoning 20th-century art of refashioning history through the manipulation of images. The action at Astapovo occupies the first half of the book. From here, in shorter sections, we move through later phases in the bleak tragicomedy of post-revolutionary Russia, ending in 1924 with the death of Lenin, whose embalming, in a scene combining the macabre and the burlesque, begins while he is still alive.</p>
        <p>This is a novel about images of one sort or another -- religious, political, erotic -- and about the power they exercise over our lives and the light, both physical and psychological, in which we see them. Some of the strongest and most effective scenes involve the ambiguous nature of light, at once deceiving and revealing, benign and destructive. The theme makes its appearance early. When the train containing Gribshin and Vorobev and the British journalist Khaitover comes through the darkness and approaches Astapovo station, Gribshin sees a radiance in the sky, ''much whiter than sunlight.'' Something happens inside the coach. ''First he felt the heat. The coach's walls burned white. Pocks on the face of an adjacent passenger seemed to be deepened by the shadows cast by the conflagration until the light became so intense that the man's face dissolved, leaving only his eyebrows and the idea of the man.'' When they alight on the platform, they find it blindingly illuminated by powerful cinematic lights mounted on tall tripods.</p>
        <p>The same effects are achieved in the striking scene in which Gribshin, who has gone through a sort of identity change and now calls himself Astapov and is a Bolshevik official in the Commissariat of Enlightenment, is struggling to gain the soul of the Russian peasant and free him from centuries of ignorance and superstition. Gribshin/Astapov sets up lights of the same powerful sort in a village church. In the age-old dimness of the interior there is a sudden explosion of light. The watching peasants are at first blinded; then they see every corner of the church mercilessly lighted up, stripped of mystery: ''The radiance was a viscid element, oozing into every corner and space of the church, into chinks, crevices, pitted surfaces, and human pores.'' Heat from the lamps starts to melt the surface of the icons. ''The pictures assumed unfamiliar hues, none of them natural. As the paint burned, the ghosts behind the icons emerged. . . . The figures of the saints simplified until they resembled newspaper cartoons or caricatures.'' The commissar's plan backfires, but he has a final resource that illustrates one of the most terrible lessons of our time: if the images cannot be controlled, destroy them, obliterate the traces, leave only the evidence of power.</p>
        <p>It is principally Gribshin/Astapov who carries the burden of human consciousness through this novel, being the only character whose experience runs all the way through it, and the only one who has anything approaching an inner life. And it is here that there are some difficulties in appreciation, because this inner life of his, as presented to the reader, is of the sketchiest sort. Indeed, he can hardly be said to exist as a moral being at all, if the characteristic of a moral being is to question one's motives. It is quite a while since I read a novel, of the kind we call serious or literary, whose protagonist shows so little capacity for communing with himself -- or with others, for that matter. Whenever an occasion for this occurs, the author seems deliberately to avoid exploiting it.</p>
        <p>To take one example among many, a formative experience in the young Gribshin's life is an encounter with a mysterious stranger, referred to as the Caucasian. (He turns out to be Stalin.) The Caucasian makes some observations about history and society and the importance of the cinema; Gribshin says almost nothing. But as they are about to part -- and only then -- it is revealed to the reader that the young man has been deeply affected: ''They understood each other. The Caucasian was privy to thoughts and ambitions that Gribshin had yet to articulate. 'What you say is the truth,' Gribshin whispered, his lips parched.''</p>
        <p>Like a bolt from the blue, like something that might happen on the road to Damascus. But Saul's conversion, as given to us in the Acts of the Apostles, has memorable life and force, whereas here there is no attempt whatever to dramatize the encounter, to register anything taking place in the minds of either man. Why on earth should we believe it? Why should a traveled and intelligent young man take a step toward fanaticism at this point? Why doesn't he see the duplicity in the other's words? Or is the duplicity itself the revelation? The novel provides no answer to such questions because there is no one in the novel to ask them.</p>
        <p>But in fiction, as in life, a lack is not necessarily a defect. It is not moral complexity or clashes of opinion that interest Ken Kalfus, but the driving force of single ideas, the power of images to reconstitute what we call history. The absence of wavering, of self-questioning, gives a relentless impetus to the narrative that makes this novel compelling to read. Some scenes of action and description are realized so vividly that they almost have the force of hallucination. There is a recurrent vein of dark humor, and a grim sense of the lethal absurdities of totalitarian politics. No one in this book looks at anyone else's face or listens to anyone else's voice, except out of fear or coercion. People's lives are shaped by images -- religious icon, propaganda poster, film. So they become in the end not much distinguishable from images themselves, manipulated elements in the dynamic of history, looking forward to our own time and the welter of mind-softening images in which we live. ''The Commissariat of Enlightenment'' is a chilling novel, but the imaginative energy that runs through it gives it a rare quality of distinction.</p>
        <p>Barry Unsworth's novels include ''Songs of the Kings,'' which will be published this spring, and ''Losing Nelson.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Barry Unsworth's novels include ''Songs of the Kings,'' which will be published this spring, and ''Losing Nelson.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
