<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Star Intellectual Who Theorized About the Ordinary</title>
    <meta content="02GIBS$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/02/arts/design/02GIBS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1461381"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="ART/ARCHITECTURE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pompidou Center (Paris)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barthes, Roland (1916-1980)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gibson, Michael F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Barthes, Roland</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E7D91039F931A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1242" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Star Intellectual Who Theorized About the Ordinary</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Star Intellectual Who Theorized About the Ordinary</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL F. GIBSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gibson, Michael F</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of French writer and artist Roland Barthes traces his life and career; his works are on exhibition at Pompidou Center, Paris; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROLAND BARTHES, a brilliant, sensitive man and an original theoretician of language and society, was a star of the French intellectual firmament when, in February 1980, a car jumped a curb here and fatally injured him as he left the Collège de France, where he had been lecturing. He was 64.</p>
        <p>Turning his generally quiet existence and intricate theory of language into the sort of stuff that can be visualized in a museum was surely a challenge, but Marianne Alphant and Nathalie Léger have put together a thoroughly elegant exhibition at the Pompidou Center devoted to Barthes's life and work. The presentation, containing videos, taped interviews, film clips, photographs and work notes, is clever and precious and admirably suited to its clever, precious subject.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Paris exhibition illuminates the life and work of Roland Barthes, a star of the French intellectual firmament who was an original theoretician of language and society.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROLAND BARTHES, a brilliant, sensitive man and an original theoretician of language and society, was a star of the French intellectual firmament when, in February 1980, a car jumped a curb here and fatally injured him as he left the Collège de France, where he had been lecturing. He was 64.</p>
        <p>Turning his generally quiet existence and intricate theory of language into the sort of stuff that can be visualized in a museum was surely a challenge, but Marianne Alphant and Nathalie Léger have put together a thoroughly elegant exhibition at the Pompidou Center devoted to Barthes's life and work. The presentation, containing videos, taped interviews, film clips, photographs and work notes, is clever and precious and admirably suited to its clever, precious subject.</p>
        <p>To do justice to Barthes, the curators had to venture into the various areas he himself touched upon: language, fashion and daily life as a system of signs, beginning with the series of wonderfully written and witty articles that brought Barthes to public attention in 1956. They were subsequently published in a book titled ''Mythologies.''</p>
        <p>The essays' originality lay in their analysis of various mundane events and things: subjects of feature articles in illustrated magazines, the idiom of advertising for detergents and plastics, the public persona of the Abbé Pierre, the style of Billy Graham's evangelizing in Paris, the abundance of sweat on the faces of great Romans in Joseph L. Mankiewicz's ''Julius Caesar'' or the conception of the Citroën DS. To Barthes, these were systems of signs and transmitters of social ''myths'' or, more simply, of commonplaces. Many of these objects, including a black DS, like the one Charles de Gaulle used, make up the first part of the exhibition.</p>
        <p>But in the late 50's Barthes was still showing symptoms of the postwar neurosis of French society. As a result, the austere tenets of his theory of language and the commonplaces of Marxism, which were pervasive then, blend rather strangely at times with his innate wit and courtesy. Many essays in ''Mythologies,'' for example, savage the unfortunate petit-bourgeois, casting him in the role of the heretic or the sinner of former days. Barthes was brilliantly on the mark, however, when criticizing the language of the self-styled spokesman of ''grass-roots'' France, Pierre Poujade, one of the first mentors of the current far-right bogeyman, Jean-Marie Le Pen.</p>
        <p>Barthes would, in due course, discard such militant language. Indeed, one thing the exhibition makes palpable is the distance France has come since the postwar years, when it was coping with the painful contradictions of recent history but was still mentally rooted in a prewar outlook. Barthes's critique of the ''grande bourgeoisie'' is no doubt a reflection of this cumbersome heritage, though a further subtext appears to have been his intimate grievance against his own class, which had callously left his mother to manage on her own after her husband, a naval officer, died at sea in 1916.</p>
        <p>In the 50's, when Barthes first came into public view, France was still locked into the conspiratorial mood of the Algerian war and political life was polarized, a condition that was dispelled only after François Mitterrand was elected president in 1981. In those days, many French intellectuals found reassurance in doctrinaire positions (''I'd rather be wrong with Sartre than right with Raymond Aron'') and based their opinions on high principles rather than on observable fact. The tremendous changes that have taken place in France since then -- starting with the student riots of 1968 but ending in a general rightward drift -- make Barthes occasional militant statements look jarringly dated today.</p>
        <p>But these represent only a moment in his career, and when he was criticized for not speaking up in favor of Maoism after his return from China in 1973 (with his Maoist friends from the magazine Tel Quel), he responded with a declaration of principle against political posturing by intellectuals. ''I claim indirection as the only locus of the intellectual,'' he declared.</p>
        <p>Barthes was in subtle ways an outsider, being a homosexual with a Protestant background (in a prudish and Catholic France) and having a personal account to settle, in his mother's name, with the bourgeois mind-set. This is no doubt part of what makes him original and interesting to us.</p>
        <p>He was a rather accomplished pianist and took a close interest in art, admiring artists like Cy Twombly, Saul Steinberg and Bernard Requichot (a schizophrenic who committed suicide in 1961). I met Barthes once, in the 70's, to talk about Requichot, and was impressed by his courteous warmth. Significantly, all the contemporary artists that interested him sought to blend painting with the written word, as sometimes happens in Japanese art.</p>
        <p>Barthes also traveled to Japan and returned with his own perspective on the country, one that is more revealing of the man than of the land. He thought he glimpsed in Japanese culture a means of escaping from what he termed ''the mental closure of the West,'' finding in Japan ''a world free of meaning.'' His book on Japan is titled ''The Empire of Signs,'' and he allowed that the title fits to the extent that, in Japan, ''the signs are empty and the ritual is without a God.''</p>
        <p>Barthes indulged briefly in painting (he stopped just after his mother's death), and though his work reveals no great merit on its own, exhibition space is rightly devoted to his easy, abstract productions of those years.</p>
        <p>The show includes an impressive number of video displays with period documents; interviews of eminent intellectuals of the day, Claude Lévi-Strauss among them; recent interviews of Barthes's childhood friends, disciples and lovers (he was a bon vivant with a penchant for diets, one reveals); a clip from ''A Night at the Opera,'' which he used to illustrate a point of his semiotic theories; an abundance of recordings of Barthes's own voice; and an intricate interactive video illustrating his theory of fashion.</p>
        <p>The show closes with a wall covered with hundreds of index cards -- a spectacular materialization of his intellectual labor -- and a fascinating collection of photographic documents and notes that Barthes assembled for his lectures at the Collège de France. The photos show the real-life counterparts of many of Proust's fictional figures, with information Barthes gleaned about each one.</p>
        <p>The exhibition, with its abundant videos, recordings of his voice and handwritten or typewritten documents, cannot be skimmed over. A knowledge of French also helps, of course, for all this material cumulatively and subtly reveals the remarkable mind and engaging personality of a man who once, elliptically and quite untranslatably, defined politeness as ''un congé discret donné a toute capture'' -- ''a gentle way of turning away the indiscrete.''</p>
        <p>Roland Barthes  Pompidou Center, Paris.  Through March 10.</p>
        <p>ART/ARCHITECTURE Michael F. Gibson is an art critic living in Paris.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael F. Gibson is an art critic living in Paris.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
