<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York Gives Up Its Hunt For Top Parking Scofflaws</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="463761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCOFFLAWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINES (PENALTIES)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PARKING VIOLATIONS BUREAU (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fines (Penalties)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2D71030F93AA15754C0A967958260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York Gives Up Its Hunt For Top Parking Scofflaws</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARRON, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York City Parking Violations Bureau is giving up on collecting more than $2.15 million in unpaid parking tickets from 28 of the city's top 44 scofflaws.</p>
        <p>Agency officials say it is just not worth the trouble. For one thing, some of them apparently do not exist -- like the city's No. 1 scofflaw, who owes $182,212 for 2,807 parking tickets on 36 cars registered under a fake identity at a false address.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New York City Parking Violations Bureau is giving up on collecting more than $2.15 million in unpaid parking tickets from 28 of the city's top 44 scofflaws.</p>
        <p>Agency officials say it is just not worth the trouble. For one thing, some of them apparently do not exist -- like the city's No. 1 scofflaw, who owes $182,212 for 2,807 parking tickets on 36 cars registered under a fake identity at a false address.</p>
        <p>The woman in whose name the ticketed cars were registered, Sylvia Matos of Manhattan, convinced agency officials more than a year ago that she had a clean record.</p>
        <p>Since then, despite repeated searches by the agency's own investigators, an outside credit-rating service and sheriff's deputies, the city has not been able to determine who used her name or racked up all the tickets. Officials say that someone stole her resident-alien card in the mid-1980's and used that as proof of identification to register the cars that got the tickets.  'Just Can't Get to It'</p>
        <p>Now officials say that it would cost more to continue trying to find the real No. 1 or the other offenders, or to find out who they really are, than simply to write off the debts. Officials suspect that many of the culprits are unlicensed cab operators who shuffle license plates from car to car. That makes it difficult for the agency to trace the daily comings and goings of heavily ticketed cars and to send in enforcement agents.</p>
        <p>"It's like the pot of gold at the end of the rainbow," said Lucius J. Riccio, who, as Transportation Commissioner, supervises the Parking Violations Bureau. "You just can't get to it."</p>
        <p>Motorists with mere handfuls of unpaid tickets, instead of bushel baskets full, should not get any ideas, the bureau says. Officials say they are not reducing efforts to track down delinquents among the 12 million outstanding parking summonses in the bureau's computers. Rather, they say they are just following commonly accepted debt-collection procedures. Bureau officials say even commercial collection agencies cannot find every last debtor.</p>
        <p>"The dollar amounts are pretty impressive: 182,000 here, 130,000 there," said Joseph DePlasco, a Transportation Department spokesman. "These are the visible ones that would give us a fast buck if we could get them, but we're spending a lot of money trying to get something we'll never see."</p>
        <p>Whether they will ever see any money from the No. 2 scofflaw, who is among the 13 top-owing motorists whom the city has not stopped trying to hunt down, is also an open question. The parking bureau stopped the manhunt for the 28 because they had been issued no summonses since the beginning of the year. But the No. 2 delinquent is still on the list because one of the cars involved was ticketed in February, 18 months after the bureau assigned the case to a collection agency and a year after sheriff's deputies tried to find the owner.  'A False Impression'</p>
        <p>The agency says taking the 28 deadbeats off its scofflaw files will promote efficiency.</p>
        <p>"We waste our efforts and create a false impression if we continue to pursue this type of debt, which is really uncollectible," said Joseph Spencer, the director of the parking bureau. "The fact is many of these cases are the result of fraud or other scams."</p>
        <p>Like the No. 1 parking-ticket delinquent, No. 2 also appears to be using a bogus address. The Parking Violations Bureau identified No. 2 as Charles Rivera of 142 Lenol Place in Lynbrook, L.I., with 2,962 parking tickets on 88 cars and a debt of $165,729. Lynbrook has a Lenox Avenue, a Leroy Place and a Lyon Place, but no Lenol Place.</p>
        <p>With that many unpaid parking tickets, he has been sent a blizzard of past-due notices. The agency's computers spewed out at least 9,000 and sent them off by certified mail before the case was referred to the sheriff's office, which sent out its own forest-felling barrage of certified letters.</p>
        <p>The bureau had a credit-reporting service check whether someone by that name charged anything in October 1989 -- a sign that the car might be in a given neighborhood -- but to no avail. Nor were there any records of assets, loans or other useful leads for the parking bureau's 65 sleuths.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
