<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PRO FOOTBALL: Sports of The Times; The Green Monsters Of 'the Meadowlands'</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="711703"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK JETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, DAVE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E6D9173BF931A2575AC0A962958260" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PRO FOOTBALL: Sports of The Times; The Green Monsters Of 'the Meadowlands'</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>OUTSIDE the Jets' locker room, Pete Carroll was holding a football. Surely it was his "game ball" for the 25-22 overtime victory over the Denver Broncos, but it wasn't.</p>
        <p>"The star of the day," the Jets' coach was saying now, "was the people in the stands. They went nuts. They went crazy about our football team and the way we played and they hung with us when it looked a little bit bleak. They brought us out of that fourth quarter."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>OUTSIDE the Jets' locker room, Pete Carroll was holding a football. Surely it was his "game ball" for the 25-22 overtime victory over the Denver Broncos, but it wasn't.</p>
        <p>"The star of the day," the Jets' coach was saying now, "was the people in the stands. They went nuts. They went crazy about our football team and the way we played and they hung with us when it looked a little bit bleak. They brought us out of that fourth quarter."</p>
        <p>Then he smiled, held up the ball and said: "We have a game ball for the fans here, but I don't know what we'll do with it. Maybe just keep it around."</p>
        <p>If only it could be cut up into 73,436 pieces.</p>
        <p>That was yesterday's attendance in what the Jets like to call "the Meadowlands," not Giants Stadium. And if the Jets qualify for the Super Bowl XXIX playoffs, maybe the Jets should send a real "game ball" to each of their season-ticket subscribers as well as one to their new team psychologist, Pete Carroll himself.</p>
        <p>"Pete has done a great job convincing us that when they put down the Jets' end zones here, it's our field," Boomer Esiason said. "He's done a great psych job."</p>
        <p>For the first time since 1987 and for only the fifth time in their 36 seasons, the Jets are off to a 2-0 start. But it's not all psychology. It's a sturdy defense that the rookie head coach still supervises. And it's the passing game that the new offensive coordinator, Ray Sherman, has humming on eight cylinders, alias eight receivers.</p>
        <p>According to several Jets, the nuances of Sherman's passing game are too subtle to explain in simple words.</p>
        <p>"He's calling more shots down the field," Rob Moore said. "He's changed the routes to get a receiver open."</p>
        <p>"He's more aggressive," Johnny Mitchell said. "He's calling some good plays at the right time."</p>
        <p>"He's brought some of the finer points we didn't have last year," Johnny Johnson said. "The way we change the routes to get a receiver open."</p>
        <p>"He didn't change the passing game much from last year," Esiason said. "He just tweaked it a little bit."</p>
        <p>Esiason might have been trying to protect Bruce Coslet, his longtime pal who was dismissed after last season's 8-8 finish. But to anyone who remembers how over four consecutive games late last season the Jets scored only one touchdown (but somehow managed to win twice), yesterday's passing game seemed sharper. As the stat sheet showed.</p>
        <p>Esiason completed 26 of 37 passes for 297 yards and 2 touchdowns, while spreading the ball around. Moore caught 9 for 147 yards and 1 touchdown, Art Monk 4 for 52 yards, Mitchell 4 for 41 yards, Johnson 3 for 27 yards, Richie Anderson 3 for 22 yards, Stevie Anderson 1 for 5 yards, Anthony Johnson 1 for 2 yards, Fred Baxter 1 for a 1-yard touchdown.</p>
        <p>It's not a coincidence. Sherman joined the Jets after having been the 49ers' wide receiver coach the previous two years, their running-back coach the year before.</p>
        <p>"Some of the short passes we completed," Esiason said. "Steve Young, Joe Montana and Jerry Rice have been living off that: hitting the receiver underneath."</p>
        <p>Outside, those big red letters still shouted "Giants Stadium," but to the Jets, it's "the Meadowlands." As if Giants Stadium had somehow disappeared. As if the Jets had constructed their own Meadowlands Stadium.</p>
        <p>But by any other name, this stadium by the swamp has seldom smelled as sweet as it did yesterday. Or sounded as sweet.</p>
        <p>Over the last 10 seasons the Jets' record here has been 38-41-1, hardly conducive to playoff dreams, much less Super Bowl hallucinations. Since their last winning season (8-7-1) and last winning record in "the Meadowlands" (5-2-1) in 1988, their ledger here had been 14-26.</p>
        <p>No wonder that Pete Carroll threw down the gauntlet last week. Not so much to the Jets' fans as to his Jets players.</p>
        <p>"We need to play well to get the fans behind us," Carroll said. "We need their help and we need to make this a place where the Jets are very tough to beat. Our fans need something. They desperately need something."</p>
        <p>For a change, the Jets provided that "something," when their fans needed it to create hope early in the season. But the Jets' players themselves needed that "something" even more.</p>
        <p>With the euphoria of their 23-3 triumph in Buffalo still lingering, the Jets now have an opportunity to sweep their Triple Quarterback Challenge (Jim Kelly, John Elway and Dan Marino).</p>
        <p>"Somewhere down the road," Pete Carroll said last week, "someone will say, 'same ol' Jets' because we'll be kicking people around again."</p>
        <p>The construction of that road may have begun. And when it's finally built, it will go through "the Meadowlands," not Giants Stadium.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
