<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Crew Is Back At Its Base To Cheers Of Welcome</title>
    <meta content="15ARRI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/15/world/15ARRI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1285925"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="COLLISION WITH CHINA: THE RETURN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Hawaii</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Navies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Hawaii</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Goodland</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Norfolk</location>
        <location class="online_producer">La Mesa</location>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Pampa</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Oak Harbor</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Pentagon</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE5DB1131F936A25757C0A9679C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Crew Is Back At Its Base To Cheers Of Welcome</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY</byline>
      <dateline>OAK HARBOR, Wash., April 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Navy crew held for 11 days in China returned home to a heroes' welcome today, reuniting with relatives and basking under cheers from thousands of area residents at an afternoon arrival ceremony.</p>
        <p>As they exited a jetliner that carried them from Hawaii to the Whidbey Island Naval Air Station, their home base, the crew of 21 men and 3 women waved back to a sea of flag-wavers who had waited hours for the plane to land.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Navy crew held for 11 days in China returned home to a heroes' welcome today, reuniting with relatives and basking under cheers from thousands of area residents at an afternoon arrival ceremony.</p>
        <p>As they exited a jetliner that carried them from Hawaii to the Whidbey Island Naval Air Station, their home base, the crew of 21 men and 3 women waved back to a sea of flag-wavers who had waited hours for the plane to land.</p>
        <p>''I had no idea what kind of welcome we would receive,'' said Lt. j.g. Jeffrey Vignery of Goodland, Kan. ''I can say I've never felt so proud to be an American in my life.''</p>
        <p>Led by Lt. Shane Osborn, the mission commander from Norfolk, Neb., the crew members shook hands with dignitaries and bear-hugged loved ones they had not seen in months. In an hour-long ceremony, they were congratulated by high-ranking Navy officials and leaders from the state of Washington, including Gov. Gary Locke. A crowd estimated at 7,000 interrupted countless times with hearty applause.</p>
        <p>Later, speaking to reporters, crew members surrounded by their families thanked officials in the Bush administration for getting them safely home and the American public for its support, prayers and the big welcome here.</p>
        <p>The crowd here saved its biggest cheers for Lieutenant Osborn. Yet many returnees said all crew members played a crucial role in the mission, from destroying sensitive equipment before the Chinese searched the plane to lifting spirits that occasionally sagged during the detention.</p>
        <p>''Definitely, there were moments of shock and disbelief at what was going on,'' said Lt. Patrick Honeck of La Mesa, Calif., adding that when Lieutenant Osborn was fighting to level the plane as it dived, ''you didn't have time to think about a lot of what ifs.''</p>
        <p>Lt. j.g. Regina Kauffman of Warminster, Pa., the navigator, said she did not realize the extent of damage to the plane until she and the others walked off. The collision caused damage to one propeller, disabling an engine, knocked off the nose cone and punctured the plane's body, causing a loss of air pressure inside.</p>
        <p>''When I saw that the nose cone was off, I was pretty surprised,'' Lieutenant Kauffman said. ''With all the damage, I felt we were pretty lucky.''</p>
        <p>Josef Edmunds of Davis, Calif., a cryptologic technician, said when the plane landed and the Chinese authorities approached, ''I was so happy to be alive, I had a big grin on my face.''</p>
        <p>Choosing words carefully in response to questions about their interactions with the Chinese on Hainan island, the crew members said they were treated reasonably well, ate a steady diet of rice and were pressed repeatedly to apologize for their actions.</p>
        <p>''They asked us for an apology the same as they were asking the United States government,'' said Lt. j.g. Richard Payne of Pampa, Tex. ''By the time they made their request, we had already spoken to General Sealock, who told us what President Bush's response was and we used those same words.''</p>
        <p>Brig Gen. Neal Sealock is the American defense attaché who met with the crew during the detention.</p>
        <p>The crew's ordeal began on April 1 over the South China Sea when a Chinese F-8 jet fighter collided with the American EP-3E surveillance plane, sending it into a momentary nosedive in which it dropped 7,500 feet in about a minute. The Chinese jet broke in two and crashed into the sea, apparently killing the pilot, Wang Wei. Lieutenant Osborn managed to level his aircraft and land safely at a Chinese military base on Hainan island, where the crew was quickly detained until officials from both countries negotiated the terms of the crew's release last week.</p>
        <p>The Americans left China on Thursday for a brief stopover in Guam before continuing on to Hickham Air Force Base on Oahu, where they took off early this morning for the final leg of their return.</p>
        <p>The obvious reverence expressed by town residents reflected a 60-year-old relationship between the huge naval base and the town of Oak Harbor, where 60 percent of the 21,000 residents are affiliated in some manner with the Navy.</p>
        <p>Mayor Patricia A. Cohen said the base and the town had become so inextricably linked that probably neither could function well without the other.</p>
        <p>''We take pride in the relationship,'' she said. ''When these folks walk off the base, they're our soccer coaches and our softball coaches, and their spouses are our deacons and our teachers. They define who we are as a community.''</p>
        <p>COLLISION WITH CHINA: THE RETURN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
