<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>ECONOMY SLOWED IN FIRST QUARTER</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="611888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEADING ECONOMIC INDICATORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER BEHAVIOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GROSS NATIONAL PRODUCT (GNP)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMERCE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASAR, SYLVIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gross National Product (GNP)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DB1F3FF93AA15756C0A965958260" item-length="1135" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>ECONOMY SLOWED IN FIRST QUARTER</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SYLVIA NASAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASAR, SYLVIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Growth in the United States economy slowed to a near-standstill in the winter while inflation sped up, the Commerce Department reported yesterday in its second look at economic performance between January and March.</p>
        <p>The report prompted investors to sell stocks, stirred fears of a tighter monetary policy and revived talk of that 1970's scourge, stagflation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Growth in the United States economy slowed to a near-standstill in the winter while inflation sped up, the Commerce Department reported yesterday in its second look at economic performance between January and March.</p>
        <p>The report prompted investors to sell stocks, stirred fears of a tighter monetary policy and revived talk of that 1970's scourge, stagflation.</p>
        <p>The gross domestic product expanded at a barely perceptible rate of nine-tenths of 1 percent in the first quarter -- the slowest pace since six-tenths of 1 percent in the fourth quarter of 1991 and a sharp slowdown from the 4 percent pace of last year's second half. Surge in Imports</p>
        <p>The revised rate was just half the meager 1.8 percent first-quarter rate that the Commerce Department reported a month ago. A big surge in imports -- much of which apparently went unsold and ended up in inventories -- accounted for the downward revision in growth.</p>
        <p>But first-quarter inflation was at its highest since a 4.9 percent rate in the first quarter of 1991. In the latest quarter, the fixed-weight G.D.P. deflator -- the broadest inflation measure -- rose at a 4.2 percent annual rate, the Commerce Department said, the same as estimated a month ago. That compared with 3.4 percent last fall and 2.2 percent in the summer.</p>
        <p>Clinton Administration officials pointed to the revised G.D.P. data and the inflation figures as reasons for advancing their agenda of economic remedies.</p>
        <p>"This shows why we needed the President's stimulus package to get the economy rolling for the short term," Jack F. DeVore Jr., the chief Treasury Department spokesman, said. "If we fail to enact his deficit reduction program, we're going to see the same kind of economic problems over the long term."</p>
        <p>Last month, President Clinton's proposal to spend nearly $20 billion for jobs and public works projects was killed by a filibuster in the Senate. But his budget measure calling for tax increases and other measures to cut the deficit was approved by the House Thursday night.</p>
        <p>Economists said fear of higher taxes and the uncertainty over the impact of the Administration's health-care proposals were the main reasons behind the slow growth.</p>
        <p>Sizable revisions in G.D.P. figures like those announced yesterday are not unusual. Many of the components of gross domestic product -- the sum of all goods and services produced within United States -- are measured only indirectly and the estimates can change as fresh data are gathered.</p>
        <p>For example, export and import figures for March were not available when the initial first-quarter G.D.P. report was issued in late April, so the quarterly trade figures had to be estimated based on the performance of January and February.</p>
        <p>Most of the sources of slower growth in yesterday's revised report looked much as they did in the department's original report: consumers, who had been buying faster than their incomes were rising, barely raised their spending in the quarter; housing weakened, and a huge drop in military purchases took a big bite out of Federal outlays.</p>
        <p>Consumer spending on goods and services accounts for two-thirds of the economy. With buying basically flat, inventories rose a hefty $36.8 billion, about what was originally estimated, much higher than the $9.8 billion inventory rise in the fourth quarter last year. The high inventories show that businesses have abundant stocks on their shelves that must be sold before more production is required.</p>
        <p>The upward creep in inflation over the last few quarters, while not necessarily likely to continue, recently led the Federal Reserve's policy-making committee to authorize the Fed chairman, Alan Greenspan, to tighten monetary policy before the next meeting if conditions warrant.</p>
        <p>"Things aren't going very well," said Joel Prakken an economist at Laurecne Meyer &amp; Associates , a St. Louis economic forecasting firm.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, despite the looming uncertainties over taxes, health-care changes and Fed policy, most forecasters see signs that the economy is doing better now than in the winter. They expect growth to return to 3 percent or so in the year's second half and inflation to subside a bit.</p>
        <p>Recent reports suggest that retail sales, car purchasing and home buying have picked up in April and May. Government spending, while on a gently downward path, is not apt to decline as sharply as it did in the winter, when military spending contracted at an abrupt annual rate of more than 25 percent. And foreign producers are likely to share some of the pain as orders are reduced to get inventories back into line with sales.</p>
        <p>"In the second quarter, we should get a substantial reversal in imports," Gordon Richards, chief economist for the National Association of Manufacturers, said.</p>
        <p>But growth in the current quarter could easily remain shy of the 3 percent rate.</p>
        <p>"A lot of businessmen were totally misled by strong consumption late last year," Mr. Richards said. "Those inventories have to be liquidated."</p>
        <p>If growth does fall short of 3 percent, further gains on the job front could be slow in coming.</p>
        <p>"Lack of momentum can beget lack of momentum," David Kelly, an economist at the Boston Company, said. Slow growth can "create pent-up demand, but it also cuts off income growth that would have been generated by stronger job growth," he added. Some Bright Spots</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department report was not all gloom. Businesses have been spending even more heavily on new equipment than originally thought, and the report indicated that this trend might continue.</p>
        <p>Equipment investment rose at a 16.5 percent annual rate in the first quarter, nearly twice as fast as the 8.6 percent annual rate initially reported. And profits were up at a 5.3 percent annual rate, to $253.8 billion, after climbing at an 8.5 percent rate in the previous quarter.</p>
        <p>Data included in the first-quarter G.D.P. follow, with all dollar amounts in billions at seasonally adjusted annual rates. Percentage changes are from the previous quarter at seasonally adjusted annual rates.</p>
        <p>Current Prices</p>
        <p>Last</p>
        <p>Pct</p>
        <p>Quarter</p>
        <p>Cng.</p>
        <p>Gross Domestic Product</p>
        <p>$6,148.0</p>
        <p>4.4</p>
        <p>Consumption</p>
        <p>4,238.6</p>
        <p>4.2</p>
        <p>Business investment</p>
        <p>571.0</p>
        <p>6.5</p>
        <p>Inventory change</p>
        <p>39.0</p>
        <p>N.A.</p>
        <p>Housing</p>
        <p>234.1</p>
        <p>3.8</p>
        <p>Net exports</p>
        <p>-59.9</p>
        <p>N.A.</p>
        <p>Government</p>
        <p>116.1</p>
        <p>-2.5</p>
        <p>Memo: Final sales*</p>
        <p>6,109.0</p>
        <p>2.5</p>
        <p>1987 Prices</p>
        <p>Gross Domestic Product</p>
        <p>$5,002.5</p>
        <p>0.9</p>
        <p>Consumption</p>
        <p>3,369.9</p>
        <p>1.2</p>
        <p>Business investment</p>
        <p>545.4</p>
        <p>11.4</p>
        <p>Inventory Change</p>
        <p>36.8</p>
        <p>N.A.</p>
        <p>Housing</p>
        <p>202.2</p>
        <p>-0.2</p>
        <p>Net exports</p>
        <p>-71.1</p>
        <p>N.A.</p>
        <p>Government</p>
        <p>919.3</p>
        <p>-7.3</p>
        <p>Memo: Final sales*</p>
        <p>4,965.7</p>
        <p>-1.2</p>
        <p>G.D.P. price deflator</p>
        <p>3.3</p>
        <p>G.D.P. fixed-weighted price index</p>
        <p>4.3.</p>
        <p>*G.D.P. less inventory change.  N.A. Data are not applicable.  Source: Commerce Department</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
