<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Attacks in Iraq Kill 2 G.I.'s, and a Bank Is Robbed of $800,000</title>
    <meta content="11IRAQ$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/12/11/international/middleeast/11IRAQ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1542166"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mosul (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baghdad (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latifiya (Iraq)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Spain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wong, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E1D7163CF932A25751C1A9659C8B63" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Attacks in Iraq Kill 2 G.I.'s, and a Bank Is Robbed of $800,000</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Attacks in Iraq Kill 2 G.I.s, and a Bank Is Robbed of $800,000</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD WONG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wong, Edward</byline>
      <dateline>BAGHDAD, Iraq, Dec. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Two American soldiers are killed and four wounded in northern Iraqi city of Mosul in two attacks, day after suicide bomber injures dozens of soldiers at base west of city; in Baghdad, senior police official says armed men robbed government bank and took about $800,000, in largest bank robbery in Iraq since widespread looting after American forces took city in spring; military officials say paratroopers' raids in Latifiya, near Baghdad, resulted in death or capture of people believed to be responsible for killings of seven Spanish intelligence agents in ambush in Nov (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two American soldiers were killed and four wounded in the northern city of Mosul on Wednesday in two attacks, a day after a suicide bomber injured dozens of soldiers at a base west of the city, military officials said.</p>
        <p>Here in the capital, a senior police official said Wednesday that armed men robbed a government bank in a northwest suburb on Tuesday and took almost 1.4 billion dinars, or about $800,000. It was the largest bank robbery in Iraq since the widespread looting after American forces took the city in the spring.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two U.S. soldiers were killed and four wounded in Mosul in two attacks and armed men robbed a government bank in Baghdad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two American soldiers were killed and four wounded in the northern city of Mosul on Wednesday in two attacks, a day after a suicide bomber injured dozens of soldiers at a base west of the city, military officials said.</p>
        <p>Here in the capital, a senior police official said Wednesday that armed men robbed a government bank in a northwest suburb on Tuesday and took almost 1.4 billion dinars, or about $800,000. It was the largest bank robbery in Iraq since the widespread looting after American forces took the city in the spring.</p>
        <p>Military officials also said paratroopers made raids at 2 a.m. in Latifiya, near Baghdad, that resulted in the death or capture of people believed to be responsible for the killings of seven Spanish intelligence agents in an ambush on Nov. 29.</p>
        <p>In Madrid, the Spanish defense minister, Federico Trillo, said that American, British and Spanish forces, working together with the Iraqi police, had arrested 41 people, among them ''the direct executors and organizers of the attack.'' American officials identified one as Abu Abdullah, whom they described as an intelligence officer, financier and doctor who acted as cell leader.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trillo also said the Iraqi police had recently arrested five people believed to be responsible for killing another Spanish intelligence agent, José Antonio Bernal Gomez, at his Baghdad home on Oct. 9. The comments came as Spain's prime minister, José María Aznar, defended his deployment of 1,300 troops in Iraq.</p>
        <p>In Mosul, the first attack took place around 11 a.m. as soldiers from the 101st Airborne Division were watching over long gas lines. Gunfire erupted from two cars driving by, killing one soldier and wounding another, military officials said.</p>
        <p>A Kurdish official driving from his office across the street was also killed, Agence France-Presse reported, quoting a Kurdish leader. But military officials said they had no details about a Kurd being killed.</p>
        <p>On Monday a soldier was shot to death in Mosul while watching over a long line at a gas station. The Army has begun posting soldiers at gas stations because in the last several weeks the fuel shortages, caused by attacks on northern pipelines, have led to lines up to two miles long. Last week, soldiers in Samawa, south of Baghdad, encountered burning cars and oil barrels during a demonstration over the shortage.</p>
        <p>In contrast, a heavily policed march in central Baghdad on Wednesday, organized peacefully by the country's major political parties, drew thousands of Iraqis to protest attacks by guerrilla fighters, which have injured and killed Iraqi civilians as well as occupiers.</p>
        <p>Wednesday's second fatal attack came at 2 p.m. An improvised bomb went off as a convoy drove through the eastern side of Mosul, followed by small-arms fire. One soldier from the 101st Airborne was killed and three were wounded, officials said.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday a suicide bomber tried to drive a car loaded with explosives into an Army base at Tall Afar, about 30 miles west of Mosul. The car exploded when soldiers fired on it, and officials initially said that 31 soldiers were injured. Reporters on the scene put the number at 58 after interviewing commanders.</p>
        <p>In Baghdad a senior police official said armed men staged a daylight bank robbery on Tuesday in the middle-class suburb of Kadhimiya, in the city's northwest, which is known for its gold market.</p>
        <p>The bank was about to close; only a few workers remained. Two policemen who were supposed to be on guard were not there, the police official said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
