<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Fashion; A Future That Is Colorful and Synthetic</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Fashion Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="797761"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPAREL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITE, CONSTANCE C R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Fashion Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDA153AF937A25753C1A963958260" item-length="708" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Fashion; A Future That Is Colorful and Synthetic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONSTANCE C. R. WHITE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITE, CONSTANCE C R</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Oct. 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the runways here ablaze, it is already evident that color is an incendiary device to be handled gingerly. It can send a powerful signal -- or lead the way to certain disaster.</p>
        <p>Junya Watanabe, a protege of Rei Kawakubo, presented his wonderfully advanced spring collection in brilliant cobalt blues, hot pinks and mustard yellows. The collection, Mr. Watanabe said, represented "a positive outlook toward the future." In addition to strong color, Mr. Watanabe made his point with new concepts in cut and fabric treatment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the runways here ablaze, it is already evident that color is an incendiary device to be handled gingerly. It can send a powerful signal -- or lead the way to certain disaster.</p>
        <p>Junya Watanabe, a protege of Rei Kawakubo, presented his wonderfully advanced spring collection in brilliant cobalt blues, hot pinks and mustard yellows. The collection, Mr. Watanabe said, represented "a positive outlook toward the future." In addition to strong color, Mr. Watanabe made his point with new concepts in cut and fabric treatment.</p>
        <p>Last season's mesmerizing welts at the body's joints became slits, exposing a peek of knee or elbow. Mr. Watanabe also placed soft gathers of fabric at joints, forming little pouches.</p>
        <p>He rendered slim shapes in bootleg pants, elongated jackets and slim dresses in laminated polyurethane, which resembled a soft cellophane, and polyester jersey. Colors clashed extraordinarily: a red blouse over pink bootlegs, a graphic-patterned double-breasted jacket in sky blue and hot pink with narrow cobalt-blue trousers, a green body-hugging shirt over an orange tank and hot-pink fitted trousers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Watanabe and Lamine Kouyate have both seen the future, and it's synthetic. Mr. Kouyate, who designs under the name Xuly Bet, proved that he was not -- as some thought -- about to be left standing at the station with only the deconstructed nylon designs that catapulted him to fame in 1992. Fashion has moved on, and so has Mr. Kouyate, who last season decided to forgo a show because, he said, "I have nothing new to say." What if more designers took this approach? Now Mr. Kouyate is talking again, and it's all about once-tasteless colors and polyester.</p>
        <p>Models in blackface dusted with sparkling powder paraded in reversible pink fake fur coat jackets thrown over hot-pink polyester jersey gowns; shiny blue, red and gold plaid bootleg pants sat snug under a fitted red and yellow floral crop shirt; a cobalt-blue crew-neck crop top went over a navy and white batik-printed asymmetrical skirt, and a chintzy red, yellow and orange melange stripe slim shirt glided over a matching ankle-length hipster skirt. It was the kind of fast-fashion collection that captures prevailing style in its own irreverent, offhand way.</p>
        <p>Dirk Bikkembergs, who was once relied upon to be among the foot soldiers of advanced fashion, also made a grab at the unusual fabrics and unharmonious colours that are now defining style's cutting edge. But it slipped from his grasp. Here the newly popular bile green looked forced in transparent wool gauze pants suits. Hot-pink tops with plunging necklines were awkward. Mr. Bikkembergs's straight white jackets -- the front leather, the back mesh -- were chic and breezy. But one left the show wondering what ever happened to the Dirk Bikkembergs who turned out intensely fresh, downtown versions of men's wear that seemed the epitome of urbane cool.</p>
        <p>Perhaps Mr. Bikkembergs should have skipped the color craze, like Costume National. That house produced a strong, up-to-the-minute collection in restrained brown, khaki and black. There is a thin line between controlled and boring, and Costume National, which skips from one to the other periodically, was firmly in control this season.</p>
        <p>Pared down and sleek, the collection opened with a black transparent V-neck tunic slipped over languid, too-long jersey pants. Tailored pants were slit a half an inch or so up the back of the hem. Brown lace mesh djellabas washed over languid brown jersey pants. Thigh-length tunics in brown or khaki with their pockets raised to shoulder height were worn over trousers or alone as a minidress.</p>
        <p>Instead of coating fabrics with plastic, as he's done in the past, Koji Tatsuno poured it into the seams of his chevron-pieced jackets. Mr. Tatsuno's bold clothing designs and fabric development is admirable. White notch-collar jackets with small but sharp right-angled shoulders sparkled with sequin insets, and trousers were sprinkled cleverly with Adidas-like sequin racing stripes down the sides of the legs. Hologram butterflies adorned pale grey pant suits and knee-length dresses. Mr. Tatsuno, always experimental, meant to conjure up an intergalactic adventure. Sometimes, it was worth the trip.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
