<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Court Expands Liability of Landlords in Attacks on Tenants by Intruders</title>
    <meta content="25HOUS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1064898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Locks and Keys</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finder, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/Upstate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Locks and Keys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981125T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE2DE1739F936A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Court Expands Liability of Landlords in Attacks on Tenants by Intruders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FINDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finder, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York State Court of Appeals, in series of decisions, expand opportunity for tenants to obtain damages from landlords when they are attacked by intruders who gain access to buildings because of broken or nonexistent locks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a series of decisions, New York State's highest court yesterday expanded the opportunity for tenants to obtain damages from landlords when they are attacked by intruders who gain access to buildings because of broken or nonexistent locks.</p>
        <p>The Court of Appeals issued three decisions, involving five cases, that tried to broaden the circumstances under which landlords -- including the New York City Housing Authority -- can be held liable for damages when faulty building security contributes to criminal assaults.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a series of decisions, New York State's highest court yesterday expanded the opportunity for tenants to obtain damages from landlords when they are attacked by intruders who gain access to buildings because of broken or nonexistent locks.</p>
        <p>The Court of Appeals issued three decisions, involving five cases, that tried to broaden the circumstances under which landlords -- including the New York City Housing Authority -- can be held liable for damages when faulty building security contributes to criminal assaults.</p>
        <p>To collect damages in such cases under New York law, a tenant must convince a jury that the landlord was negligent in maintaining building security and that the assailants were outsiders who got into the building specifically because the door locks were broken or nonexistent.</p>
        <p>It is often difficult, if not impossible, to prove that a broken lock was directly responsible for an assault, that it was the ''proximate cause,'' as the principle is known in the law. An assailant's identity is often unknown; he might have lived in the building or been visiting someone, or he might have follow a tenant through a locked door.</p>
        <p>State appeals courts in recent years have generally limited landlords' liability in such cases. But the thrust of most of the court's rulings yesterday was to make it easier for tenants to collect damages from landlords, even when the identity of an assailant is unknown.</p>
        <p>The most significant case involved Norma Burgos, who lived in a privately owned building on West 182d Street in Manhattan. Ms. Burgos was robbed and beaten by two men who pushed into her apartment when she opened her door to go out one afternoon. Ms. Burgos said that locks on the front and back doors of her building were broken and that she had not known her assailants.</p>
        <p>The owners of the building, Aqueduct Realty Corporation, moved to have the case dismissed because Ms. Burgos could not prove conclusively that her assailants were strangers who had entered the building uninvited. The trial court denied the landlord's motion to dismiss, but a state appeals court reversed the ruling, throwing out the case.</p>
        <p>In a unanimous decision, the Court of Appeals reversed the appellate decision, reinstating Ms. Burgos's case. While the court did not decide whether the landlord was liable, it said Ms. Burgos had offered enough information to enable that decision to be made by a jury. Ms. Burgos's assertions ''are sufficient to raise a triable issue of fact as to whether the assailants were intruders who entered the building through a negligently maintained door,'' Chief Justice Judith S. Kaye wrote.</p>
        <p>A related case was brought on behalf of a 12-year-old girl from the Bronx, who was raped and sodomized by an unidentified man who had entered her building in a city housing project by walking through a back door that could not be closed or locked. A jury found that the New York City Housing Authority was liable for damages, but the judge dismissed the case because the girl could not prove that her assailant was an intruder. A state appeals court affirmed the decision, saying that just because the victim did not know the rapist was insufficient proof that he was an intruder.</p>
        <p>The Court of Appeals reversed the appellate decision yesterday, and ordered the case returned to State Supreme Court. Justice Kaye said there was significant evidence that the rapist was an intruder. He was seen entering the building through the broken and unlocked door, she wrote. He made no attempt to conceal his identity when he rode on an elevator with the victim and other residents, and he did not select a floor. He simply followed the young woman when she exited at her floor.</p>
        <p>Even if an assailant is not identified, Justice Kaye wrote, a tenant can successfully sue a landlord for negligence over an assault ''if the evidence renders it more likely or more reasonable than not that the assailant was an intruder who gained access to the premises through a negligently maintained entrance.''</p>
        <p>But in another case decided yesterday, the Court of Appeals upheld lower court rulings that found that the Housing Authority was not responsible for the sexual assault and robbery of a 17-year-old Manhattan girl. Even though the front door of the girl's building in a city housing project had no lock -- and even though her attacker was clearly an intruder -- the court found that the Housing Authority's negligence had not caused the assault. The attacker was a serial rapist who had assaulted women in many buildings, including some that had been locked, the court said in a 5-to-1 ruling.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
