<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jesse Jackson Jr. Is His Father's Son, But He Reaches Beyond the Rainbow</title>
    <meta content="Y03JES$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="999437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Politics and Government (U.S.)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Illinois</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chicago (Ill)</location>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Jesse L. Jackson Jr.</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Jesse L Jr (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Jesse L (Rev)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Dirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Illinois/Chicago</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suburbs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E2DF1531F930A35750C0A96E958260" item-length="1869" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jesse Jackson Jr. Is His Father's Son, But He Reaches Beyond the Rainbow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Dirk</byline>
      <dateline>FLOSSMOOR, Ill.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rev Jesse L Jackson Jr, after slightly more than two years in Congress as Democratic representative from Chicago's Second Congressional District, has become force in Illinois politics in way that eluded father, Rev Jesse L Jackson; courted by politicians in both parties, he has become best known as champion of south suburban interests, and may come to reflect suburbanization of black political power; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tudor architecture and pricey boutiques line the broad sidewalks of Sterling Avenue in this elegant Chicago suburb, where a Land Rover slips into a parking lot near a micro-brewery.</p>
        <p>Out of the vehicle steps a young man in a crisp white shirt and blue tie, the collar of his overcoat stylishly upturned.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tudor architecture and pricey boutiques line the broad sidewalks of Sterling Avenue in this elegant Chicago suburb, where a Land Rover slips into a parking lot near a micro-brewery.</p>
        <p>Out of the vehicle steps a young man in a crisp white shirt and blue tie, the collar of his overcoat stylishly upturned.</p>
        <p>The man on the move is Representative Jesse L. Jackson Jr., a rising political star at 32. He has spent the day striding across his turf, stretching from the South Side of Chicago deep into suburbia: the broken-glass-strewn neighborhoods of Ford Heights, median-income and racially mixed Matteson, well-to-do Flossmoor.</p>
        <p>''My colleagues in Washington tend to see me as simply 'the guy from the South Side, the guy from the neighborhood,' '' Mr. Jackson says, his voice a mix of amusement and annoyance at the stereotypical soul brother image. ''And during campaigns, I'm usually asked to run the 'black circuit.' They usually don't tell the press I'm in town, because they don't want to scare the white voters. But I tell them, the white voters in my district love me.''</p>
        <p>After just over two years in Congress, Mr. Jackson has become a force in Illinois politics in a way that eluded his father, the Rev. Jesse L. Jackson. Courted by politicians in both parties, the young Democratic Congressman has become best known here as a champion of south suburban interests, pursuing a meat-and-potatoes agenda of jobs and economic development and joining forces with a conservative Republican powerhouse, Representative Henry J. Hyde, in pressing for building a new airport in the cornfields 40 miles south of downtown Chicago.</p>
        <p>If his father came to embody one moment in history, Representative Jackson may come to reflect another: the suburbanization of black political power. His district is 65 percent black and 35 percent white; it is also one-third suburban, a percentage that is growing fast as middle-class blacks leave the South Side.</p>
        <p>''Jesse Jackson Jr.'s persona is very different from his father's,'' said David Bositis, a political analyst for the Joint Center for Political Studies, a research group focused on black concerns. ''He represents the new black politics, the new black middle class.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Jackson entered Congress in 1995, filling a vacancy left by the resignation of Mel Reynolds after his criminal conviction for having sex with a teen-age girl, there was plenty of skepticism about this young man's easy path to elective office -- his first. He was regarded, even by many who voted for him, as a child of privilege with a famous name who would take predictable stands on the issues and make fiery speeches denouncing the evils of racism in America. Before he became a Congressman, he was a field director for the Rainbow Coalition, the organization founded by his father.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Jackson quickly won over many skeptics. He ran virtually unopposed in 1996, and is expected to coast to re-election this fall.</p>
        <p>Since the 1970's, blacks have been leaving American cities for the suburbs at the same rate as whites. In Chicago, blacks have largely moved to the mostly white south suburbs, where housing is more affordable than on the woodsy, wealthy North Shore. This changing racial mix has met with some fears among whites, many of whom left the city a generation ago as neighborhoods changed from white to black, sometimes in what seemed an instant, and property values collapsed.</p>
        <p>Despite the anxieties among whites -- and some blacks, who fear resegregation -- the experience of racial change in the suburbs has not brought a decline in property values.  Middle-class blacks who are moving to places like Homewood, not to mention those buying $400,000 houses in Olympia Fields and Flossmoor, tend to share economic perspectives with their white suburban neighbors.</p>
        <p>This changing mix has complicated district politics and blurred some traditional divisions between blacks and whites, suburbanites and city dwellers. When Mr. Jackson talks about attracting people to the south suburbs ''who share our values,'' he is speaking for blacks and whites.</p>
        <p>In Congress, Mr. Jackson's voting record is reliably liberal. But he defies easy categories. A man who likes to hunt and enjoy a fine cigar, young Mr. Jackson is not uncomfortable in the company of Republicans. He has not ruled out endorsing a Republican in the race for governor if the Democratic nominee opposes the airport.</p>
        <p>On race relations, Mr. Jackson has emerged as an uncommon Chicago politician who can speak a language that seems to be understood by blacks and whites alike. He talks of the difficulties of a black man hailing a cab on Capitol Hill. And he talks with empathy about whites anxious about racial changes in the suburbs.</p>
        <p>''White people in the far south suburbs drive down Dixie Highway every day, and this is what they see,''  Mr. Jackson said, lifting his hand from the gear shift of his Land Rover and pointing toward the shuttered factories and stores of Harvey, once a vibrant working-class steel town, a community that has been withering since its smokestacks vanished a decade ago. ''They see an increasing African-American population. They see problems. And they say, 'I don't want that coming my way.' ''</p>
        <p>In the view of Mr. Jackson, the color that matters most is green. It is the collapse of the industrial economy, not the influx of blacks, that has brought down towns like Harvey.</p>
        <p>''Ninety percent of the racial debate is really about economics,'' he said. ''If we frame the discussion in terms of growth, jobs, the economy, we can move beyond the racial battleground.''</p>
        <p>Toward that end, Mr. Jackson has been single-minded in his drive to  build an airport in the south suburbs, a $2.7 billion project that would shower the region with jobs. It would also transform suburbs like Ford Heights, so poor it cannot afford a police department, into property that is suddenly quite valuable.</p>
        <p>It is not altogether surprising when Mr. Jackson drives through black neighborhoods, and people respond with honking horns and clenched fists, as if to honor a hero. But it is astonishing in suburban Chicago to see so many whites fawn over a black liberal, some of them the same people who scorned his father.</p>
        <p>At a breakfast shop in Chicago Heights, a working-class town with a history of racial tension, blue-collar white men crowded around Mr. Jackson as if he were an old pal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hyde, who has made joint appearances with Mr. Jackson at rallies to promote the new airport, said Mr. Jackson had earned the respect of his colleagues by working hard and acknowledging that, as a freshman, he had a lot to learn.</p>
        <p>In the view of political experts in Illinois, Mr. Jackson's appeal among whites and suburbanites, as well as urban blacks, makes him a political figure of enormous potential.</p>
        <p>''The upside for this guy is the moon -- I mean it's unlimited,'' said Paul Green, a professor of political science at Governor's State University in the south suburbs. Mr. Green said Mr. Jackson was in a special position to reach across racial boundaries, given the reservoir of good will many blacks have for the son of a famous civil rights fighter.</p>
        <p>''With his name, there is very little he can do to alienate black voters,''  Mr. Green said. ''He's like Daley with the Irish: there's always going to be that cushion of support.''</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Green said, Mr. Jackson can take some chances that other black politicians cannot, like forging alliances with conservative Republicans and playing down racial politics. In fact, Mr. Green said that some black leaders privately complained that Congressman Jackson was too moderate but that they did not dare criticize him publicly.</p>
        <p>Some liberals in Chicago say they hope he will run for mayor, a move Mr. Jackson dismisses. But most political experts seriously doubt that Mr. Jackson would make such a run,  especially against an incumbent mayor as popular as Richard M. Daley. Most analysts say it is more likely that Mr. Jackson would someday try for the Senate.</p>
        <p>But first, he must build a record.  So far, he has been careful to tend to business at home, building roads and working on Federal grants for jobs. In more than two years in Congress, he has not missed a vote. And he has held only four news conferences.</p>
        <p>It was the rap on the elder Mr. Jackson that he was always looking for the TV cameras, never staying to finish a job. ''Jesse Jetstream,'' the Chicago press long ago nicknamed the father, a man always flying off to the next news conference.</p>
        <p>The upbringing of the younger Mr. Jackson, of course, differs starkly with the childhood of his father, a product of poverty and the segregated South. The younger Mr. Jackson attended the prestigious St. Albans preparatory school in Washington, a bastion of the well connected, the alma mater of Vice President Al Gore. He has a law degree from the University of Illinois and lists fencing among his hobbies.</p>
        <p>As a child, Mr. Jackson said, he was shaped more by his mother, Jacqueline, than by his father, who was often on the road. Time spent with his father, he recalled, ''was often a 15-minute ride from the airport to another meeting.''</p>
        <p>But the father has taught him some important lessons, he said.</p>
        <p>Representative Jackson recalled a time, more than a decade ago, flying with his father over Iowa. His father called him to the window and told him to look down. The son saw great expanses of cultivated corn and bean fields. But it was impossible to see the sweat of the farmers, or their struggles, below.</p>
        <p>''Son, if you're flying high, you miss a lot of the details,'' the Congressman said his father told him. ''It was his way of saying, 'Don't get too heady.'</p>
        <p>''He was also telling me, 'You've been given a lot. A lot is expected of you.' ''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
