<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Favoritism Is Found in Magnet School's Admissions</title>
    <meta content="03STAT$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="999479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nepotism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Archibold, Randal C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crew, Rudolph F (Chancellor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DB1531F930A35750C0A96E958260" item-length="946" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Favoritism Is Found in Magnet School's Admissions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RANDAL C. ARCHIBOLD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Archibold, Randal C</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Independent investigator finds that political favoritism and nepotism have tainted admissions practices at Michael J Petrides School, Staten Island magnet school that had promised to select students only by random lottery; report finds that disproportionate number of students were related to school district or government employees; Schools Chancellor Dr Rudy Crew comments; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Political favoritism and nepotism have tainted the admissions practices at a Staten Island magnet school that had promised to select students only by random lottery, according to a report by an independent investigator that was released yesterday.</p>
        <p>A disproportionate number of students were related to school district or government employees, the investigators found, noting that 52 percent of the sixth-grade students who were accepted for this school year had parents who worked for the school board or city government agencies. But the extent of the problem could not be determined because many crucial admissions documents such as applications are missing, the investigators said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Political favoritism and nepotism have tainted the admissions practices at a Staten Island magnet school that had promised to select students only by random lottery, according to a report by an independent investigator that was released yesterday.</p>
        <p>A disproportionate number of students were related to school district or government employees, the investigators found, noting that 52 percent of the sixth-grade students who were accepted for this school year had parents who worked for the school board or city government agencies. But the extent of the problem could not be determined because many crucial admissions documents such as applications are missing, the investigators said.</p>
        <p>Schools Chancellor Rudy Crew yesterday ordered the superintendent who oversees the school to come up with a plan to correct the admissions process. Although the report concluded that no board policies had been broken, Dr. Crew said he was concerned about the ''appearance of impropriety surrounding the admission of students to the school.'' There were no plans to discipline school officials, a Board of Education spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Edward F. Stancik, the Special Commissioner of Investigation for the New York City school system, began looking into how the Michael J. Petrides School, which opened in 1995, has been selecting pupils after receiving complaints from parents. The parents said that, among other things, school officials were not living up to their promise to use a lottery to pick students. School officials have said they use a computerized selection process intended to reflect the geography, demographics and academic ability of the island's students.</p>
        <p>Investigators found that some applications had words like ''sibling'' or the names of prominent people in the community written on them, though none were identified by name in the 40-page report. In addition, an analysis of the students showed many were related to teachers and other district employees.</p>
        <p>For the current school year, for example, of 650 applicants for the sixth grade, 67 students, or 10 percent, were children whose parents were board employees. But of the 93 applicants who were accepted, 29 students, 31 percent, were children  of parents employed by the board; 52 percent of the accepted sixth graders, 48 students, had parents employed by the board or by city government agencies like the Police and Fire Departments, the report said.</p>
        <p>''What I found most alarming is that the average parent without connections, without influence, was cheated,'' Mr. Stancik said in an interview. ''A promise was made that every child on the island would have an equal chance to get into this school, and that turns out not to be the case because so many back channels of admission policies really made it impossible to get a random, fair lottery.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Stancik went beyond the report in noting the disappearance of applications. ''The fact that records are missing suggests somebody wanted to prevent us from finding the truth,'' he said. ''There was sloppy record keeping, but it is not a coincidence that all politically related written recommendations are now missing.''</p>
        <p>In the report, Petrides School officials acknowledged they had received many letters of recommendation, but played down their influence.</p>
        <p>Investigators said they found only four applications that had names of influential people written on them -- all four students were admitted -- but teachers told investigators there were many more.</p>
        <p>The school's principal, Gregory Gallo, was also faulted for a lack of candor in responding to investigators' queries. Mr. Gallo gave conflicting answers to questions such as who generated the random lists used to select students, the report said, noting that he finally admitted he probably did it himself despite his lack of proficiency with computers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gallo did not return telephone calls.</p>
        <p>Christy Cugini, the Superintendent of Community School District 31, whom the report criticized for lack of supervision of the process, said he would soon meet with the Chancellor to discuss ways to improve oversight of the program. He disputed the suggestion of a cover-up of records, saying officials had no reason to keep applications once students were accepted.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cugini said he was disturbed only at the number of children with relatives working for the school or board. Mr. Cugini's two grandchildren attend the school, a fact the report suggested was the result of an unofficial professional courtesy policy. Mr. Cugini denied any intercession on his relatives' behalf and vowed to insure such a practice was not followed.</p>
        <p>The school, on a 42-acre campus at 715 Ocean Terrace that once housed the College of Staten Island, promotes itself as a ''seamless'' kindergarten-to-12th-grade laboratory turning out students adept at technology, analytic thinking, languages and cultural awareness. Named for a Board of Education member who died in 1994 and had pushed for the creation of the school, it now enrolls 800 students in kindergarten through ninth grade, with plans for students in all grades by 2001.</p>
        <p>Timothy Violette, a member of Parents for Effective Education, a 75-member ad-hoc group that asked for the investigation, praised the report for shedding light on the selection process but complained it did not fully address the group's concerns that the school has fallen short of its academic promise.</p>
        <p>Borough President Guy V. Molinari said that he had been called by several people asking him to use his influence to help their children gain admission, but that he had rebuffed them. ''I doubt very much anyone on my staff ever'' tried to interfere either, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
