<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Skin-Deep Beauty in Westhampton</title>
    <meta content="28DIN.$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1027863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlantica (Westhampton Beach, Ny, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starkey, Joanne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Beaches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E2DA113CF93BA15755C0A96E958260" item-length="831" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Skin-Deep Beauty in Westhampton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOANNE STARKEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Starkey, Joanne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joanne Starkey reviews Atlantica restaurant at Westhampton Bath &amp; Tennis Hotel, Westhampton Beach, NY; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ATLANTICA is gorgeous. This Westhampton Beach newcomer has leap-frogged over the competition to capture the title of best-looking restaurant in the Hamptons. Given its location on the sea side of Dune Road, diners are prepared for the splendid water views. But those enchanting ocean vistas must share bragging rights with the spectacular dining room.</p>
        <p>A palatial crystal chandelier makes a regal first impression. Second glances reveal masses of hanging lanterns, thick white columns, potted palms and three walls of floor-to-ceiling windows. The sky-high ceiling is draped in blue and white striped fabric, creating a crisp, summer-in-the-Hamptons look.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ATLANTICA is gorgeous. This Westhampton Beach newcomer has leap-frogged over the competition to capture the title of best-looking restaurant in the Hamptons. Given its location on the sea side of Dune Road, diners are prepared for the splendid water views. But those enchanting ocean vistas must share bragging rights with the spectacular dining room.</p>
        <p>A palatial crystal chandelier makes a regal first impression. Second glances reveal masses of hanging lanterns, thick white columns, potted palms and three walls of floor-to-ceiling windows. The sky-high ceiling is draped in blue and white striped fabric, creating a crisp, summer-in-the-Hamptons look.</p>
        <p>Service is not as crisp as the look. One quiet weeknight, after a long wait with only a few olives to nibble, we had to ask for bread. During the meal, the empty bread basket was ignored. Surprisingly, on a busy Saturday, service was snappier with bread refills arriving as if by magic. (Had I been recognized?)</p>
        <p>The food takes a back seat to the view and decor. Most of the dishes pass muster but none creates excitement. That is a surprise, for Todd Jacobs is at the helm here. Mr. Jacobs, an innovative and talented chef, is also owner and chef of Tierra Mar, also in Westhampton, one of the East End's star establishments.</p>
        <p>A restaurant makes a statement when it eliminates salt and pepper shakers from the table as Atlantica does. It asserts that dishes emanating from its kitchen are perfectly seasoned. Unfortunately, one sip of a bland asparagus and spinach soup had us waving for a salt shaker. It was also needed for the hearts of romaine salad with its thin, watery blue-cheese dressing.</p>
        <p>Instead, opt for the endive and mesclun mix sporting a spirited lemon-chive dressing or the spunky arugula-frisee toss with marinated fennel, oven-dried tomatoes and bits of orange in a citrus vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>The most satisfying opener sampled, a special, was a trio of giant barbecued shrimp surrounding a mound of chunky guacamole all atop a few leaves of arugula drizzled with a smoky red chili vinaigrette. The soft-shell crab enclosed in a crunchy batter also won friends. But avoid the heavy, gummy potato gnocchi.</p>
        <p>A steamer basket of local organic vegetables will delight only purists. Those looking for flavor have to use the pungent dipping sauce of soy, wasabi and ginger.</p>
        <p>Atlantica's name, location and menu all stress the sea. Fish and seafood are definitely the way to go. A landlubber selection of rib steak was a disappointment. The meat was dry and gray throughout, not medium-rare as ordered. What's more, the steak's topper of crisp garlic chips (overly brown slices) gave the dish a bitter taste. Yummy whipped Yukon gold potatoes were a saving grace.</p>
        <p>Fish fared better. Lobsters were sweet and firm, whether simply steamed and presented with asparagus and basmati rice or combined with giant mussels and sauteed greens and placed atop linguine. Wild king salmon was cooked correctly, as was pan-fried flounder. The shoestring potatoes that accompanied the flounder, however, were limp and thicker than shoestrings should be.</p>
        <p>Two poultry picks to consider are the grilled breast of duck, which shares the plate with caramelized sweet potatoes and crisp green beans, and a moist, juicy, sauteed chicken breast tossed with vegetables and fettuccine.</p>
        <p>Dessert was our favorite course. Only a heavy, dull chocolate hazelnut torte failed to please. Show-stoppers include a silken creme brulee, a tangy raspberry Bavarian mousse, white and dark chocolate mousses with a hazelnut creme anglaise and a rich rice pudding christened creamed vanilla risotto. It was dotted with fresh strawberries and flavored with Grand Marnier.</p>
        <p>Atlantica's wine list does not follow the herd. It offers no white zinfandel or pouilly fuisse and only one Italian choice. Yet there is a riesling, a grape considered more noble than chardonnay in many nations but rarely seen here. It is a 1995 Trimbach from the Alsace, an austere, bone-dry delight. Two Vinas del Veros from Spain, a 1995 cabernet sauvignon and a '95 merlot ($6 by the glass, $23 and $24 by the bottle) are youthful, uncomplicated, upfront wines that are good values.</p>
        <p>Atlantica</p>
        <p>At The Westhampton Bath &amp; Tennis Hotel, 231 Dune Road, Westhampton Beach, 288-6577.</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>Atmosphere Spectacular seaside summer in the Hamptons.</p>
        <p>Service Always pleasant but erratic: from attentive to casual.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes Barbecued shrimp, mesclun salad, arugula and frisee salad, soft-shell crab, flounder, salmon, lobster, lobster over linguine, chicken with fettuccine, duck breast, Bavarian mousse, chocolate mousse, creme brulee, vanilla risotto.</p>
        <p>Price range Lunch, entrees $4.50 to $16.95. Dinner, appetizers $6.50-$18, entrees $17.50-$30, desserts $5.50-$7.50.</p>
        <p>Credit cards All major cards.</p>
        <p>Hours Breakfast 8-11 daily, lunch 11:00 A.M.-4:00 P.M. daily, dinner 4-11 nightly. Sunday brunch 11:00 A.M.-2:00 P.M.</p>
        <p>Reservations A must on weekends.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility Dining room is up a flight of stairs.</p>
        <p>DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
