<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Too Cool for Words</title>
    <meta content="28ESPENT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1027739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Espen, Hal</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hornby, Nick</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">About A Boy (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F07EFD71F3DF93BA15755C0A96E958260" item-length="971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Too Cool for Words</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Hal Espen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Espen, Hal</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hal Espen reviews book About a Boy by Nick Hornby; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABOUT A BOY</p>
        <p>By Nick Hornby.</p>
        <p>307 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Riverhead Books. $22.95.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABOUT A BOY</p>
        <p>By Nick Hornby.</p>
        <p>307 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Riverhead Books. $22.95.</p>
        <p>IF it's comedy you want, there's a whole hilarity industry busily supplying the world of American entertainment -- except when it comes to the book business, where heroic exemplars of drollery have been a dwindling species in recent years. Despite the boom in waggish humor on television and in the movies, in the United States the comic novel is virtually a dead genre.</p>
        <p>Which is why the one-man British invasion led by Nick Hornby is such a welcome phenomenon. His debut novel, ''High Fidelity,'' which landed on these shores in 1995, quickly won a following for its sweet but unsaccharine account of the travails of a 35-year-old London record-store owner who's too hip to commit to the woman he loves. In contrast to his often riotous but essentially sulfurous countryman Martin Amis, Hornby is a writer who dares to be witty, intelligent and emotionally generous all at once. He combines a skilled, intuitive appreciation for the rigors of comic structure with highly original insights about the way the enchantments of popular culture insinuate themselves into middle-class notions of romance.</p>
        <p>''Pop culture'' and ''youth culture'' used to mean nearly the same thing; Hornby is the chronicler of the aging fan tyrannized by his passionate taste in music and movies and fashion, spellbound by a code of sex, drugs and rock-and-roll. As a novelist, Hornby latches onto the dramatic possibilities of a hero terrified that he must renounce the vistas of endless choice held out by his pantheon of greatest hits and all-time favorites, even as he is drawn toward the apparent compromises of quotidian love and vocation.</p>
        <p>A great R &amp; B album can become a touchstone of independence and adventurousness. In ''High Fidelity,'' Hornby's hero, puzzling over ''accepted notions of seriousness,'' declares that '' 'Al Green Explores Your Mind' is as serious as life gets.'' How to hold onto such convictions without progressively disengaging from one's actual grown-up life is the problem posed in the novel, which may be the first comedy of manners in which the romantic complication derives from a struggle over how much credence to give the Clash, Marvin Gaye and Dusty Springfield.</p>
        <p>In Hornby's second novel, ''About a Boy,'' this pop problem is compounded by the problem of Pop: As in Dad, the frustrated songwriter who died and bequeathed his son, Will (another of Hornby's feckless mid-30's London bachelors), a steady fortune in royalties from his one success, a Christmas ditty called ''Santa's Super Sleigh.'' As in no father to speak of for 12-year-old Marcus, whose divorced ex-hippie mum is too depressed to notice that her son has become a bullied, friendless misfit.</p>
        <p>Will is a fussy, smug consumer-esthete who has never bothered with a career and who thinks he's leading a cool and uncomplicated existence. While his formerly club-hopping friends are settling into marriages and untidy households cluttered with children and toys, Will is determined to stay single and leave his own depths unexplored. But he is drawn from the shallows -- and closer to Marcus and his chaotic world -- when he hits on a breathtakingly cynical dating stratagem. A chance affair with a beautiful single mother (significantly, she looks and emotes like Julie Christie) convinces Will that sexy divorced women saddled with children and not yet ready for another long-term relationship are a natural resource ripe for exploitation. The only hitch is finding them, so Will decides to pretend he's a single father and joins a support group populated almost exclusively by single mothers.</p>
        <p>This predatory scheme eventually backfires, of course, but by then Will's pretense has taken on a life of its own. Once the drama and messiness of real life intrude (Marcus's mother attempts suicide on the day of a picnic sponsored by Single Parents -- Alone Together, or SPAT), Will finds himself ''completely absorbed in all of this -- absorbed almost to the point of enjoyment.'' And although it doesn't take Marcus long to figure out that Will is a phony, he starts coming around to Will's apartment uninvited, sensing that this purposeless man who knows all about music and clothes might be able to teach him how to be a proper kid. With great mutual reticence and without a shred of sentimentality, Will and Marcus gradually allow themselves to depend on each other.</p>
        <p>The novel is set in 1993 and 1994, and unfolding in the background are the events leading up to the suicide of Kurt Cobain, leader of the rock group Nirvana. (''About a Girl'' is the title of a song on Nirvana's first album.) As in ''High Fidelity,'' Hornby is wonderfully attuned to the way pop stars function as presiding spirits in the contemporary imagination. With Cobain hovering over the proceedings, moroseness, numbness and levels of empathy that barely register are the emotional constants through most of the novel, yet Hornby's unashamed embrace of these moods renders them as pleasurable as those gloomy songs that somehow manage to cheer us up.</p>
        <p>''About a Boy,'' which was published earlier this year in England, has been a best seller there and deserves to be one here too. A few critics, mistakenly interpreting the arrested development of Hornby's protagonists as an argument in favor of privileged infantilism, have characterized his popularity as evidence of some kind of retrograde trend. Others have compared his work, dismissively, to ''Seinfeld.'' I suspect that these detractors are so underexposed to humorous fiction with a real heart that they don't quite know how to respond. With any luck, we'll soon have lots of fab and funny writers emulating Nick Hornby, and his kind of accomplishment won't seem quite so foreign.  Hal Espen is the features editor of Outside magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Hal Espen is the features editor of Outside magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
