<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newly Found Fungus Is Tied To Vanishing Species of Frog</title>
    <meta content="28FROG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1028118"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fungi</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Australia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Latin America</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Australia and Pacific/Australia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Amphibians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805E1DA143FF93BA15755C0A96E958260" item-length="883" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newly Found Fungus Is Tied To Vanishing Species of Frog</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Newly discovered fungus appears to be cause of epidemic among amphibians that is killing off frogs and toads of wide variety of declining species in rain forests in Australia and Central America; new report by international team of researchers lists 19 species of frogs that are succumbing to newly discovered fungus called chytrid; it remains to be seen how and why fungus is killing frogs in such large numbers over such a wide area, as well as whether it is killing in areas other than Central America and Australia; findings are described in Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A newly discovered fungus appears to be the cause of an epidemic among amphibians that is killing off frogs and toads of a wide variety of declining species in rain forests in Australia and Central America, according to a new report by an international team of researchers. Scientists say the new study may help solve the mystery of why amphibians are vanishing around the world, often from pristine, isolated habitats.</p>
        <p>Nineteen species of frogs, researchers report, are succumbing to a newly discovered fungus called a chytrid, a type of fungus known previously to live only on decaying matter and insects. Researchers say it remains to be seen how and why the fungus is killing frogs in such large numbers over such a wide area, as well as whether the fungus is doing its deadly work in areas other than Central America and Australia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A newly discovered fungus appears to be the cause of an epidemic among amphibians that is killing off frogs and toads of a wide variety of declining species in rain forests in Australia and Central America, according to a new report by an international team of researchers. Scientists say the new study may help solve the mystery of why amphibians are vanishing around the world, often from pristine, isolated habitats.</p>
        <p>Nineteen species of frogs, researchers report, are succumbing to a newly discovered fungus called a chytrid, a type of fungus known previously to live only on decaying matter and insects. Researchers say it remains to be seen how and why the fungus is killing frogs in such large numbers over such a wide area, as well as whether the fungus is doing its deadly work in areas other than Central America and Australia.</p>
        <p>The research is described in a report to appear in next month's issue of the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences. The mystery of the vanishing amphibians has been plaguing scientists for a decade, ever since they began noticing that frogs were disappearing. At various times, researchers have proposed ultraviolet light, pollution and disease as the villains, but scientists lacked direct evidence that any of these factors was causing large, widespread declines.</p>
        <p>Searching the tissues of dead frogs, biologists on the new study say, they found fungi as the clear culprit. When researchers scraped fungi off the skin of the dead frogs and infected the water of healthy frogs, within a couple of weeks all the exposed frogs were dead or dying.  But while researchers described the new study as convincing, they noted that skin scrapes were not pure samples of fungus. To be sure that the fungus alone is killing the frogs, researchers must await the results of a last crucial test.</p>
        <p>Dr. Joyce Longcore, chytrid fungal specialist at the University of Maine at Orono, said that she had grown a pure culture of the fungus and that she and colleagues at the National Zoo were in the process of doing the experiment find out whether the pure fungus can kill frogs.</p>
        <p>Researchers say the new fungus is unlikely to be related to the limb deformities in Minnesota frogs.</p>
        <p>The report that will appear next month provides a long-awaited answer for scientists, who had been mystified by the increasing reports of large numbers of dead frogs in rain forests in Central and South America and Australia. Quickly eaten by scavengers, wild frog cadavers are a rare sight, with biologists typically seeing no more than two or three in the wild in a lifetime. The numbers were ''just stunning,'' said Dr. David Wake, amphibian biologist at the University of California at Berkeley. ''When you find carcasses in a rain forest, you know you're only finding a tiny fragment of the number really there.''</p>
        <p>Researchers still do not know exactly how the fungus kills so many frogs, but say they suspect it is by suffocation. Frogs breathe not only through their lungs, but also by absorbing oxygen through their moist skin. As the fungus grows in the skin of frogs, the skin appears to grow more layers, making it more difficult for the frog to absorb oxygen.</p>
        <p>While biologists say they are confident that the newly discovered fungus is the immediate cause of the death of these frogs, it is unclear whether the frogs were already weakened by other factors and so more susceptible. Researchers are now studying air, water and other samples from regions where the frogs died in a search for such factors.</p>
        <p>Researchers agree that other factors are certainly at play in the amphibian deaths around the globe. For example, Dr. Wake said it was very likely that chemical contamination was involved in California and that ultraviolet light was a factor in Oregon.</p>
        <p>''Nobody thinks there's a single answer to this problem,'' Dr. Wake said.</p>
        <p>Researchers do not know why the fungal disease is emerging now. Dr. D. Earl Green, a veterinary pathologist who worked on the project at the Maryland Animal Health Laboratory, said the new fungus had been seen in healthy frogs from Maryland and Illinois, suggesting that the disease may be from more northern climes and made its way to the tropics recently, perhaps on the boot of a tourist or the net of a biologist. Once there, it might easily attack populations that had never been exposed to it before. Alternatively, the disease may have been around for years and is only now able to ravage populations weakened by other factors.</p>
        <p>''It's one thing to go and look for frogs and say they're gone, but what we needed were the bodies to work on,'' said Dr. Peter Daszak, parasitologist at Kingston University in England and an author of the report. Now, with all the carcasses at their disposal, he said, ''at last we seem to be getting somewhere.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
