<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Long-Distance Discounts, More Numbers to Dial</title>
    <meta content="28NUMB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1028019"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="SPENDING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mci Communications Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">West, Debra</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980628T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E3DF173FF93BA15755C0A96E958260" item-length="863" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Long-Distance Discounts, More Numbers to Dial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEBRA WEST</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">West, Debra</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Dial-around long-distance companies, largest of which is MCI Communications, are changing ad campaigns to accommodate government's new 7-digit dialing requirements; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG before the actor John Lithgow started urging people to save on long-distance telephone calls by dialing 10-321, officials at MCI Communications knew that the easy-to-remember code would soon be complicated by a couple of extra digits.</p>
        <p>Before introducing the service in mid-1996, MCI executives had to make a choice: they could either promote their ''dial-around'' service with the seven-digit code it would eventually have to carry or use a catchier five-digit number for as long as the Federal Communications Commission allowed, then go through the expense of re-educating customers when the change inevitably came.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LONG before the actor John Lithgow started urging people to save on long-distance telephone calls by dialing 10-321, officials at MCI Communications knew that the easy-to-remember code would soon be complicated by a couple of extra digits.</p>
        <p>Before introducing the service in mid-1996, MCI executives had to make a choice: they could either promote their ''dial-around'' service with the seven-digit code it would eventually have to carry or use a catchier five-digit number for as long as the Federal Communications Commission allowed, then go through the expense of re-educating customers when the change inevitably came.</p>
        <p>They took the latter path, investing nearly $79 million on the 10-321 ad campaign in 1997 and another $38 million in the first quarter of this year to establish the service, according to Competitive Media Reports, which tracks ad spending.</p>
        <p>''There were less numbers and it was easier to remember,'' said Brad Burns, a spokesman for MCI and Telecom USA, the subsidiary that runs 10-321. ''This product lives on advertising. We wanted to keep it in the top of the mind. Now, considering 10-321 has such great brand awareness, we'll just roll it over.''</p>
        <p>Judgment day is nigh. As of Wednesday, customers of the service will have to dial 10-10-321 to gain access to MCI's lines and discounted long-distance rates. Though it declined to disclose how much the new campaign was costing, MCI has been promoting the new number ferociously, with direct mailings and new TV ads featuring Mr. Lithgow. Last Wednesday, the service went so far as to offer one free 20-minute phone call to anyone using the new number from 5 P.M. to midnight that night.</p>
        <p>''There might be a little bit of a hiccup,'' Daniel E. Zito, a telecommunications analyst at Legg Mason Wood Walker in Baltimore, said of the short-term prospects for the new number. ''It will require some consumer education. But I think it will still be successful. It's a very mass-market way to tap into the casual long-distance user.''</p>
        <p>Dozens of companies now operate dial-around telephone services, which promise lower long-distance rates in return for dialing the codes that direct the telephone network to connect the call to a specific carrier. The size of the discount from dial-around services is a matter of debate, since they usually compare their lower rates with the highest nondiscounted residential rates available.</p>
        <p>Many dial-around services will be making the adjustment to seven digits -- a change intended in part to accommodate the growing number of carriers. But because the MCI service, the most heavily marketed, dominates the niche, it faces the most public re-education campaign.</p>
        <p>''MCI, by putting all the dollars it has in, has made the whole category float,'' said Amanda McCarthy, an analyst at the Yankee Group, a telecommunications research firm in Boston. She said 9.4 percent of American households used a dial-around service in 1997.</p>
        <p>Ms. McCarthy estimated that MCI controls more than 50 percent of the dial-around segment, which had revenues of $1.5 billion in 1997. That figure could grow to $2 billion this year, in large part because of MCI's push for its new number, she said.</p>
        <p>Dial-around numbers allow users to gain access to different phone companies' lines, one call at a time, without committing to switch their long-distance carriers permanently.</p>
        <p>A subscriber to the AT&amp;T long-distance service, for instance, could dial 10-321 before making a call to route that call over MCI's network. Similarly, an MCI customer could dial 10-288 (for 10-ATT) to route a call over AT&amp;T's system.</p>
        <p>WHY the change in the number? The first two digits in the code -- 1 and 0 -- exist only to inform the telephone system that a three-digit code identifying the desired carrier is about to follow. That means that only 1,000 dial-around codes have been available.</p>
        <p>Since 1989, telecommunications companies have known that the supply of those three-digit numbers, called carrier identification codes, would run out eventually. Indeed, the numbers, which are also used by wireless carriers and large corporate accounts, were exhausted in 1995.</p>
        <p>Industry executives and the F.C.C. debated when to start requiring the seven-digit numbers, which make about 10,000 codes available for use. A transition period began in 1995, with carriers having the option of using their five-digit numbers or switching to seven.</p>
        <p>Last October -- a month before MCI expanded 10-321 from 19 test markets into a national service -- the F.C.C. set July 1 as the mandatory changeover date. Kris Monteith, a senior lawyer for the F.C.C., says the seven-digit rule is intended to give all the competitors a level playing field.</p>
        <p>''We knew this was coming,'' said Mr. Burns of MCI. ''It was a business decision to wait. We think customers will adjust to the change.''</p>
        <p>SPENDING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
