<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Campus Life: Swarthmore;   Dropping Books, 37 Students Enter A Library Race</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="331781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RACES AND REGATTAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LIBRARIES AND LIBRARIANS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SWARTHMORE COLLEGE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Libraries and Librarians</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1DA133EF937A35750C0A966958260" item-length="315" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Campus Life: Swarthmore;   Dropping Books, 37 Students Enter A Library Race</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>SWARTHMORE, Pa.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: With midterms approaching this week, 25 male and 12 female Swarthmore College undergraduates took a break from their books last Sunday to take part in the annual McCabe Mile - an 18-lap race amid the bookshelves in the McCabe Library basement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: With midterms approaching this week, 25 male and 12 female Swarthmore College undergraduates took a break from their books last Sunday to take part in the annual McCabe Mile - an 18-lap race amid the bookshelves in the McCabe Library basement.</p>
        <p>With midterms approaching this week, 25 male and 12 female Swarthmore College undergraduates took a break from their books last Sunday to take part in the annual McCabe Mile - an 18-lap race amid the bookshelves in the McCabe Library basement.</p>
        <p>Running in the men's race for the third time, Paul Harrison, a senior from Stratford, Conn., majoring in economics, won for the second year in a row. His time was 5 minutes, 24.5 seconds.</p>
        <p>A first-time entrant, Margaret Cooley, a junior from Rochester majoring in literature, won the women's race in 6 minutes, 20.2 seconds.</p>
        <p>Carolyn Comiskey, a senior history major from Darien, Conn., and Caroline Soter, a senior majoring in sociology and anthropology from Lake Bluff, Ill., entered the race dressed as ''nerds,'' carrying backpacks, books and a calculator. They finished last in the women's race, their times being the slowest recorded in the event's 21-year history at 10 minutes, 15.2 seconds.</p>
        <p>First Prize - Tissue</p>
        <p>Instead of a starting pistol, the races began with the starter reading passages from a book - from the writings of Mao Zedong for the women, and from a book by Percy Shelley for the men - and then slamming the books shut. One runner, Kerry Ann King, a senior philosophy major from Manhattan, correctly identified the passage from the book and, as a reward, was allowed to move to the front rank of runners at the starting line.</p>
        <p>First prizes were rolls of Scott toilet tissue in honor of Thomas McCabe, a former chairman of the Scott Paper Company for whom Swarthmore's library is named.</p>
        <p>The races attracted almost a hundred spectators, many of whom climbed on top of shelves to get better views.</p>
        <p>The race originated in 1969, when two students started running amid the stacks to let off nervous energy during exam week. The practice continued, with other students joining in, until the race became a tradition.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
