<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Give Us This Day Our Daily Supplements</title>
    <meta content="04play-supplement" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="0" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1830671"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PHYS ED"/>
      <identified-content>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romanowski, Bill, Reynolds, Gretchen, Bechler, Steve, Romanowski, Bill, Reynolds, Gretchen, Bechler, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EFD61731F937A35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1528" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Give Us This Day Our Daily Supplements</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRETCHEN REYNOLDS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's no surprise that athletes like their dietary supplements. By conservative estimates, they spend nearly $4 billion annually on pills, powders and other sports-nutrition products in the hope that they'll improve health and increase performance. New Orleans Saints center Jeff Faine recently told a reporter that he takes about 65 pills a day; for the sake of time management, he has taught himself to swallow as many as 17 at a time. This daily gorging pales next to that of Bill Romanowski, the former linebacker. In his 2005 autobiography, ''Romo: My Life on the Edge,'' Romanowski writes that he kept a tackle box filled with some 500 pills and would take handfuls a day, all washed down with protein shakes. He also famously admits to taking vials of THG, an anabolic steroid, but most of what he consumed were legal supplements available at any Walgreens or GNC store.</p>
        <p>Such supplements are not necessarily benign. In 2003, Baltimore Orioles pitcher Steve Bechler died, in part, from a reaction to ephedrine, a wildly popular supplement used to increase energy and metabolism. Ephedrine, a stimulant derived from the ephedra plant, can elevate heart rate and blood pressure, in some cases fatally. It's now illegal to market ephedrine as a dietary supplement, though it's still widely available, often as a decongestant or a cold remedy. Sales are brisk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's no surprise that athletes like their dietary supplements. By conservative estimates, they spend nearly $4 billion annually on pills, powders and other sports-nutrition products in the hope that they'll improve health and increase performance. New Orleans Saints center Jeff Faine recently told a reporter that he takes about 65 pills a day; for the sake of time management, he has taught himself to swallow as many as 17 at a time. This daily gorging pales next to that of Bill Romanowski, the former linebacker. In his 2005 autobiography, ''Romo: My Life on the Edge,'' Romanowski writes that he kept a tackle box filled with some 500 pills and would take handfuls a day, all washed down with protein shakes. He also famously admits to taking vials of THG, an anabolic steroid, but most of what he consumed were legal supplements available at any Walgreens or GNC store.</p>
        <p>Such supplements are not necessarily benign. In 2003, Baltimore Orioles pitcher Steve Bechler died, in part, from a reaction to ephedrine, a wildly popular supplement used to increase energy and metabolism. Ephedrine, a stimulant derived from the ephedra plant, can elevate heart rate and blood pressure, in some cases fatally. It's now illegal to market ephedrine as a dietary supplement, though it's still widely available, often as a decongestant or a cold remedy. Sales are brisk.</p>
        <p>Which underscores the disturbing truth about supplements: science and common sense often have less effect on their use than hope, hype and word of mouth. ''A lot of the information about supplements is generated by the manufacturers or by personal testimonials,'' says Kathleen Laquale, a leading nutritionist and an associate professor of athletic training at Bridgewater State College in Massachusetts. ''Someone at the machine next to you in the gym says, 'You've got to try this.' ''</p>
        <p>That person could be right. Some supplements do what they promise. But the vast majority are ineffective -- hard news for people (like me) who load up on vitamins and other pills and powders in the belief that they must be doing something. So how to separate the dross from the goods? Aside from the obvious -- don't take a supplement you haven't thoroughly researched -- it's a matter of trial and error. What works for others might not work for you. Also bear in mind that positive results may have more to do with what's going on in your mind than in your body. Try a high-profile supplement, some of the most popular of which are discussed here, and chances are you'll swear it works, even if, strictly speaking, it doesn't. The placebo effect, Laquale says, ''is still an effect.''</p>
        <p>Vitamins and Minerals: Way Too Much of a Good Thing</p>
        <p>Unless you're on an outré diet (grapefruit, cabbage soup, even Atkins), you're probably getting enough daily nutrients without help from pills. ''Most Americans easily get 100 percent of the vitamins and minerals they need from their food,'' says Ellen Coleman, a sports dietician who consults for the Los Angeles Lakers and Angels.</p>
        <p>It's often presumed, however, that athletes need more than their three balanced meals a day. Heavy exertion increases the body's use of oxygen and subsequently produces more free radicals: unstable atoms and molecules known to be harmful to cells. In theory, athletes should benefit from extra doses of antioxidants like vitamins C and E, beta carotene and coenzyme Q10, which reduce free radicals.</p>
        <p>But research has produced mixed results. Several recent studies of animals suggested that large single doses of antioxidants (1,000 I.U. of vitamin E, say, instead of 100 I.U.) actually increased signs of oxidative damage; other studies have suggested that antioxidants might help speed muscle recovery, particularly for older athletes. To further the confusion, researchers have recently speculated that those who exercise less vigorously could possibly benefit more from antioxidant supplements than could elite athletes, whose bodies, the thinking now goes, might be better equipped to combat oxidative stress.</p>
        <p>Athletes also tend to overdo the B-complex vitamins. Because B vitamins are essential for turning carbohydrates, fats and proteins into energy, many vitamins contain -- and trumpet on their labels -- mega-doses of the stuff. But ''there's not much evidence that extra doses of B vitamins give you better athletic performance or anything else,'' Laquale says -- besides a lighter wallet.</p>
        <p>If you still can't bear the thought of parting with your vitamins, limit yourself to a one-a-day multivitamin. ''It's hard to overdose on any one nutrient that way,'' says Alicia Kendig, a sports dietician with Carmichael Training Systems in Colorado Springs, ''and it gives you that little bit of extra insurance that you're getting all the nutrients you need.''</p>
        <p>Creatine: Speed, Strength and Some Minor Gastric Upset</p>
        <p>Creatine, an amino acid compound stored in muscle tissue, is the top-selling sports supplement in the country. Available in powdered form, it aids the production of phosphocreatine (PCr), an important fuel used during short, intense exercise.</p>
        <p>This is one supplement that actually seems to work. ''There's solid research that creatine helps to increase muscle mass and strength,'' Coleman says. One recent study of male United S tates Army soldiers found that those taking creatine could do 14 percent more bench press repetitions than those taking a placebo. And a 2002 study conducted by Australian researchers showed that elite female soccer players who took the supplement were faster in a series of sprints than those on a placebo.</p>
        <p>But creatine's benefits are limited to activities that demand strength or short bursts of speed. It won't do much for marathoners or other distance athletes. It's not gentle on the system, either. Creatine pulls water into muscles, and in the process can dehydrate the rest of the body. Studies done in the late 1990s suggested that there were links between the supplement and muscle cramping and diarrhea, but those side effects were found at doses higher than what is generally recommended today. Coleman says five grams a day should get you the benefits without too much . . . distress.</p>
        <p>DHEA: Increased Productivity at the Testosterone Factory?</p>
        <p>Dehydroepiandrosterone, or DHEA, is a hormone produced naturally in human adrenal glands. Without it, the body can't make testosterone or estrogen. Because of this link to testosterone, many athletes take DHEA capsules in the hope of building more muscle.</p>
        <p>Studies conducted in the 1990s showed that rats and mice developed stronger bones, muscles and immune systems when given DHEA. Rodents, however, produce little DHEA naturally, so some researchers speculated that the supplement merely acted as a temporary jolt to their systems. Although a few small studies suggested that some elderly people with low levels of DHEA benefited from taking the supplements, the overall results were equivocal.</p>
        <p>Then last October, in the New England Journal of Medicine, researchers from the Mayo Clinic published the results of a two-year, double-blind study on the efficacy of DHEA. The study found no beneficial effects. A 75-milligram daily dose for men did increase blood levels of DHEA but didn't increase muscle strength or oxygen consumption. Neither did it decrease body fat. DHEA had no ''physiologically relevant beneficial effects,'' the authors concluded.</p>
        <p>Undeterred, the Council for Responsible Nutrition, a trade group for the supplement industry, released a statement saying that the Mayo study confirmed ''the safety of relatively high-dose DHEA.'' It didn't work, but it didn't kill anyone, either.</p>
        <p>It's this kind of cheery obfuscation that keeps the supplement industry humming. ''The amount of deliberate misinformation out there is amazing,'' Laquale says. ''It would be funny if it weren't so disturbing.''</p>
        <p>Because the Food and Drug Administration doesn't closely regulate the nutritional supplement business -- a 1994 law exempted supplements from strict oversight -- the claims made by manufacturers tend to be extravagant. (''Instantly Triggers Extreme Muscle Expansion!'') The fine print adds that these statements have not been evaluated by the F.D.A. ''But most people don't read that far,'' Coleman says.</p>
        <p>Where, then, can you look for reliable, unbiased information? One place to start is ConsumerLab.com, an independent research organization that tests supplements. A yearly subscription to the site, which posts all of the lab's product reports, costs $27.</p>
        <p>In some instances, supplements tested by ConsumerLab have been found to contain ingredients not printed on their labels. A recent test of weight-loss supplements found that some were contaminated with lead. More often, though, the lab discovers what's not in the supplement. ConsumerLab's creatine study, for example, revealed products that contained little or no creatine at all. ''The labels of supplements can be misleading,'' says Tod Cooperman, a medical doctor who specializes in pharmaceuticals and is ConsumerLab's president. ''You should always be skeptical.''</p>
        <p>One abiding fact about supplements is that their allure waxes and ebbs. The newest ''it'' supplement is resveratrol, a substance found in the skin of red grapes that was recently shown to protect against weight gain in rodents and to almost double the animals' endurance on a treadmill. Since the results of this research were announced last year, companies have been scrambling to produce resveratrol formulations. Dozens are now available.</p>
        <p>Studies have yet to be conducted to determine whether resveratrol improves performance in humans. Until then, it might be easier just to swallow your vitamins with a glass of Shiraz.</p>
        <p>PHYS ED</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
