<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Laundry Instructions, With Life Lessons Attached</title>
    <meta content="04RGENCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1830384"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="GENERATIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Laundries and Laundry Aids</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stewart, Susan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Laundries and Laundry Aids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Families and Family Life</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E7DE1631F937A35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="899" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Laundry Instructions, With Life Lessons Attached</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUSAN STEWART</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stewart, Susan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Susan Stewart Generations essay on laundering instructions and life lessons her mother wrote to her before she went away to college and changes her daughter noticed when instructions were passed on; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT was a laundry list. Not a metaphorical laundry list, an actual one. On the eve of my departure for college, my mother had practically filled a small spiral notebook with instructions on washing clothes, making abundant use of capitals and underlines.</p>
        <p>''Hand wash all good cotton sweater tops,'' it read. ''Rinse well and roll in towel. Lay flat to dry. This is a general rule for all good tops.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT was a laundry list. Not a metaphorical laundry list, an actual one. On the eve of my departure for college, my mother had practically filled a small spiral notebook with instructions on washing clothes, making abundant use of capitals and underlines.</p>
        <p>''Hand wash all good cotton sweater tops,'' it read. ''Rinse well and roll in towel. Lay flat to dry. This is a general rule for all good tops.''</p>
        <p>This was the '70s, a decade when it was still possible to make the distinction between ''good'' and ''everyday'' clothes. There were further instructions: on ''good cotton slacks,'' ''polyester pantsuits,'' ''bodysuits'' (did we really wear those?) and, yes, underwear.</p>
        <p>''Best to hand-wash bras  -- do not dry in dryer. They can be put into washer with underpants if water is cool and you are using Ivory Snow.''</p>
        <p>Laundry was more complex then. My mother devoted an entire page to the care of shirts (''Take out of dryer when nearly dry and hang up  stretch fabric delicately on hanger  no ironing needed if you do this effectively'').</p>
        <p>I doubt I ever did this effectively. I know I never used an iron in four years. Did my mother know how lightly I would take her instruction? How bad my shirts would look? Probably.</p>
        <p>''Ask around for a reputable cleaner,'' she wrote. ''If you don't find one, bring good slacks and pantsuits home.''</p>
        <p>Occasionally my mother's instructions seemed to reflect a sense of alarm.</p>
        <p>''Madras fades,'' read one entry. ''That orange and yellow top of yours is the worst thing ever to fade. Do not wash with anything else or touch anything with it!!!''</p>
        <p>Hmm. Maybe this was a metaphor. After all, the sexual revolution was still big news, and I was leaving home for a large university 400 miles away. My mother was well versed in the double entendre (10 years hence, she would, in a humiliating conversation, ask my husband-to-be to make sure I remembered to take my birth-control pills -- ''for her skin.'' ''We don't want any unexpected breakouts, do we?'' she said to my stunned fiancé). Back then, writing my college-eve instructions, she was clearly concerned about more than laundry.</p>
        <p>''So many things '' she began on one page, and I could almost hear the heavy maternal sigh. ''Just be as nice a young woman as I know you are. Don't change.''</p>
        <p>I was 18 and full of self-loathing. I wanted to change.</p>
        <p>''Please don't stay up too late, or go out with strangers. You are real good-looking and this makes for more passes, problems.''</p>
        <p>At the time, I wanted passes, problems, late nights and a chance to mingle my laundry with the laundry of some of those 25,000 strangers I was about to meet. She wanted me to stay as pure, and as boring, as Ivory Snow.</p>
        <p>My mother died last summer, just before my older daughter left for college. I found the laundry list a few weeks later, when I was clearing out her house. Sensing a touching family moment in the making, I copied the entire notebook and mailed it to the freshman in question.</p>
        <p>She didn't mention the laundry list until I asked about it during the December break.</p>
        <p>''I didn't read it for a long time,'' she said. ''It was just too sad. But then I did, and I thought it was really touching -- and funny. You had a good mother.''</p>
        <p>Wait a minute. Doesn't my daughter have a good mother, too?</p>
        <p>She gave me a look. ''Not in terms of laundry.''</p>
        <p>''What do you mean?'' I said. ''I gave you plenty of laundry instruction. I just didn't write it down.''</p>
        <p>''Mom,'' she said, ''we never had the laundry talk. You just gave me one of those white-out sticks. You know, you just put it in your bag and go? For emergencies?''</p>
        <p>I remembered. Tide to Go. You spill something on yourself (as my daughter is wont to do) and you rub the stick into the stain and forget about it until laundry day. Progress is wonderful.</p>
        <p>I thought we were done, but my daughter was not ready to let the subject drop so fast. She had, after all, just finished Psych 101. ''It's so indicative of the different generations and their parenting styles,'' she said. ''Gran wrote an entire book on laundry, and you just give me a little stick to protect me, like Mace or something. It's certainly easier for you.''</p>
        <p>''You can call me anytime with a laundry question,'' I assured her. ''And I can tell you the answer, or even e-mail it to you.''</p>
        <p>But was this too little, too late? Had I been too sanguine about the efficacy of the new detergents? Had I missed the boat, parentally speaking? Did my daughter have any standards about her own laundry? Or was it already permanently stained?</p>
        <p>I thought all this. What I said was, ''Has the stain stick been working?''</p>
        <p>''If you mean, have I washed my clothes in the last three weeks, the answer is no. But I carry the stick with me everywhere.''</p>
        <p>''Better safe than sorry,'' I said. ''Have you had to use the stick?''</p>
        <p>''I have not yet had a laundry emergency,'' she said. She sighed a heavy filial sigh, and I was reminded, painfully, of my mother. ''But you don't have to worry. I know I'll be prepared when I do.''</p>
        <p>GENERATIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
