<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Official and 3 Journalists Arrested in Newark</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="643662"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRESPASS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEWARK (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">STAR-LEDGER (NEWARK, NJ)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NIEVES, EVELYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HILDAGO, HILDA (ASST COMR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931021T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DD143EF932A15753C1A965958260" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Official and 3 Journalists Arrested in Newark</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EVELYN NIEVES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NIEVES, EVELYN</byline>
      <dateline>NEWARK, Oct. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tensions between state education officials and the Newark school district erupted today when a state education commissioner and three journalists for The Star-Ledger were arrested after refusing to leave an elementary school.</p>
        <p>Hilda Hidalgo, an assistant commissioner for professional development and licensing, Robert J. Braun, education editor for The Star-Ledger and two photographers, Joe Gigli and John O'Boyle, were arrested at the Morton Street School after a fracas with school guards and Newark police officers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tensions between state education officials and the Newark school district erupted today when a state education commissioner and three journalists for The Star-Ledger were arrested after refusing to leave an elementary school.</p>
        <p>Hilda Hidalgo, an assistant commissioner for professional development and licensing, Robert J. Braun, education editor for The Star-Ledger and two photographers, Joe Gigli and John O'Boyle, were arrested at the Morton Street School after a fracas with school guards and Newark police officers.</p>
        <p>Dr. Hidalgo, who was making a spot check of the school as part of an investigation that could lead to a state takeover of New Jersey's largest school system, was charged with creating a disturbance and resisting arrest. The three journalists, who were accompanying her, were charged with trespassing and assaulting a school guard. All four were issued summonses and released.</p>
        <p>Eugene C. Campbell, executive superintendent of the nearly 50,000-student district, said the police were called after Mr. Braun and the photographers refused to follow the standard procedures when members of the media enter a school. Asked to sign in at the principal's office by a school guard and assistant principal, the photographers, Mr. Braun and Dr. Hidalgo locked arms, Mr. Campbell said, and pushed their way past school workers. Very Different Claims</p>
        <p>Barbara Ervin, a vice principal of the school, which has 563 students in kindergarten through the eighth grade, said that Dr. Hidalgo and the others pushed into her and that a photographer took pictures of kindergarten girls as they left a bathroom.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Braun said in a statement that he and the photographers had been in the school with Dr. Hidalgo for about a half-hour when they were confronted in a third-floor staircase by Newark police officers and Newark school officials, who ordered them to leave. He said Dr. Hidalgo stated that they were there at the request of the Education Commissioner, whose orders were to let them stay. Dr. Hidalgo was then dragged down the stairway, he said. The photographers were blocked from taking pictures of the arrest, he said, and both he and the others were arrested for trespassing outside on the street, not on school property.</p>
        <p>State Education Commissioner Mary Lee Fitzgerald said she was shocked at Dr. Hidalgo's arrest.</p>
        <p>"I am just really overwhelmed that she could be treated this way," she said. The state department issued a terse statement later that said Dr. Hidalgo would be represented by counsel and the Attorney General. Visiting 6 Schools</p>
        <p>Mr. Braun said he and the photographers had visited six schools in the last two weeks -- at the express invitation of Dr. Fitzgerald -- with members of a state team that is reviewing the schools' performance. The state's review, known as a comprehensive compliance investigation, is the final step in a process that may lead to the state takeover of Newark's troubled system, which has been charged with mismanagement, nepotism and political interference.</p>
        <p>Mr. Campbell said that while the district had been cooperating with the state since the investigative team began monitoring schools in May, he had called a Star-Ledger editor last week and complained about how Mr. Braun and the photographers were entering the schools and, in at least one case, taking pictures of students without getting permission.</p>
        <p>Last week, he said, Mr. Braun signed into Central High School as a member of the comprehensive compliance investigation team.</p>
        <p>"He didn't identify himself as a reporter," Mr. Campbell said. "He said he was with the C.C.I. team. Either he's a reporter, or he's a member of the team. He wasn't on the list of the members of the team." Reporter and Columnist</p>
        <p>But Mr. Braun said that he simply "dittoed" on a sign-in sheet that the team members signed when they entered the schools.</p>
        <p>"As a consequence of our dittoing it, we're being accused of misrepresenting ourselves," he said. "We weren't trying to hide who we were."</p>
        <p>Mr. Braun works as both chief education reporter for The Star-Ledger and as a regular education columnist, and has written several columns in which he has called for a state takeover. He was touring schools with the state team, he said, in order to do a series of stories on the schools.</p>
        <p>Mr. Campbell said he had been encouraging reporters to visit the schools to show that they were not as bad as news reports had made them seem.</p>
        <p>"We're in a lose-lose situation," Mr. Campbell said. "Now it looks like we've got something to hide, that we're trying to keep reporters out. All you have to do is call us up and we'll arrange it."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
