<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Group Aims to Save Hudson Main Streets</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="795046"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HUDSON RIVER</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HISTORIC RIVER TOWNS OF WESTCHESTER (ORGN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SINGER, PENNY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1D91239F93BA35753C1A963958260" item-length="1028" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Group Aims to Save Hudson Main Streets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PENNY SINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SINGER, PENNY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF 10 are good, 1 is better. Such was the reasoning of the mayors and supervisors of 10 municipalities along the Hudson River, who have banded together to form a public-private partnership known as Historic River Towns of Westchester in order to market themselves as a single tourist destination.</p>
        <p>Mayor Robert W. Elliott of Croton-on-Hudson is the founder and chairman of the consortium. Mr. Elliott, who ran a family-owned hardware business in Croton for many years, said it was the plight of local businesses, such as his,  that led him to contact other mayors in an effort to mount a joint economic development program that would benefit all businesses and towns on the Hudson River.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF 10 are good, 1 is better. Such was the reasoning of the mayors and supervisors of 10 municipalities along the Hudson River, who have banded together to form a public-private partnership known as Historic River Towns of Westchester in order to market themselves as a single tourist destination.</p>
        <p>Mayor Robert W. Elliott of Croton-on-Hudson is the founder and chairman of the consortium. Mr. Elliott, who ran a family-owned hardware business in Croton for many years, said it was the plight of local businesses, such as his,  that led him to contact other mayors in an effort to mount a joint economic development program that would benefit all businesses and towns on the Hudson River.</p>
        <p>Our main street in Croton was dying," Mr. Elliott said. "So I asked myself, what makes a main street tick, and the obvious answer was people. The problem we were having was a lack of people who would support the shops, the restaurants and everything else in town. Other communities all along the river, from Hastings to Peekskill, were having the same problems. What was lacking I felt, was a critical mass and identity. We needed to make a bigger bang. Rather than trying to reposition Croton on my own, I decided to contact all the mayors and supervisors along the river from Peekskill, Cortlandt, Ossining, North Tarrytown and Tarrytown, Irvington, Dobbs Ferry and Hastings to see if we could do something together to help us all. They were tremendously responsive. So one cold night in January 1993, we had a meeting at the Van Cortlandt Manor and that's when we began joining forces for our mutual benefit."</p>
        <p>By combining the attractions of each town into one entity, Historic River Towns of Westchester, Mr. Elliott said, "would fully capitalize on the tourist potential of the region." "We hired a project manager, Nancy Gold, to implement an effective marketing campaign," he continued. "Historic Hudson Valley is also a founding member of our group."</p>
        <p>To date, the joint economic initiative has raised $40,000 in private funds, Ms. Gold said, and $50,000 in public funds. Ms. Gold said that Citibank made the largest private contribution, $27,000, to the Historic River Town's project.</p>
        <p>Peter Mosbacher, Citibank vice president for community relations in Westchester and Rockland, said: "Citibank supports the project because Citibank  supports private-public sector efforts that encourage inter-municipal government planning and cooperation. The way the mayors and supervisors of the river towns  came together in a community development effort is a great example of intermunicipal cooperation.</p>
        <p>"We feel that the historic river towns of Westchester and the local economic  programs they are initiating can serve as a model not only for the rest of Westchester but for the entire Hudson Valley region."</p>
        <p>Westchester County allocated a matching grant of $30,000, which was used, in  part, Ms. Gold said, to subsidize a trolley service linking the historic sites,  hotels, main street shopping areas and train stations in Irvington, Tarrytown and North Tarrytown for 10 weekends this summer.</p>
        <p>Anthony Matero, who owns the River Gallery in Irvington, said: "More than 2,000 people rode the trolleys. Most of them were tourists, which resulted in an increase in business for stores and restaurants who say they have done better this past summer." Mr. Matero, who is also president of the Irvington Chamber of Commerce, added: "Everybody is behind this project. The success of the trolleys  in bringing in new people to the area shows how a coordinated effort can really  turn things around."</p>
        <p>Metro-North, New York Waterway cruises, hotels and historic sites were all involved in the effort, Mr. Matero said. "And so were people in our towns," he added. "The trolley was staffed by more than 30 volunteer tour guides belonging  to local historic societies. We have a lot of local pride in our river towns and their historic significance. Bringing tourists into our main streets, we're not  only improving the economic vitality of our towns but we're also drawing attention to the great tour sites we have here."</p>
        <p>The success of the initial trolley venture is expected to be replicated in other towns next summer, said William E. Burton, Supervisor of Ossining.</p>
        <p>"We expect to get the funding, and we were already promised funding next year from the county, and we're going to run the trolleys because they work," he said. "They are the sort of thing that attracts people. The route here would connect Ossining, Peekskill and Croton with attractions in all areas. In Ossining, for example, we have the Ossining Urban Cultural Park. It's most unusual, with exhibits of prison cells, Sing Sing and exhibits of the building of the Croton Aqueduct. And in Peekskill, the city is an example of how an old river town has revitalized itself through art. Peekskill has the top performing  arts center, the Paramount Center for the Arts, and a number of galleries and artists studios."</p>
        <p>The newest promotional program in the tourism-development project is Citibank's Pastport to the historic river towns of Westchester. "The Pastport comes in a color brochure and is available at 120 Citibank branches in Westchester, Rockland, the Bronx and Manhattan and at Grand Central Terminal and the New York Waterway ferry terminals," Mr. Mosbacher said..</p>
        <p>With the brochure and Pastports in hand, he said tourists can get discounted  admissions to most of the cultural and historic sites in the area. At each location the Pastport is stamped. "After the Pastport is stamped by three places and returned to any Citibank branch by Dec. 31, 1995," he said, "the bearer becomes eligible to win a weekend for two, which includes lodging, breakfast, dinner at one of our top hotels and restaurants."</p>
        <p>Ms. Gold said that a brochure and Pastport can be obtained by calling 271-2238. Information on coming events is available from River Fax at 591-3216,  extension 020.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
