<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hotels Stricter On Cancellations</title>
    <meta content="07PRAC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/07/travel/07PRAC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010121T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1260700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRACTICAL TRAVELER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reservations (Airlines, Hotels, Etc)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wade, Betsy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Columns/Practical Traveler</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reservations (Airlines, Hotels, Etc)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010107T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E4D9163BF934A35752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1295" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hotels Stricter On Cancellations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BETSY WADE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wade, Betsy</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Practical Traveler column on stricter cancellations policies now in effect at many hotels (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A COLLEAGUE making a hotel reservation at the Wyndham Inner Harbor in Baltimore was told that if she changed her plans, she had to cancel 72 hours -- three days -- in advance to avoid being charged for one night's stay. The colleague, who stays at chain hotels primarily for convenience and flexibility, was taken aback. The 72-hour policy was repeated in the confirmation letter.</p>
        <p>Wyndham's normal cancellation deadline is 48 hours, and this is what the hotel had recorded with the reservation, according to Darcie Brossart, a spokeswoman for Wyndham International in Dallas. The 72-hour warnings were described as a computer glitch: Wyndham International only recently took over the hotel from Omni, Ms. Brossart said, and new software for confirmation letters was generating information that conflicted with the hotel's policy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A COLLEAGUE making a hotel reservation at the Wyndham Inner Harbor in Baltimore was told that if she changed her plans, she had to cancel 72 hours -- three days -- in advance to avoid being charged for one night's stay. The colleague, who stays at chain hotels primarily for convenience and flexibility, was taken aback. The 72-hour policy was repeated in the confirmation letter.</p>
        <p>Wyndham's normal cancellation deadline is 48 hours, and this is what the hotel had recorded with the reservation, according to Darcie Brossart, a spokeswoman for Wyndham International in Dallas. The 72-hour warnings were described as a computer glitch: Wyndham International only recently took over the hotel from Omni, Ms. Brossart said, and new software for confirmation letters was generating information that conflicted with the hotel's policy.</p>
        <p>The micro-lesson at hotels with new managements is to ask if an unusual cancellation deadline is correct. The broader message is that cancellation deadlines are stretching out, and $50 early-departure penalties are coming in the door.</p>
        <p>According to Bjorn Hanson, director of the hospitality division of the PricewaterhouseCoopers accounting firm, these hotel policies have been unfolding over three to four years.</p>
        <p>And credit card companies no longer automatically resolve disputes in favor of the guest: Dave Richey, vice president for service management at Visa International, said that guests now win 50 percent of the time, as opposed to 80 percent the American Hotel and Motel Association estimated three years ago.</p>
        <p>Greater Demand Does It</p>
        <p>The recent economic boom has been creating the stricter policies: hotels generally have guests waiting  who will eventually give up and try elsewhere, so they force no-shows to declare early. Doug Jenkins, another Visa spokesman, called higher occupancy rates the driving factor in cancellation penalties. The occupancy rate nationwide this year was 63.7 percent, according to PricewaterhouseCoopers, and while the company expects this to decline slightly, to 63.1 percent in 2003, it does not sound as if penalties will melt away soon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hanson said that five years ago, 90 percent of American hotels -- excluding resorts -- required cancellation only by 6 p.m. of the day of arrival. ''Then starting in '96 and '97, a number of urban hotels, seeing increases in occupancy rates, got aggressive,'' he said. ''They said, 'Let's make it 6 p.m. of the day before.' They met little resistance. Then two years ago, hotels began to say 24 hours wasn't enough. And now it appears that 20 percent of urban hotels have a policy requiring cancellation 48 hours ahead of time.'' Ray Vastola, the president of Quikbook.com, a discount reservation service, said that in the last year his employees had noticed business hotels' increasingly moving to 24-hour deadlines.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hanson said that 60 percent of the time these days, hotels refused to waive the penalty, even for their best guests or for those who might have good reason to cancel late.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richey said that Visa did not get involved in most disputes over refunds; Visa gets those bucked up the line from the hotel, the cardholder's bank or the hotel's bank. Most disputes focus on whether the hotel told the guest the rules, whether the guest was given a phone number to call to cancel, whether the guest called in time and whether the guest was given a cancellation number.</p>
        <p>''Faced with complete conflict, we will mystery shop -- make a reservation anonymously to see what we are told,'' he said. ''We try to use every method to get the right resolution.'' If a hotel does not provide a clear statement of the policy on several calls, Mr. Richey said, Mr. Jenkins will be told that is a good spot for employee training. No area of the country performs worse than another, he said, but lower-priced hotels like Days Inns do. ''It's at a level where a $50 no-show penalty is a big piece of revenue,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Credit-Card Alert</p>
        <p>The credit-  and charge-card companies are in the middle: Guests guarantee the holding of their rooms beyond 6 p.m. by giving the hotel  card numbers. This enables the hotel to charge the no-show guest even though it does not have a signature. In addition to educating hotel staffs, card companies are educating cardholders about avoiding a penalty. American Express notified its members in 1996 of a policy revision: the deadline set by the hotel would prevail, not the 6 p.m. or 4 p.m. set earlier by American Express.</p>
        <p>Nancy Muller, a spokeswomen for American Express, said that her company had reduced by 20 percent the member complaints it got about hotel charges for failure to cancel when it added the words ''no show'' to the line with the hotel charge.</p>
        <p>Resorts set early deadlines because there may not be a waiting list of people nearby to take the room. Ms. Muller said that, in the main,  business travelers incurred no-show penalties; a plan to provide resort deposits produces few disputes, she said.</p>
        <p>In a city with a gorilla-size convention -- teachers, doctors and politicians -- all the hotels may agree upon an early deadline. Jeff Wagoner, senior vice president for hotel operations at Wyndham, said that sometimes the group organizing a convention would itself ask that the hotel or booking agency impose a 72-hour deadline so that if rooms closer to the convention hall became vacant, delegates could shift.</p>
        <p>Jeanne K. Datz, Hilton's director of communications, said that hotels did not want to overbook, but did face losses on no-shows. ''We estimate the demand level and look at the competition'' in setting deadlines, she said. The New York Hilton and the Waldorf-Astoria have 24-hour deadlines, she said, while the Hilton at O'Hare Airport is ''such a transient hotel'' that the deadline is 6 p.m. the same day, and the hotel knows it can fill the room. The San Francisco Hilton has a 72-hour deadline and the Fontainebleau in Miami Beach a resort deadline -- five days. The Peabody Orlando has a 72-hour policy, too.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hanson is sympathetic to deep deadlines at resorts. The trend he has trouble with is early-departure penalties. He estimated 15 to 20 percent of United States hotels, mostly chains and places in cities, had them. The Wyndham Inner Harbor does: leaving without 24 hours' notice, its confirmation letter said, costs $50. The Westin St. Francis in San Francisco charges $25 if the departure date is changed during the stay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hanson said the most common penalty was $50, and he did not understand how it was chosen. He also questioned the rationale for it.</p>
        <p>''If the city is filled up, the hotel has a waiting list and will rent the room to someone else and therefore is not entitled to the revenue,'' he said. ''If the city is empty, the hotel was lucky to have the guest who might have stayed that extra day and is not necessarily entitled to the revenue.''</p>
        <p>He put the start of this penalty at 10 years ago. ''And when this first appeared,'' he said, ''if the customer put up any argument at all, it was waived, until about two years ago. If I had to guess, I would say two-thirds to three-quarters of the hotels are now adhering to this policy.''</p>
        <p>''It's all an interesting philosophical question,'' he said.</p>
        <p>PRACTICAL TRAVELER  Correction:  January 21, 2001, Sunday  The Practical Traveler column on Jan. 7, about hotel cancellation policies, misstated Wyndham International's normal cancellation deadline. It is 24 hours (48 hours applies  on a holiday weekend).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: January 21, 2001, Sunday</p>
        <p>The Practical Traveler column on Jan. 7, about hotel cancellation policies, misstated Wyndham International's normal cancellation deadline. It is 24 hours (48 hours applies  on a holiday weekend).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
