<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In a Game of Streaks, Rockets Stand Taller</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="586850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSTON ROCKETS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY NETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREEMAN, MIKE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Houston Rockets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3D61038F932A05752C0A965958260" item-length="698" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In a Game of Streaks, Rockets Stand Taller</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREEMAN, MIKE</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Jan. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The effort, the hustle, the heart. Everything but the victory was there for the Nets against the Houston Rockets tonight. In a wild game that featured an even wilder fourth quarter, New Jersey lost its second straight, 108-105, before 11,801 at The Summit.</p>
        <p>Now, with apologies to the Dallas Cowboys and Buffalo Bills, Nets Coach Chuck Daly said that Monday's game against the lowly Dallas Mavericks is a must. "For us, that's the Super Bowl when you lose two," Daly said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The effort, the hustle, the heart. Everything but the victory was there for the Nets against the Houston Rockets tonight. In a wild game that featured an even wilder fourth quarter, New Jersey lost its second straight, 108-105, before 11,801 at The Summit.</p>
        <p>Now, with apologies to the Dallas Cowboys and Buffalo Bills, Nets Coach Chuck Daly said that Monday's game against the lowly Dallas Mavericks is a must. "For us, that's the Super Bowl when you lose two," Daly said.</p>
        <p>It was how the Nets (24-19) lost this game that probably frustrates them the most. They overcame a 91-79 Rockets lead with 9:39 left in the game. With their starting front court of Derrick Coleman (17 points, 7 rebounds), Sam Bowie (2 points) and Chucky Brown (10) sitting on the bench, the Nets went on an unlikely 14-0 run. In their place were Chris Dudley, Rick Mahorn and Rafeal Addison. The Nets eventually tied the score at 91-91 with 5:16 left and even took a 93-91 lead on one of many acrobatic moves to the basket by Kenny Anderson.</p>
        <p>But what has been a problem for New Jersey all season -- getting defensive stops when it really matters, as when there are only minutes left and the game is on the line -- was once again a problem. Morris Misses</p>
        <p>Houston, the home crowd lending the requisite vocal support, went on a 12-4 spurt of their own, and guard Vernon Maxwell made it 103-96 with 1:07 left. Though Houston missed three of its final six free throws, the Rockets did somehow manage to hold on. An off-balance 3-pointer by Chris Morris from about 30 feet banged off the side of the rim as the game ended.</p>
        <p>"It's tough to win on the road like that in the end," said Anderson, who had 25 points, a team-high 11 assists, and drew about 10 ooohs and aahhs from the crowd. "But the effort was there. We were tenacious, we didn't give up."</p>
        <p>Morris, who is still on the mend from a hip injury, had 8 points and 6 rebounds. Dudley came off the bench and grabbed a team-high 11 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Again, guard Drazen Petrovic lit up the Rockets. In fact, much of the talk of this game centered around Petrovic and Maxwell. When we last left our two combatants, it was Sunday and Petrovic had burned Maxwell for a career-high 44 points. Before the game, Maxwell, hinting at revenge and speaking of his honor, talked about how he hadn't forgetten the scorching.</p>
        <p>Whether Maxwell remembered or not, it didn't seem to matter to Petrovic. In 45 minutes he had a team-high 32 points on 12-of-24 shooting. In his four games against Houston, Petrovic has made 50 of 80 field-goal attempts (62 percent). Matchup Suits Him</p>
        <p>"I thought we had the comeback, but we missed some wide open shots in the end," said Petrovic. Asked about why he seems to play so well against the Rockets, he said, "I've always matched up well against Houston, even when I played with Portland. Maxwell is a very good player and a real tough competitor. He was kind of confused tonight and just wasn't on his game."</p>
        <p>Maxwell, who scored just 6 points, seems to have gained some newfound respect for Petrovic. He said the Nets guard should make the All-Star team, adding, "He's a great shooter, one of the best shooters I've ever played against. He's the real rifleman. I've never seen anyone shoot like that. He's got it all."</p>
        <p>Four Rockets players scored in double figures, led by Hakeem Olajuwon, who fouled out with 22 points, 14 rebounds and 6 assists. Guard Kenny Smith, who made his first five shots, finished with 20 points.</p>
        <p>Though he wasn't as much of a factor in the final minutes, Houston forward Robert Horry was a big factor in the Rockets' win. Horry Scores 21</p>
        <p>A first-round draft pick out of the University of Alabama, Horry averages 10.4 points and 5.3 rebounds a game. Scheduled to participate in the slam-dunk contest at the All-Star game, Horry is the first Rockets rookie to start on a regular basis since Olajuwon did it in 1984-85. Against the Nets he had 21 points -- on 8-of-12 shooting -- and grabbed 6 rebounds.</p>
        <p>After a terrific start on the road, the Nets' record away from home has slumped to a mediocre 11-11. So Daly isn't stretching the truth when he says that the Dallas game is a big one.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
