<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Reports of New Andrew Cuomo Post Praised</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="38" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="586771"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">APPOINTMENTS AND EXECUTIVE CHANGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSING AND URBAN DEVELOPMENT DEPARTMENT (HUD)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CISNEROS, HENRY G (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUOMO, ANDREW M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DD1239F932A05752C0A965958260" item-length="657" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Reports of New Andrew Cuomo Post Praised</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. McFADDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCFADDEN, ROBERT D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Advocates for the homeless and Mayor David N. Dinkins yesterday reacted enthusiastically to reports that Andrew M. Cuomo, a champion of housing for the homeless and the son of Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, will be named to a key Clinton Administration post in charge of homelessless and other urban problems.</p>
        <p>"I can't tell you how pleased I am," said George McDonald, president and founder of the Doe Fund, which aids the homeless. "No one in America is more qualified than Andrew Cuomo. He's a man of great character and love for people. He has accomplished things when he could have been lying on the beach."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Advocates for the homeless and Mayor David N. Dinkins yesterday reacted enthusiastically to reports that Andrew M. Cuomo, a champion of housing for the homeless and the son of Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, will be named to a key Clinton Administration post in charge of homelessless and other urban problems.</p>
        <p>"I can't tell you how pleased I am," said George McDonald, president and founder of the Doe Fund, which aids the homeless. "No one in America is more qualified than Andrew Cuomo. He's a man of great character and love for people. He has accomplished things when he could have been lying on the beach."</p>
        <p>Steven Banks, coordinating lawyer for the Legal Aid Society's Homeless Family Rights Project, also hailed reports yesterday in The New York Times and Newsday that the Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, Henry G. Cisneros, had chosen Mr. Cuomo to be his Assistant Secretary for Community Planning and Development, with a focus on homelessness, enterprise zones and other urban matters. The reports said the appointment is awaiting White House approval. 'Cautiously Optimistic'</p>
        <p>"Andrew Cuomo certainly knows firsthand the need for Federal intervention to prevent and alleviate homelessness," Mr. Banks said. "After 12 years of darkness on the Federal level, you can't help but be cautiously optimistic that people who have experience in combating homelessness will hold key positions in the new Administration."</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for Mayor Dinkins, Ana Marengo, said the Mayor was "very pleased" about the reported appointment. "Andrew Cuomo obviously knows the city's problems, and we hope that will reverberate to New York's benefit," she said in a City Hall statement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo, a 35-year-old lawyer who has worked on his father's campaigns, was on President Clinton's transition team and founded Housing Enterprise for the Less Privileged, a not-for-profit group that has tried to expand and redirect programs for the homeless, declined to comment on his reported appointment. The Governor's office also declined to comment.</p>
        <p>But advocates for the homeless were sanguine over prospects of his working with Mr. Cisneros, the former Mayor of San Antonio who gained a national name as the first Hispanic mayor of a major American city and a vocal advocate of innovative solutions to urban problems. 'A Human Dimension'</p>
        <p>"They are going to put a human dimension and a real face on all these poor people who have been left out in the cold for so long," said Mr. McDonald, who served with Mr. Cuomo on a mayoral commission that drew up a blueprint last February for dealing with the city's homeless problems.</p>
        <p>The commission, with Mr. Cuomo as chairman, recommended smaller residences to replace huge shelters where thousands live, wide expansion of transitional residences where the homeless are evaluated and enrolled in programs, and more permanent housing with social service support. It also urged the city to remove homeless programs from the troubled City Human Resources Administration. Mr. Dinkins has moved recently to put into practice many of the recommendations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Banks, who said some studies showed as many as three million homeless people in America, said it would be up to Mr. Cisneros and Mr. Cuomo to reverse many Reagan-Bush policies and to "get H.U.D. back in the business of seeking funding for its programs rather than attempting to dismantle them."</p>
        <p>Mr. McDonald, who estimated there were 80,000 single homeless people and 6,000 homeless families in the city, said he thought Mr. Cuomo's departure would not hurt the not-for-profit group he founded, and said Mr. Cuomo's background might enhance New York's prospects for Federal aid.</p>
        <p>"He's built a wonderful organization that will continue as he's called to higher service," Mr. McDonald said. "I'm certain that the transition will be smooth. And we will only benefit from his specific knowledge of the needs of our city and state."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
