<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>After Just 11 Days, TV Issues Verdict on Clinton</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930207T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="587066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="THE GAY TROOP ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D8123EF932A05752C0A965958260" item-length="715" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>After Just 11 Days, TV Issues Verdict on Clinton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELIZABETH KOLBERT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KOLBERT, ELIZABETH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If all honeymoons were like this, heart-shaped pools might never have been invented.</p>
        <p>Just 10 days ago, Bill Clinton took the oath of office in a warm, exuberant burst of television coverage complete with blue skies, fluttering flags and gauzy shots of the Capitol dome. But no sooner had the President hung up his formal wear than the glow of the inauguration gave way to cold assessments of his first 100 hours.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If all honeymoons were like this, heart-shaped pools might never have been invented.</p>
        <p>Just 10 days ago, Bill Clinton took the oath of office in a warm, exuberant burst of television coverage complete with blue skies, fluttering flags and gauzy shots of the Capitol dome. But no sooner had the President hung up his formal wear than the glow of the inauguration gave way to cold assessments of his first 100 hours.</p>
        <p>After what may be remembered as one of the shortest grace periods in Presidential history, many in the news media were already pronouncing Mr. Clinton's Administration in serious trouble before he had even had a chance to unpack his position papers.</p>
        <p>"From up close, the Clinton White House has looked like the 'Not-Ready- for-Prime-Time Players,' " Lisa Myers of NBC said two days after the new President was sworn in.</p>
        <p>"He hit the ground back-pedaling," Fred Barnes said on CNN's "McLaughlin Group" after three days.</p>
        <p>"It is just the first week of the Clinton Administration," Dan Rather said on CBS after seven days. "But oh, what a week." A Rush to Judgment</p>
        <p>Gauging by the tone of the coverage, it took just a bit more than a day for Mr. Clinton to be converted from the inspiring leader of a new generation to an old-fashioned, embattled incumbent. This rush to judgment was apparent both in the print and the electronic media. But it was especially pronounced among the television pundits who, it seemed, could barely conceal their impatience for an opportunity to evaluate Mr. Clinton's performance.</p>
        <p>Fortuitously, such an opportunity arose within 48 hours of Mr. Clinton's swearing in, when Zoe Baird, his choice for Attorney General, was forced to withdraw her nomination. The President had suffered his first official embarrassment. Among the pundits, Ms. Baird's sudden departure prompted much talk about how Mr. Clinton, once so attuned to his middle-class constituency, seemed to have lost touch with popular opinion.</p>
        <p>Ms. Baird had not yet been forgotten when, appearing Sunday on the NBC News program "Meet the Press," the President's Treasury Secretary, Lloyd Bentsen, said that the Administration was considering a broad-based energy tax to reduce the deficit. This provoked much head-shaking over what appeared to be the President's backing away from his campaign pledge not to raise taxes on the middle class.</p>
        <p>By Tuesday the debate about energy taxes had already been eclipsed by the growing public outcry against the President's efforts to allow homosexuals in the military.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, it was time to look back on the President's first full week in office. A casual viewer tuning into these sober retrospectives might have been forgiven for wondering if, like Mel Gibson in "Forever Young," he had somehow been frozen and missed the entire Clinton Administration.</p>
        <p>In a feature titled "Reality Check," Eric Engberg of CBS, reviewed the President's first seven days, one blunder at a time. Mr. Engberg's conclusion: Mr. Clinton's "promise to focus on the economy like a laser seemed to come unstuck in the Washington centrifuge."</p>
        <p>The political panel on NBC's "Today" show had a similarly gloomy assessment of Mr. Clinton's tenure.</p>
        <p>"Well, if he's trying to get the Republicans overconfident, he's succeeding," said Al Hunt of The Wall Street Journal. "I think it's been a rough six or seven days."</p>
        <p>To be sure, even at the end of the President's first seven days, there were those who said they did not yet have enough information to reach a conclusion about the new Administration. "This is not, it seems to me, a signature for the next few years," Tom Brokaw of NBC said. "We ought to judge him week by week."</p>
        <p>But it was a sign, perhaps, of just how harshly Mr. Clinton was treated last week by the news media that it was left to Ross Perot, his once and potentially future rival, to offer the most vigorous defense of the new Administration.</p>
        <p>Appearing on the CBS program "This Morning," Mr. Perot was asked by Paula Zahn whether he thought Mr. Clinton was faltering.</p>
        <p>"I think it's too soon to tell," he replied. "You see you're up there all alone. You're like being inside of a barrel with everybody beating on it with sticks and hammers, and I'm sure he is just sort of stunned now with everything hitting him at once."  THE GAY TROOP ISSUE  Correction:  February 7, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about television commentary on President Clinton's first 10 days in office referred incorrectly to "The McLaughlin Group." The program appears on some NBC and some PBS stations, not on CNN.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 7, 1993, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about television commentary on President Clinton's first 10 days in office referred incorrectly to "The McLaughlin Group." The program appears on some NBC and some PBS stations, not on CNN.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
