<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Comptroller Versus Chief, The Sequel</title>
    <meta content="23COMP$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Political Memo" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="879075"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Political Memo"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levy, Clifford J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Alan G (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccall, H Carl (Comptroller)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mayors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DA103DF930A1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1272" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Comptroller Versus Chief, The Sequel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLIFFORD J. LEVY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Levy, Clifford J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clifford J Levy column comments on hostile exchanges between Mayor Rudolph Giuliani of New York and city Comptroller Alan G Hevesi and between Gov George Pataki and state Comptroller H Carl McCall; says that in both cases the executive suspects that his financial overseer wants his job (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani took to the airwaves the other day to alert the public to a threat to his great metropolis. His target was not the usual roster of heartless criminals, impudent bureaucrats or other troublemakers. The Mayor, it seemed, was simply fed up with City Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani asserted that an audit released by Mr. Hevesi on the driving records of city workers had been slanted to embarrass him. ''Reckless and unfair,'' the Mayor intoned on his radio program, calling the Comptroller a scaremonger more interested in publicity than public service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani took to the airwaves the other day to alert the public to a threat to his great metropolis. His target was not the usual roster of heartless criminals, impudent bureaucrats or other troublemakers. The Mayor, it seemed, was simply fed up with City Comptroller Alan G. Hevesi.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani asserted that an audit released by Mr. Hevesi on the driving records of city workers had been slanted to embarrass him. ''Reckless and unfair,'' the Mayor intoned on his radio program, calling the Comptroller a scaremonger more interested in publicity than public service.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi replied with an equally cantankerous retort, dismissing the Mayor's barbs as ''very sad.'' Their comments continued a feud that will probably get nastier as the two men elbow their way toward elections next year.</p>
        <p>It is a rivalry that has become somewhat of a tradition in city government, one that is being echoed in Albany, where Gov. George E. Pataki and State Comptroller H. Carl McCall are also not exactly drinking buddies. At the root of the immediate disputes is this: Mr. Giuliani, a Republican, suspects that Mr. Hevesi, a Democrat, wants his job. Mr. Pataki, a Republican, feels the same about Mr. McCall, a Democrat. Mr. Hevesi and Mr. McCall will not discuss their aspirations, but they are clearly mulling over running.</p>
        <p>The roots of the tradition, however, lie in the structure of both the city and state government. The comptrollers, who are charged with overseeing government finances and rooting out waste, are not the best known of politicians. But they are independently elected, and through their muckraking they can damage the standing of mayors and governors.</p>
        <p>In recent decades, the holders of these offices have occasionally got along, but the current bickering is more typical.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi: ''The Mayor takes the position that if you agree with him, you are a statesman, and if you disagree with him, it's political.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani: ''Comptroller Alan Hevesi has a penchant for putting out reports that tell only half the picture, because if he tells the whole picture, he doesn't get any attention.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall: ''It's more the people around the Governor than the Governor himself. I think that I fall into the category as a perceived threat.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki: ''I hope that we can work together. But at this point, Carl McCall is an ambitious politician looking for an office and unfortunately, that makes it very difficult.''</p>
        <p>(To complicate matters, it should be noted that Mr. Giuliani and Mr. McCall have expressed strong distaste for each other. Mr. McCall, who plays a role in monitoring the city's finances, has all but said he does not want to be Mayor, but Mr. Giuliani still questions his motives.)</p>
        <p>Comptroller positions are two of the few citywide and statewide offices, so their occupants always become the subject of speculation. Mr. McCall recalled that just a few days after he got the job in 1993, the gossip began about his interest in moving into the Governor's mansion.</p>
        <p>City comptrollers have used their positions as springboards more than their state counterparts in recent decades. Abraham D. Beame served as City Comptroller before becoming Mayor, and his successor as Comptroller, Harrison J. Goldin, challenged Mayor Edward I. Koch in the 1989 Democratic primary. Both lost to David N. Dinkins, ending years of discord between the two. Their relations were so antagonistic that Mr. Koch once likened Mr. Goldin's tactics to Nazi propaganda, and Mr. Goldin called Mr. Koch petty and divisive.</p>
        <p>''There is a natural tension that exists,'' Mr. Koch said last week, speaking generally of the two offices.</p>
        <p>''Much of it probably comes from the fact that in many cases, they see one another as future opponents in an election,'' Mr. Koch said. ''The mayor is saying to himself, whoever the mayor is, 'This guy is looking to bring me down in the next election and anything that he says, I have to look at very carefully.' The comptroller sees himself as the only real monitor of what the mayor does.''</p>
        <p>So what ensues is a kind of shadow campaign. Unlike in an actual campaign, when the sparring is mostly over populist issues like crime, jobs and tax cuts, in this case the officials often argue over the arcana that tend to be the purview of comptrollers: botched contracts and bungled oversight,  revenue bonds and civil service pensions.</p>
        <p>The statistics-laden audits produced by the comptrollers turn into vehicles for each side to try to score points. The comptrollers cite their work as evidence of problems with the men in charge, who react by painting those same results as political, biased and meaningless.</p>
        <p>The fights have been particularly bare-knuckled when the comptrollers have used their power to block major initiatives. Mr. Hevesi prevented Mr. Giuliani from raising money by selling the city's water system to a quasi-public agency. Mr. McCall stopped Mr. Pataki from shifting some state jobs from Democratic areas to Republican ones.</p>
        <p>The comptrollers insist that their work is not colored by partisanship, noting that their auditors are nonpolitical, career civil servants (there are 818 employees in the city comptroller's office, 2,100 in the state one).</p>
        <p>But it is also clear that comptrollers are always making choices about what to audit and how to publicize the results -- and such decisions are inevitably influenced by politics.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, the mayors and governors know that they can always tar the comptrollers' work as politically inspired, no matter what the results.</p>
        <p>''It is a very convenient way for your antagonist, a mayor or governor, to try and deflect and discredit the substance of your criticism,'' Mr. Goldin said.</p>
        <p>In recent months, Mayor Giuliani has accused news organizations of taking Comptroller Hevesi's side. When Mr. Giuliani criticized Mr. Hevesi for the audit on driving records, which found that nearly 1,200 city employees did not have valid driver's licenses, the Mayor also faulted The New York Times for publishing an article about it.</p>
        <p>Giuliani aides later contended that reporters too often accept the work of the comptrollers at face value.</p>
        <p>''You tend to give less scrutiny to what goes on in a comptroller's office from a political standpoint, and whether the actions are politically  motivated,'' said Randy M. Mastro, the Deputy Mayor for Operations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hevesi's response? ''The bottom line is that we are trying to govern, while the Mayor is using personal attacks to avoid responding to substantive issues.''</p>
        <p>Some governors, mayors and comptrollers have had relatively smooth relations. Mayor David N. Dinkins and City Comptroller Elizabeth Holtzman, both Democrats, did not clash often. Gov. Mario M. Cuomo, a Democrat, recalls that he usually got along with State Comptroller Edward V. Regan, a Republican.</p>
        <p>More often, things get testy -- at least, until both people are out of office. In fact, since entering private life, Mr. Koch and Mr. Goldin have patched up their friendship.</p>
        <p>''We now have lunch about every three months,'' Mr. Koch said. ''And we enjoy talking about the current administration and the problems between the Comptroller and the Mayor. It is so much more fun to be critics than victims.''</p>
        <p>Political Memo</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
