<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Isn't It Antiromantic?</title>
    <meta content="10MAXL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/10/books/review/10MAXL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1663553"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Hempel, Amy</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Dog of the Marriage, The: Stories (Book)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901E2D7133FF933A25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Isn't It Antiromantic?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">'The Dog of the Marriage': Isn't It Antiromantic?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. T. Max</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DOG OF THE MARRIAGE</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Amy Hempel.</p>
        <p>141 pp. Scribner. $20.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Amy Hempel's stories they tell us not just what life is like but the authentic way to see it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DOG OF THE MARRIAGE</p>
        <p>Stories.</p>
        <p>By Amy Hempel.</p>
        <p>141 pp. Scribner. $20.</p>
        <p>IT'S said that the music you hear when you are first sexually active is the music you keep wanting to hear your whole life. Something similar may explain my affection for the writing of Amy Hempel, whose new book, ''The Dog of the Marriage,'' is only her fourth slender story collection in 20 years. Hempel began publishing in the mid-80's, a period during which, just having graduated from college, I discovered that living people wrote in ways that could touch me. The pleasure of my reading then was exceptional, and the objects of my admiration were short-story writers like Hempel, Frederick Barthelme and Raymond Carver, writers whose postmodern emphasis on brand names and highwayscapes was the literary movement of the moment, their floppy paperbacks at the front of the bookstore. Nicknamed ''dirty realists,'' these writers approached modern reality with an affectless tone that was later much derided. As John Updike wrote in an essay that appeared in these pages in 2001, ''These writers wrote out of a certain late-20th-century mood of burnout, of humorous antiromanticism; how much 'point' will be left when that mood has evaporated?''</p>
        <p>I did not agree with Updike then, and judging from the pleasure Hempel's new collection brought me, I think I never will. Yes, this book is deeply antiromantic. (''I suppose there are many things one should try not to take personally,'' she writes in the title story. ''An absence of convenient parking, inclement weather, a husband who finds that he loves someone else.'') And it is full of a rather easy resignation. (''I bought a bag of shiny red chiles. Wouldn't they be good for whatever there was to be good for?'') All the same, these pinpointed stories achieve something more fleshed-out work often doesn't: they tell us not just what life is like but the authentic way to see it. Dirty realism is remarkably clean; its language is just adequate to what it does and avoids the hackneyed descriptions that stuffed up so much fiction before and since. ''Think of it as fancy camping,'' the protagonist of ''The Uninvited'' says about her lifestyle -- she divides her time between a housesitting gig in the South and a home in the North. ''Fancy camping'' might characterize the effect of Hempel's stories too -- reading them, you are never entirely comfortable and you never stop trying to understand what your eyes are seeing.</p>
        <p>The events narrated in the pages of ''The Dog of the Marriage'' are often unclear, but what underlies them is more evident: pain, the inability to escape it, and the unwillingness to face it. ''The Uninvited'' provides a nice exploration of this motif. It's the story of a 50-year-old woman who takes a job housesitting -- ''if you can call that a job'' -- for a professor who's on sabbatical. She thinks she is pregnant. If so, the father will be one of two men: ''my husband, whom I did not live with, or the man in the auditorium, whom I did not report.'' We learn a bit about her estranged husband and about the rape and the rapist -- after the man tried to rape her and failed, she helped him -- but not much more about the protagonist, beyond that she is a particular fan of the 1944 movie ''The Uninvited,'' in which a brother and sister buy a haunted house in Cornwall. At the end of the story, we find her participating in a parapsychological program. A researcher walks in and holds a chain over the hips of a dog she suspects is pregnant. ''A hundred percent accurate,'' she says to the narrator, sounding like a character in the film ''The Uninvited,'' ''something to do with the magnetic field. . . . Would you like to try it?'' The narrator misinterprets the lab technician, getting down ''on all fours,'' ready to find out what her future holds.</p>
        <p>This story delivers many different pleasures. There is the pleasure of discovering how varied the title might be -- does ''The Uninvited'' refer to the ghosts or the guests in the house in the movie, or to the narrator or her potential fetus or the rapist? There's also the pleasure in the way Hempel lets us hear what's behind the barbed voice of the narrator -- the pain of people who think too much.</p>
        <p>It is that only partly articulated pain that also animates ''Reference #388475848-5,'' which consists of the text of a letter a woman writes to the New York City Parking Violations Bureau to protest a summons. She has been ticketed for obscuring the words ''The Empire State'' on her license plate, and she is ''not a person who can take this ticket in stride with the kind of urbanity urbane people prize in each other.'' In other words, we are going to get a story. The narrator relates how she bought the car expecting to use it outside Manhattan, only to find it playing a comforting role in a series of personal city disasters. ''I think it was worth paying the insurance and having to park the car and get this ticket to have the car there to use that day,'' she rationalizes, apologizing for ''trying to put a human face'' on the tiny tragedy of the ticket.</p>
        <p>And a similar pain informs the title story. On the night that turns out to be the last of their marriage, a woman sits with her husband behind a blind man, admiring his guide dog while watching a ballet. It turns out the wife raises dogs for the blind, and in fact has lost her own dog. (Dogs appear everywhere in Hempel's fiction, gentle, intuitive counterparts to our neurotic selves.) She has called the third-best psychic in the area -- the best works only with celebrities, the second-best is away for the holidays -- who supposedly can find lost animals. ''Where's the one who finds missing husbands?'' she asks with quiet bitterness.</p>
        <p>The narrators of ''The Dog of the Marriage'' use their impressive intelligences to tamp down their emotions, and there is something even more sad about their inability to express their pain for the very sophistication they bring to it. Why, if they are stressed or frantic, do they not just tell us so? And if they spend every living moment being horrified at the mess they have made of their lives, why displace their feelings onto, say, a missing dog? To which my answer would be: reading ''The Dog of the Marriage,'' you understand they have no other choice -- and the rest of us don't either.</p>
        <p>D. T. Max is a contributing editor for The Paris Review. He is at work on ''The Dark Eye,'' a cultural and scientific history of mad cow, fatal familial insomnia and other prion diseases, to be published next spring.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">D. T. Max is a contributing editor for The Paris Review. He is at work on ''The Dark Eye,'' a cultural and scientific history of mad cow, fatal familial insomnia and other prion diseases, to be published next spring.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
