<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No O'Neal, and Plenty of Misery for Bryant</title>
    <meta content="10HOOP$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/10/sports/basketball/10hoops.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1663890"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="INSIDE THE N.B.A."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Robbins, Liz</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bryant, Kobe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Phil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Neal, Shaquille</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Los Angeles Lakers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Lakers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bryant, Kobe</person>
        <person class="online_producer">O'Neal, Shaquille</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Jackson, Phil</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E5DE153EF933A25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No O'Neal, and Plenty of Misery for Bryant</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">No O'Neal, but Plenty of Misery for Bryant</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Liz Robbins</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Robbins, Liz</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Liz Robbins Inside The NBA column discusses Los Angeles Lakers, which were eliminated from playoffs for first time since 1994 and have struggled since center Shaquille O'Neal left for Miami Heat and coach Phil Jackson resigned, leaving guard Kobe Bryant to carry team; photos (M)o</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some would say the Los Angeles Lakers' fate was determined on July 14, 2004, when the franchise let a very large man march to Miami, and allowed another, more mysterious man to stay and defend his pride.</p>
        <p>This Lakers season was always going to be decided by the play of Kobe Bryant. His clashes with Shaquille O'Neal and Phil Jackson, combined with their contract issues, led to the dissolution of a dynasty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Kobe Bryant's clashes with Shaquille O'Neal and Phil Jackson, combined with that twosome's contract issues, led to the dissolution of a dynasty in Los Angeles.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some would say the Los Angeles Lakers' fate was determined on July 14, 2004, when the franchise let a very large man march to Miami, and allowed another, more mysterious man to stay and defend his pride.</p>
        <p>This Lakers season was always going to be decided by the play of Kobe Bryant. His clashes with Shaquille O'Neal and Phil Jackson, combined with their contract issues, led to the dissolution of a dynasty.</p>
        <p>Last Tuesday came the inevitable -- tellingly, with an injured Bryant on the bench. The Lakers were eliminated from playoff contention for only the fourth time in franchise history and for the first time since 1994.</p>
        <p>''It's been an emotional year,'' General Manager Mitch Kupchak said in a telephone interview Friday. ''We all expected to be in the playoffs.''</p>
        <p>Trading one of the best players in the league, albeit one the Lakers knew was not getting any younger, led to an attitude readjustment.</p>
        <p>''Certainly, when you make a trade like that, you are a looking at a different season,'' Kupchak said of the July deal that sent O'Neal to the Heat for Lamar Odom, Caron Butler and Brian Grant. ''We knew we would not have the same degree of success. We didn't expect to have a 55-win season.''</p>
        <p>But Kupchak added that he had not expected the team to wind up with its first losing season in 11 years. The Lakers (34-42) may finish behind the Clippers (also 34-42), and that has not happened since 1993.</p>
        <p>The litany of unforeseen disaster for the Lakers began a little more than two months after the O'Neal trade.</p>
        <p>Vlade Divac injured his back in September and missed virtually the entire season, leaving the Lakers with a crater-sized hole in the middle; the team's new coach, Rudy Tomjanovich, resigned in January; Karl Malone retired; Bryant missed 14 games with a sprained ankle; and the team had an eight-game losing streak last month.</p>
        <p>''It's a disappointment,'' Kupchak said. ''I'm not sure how much better we could have played under the circumstances.'' He also acknowledged that in the end, the circumstances were excuses.</p>
        <p>Even with Bryant healthy, the signs were ominous. Under Tomjanovich's system, Bryant initially found it hard to involve his new teammates. By the time Tomjanovich started to reinstate Jackson's triangle offense, at Bryant's suggestion, the new Lakers could not pick it up on the fly.</p>
        <p>Bryant was averaging 27.5 points, second to only Allen Iverson, heading into the weekend. But Odom never blossomed in his new role (he is still rehabilitating a shoulder injury), Grant was injured early and Butler's talent was lost amid the losing.</p>
        <p>The Lakers' interim coach, Frank Hamblen, had little success and expressed frustration with his players' lack of motivation. The Lakers lost 13 of 14 (their lone victory was against the Knicks) before winning at Seattle, 117-94, on Friday night.</p>
        <p>For the Knicks and the Lakers, the anchors of the N.B.A.'s two largest markets, it will be the first time since 1976 that they failed to make the playoffs in the same season.</p>
        <p>But the N.B.A. goes on. No Bryant? No Stephon Marbury? In their place, there is the Steve Nash-led offense in Phoenix; the post-Michael Jordan revivals in Washington and Chicago; the intrigue over Tim Duncan's ankle; and the Big Obvious: Shaq.</p>
        <p>Without him, the Lakers are a size 22 footnote.</p>
        <p>''We knew Shaq would have a good year,'' Kupchak said. ''He was motivated. He will go down as the best of all time.''</p>
        <p>Although he said that he and Jerry Buss, the team owner, were upset over missing the playoffs, Kupchak said, ''We're comfortable with the decisions we've made to date.''</p>
        <p>In 1994, Kupchak was the Lakers' assistant general manager and saw the team's down cycle for the first time. ''It's 10 or 12 years until it happens again,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''In baseball you can pretty much, via revenue, keep a team at a certain level. In basketball, it's just a cyclical type of deal. We could have made the argument that we could have kept it together for another year, but it was coming to an end in a year or two anyway.</p>
        <p>''Karl was in his 40's, Gary was going to be 37,'' Kupchak said of Malone and Gary Payton, last year's Lakers-for-a-season, adding, ''We had the issues with Shaquille and Kobe's pending free agency.''</p>
        <p>In the draft, the Lakers will have a first-round pick and two second-round picks. Their most important pick might just be their new coach.</p>
        <p>Phil Jackson sat in Buss's luxury suite Thursday, alongside his girlfriend, Jeanie Buss. They watched the Houston Rockets dismiss the Lakers; not even Bryant's half-limping return could change the outcome.</p>
        <p>''From what I understand, that was just a social visit,'' Kupchak said.</p>
        <p>There is no word on whether the Lakers will even extend an offer to Jackson or if Jackson even wants to coach the team.</p>
        <p>Demanding fans expect the team to be busy this time of year.</p>
        <p>As if the injuries and insults are not enough, the Lakers conclude their home schedule with a reminder of what could have been -- three games against Phoenix, Sacramento and Dallas, all bound for the playoffs.</p>
        <p>Drilling Defense</p>
        <p>The Mavericks are 9-2 under Coach Avery Johnson since his promotion as Don Nelson's replacement on March 19.</p>
        <p>Film sessions are longer and more detailed with Johnson, his players say. Just a year removed from having limited playing time as one of the team's point guards, Johnson is an adept communicator with a team chock full of starters, not all of whom start.</p>
        <p>''Avery, he does a good job of managing all of us,'' said Jerry Stackhouse, who comes off the bench with Keith Van Horn. ''Everybody understands, it could either be your night or not. Seven guys on this team that average double figures. That's unheard of.''</p>
        <p>What Johnson has been trying to manage most are not the offensive figures, but the defensive ones.</p>
        <p>''When the Patriots go to the playoffs, they're the same team,'' Johnson said last week in Cleveland, where the Mavericks had their worst performance of his tenure. ''The problem for us was in years we were an offensive team and then in the playoffs, all of a sudden you say, 'Let's play defense.' You can't do that.''</p>
        <p>In the four weeks since being officially named the coach, Johnson has put some D back in Dallas. Entering last night's game against Utah, the Mavericks were holding opponents to 92.3 points a game, compared with 98 points before he took over. More tellingly, the Mavericks have reduced opponents' field-goal percentage to 42.3 percent from 44.1 percent.</p>
        <p>With all the talk about the Suns and the Spurs, Johnson said Dallas should not be overlooked for a long playoff run.</p>
        <p>''There are no invincible teams -- I don't see any Chicago Bulls here, winning 70 games,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Mavericks have as good a chance as anybody, Johnson figures, especially if they continue to adhere to defense. He does not intend to change in his playoff debut.</p>
        <p>''You don't do anything different -- when you go to the playoffs, your coach should not have to go into a phone booth and change his personality,'' Johnson said. ''He should pretty much remain the same. If you do it right, if you lay the groundwork right during the regular season, then you'll be O.K.''</p>
        <p>Summer Plans</p>
        <p>Basketball Without Borders, the N.B.A.-sponsored program geared toward community outreach and developing foreign basketball talent, will feature for the first time camps in four countries, adding China and Argentina to South Africa and Italy.</p>
        <p>Yao Ming will return to China, Manu Ginóbili, a sports icon in Argentina, will appear at a clinic in his home country. Andrei Kirilenko of Russia will go to Treviso, Italy, and Dikembe Mutombo is scheduled to visit South Africa.</p>
        <p>INSIDE THE N.B.A.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
