<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Case for Minimal Bach: One Singer to a Part</title>
    <meta content="26VANT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts and Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1012411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="CLASSICAL MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Van Tassel, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rifkin, Joshua</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parrott, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bach, Johann Sebastian (1685-1750)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EED7163FF935A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="1951" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Case for Minimal Bach: One Singer to a Part</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC VAN TASSEL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Van Tassel, Eric</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Eric Van Tassel article on view long espoused by Joshua Rifkin, and later championed by conductor Andrew Parrott, that Bach performed most of his sacred music with just one singer to a part; Parrott and some of his vocal soloists comment, interview; drawing (L).</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUSICOLOGISTS don't often come to blows. But it happened at the 1981 meeting of the American Musicological Society, when Joshua Rifkin announced that Bach's ''chorus'' was really a quartet. Introducing no newly discovered documents but simply taking a fresh look at familiar ones, Mr. Rifkin argued that Bach performed most of his sacred music with just one singer to a part. On the rare occasions when Bach added extra voices to his ensemble, they would merely have been ''ripienists,'' doubling the solo ''concertists.'' So the B minor Mass would need only 10 singers.</p>
        <p>The furor didn't last long. Senior scholars joked about the ''B minor Madrigal'' and dismissed the idea as Mr. Rifkin's private folly. But over the years, as Mr. Rifkin has developed his case in ever greater detail, many younger British and American scholars have begun to see his point. ''Virtually everything Rifkin says is very convincing,'' the Bach expert John Butt states in Bernard D. Sherman's recent book, ''Inside Early Music.'' Bach's original parts, Mr. Butt adds, ''with a few exceptions, almost certainly suggest he used single voices.'' Yet the debate stayed surprisingly quiet until two years ago, when a thoughtfully feisty essay in the quarterly ''Early Music,'' by the English conductor Andrew Parrott, reopened the war of words.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUSICOLOGISTS don't often come to blows. But it happened at the 1981 meeting of the American Musicological Society, when Joshua Rifkin announced that Bach's ''chorus'' was really a quartet. Introducing no newly discovered documents but simply taking a fresh look at familiar ones, Mr. Rifkin argued that Bach performed most of his sacred music with just one singer to a part. On the rare occasions when Bach added extra voices to his ensemble, they would merely have been ''ripienists,'' doubling the solo ''concertists.'' So the B minor Mass would need only 10 singers.</p>
        <p>The furor didn't last long. Senior scholars joked about the ''B minor Madrigal'' and dismissed the idea as Mr. Rifkin's private folly. But over the years, as Mr. Rifkin has developed his case in ever greater detail, many younger British and American scholars have begun to see his point. ''Virtually everything Rifkin says is very convincing,'' the Bach expert John Butt states in Bernard D. Sherman's recent book, ''Inside Early Music.'' Bach's original parts, Mr. Butt adds, ''with a few exceptions, almost certainly suggest he used single voices.'' Yet the debate stayed surprisingly quiet until two years ago, when a thoughtfully feisty essay in the quarterly ''Early Music,'' by the English conductor Andrew Parrott, reopened the war of words.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Parrott and Mr. Rifkin are as much performers as scholars, and the issue, they insist, is not only musicological but also musical. Mr. Rifkin and his Bach Ensemble have recorded the B minor Mass for Nonesuch and a dozen cantatas for L'Oiseau-Lyre; Mr. Parrott and the Taverner Players and Consort have recorded the Mass, the ''St. John Passion'' and several cantatas for Virgin Classics and EMI. And there has been a scattering of concerts, generally well received, in Europe and America.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, all of the complete recordings of Bach's 200 or so cantatas (three series have begun since 1981, and a fourth was announced just months ago) use choruses of at least a dozen voices. Apparently the one-on-a-part idea still makes performers uncomfortable, and makes record producers downright queasy.</p>
        <p>In Mr. Parrott's newest album, ''Heart's Solace'' (Sony Classical SK 60155; CD), three of Bach's vocal works receive three different approaches to one-on-a-part performance.</p>
        <p>The motet ''Jesu, Meine Freude'' is written for just voices and continuo, in 11 short movements varying from three to five parts. Mr. Parrott uses ripienists selectively in some of the movements, highlighting the work's formal structure and its diversity of musical idioms, ranging from soloistic word-painting to the simplicity of a chorale setting.</p>
        <p>''Komm, Jesu, Komm,'' on the other hand, is for two antiphonal choirs throughout. Following Bach's known practice in a similar motet for double choir, Mr. Parrott supports his vocal concertists with instrumental ripienists; a color contrast -- four string players with the four singers of the first choir, four woodwinds with those of the second -- enhances the dialogue effects between the ensembles.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of the CD, the Cantata No. 198, or ''Trauer-Ode,'' uses Bach's most varied palette of colors and textures, with flutes, oboes d'amore, violas da gamba and lutes as well as the usual strings and continuo. Here Mr. Parrott uses the minimum: 4 voices, with 14 instrumentalists. He believes that the music of this funeral ode ''is so rich and full in sonority that it doesn't seem to need the extra weight or variety that ripienists would give.''</p>
        <p>In recent conversations with Mr. Parrott and some of his vocal soloists, a recurring theme was their bemusement at the continuing opposition to the one-on-a-part idea. ''My experience of performing Bach with single voices has always been so positive and rewarding, and has made such effortless good sense,'' the American soprano Emily Van Evera said, ''that I'm surprised at people's puzzlement.''</p>
        <p>The German bass Christian Hilz, when still a conservatory student, attended a summer course taught by Mr. Rifkin. ''I wanted to meet someone who did Bach in a radical way, the opposite of what was taught in Germany,'' he said. ''Rifkin can be very convincing as a lecturer, and I thought, 'Well, this sounds logical, but it just can't be right.' It was the experience of actually performing in this way myself that really convinced me. Now I'm just disappointed that so many people refuse to deal with it.''</p>
        <p>As the musicological arguments against the one-on-a-part thesis have seemed to grow weaker, its critics have tended to appeal more to ''practical'' arguments.</p>
        <p>How, they ask, could one little boy soprano have held his own against two or three big, bold trumpets? But in 18th-century Germany, boys' voices ordinarily changed three or four years later than they do in developed countries today. Bach's sopranos and altos weren't angelic tots but beefy teen-agers. On the other hand, the finest trumpeters of Bach's day were admired not for their power but for their ability to play softly and sweetly. It was Bach, after all, who scored the Second ''Brandenburg'' Concerto for violin, recorder, oboe and trumpet on equal terms.</p>
        <p>''Most of the singers I've performed with find that everything works just fine in real life, if people know how they should sing and play,'' Mr. Rifkin remarked in a recent E-mail exchange: ''the singers not too loud but with up-front diction; the players not aggressive -- which is not the same thing as not too loud -- and with supple phrasing, especially when doubling singers.''</p>
        <p>As the argument has heated up again, some of Mr. Parrott's and Mr. Rifkin's antagonists have come close to alleging outright deception in the recording studio, as when the Dutch conductor Ton Koopman (one of those compleatists in the cantatas) writes darkly of colleagues who ''cheat'' and ''tamper'' with multiple microphones to achieve ''unnatural'' balances.</p>
        <p>But on this point John Hadden, the producer of Mr. Parrott's new recording, is uncompromising. ''I just use a stereo pair,'' Mr. Hadden said. ''Together with the conductor, I position people so that the balance works as it would in a performance, and I just record what I hear.''</p>
        <p>A related practical objection to one-on-a-part performance is that a single team of concertists would lack the stamina to carry all the arias and the chorus movements on their shoulders. Singers who have tried it reply that what is really taxing is being a soloist while also joining in with a large choir. ''I find that the restraint required to blend chorally, in such acrobatic -- soloistic -- music, tires one more than singing freely and fully in a team of soloists,'' Ms. Van Evera said.</p>
        <p>Lacking objective ammunition, critics of the one-on-a-part idea appeal instead to ''artistic intuition'': the conventional contrast between solo and chorus, they say, is built into Bach's music.</p>
        <p>''Intuition'' all too often turns out to endorse what we are used to. Intuition might say that classical Greek sculpture is the embodiment of pure form, and that adding color would be unbearably vulgar; but archeology replies that Greek statuary was highly colored, and we have to live with it.</p>
        <p>Bach wasn't influenced by the Handel oratorios and 19th-century Requiems that have done so much to shape our intuition. Conversely, we know little of the wealth of music that conditioned Bach's thinking -- music by Schutz and Buxtehude, by Rosenmuller and Kuhnau, by Bach's own uncles and cousins. Much of that music was an extension of chamber music: in a marvelously fluid texture, solo voices, ensemble voices and instruments interweave and trade ideas. Such music wears one-on-a-part performance like a custom-tailored suit.</p>
        <p>A variation on the ''intuition'' theme is the ''Bach's ideal'' argument. Even if Bach used only concertists much of the time, it runs, we should emulate not what he was forced to do but what he would have liked to do. The penny-pinching philistinism of the Leipzig town council in the 1730's shouldn't reduce these great works to Bach Lite.</p>
        <p>In a single surviving document, Bach does seem to be wishing for a chorus of 12 to 16 singers. This memorandum was a move in the chess game of Leipzig politics, and so was far from idealistic. But it is irrelevant for another reason. Bach's church repertory included not only his own cantatas but also chorales and simple motets. Most of his choristers would sing in those works; but in the cantatas, some would be needed to play instruments, while others would lack the skill to master Bach's virtuoso choral writing. ''Perhaps Bach's 'ideal.' '' Mr. Parrott said, ''would be not to have the most singers but to have only the best.''</p>
        <p>In any case, Mr. Parrott and Mr. Rifkin find that the forces Bach actually used offer musical gains. Instead of the solo-chorus contrast we're accustomed to, there is a fresh continuity -- indeed, integrity -- when vocal colors and textures carry over between solo and chorus. An example is the second of the three choruses in the ''Trauer-Ode.'' This fugue, for the whole ensemble of voices and instruments, is set in motion by the tenor alone (supported by viola and gamba), entering on the very note with which a tenor recitative has just ended. With a traditional chorus, not only the color but also the aural perspective changes abruptly, from a soloist up front to the massed voices in the rear. When the same lone singer starts the fugue, the transition is more graceful and more natural.</p>
        <p>Bach's ''choral'' writing is constantly infused with soloistic elements, which come to life in a one-on-a-part realization. A charming example is the opening movement of the ''Trauer-Ode,'' written in the distinctive French Baroque style: the lines go with a swing that cannot be precisely notated, varying subtly with the words and with the shape of each phrase. In places like this, the English tenor Charles Daniels says, singing one-on-a-part is liberating: ''you feel that you have the controls in your hands.''</p>
        <p>In ''Komm, Jesu, Komm,'' Bach sets the phrase ''the bitter path'' with a tortured falling interval on the word ''saure'' (''bitter''), and each of Mr. Parrott's concertists shapes the line with a soloist's expressive freedom. In such passages, Ms. Van Evera said, ''the subtle coloring of words is something a good choir could dutifully imitate, but not with the conviction that single voices can bring.''</p>
        <p>ALL the same, massed voices singing together call out to something rooted deep in our culture, if not in our primate instincts. Early-music specialists are not deaf to its summons.</p>
        <p>''The pleasure of that experience, which is how almost all of us have gotten to know Bach,'' Ms. Van Evera said, ''is part of what people are loath to give up.'' Mr. Daniels, an alumnus of the Choir of King's College, Cambridge, admits to a certain nostalgia for that ''gargantuan grandeur.'' And Mr. Hilz, steeped in the Bach tradition of the great church choirs of Leipzig and Dresden, points out that the very notion of one-on-a-part performance ''can be seen as a threat to the religious and social idea of congregational singing.''</p>
        <p>At a recent ''mainstream'' performance of Bach's ''St. Matthew Passion'' at Avery Fisher Hall, James R. Oestreich, the New York Times reviewer, perhaps feeling that tug at his roots, missed a certain ''monumentality.'' But that quality need not disappear in one-on-a-part performance; it can be transmuted into a subtler, and perhaps more profoundly moving, gravitas.</p>
        <p>''The resistance to one-on-a-part seems to come mostly from those who haven't experienced it fully,'' Ms. Van Evera said. ''I find -- and audiences seem to, too -- that less can indeed be more.''</p>
        <p>CLASSICAL MUSIC Eric Van Tassel is an American writer about classical music living in Cambridgeshire, England. He wrote booklet notes on Bach's music for the Sony recording ''Heart's Solace.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Eric Van Tassel is an American writer about classical music living in Cambridgeshire, England. He wrote booklet notes on Bach's music for the Sony recording ''Heart's Solace.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
