<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Starter Mansion's Interiors With Elan</title>
    <meta content="DESIGN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1012392"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Young Women's League of New Canaan</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Country Club Homes Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Liebenson, Bess</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mansions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E5DB1F3CF935A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Starter Mansion's Interiors With Elan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BESS LIEBENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Liebenson, Bess</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Young Women's League of New Canaan is using new mansion built by Country Club Homes Inc, priced at $1,695,000, as its 1998 designer showcase; drawings; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT could have been a tumbledown shack they rejuvenated. Instead the Young Women's League of New Canaan chose a newly built starter mansion with an asking price of $1,695,000 for a designers' show house in New Canaan. Rosebrook Farm is the name given the 5,200-square-foot center hall Colonial-style house lent to the organization for the event by the designer and builder, Country Club Homes Inc. in New Canaan.</p>
        <p>The president of the Young Women's League, Karen Murray, said that all proceeds from the show house would go to charities in Fairfield County. Over the past five years, she said, the league has given more than 25,000 volunteer hours and $230,000 to various causes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT could have been a tumbledown shack they rejuvenated. Instead the Young Women's League of New Canaan chose a newly built starter mansion with an asking price of $1,695,000 for a designers' show house in New Canaan. Rosebrook Farm is the name given the 5,200-square-foot center hall Colonial-style house lent to the organization for the event by the designer and builder, Country Club Homes Inc. in New Canaan.</p>
        <p>The president of the Young Women's League, Karen Murray, said that all proceeds from the show house would go to charities in Fairfield County. Over the past five years, she said, the league has given more than 25,000 volunteer hours and $230,000 to various causes.</p>
        <p>Karol DeWulf Nickell, editor in chief of Traditional Home magazine, will be the honorary chairwoman of the show house, which will be open to the public May 3 through May 17. In preparation for the fund-raising event, the mansion has been a hub of activity with 16 Connecticut designers going to work at making conventional rooms -- a foyer, mud-laundry-powder room, library, family room, L-shaped kitchen, sunroom, four bedrooms and two outdoor  areas -- less conventional, offering ideas to be taken home.</p>
        <p>''It's about taking risks,'' said Anne Haydon, a chairwoman of the event, adding, ''The majority of walls have been faux-painted with effects from rag-rolling to cross-hatching to trompe l'oeil.''</p>
        <p>A two-story entrance foyer, redefined by Anna d'Onofrio to dramatize soaring height in otherwise tight space, includes a crystal chandelier played against Pompeian red walls and sheer fabric billowing from tall windows.</p>
        <p>Joan Nemirow's powder room has a belle epoque-style tented ceiling and wall of illusionary cabinetry making much of the room's size -- that of an elevator.</p>
        <p>In Diana Sawicki's bath and dressing area, silk taffeta decorates a window framed on both sides by Queen Anne-style steel mirrors and a pair of skirted vanities.</p>
        <p>David Devendorf's kitchen with an air of Provence -- it opens into a sunroom -- uses grainy butterscotch travertine with faience plates imbedded into the backsplash.</p>
        <p>And a bedroom suggestive of a grass hut created by Cathy Jones has  an artist-photographer, perhaps an eccentric aunt, in mind. In the midst of unframed art, memorabilia and collectibles is an old silver tea set, a kind of reminder of the civility of tea at 4.</p>
        <p>Mary Mullaney has designed a bedroom for a woman who plays the harp; the adjoining bath is where she is imagined dressing for opening night performances.</p>
        <p>Dianne Lowenthal's Victorian gothic library with cherry wood and  drapes takes note of contemporary computer use, and Pauline Dora's space is done as a child's bedroom with Maine cottage furniture. Janice Parker, a landscape designer, offers a view of her work with two outdoor spaces.</p>
        <p>Admission to the Young Women's League ''Show House 1998'' (Rosebrook Farm, 30 Twin Pond Lane, New Canaan) is $20. The show house is open Monday through Friday from 10 A.M. to 3 P.M., Saturday and Sunday 11 A.M. to 4 P.M. Show house events with separate admissions include a preview lunch on Friday a lunch on May 6 with Karol DeWulf Nickell of Traditional Home magazine, morning tea on May 15 with Kathleen Mahoney of House Beautiful magazine and the author of ''Gothic'' The number to call for events, reservations and more information is (203) 966-1487.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
