<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A 50th Jubilee For Israel</title>
    <meta content="ISRAEL$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Travel Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1012302"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmemann, Serge</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Sunday Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE6D7113CF935A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="1478" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A 50th Jubilee For Israel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SERGE SCHMEMANN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmemann, Serge</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Israel's plans for gala celebrations of 50th anniversary of independence; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TO read the official guide to Israel's 50th anniversary celebrations this year, one might think hardly a day has passed since last November without some gala event to mark the jubilee, and the hectic pace of revelry will persevere right through a Closing Event at the end of 1998.</p>
        <p>In fact, the closing event has yet to be scheduled, and the large majority of events listed in the glossy book are annual or local affairs, often having little to do with the 50th, that have deftly been heaped onto the anniversary bandwagon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TO read the official guide to Israel's 50th anniversary celebrations this year, one might think hardly a day has passed since last November without some gala event to mark the jubilee, and the hectic pace of revelry will persevere right through a Closing Event at the end of 1998.</p>
        <p>In fact, the closing event has yet to be scheduled, and the large majority of events listed in the glossy book are annual or local affairs, often having little to do with the 50th, that have deftly been heaped onto the anniversary bandwagon.</p>
        <p>To a degree, that's the nature of the beast. Anniversaries are a natural time for civic boosters, museums, annual festivals, veterans' groups, municipal councils, military organizations and the like to reach for some extra attention and attendance.</p>
        <p>In Israel, however, the recently issued program, ''Israel Celebrates Its 50th Anniversary,'' is still a fairly transparent effort to put a cheery and busy facade on a jubilee whose organization has suffered from severe infighting, and whose gloss has been tarnished by a political climate that has caused a serious drop in tourism.</p>
        <p>That is not to say there won't be partying. On Thursday, Israeli Independence Day, the Givat Ram Stadium in Jerusalem will play host tothe central event, a ''Jubilee Bells Show,'' which will include music, dance, ballet, literature and theater by dozens of Israeli performers and artists (but no literal bell-ringing). Ticket prices are about $28, $55 and $83, and are available through the Kastel ticket agency, (972-3) 604-4725 or Bimot, (972-2) 624-0896.</p>
        <p>The gala celebration will be broadcast on both major Israeli television channels and in many countries overseas. TV, in fact, may be the best way to watch. The Givat Ram stadium has only 12,000 seats, and 5,000 are reserved for invited guests from the world over, including Vice President Al Gore, as well as Israel's President Ezer Weizman, Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu and other officials. Israel does have bigger stadiums, but organizers wanted Jerusalem, to drive home the point that this is the Israeli capital, even if most foreign governments have yet to recognize it.</p>
        <p>Other events planned for Thursday include a march by thousands of soldiers through Jerusalem, a naval review with as many as 400 vessels along the coast, culminating north of Tel Aviv, and a combined Army-Navy-Air Force spectacle on the shores of Tel Aviv. Military bases will be open to civilian visitors.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, the eve of Independence Day, both the Israel Philharmonic and the Jerusalem Symphonic Orchestras will offer special concerts in Jerusalem, the former at the International Convention Center (Binyene ha-Uma), the latter at the Jerusalem Theater. Ticket prices for the Israel Philharmonic concert range from about $42 to $140, and are available from major ticket agencies, including Klaim, (972-2) 625-6869, and Bimot, (972-2) 624-0896. The Independence Day Gala at the Jerusalem Theater will also include ethnic music and a dance party with a 1960's band. Tickets are about $33 for the balcony and $42 in the orchestra. They can be purchased through the box office at (972-2) 561-1498.</p>
        <p>According to a Government decision made in March, the holiday will extend to Friday, when most offices and stores will be closed. Among events on that day, the declaration of Israel's independence will be re-enacted at the Great Synagogue in Tel Aviv, followed by a concert of cantors.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Zubin Mehta will conduct the Israel Philharmonic Orchestra, with stars like Itzhak Perlman and Pinchas Zukerman participating, in a free evening concert of Hebrew songs, at the Ganei Yehoshua Park in Tel Aviv. The concert will be televised live.</p>
        <p>Various special exhibitions have been planned. The Israel Museum in Jerusalem will hold eight exhibitions throughout the year to explore Israel's cultural heritage, including one on the menorah, and others on Orientalism in Israeli arts, the home in Israeli society, photography in Israel, and watercolors in Israeli art.</p>
        <p>Among the more colorful jubilee events is a simultaneous chess match May 19 and May 21 between Gary Kasparov, the world chess champion, and the Israeli national chess team, at the Kasparov Chess Academy in Tel Aviv.</p>
        <p>Another, starting on May 10 in London, stars 25 rare antique cars that will leave for Israel to raise money for reservoirs in the southern Negev Desert. With the cars will come the British flag that was taken down in Haifa in 1948 at the end of the British Mandate governing Palestine. The cars are scheduled to arrive in Haifa on May 24, after making the last leg of their journey by sea from Greece. They will then drive through various settlements before being displayed in Jerusalem on May 26 and 27.</p>
        <p>In August, the Israeli Government will mount a jubilee exhibition (with a gala opening on Aug. 3) tracing the development of the state at Tel Aviv's fairgrounds. In the words of the official program: ''The exhibition also focuses on the younger generation so that it will know how to appreciate the magnitude of the achievement called the State of Israel, thus laying down roots and reinforcing them in the world's only Jewish state.'' The festival will continue through Aug. 31.</p>
        <p>Among events in the fall will be a mass public assembly on Oct. 6 at the Western Wall plaza in Jerusalem, intended to renew ''the ancient Jewish tradition of holding mass public gatherings at the temple once every seven years.'' Another event tied to the anniversary will be the Festival of Humor, Laughter and Satire in the Negev city of Beersheva Oct. 6 to 8.</p>
        <p>These festive events have failed to cloak the confusion and controversy that have accompanied the preparations. Three directors of the jubilee organizing committee quit in political, budgetary and personal squabbles with Tourism Minister Moshe Katsav. In February, Mr. Katsav also withdrew as the minister overseeing the events. In the same month the current director, Doron Shmueli, took charge.</p>
        <p>As a result, the opening date for the year was repeatedly pushed back. Originally to take place Nov. 29, the anniversary of the United Nations partition plan for Palestine, it then moved to the first night of Hanukkah, Dec. 23. The formal inauguration finally occurred on Feb. 11, the tree-planting holiday of Tu b'Shevat, and passed without much notice.</p>
        <p>Though the motto of the jubilee is ''Together With Pride, Together in Hope,'' the Labor Party has complained that its dominant role in the early decades of the state is being played down, and that its leaders were not invited to some events.</p>
        <p>The collage on the official program includes various historic events, but conspicuously excludes the handshake between Yitzhak Rabin, the late Prime Minister, and Yasir Arafat, the Palestinian leader, marking the Israeli-Palestinian agreement in 1993.</p>
        <p>The singer chosen to perform the national anthem on Independence Day, Rita, backed out in a huff after a minister questioned her $20,000 fee, and agreed to participate only after Prime Minister Netanyahu appealed to her by phone. She then said she would donate the money to charity.</p>
        <p>The listings of events under the broad umbrella of the 50th anniversary have also drawn criticism for lumping together official jubilee events, annual festivals, and locally organized events, both commercial and public. Many of these, such as the Arad music festival, or the Tiberias-to-Eilat bicycle trek, take place every year, and some tickets are quite expensive.</p>
        <p>Hotel and tour managers said they expect an increase in tourists for Independence Day, but that the jubilee year overall was likely to be another in a series of bad years. Ami Etgar, general manager of the Association of Tour Organizers, said tourism has been dropping since 1995, when 2.5 million tourists came to Israel. Original expectations, he said, had been for well over 3 million tourists in the jubilee year. But the prognosis now is for 1.9 million to 2.1 million tourists in 1998.</p>
        <p>''We expected 1998 to be a good year because it is the jubilee year,'' said Yaakov Katz, marketing manager of the Hotels Association. ''Unfortunately, when we look at the figures for the year, we do not see it turning out that way. We are entering our third year of crisis in the tourism industry. It started with the bombings in Jerusalem in February 1996, and goes on.''</p>
        <p>More details about Jubilee events are available through the Ministry of Tourism in Jerusalem, at (972-2) 675-4846; in the United States at (888) 774-7723, or on the Internet, www.goisrael.com.</p>
        <p>SERGE SCHMEMANN is chief of the Jerusalem bureau of The Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">SERGE SCHMEMANN is chief of the Jerusalem bureau of The Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
