<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Disputes Accusations Of Abuses By the I.R.S.</title>
    <meta content="26IRS.$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1012698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Treasury Department</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Internal Revenue Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David Cay</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Long, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EEDB103FF935A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="557" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Disputes Accusations Of Abuses By the I.R.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David Cay</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Treasury Dept Inspector General report concludes that most of allegations of abuse of taxpayers that Internal Revenue Service agent Jennifer Long made at Senate hearings last Sept are 'unfounded' or cannot be substantiated (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Most of the allegations of abuse of taxpayers that an Internal Revenue Service agent made at Senate hearings last September are ''unfounded'' or cannot be substantiated, the Treasury Department Inspector General said in a report released on Friday night.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Long, an agent in the Houston I.R.S. office, testified under oath that I.R.S. managers pressure subordinates to fabricate evidence ''to extract unfairly assessed taxes from taxpayers, literally ruining families, lives and businesses -- all unnecessarily and sometimes illegally.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Most of the allegations of abuse of taxpayers that an Internal Revenue Service agent made at Senate hearings last September are ''unfounded'' or cannot be substantiated, the Treasury Department Inspector General said in a report released on Friday night.</p>
        <p>Jennifer Long, an agent in the Houston I.R.S. office, testified under oath that I.R.S. managers pressure subordinates to fabricate evidence ''to extract unfairly assessed taxes from taxpayers, literally ruining families, lives and businesses -- all unnecessarily and sometimes illegally.''</p>
        <p>People with little education or understanding of their legal rights, or who have suffered personal difficulties, are preyed upon by the I.R.S., Ms. Long testified, because they are seen as ''vulnerable'' to pressure tactics, while friends of I.R.S. managers are shielded from audits.</p>
        <p>She said that ''as of late, we seem to be auditing only poor people.''</p>
        <p>''The current I.R.S. management does not believe anyone in this country can possibly live on less than $20,000 per year and anyone living below that level must be cheating by understating their true income,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The inspector general's 11-page report dismissed these and other accusations, but did find ''areas of concern'' about Ms. Long's charges that I.R.S. managers are seldom disciplined for conduct for which subordinates are punished, retaliate against subordinates who report misconduct and harass subordinates, sometimes for being overweight, and otherwise create an atmosphere of intimidation and fear among employees.</p>
        <p>Ginny Flynn, a spokeswoman for Senator William V. Roth Jr., the Delaware Republican who held the hearings, said the release of the report just before a new round of hearings begins on Tuesday ''is suspect.'' She characterized the report as a shield constructed by ''forces that want to protect the status quo at the I.R.S.''</p>
        <p>''We believe Jennifer Long and all of the witnesses'' who testified about abuse of taxpayers, she added. Ms. Long could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>Ms. Long's testimony, and that of taxpayers who told of mistreatment by auditors and their bosses, set off a firestorm of criticism of the income tax system, which Congressional Republicans have vowed to scrap in favor of a consumption-based tax.</p>
        <p>The report, which was released by Senator Daniel Patrick Moynihan, Democrat of New York, said that Ms. Long could identify only one case where evidence may have been fabricated and that it was in 1986 or 1987. The report said it had been determined that an unknown taxpayer was asked about changes on his tax return, that the taxpayer was aware of the changes and that there was no evidence of impropriety.</p>
        <p>The report said no evidence was found to support the charge that the I.R.S. preys on the uneducated, troubled and uninformed or that those making less than $20,000 are audited excessively.</p>
        <p>The I.R.S. stepped up audits of the poor in 1995 at the direction of Senator Roth and other Republican leaders who cut the I.R.S. budget over all, but authorized more money to audit people claiming the Earned Income Credit, a form of negative income tax for the working poor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
