<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Love of Music Inspires a Crusade</title>
    <meta content="BARBASH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="MAKING A DIFFERENCE: Another in a series of articles about men and women who have changed life on Long Island." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1012425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">Lillian Barbash; Murray Barbash</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Long Island Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbash, Murray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barbash, Lillian</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delatiner, Barbara</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980426T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400E5DC173FF935A15757C0A96E958260" item-length="2573" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Love of Music Inspires a Crusade</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA DELATINER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Delatiner, Barbara</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article in series (Making A Difference) traces major role of Murray and Lillian Barbash in Long Island's culture and classical music scene, particularly founding and nurturing of Long Island Philharmonic; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Growing up in the same East Bronx neighborhood during and after the Great Depression, Murray and Lillian Barbash always seemed to be surrounded by music.</p>
        <p>There were free Goldman Band concerts in the local parks and 55-cent tickets to Lewisohn Stadium to hear Rise Stevens sing ''Carmen'' or Yehudi Menuhin play his violin. And there was music constantly playing on the radios or phonographs in their working-class homes.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Growing up in the same East Bronx neighborhood during and after the Great Depression, Murray and Lillian Barbash always seemed to be surrounded by music.</p>
        <p>There were free Goldman Band concerts in the local parks and 55-cent tickets to Lewisohn Stadium to hear Rise Stevens sing ''Carmen'' or Yehudi Menuhin play his violin. And there was music constantly playing on the radios or phonographs in their working-class homes.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to hear the Giants games,'' Mr. Barbash, 73, recalled. ''My father wanted the New York Philharmonic. He usually won.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Barbash, 70, remembered that ''one of the newspapers, I think The New York Post, had this giveaway of classical music records for a quarter, or something like that,'' she said. ''And my folks bought one every week.''</p>
        <p>''It was wonderful to grow up with music,'' Mr. Barbash said. ''I can't imagine people not taking advantage of good music. It's strictly a matter of exposure.''</p>
        <p>Not content merely to enjoy music themselves -- and believing that if music is made available, people will come to hear it -- the Barbashes have played a major role in Long Island's cultural life for more than two decades.</p>
        <p>She is the executive director of the Islip Arts Council, an innovative community organization that provides free chamber music concerts year round and presents the New York Philharmonic in a free summer concert at Heckscher State Park. He is a philanthropist who, one colleague said, ''puts his money where his mouth is'' by supporting cultural as well as other civic programs.  Together, they have been forces in the founding and continued survival of the Long Island Philharmonic, which had its annual gala last night.</p>
        <p>''The cultural scene on Long Island would not be the same without them,'' said Judith Sneddon, the former director of Suffolk County's Office of Cultural Affairs.</p>
        <p>Barry Shapiro, a former president of the Long Island Philharmonic's board, agreed. ''Every organization has people who set a tone of what is expected,'' he said, ''and Murray and Lillian, through their commitment, knowledge and caring, are the people I try to emulate. If there was a soul of the orchestra, I'd say Murray and Lillian would be on the short list for the title.''</p>
        <p>Childhood sweethearts who met through Irving Like, Mrs. Barbash's older brother and Mr. Barbash's best friend, the two have shared a passion  for music since their courtship.</p>
        <p>When they were married in 1947, the third item they bought for their apartment in Mount Vernon, after a bed and a table, was a phonograph. So it isn't surprising that when they moved to Long Island in 1954 to be closer to Mr. Barbash's career as a developer and contractor, music would help determine the location.  They chose Brightwaters because, Mrs. Barbash said, ''we heard that the Bay Shore schools had a great music faculty.''</p>
        <p>In the beginning, while Mrs. Barbash was busy raising their three children and Mr. Barbash was preoccupied with establishing Barbash Associates in Babylon, a company that would become known for its environmentally sensitive approach to development, music was strictly a private, family affair.</p>
        <p>The children all took music lessons. Cathy, of Ardmore, Pa., the former manager of the Philadelphia Orchestra, currently heads an agency that books musicians from the West into China. Susan, of Bay Shore, now runs the family business and continues the Barbash passion for community involvement as head of the South Bay Y.M.C.A. Shepard, of Atlanta, is a freelance writer. While they were growing up, the older Barbashes had season tickets to the South Shore Symphony as well as to the Metropolitan Opera and the New York Philharmonic, and, on occasion, would take their youngsters into New York to sample the music.</p>
        <p>''I've always been interested in music, but not talented,'' Mrs. Barbash said, explaining that she studied piano as a child and resumed lessons as an adult. ''Instead, I like to see it all happen. Put it together. I call myself a music groupie.'' Mr. Barbash tried to learn to play the clarinet at age 50 ''and blew my brains out,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The couple's involvement in ''organized'' cultural affairs began in 1955, with a donation they made to the South Shore Symphony. ''We had a dog, an Irish terrier, who had puppies,'' Mrs. Barbash said, ''and I gave one of the puppies to the symphony to be auctioned off at a benefit. So they put me on the board.''</p>
        <p>When that community orchestra was dissolved, Mrs. Barbash became involved with the Suffolk Symphony. Because of her interest in the arts, ''her sense of organization, her honesty and her commitment,'' said Joe Herbison, who served on the board of the Suffolk Symphony with her, Mrs. Barbash was asked to serve on the advisory board of the town of Islip's new arts council in 1976.</p>
        <p>''They gave us $5,000,'' she recalled, ''but for the first year, nothing was done except for putting out a calendar of events.''</p>
        <p>After the group's first chairman left, Mrs. Barbash took the helm and in quick order made the council an independent, nonprofit entity. She spent the $5,000 stipend on three affordable chamber music concerts and a series of free concerts.</p>
        <p>The first year Mrs. Barbash was head of the council, it offered a $10 subscription, presenting the Juilliard String Quartet, the Beaux Arts Trio and Music from Marlboro, selling 350 seats in the 400-seat house.</p>
        <p>''And don't forget the free concerts,'' Mr. Barbash said. ''You called the music schools and booked all these marvelous students who came for $50. But the fee wasn't what mattered to them. It was really the chance to play before an audience.''</p>
        <p>These days, the Islip Arts Council, which no longer receives financial aid from Islip but does get town offices and other services, has an annual budget of $335,000, raised from state and county grants, ticket sales and corporate and private donations. Last year, it ran a surplus.</p>
        <p>The chamber music series now costs just under $30,000 to produce, but subscriptions have been kept down to $75 for five concerts, or $70 for four, and the series continues to play to a full, if graying, house in Sayville. It presents free standing-room-only weekly concerts throughout the winter and summer, performed mostly by professional musicians whose fee has risen to $300. Also on its agenda are various in-school cultural programs and the New York Philharmonic's annual summer visit to Heckscher State Park, which began in 1978.</p>
        <p>''My brother Irving was in his car one day and heard a concert from Tanglewood on the radio,'' Mrs. Barbash recalled. ''He came home and asked me why we couldn't have a Tanglewood, and while I knew we couldn't afford that, I decided to at least try for an outdoor concert by the New York Philharmonic, which was then playing two concerts in Nassau.''</p>
        <p>She contacted the orchestra and was told that there were no openings on its summer calendar, even though Mrs. Barbash had secured $37,500 from a single sponsor.</p>
        <p>''By coincidence, about that time I was at the New York State Council on the Arts, going over some applications,'' she said, ''and mentioned how I had been unsuccessful in getting the Philharmonic, and one of the officials told me Nassau was cutting back to one concert. Now, they don't have any at all.</p>
        <p>''Knowing this, I called the orchestra again and told them to keep us in mind if an opening came about. They did after Nassau canceled, and that first year, with Zubin Mehta conducting, 20,000 people showed up. Zubin couldn't get over it and kept on asking, 'Where are all these people coming from?' ''</p>
        <p>As many as 40,000 Long Islanders have attended one of the concerts, which conclude with fireworks. ''Some people on the board objected to the fireworks at first,'' said Ellen Jones, a longtime member of the council's board. ''They felt that fireworks didn't go with classy music. But Lillian always said that even if people do come for the fireworks, they'll still be exposed to wonderful music, and that's what matters.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Barbash, who is a former science teacher in the New York City schools and who recently became a member of the advisory committee of the Suffolk County Office of Cultural Affairs, has never accepted a salary from the council. At the insistence of the New York State Council on the Arts, however, the budget does contain a line item listing her annual salary at $30,000. She donates it to the council.</p>
        <p>''We don't need the salary,'' Mrs. Barbash said. ''And not taking it gives me more independence from political life in town.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Barbash joined the cultural wars in 1979 when he was invited to lunch with the singer and songwriter Harry Chapin.</p>
        <p>''Harry was one of the greatest salesmen I ever met,'' Mr. Barbash recalled, ''and before lunch was over, he had me convinced that the Suffolk Symphony and the Long Island Symphony, which used to be the Huntington Symphony, should be merged to form one single all-professional orchestra, the Long Island Philharmonic.</p>
        <p>''I agreed to serve on the first board, but told them they needed someone with more experience -- my wife. So Lil was invited to join the board, too.''</p>
        <p>Through contacts at the New York Philharmonic, Mrs. Barbash and the committee charged with finding a musical director for the new orchestra were led to Christopher Keene, then the relatively unknown conductor of the Syracuse Symphony. During his stint with the Long Island Philharmonic, Mr. Keene became the artistic director of the New York City Opera Company, a post he held until his death last year.</p>
        <p>Jack Russell, another founding member of the Long Island Philharmonic who, like the Barbashes, still remains on the board, said: ''Also in the beginning, when we found ourselves in financial trouble because we expected the New York State Council on the Arts to give us what the two orchestras had received, $137,000, but we only got $37,000, it was Lillian who knew about New York State's Natural Heritage Trust Awards. They're members' items, and we were able to convince our representatives in Albany to get us funds that enabled us to survive.''</p>
        <p>In 1990, late payments from the state threatened the orchestra's continuation. Mr. Russell said Mr. Barbash ''issued a challenge, offering a check for $25,000 immediately, if other members of the board would match the sum.''</p>
        <p>With a substantial donation from Roger Tilles, the other board members raised an additional $75,000, and the orchestra, which currently operates in the black on a $1.7 million annual budget, weathered the storm.</p>
        <p>''The orchestra is the best regional orchestra in the country,'' Mr. Barbash said, ''but raising funds for it can be hard. It doesn't get what I call 'the charitable ego buck,' money from people who want to see their names in concrete or brass in return for their money.''</p>
        <p>To the Barbashes, however, generosity without credit is the norm. Mr. Barbash, who is retired, also heads the North American Friends of the Israel Oceanographic and Limnological Research Institute. He was active in the fight against the Shoreham nuclear plant and is currently involved in the Rate Payers Against the Lilco Bailout.</p>
        <p>Just as Mrs. Barbash has never met a person she didn't want to ''turn on to the joys of music,'' Mr. Barbash rarely finds a good cause for which he doesn't want to raise funds.</p>
        <p>For example, in 1995, at a cost of $17,000, the Barbashes took 700 11th-  and 12th-grade students from Bay Shore to New York to see the play ''Having Our Say.'' The experience was so rewarding that Mr. Barbash has founded the Bay Shore School Arts and Endowment Fund to supplement the school district's cultural activities. The seed money consists of $50,000 from the Barbash Family Fund and, he said, ''another deep pocket who wants to be anonymous.''</p>
        <p>Similarly, just last month, when an instructor at the ski resort in New Mexico where the Barbashes vacation was killed in a skiing accident, Mr. Barbash established a fund in the late teacher's name for scholarships to the Taos School of Music. The couple are also financial patrons of the New York Philharmonic, the Metropolitan Opera Company and the New York City Opera.</p>
        <p>It's all part of the philosophy governing what Mr. Barbash calls their  ''modest philanthropy.''</p>
        <p>''We're not talking about a a lot of money,'' he insisted. ''We can't compare with the computer money that's floating around now. We're not in that league at all.''</p>
        <p>''The question is where you want to spend the money you have,'' Mrs. Barbash said.</p>
        <p>''We live in the same house we first bought,'' she added. ''We don't have fancy cars, clothes or jewelry. We spend our money on what we enjoy, things like skiing and music. Sharing the music with others so that they can enjoy it the way we do.''</p>
        <p>In honor of their 40th anniversary, the Barbashes commissioned a cello concerto for Yo-Yo Ma, whom they have known since their daughters were students with Mr. Ma at Harvard University. He recently phoned Brightwaters to sing and play ''Happy Birthday'' during Mrs. Barbash's 70th birthday party.</p>
        <p>''We were in a car one day and heard a work by Stravinsky that the announcer said was commissioned in honor of someone's birthday,'' Mrs. Barbash recalled. ''I said that's what I want for our anniversary.''</p>
        <p>They got in touch with Mr. Ma and told him they wanted to commission a work for him. They chose Leon  Kirchner, a mentor of Mr. Ma's, to compose it.</p>
        <p>Performed by Mr. Ma and the Philadelphia Orchestra, ''Music for Cello and Orchestra'' had its premiere in 1992, just before the Barbashes' 45th anniversary. It has been recorded by Mr. Ma and continues to be performed throughout the world. The piece is included on Mr. Ma's album ''Premieres: Cello Concertos,'' which won two Grammy Awards in March.</p>
        <p>''I was apprehensive at first because it's modern,'' Mrs. Barbash said, ''but I love the piece. It's so accessible. We'll be leaving something permanent behind us.'' The joint gift cost the Barbashes $40,000.</p>
        <p>For their 50th anniversary, celebrated last year, they commissioned  Christopher Rouse, a composer, to create his first piano concerto for Emanuel Ax.</p>
        <p>''Look,'' Mr. Barbash said, ''as my son, Shepard, says, 'Philanthropy is an act of love.' And when people came to me and tell me they want to get involved in something, I advise them not to just throw money at a cause.</p>
        <p>''The most satisfaction you get is in investing time and money in a cause in which you are truly interested. If you're interested, you're going to have a lot of fun. If you're not, you're not going to be satisfied with just contributing.</p>
        <p>''We're not do-gooders. We've just done what was interesting to us and if it contributed to the happiness of people in the area, fine.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
