<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fugitive Bolivian Ex-Ruler Gets 30-Year Term</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19930424T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="603977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SENTENCES (CRIMINAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOLIVIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">NASH, NATHANIEL C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GARCIA MESA, LUIS (GEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PAZ ZAMORA, JAIME (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Bolivia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5DC113BF931A15757C0A965958260" item-length="667" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fugitive Bolivian Ex-Ruler Gets 30-Year Term</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATHANIEL C. NASH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NASH, NATHANIEL C</byline>
      <dateline>SUCRE, Bolivia, April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Supreme Court today sentenced Gen. Luis Garcia Mesa, a former military dictator, to 30 years in prison on charges of murder, looting the country's treasury, corruption and abuse of constitutional power during his bloody 14-month rule in 1980 and 1981.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia Mesa, who was sentenced in absentia, disappeared in 1989 while his trial was going on. The Government of Jaime Paz Zamora has promised to capture Mr. Garcia Mesa before its term expires in August, but few Bolivians expect it to deliver on its promise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Supreme Court today sentenced Gen. Luis Garcia Mesa, a former military dictator, to 30 years in prison on charges of murder, looting the country's treasury, corruption and abuse of constitutional power during his bloody 14-month rule in 1980 and 1981.</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia Mesa, who was sentenced in absentia, disappeared in 1989 while his trial was going on. The Government of Jaime Paz Zamora has promised to capture Mr. Garcia Mesa before its term expires in August, but few Bolivians expect it to deliver on its promise.</p>
        <p>Bolivian lawmakers nonetheless described the Supreme Court's decision as a landmark in the nation's fight to shake off its history of military coups and dictatorships. Coups occured about every two years until the return to democratic rule in 1985.</p>
        <p>"This is a very important day for Bolivia since it represents not only a rejection by the people of military rule but also strong action by the court to put these people and those who cooperate with them in prison," said Ernesto Machicao, president of the committee on human rights in the House of Deputies. "I think people will think twice before they again plan to overthrow the Government by military power."</p>
        <p>Antonio Araniver, leader of the Bolivian Movement for Freedom, a leftist party, said, "At last the country has destroyed the power of impunity."</p>
        <p>Ending a trial that lasted more than 7 years, the high court also sentenced 46 of Mr. Garcia Mesa's aides to prison terms ranging up to 30 years. Mr. Garcia Mesa was convicted on 33 criminal counts that would have drawn a total prison term of 235 years, but under Bolivian law the maximum term is 30 years. The sentence does not allow for a pardon.</p>
        <p>A former colonel, Luis Arce Gomez, who was Mr. Garcia Mesa's Interior Minister and, it is widely believed, carried out most of the regime's assassinations, received a 30-year sentence. In 1989 Mr. Arce Gomez was extradited to the United States and tried in Florida on drug-trafficking charges; he is serving a 30-year prison sentence in the United States.</p>
        <p>After the sentences were read, a cheer went up from the 700 people gathered inside and outside the Supreme Court building. They sang the national anthem and family members of victims of Mr. Garcia Mesa wept and embraced each other.</p>
        <p>As the trial was nearing completion in this picturesque colonial city, Army and police reinforcements were brought in to tighten security. Each of the 13 Supreme Court judges and the prosecuting attorney have received death threats in the last month; many believe the threats came from the "Angels of Death," an execution squad directed by Mr. Arce Gomez.</p>
        <p>Though his term in office was brief, Luis Garcia Mesa's rule was marked by a brutal crackdown on the political opposition and an opening of Bolivia to widespread drug trafficking.  Funds for His Friends</p>
        <p>Mr. Garcia Mesa ordered the killing of eight leaders of the Revolutionary Leftist Movement, the main left-wing opposition party. Documents showed he spent more than $2 million rewarding faithful generals and military officers after his coup.</p>
        <p>Former military aides testified that he enlisted the help of Argentina's military Government and even that of Klaus Barbie, the Nazi doctor of Auschwitz, who was living in Bolivia and who apparently instructed Bolivia's secret police on torture.</p>
        <p>The former general is believed to have organized operations sending raw cocaine to the Medellin cartel in Colombia. But charges of drug trafficking were not part of the case. Politicians are unable to say, but they note that a number of Mr. Garcia Mesa's associates remain active, even in the current Government.</p>
        <p>To a certain extent Mr. Garcia Mesa has become a legendary anti-hero in Bolivia. Articles appear almost monthly saying he has been seen in La Paz, the capital, or that he has a huge estate deep in the jungle. Most officials say he is being protected by loyal members of the armed forces and that he continues drug-trafficking activities.</p>
        <p>Correction:  April 24, 1993, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about the sentencing of a former Bolivian military dictator referred incorrectly to Klaus Barbie, a German who was extradited from Bolivia to France in 1983 to face trial for crimes against humanity. Mr. Barbie served from 1942 to 1944 as the Gestapo chief in Lyons, France, not as a doctor at Auschwitz.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: April 24, 1993, Saturday</p>
        <p>An article on Thursday about the sentencing of a former Bolivian military dictator referred incorrectly to Klaus Barbie, a German who was extradited from Bolivia to France in 1983 to face trial for crimes against humanity. Mr. Barbie served from 1942 to 1944 as the Gestapo chief in Lyons, France, not as a doctor at Auschwitz.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
