<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Book's Dark Tales Of Bush's Arts Agency</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="604054"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CULTURE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ENDOWMENT FOR THE ARTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HONAN, WILLIAM H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FROHNMAYER, JOHN E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SUNUNU, JOHN H</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">LEAVING TOWN ALIVE: CONFESSIONS OF AN ARTS WARRIOR (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DE173EF931A15757C0A965958260" item-length="1059" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Book's Dark Tales Of Bush's Arts Agency</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM H. HONAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HONAN, WILLIAM H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John E. Frohnmayer, the former chairman of the National Endowment for the Arts, charges in a new book that long before President George Bush dismissed him in February 1992, the White House staff worked steadily "to cripple the N.E.A. internally by putting in political operatives."</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohnmayer, 50, denounces John H. Sununu, President Bush's former chief of staff, as the main culprit in sabotaging his agency. He also states that while President Bush was encouraging him in a series of private meetings, Mr. Sununu would "bark out his orders," which were invariably contrary to the President's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John E. Frohnmayer, the former chairman of the National Endowment for the Arts, charges in a new book that long before President George Bush dismissed him in February 1992, the White House staff worked steadily "to cripple the N.E.A. internally by putting in political operatives."</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohnmayer, 50, denounces John H. Sununu, President Bush's former chief of staff, as the main culprit in sabotaging his agency. He also states that while President Bush was encouraging him in a series of private meetings, Mr. Sununu would "bark out his orders," which were invariably contrary to the President's.</p>
        <p>Reached yesterday at his office in Washington, Mr. Sununu blasted back at Mr. Frohnmayer, arguing that among his other failings Mr. Frohnmayer "could never be honest with himself." The Mapplethorpe Incident</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohnmayer's book, "Leaving Town Alive: Confessions of an Arts Warrior," which will be published next week by Houghton Mifflin, describes his stormy two-and-a-half-year tenure as the chairman of the arts endowment, during which this Federal agency became increasingly embroiled in heated disputes, the most famous of which stemmed from the endowment's earlier financing of an exhibition by the photographer Robert Mapplethorpe that included homoerotic pictures.</p>
        <p>Caught up in criticism from both those who said the agency's grants fostered obscenity and blasphemy and those who said he had been cowed by shrill attacks from conservatives and had stifled free expression, Mr. Frohnmayer was the first chairman of the agency to be dismissed.</p>
        <p>In the book, he justifies the Federal agency's sudden and unpredictable swings between permissiveness and restraint under his leadership as an attempt to find a middle ground. The Bush White House never helped him in this quest, he writes, because it was "bleakly barren of both commitment and soul."</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohnmayer, a former trial lawyer from Portland, Ore., who now practices law in Washington, says he vigorously resisted political intrusions from the White House. He discharged his deputy, Alvin S. Felzenberg, who was among the first political appointees, and then refused to hire as a replacement Steve Danzansky, who was nominated by the White House. He finally agreed to accept Anne-Imelda Radice as his deputy chairwoman, who succeeded him to become the acting head of the agency when he was dismissed.</p>
        <p>The White House had initially wanted Ms. Radice to act as chief operating officer, he says, but he insisted on limiting her role and the White House backed down.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, he says, once installed, Ms. Radice and four other political appointees established "a shadow government within the endowment" and created a situation in which "there were in effect two chairpersons with differing agendas.</p>
        <p>Jill Collins, the former director of public affairs for the arts endowment and a political appointee, said in an interview yesterday: "Our only effort was to help him out."</p>
        <p>In early March 1990, President Bush sent Mr. Frohnmayer an "eyes only" note stapled to a representation of Jesus holding a hypodermic needle to his arm, asking whether such provocative artworks should receive Federal support, Mr. Frohnmayer writes. Mr. Frohnmayer says he told the President that his job was not to second-guess the decisions made by panels of knowledgeable artists, and that "American creativity needs some elbow room." President Bush, he writes, later congratulated him for his perceptiveness.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohnmayer writes that the high point of his relationship with President Bush came a few days later, when the President renewed his support for him and called Mr. Frohnmayer "a very sensitive, knowledgeable man of the arts" who could deal with the problem of obscene and blasphemous art much better than censorship.</p>
        <p>Within hours, however, the White House switchboard lighted up with calls from organized conservatives outraged by the image of Jesus with a hypodermic needle that the arts endowment was supporting, Mr. Frohnmayer writes. From then on, things deteriorated for Mr. Frohnmayer.</p>
        <p>Later, Mr. Frohnmayer writes, an unnamed White House staff member told him that it would please the President if he demonstrated that he was "a little right of center" and that he should refuse grants to artists who were "flash points," a proposal Mr. Frohnmayer said he regarded as "illegal, unethical and stupid."</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohnmayer said he told the President that the courts -- and not the arts endowment -- should decide issues of obscenity. He writes that he then complained to President Bush that he was being "undercut by the staff of the White House," mentioning the names of Mr. Sununu and William Kristol, Vice President Quayle's chief of staff.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, Mr. Frohnmayer says in his book, concluded the meeting by declared that he would soon find a way to support him publicly and then remarked, "Hang in there and keep doin' what you're doin'."  'Price of a Free Society'</p>
        <p>After that, Mr. Frohnmayer writes, the President did support him publicly although he could never convince Mr. Bush that "the 'raunchy stuff' was part of the price of a free society."</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohnmayer also writes that President Bush dismissed him after Patrick J. Buchanan, Mr. Bush's conservative challenger, created "near-panic" in the White House when he began to attack Mr. Bush for supporting an arts endowment that financed pornographic and blasphemous art.</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohnmayer concludes that in the Bush Administration "loyalty mattered more than ability."</p>
        <p>"I understand the political process in Washington," he writes, "but I do not embrace it."</p>
        <p>Commenting on the book, Mr. Sununu said yesterday: "John Frohnmayer's problem is that he confused the courtesy of the President with encouragement for what he was doing. He was desparately looking for justification. My conversations with Mr. Frohnmayer were always a reflection of what the President was thinking.</p>
        <p>"He could come in and represent one philosophical position and then do something else. John Frohnmayer could never be honest with himself. He heard whatever he wanted to hear."</p>
        <p>Mr. Frohnmayer concludes by recalling that after he was dismissed he tried to calm his nerves by constructing a rustic bentwood chair, which, when he sat in it, "exploded apart, perhaps an appropriate metaphor for my endowment days."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
