<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Video Releases</title>
    <meta content="16VIDB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1271093"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Beautiful (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">City, the (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bring It on (Movie)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Bless the Child (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E3DC1530F935A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Video Releases</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Brief reviews of films now released on video: Beautiful, The City (La Ciudad), Bring It On and Bless the Child; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Beautiful</p>
        <p>As a child Mona Hibbard dreams of victory in beauty pageants. As a grown-up contestant Mona (Minnie Driver, left) is crowned Miss Illinois and aims for the Miss American Miss contest. Mona plays rough, sabotaging other contestants, but her potential undoing is that she has a young daughter (Hallie Kate Eisenberg), which would disqualify her. Sally Field's first feature film, Stephen Holden wrote in The New York Times, ''teeters from a noisy sitcom (only one step removed from the 'Beverly Hillbillies') to brickbat satire until it collapses in a pool of redemptive mush.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Beautiful</p>
        <p>As a child Mona Hibbard dreams of victory in beauty pageants. As a grown-up contestant Mona (Minnie Driver, left) is crowned Miss Illinois and aims for the Miss American Miss contest. Mona plays rough, sabotaging other contestants, but her potential undoing is that she has a young daughter (Hallie Kate Eisenberg), which would disqualify her. Sally Field's first feature film, Stephen Holden wrote in The New York Times, ''teeters from a noisy sitcom (only one step removed from the 'Beverly Hillbillies') to brickbat satire until it collapses in a pool of redemptive mush.''</p>
        <p>2000. Columbia TriStar. $105.77; DVD, $24.95. 112 minutes. Closed captioned. PG-13. Release date: Feb. 20.</p>
        <p>The City (La Ciudad)</p>
        <p>Made up of four vignettes featuring nonprofessional Latin American actors, David Riker's deeply disquieting film plunges onto the streets of some of New York's poorer neighborhoods, where immigrants live at the mercy of exploitative employers and inflexible institutions. Workers are promised one wage and given one-third of that, if they get anything at all. Their children are denied education. '' 'The City' doesn't go out of its way to pull your heartstrings, but its understatement makes it all the more devastating'' (Holden).</p>
        <p>1999. New Yorker. $94.98. 88 minutes. English and Spanish with English subtitles. No rating.</p>
        <p>Bring It On</p>
        <p>''That's all right, that's O.K./You're going to pump our gas someday,'' the suburban Rancho Grande high school cheerleading squad yells at a rival group from a less affluent school district. Snappy routines and skimpy outfits have led the Toros, as they're called, to five national cheerleading championships. But then their captain (Kirsten Dunst) discovers that the team's previous leaders have been stealing their moves from an inner-city school. That might have made a whole movie instead of a subplot, but ''the fact that a bouncy teenage sports comedy can even gesture toward serious matters of race and economic equality is pretty impressive'' (A. O. Scott).</p>
        <p>2000. Universal. $108.97; DVD, $26.98. 110 minutes. Closed captioned. PG-13. Release date: Jan. 23.</p>
        <p>Bless the Child</p>
        <p>Maggie (Kim Basinger) is a psychiatric nurse with a warmth about her, but when her younger sister, Jenna (Angela Bettis), shows up with a newborn daughter, old family tensions flare. After a row, Jenna departs, leaving Maggie to raise the child, whose autism is diagnosed when she is 6. Maggie, however, suspects Satanic influences at work, especially when a creepy cult leader (Rufus Sewell) seeks custody. An F.B.I. agent (Jimmy Smits) attempts to help, but Maggie must cope by herself in a film that tries for the hushed elegance of ''The Sixth Sense'' but amounts to a ''supernatural soap opera'' (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
        <p>2000. Paramount. $107.37; DVD, $29.99. 107 minutes. Closed captioned. R.</p>
        <p>Straight to Video</p>
        <p>Other new titles of interest, some of which may have had a theater release, appeared on television or been on videocassette in earlier editions.</p>
        <p>MICHAEL JORDAN TO THE MAX. As if we needed further convincing, a big, loud expensive film originally shown in the Imax format is dedicated to the proposition that the former Chicago Bulls guard was the greatest basketball player of all time. A sports documentary ordinarily trades in nostalgia or revelation, but the Jordan public image, obviously crucial to his role as spokesman for many products, discourages much digging or revelation. Instead, his career is telescoped into his last season in a film that, A. O. Scott wrote in The New York Times, ''is more like an infomercial in which the pitchman is also the product.'' 2000. Fox. $14.98; DVD, $19.98. 45 minutes. No rating.</p>
        <p>STOMP OUT LOUD. The percussion team from the New York stage show ''Stomp'' takes to the streets to bang its mop handles, trash-can lids and any other object that makes a rhythmical racket. 2001. HBO. DVD, $19.98. 50 minutes.</p>
        <p>THE MIRACLE WORKER. Best known for her Pepsi commercials, the 8-year-old actress Hallie Kate Eisenberg has that image to overcome in her portrayal of a young Helen Keller in an often stormy relationship with her teacher, Annie Sullivan (Alison Elliott). But like many productions for ABC's ''Wonderful World of Disney,'' this one does its best not to dumb down a classic story. ''If anything,'' Julie Salamon wrote in The New York Times, ''the problem with Nadia Tass's direction may be that it's too respectful toward the film's subject and slightly fearful of it.'' 2000. Disney. $104.16. 96 minutes. Closed captioned.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
