<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paying the Price Pays Off for Franco</title>
    <meta content="16METS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/16/sports/16METS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1271164"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kepner, Tyler</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Franco, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DD1230F935A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1692" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paying the Price Pays Off for Franco</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of New York Mets' player John Franco, who at 40 years old remains one of baseball's best relief pitchers; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was a batting practice fly ball this past August, like thousands he has seen, and John Franco was in the outfield to track it down. As the ball climbed above him, Franco flipped his glove in the air to try to stop its flight. It is a casual move; players do it every day. Franco will never do it again.</p>
        <p>As soon as he let go of his glove, Franco felt discomfort in his left pectoral muscle. He never went on the disabled list, but he missed two weeks and his absence helped touch off a September swoon for the Mets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was a batting practice fly ball this past August, like thousands he has seen, and John Franco was in the outfield to track it down. As the ball climbed above him, Franco flipped his glove in the air to try to stop its flight. It is a casual move; players do it every day. Franco will never do it again.</p>
        <p>As soon as he let go of his glove, Franco felt discomfort in his left pectoral muscle. He never went on the disabled list, but he missed two weeks and his absence helped touch off a September swoon for the Mets.</p>
        <p>''You live and learn,'' Franco said recently. ''As you get older, there are some things you can't do anymore like you used to.''</p>
        <p>Pitching effectively is not one of them. At 40 years old, Franco remains one of baseball's best relievers, and he thrived last year in his first full season as a setup man. Today, he reports with the rest of the Mets' pitchers and catchers to training camp in Port St. Lucie, Fla. It is Franco's 20th spring training, and the three-year contract he signed in November ensures there will be at least two more.</p>
        <p>The Mets' first offer to Franco was for one year, but when other teams made him two-year offers to be their closer, General Manager Steve Phillips gave Franco a contract that lasts through his 43rd birthday. Phillips is comfortable with the commitment.</p>
        <p>''The quality of his postseason performance I think has made a lot of people recognize what a quality pitcher he is,'' Phillips said. ''And I know around baseball, scouts and other G.M.'s I've talked to were amazed and astounded by the quality of John's stuff in the postseason.''</p>
        <p>While the two-week layoff gave Franco a rest before October, his postseason success (he had the Mets' lone victory in the World Series and a 2.25 earned run average in eight games over all) was mostly a testament to his conditioning. Barry Heyden, a fitness coordinator for the Mets, said Franco is the most dedicated athlete he has seen, because he is consistent in his workouts and open to suggestions.</p>
        <p>Franco has trained with Heyden three days a week in each of the last four winters. His workouts became more serious as he approached and passed age 40, with Heyden there to push him in their midmorning sessions at the Shea Stadium weight room every Monday, Wednesday and Friday. In the late afternoons on those days, Franco also works out on his own at a gym in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Franco has trained vigorously since entering St. John's in 1978, when some wondered if he was too small to succeed. The 5-foot-10-inch Franco quickly learned the benefits of weight training, said his St. John's pitching coach, Howie Gershberg, and he made a commitment to fitness that lasted through his tenure with the Cincinnati Reds in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>''You'd see guys coming into spring training out of shape, and you'd wonder what they were thinking,'' said Franco, who is entering his 18th year in the majors. ''Dave Parker told me, 'Enjoy yourself, kid, because this game goes by so fast.' I can remember him just saying that, and the next thing you know, it's 18 years later.''</p>
        <p>The Reds traded Franco to the Mets in 1990, about the time young players started reporting to camp in outstanding shape. For the already fit Franco, that was a challenge to turn it up a notch, which he did. ''I'm in better shape now than I was when I was 30,'' he said.</p>
        <p>With encouragement from his wife, Rose, and his former teammate Orel Hershiser, Franco has gotten hooked on pilates, exercises that originated in the dance community and focus on flexibility in the hips and midsection. Flexibility is the first thing to go when a pitcher ages, Heyden said, and the specialized exercises help Franco cheat professional death.</p>
        <p>Franco still consults Gershberg on his pitching mechanics two days a week in the winter. Franco's fluid delivery has helped him last so long, Gershberg said, and it is essentially the same motion Franco used in college.</p>
        <p>''A delivery is basically a rhythmic thing, and you've got to stay in control, nice and loose and flexible,'' said Gershberg, now a coach in the Anaheim Angels' system. ''Sometimes pitchers like John who are very competitive can let that take over, and the next thing they know they're getting violent in their delivery. John stays within himself.''</p>
        <p>When Franco sprained the middle finger of his left hand in July 1999, he lost the closer's job to Armando Benitez. But Franco worked while he was off. Even though he could only throw from 10 feet, he did it to keep his arm in motion. When he returned that September, he allowed one earned run in 12 games to help the Mets win the wild card.</p>
        <p>Last year, Franco had a 3.40 E.R.A. and pitched in 62 games, his highest total since 1988. Fourteen of the 21 earned runs Franco allowed came in four games -- one in April, another in June and two in September. In his other 58 games, he gave up just 7 earned runs in 54 innings, a 1.17 E.R.A.</p>
        <p>In October, Franco shook off Mike Piazza and caught Barry Bonds looking on a 10th-inning changeup on the inside corner that ended Game 2 of the division series in San Francisco. That save -- the biggest of his career, Franco said -- followed a blown save by Benitez an inning earlier. And it was Benitez who later blew the save in the first game of the Subway Series, after Franco had tossed a scoreless eighth inning to keep the Mets ahead by a run.</p>
        <p>Working out with Franco at Shea last month, the left-hander Bobby Jones verbalized what many Mets fans have wondered since then. ''If he's closing, you never know how that Series turns out,'' Jones said. ''He comes in and bangs out Game 1, and it's a whole different Series. I understand you've got to go with the guy who did it all year, but Johnny was great.''</p>
        <p>Franco wonders the same thing, and he would love to return to closing; his contract will pay him more if he ever does. But he understands the job is not his, and takes a measured view of October.</p>
        <p>''Sometimes it's a whole different mindset pitching the eighth, knowing I have Armando behind me,'' Franco said. ''If I'm coming in for the ninth inning, maybe I wouldn't have been as aggressive. But you never know. That's the way it's been for the last two years. I'm not going to rock the boat. Would I like to have been in that role in that situation? Of course. But that's not for me to do.''</p>
        <p>Leaving the glare of the closer's role, where losses could be pinned squarely on him, has had a positive effect: fans, who had turned against him in recent years when he blew saves, are squarely behind him now, and Franco tries to return the favor. As the only veteran Met who lives in New York all winter, he is the team's most visible presence in the community. Franco's annual bowling event raised more than $300,000 last month for the March of Dimes, and he was moved to tears while talking about it at a news conference.</p>
        <p>''He is New York, and I think people realize that now,'' Gershberg said. ''Someone will ask him to do something, and he'll run and do it. That's his upbringing. His father and mother were good people.''</p>
        <p>Franco's mother, Mary, died of ovarian cancer on Valentine's Day 1986; his father, James, died of a heart attack in October 1987. Franco wears a Department of Sanitation T-shirt when he pitches to honor his father, who worked there, and he thinks of his parents often.</p>
        <p>Losing both parents so quickly made him angry, Franco said; they never saw their grandchildren, never saw him play for his hometown team. But Franco believes they would be proud of him for his work off the field, and at least part of the reason he is so serious about his workouts is because of his father.</p>
        <p>''We don't know if heart disease runs in our family,'' Franco said, ''but we're going to try to do whatever we can to prevent it.''</p>
        <p>Jimmy Franco, 45, nods softly as his younger brother speaks. This winter, Franco began bringing Jimmy to Shea for his workouts, and it was Jimmy who noticed that even if Franco never gets the 59 saves he needs to break Lee Smith's record of 478, he could become baseball's career leader in games pitched -- ''if Jesse ever stops pitching.''</p>
        <p>Jesse Orosco was recently signed to a minor league contract and invited to spring training by the Los Angeles Dodgers. Orosco, who turns 44 in April, is the leader with 1,096 games. Franco is ninth with 940.</p>
        <p>When he reached the majors, Franco said, all he wanted was to make $1 million to take care of his parents. Now he is starting a $10.5 million deal, and when he is done he may have pitched in more games than anyone. He would be pleased with that record, Franco said, but he will know when he's done.</p>
        <p>''As long as I'm competitive enough to get people out and I still feel capable of doing the job, I'll be fine,'' he said. ''But I don't want to be one of those guys who just keep pitching because they want to be out there. I don't want to make a fool of myself, either. I've got a lot of pride.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
