<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Opening the Gates With a Favorite, Priced to Appeal</title>
    <meta content="12butt" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/12/arts/music/12butt.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1701477"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CITY OPERA REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York City Opera</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Midgette, Anne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Puccini, Giacomo (1858-1924)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jovanovich, Brandon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jee Hyn Lim</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Madama Butterfly (Opera)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Opera</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York City Opera</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Wainwright, Rufus</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Nixon, Cynthia</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDD1031F931A2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="550" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Opening the Gates With a Favorite, Priced to Appeal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Opening the Gates With a Favorite, Priced to Appeal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNE MIDGETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Midgette, Anne</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anne Midgette reviews City Opera performance of Puccini's Madama Butterfly, conducted by Ari Pelto and starring Jee Hyn Lim and Brandon Jovanovich; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If you had never been to an opera and decided to check out Opera for All, the two-night, season-opening event at the New York City Opera on Thursday and Friday, it seems you made a pretty good decision. For one thing, every seat in the house cost $25, a signal improvement over the $45-to-$120 price tag for performances during the regular season. For another, the offerings were quite respectable.</p>
        <p>Thursday, they tell me, was a concert including everything from a performance by Rufus Wainwright to an excerpt from Puccini's ''Turandot.'' On Friday the company presented straight opera -- Puccini's ''Madama Butterfly,'' in one of its best productions -- and bedded it in introductions from Paul Kellogg (City Opera's general and artistic director), the actress Cynthia Nixon and a very good documentary film that gave a behind-the-scenes look, from singers, stagehands, the production team, etc., about what it's like to put this thing on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A beautiful production and supporting cast made the performance of Puccini's "Madama Butterfly" on Friday worthwhile.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If you had never been to an opera and decided to check out Opera for All, the two-night, season-opening event at the New York City Opera on Thursday and Friday, it seems you made a pretty good decision. For one thing, every seat in the house cost $25, a signal improvement over the $45-to-$120 price tag for performances during the regular season. For another, the offerings were quite respectable.</p>
        <p>Thursday, they tell me, was a concert including everything from a performance by Rufus Wainwright to an excerpt from Puccini's ''Turandot.'' On Friday the company presented straight opera -- Puccini's ''Madama Butterfly,'' in one of its best productions -- and bedded it in introductions from Paul Kellogg (City Opera's general and artistic director), the actress Cynthia Nixon and a very good documentary film that gave a behind-the-scenes look, from singers, stagehands, the production team, etc., about what it's like to put this thing on.</p>
        <p>For all of you who are new to opera, here's another part of your introduction: the review, which many people see as the part where the critic takes something they liked and tears it apart. For me, as someone who loves opera, the point is actually to encourage everyone to think more critically about what they did and didn't like and challenge the things that didn't work, rather than simply praising it for being lovely and letting people continue to believe that if they don't like classical music, the fault lies with them rather than a possibly indifferent performance.</p>
        <p>But I don't think City Opera's performance Friday night was indifferent. There was a lot to like here, even beyond the music, starting with Mark Lamos's simple, beautiful production. The orchestra, under Ari Pelto, had its moments, though there were quite a few muddy patches, and the supporting cast -- Robert Mack as Goro, Kathryn Friest as Suzuki, Jake Gardner as an urbane Sharpless -- was strong.</p>
        <p>The weakness lay with the two leads, who were visually attractive but lacked the vocal goods to do more than simply act as place-holders, going through the motions of the Butterfly tradition. Brandon Jovanovich produced loud tenor sounds as a callow Pinkerton; as Cio-Cio San, Jee Hyun Lim had shrill top notes that gradually deteriorated to mere screaming. If this seems mean-spirited, let me explain: did you find your mind wandering during the singing? Trust me: it isn't you, and it isn't that opera is boring. There are singers who can keep your mind from wandering.</p>
        <p>This doesn't mean, though, that you were wrong if you liked it. What it means is that if you liked it, there are more nice things in store for you. Try a CD of highlights from the opera with the soprano Renata Tebaldi as Butterfly. Try another production of this opera. Or try another opera. Many of us believe there's a lot to love in this field. It's to City Opera's credit that it tried to do something concrete, even for a couple of nights, to spread the word a little wider.</p>
        <p>CITY OPERA REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
