<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuba Arrests Salvadoran in Hotel Blasts</title>
    <meta content="T12CUBA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="956900"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cuban-American National Foundation</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cruz Leon, Raul Ernesto</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rohter, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970912T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06EFDB1039F931A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="834" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuba Arrests Salvadoran in Hotel Blasts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY ROHTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rohter, Larry</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Sept. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cuba arrests Salvadoran, Raul Ernesto Cruz Leon, as 'mercenary' who allegedly has confessed to series of recent bombings of hotels and restaurants in Havana; charges 'terrorist plot' was orchestrated by Cuban-American National Foundation; Cruz Leon photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Cuban authorities have arrested a Salvadoran they describe as ''a mercenary agent recruited abroad,'' saying he has confessed to a series of recent bombings of hotels and restaurants in Havana that they called part of a vast ''terrorist plan'' orchestrated by the largest Cuban exile group here.</p>
        <p>In an official communique Wednesday night, the Ministry of the Interior said it was holding the suspect, Raul Ernesto Cruz Leon, a former soldier in the Salvadoran Army. The statement asserted that Mr. Cruz was part of ''an operation meticulously organized from Miami'' by ''a subversive structure subordinated to the Cuban-American National Foundation.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Cuban authorities have arrested a Salvadoran they describe as ''a mercenary agent recruited abroad,'' saying he has confessed to a series of recent bombings of hotels and restaurants in Havana that they called part of a vast ''terrorist plan'' orchestrated by the largest Cuban exile group here.</p>
        <p>In an official communique Wednesday night, the Ministry of the Interior said it was holding the suspect, Raul Ernesto Cruz Leon, a former soldier in the Salvadoran Army. The statement asserted that Mr. Cruz was part of ''an operation meticulously organized from Miami'' by ''a subversive structure subordinated to the Cuban-American National Foundation.''</p>
        <p>Since it was created in 1981, the Cuban-American National Foundation and its founder, Jorge Mas Canosa, have called for the overthrow of President Fidel Castro and the Communist dictatorship he leads. But the organization has not advocated the use of violence to achieve that goal, and today it denied any involvement in the series of attacks aimed at tourist installations.</p>
        <p>''These latest accusations by the Castro regime against the Cuban-American National Foundation and our community are an abject absurdity,'' the group said in a statement issued here, ''and are to be expected from an outlaw and rogue Government that over the years has routinely attempted to export blame for its domestic failures.''</p>
        <p>Over the last six months, a dozen bomb explosions have been reported at hotels, restaurants and discotheques in Havana and the beach resort of Varadero. The Cuban communique did not indicate whether the Salvadoran suspect was also believed to be involved in the initial attacks, which took place in Havana in April.</p>
        <p>In the statement, Mr. Cruz Leon was described as a former Salvadoran Army paratrooper and sharpshooter. According to the communique, he told his Cuban interrogators that he had attended United States Army training courses ''at a military school in the state of Georgia,'' and had also received training in the use of explosives from American military instructors.</p>
        <p>In previous declarations about the wave of bombings, which diplomats and other analysts have said are aimed at dampening the boom in foreign tourism that has provided much-needed foreign exchange to Cuba, the Havana Government has accused the United States of encouraging and tolerating the attacks. The State Department has denied those accusations.</p>
        <p>The Cuban Government statement, broadcast on national television, was not accompanied by any concrete evidence that exile groups or the United States Government were involved in the bombings. The Interior Ministry merely asserted  that it does have such evidence, but that ''for operative reasons, it is not considered convenient to reveal'' any further evidence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cruz Leon was said to have entered Cuba most recently with a tourist visa on Aug. 31, aboard a flight from Guatemala. The statement said he was arrested shortly after bombs exploded on Sept. 4 at three popular Havana hotels and a tourist restaurant made famous by Ernest Hemingway, La Bodeguita del Medio.</p>
        <p>One person, a 32-year-old Italian businessman who lived in Canada, was killed in the first of that day's hotel blasts. Cuban authorities said an examination of the backpack the Salvadoran carried revealed traces of a plastic explosive, a drawing of an explosive device, ''tools and electric material'' and a tourist map, but they did not say if he had been charged with murder in the death of the businessman.</p>
        <p>The Interior Ministry also said that traces of explosives had been detected on Mr. Cruz Leon's hands, and that his backpack contained clothing worn by a person placed by witnesses at the sites of all four explosions. The Cuban statement said the suspect had admitted responsibility for two bomb attacks at the Nacional and Capri hotels in Havana in mid-July in which four people were hurt, indicating he had been in Cuba at least once previously.</p>
        <p>The bombings have flustered Cuba's large, watchful security apparatus, which has come under official pressure to halt the attacks and twice has mistakenly detained European tourists in connection with the explosions. A Portuguese visitor was held late last month after nitroglycerine was found in pills he took for a heart ailment, and a German tourist was expelled earlier this summer after detonating firecrackers in a Havana tunnel.</p>
        <p>The official statement portrayed the detainee as part of what was described as a ''network of mercenaries operating out of El Salvador, dedicated to terrorism and international drug trafficking, closely linked to counterrevolutionaries in Miami.'' Mr. Cruz Leon was said to have acted  for personal gain and to have received $4,500 for each bomb placed.</p>
        <p>''It is hard to believe that the American intelligence services could not have been capable of aborting these plans,'' the Government news agency Prensa Latina said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
