<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Dangerous CaperImitating The Beatles</title>
    <meta content="03rodn" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/03/movies/03rodn.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1706913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Catsoulis, Jeannette</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farley, Lindley</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rodnees, The: We Mod Like Dat! (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <object.title class="online_producer">The Rodnees (Movie)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE7D91030F930A35753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="530" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Dangerous CaperImitating The Beatles</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Dangerous Caper Imitating the Beatles</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JEANNETTE CATSOULIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Catsoulis, Jeannette</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Jeannette Catsoulis reviews movie the Rodnees: We Mod Like Dat!, written and directed by Lindley Farley; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Striving to be a mockumentary and succeeding only in establishing an idea for one, ''The Rodnees: We Mod Like Dat!'' is messy, unfunny and unforgivably dull. The plot, such as it is, involves four young African-American men from Brooklyn whose failure to succeed in hip-hop prompts a change of direction. Discovering the Beatles, they decide to reinvent themselves as a modern-day British Invasion-style band, complete with horrendous wigs and psychedelic shirts. Our guide to their career is a roly-poly narrator named Wm. D. Kappelmeyer (Moogy Klingman), a squawking former stockbroker who has abandoned family and career to promote his heroes.</p>
        <p>Working from the historically accurate premise that the Fab Four's music was heavily influenced by the likes of Chuck Berry and Little Richard, the Rodnees (Charles Harding, Alexandre Baptiste, Mike Hunter and Davin McLeod) view their conversion as artistically appropriate. (''What the Beatles took, we'll take back'' is their motto.) They even have their own Brian Epstein in the form of an ex-Marine called Roy (Sweet) Bailey (C.F. Jarmon), an irascible dry cleaner whose customers unwittingly provide the band with most of their outfits. But as we watch them parody ''Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band'' and ''Abbey Road,'' compose a ballad about a postal worker and perform at grade schools, the limp music and excruciating acting finally take their toll.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This mockumentary, in which young African-American men reinvent themselves as a modern-day British Invasion-style band, is messy, unfunny and unforgivably dull.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Striving to be a mockumentary and succeeding only in establishing an idea for one, ''The Rodnees: We Mod Like Dat!'' is messy, unfunny and unforgivably dull. The plot, such as it is, involves four young African-American men from Brooklyn whose failure to succeed in hip-hop prompts a change of direction. Discovering the Beatles, they decide to reinvent themselves as a modern-day British Invasion-style band, complete with horrendous wigs and psychedelic shirts. Our guide to their career is a roly-poly narrator named Wm. D. Kappelmeyer (Moogy Klingman), a squawking former stockbroker who has abandoned family and career to promote his heroes.</p>
        <p>Working from the historically accurate premise that the Fab Four's music was heavily influenced by the likes of Chuck Berry and Little Richard, the Rodnees (Charles Harding, Alexandre Baptiste, Mike Hunter and Davin McLeod) view their conversion as artistically appropriate. (''What the Beatles took, we'll take back'' is their motto.) They even have their own Brian Epstein in the form of an ex-Marine called Roy (Sweet) Bailey (C.F. Jarmon), an irascible dry cleaner whose customers unwittingly provide the band with most of their outfits. But as we watch them parody ''Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band'' and ''Abbey Road,'' compose a ballad about a postal worker and perform at grade schools, the limp music and excruciating acting finally take their toll.</p>
        <p>By the time the lads are on the downslide -- facing controversy over their Eurocentric style -- this 77-minute film feels at least 67 minutes too long.</p>
        <p>Sloppily directed by Lindley Farley (''The Bulls' Night Out''), ''The Rodnees'' relies on endless interviews and lengthy performance scenes, during which the guys mug and pose in what is meant to be a Beatles-esque manner. The rare sparks of surreal wit -- a Rodnee grooving to Herman's Hermits in an inner-city bus shelter, a strategy session overlooked by a huge pinup of Jim Morrison -- never come close to relieving the film's listlessness and lack of organization.</p>
        <p>Mr. Farley may want to look at Eric Idle's 1978 classic, ''The Rutles: All You Need Is Cash,'' one of the first mockumentaries and a brilliant parody of the Beatles' career bolstered by Neil Innes's inspired original songs. The film's subtitle may have particular resonance for Mr. Farley, whose film was made for exactly $13,028.75. The Beatles never said that money can't buy you a decent screenplay.</p>
        <p>The Rodnees  We Mod Like Dat!</p>
        <p>Opens today in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Lindley Farley; directors of photography, Michael Dennis, Mr. Farley, Andre Middleton and Derrick Hill; edited by Kate Cunningham, Joshua Geisler and Elizabeth Bouiss; music by Mr. Farley; produced by Stuart Rifkin; released by LSM Productions. At the Anthology Film Archives, 32 Second Avenue at Second Street, East Village. Running time: 73 minutes. This film is not rated.</p>
        <p>WITH: Moogy Klingman (Wm. D. Kappelmeyer), Charles Harding (Rodney Barnett), Alexandre Baptiste (John Rodney), Mike Hunter (Rodney York), Davin McLeod (Rodney ''Modney'' Wolcott), C.F. Jarmon (Roy ''Sweet'' Bailey).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
