<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Exiling Sex Offenders From Town; Questions About Legality and Effectiveness</title>
    <meta content="03offenders" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/03/nyregion/03offenders.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1706956"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Florida</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex Crimes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Florida</location>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E3D81030F930A35753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1797" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Exiling Sex Offenders From Town; Questions About Legality and Effectiveness</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Exiling Sex Offenders From Town</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT F. WORTH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In Hillsborough County, Fla., local officials voted unanimously in June to ban convicted sex offenders from public hurricane shelters. In Ohio, prosecutors have begun moving to evict sex offenders who live too close to a school. And in towns and counties across the country, including Binghamton, N.Y., and Brick, N.J., local officials have passed laws in recent months that effectively banish anyone convicted of a sex crime against a minor.</p>
        <p>The new crackdown comes after several horrific and well-publicized cases, including two involving young girls, Jessica Lunsford, 9, and Sarah Lunde, 13, who were abducted and murdered this year in Florida by registered sex offenders. Although state lawmakers across the country have introduced similar proposals aimed at sex offenders, some local elected officials say they have received so many anxious calls from constituents that they cannot afford to wait.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In towns and counties across the country, local officials have passed laws that effectively banish anyone convicted of a sex crime against a minor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In Hillsborough County, Fla., local officials voted unanimously in June to ban convicted sex offenders from public hurricane shelters. In Ohio, prosecutors have begun moving to evict sex offenders who live too close to a school. And in towns and counties across the country, including Binghamton, N.Y., and Brick, N.J., local officials have passed laws in recent months that effectively banish anyone convicted of a sex crime against a minor.</p>
        <p>The new crackdown comes after several horrific and well-publicized cases, including two involving young girls, Jessica Lunsford, 9, and Sarah Lunde, 13, who were abducted and murdered this year in Florida by registered sex offenders. Although state lawmakers across the country have introduced similar proposals aimed at sex offenders, some local elected officials say they have received so many anxious calls from constituents that they cannot afford to wait.</p>
        <p>''These measures are a cry for help,'' said Richard A. Bucci, the mayor of Binghamton, where a law barring sex offenders, passed in May, has been suspended until a court challenge is resolved. ''There is a broad concern that the system in place is not working, and that these individuals are prone to repeat their crimes.''</p>
        <p>The new laws typically bar offenders from living, working, or in some cases even being within 2,500 feet of a school, day care center, park, or school bus stop. In some cases, that means offenders cannot live or work within the town at all. Mr. Bucci and other local officials who have drafted the laws say the intention is simple: to keep sex offenders as far away from children as possible.</p>
        <p>But many forensic psychiatrists, victim advocates and law enforcement officials say the effort to zone out sex offenders is unlikely to make towns and cities safer, and could even be harmful. They say other solutions, including longer sentences, are more effective, though they may be more costly.</p>
        <p>The restrictions could create a false sense of security, since many convicted sex offenders did not live or work near their victims, said Ernie Allen, the president of the National Center for Missing and Exploited Children. The laws could also end up bouncing sex offenders from one community to the next, setting off a competitive spiral of ever-tougher ''not in my backyard'' ordinances.</p>
        <p>Worse, some experts say, the laws could drive some sex offenders out of sight and away from the sources of stability in their lives, perhaps putting them at greater risk of committing more crimes.</p>
        <p>''When you push offenders out of the more populated areas, they can lose access to jobs and treatment, and it makes them harder to track,'' said Jill S. Levenson, a researcher on sexual violence at Lynn University in Boca Raton, Fla., who published a study of sex offender zoning laws this year.</p>
        <p>The new zoning initiatives come as many states are making efforts to strengthen federal mandates like Megan's Law, the landmark 1996 measure named for a child victim in New Jersey that orders law enforcement officials to notify communities about sex offenders in their midst. There are now more than 500,000 registered sex offenders. The public debate has grown more heated since the child murders in Florida. In May, the revelation that some sex offenders were receiving taxpayer-financed Viagra through Medicaid prompted a national uproar, and Congress quickly passed a provision barring offenders from receiving the drugs.</p>
        <p>One common concern has been flaws in public registries and notification policies. In New York, where some offenders are scheduled by law to drop off the registry starting next year, Gov. George E. Pataki has proposed to keep them on for life. Pending federal legislation would create a national registry to fill in the gaps in state lists and help track offenders who move across the country.</p>
        <p>But some proposals go much further. In Alabama, the State Assembly voted unanimously in July to require surgical castration for some offenders. (The State Senate did not support the measure.) In Florida, Gov. Jeb Bush signed a new law in May that will increase penalties for those who molest children younger than 12, and force them to wear satellite-based G.P.S. tracking devices for life after they leave prison.</p>
        <p>Other states, including New York and New Jersey, are weighing stricter supervision of offenders, through G.P.S. tracking, more frequent visits from parole officers, and limits on where offenders can work and live, like the so-called distance-marker laws being passed by towns and counties.</p>
        <p>''These predators seem to orbit around these areas -- wherever there are children they want to get close,'' said State Senator Leonard T. Connors Jr. of New Jersey, a Republican from Forked River who is the primary sponsor of a bill that would forbid convicted sex offenders from living within 500 feet of any New Jersey school, day care center or playground. ''They can't help themselves. So it's our duty to protect the children and see that the sex offenders are separated.''</p>
        <p>Many of the new laws appear to be driven by the perception that sex offenders in general are bound to repeat their crimes, and only the most drastic measures can stop them.</p>
        <p>In fact, a number of studies have found that pedophiles -- the group of sex offenders that has provoked the most public fear -- have recidivism rates of more than 50 percent, and do not tend to respond to treatment. But many other criminal groups have higher recidivism rates than these ''high-risk'' sex offenders, said Dr. Karl Hanson, a Canadian researcher and leading authority in the field.</p>
        <p>And outside of the high-risk cases, sex offenders are unlikely to repeat their crimes, studies suggest. Sex offenders over all are less likely to be rearrested than drunk drivers, drug offenders, and domestic violence offenders, Dr. Hanson said. Violent repeat offenders like those who committed the child murders in Florida earlier this year are extremely rare.</p>
        <p>The first distance-marker laws appeared almost a decade ago, and 14 states have now passed versions of them. Some states, though, have expressed doubts about the laws' effectiveness. Minnesota and Colorado considered passing versions of the law, and decided against it after commissioning studies. Minnesota's study, published by the State Department of Corrections in 2003, showed no relationship between offenders' proximity to schools and their risk of committing new crimes. It concluded that new restrictions would make it harder to track offenders and would ''not enhance community safety.''</p>
        <p>The laws have been challenged in court on the grounds that they violate the Constitution by subjecting sex offenders to an additional punishment after their release from prison. But state and federal appeals courts in Iowa rejected that argument earlier this year, ruling that the laws were administrative measures justified by the state's interest in preserving public safety.</p>
        <p>The local distance-marker laws, which began to proliferate earlier this year after the child murders in Florida, may not fare as well in court. Unlike their state counterparts, they often bar sex offenders from working or even being in the restricted areas -- a modern-day sentence of exile. They are therefore vulnerable to the argument that they violate the Eighth Amendment's ban on cruel and unusual punishment, said Robert A. Perry, the legislative director of the New York Civil Liberties Union, which has filed a supporting brief for the plaintiff in a suit filed against the new law in Binghamton. The local laws could also be challenged on the grounds that they conflict with the state's authority to legislate such matters.</p>
        <p>''Distance-marker laws are a Band-Aid,'' saidLaura A. Ahearn, the director of Parents for Megan's Law, a national organization based in New York. A better answer, she said, is longer prison sentences and some form of supervision for life. Those approaches, she added, are expensive, and have been less popular with legislators for that reason.</p>
        <p>Another option now under consideration in New York and other states is civil commitment, in which the most dangerous offenders can be transferred indefinitely to secure psychiatric institutions after their prison terms. Housing offenders this way is far more expensive than prison, and has generated criticism on constitutional grounds.</p>
        <p>Distance-marker laws are cheaper. But they can blur the difference between dangerous sexual predators -- who are not likely to be deterred by them -- and moderate or low-risk offenders, who are more amenable to treatment and far less likely to commit more crimes, said Dr. Richard Hamill, a forensic psychologist who runs a treatment center in Albany.</p>
        <p>Refining those distinctions would better serve the public, Dr. Hamill said. New York State now classifies offenders using an outdated system that often mistakenly identifies a high-risk offender as lower-risk, and vice-versa. That inaccuracy, Dr. Hamill said, can result in dangerous offenders' being released into communities without sufficient warnings, and relatively harmless ones' being treated as pariahs.</p>
        <p>Even some of the elected officials who have passed distance-marker laws acknowledge that they may not be the best defense against sex offenders, and are vulnerable to legal challenges.</p>
        <p>''I think all the towns will get involved, and it'll be one-upmanship, and then the courts will probably get involved,'' said Joseph C. Scarpelli, the mayor of Brick, N.J., which passed a law last month that bars sex offenders from living or working within 2,500 feet of a school, park, playground, day care center, or school bus stop.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Scarpelli defended the intent of the law, which drew applause from dozens of residents who had come to the Town Council's meeting to witness the vote.</p>
        <p>''I think it sends a loud and clear message: we don't want anybody moving to town that is of that persuasion,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
