<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; If It's Testaverde to the Rescue, Then All Hope Has Been Lost</title>
    <meta content="03rhoden" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1706992"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/William C Rhoden</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051003T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7D71030F930A35753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; If It's Testaverde to the Rescue, Then All Hope Has Been Lost</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William C. Rhoden</byline>
      <dateline>BALTIMORE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEFORE Jets fans pick up their phones or hit the buttons to send e-mail messages, know this: Vinny Testaverde would not have been the answer yesterday against the Ravens. He will not be the difference next Sunday against Tampa Bay. Testaverde is not the answer, period. At best, he's a stop gap.</p>
        <p>But the hue and cry has already begun for the 41-year-old Testaverde to replace 25-year-old Brooks Bollinger as the starting quarterback.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEFORE Jets fans pick up their phones or hit the buttons to send e-mail messages, know this: Vinny Testaverde would not have been the answer yesterday against the Ravens. He will not be the difference next Sunday against Tampa Bay. Testaverde is not the answer, period. At best, he's a stop gap.</p>
        <p>But the hue and cry has already begun for the 41-year-old Testaverde to replace 25-year-old Brooks Bollinger as the starting quarterback.</p>
        <p>In the wake of his team's unspectacular loss to the Baltimore Ravens, Jets Coach Herman Edwards was peppered with ''who's the answer'' questions about the Jets' battered quarterback position.</p>
        <p>Chad Pennington is out, Jay Fiedler is out and Testaverde is waiting on the sideline.</p>
        <p>Bollinger made his first N.F.L. start, and no one in his right mind could have expected anything better.</p>
        <p>Facing one of the most physical defenses in football and facing down Ray Lewis, one of the greatest middle linebackers in N.F.L. history, Bollinger did O.K.: 28 passes thrown, 14 completed and, most important, none intercepted.</p>
        <p>In fact, he did everything but throw passes into the upper deck to avoid sacks and interceptions. Edwards said he never gave a thought to putting Testaverde in the game.</p>
        <p>''Not at all,'' he said. ''Nope.''</p>
        <p>Jets receivers dropped passes they should have caught, and the offensive line failed to keep the Ravens' rush in check.</p>
        <p>Bollinger's one major blunder came in the third quarter on a second-and-1 on the Ravens' 1-yard line. He took a sack instead of throwing the ball in the stands. Other than that, the kid was all right and earned the right to start again next week.</p>
        <p>''Brooks is the quarterback, he can't play every position,'' Edwards said. ''He didn't turn the ball over -- he didn't hit every pass -- but he made some plays. We stalled.''</p>
        <p>Edwards stalled, too. Asked if he was inclined to stay with Bollinger, he said: ''We're going to sit down Monday and figure out what we have to do better offensively. Whatever we have to do now, we've go to do to try to score some points and move the ball.''</p>
        <p>Sure, Bollinger wasn't that impressive, but how could anyone short of a young Joe Montana look impressive under these circumstances? The hungry Ravens were 0-2 and fresh from a week off.</p>
        <p>Yank him now and put in Vinny?</p>
        <p>Then what? Testaverde could have been worse in the face of a seemingly constant Ravens rush.</p>
        <p>Next week, Tampa Bay's defense will not be as physical as Baltimore's, but it may be quicker. Testaverde would be a treat for Tampa Bay because of his lack of mobility; Bollinger is a liability because of a lack of experience. You can cure a lack of experience; a lack of mobility is permanent.</p>
        <p>Still, Edwards would not be pressed into even a hint of a decision on Sunday's starter. ''I don't want to answer that because I haven't met with the coaches and we haven't really sat down,'' he said. ''By Wednesday, I'll tell you exactly what we're going to do. We've got to figure something out.''</p>
        <p>But what did he expect yesterday? What did Jets fans expect?</p>
        <p>Dan Marino? Joe Namath dazzling the defense in his first start as a pro?</p>
        <p>The Jets' season isn't over, but the decision the coach and the general manager make about the starter this week could determine how the season goes. Who is the answer? Is Bollinger the answer? Is Testaverde the answer? In the long run, is Chad Pennington really the answer?</p>
        <p>Maybe there are no answers.</p>
        <p>But there are decisions for Edwards to make. Let Bollinger play. By December, he will have made a veteran out of a veritable rookie. Edwards knows as well as anyone that everybody needs a chance in order to grow, and there will be definite growing pains.</p>
        <p>With Pennington's status uncertain, the Jets know, even if they sign an accomplished starter next season, that they will need an equally accomplished backup. That could be Bollinger.</p>
        <p>Go with Bollinger the rest of the way. Give him a fair and equal opportunity. Yesterday was neither fair nor equal.</p>
        <p>We make these calls from the luxury of a press box. No job on the line, no consequences, no price to pay for a bad decision.</p>
        <p>Edwards has a bad situation to manage and a season to save. On the surface, the easiest choice is good old reliable Vinny Testaverde. He still has a strong arm and a wealth of experience.</p>
        <p>But he's not the answer to this season.</p>
        <p>Let Bollinger play. There's plenty of time for the hook. Don't use it yet.</p>
        <p>E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: wcr@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
