<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Murdoch Defends Fox In Minority Challenge</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="745860"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MINORITIES (ETHNIC, RACIAL, RELIGIOUS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOX TELEVISION</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOX INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ASSN FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF COLORED PEOPLE</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL COMMUNICATIONS COMMISSION (FCC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CARTER, BILL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Minorities (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE2DE1138F93BA15751C0A963958260" item-length="640" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Murdoch Defends Fox In Minority Challenge</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CARTER, BILL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rupert Murdoch made an aggressive and personal response yesterday to the regulatory challenge to his Fox television network, saying that Fox had fully informed the Federal Communications Commission of all details of its ownership structure in 1985 when it bought the stations that make up the foundation of the network.</p>
        <p>The N.A.A.C.P. has challenged Fox at the Federal Communications Commission, saying that Fox did not make clear to the commission that the amount of foreign investment in its core stations would greatly exceed the 25 percent limit that has always been enforced by the F.C.C.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rupert Murdoch made an aggressive and personal response yesterday to the regulatory challenge to his Fox television network, saying that Fox had fully informed the Federal Communications Commission of all details of its ownership structure in 1985 when it bought the stations that make up the foundation of the network.</p>
        <p>The N.A.A.C.P. has challenged Fox at the Federal Communications Commission, saying that Fox did not make clear to the commission that the amount of foreign investment in its core stations would greatly exceed the 25 percent limit that has always been enforced by the F.C.C.</p>
        <p>Speaking to reporters at a news conference in Manhattan, Mr. Murdoch, the chairman of Fox Inc., responded specifically to the disclosure last week that one F.C.C. official, Roy Stewart, had said that he had not been aware in 1985 that 99 percent of the equity in the Fox stations was being supplied by News Corporation, an Australian company controlled by Mr. Murdoch. Mr. Steward said if he had known this, he would have requested more information.</p>
        <p>"He did not say we misled him or the F.C.C.," Mr. Murdoch said. "Nor did he say we were not candid. He said he simply didn't know."</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch attempted to counter any damage Mr. Stewart's statement might have done by citing the declarations of three former F.C.C. staff lawyers who, when supplied by Fox with a complete record of documents about the stations' ownership, said the Fox applications had made clear that News Corporation was supplying all the money.</p>
        <p>In addition, Mr. Murdoch cited the conclusion of a law professor who read Fox's documents and said they were completely clear and unambiguous as to the ownership structure of the stations.</p>
        <p>David Honig, the lawyer representing the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, said there was nothing new in Mr. Murdoch's arguments yesterday "other than the statement of a law professor whose opinion they paid for."</p>
        <p>Mr. Honig said his reading of the record showed that Fox tried to hide its foreign ownership, and that the F.C.C. was deceived in 1985. "If the staff members examining the case felt this issue was buttoned up, they would have addressed it in their memos," he said. "They did not, even though this was clearly an issue of great importance."</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch accused the N.A.A.C.P. and NBC, which also challenged Fox until dropping out after concluding a separate business deal with Mr. Murdoch, of abusing the regulatory process. He repeated Fox's arguments that the central issue should be voting control of the Fox network. That control had always been his, he said, adding that Fox had clearly stated that the equity in the company would reside with News Corporation. He said that Fox had served the public interest by establishing a fourth broadcast network.</p>
        <p>Yesterday was the deadline for filing comments on the case, but Mr. Murdoch's highly visible appearance was an indication of how seriously Fox was still taking this challenge. Mr. Murdoch said if the issue went to an administrative hearing, as the N.A.A.C.P. was seeking, the case would drag on for years.</p>
        <p>"That would seriously hold up our progress and expansion," Mr. Murdoch said. He said that process could turn into a "kangaroo court," but added, "when it gets into a proper court, we'll win."</p>
        <p>In the meantime, "We'd get our revenge by making Fox stronger in the marketplace," he said.</p>
        <p>The N.A.A.C.P. has filed a petition with the F.C.C. to deny Fox a renewal of its license for Channel 5 in New York, saying that the introduction of foreign capital made it much harder for minority investors to buy television stations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murdoch said, "We've had no trouble with the N.A.A.C.P., except perhaps a small coterie of them in New York." In fact, he added, minority audiences find most of their favorite shows on Fox.  THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
