<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Colts Ready to Heed Playoff Alarm Clock</title>
    <meta content="12colts" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1731483"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indianapolis Colts</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pittsburgh Steelers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Indianapolis Colts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Pittsburgh Steelers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060112T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3D6163FF931A25752C0A9609C8B63" item-length="969" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Colts Ready to Heed Playoff Alarm Clock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>INDIANAPOLIS, Jan. 11</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Indianapolis Colts prepare to face Pittsburgh Steelers in playoffs; photo (M)1</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Quarterback Peyton Manning looked tired Wednesday as he spoke to reporters. Then again, he and the rest of the Colts could not be blamed for taking a long winter's nap.</p>
        <p>They have not played a meaningful game since Dec. 11, when they secured home-field advantage throughout the American Football Conference playoffs with a 26-18 victory over Jacksonville. Although an undefeated season was still on the line, they headed for the N.F.L. equivalent of a La-Z-Boy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Quarterback Peyton Manning looked tired Wednesday as he spoke to reporters. Then again, he and the rest of the Colts could not be blamed for taking a long winter's nap.</p>
        <p>They have not played a meaningful game since Dec. 11, when they secured home-field advantage throughout the American Football Conference playoffs with a 26-18 victory over Jacksonville. Although an undefeated season was still on the line, they headed for the N.F.L. equivalent of a La-Z-Boy.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, when they play the Pittsburgh Steelers in an A.F.C. divisional playoff game, it will be the first time in more than a month that all of the Colts' regular starters have been on the field together.</p>
        <p>It was a long and sometimes painful period for Indianapolis. The Colts lost their perfect season to the San Diego Chargers, lost to the Seattle Seahawks, then struggled, with most of the starters on the bench, to beat the woeful Arizona Cardinals, 17-13, in the regular-season finale. They also confronted a situation that dwarfed those losses, the death of Coach Tony Dungy's son James.</p>
        <p>But Wednesday, their first day of preparation in earnest for the Steelers, the Colts returned to work, rested and, they hoped, refreshed.</p>
        <p>Defensive tackle Corey Simon, who has not played or practiced since Dec. 11 because of a foot injury, returned Monday. Manning has played just three series -- and thrown 14 passes -- since the Colts lost to the Chargers on Dec. 18.</p>
        <p>''I think mentally you're a little fresher when you're not cramming every week,'' Dungy said Wednesday. ''It's like cramming for an exam. When you get a little time off, it helps you. Physically, he was able to throw just as much as he wanted to, and not have to throw a certain number of balls every day.</p>
        <p>''I think a lot of us are in that boat. We had 25 guys in here yesterday on the off day, lifting and wanting to run. That normally does not happen on a Tuesday after you've played a game.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps only one person -- Denver Coach Mike Shanahan -- could tell Dungy what to expect from his team this week. In 1998, the Broncos wrapped up home-field advantage with their 13th consecutive victory. Then they lost their next two games with their starters resting and won the regular-season finale.</p>
        <p>The good news for the Colts is that Denver won the Super Bowl that season. The bad news is that Shanahan, immersed in preparations for his team's game against the New England Patriots on Saturday, is not giving out any pointers.</p>
        <p>Dungy, like many coaches, says that teams play the way they practice. He was delighted that the Colts were so crisp in practice last Thursday that they had to repeat nothing, ending the session 14 minutes ahead of schedule.</p>
        <p>Ramping up for a football team entering the playoffs may not be as difficult as it is to return to the office after a vacation. The former Patriots linebacker Ted Johnson, who retired before the season, recalled spending part of the Patriots' bye week last year with his teammate Larry Izzo in Vermont, where they drank beer in front of a fire while watching the other playoff teams beat up on each other.</p>
        <p>''In two weeks, you can't wait to go out and hit someone again,'' Johnson said in a recent telephone interview.</p>
        <p>But for a finely tuned offense that thrives on rhythm and timing, a question remains: Does the slightest alteration in the routine cause the offense to start skipping like a bad record?</p>
        <p>The danger, Simon said, would be a sluggish start. Last season, Simon was with the Eagles, who clinched home-field advantage early enough to rest starters down the stretch. They crushed both of their National Football Conference playoff opponents before losing to the Patriots in the Super Bowl. The Colts have a similar makeup: considerable playoff experience and veteran leadership.</p>
        <p>The balance between readiness and rust may be most critical for Manning, and he insists that a layoff this late in the season does nothing but keep his arm fresh.</p>
        <p>''People talk about, 'How are you going to be ready to play when you haven't played?' '' Manning said. ''Well, we don't have a choice. It is our job to be ready to play. To me, when you are out there in the playoff games and executing a third-and-5, that's when your off-season work is supposed to kick in.''</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most remarkable thing, then, was how normal things seemed even after more than a month that nobody could have been prepared for.</p>
        <p>Dungy returned to the team after burying his son in time to coach against Arizona, and he presented a stunningly upbeat face. The Colts flew to Tampa, Fla., for the funeral, and they seemed to absorb the shock and press on. Dungy has been careful to not make his mourning a rallying point for the team, suggesting instead that his players should try to win for the city and for the team's owner, Jim Irsay.</p>
        <p>''You're always looking to be in the playoffs, and that's what you take this job for,'' Dungy said. ''With my son's situation and our family, it puts it all into perspective. I always thought that the playoffs are great and the Super Bowl's great, but it's not the most important thing in the world.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
