<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Privatization: Leaner Government, or Just Another Fad?</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="765235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="CONFERENCE CALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRIVATIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEPARTMENTS AND AGENCIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLZER, MARC</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">EISENBERG, LEWIS M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHEN, DAVID W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Privatization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D71138F93BA15756C0A963958260" item-length="931" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Privatization: Leaner Government, or Just Another Fad?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHEN, DAVID W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Republicans talk about reinventing government, they invariably talk about turning public services over to the private sector. Governor Whitman is no exception. When she took office, she promised a far-ranging examination of how and who delivers state services, from testing motor-vehicle emissions to feeding prisoners.</p>
        <p>Privatizing at least some of these services, she said, could save taxpayer dollars by forcing private entrepreneurs to bid against one another -- and by letting them use their competitive energy to do a better job of delivering services.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Republicans talk about reinventing government, they invariably talk about turning public services over to the private sector. Governor Whitman is no exception. When she took office, she promised a far-ranging examination of how and who delivers state services, from testing motor-vehicle emissions to feeding prisoners.</p>
        <p>Privatizing at least some of these services, she said, could save taxpayer dollars by forcing private entrepreneurs to bid against one another -- and by letting them use their competitive energy to do a better job of delivering services.</p>
        <p>So far, she has recommended transferring the Division of Motor Vehicles to private control, and her administration is studying privatization at the Division of Youth and Family Services and the food-service contracts at state hospitals.</p>
        <p>Not everyone is happy with this trend. Critics, including public-employee unions whose members' jobs are at stake, say privatization means that government has less contol of its resources and its ability to function as a watchdog. They warn that privatization can easily be just another term for political patronage. And they say that a few dollars saved here and there may cost more in the long run because of reduced services.</p>
        <p>The New York Times arranged a conference call with experts on both sides of the issue: Lewis M. Eisenberg, a business executive who is chairman of the New Jersey Advisory Council on Privatization, and Marc Holzer, a Rutgers University professor of public adminstration who is executive director of the National Center for Public Productivity.</p>
        <p>Q. How is privatization supposed to work, in theory?</p>
        <p>HOLZER I think the underpinning philosophy, which is competition, is a good idea. Competition can do things like lower costs, allow economies of scale, avoid large start-up costs, provide access to specialized skills and training, etc. But I think competition doesn't have to mean privatization. We can achieve the advantages of competition without giving away control over services which really should be in the public domain. I don't think we want private-sector firms running our schools or prisons, for example, and certainly not police departments. What we really need to do is create more competitive entities in the public sector.</p>
        <p>EISENBERG I'm not sure that I would agree, activity by activity, with the professor's comments that they shouldn't be open to private competition. The public sector should be allowed to compete with the private sector for the very same services. If you look at some of the successes we've had here at home in New Jersey, in Mercer County or Bergen County, where they've actually privatized a meaningful portion of the correctional facilities, saved the taxpayers a lot of money, and have improved, I think, both by inmate reaction and by recidivism rates.</p>
        <p>Q. What does this mean for government employees?</p>
        <p>EISENBERG In a free capitalist society, assuming all things are equal, government is overburdened; the costs have basically been breaking the back of the camel. I don't think it serves a worker well to argue for preserving his job by saying that someone in the private sector is willing to accept lower wages and lower fringe benefits for the same job.</p>
        <p>HOLZER I think you cut to the core of the question. Is it the same job with the same outcome or have we changed the nature of the service when we moved it to the private sector? If you're dealing with more complicated functions, whether it's air traffic control or corrections or education, is it really the same job people are doing? Or are they operating at a lower level, which has hidden long-term costs for our society?</p>
        <p>Q. What, then, should be the goal of government?</p>
        <p>HOLZER I think the endgame is service. When you ask the public what it wants, it wants improved services before it wants reduced costs.</p>
        <p>I think we're suffering from political hysteria in terms of a desire to cut taxes. If you ask them whether they want better schools or lower taxes, they will almost always select better schools because they understand that's an important long-term payoff.</p>
        <p>They want an improved system and they're willing to pay for it, but what I think we lack is the political courage to do that.</p>
        <p>EISENBERG I disagree with him strongly; I think the quality of service is integrally interwoven with the costs. I think the 1994 elections and Governor Whitman's election  [ in 1993 ]  basically said people feel they're being taxed way too much for the services they're getting, and I think we're duty-bound to find those places to try, by using competition as an arrow and a quiver of government, to provide the same or better service at lower cost.</p>
        <p>Q. Where do you think privatization will go in New Jersey?</p>
        <p>EISENBERG I think the Governor has basically been cautious and at the same time has taken expeditious steps to bring in competition where it can provide the same or better service at lower cost.</p>
        <p>There were 20 initiatives that were recommended by the Commission on Privatization at the end of 1994, and 14 of them are in some form of implementation. My expectation is that they will result in $200 million to 300 million in recurring savings to the state.</p>
        <p>HOLZER The Governor has got well-intentioned objectives, but I'm a skeptic in terms of how much we need to do in terms of privatization. I think she should be giving public servants more opportunity to compete with the private sector and with each other.</p>
        <p>I think there should be more competition within government before we start looking for alternatives on the outside.  CONFERENCE CALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
