<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fiery Nationalism Drove Venezuelan Plotters</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506908"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COUPS D'ETAT AND ATTEMPTED COUPS D'ETAT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSASSINATIONS AND ATTEMPTED ASSASSINATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">VENEZUELA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKE, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEREZ, CARLOS ANDRES (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Venezuela</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coups D'Etat and Attempted Coups D'Etat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920211T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DE1E39F932A25751C0A964958260" item-length="663" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fiery Nationalism Drove Venezuelan Plotters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BROOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKE, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>CARACAS, Venezuela, Feb. 10</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A violently nationalist ideology inspired army officers who mounted an unsuccessful coup last week and came close to killing the President of Venezuela, the second-largest net supplier of oil to the United States after Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>According to documents made available here, the officers drew on writings by 19th-century Venezuelan military leaders to advocate redeeming the "lost" 20th century by wiping away "the so-called democratic experiment."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A violently nationalist ideology inspired army officers who mounted an unsuccessful coup last week and came close to killing the President of Venezuela, the second-largest net supplier of oil to the United States after Saudi Arabia.</p>
        <p>According to documents made available here, the officers drew on writings by 19th-century Venezuelan military leaders to advocate redeeming the "lost" 20th century by wiping away "the so-called democratic experiment."</p>
        <p>A "national salvation government" also would have jettisoned orthodox free-market economic policies that currently prevail in Venezuela, which is endowed with the largest oil reserves in South America.</p>
        <p>The price of these "deep changes" would be fire and blood, the plotters warned. A 12-page manifesto opened with a quote attributed to Thomas Jefferson that "the tree of liberty should be irrigated from time to time with the blood of patriots and tyrants."</p>
        <p>Pamphlets by the officers' group, "Los Bolivarianos," -- named after Simon Bolivar, the liberator of Venezuela from Spanish rule -- proposed hanging civilian politicians in public squares or executing them by firing squads in sports stadiums, according to a recently retired Commander in Chief of the Army, Carlos Julio Penaloza Zambrano.</p>
        <p>"The level of hate especially caught my attention," General Penaloza said last week in a television interview before censorship ended public discussion here of the movement. "They were convinced that the only way to wash the honor of the humiliated fatherland was through a ritual bath using the blood of corrupt men who had put our nation on its knees. Chavez Frias was our Saddam Hussein."</p>
        <p>Army Lieut. Col. Hugo Chavez Frias, the coup's mastermind, told army interrogators last week that his movement's intention was to select "an honor tribunal" that would try President Carlos Andres Perez and have him executed by a firing squad.</p>
        <p>The 69-year-old President, who reportedly asked for a machine gun to defend himself during last Tuesday's predawn palace attack, has maintained that the plotters intended to kill him in the palace. His wife, Blanca Rodriguez de Perez, says the attackers wanted to wipe out the family.</p>
        <p>She said the rebels continued to fire machine guns and mortars at the presidential residence for hours after the President had appeared live on national television from a studio across town.</p>
        <p>Twelve army battalions in four major cities -- roughly 10 percent of the army -- participated in the revolt.</p>
        <p>Interrogations of the 176 army officers detained have revealed an ultranationalist streak as the primary cause for the uprising. Leading the list were border issues: statements by President Perez that Colombia has "small rights" over the Gulf of Venezuela, the invasion of Venezuela's Amazon by Brazilian gold miners and the donation by Mr. Perez of police equipment to Guyana, a neighboring country with a large territorial dispute with Venezuela.</p>
        <p>The mutinous officers, most in their 20's and 30's, also complained of unpunished cases of corruption involving military and political leaders, of privatization of state companies and of the withdrawal of subsidies for food and medicines.</p>
        <p>In addition to denouncing economic "shock policies" implemented by "savage hands," the young officers' manifesto proposed that Venezuela adopt an obscure new ideology -- the "EBR System."</p>
        <p>Apparently drawn up by Colonel Chavez and by colleagues who served with him as history instructors at Venezuela's military academy, the system's initials stand for three prominent 19th-century Venezuelans -- Ezequiel Zamora, a populist general; Bolivar, a general who liberated most of the Andes from Spanish colonial rule, and Simon Rodriguez, a teacher of Bolivar in late 18th-century Caracas.</p>
        <p>The manifesto called for the creation of a vaguely defined "different political model" that would break with imported models and that would provide for "individual and collective human necessities."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
