<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>WorldCom Messages Suggest a Silencing Effort</title>
    <meta content="Y27TEL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/27/technology/27TELE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1419004"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Worldcom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Andersen, Arthur, &amp; Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feder, Barnaby J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myers, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brabbs, Steven</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">WorldCom Incorporated</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Myers, David</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020827T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E0D7113CF934A1575BC0A9649C8B63" item-length="566" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>WorldCom Messages Suggest a Silencing Effort</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">WorldCom Messages Suggest a Silencing Effort</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARNABY J. FEDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feder, Barnaby J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>House Financial Services Committee releases copies of internal WorldCom e-mail messages that it says suggests that former company controller David Myers tried in January to silence Steven Brabbs, accounting executive based in London, who had questioned company's accounting practices; e-messages center on meeting with Brabbs, apparently organized with representatives in Britain of Arthur Andersen, WorldCom's outside accountant at time; Myers expressed anger in one message after being told that Brabbs appeared to be dealing with accountants on issues Brabbs had been forbidden to discuss; Myers ordered him not to have any more meetings with Andersen (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Congressional committee released copies of internal WorldCom e-mail messages yesterday that it says suggest that David Myers, the company's former controller, tried early this year to silence an executive who had questioned accounting practices at WorldCom.</p>
        <p>The e-mail messages, which were released by the House Financial Services Committee, center on a meeting that Steven Brabbs, a WorldCom accounting executive based in London, apparently organized in January with representatives in Britain of Arthur Andersen, WorldCom's outside accountant at the time. In one of the messages, Mr. Myers expressed anger after being told that Mr. Brabbs, vice president for international finance and control, appeared to be dealing with the accountants on issues Mr. Brabbs had been forbidden to discuss. Mr. Myers ordered him not to have any more meetings with Andersen.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Congressional committee said copies of internal WorldCom e-mail messages tried to silence an executive who had questioned accounting practices at the company.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Congressional committee released copies of internal WorldCom e-mail messages yesterday that it says suggest that David Myers, the company's former controller, tried early this year to silence an executive who had questioned accounting practices at WorldCom.</p>
        <p>The e-mail messages, which were released by the House Financial Services Committee, center on a meeting that Steven Brabbs, a WorldCom accounting executive based in London, apparently organized in January with representatives in Britain of Arthur Andersen, WorldCom's outside accountant at the time. In one of the messages, Mr. Myers expressed anger after being told that Mr. Brabbs, vice president for international finance and control, appeared to be dealing with the accountants on issues Mr. Brabbs had been forbidden to discuss. Mr. Myers ordered him not to have any more meetings with Andersen.</p>
        <p>''I do not want to hear an excuse just stop,'' Mr. Myers wrote, before concluding, ''Don't make me ask you again.''</p>
        <p>The e-mail messages shed new light on Mr. Brabbs's troubled relationship with his superiors. The matter became public last month when the House Energy and Commerce Committee, which is conducting a separate investigation, released a memorandum he had written to WorldCom's internal investigators on June 26, the day after Mr. Myers was forced to resign. In that memo, Mr. Brabbs recalled for the investigators how he had objected in the spring of 2000 to the company's handling of $33.6 million in reported international expenses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brabbs said in the memo that officials at the company's headquarters in Clinton, Miss., had unilaterally reduced reported expenses by that amount through a technique known as a journal entry. He said in the memo that the officials refused to provide him with an explanation for the change, which had the effect of increasing publicly reported profits.</p>
        <p>At the time Mr. Brabbs wrote his memo, WorldCom had acknowledged that it had improperly accounted for $3.8 billion in expenses but had not indicated that any irregularities took place before last year. Early this month, WorldCom raised its total estimate of the misstatements to $7.1 billion and said the irregularities began as far back as 1999.</p>
        <p>Just before WorldCom revised the scope of the scandal, Mr. Myers and Scott D. Sullivan, the former chief financial officer at WorldCom, were arrested on criminal fraud charges. They are scheduled to be indicted in New York next Tuesday.</p>
        <p>The e-mail messages released yesterday disclose tension between Mr. Brabbs and his superiors involving WorldCom's need to further write down the value of various assets. It is unclear from the e-mail messages whether WorldCom officials objected to the results of Mr. Brabbs's meeting or simply the fact that he had organized it and appeared intent on pursuing topics they wanted to control centrally.</p>
        <p>In a response to Mr. Myers, Mr. Brabbs said that ''mixed and inaccurate messages'' had been exchanged ''as usual'' and that he would be calling Mr. Myers and Mark Willson, another executive, to sort out the confusion. There is no indication of whether such a call took place.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brabbs could not be reached for comment. N. Richard Janis, Mr. Myers's lawyer, declined to comment.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
