<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Armada's Gone, Leaving a Savory Memory</title>
    <meta content="06LAKS$10" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1299297"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Malaysia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Craig S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Malaysia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E0D9133FF935A35755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1576" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Armada's Gone, Leaving a Savory Memory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG S. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Smith, Craig S</byline>
      <dateline>SINGAPORE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Craig S Smith artucke on Malaysian dish called laksa, spicy noodle dish; recipe; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MORE than half a century before Columbus sailed the ocean blue, China's Muslim admiral, Zheng He, sailed through the Strait of Malacca on his way to India.</p>
        <p>Some of the 28,000 men in his armada stayed behind in the strait to marry local women, and their legacy persists, largely because of the cuisine borne of those unions, a mix of southern Chinese and Malay that has become a defining culinary feature of the region. There is no dish more identified with this cuisine than laksa, a rich preparation of rice-flour noodles, bean curd, shrimp and other ingredients, all bathed in a silky, spicy coconut sauce. It is an addicting blend.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MORE than half a century before Columbus sailed the ocean blue, China's Muslim admiral, Zheng He, sailed through the Strait of Malacca on his way to India.</p>
        <p>Some of the 28,000 men in his armada stayed behind in the strait to marry local women, and their legacy persists, largely because of the cuisine borne of those unions, a mix of southern Chinese and Malay that has become a defining culinary feature of the region. There is no dish more identified with this cuisine than laksa, a rich preparation of rice-flour noodles, bean curd, shrimp and other ingredients, all bathed in a silky, spicy coconut sauce. It is an addicting blend.</p>
        <p>The dish is found mostly in Malaysian restaurants in the West, but people along the strait know it has a more complex pedigree. Southern Chinese traders followed Zheng He's route, and their descendants became known as the Peranakan, which means ''born here'' in Malay. To the British, they were the King's Chinese or Straits Chinese. They are also called Babas, an honorific term that was used by Malaysians to refer to the Chinese who settled along the strait starting nearly 600 years ago.</p>
        <p>The word laksa (also spelled lakhsa or laksha) comes from luak sua, which in southern China's Hokkien dialect means spicy sand -- a reference to the coconut sauce, which is made with ground candlenuts, waxy beige nuts related to the macadamia.</p>
        <p>There are many kinds of laksa in Southeast Asia. Some people say it is a Malaysian dish adopted by the Chinese that arrived with Zheng He. Other people say it is a Peranakan creation, bringing Chinese noodles together with local sauce. In any case, the wealthy Chinese traders who followed Zheng He's route developed a rich, shrimp-studded laksa that outclassed local rivals and became a regional favorite.</p>
        <p>Even Peranakan laksa varies widely, according to who makes it. Nonyas, as Peranakan women are called, generally make a thick sauce and serve it with white rice noodles and shrimp, bean sprouts, quail eggs, deep-fried bean curd and chopped laksa leaves, called daun kesom in Malay and known as Vietnamese mint in the West. Some people serve the ingredients in separate bowls so they can be combined to personal taste. The Peranakan of Penang, on the north end of the strait, don't use coconut at all, but make a sour tamarind sauce that gives their laksa an edge more akin to Thai cuisine.</p>
        <p>Other people add tomatoes, giving the sauce a rich orange hue. The commercial version tends to be soupier, perhaps because watering down the sauce cuts costs.</p>
        <p>In any case, it is home cooking here, and anyone will tell you that it's not complicated to make. (But isn't that the way it always is?) For cooks in the United States, the hardest part is finding the ingredients, but they are all available at good Asian markets. Making laksa is considerably easier if you can find commercial laksa paste -- which eliminates hunting down the spices and grinding them for the sauce base. Commercial laksa pastes are made by several companies, including one owned by Charmaine Solomon, the Asian food expert, and sold through her Web site at http://www.spicespl .com.au/index.html.</p>
        <p>But no matter what the variation, the common theme for most laksa is a sweet, spicy, fishy coconut sauce over noodles. The creamy flavor is reflected in the name: laksa lemak, lemak being the Malay word for rich.</p>
        <p>I recently traced the route of Zheng He, albeit by air, to Singapore from my home in Shanghai. A friend took me to eat laksa in Katong, a sleepy Singapore suburb that is the heart of the island's Peranakan community. There, along East Coast Road, a few doorways are still hung with pintu pagan, traditional saloon-style doors that allow the people inside ventilation with a measure of privacy during the heat of the day. I soon found myself wandering beneath ceiling fans at one of the neighborhood's many kopi tiams, or open air coffee shops, which are themselves a legacy of the Peranakan: kopi is the Malay word for coffee and tiam is the word for shop in the Hokkien dialect.</p>
        <p>We sat on stools and each paid five Singapore dollars, about $2.75, to a cheerful woman who served us steaming bowls of the noodles, which we ate, Peranakan style, with a spoon. They were hot and rich, the sharp edge of red pepper offset by mellow coconut, and they carried a hint of the sea. I imagined that for a weary 15th-century Chinese trader, this was comfort food.</p>
        <p>The laksa of Katong is soupier and sweeter than some renditions, and, perhaps for that reason, has become a standard across Asia. Some kopi tiams add condensed milk to the soup to make it richer and sweeter, and many add fresh cockles, too.</p>
        <p>Siew Boon Kiong, who works at one of the most popular laksa stalls, at 49 East Coast Road, put it most succinctly, ''Katong laksa tastes so good, it became very famous.''</p>
        <p>Peranakan restaurants didn't appear until the second half of the 20th century, when the culture was in decline and many upper-class Peranakan families fell on hard times. One of the first laksa stalls in Katong was started a half century ago by a Baba nicknamed Janggut, which means Long Beard in Malay, because of the hairs sprouting from a mole on his chin. The dish spread and is now a standard on five-star hotel menus from Beijing to Brisbane and is ladled up by thousands of laksa hawkers at stalls all over Southeast Asia.</p>
        <p>But it wasn't until fairly recently that Peranakan culture became hip again. Now, Singaporean yuppies fill newly fashionable Peranakan restaurants like Blue Ginger, whose latest branch is a modern, minimalist open-plan bistro several escalators up in a crowded, air-conditioned mall.</p>
        <p>The restaurants sell more elaborate Peranakan fare, like ayam buah keluak, chicken cooked in a rich tamarind sauce with plum-size black Indonesian nuts that, fermented and stewed, yield something in taste and texture reminiscent of truffles or even an undercooked chocolate brownie.</p>
        <p>But laksa is the Peranakan standard bearer. At the Katong laksa stall, we also ordered otak-otak, a Peranakan concoction of fish paste, coconut milk and chilies wrapped and grilled in a banana leaf into a dense, spicy patty. A cool glass of barley water calmed our taste buds. To finish the meal we had a muddy cup of black coffee with a sediment of condensed milk hiding at the bottom. The coffee is served in thick-lipped off-white porcelain cups and deep saucers, into which the locals pour their brew to cool after stirring up the sweet milk with a spoon.</p>
        <p>We drank our coffee with Peranakan kueh, glutinous rice-flour cakes that come in a variety of colors and are filled or flavored with sweet bean paste, banana or coconut. The most dazzling is kueh lapis, made with thin layers of coconut-flavored rice flour, each of the dozen layers a different bright color, so that when the cake is sliced into squares it presents a Day-Glo rainbow.</p>
        <p>LAKSA  Adapted from Violet Oon  Time: 1 hour</p>
        <p>25 dried red Thai chili peppers  1 1/2 ounces dried shrimp  3 ounces fresh galangal, washed and sliced  1 3-inch length turmeric (fresh, or frozen and defrosted)  5 stalks fresh lemon grass, white part only, sliced  5 candlenuts or macadamia nuts  5 cloves garlic, peeled  1 tablespoon shrimp paste  8 shallots, peeled  2 teaspoons ground white pepper</p>
        <p>1/4 cup vegetable oil  3 to 4 tablespoons ground coriander  3 16-ounce cans coconut milk  2 teaspoons salt, or to taste  6 handfuls fresh bean sprouts, blanched and drained  1 pound wide rice noodles or rice vermicelli, cooked  3 ounces cooked and shelled cockles or minced clams  24 peeled, cooked medium shrimp  1 cucumber, peeled and cut into julienne</p>
        <p>1/2 cup fresh laksa leaves (also known as daun kesom or Vietnamese mint), chopped  20 fresh chilies, finely minced.</p>
        <p>1. Slice chili peppers lengthwise, and shake out as many seeds as possible. Put peppers in a bowl; cover with hot water until softened, 10 to 15 minutes. Put dried shrimp in another bowl; cover with hot water until softened, about 15 minutes. Meanwhile, in the bowl of a food processor, combine the galangal, turmeric, lemon grass, candlenuts, garlic, shrimp paste, shallots and white pepper.</p>
        <p>2. Remove chili peppers from water, discarding seeds. Add peppers to food processor, and process to a paste, scraping bowl as needed.</p>
        <p>3. Place a large wok over high heat until very hot. Add oil. Drain dried shrimp and pat with paper towels. When oil is hot, add chili pepper mixture and dried shrimp. Stir-fry until fragrant and beginning to brown, 6 to 8 minutes. Add ground coriander and stir 30 seconds. Add coconut milk and 6 cups water. Bring to a boil, and boil for 20 minutes, stirring occasionally. Add salt.</p>
        <p>4. To serve, place a handful of bean sprouts in each of six large soup plates. Top with a portion of noodles and cockles, and a generous serving of soup. Garnish each plate with equal portions of shrimp, cucumber, laksa leaves and minced fresh chilies to taste. Serve immediately.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
