<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Away From the Zoo, Emus Are Raised for Profit and Fun</title>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="682706"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EMUS (BIRDS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JONES, JOYCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940424T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9904E1DC1331F937A15757C0A962958260" item-length="1085" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Away From the Zoo, Emus Are Raised for Profit and Fun</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOYCE JONES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JONES, JOYCE</byline>
      <dateline>BUENA VISTA TOWNSHIP</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON a recent evening at the Plaza Hotel in New York, members of the Confrerie de la Chaine des Rotisseurs, a gathering of epicures, sipped 1986 cabernet sauvignon in between bites of emu medallions. Earlier that day, on Route 34 south just outside Carlisle, Pa., the luncheon crowd at T Jimmy's ordered the usual, emu burgers and fries.</p>
        <p>The emu is the national bird of Australia. Emus that have made it to this country did so mainly as zoo attractions. In the 1950's, Australia, deciding to keep the bird to itself, banned the export of emus or emu eggs, allowing only the emu meat and its byproducts to be exported.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON a recent evening at the Plaza Hotel in New York, members of the Confrerie de la Chaine des Rotisseurs, a gathering of epicures, sipped 1986 cabernet sauvignon in between bites of emu medallions. Earlier that day, on Route 34 south just outside Carlisle, Pa., the luncheon crowd at T Jimmy's ordered the usual, emu burgers and fries.</p>
        <p>The emu is the national bird of Australia. Emus that have made it to this country did so mainly as zoo attractions. In the 1950's, Australia, deciding to keep the bird to itself, banned the export of emus or emu eggs, allowing only the emu meat and its byproducts to be exported.</p>
        <p>The emu has survived, however, and is doing well in this country. While emu meat from game ranches in the West is growing more popular, even its staunchest proponents are not saying it is a mainstay of the American menu yet. Suitable as a Pet</p>
        <p>But the American Emu Association, whose membership rose in 1993 to 4,600 from 1,800, thinks that the bird's low-fat red meat and its oil, used in some skin-care products, are destined at some point to change American diets and complexions.</p>
        <p>In addition, some people find that the emu's nonaggressive personality and inquisitiveness make it a good pet.</p>
        <p>Pierce Allman, managing director of the American Emu Association, based in Dallas, regards the breeding of emus today as a viable agricultural business. "Daily, we process 50 calls asking us about raising emus, and we encourage farmers and entrepreneurs alike to view it as an investment opportunity," he said.</p>
        <p>William J. Hayes, who heads a law firm in Collings Lakes, decided he needed a hobby to counteract the stress from his law practice. Raising emus to sell for breeding, not for eating, seemed to be an engaging activity for his family. Return on Investment</p>
        <p>This is Mr. Hayes's third year of operation, and he is already realizing some return on his investment. Pairs of emu chicks at 3 months old sell for $9,000; pairs of yearlings, 8 to 15 months go for $18,000 and a mature pair of breeder emus brings $45,000. The emu has a life expectancy of 60 years and in the breeding season,from November to May, may lay 20 to 45 eggs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayes approached emu breeding with the same intensity he gives to the law, he said. He bought 80 acres of land in Buena Vista Township and named it Golden Pond Ranch. There, some 70 emus of seven bloodlines ranging from the newly hatched to mature birds live amid surroundings that look more like a spa for emus than just breeding grounds.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayes cares for his emu population with two ranch assistants. He may interrupt his work at his office to attend to a detail, and in the breeding season he is at the ranch late into the evening. Emus lay their eggs starting at 4:30 P.M. and as late at 10:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>On a recent Sunday, Mr. Hayes approached the fenced ranch and pressed a switch that opened the gate allowing him to drive through. Inside the grounds, he handed a visitor a hollow emu egg, six inches long, its usual size, with a textured green leatherlike exterior.</p>
        <p>His arrival prompted the watchdogs to yap at his heels as he headed toward some 30 yearlings, which instantly took notice of his appearance. "Daddy's home!" he shouted.</p>
        <p>Once he was in the midst of them and raised his arms, the emus made grunting sounds and began to dance. Two emus raced the length of the enclosure; out in the open, their speed has been clocked at 45 miles an hour.</p>
        <p>While Mr. Hayes's manner is jocular, his venture is a serious operation to insure that the emus lay eggs, the eggs hatch and the chicks exercise and eat properly.</p>
        <p>If he can't buy the equipment to make this happen, he puts together pieces like the humidifier that provides the right amount of moisture an emu egg needs. Outside the building that houses the three-month-old emus, he has constructed an obstacle course in sand. Running it helps to strengthen the young birds' legs.</p>
        <p>Because it is the male emu that sits on the nest, Mr. Hayes thinks of himself as something of a surrogate father. The male is prone to hide the egg in straw, and Mr. Hayes retrieves it. Once a week he puts the eggs he has gathered into the incubator. Between 52 and 56 days later, the chicks hatch and are tagged with identifications like C-16, for Christina's 16th egg.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayes carefully removed an egg from the hatchery. "Put it to your ear," he said. "First you'll hear scratching, then a peep. In about three days that chick will hatch. It takes an emu 5,000 pecks to break a tiny hole through the egg. Then the bird rests."</p>
        <p>Emus must be taught to eat. Mr. Hayes, his wife, Pat, and their three daughters -- Patricia, 16, Alyssa, 11, and Dorothea, 13 -- peck at the grain with their fingers. "Emus are copycats, and soon they start to peck and then eat," Mr. Hayes said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hayes addressed the eight pairs of breeders by name. When Alyssa was 10, she paired off the birds, he said. She matched up the aggressive Ralph with the preening Jen, Edwina with Danny, John with Dorothea, and Billy with Patti, and the list goes on. The chemistry seems right for, to date, 36 eggs have been hatched.</p>
        <p>Hugh Pribell, who raises pheasants and quails in Burlington County, is waiting for his pair of chicks from the Golden Pond Ranch. He has read literature about raising emus and hopes eventually to earn a living breeding them. "It's a whole new industry," he said, adding: "With dairy farming, you need so many acres and cows. You can raise emus on a minimum of a quarter of an acre of land."</p>
        <p>Not all people who raise emus are doing it to raise money. Linda Lew Woo, who worked on Wall Street while living in New York City, took a memento of the city with her when she moved to a 55-acre farm in Hunterdon County, adopting several emus from a New York City zoo.</p>
        <p>"There was little information then about emus," Ms. Woo recalled, "and I had to do major research to find what food they liked and why the first year my emus laid 75 eggs and none hatched." The reason none hatched, Ms. Woo said, was that the birds had been placed on a diet similar to a turkey's diet.</p>
        <p>"It is the emus' personality and their inquisitive nature that makes them such good pets," she said. Ms. Woo is the wildlife president for the Morris Animal Foundation, a group based in Englewood, Colo. that is dedicated to animal health whose president emeritus is the actress Betty White.</p>
        <p>"When Betty visits the farm," Ms. Woo said, "she gives me a 'Hi,' and then heads right out to play with the emus."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
