<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Angry and Motivated, Trinidad Has Returned</title>
    <meta content="04BOXI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/04/sports/othersports/04boxing.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1616472"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BOXING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sandomir, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Trinidad, Felix Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mayorga, Ricardo</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Trinidad, Felix Jr</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Mayorga, Ricardo</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1D81138F937A35753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Angry and Motivated, Trinidad Has Returned</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Angry and Motivated, Trinidad Has Returned</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD SANDOMIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sandomir, Richard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Felix Trinidad Jr wins middleweight bout against Ricardo Mayorga with eighth-round knockout; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Felix Trinidad Jr. had everything when he stopped Ricardo Mayorga with 21 seconds left in the eighth round of their middleweight fight on Saturday night at Madison Square Garden. He had hand speed, punching power, lively legs and deadly accuracy. He connected on 63 percent of his punches and 66 percent of his power shots against the defenseless Mayorga.</p>
        <p>No one had knocked Mayorga to the canvas until Trinidad did it three times. Mayorga, his left eye swollen, and a gash beneath it, went to Bellevue Hospital Center afterward for observation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Felix Trinidad Jr. had everything when he stopped Ricardo Mayorga with 21 seconds left in the eighth round of their middleweight fight on Saturday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Felix Trinidad Jr. had everything when he stopped Ricardo Mayorga with 21 seconds left in the eighth round of their middleweight fight on Saturday night at Madison Square Garden. He had hand speed, punching power, lively legs and deadly accuracy. He connected on 63 percent of his punches and 66 percent of his power shots against the defenseless Mayorga.</p>
        <p>No one had knocked Mayorga to the canvas until Trinidad did it three times. Mayorga, his left eye swollen, and a gash beneath it, went to Bellevue Hospital Center afterward for observation.</p>
        <p>Trinidad's domination showed that after a 29-month retirement, he had not taken much of a risk by facing the strong but undisciplined Mayorga, who landed only 25 percent of his punches.</p>
        <p>''I came back, I will come back and I will still win,'' Trinidad said through an interpreter during the postfight news conference.</p>
        <p>Trinidad's victory puts him at the forefront of the middleweight division, in which two weeks ago Bernard Hopkins, the undisputed champion and the only boxer to have beaten Trinidad, knocked out Oscar De La Hoya, whom Trinidad has beaten.</p>
        <p>There is resentment simmering within Trinidad and his father, Felix Sr., who is his son's manager and trainer. The elder Trinidad said that his son retired after Hopkins reneged on an agreement for a rematch. ''Other fights of that caliber never came,'' Felix Trinidad Sr. said through an interpreter.</p>
        <p>The Trinidads declined to say whom they want to face; such decisions, they said, would be made after talking to their promoter, Don King, who used the news conference to praise the Trinidad family. ''Tito,'' he said, one arm around the boxer's shoulder, ''you are my shining star.''</p>
        <p>But praise for the Trinidads mixed discordantly with King's lengthy rant about HBO -- complaints that had nothing to do with Trinidad's comeback. HBO carried Saturday night's fight card on pay-per-view.</p>
        <p>''There's a time for liberation and freedom,'' King said, insisting that he would leave HBO after he fulfills his obligations to it, a Nov. 13 heavyweight extravaganza and a final Trinidad bout.</p>
        <p>''I'm a homeless promoter,'' he said.</p>
        <p>King accused the HBO analyst Larry Merchant of trying to ''denigrate and disparage'' Zab Judah, who pummeled Wayne Martell into a first-round technical knockout Saturday night; of being purposely ignored by HBO in postfight interviews; of having his fight cards inadequately promoted by HBO; and of paying meager attention to Hopkins until he was no longer promoting him.</p>
        <p>''I'm serving notice that I won't be on HBO anymore,'' King said, then adding that he could still do business with HBO, even match Trinidad with Hopkins (''Just because I don't like Bernard doesn't mean I wouldn't want to make millions off him''), but he would accept nothing solely on the word of its executives, including Ross Greenburg, president of HBO Sports, who he said is ''not the boss'' of the network's sports division.</p>
        <p>King has feuded publicly with HBO before, most notably when he took Mike Tyson to Showtime in the late 1980's, in part because of remarks by Merchant. A decade later, when King returned to HBO, he stood in the lobby of the network's building and exclaimed, ''I have returned to the land of Abraham,'' a reference to Greenburg's predecessor, Seth Abraham.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, Merchant told Judah after the bout that Martell was not much of an opponent, which was enough to rile King.</p>
        <p>''And as soon as Tito said my name, they cut him off,'' King said.</p>
        <p>Greenburg said yesterday that he must treat King with ''tough love.''</p>
        <p>''I don't understand why he lets his ego get out of control and why he feels he needs to run HBO's boxing programming,'' Greenburg said. ''He just needs to put together good shows, sell them to us and enjoy the fruits of his labors.'' He added, ''We do more for Don King than any promoter.''</p>
        <p>BOXING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
