<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>AUTOS ON MONDAY/Collecting; Shaped in Europe, Powered by Detroit</title>
    <meta content="04CARS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/10/04/automobiles/04CARS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1616421"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="Collecting"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Detroit (Mich)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Europe</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matras, John</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles/Topics/Automobile Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Detroit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041004T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EFDB1138F937A35753C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1225" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>AUTOS ON MONDAY/Collecting; Shaped in Europe, Powered by Detroit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Shaped in Europe, Powered by Detroit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN MATRAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Matras, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John Matras Autos On Monday/Collecting column discussing vintage automobiles that combine design attributes from Europe with engines made in Detroit (Mich); photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>HYBRID cars, such a hot topic this year, may not seem like such a new thing for those with long memories. But the hybrids they recall from the 1950's and 60's were not designed to save fuel and reduce air pollution.</p>
        <p>Back then, the term was applied to cars created by the coupling of sleek sporty bodies from England, France and Italy with big powerful engines from Detroit.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the 1960s, the divide between American and foreign cars was wide. But a few sports cars combined Detroit V-8s with sexy European styling to achieve the best of both worlds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>HYBRID cars, such a hot topic this year, may not seem like such a new thing for those with long memories. But the hybrids they recall from the 1950's and 60's were not designed to save fuel and reduce air pollution.</p>
        <p>Back then, the term was applied to cars created by the coupling of sleek sporty bodies from England, France and Italy with big powerful engines from Detroit.</p>
        <p>The intent of this ''one from column A and one from column B'' approach was to create a car that looked and performed far better than the comfortable but often clumsy American products of the era. American power and European lithe bodies seemed a perfect union, a match as complementary as Cary Grant and Ingrid Bergman in ''Indiscreet.''</p>
        <p>Among the hybrids that fit the term's former use are a number with the sort of memorable shapes and limited production numbers that qualify them as desired collectibles. To many owners of these cars, however, there is an equally important attraction: they can be driven daily with the comfort of knowing that, if necessary, basic repairs can often be done by Mr. Goodwrench, using a widely available generator or carburetor from Pep Boys.</p>
        <p>Officiating at one of the early trans-Atlantic marriages was Sydney Allard, a British racer and independent sports car builder. Though the Allard Motor Company made several four-seat models with British Ford engines after World War II, the company is probably best remembered for the Allard J2, an aluminum-body two-seater. Introduced in 1949, it was powered by a V-8 engine from -- take your pick -- Cadillac, Chrysler or Mercury. Allards were fast and they won races, despite a reputation for treacherous high-speed handling.</p>
        <p>Among the Americans who saw the wisdom of Allard's plan was Briggs Swift Cunningham II, a wealthy sportsman who raced his own all-American sports cars at the Le Mans 24-hour race in the early 50's. To qualify as an automaker for the race organizers, Mr. Cunningham commissioned Vignale, a coachbuilder in Italy, to build a run of elegant convertibles and fastback coupes for the street. Each of these cars, known as Cunningham C-3's, had Chrysler Hemi engines.</p>
        <p>Nash-Kelvinator, a predecessor of American Motors and maker of kitchen appliances based in Kenosha, Wis., teamed with Donald Healey, a British sports car pioneer, in 1951 to produce the Nash-Healey. The body came from Pinin Farina in Italy, the engine was a Nash Dual Jetfire 6 and the car was assembled in England. But the multinational effort did not enough attract enough attention and production ended in 1954.</p>
        <p>About the same time, Jean Daninos, a French industrialist whose company specialized in metal stamping, designed a coupe that he outfitted with powerful versions of the Chrysler Hemi. Though not well known, the Facel Vega coupes were considered great road cars -- and with up to 425 horsepower when production ended in 1964, they were fast, too.</p>
        <p>Some trans-Atlantic hybrids were created by transplanting American engines into existing cars. One of the most famous got its start when a racecar driver from Texas named Carroll Shelby shoehorned a 260-cubic-inch Ford V-8 into a small Ace sports car from A.C. Cars of England. The resulting hybrid, the Shelby Cobra, is still considered one of the most evocative cars ever produced.</p>
        <p>The Sunbeam Alpine, a pleasant sportster in the MG mien, underwent a similar transplant in the mid-60's to become the Sunbeam Tiger, with a Ford V-8 installed where a mild-mannered four-cylinder had been. More civilized than the Cobra, the Tiger was still far from boring to drive.</p>
        <p>Rob Guerra of Pleasanton, Calif., owner of several Sunbeam Tigers, met his future wife at an auto parts store and saw his first Tiger at her father's house. It has been love ever since. ''It's a fantastic car,'' Mr. Guerra said.</p>
        <p>Tigers, Mr. Guerra points out, have roll-up windows, a reasonably weather-tight convertible top, a functional heater and defroster and other comfort features lacking in a Cobra, making the Tiger more usable. And it is not too valuable to drive regularly.</p>
        <p>Jack Griffith, a New York Ford dealer, saw an opportunity in the TVR Grantura, a tiny British sports car, to become a Carroll Shelby of the East Coast. With its short wheelbase and pudgy fiberglass body, the car, renamed the Griffith 200, had its Ford V-8 practically in the driver's lap for a wild, unforgettable ride. ''I just like the way the British build a car,'' said Chris McArdle, a Griffith owner in Media, Pa. ''And I like the American engine.''</p>
        <p>In Italy, Renzo Rivolta used the hybrid formula to produce something of an alternative Ferrari. The Italian refrigerator magnate, who already had the tiny Isetta bubble car to his credit, had a two-door body designed by Giorgetto Giugiaro and built by Bertone. With a Corvette engine under the hood, the Iso Rivolta was successful enough to prompt several follow-ups, including the beautiful Iso Grifo.</p>
        <p>''It's good old American torque,'' said Howard Turnley of Oakland, Calif., who has owned both Rivoltas and Grifos. Indeed, the Iso Rivolta produces the same mechanical sensations -- in particular, the bellowing V-8 -- as a mid-60's Corvette.</p>
        <p>In 1953, the new Jensen 541 was powered by a big Austin in-line 6, but 10 years later it got a 331-cubic-inch Chrysler V-8. The next all-new Jensen, the Interceptor of 1967, was a striking 2+2 easily identified by a huge round rear window that lifted up.</p>
        <p>Designed by Touring of Italy, it was powered by a Chrysler 383. The FF version was equipped with four-wheel drive, and a Chrysler 440 V-8 became available in some models.</p>
        <p>Compared with other Detroit-powered Europeans, few of which were sold in the showrooms of mainstream automakers, the DeTomaso Pantera was easy to find -- as close as the local Lincoln Mercury dealer. Arriving in the United States as the government was imposing stricter safety and emissions rules, the Pantera resulted from a liaison between Ford and Alejandro DeTomaso, a racer-turned-automaker. Styled by Ghia and fitted with a 351-cubic-inch Ford V-8 in the middle of the car, the Pantera made its debut in 1971.</p>
        <p>Like many cars of the era, the Pantera could not comply with new American bumper regulations and by 1974 Ford had stopped importation.</p>
        <p>Subsequent attempts in the 1980's to meld Continental charm with American muscle, like the Cadillac Allanté or the Chrysler TC by Maserati, have usually missed the point. Except for a handful of models built in very small numbers, the 1950's concept of a hybrid has given way to the clean-living gasoline-electric combinations of today.</p>
        <p>Collecting</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
