<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Goss Set Back by Mishap During Yacht's Maiden Trials</title>
    <meta content="02BOAT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1188824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THE BOATING REPORT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goss, Pete</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Herb</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Boating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boats and Boating</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9800E5D6113CF931A35757C0A9669C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Goss Set Back by Mishap During Yacht's Maiden Trials</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERB McCORMICK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mccormick, Herb</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Section of British adventure sailor Pete Goss's new 120-foot catamaran, Team Philips, breaks off during maiden trials; he comments after boat is towed to port, phone interview; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the British adventure sailor Pete Goss, the month of March will be remembered for highs and lows of kingly proportions. Just over two weeks ago, Goss's radical new 120-foot catamaran, Team Philips -- a craft embodying Brittania's fervent wish to once again rule the waves -- was christened and blessed by Queen Elizabeth II in an emotional ceremony in the heart of London.</p>
        <p>But last Wednesday, in a cold, gray North Atlantic seaway, Goss's worst nightmares were realized when a 45-foot section of the spindly port bow cracked off like an icicle dangling from a sill, on the third day of the boat's maiden trials. Suddenly, Goss had a royal problem on his hands.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the British adventure sailor Pete Goss, the month of March will be remembered for highs and lows of kingly proportions. Just over two weeks ago, Goss's radical new 120-foot catamaran, Team Philips -- a craft embodying Brittania's fervent wish to once again rule the waves -- was christened and blessed by Queen Elizabeth II in an emotional ceremony in the heart of London.</p>
        <p>But last Wednesday, in a cold, gray North Atlantic seaway, Goss's worst nightmares were realized when a 45-foot section of the spindly port bow cracked off like an icicle dangling from a sill, on the third day of the boat's maiden trials. Suddenly, Goss had a royal problem on his hands.</p>
        <p>''There was a very loud bang,'' the 38-year-old former marine said in a telephone interview from St. Mary's in the Scilly Isles, the port to which he, his five-man crew and his crippled sailboat had been towed after the incident. In typical understatement, he added, ''We found that the port bow had a major structural problem and was starting to work itself off.''</p>
        <p>This, of course, was not supposed to happen to a boat that was scheduled to undertake not one but two round-the-world voyages over the next several months. First, Goss had planned an imminent assault on the so-called Jules Verne record for the fastest circumnavigation, which is currently just over 71 days. But that trip was viewed as a mere warm-up for Goss's entry in The Race, the fully crewed, nonstop, around-the-world competition waged with no limits on the size of boat or crew. That race will begin from Barcelona, Spain, on Dec. 31.</p>
        <p>The record attempt is now out of the question. But Goss vows that he will be on the starting line for The Race. ''We didn't hit anything,'' Goss said. ''It's something to do with the structure or the manufacture. We need to distill it down to that kernel of truth as to what happened. I feel confident we can resolve it.''</p>
        <p>Goss has gotten into tight jams before. In a desperate feat during the 1996-97 Vendee Globe single-handed race around the world, he turned around and sailed 160 miles into the teeth of hurricane-force winds to rescue a French skipper, Raphael Dinelli, whose boat was sinking. For his heroics, Goss was awarded the Medal of the British Empire and the Legion d'Honneur of France.</p>
        <p>The shakedown of Team Philips, named for the Netherlands-based electronics company bankrolling the roughly $4 million campaign, began far less dramatically. After setting out from Dartmouth on England's south coast, Goss tacked north for the Irish Sea on the first leg of what was planned as a five-day voyage.</p>
        <p>''We were making 21 knots with ease,'' Goss said. ''It was just fantastic, the boat was sailing like a dream.''</p>
        <p>Shortly after midnight last Wednesday morning, Team Philips jibed back toward Land's End at the mouth of the English Channel. Just after first light, with the boat cruising at 18 knots in a 20-knot northeasterly, Goss was off watch and in his bunk when he was awakened by the sound of splintering carbon fiber. The port bow was in critical condition, but the starboard bow had also incurred a serious crease.</p>
        <p>''All hands were called on deck in survival suits,'' Goss said. ''We let the mainsheets go and immediately depowered the boat, and then called the marine rescue control center. They immediately sent out a lifeboat and a helicopter.''</p>
        <p>Team Philips began limping towards the Scillys, some 30 miles to the south, under her own power. But the port bow parted ways with the vessel soon after, and the craft was then towed into St. Mary's. The missing piece was later recovered in a separate salvage operation. Last Friday, with its rudders removed, Team Philips was towed backward to Dartmouth, where further inspection awaited.</p>
        <p>With an all-up weight of just 44,000 pounds, a 70-foot beam, and twin, unstayed wing masts, the Adrian Thompson design is one of a handful of unlimited nautical projectiles setting course for The Race. At least two American boats are also planning to compete: Steve Fossett's PlayStation, which has also its share of work-up woes, and Cam Lewis's Team Adventure, currently under construction in France.</p>
        <p>''The good news, if there is such a thing, is that the damage on the starboard hull gives us a good indication of where the crack started,'' said Thompson. ''We believe both hulls failed in the same manner. We can't attempt a repair until we completely understand what caused the problem. Next time, this boat has got to be bulletproof.''</p>
        <p>Goss has managed to stay focused on the silver lining of the dark cloud obscuring his dream. ''In a funny way this has pulled us together,'' he said. ''It's easy when things are going well; the real measure is when you're at the bottom. Everyone's pulled tight as a knot and we're going forward.''</p>
        <p>THE BOATING REPORT Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Herb McCormick is the editor of Cruising World magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
