<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Home Video</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="566435"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (VIDEO)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">NICHOLS, PETER M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Video)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D7143FF93AA15753C1A964958260" item-length="1194" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Home Video</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter M. Nichols</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NICHOLS, PETER M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The release of Disney's "Beauty and the Beast" on tape tomorrow can be seen two ways by fans of laser disks. To help prevent pirating abroad, release of the movie on disk, which doesn't have the copying safeguards of tape, is being delayed. On the other hand, in its place Disney will release the disk of a film about the film called "Beauty and the Beast: The Work in Progress."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The release of Disney's "Beauty and the Beast" on tape tomorrow can be seen two ways by fans of laser disks. To help prevent pirating abroad, release of the movie on disk, which doesn't have the copying safeguards of tape, is being delayed. On the other hand, in its place Disney will release the disk of a film about the film called "Beauty and the Beast: The Work in Progress."</p>
        <p>The real thing is to be preferred, of course, but in a way the substitute points up the strengths of laser disk. The "Work in Progress," which was shown at the New York Film Festival last year, is itself an acclaimed film that gives a behind-the-scenes look at how the film was made.</p>
        <p>This is the sort of extra material disk owners want with their movies. "It really is a windfall," said Douglas Pratt, the editor of The Laser Disk Newsletter, a monthly publication of reviews and commentary about new laser disks. Information: (516) 594-9304.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pratt and other analysts note steady if unspectacular growth for laser disks this year. A new catalogue by Movies Unlimited of Philadelphia lists more than 7,000 disk titles (information: 800-466-8437). People in the industry estimate that there are nearly a million disk players in use and that 12 million disks will be sold this year. Disk rental, already offered by many smaller stores, is being explored by larger chains.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pratt said the biggest steps had been greater awareness and improved quality. "More film makers have become interested in disk and anxious to supervise the transfer to disk because of its potential as a format for collectors," he said.</p>
        <p>As recent examples of directors who have either completed or are working on laser editions of their films, he cited Martha Coolidge and "Rambling Rose," Danny DeVito and "War of the Roses" and James Cameron with "Aliens" and "The Abyss."</p>
        <p>The primary appeal of disk is superior picture and sound quality. "More studios are cognizant of the need of superior transfers, and quality has improved tremendously," Mr. Pratt said. "Disks that are done well sell better. In the past some companies didn't understand that. Now they do."</p>
        <p>One series that impresses him is "Chaplin: A Legacy of Laughter," a 10-disk set of Chaplin films and related materials to be released by CBS-Fox beginning next month. Each volume is $69.98.</p>
        <p>Such prices are sometimes called too high. Disks are generally $25 to $40, much more for special editions with extras like scripts, interviews and production notes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pratt says prices are about where they should be. "Higher-priced disks are generally those where producers have spent large amounts for excellent transfers and licensing costs for extra footage and other materials," he said.</p>
        <p>He also noted that some distributors have begun to lower the prices of some older films on disk to under $20, just as they have on tape. NEW VIDEO RELEASES Beauty and the Beast  1991. Disney. $24.99. 1 hour 30 minutes. Closed captioned. G.</p>
        <p>Using computer animation techniques, Disney's story of Belle and the Beast pays homage to the Broadway musical and bursts into another dimension. In an updated version of the story, the prettiest girl in town fends off the sexist golden boy in favor of something different. In the hands of Disney animators, the anthropomorphism of the characters takes on a spectacular scale. Spectacular, too, is the "witty, soaring musical score that is now virtually extinct on the stage," wrote Janet Maslin in The New York Times. Incident at Oglala  1992. LIVE. $89.98. Laser disk, $34.95. 1:30. CC. PG.</p>
        <p>In a companion piece to his fictional "Thunderheart," Michael Apted explores injustices on a Sioux reservation in Oglala, S.D. This film, a documentary narrated by Robert Redford, tells the story of Leonard Peltier, an Indian advocate found guilty of the murder of two F.B.I agents. As it questions Mr. Peltier's guilt, the earnest nonfictional account unfolds with none of the dramatic flair of its fictional counterpart. Still, it manages to make its points, if in a "simple and often arid style" (Maslin). Deep Cover  1992. New Line. $94.95. 1:52. CC. R.</p>
        <p>Intended as a police thriller, Bill Duke's film gets lost in its fascination with the viciousness and seamy glamour of the big-time drug world. Larry Fishburne goes undercover to break up a drug cartel and ends up committing most of the crimes he is sent to fight. Though the workings of the drug culture are portrayed effectively, the film is "less successful in separating the many strands of a deeply cynical and convoluted plot" (Maslin). Heart of Glass  1974. New Yorker. $79.95. 1:33. German with English subtitles. No rating.</p>
        <p>A medieval town that has thrived making ruby-colored glass is threatened with the loss of its livelihood when the one man who knows the formula dies. Attempts to restore prosperity drive the people mad, a state of mind the director Werner Herzog attempts to recreate by hypnotizing his actors. This does nothing to clarify much of the film, which remains virtually indecipherable, though "too mysteriously lovely to be regarded as a failure" (Maslin).  The Sleazy Uncle  1989. Triboro. $89.95. 1:44. Italian with English subtitles. No rating.</p>
        <p>Riccardo (Giancarlo Giannini) finds himself saddled with an uncle he never heard of (Vittorio Gassman). Not only does the old fellow stick him with hospital bills, but he seduces his mistress and purposely does everything he can to raise the nephew's hackles. There is a reason for all this, but Franco Brusati's film is better "when moving aimlessly than it is in arriving at its heart-tugging destination" (Maslin). FROM YEARS PAST  Laser Disk Best Sellers Mix the Old and the New</p>
        <p>Laser disk best sellers are a mix of older films and new movies that are also high on tape best-renter lists. Here are some disks from both categories in the top 25 on the current Billboard list.</p>
        <p>FRIED GREEN TOMATOES. (No. 1) Jon Avnet's film about life and friendship in a small Southern town stars Mary Stuart Masterson, Mary-Louise Parker, Jessica Tandy and Kathy Bates. 1991. MCA/ Universal. $39.98. 2 hours 10 minutes. PG-13.</p>
        <p>RAIDERS OF THE LOST ARK. (No. 3) This 1981 Indiana Jones action saga (1:55, PG) is accompanied on the list by its two sequels: "Indiana Jones and the Temple of Doom" (1984, 1:58, PG) at No. 5 and "Indiana Jones and the Last Crusade" (1989, 2:06, PG-13) at No. 22. All are from Paramount and are $24.95 each.</p>
        <p>THE LAWNMOWER MAN. (No. 4) Video-gamelike special effects spice Brett Leonard's film, based on a Stephen King story about a young man (Jeff Fahey) with delusions of ruling the world. New Line. $34.95. 1:48. No rating.</p>
        <p>MEDICINE MAN. (No. 6) John McTiernan's film about a scientist (Sean Connery) who finds a cure for cancer has spectacular jungle settings. 1992. Hollywood. $39.99. 1:45. PG-13.</p>
        <p>EXCALIBUR. (No. 17) John Boorman's film about the Arthurian legend stars Nicol Williamson, Nigel Terry and Helen Mirren, among others. 1981. Warner. $39.98. 2:20. PG.</p>
        <p>AMERICAN ME. (No. 18) Edward James Olmos's film explores Los Angeles gang violence. 1992. MCA/Universal. $39.98. 2:05. CC. R.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
