<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Candidate Perot Might Learn From Strategist Perot</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="566332"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1992 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLMES, STEVEN A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, ROSS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0D81138F93AA15753C1A964958260" item-length="908" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Candidate Perot Might Learn From Strategist Perot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN A. HOLMES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HOLMES, STEVEN A</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS, Oct. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Looking at the way he has planned his campaign, almost any candidate would long to have Ross Perot as a campaign manager. But few handlers would like to have him as a candidate.</p>
        <p>As a tactician, Mr. Perot has devised a campaign strategy that focuses a strong, clear message on the economy and using his vast financial resources to get that message out through paid advertising. At the same time he has minimized his weaknesses, limiting time on the stump where he can be a rambling, awkward speaker and, for the most part, keeping away from reporters who tend to draw out his white-hot temper.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Looking at the way he has planned his campaign, almost any candidate would long to have Ross Perot as a campaign manager. But few handlers would like to have him as a candidate.</p>
        <p>As a tactician, Mr. Perot has devised a campaign strategy that focuses a strong, clear message on the economy and using his vast financial resources to get that message out through paid advertising. At the same time he has minimized his weaknesses, limiting time on the stump where he can be a rambling, awkward speaker and, for the most part, keeping away from reporters who tend to draw out his white-hot temper.</p>
        <p>As a candidate, however, he ignited a distracting controversy with accusations that Republican operatives sought to besmirch his daughter Carolyn and disrupt her wedding.</p>
        <p>In addition, he has allowed himself to become the flame that attracts the likes of Scott Barnes, a proponent of unsubstantiated tales of worldwide conspiracies, who drew Mr. Perot into an unseemly attempt to entrap a top Texas Republican. Erring With Flair</p>
        <p>Indeed, at times there seems to be two Ross Perots.</p>
        <p>"He's a good strategist and tactician," said Frank I. Luntz, a poll taker who worked for Mr. Perot in the first phase of his campaign. "He's got about a 90 percent success rate. The best political strategists have about a 70 percent success rate. But the problem is that the 1 in 10 mistake is usually big."</p>
        <p>Even associates of Mr. Perot acknowledge that his interview on "60 Minutes," where he made the assertions of Republican "dirty tricks," and his surprise appearance at a news conference here on Monday, where he repeated the accusations, were errors that a smart campaign manager would not have allowed to occur.</p>
        <p>Yet it is difficult to separate Ross Perot the campaign manager from Ross Perot the candidate. Moreover, even when Mr. Perot had veteran political strategists like Edward J. Rollins and Hamilton Jordan advising him, the strong-willed billionaire did not listen to them. Sure-Footed Ad Campaign</p>
        <p>When Mr. Perot got back into the race, many political professionals felt that without seasoned political strategists to advise him, he would fall flat on his face. He did not.</p>
        <p>In the 28 days since his return Mr. Perot has done a masterly job in rehabilitating his image and clawing his way back into the Presidential race. His commercials have created enough of a sense of urgency over the national debt to make a vote for an independent candidate seem perhaps the only way to avert a crisis. His half-hour programs on the economy, complete with charts, seem authentic and appealing to voters weary of the mudslinging of the other candidates.</p>
        <p>He injected himself into the three Presidential debates, where he seemed a refreshingly unrehearsed alternative to President Bush and Gov. Bill Clinton. And he has spent $34.8 million on advertising, broadcasting many of his commercials during sports events like the World Series and Monday Night Football. These shows not only have high ratings, but their audience is primarily men, a group more receptive to Mr. Perot's can-do image.</p>
        <p>"During the month of October, he moved from 7 percent to 20 percent in the polls, and his negatives continued to fall," Mr. Luntz said. "That's the biggest run in such a short time that any independent candidate has ever had."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Perot the tactician, has, at times, been tripped up by Mr. Perot the candidate. His biggest mistake may have occurred over the weekend, when he publicly asserted that the Republicans were plotting against his daughter and planning to wiretap his telephones. Distracting From Message</p>
        <p>The story about his daughter, for which he has yet to offer any proof, may have helped him with some voters by banishing the image of Mr. Perot as a quitter who abruptly left the race in July because he could not take the heat. Here is a man, some voters may reason, who was willing to give up his goal to protect his family.</p>
        <p>But by not coming forward with corroboration from a credible source, Mr. Perot not only risks his own veracity, he reinforces the image of a man willing to make seemingly wild accusations on the slimmest of evidence.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perot's involvement in an undercover operation to offer stolen information to Jim Oberwetter, head of the Bush campaign in Texas, also creates an image of a man who would stop at nothing to destroy a political rival. "He talks about his family," an indignant Mr. Oberwetter said today. "I have one, too. And my three daughters don't want to see their daddy in jail."</p>
        <p>The charges and countercharges have also shifted the focus of the Dallas billionaire's campaign away from his core economic message. In recent days Mr. Perot's aides have vainly tried to turn news stories back to the issues. Nonetheless, his rise in the polls appears to have stalled.</p>
        <p>Ross Perot the strategist seems to have gauged well the public mood. He has discerned that many voters have become fed up with the usual brand of incumbents and blow-dried candidates. Even as he obfuscates, he has created an aura of himself as a straight-shooter who speaks his mind. But as a candidate, he doesn't seem to know, or seems incapable of knowing when to stop.</p>
        <p>"It has a lot to do with when he uses his head or uses his heart," said Mr. Luntz. "When Ross Perot uses his head, he's unbeatable. He's focused, straightforward and compelling. When he uses his heart, sometimes his emotions get carried away."  THE 1992 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
