<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Name Is Howard, The Game Is Magic</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="483308"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOWARD, DESMOND</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4DE153DF93BA15753C1A967958260" item-length="776" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Name Is Howard, The Game Is Magic</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY,</byline>
      <dateline>MINNEAPOLIS, Oct. 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There are few events that could take Minnesotans' minds off the World Series. Maybe an appearance by Prince would do it, or some magical words from Garrison Keillor.</p>
        <p>A 21-year-old whippet from Cleveland with no baseball background and no connection to the state is not supposed to dominate discussions on a chilly October evening. Not when the World Series is in town. But last Friday night at the Metrodome, the whippet was Desmond Howard and the event was watching him with a football. The Michigan receiver and kick returner can seemingly do anything he wants. Teammates call him Magic.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There are few events that could take Minnesotans' minds off the World Series. Maybe an appearance by Prince would do it, or some magical words from Garrison Keillor.</p>
        <p>A 21-year-old whippet from Cleveland with no baseball background and no connection to the state is not supposed to dominate discussions on a chilly October evening. Not when the World Series is in town. But last Friday night at the Metrodome, the whippet was Desmond Howard and the event was watching him with a football. The Michigan receiver and kick returner can seemingly do anything he wants. Teammates call him Magic.</p>
        <p>While the baseball players rested for a day from their run at the Series title, Howard staged his continuous sprint to the Heisman Trophy by scoring two touchdowns in Michigan's 52-6 thrashing of Minnesota. The 5-foot-9-inch, 176-pound Howard is no rock idol, no storyteller. But he may be the best college player since the Rocket was launched last year -- and Raghib Ismail never pocketed touchdowns like Howard.</p>
        <p>"I just love to hear the crowd ooh and aah when I get the ball," said Howard, who broke Anthony Carter's Big Ten and Michigan records by boosting his season touchdown reception total to 15 Friday. "I love to hear the hush as the ball comes to me and then the roar when I take off."</p>
        <p>Although he is likely to become the first Michigan player since Tom Harmon in 1940 to win the Heisman, Howard is more than a football hero. He is an engaging young man who ends conversations with "Peace" and answers his phone saying "Magic." The flower child with a fade haircut wears ties to class every day and has posters of Malcolm X and Martin Luther King on his wall. No Smoking or Drinking</p>
        <p>"He is an individual and he's got his own ideas," said the Michigan coach, Gary Moeller. "I think that is part of what motivates him."</p>
        <p>Howard is a loner who likes to laugh. To concentrate on his studies, he lives by himself in Ann Arbor in an off-campus apartment, but he is never far from the latest gag.</p>
        <p>He said he does not smoke or drink because "I do not give in to peer pressure." He is the type of person who not only grants an interview to a 10-year-old reporter, but offers advice to the boy on how to ask proper questions.</p>
        <p>"That," said Bruce Madej, a Michigan assistant athletic director, "is just Desmond."</p>
        <p>And when Desmond is just being Desmond on the football field, it is a gorgeous sight. He scores a touchdown every fourth time he touches the ball. Count the receptions, count the kickoff returns because he is bound to score soon. Just watch. Howard has scored at least two touchdowns in 10 straight games. He has scored 102 of Michigan's 254 points this season.</p>
        <p>"After the way Desmond ran from our defensive backs, I would definitely vote for him for the Heisman," said Minnesota Coach John Gutekunst.</p>
        <p>And what does Desmond think?</p>
        <p>"I know it is attainable, but I still have not set it as a goal," he said. "I want to be the best college player I can be so I guess they go hand in hand." 'We've Come a Long Way'</p>
        <p>Howard is not amazingly fast, just amazingly exciting. He has superb acceleration, navigates precise routes, knows where the ball is supposed to be and catches it. Howard always catches it.</p>
        <p>"I just throw it into his area and he gets it," said quarterback Elvis Grbac, who attended St. Joseph High School in Cleveland with Howard. "They put single coverage on Desmond and when you see that your eyes light up."</p>
        <p>Michigan, never a true passing team under Bo Schembechler, has a veritable passing fancy with Howard and Grbac as weapons. The two paired for only one touchdown in high school because Howard was a tailback and Grbac did not start until he was a senior.</p>
        <p>"We've come a long way," Howard said with great understatement.</p>
        <p>The Heisman talk has fueled speculation that Howard will walk into the National Football League if he wins the coveted award. Howard has another season of eligibility after this one because he did not play as a freshman in 1988, but he should earn his degree in May.</p>
        <p>He insists he wants to attend graduate school and stay at Michigan. If Howard snares the Heisman, will he stay in Ann Arbor? It is doubtful. School insiders say that if that happens, his days at Michigan will be over. Howard will not decide until after the Rose Bowl, which Michigan (6-1) hopes to make and win.</p>
        <p>Tell Howard it would be shocking if he won the Heisman and did not jump to the N.F.L. and he smiles another version of his smile, throws his head back and talks about maybe winning two Heismans. Then he offers you his can of soda and, Heisman or not, it is easy to surmise how special he really is.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
