<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Tired Cardinals Tap a Reserve to Win Game 1</title>
    <meta content="22series" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/22/sports/baseball/22series.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1798917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/St Louis Cardinals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E2DF173FF931A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1211" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Tired Cardinals Tap a Reserve to Win Game 1</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Tired Cardinals Tap a Reserve to Win Game 1</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TYLER KEPNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kepner, Tyler</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Oct. 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anthony Reyes made his first start this season at a place called Bricktown Ballpark in Oklahoma City, against a team called the RedHawks. He gave up nine hits and his team lost.</p>
        <p>Reyes was not the preferred choice for the St. Louis Cardinals in Game 1 of the World Series on Saturday. He had not won in 47 days, and his five regular-season victories were the fewest for a Game 1 starter in 77 years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rookie Anthony Reyes pitched into the ninth inning, retiring 17 Tigers in a row from the first to the seventh in the Cardinals’ first victory in the World Series since 1987.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anthony Reyes made his first start this season at a place called Bricktown Ballpark in Oklahoma City, against a team called the RedHawks. He gave up nine hits and his team lost.</p>
        <p>Reyes was not the preferred choice for the St. Louis Cardinals in Game 1 of the World Series on Saturday. He had not won in 47 days, and his five regular-season victories were the fewest for a Game 1 starter in 77 years.</p>
        <p>But Reyes was rested, unlike the other Cardinals starters, so there he was on the mound at Comerica Park, hunching over from the windup, looking in for the signs and pumping strike after strike.</p>
        <p>''I tried not to worry about it being the World Series or anything,'' Reyes said. ''Just focus on the mitt.''</p>
        <p>With his socks pulled high and his brim flat above his eyebrows -- better to see the signs, he said -- Reyes pitched into the ninth inning in a 7-2 victory. Scott Rolen and Albert Pujols homered to help the Cardinals to their first victory in the World Series since 1987.</p>
        <p>For the Tigers, the loss brought an end to a seven-game winning streak and a week of rest following their sweep in the American League Championship Series.</p>
        <p>''Nobody felt the layoff was that bad,'' said the Tigers' Craig Monroe, who homered on the first pitch of the ninth to chase Reyes. ''We're not going to make any excuses.''</p>
        <p>Yet the Tigers could not explain how Reyes, without an overpowering fastball, handled them so easily. Reyes threw almost all fastballs after the first inning, taking a suggestion from the pitching coach Dave Duncan, and he rarely missed a spot.</p>
        <p>He was a marvel of efficiency, throwing only 90 pitches and allowing four hits and a walk with four strikeouts. From the last out of the first inning to the first out of the seventh, he retired 17 Tigers in a row. It was the longest such streak in the World Series since Cincinnati's José Rijo set down 20 Oakland hitters in 1990.</p>
        <p>''He was spotting his fastball, getting up early on us,'' said Sean Casey, who was 0 for 3. ''I don't know -- we kept popping him up. We couldn't get a bead on him all night.''</p>
        <p>The Cardinals are the most decorated franchise in the National League, with nine championships, but they have gone 24 years since their last. It is the longest drought ever for the Cardinals, who have recent demons to slay.</p>
        <p>Two years ago against Boston, the Cardinals lost perhaps the most lopsided World Series ever. They never held a lead in a four-game sweep, and their sluggers deserted them. Rolen went 0 for 15 and Pujols never drove in a run.</p>
        <p>Three innings into Game 1, the Cardinals had already had a better series: Rolen had a hit, Pujols had a run batted in and St. Louis had a lead.</p>
        <p>''Who cares about 2004?'' Pujols said. ''That was then, this is now. We didn't think, 'Oh man, we struggled in 2004.' We care about Game 1, and what can we do to win the game tonight.''</p>
        <p>What they did was take advantage of Tigers starter Justin Verlander, a rookie with a better résumé than Reyes. Since the start of the regular season, Verlander was 19-9. He threw 100 miles an hour against the Yankees in the division series.</p>
        <p>But his velocity was down Saturday -- ''I don't know,'' he explained. ''Late in the year?'' -- and he quickly lost a 1-0 first-inning lead.</p>
        <p>Rolen came up with one out in the second and drove a 90-mile-an-hour fastball high over left field. It was a telling swing for Rolen, whose left shoulder -- the lead shoulder in his swing -- needed a cortisone shot before the championship series.</p>
        <p>The Mets held Rolen without an run batted in during that series, though left fielder Endy Chávez had to scale the left-field wall to pull back a homer in Game 7. There was no hauling in this ball: it sailed into the bleachers for a homer that tied the score, 1-1.</p>
        <p>''I wanted to see how he was handling that pitch tonight,'' Verlander said of Rolen. ''I really didn't get a chance to see how he was handling it, because the first pitch in there was a home run.''</p>
        <p>Verlander was one out away from escaping the third inning with the same 1-1 score. But two bad pitches led to three runs. With Yadier Molina on second and two out, Chris Duncan doubled down the right-field line to score a run.</p>
        <p>That pitch was a high changeup, and Verlander's next one, to Pujols, was a high 93-m.p.h.-fastball over the outside part of the plate. Pujols drove it into the seats in right center for a two-run homer.</p>
        <p>With two outs and a base open, Verlander had allowed the best hitter in the lineup -- the best hitter in the majors, perhaps -- to put his team in a 4-1 hole. Verlander smirked on the mound.</p>
        <p>''I missed my spot -- a couple of inches up, a couple of inches over,'' he said. ''But it was still almost off the plate.''</p>
        <p>The Mets had walked Pujols intentionally four times in the N.L.C.S. Jim Leyland, the Tigers' manager, pitched to Pujols and paid.</p>
        <p>''I'm not going to get into a lot of explanation about what the thinking was,'' Leyland said. ''But I take the bullet there, and if somebody gives criticism, you accept it, because ultimately, it's my decision. I'll take the heat for that.''</p>
        <p>Asked if he expected to be walked, Pujols dismissed the question.</p>
        <p>''That's not the way I think,'' he said. ''I'm thinking about seeing the ball and putting a good swing on it. If they don't want to pitch, I take my walk.''</p>
        <p>He did that in the sixth, when Verlander walked him to lead off the inning. Pujols is no threat to steal, but Verlander fired a wild pickoff throw that put him at third.</p>
        <p>A single scored him, and two more runs scored on a grounder to third baseman Brandon Inge, who threw wildly to the plate to allow Jim Edmonds to score and then blocked Rolen's path home. Inge was charged with two errors.</p>
        <p>The score was 7-1 by then, plenty of run support for Reyes, who lasted four innings in his start against the Mets, when the Cardinals believed he was tipping his pitches. On Saturday, when Reyes thought the Tigers were onto his changeup, he stopped throwing it.</p>
        <p>''It's just a mind game,'' he said. ''I just tried to go to a good mix. Just tried to not throw the ball to the same spot more than a couple of times, tried to give them a different eye level, different speeds -- do something.''</p>
        <p>Reyes did plenty, exceeding his team's expectations. At dinner Friday, Cardinals Manager Tony La Russa asked his coaches to predict how Reyes would do. Two said they expected him to reach the eighth inning. La Russa was more realistic.</p>
        <p>''I thought if he went five or six, with low runs, that he had done a great job,'' La Russa said. ''But he doesn't scare. He's got great composure and he gets it rolling.''</p>
        <p>The Cardinals were rolling right along with him, and 2004 seems long ago.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
