<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Injury Inspires a Push to Limit Metal Bats in New Jersey</title>
    <meta content="22bat" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="37" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/22/nyregion/22bat.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1798854"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball Bats</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schweber, Nate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950CE2D7163FF931A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="991" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Injury Inspires a Push to Limit Metal Bats in New Jersey</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ball Field Injury Spurs Push to Limit Metal Bats in New Jersey</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NATE SCHWEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schweber, Nate</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, N.J., Oct. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Assembly committee passes bill banning metal, titanium and composite bats from league baseball and softball games played by children 17 and under, including those on high school teams; proponents testify about young players injured because of metal bats; opponents say use of wooden bats would put New Jersey teams at disadvantages playing out-of-state teams and would discourage youngsters from taking up game; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Joseph Domalewski fought back tears as he told a legislative committee just how his son's heart stopped after he was hit by a line drive in a baseball game this summer.</p>
        <p>He said the boy's life might be different today if only the hitter had used a bat made of wood rather than metal, which he believes would have slowed the speed of the ball.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A proposed bill would ban metal bats from league baseball and softball games played by children 17 and younger.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Joseph Domalewski fought back tears as he told a legislative committee just how his son's heart stopped after he was hit by a line drive in a baseball game this summer.</p>
        <p>He said the boy's life might be different today if only the hitter had used a bat made of wood rather than metal, which he believes would have slowed the speed of the ball.</p>
        <p>''A split second would've probably had him home with a bruised shoulder,'' Mr. Domalewski said of his 13-year-old son, Steven Domalewski, who suffered brain damage from going out without oxygen for too long and now cannot see or talk, and is now at Children's Specialized Hospital in Mountainside, N.J.</p>
        <p>Steven's injury, which occurred in a Police Athletic League game in June, is the inspiration behind a bill that passed the Assembly Law and Public Safety Committee by a 4-to-2 vote on Thursday, but still needs Senate and Assembly approval.</p>
        <p>The bill would ban metal, titanium and composite bats from league baseball and softball games played by children 17 and younger, including those on high school teams.</p>
        <p>It would be the first statewide ban of its scope in the country, although, beginning next year, metal bats will be banned in all North Dakota high school games.</p>
        <p>Some high schools in Illinois and all Catholic high schools in Massachusetts have also switched to wooden bats.</p>
        <p>''I've never felt so strongly about anything,'' said Assemblyman Patrick J. Diegnan, a Democrat from Middlesex County who sponsored the legislation in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>The Assembly bill is similar to a measure scheduled to be debated on Monday by the New York City Council's Youth Services Committee, which also would ban metal bats in youth baseball and softball games.</p>
        <p>That measure was sponsored by Councilman James S. Oddo, a Republican, who also cites the injury to Steven as well as to other children over the years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Oddo, who held a hearing in the New York City Council in 2002 in an effort to ban metal bats, likened Mr. Diegnan's effort to the story of David and Goliath. ''He's up against an industry that is well-financed and well-represented,'' Mr. Oddo said to the New Jersey panel.</p>
        <p>Opponents of the New Jersey measure include some university and high school coaches, the chief executives of Little League, P.O.N.Y. baseball and softball, and Babe Ruth leagues, representatives from American Legion baseball and a manufacturer of metal bats.</p>
        <p>They say banning metal bats would put New Jersey teams at a disadvantage when playing out-of-state teams because the New Jersey players would not be used to playing with the metal bats. The bill allows metal bats to be used in games played with teams visiting New Jersey.</p>
        <p>In addition, Brian Giallella, the head baseball coach at Steinert High School in Hamilton Township, said taking metal bats out of the hands of young players could discourage them from playing, because it is harder to make good contact with a wooden bat.</p>
        <p>''How can you take our national pastime and make its numbers decrease?'' Mr. Giallella asked.</p>
        <p>Scott Bradley, Princeton University's head baseball coach and a former major leaguer, said banning metal bats would put average and below-average players at a disadvantage on the field and when competing for scholarships.</p>
        <p>But Norm Schoenig, the head baseball coach at Montclair State University, disagreed, telling lawmakers that banning metal bats would force young players to develop their abilities and provide an easier transition into the minor leagues, which use wooden bats.</p>
        <p>The opponents also disputed claims about the dangers posed by metal bats.</p>
        <p>Stephen D. Keener, president and chief executive of Little League Baseball International, said that statistics did not suggest a need to ban the bats.</p>
        <p>Mr. Keener told the panel that according to his organization's insurance provider, a record 145 Little League pitchers were injured by batted balls in 1992, the year the league adopted a rule that metal bats could be used only if they were manufactured in such a way that there was an ''almost insignificant difference'' between the speeds of a ball hit with metal and wooden bats.</p>
        <p>As a result, he said, the number of Little League pitchers reported injured by hit balls had dropped to 19 by 2002.</p>
        <p>And Jim Darby, vice president of promotions and public relations for Easton, a manufacturer of metal bats, testified that his company adhered to standards set by organizations like Little League, which require them to have characteristics comparable to wooden bats.</p>
        <p>''If a ball is hit on the sweet spot, it's coming off at the same speed'' as if it were hit on the sweet spot of a wooden bat, Mr. Darby told the panel.</p>
        <p>But John Della Volpe of Concord, Mass. -- whose 11-year-old son, Andrew, had his nose crushed by a line drive off a metal bat in May -- cited a 2002 Brown University study to dispute Mr. Darby's assertion.</p>
        <p>In the Brown study, young ballplayers hit more than 1,000 pitches from a machine using two brands of wooden bats and five brands of metal bats. Balls coming off the fastest bat, a metal one, went an average of 93.3 miles per hour, while those hit by the slowest bat, a wooden one, went 86.1 m.p.h. In addition, 37 percent of the balls hit with metal bats traveled more than 100 m.p.h., compared with 2 percent of the balls hit with wooden bats.</p>
        <p>''Every mile an hour makes a difference,'' Mr. Della Volpe said. ''If a kid with a wooden bat hit Andrew, there's no question in my mind he would've had time to react.''</p>
        <p>Joseph Domalewski agreed. His son still shows minimal response to stimuli, though he has recently started to chew and swallow food. ''He's got a long road ahead of him, and no one can give us an answer what the final outcome will be,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In the back row of the hearing room, Steven's mother, Nancy Domalewski, wept softly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
