<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Relentless SUNY Downsizing Means Loss of Quality Education</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="796224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">STATE UNIVERSITY OF NEW YORK (SUNY)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SCHEUERMAN, WILLIAM E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951010T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E5DC1339F933A25753C1A963958260" item-length="339" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Relentless SUNY Downsizing Means Loss of Quality Education</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The State University of New York's latest proposal to reduce its costs (news  article, Oct. 4) again hits two groups in the university community that have been under attack for months: students and faculty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>The State University of New York's latest proposal to reduce its costs (news  article, Oct. 4) again hits two groups in the university community that have been under attack for months: students and faculty.</p>
        <p>Administrators want to end remedial education at the four-year colleges, charge higher tuition for students who can't get through programs in the required time and jam more students into already overcrowded classrooms. Add to this a proposed reduction in faculty, and you have a less affordable, less accessible educational experience for those who remain behind.</p>
        <p>More students can't complete their degree programs in four years because they are shut out of the courses they require for graduation. Hundreds of courses and thousands of classes have been eliminated throughout the system in the past decade because of a steady erosion of state support for SUNY.</p>
        <p>Several thousand SUNY employees have lost their jobs; we're down more than 700 just from last year. Students are lining up to take courses that are already chock full, if they exist at all anymore.</p>
        <p>Yet instead of addressing this serious problem, SUNY proposes to penalize these students by nearly tripling their tuition. And what timing! SUNY students  are just now coming to grips with the largest tuition increase in the university's history, while trustees are already making noises about another increase.</p>
        <p>Many SUNY campuses are already close to the maximum students they can safely  allow in a classroom. Increasing class size may not be permitted by law. Will trustees fork over the millions to bring campus classroom buildings up to code?</p>
        <p>A university's vision should not be driven by statistical averages or fiscal  bottom lines. SUNY appears to be undertaking an exercise simply to downsize, and reports are being developed to meet a predetermined conclusion.</p>
        <p>WILLIAM E. SCHEUERMAN Pres., United University Professions Albany, Oct. 4, 1995</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
