<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Fragonard Came to Met</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="115396"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART SHOWS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCGILL, DOUGLAS C</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRAGONARD, JEAN HONORE (1732-1806)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DB133BF930A35751C0A96E948260" item-length="940" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Fragonard Came to Met</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOUGLAS C. McGILL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MCGILL, DOUGLAS C</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In the Jean-Honore Fragonard exhibition that opens this Saturday at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, both the artist and the museum have done their magic. The show radiates color, clarity and completeness of design, and the paintings hang like seemingly inevitable expressions in a seemingly permanent home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In the Jean-Honore Fragonard exhibition that opens this Saturday at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, both the artist and the museum have done their magic. The show radiates color, clarity and completeness of design, and the paintings hang like seemingly inevitable expressions in a seemingly permanent home.</p>
        <p>In the Jean-Honore Fragonard exhibition that opens this Saturday at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, both the artist and the museum have done their magic. The show radiates color, clarity and completeness of design, and the paintings hang like seemingly inevitable expressions in a seemingly permanent home.</p>
        <p>Yet there is a story that this sense of timelessness, so familiar to exhibitions at the Met, does not tell: the story of the creative give and take, the scholarly sleuthing, the hard bargains and the tender pleas, the starts and stops from both a logistical and an art-historical point of view, that form the history of the show.</p>
        <p>From a tactical standpoint, the challenges began with the fact that Fragonard's oeuvre was distributed among a huge number of museum and private collections. In the present show, of the approximately 220 paintings and drawings, around 30 came from the Louvre, 10 from the Met and the rest from museums and private collections that literally spanned the globe. Soviet Bargaining</p>
        <p>In some cases, despite hard bargaining, the Met was unable to borrow paintings it would have liked for the show. Several paintings, for instance, were owned by the Hermitage and the Pushkin Museums in Leningrad and Moscow, respectively. While the Met would have liked to show the paintings, it chose not to pursue them after the Russians requested that the museum lend them what the Met considered to be too many of its own works in return.</p>
        <p>''They started asking for the world,'' said Philippe de Montebello, the director of the Metropolitan Museum, who arranged to borrow some of the paintings in the show. ''It wasn't worth the trouble of going to Russia five times.''</p>
        <p>There was the added problem, also, of paying for the show.</p>
        <p>''It's very hard to get subsidy for French 18th-century exhibitions,'' said a curator of the department of European paintings at the Met, Katharine Baetjer, who helped organize the Fragonard show. ''You can go out and get as much as you want, to show van Gogh or Monet. Sad to say, the same is not true of Fragonard.'' Sources for Financing</p>
        <p>Eventually, financing for the show was provided not from a single corporate grant, but from various sources, including Ann and Gordon Getty, the Sharp Foundation, the Real Estate Council of the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the National Endowment for the Arts. Altogether, $600,000 was raised.</p>
        <p>In some cases, key works in Fragonard's career were unavailable for loan. For instance, a series of paintings Fragonard made for the Louveciennes residence of one of his patrons, Mme. du Barry - which are considered among the finest decorative ensembles in all of French art - could not be lent for policy reasons by the Frick Collection, at Fifth Avenue and 70th Street in Manhattan, where they are displayed.</p>
        <p>And in other cases, private owners were unwilling or extremely reluctant to part with major paintings for similar reasons.</p>
        <p>''They occupy a highly decorative place in French 18th-century interiors, and therefore the hole they leave on the wall is particularly conspicuous,'' said Mr. de Montebello, explaining one hurdle the museum often faced on its way to mounting the present show. ''A lot of cajoling was needed.'' A Mysterious Man</p>
        <p>With this exhibition, the art-historical problems were no less daunting and stemmed from essential questions about Fragonard's life and career. For while the artist is now regarded as a giant of 18th-century French painting, the details of his life in many important ways remain a mystery.</p>
        <p>The problem was especially nettlesome for the chief curator of the department of paintings at the Louvre, Pierre Rosenberg, who organized the show and wrote the accompanying catalogue. The exhibition was first shown at the Grand Palais in Paris, from last fall through early January.</p>
        <p>''We have very little information on Fragonard,'' writes Mr. Rosenberg in the exhibition catalogue. ''He left nothing in writing (if, indeed, he knew how to write), no disclosures. He is but rarely mentioned by his contemporaries.''</p>
        <p>The 635-page catalogue is a result of Mr. Rosenberg's painstaking stitching together of small bits of information from hundreds of sources, ranging from 18th-century sales catalogues to occasional pamphlets, scattered references to the artist in other artists' letters and journals, and reviews of Fragonard's rare contributions to the Paris Salon. The Artist's Career</p>
        <p>The flowing account of the artist's life that Mr. Rosenberg has assembled from such diverse sources is probably the fullest of the artist that has ever been offered.</p>
        <p>In this account, Fragonard ''seems to have been a secretive man, lacking in self-confidence, moody, capricious, mysterious, accommodating, indecisive, incapable of finishing his projects.'' Largely self-taught, he gained the patronage of the King (and a studio in the Louvre) with his skillful work while in his middle 20's.</p>
        <p>Thenceforth, however, Fragonard disdained most public commissions, preferring instead to paint smaller works, mostly deftly painted portraits, landscapes and interior scenes that rarely failed to include two lovers or some other decidedly sensuous, often saucy touch.</p>
        <p>Exactly why Fragonard turned away from the ''big career'' that was expected of him, and exactly who his patrons were after this change, remain major questions for scholarship, according to Mr. Rosenberg.</p>
        <p>With the coming of the French Revolution, the Rococo style went out and a Neo-Classical style came in; Fragonard lost not only his popularity, but also many of his patrons, who fled the country. He died in obscurity in 1806.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
