<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Carpet Quest II: The Nervous Bidder</title>
    <meta content="11SHOP$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/11/technology/circuits/11shop.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1565408"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="ONLINE SHOPPER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Carpets and Rugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Slatalla, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Columns/Online Shopper</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Furnishings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Carpets and Rugs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Amazon.com Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Sotheby's Holdings Incorporated</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E7D7153EF932A25750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1287" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Carpet Quest II: The Nervous Bidder</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Nervous Bidder Takes On Carpet Quest II</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michelle Slatalla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Slatalla, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Slatalla Online Shopper column offers Web sites for auction houses where buyers can purchase Oriental rugs; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IT has proved easier for me to buy a house than a rug to put in it.</p>
        <p>This makes no sense. I have bought cars online. Swimsuits. Even 12 dozen black yarmulkes with pink buttons. And yet I have been struggling for two months to harness the power of the Internet to put a stop to the echoing sound I hear every time I walk through the living room.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>By way of the Net, an indecisive rug buyer is lured to a new frontier: the auction house.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IT has proved easier for me to buy a house than a rug to put in it.</p>
        <p>This makes no sense. I have bought cars online. Swimsuits. Even 12 dozen black yarmulkes with pink buttons. And yet I have been struggling for two months to harness the power of the Internet to put a stop to the echoing sound I hear every time I walk through the living room.</p>
        <p>Since I last wrote of my carpet quest, I have sent e-mail to more than a dozen dealers to inquire about the tiny digital images of carpets on their sites. I have visited local dealers to see how online images compare with the specimens hanging on their shop walls. (Generally the resemblance is minimal.)</p>
        <p>I have ordered such references as P.R.J. Ford's ''Oriental Carpet Design'' from Amazon.com and such turn-of-the-20th-century gems as John Kimberly Mumford's ''Oriental Rugs'' from Abebooks.com. I have dragged home more than two dozen rugs -- three of which I first saw online -- to see how they looked in my living room. (My relations have cooled with several local dealers.)</p>
        <p>I had formed three conclusions: I am drawn to antique Oriental rugs (a description that for many dealers' purposes refers to rugs predating 1920). I cannot afford to buy one I want. I may be on the verge of losing my mind.</p>
        <p>I started out thinking $5,000 was too much. Within weeks, I've graduated to lusting after rugs that cost many times that much. I recently borrowed three antique rugs from a local dealer, all with price tags above $20,000. What if my house had burned down while they were there?</p>
        <p>''I'm a rug addict,'' I said on the phone the other day to Barry O'Connell, a former rug dealer and longtime collector who is the host of the online Oriental Rug Newsgroup (to read postings, click on the FAQ link at spongobongo.com, Mr. O'Connell's rug information site).</p>
        <p>''Do you like the rugs you've seen?'' he asked.</p>
        <p>''One I would kill for,'' I said.</p>
        <p>''An auction might be the answer,'' he said. ''You could get the best possible value, if you can bear the increased risk of buying a rug you can't return.''</p>
        <p>I was intrigued.</p>
        <p>At auction, rugs sell at wholesale prices -- typically one-third of the retail price. A dealer who buys a $10,000 rug at auction may clean it, repair it as necessary and mark it up to about $30,000.</p>
        <p>That said, auctions aren't for the faint of heart. ''Although dealers may triple the price, they provide a lot of service that you don't get at auction,'' said Mary Jo Otsea, the senior vice president of Sotheby's carpets division. ''They fix a rug, they let you take it home for a week to decide if you want it.''</p>
        <p>Dealers know exactly which rugs are good buys at auction. But would I? Carpets spoil. This is not always obvious to the casual observer. Carpets rot, they get eaten by moths, their wool fibers break after about the 20,000th time someone walks across them. Certain colors literally disappear as old dyes oxidize the wool, creating an effect that collectors call ''sculptural'' and I think of as ''disintegrated.''</p>
        <p>The place to start was the Internet, where potential bidders can do everything from conducting research to virtually attending auctions held worldwide.</p>
        <p>Sites like Jozan Magazine (at jozan.net) list auction dates and links. From houses like Sotheby's (sothebys.com, where you can preview lots, look up previous sale prices and order catalogs) to Nagel Auctioneers in Germany (www.auctions.de) to Woolley &amp; Wallis in England (woolleyandwallis.co.uk), sites are troves of information.</p>
        <p>Online I learned that Bonhams &amp; Butterfields, a West Coast auction house, had a coming sale of carpets. I decided I would bid. At butterfields.com, I previewed more than 250 lots with price estimates that ranged from a few hundred dollars for a Senneh kilim (circa 1900) to $100,000 for a late 19th-century Oushak carpet.</p>
        <p>Luckily, the Oushak was too big for my living room.</p>
        <p>The next step was inspection. Ms. Otsea said that Sotheby's sells about 25 percent of its rugs to savvy bidders who never physically inspect them first. ''Usually those bidders will call to ask for a condition report, but sometimes they go on size, design and colors,'' she said. But she recommended that bidders attend a preview session if possible.</p>
        <p>Bonhams &amp; Butterfields held a preview in San Francisco a few minutes from my house. In the gallery, I felt as if I were in heaven. More than 200 carpets hung for me to see and touch for as long as I wanted.</p>
        <p>Hadji Rahimipour, vice president of Bonhams &amp; Butterfields' rug division, offered prospective bidders on-the-spot assessments. He pointed out such features as reweaves, splits and areas of low pile.</p>
        <p>I homed in on Lot No. 3096, described as a Kerman rug from the last quarter of the 19th century. I had some doubts -- were the colors too bright? -- but I quelled them.</p>
        <p>A few days later came the auction.</p>
        <p>I picked up my paddle at the front desk. I was bidder No. 400. I was terrified.</p>
        <p>The rugs had been moved to the auction house's Los Angeles gallery, and that's where most of the action was, too. In San Francisco, I was one of only four bidders on the premises as the auction got under way.</p>
        <p>We had our own live auctioneer to convey bids over a phone hookup. Each lot appeared on a TV screen, and the audio portion of the auction blared from speakers:</p>
        <p>''Open at 1,500 -- 16 -- 17. Let's see 18. I have 18 from San Francisco. Fair warning. Sold to San Francisco. Thank you, 403.''</p>
        <p>During the first hour I took enough frantic notes to ascertain that opening bids started well below sellers' reserves, that a few Los Angeles bidders (dealers?) seemed to be buying many of the rugs and that many others never reached their reserves.</p>
        <p>Then came Lot No. 3096, estimated to sell for $8,000 to $12,000.</p>
        <p>I distinctly felt like throwing up.</p>
        <p>Bidding opened at $5,000.</p>
        <p>Gamely I held up my paddle.</p>
        <p>''We have $6,500 in San Francisco,'' I heard, which was my first indication that there were other bidders or of exactly how much I personally had agreed to pay for that shockingly pink rug.</p>
        <p>$7,000.</p>
        <p>$7,500 (that was me, I think, because my paddle was still up, shaking, in front of my face).</p>
        <p>$8,000.</p>
        <p>$8,500. (Me?!)</p>
        <p>$9,000.</p>
        <p>I lowered my paddle. The auctioneer looked at me. No, I shook my head. No, no, no.</p>
        <p>Sold to Bidder No. 1009 in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Relief flooded through me. Was it because I hate to bid against other people (a detail I had somehow forgotten in the previous weeks)? Or was it because I had come to my senses and realized that $8,500 belonged in a college fund, not on the floor? No. The rug was too pink.</p>
        <p>By the time I drove home, however, I had regained my confidence. I learned a lot, right? There are other rug auctions out there; maybe someone with nerves of spaghetti would be better off conducting all her business online -- looking at an electronic catalog, obtaining a condition report and images by e-mail, even bidding in real time.</p>
        <p>Cheered, I stopped at one of the few local rug stores that doesn't have my photo taped near the cash register like a Most Wanted poster and borrowed an antique Serapi to test at home. It was too brown.</p>
        <p>ONLINE SHOPPER E-mail: Slatalla@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: Slatalla@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
