<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Recent Slide in Stocks Steepens, With Dow Falling 160</title>
    <meta content="11STOX$07" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1565517"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Industrial Average</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940CEED8123EF932A25750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Recent Slide in Stocks Steepens, With Dow Falling 160</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shares continue their recent slide as investors seem increasingly worried about weakness in economy and prospects for growth in profits; week's drop has wiped out year's gains for Nasdaq composite index and Dow Jones industrial average, though Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index is still up slightly for year; several big investors say stocks, while no longer cheap, are still reasonably valued and that possibility of steep pullback appears slight; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index drops 16.69 points, or 1.5 percent, to 1,123.89; Nasdaq composite index falls 31.01 points, or 1.6 percent, to 1,964.15; Dow Jones industrial average declines 160.07 points, or 1.7 percent, to 10,296.89; graph; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shares continued their recent slide yesterday as investors seemed increasingly worried about weakness in the economy and the prospects for growth in profits.</p>
        <p>This week's drop has wiped out the year's gains for the Nasdaq composite index and the Dow Jones industrial average, though the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index is still up slightly for the year. But several big investors said that stocks, while no longer cheap, were still reasonably valued and that the possibility of a steep pullback appeared slight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Shares continued their recent slide yesterday as investors seemed increasingly worried about weakness in the economy and the prospects for growth in profits.</p>
        <p>This week's drop has wiped out the year's gains for the Nasdaq composite index and the Dow Jones industrial average, though the Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index is still up slightly for the year. But several big investors said that stocks, while no longer cheap, were still reasonably valued and that the possibility of a steep pullback appeared slight.</p>
        <p>No single news event accounted for yesterday's slide, economists and professional money managers said. But investors appear concerned that the economy's growth over the last year has come mainly as a result of short-term stimulus from the federal government and Federal Reserve, not because of increased corporate investment or sustainable increases in consumer spending.</p>
        <p>Recent government reports showing that job creation has been weaker than expected have fueled those fears, said Thomas Giovine, a hedge fund manager in Los Angeles. Although the economy still appears solid, he said, investors no longer believe that growth will continue to accelerate unless the job market improves.</p>
        <p>''If you calibrate to the beginning of the year, the consensus was that we were going to get strong growth,'' Mr. Giovine said. ''Because the consensus was bullish, there was very little room for any weak economic data.''</p>
        <p>In addition, stocks have rallied strongly over the last year and are no longer cheap, said Scott Black, the president of Delphi Management. The S.&amp;P. 500, which includes the largest publicly traded companies, has risen 39 percent over the last 12 months. The average S.&amp;P. 500 stock trades at a multiple of 23 times its profits, well above the historical average of 15 times earnings.</p>
        <p>''It's tough to find cheap stocks,'' Mr. Black said. ''In the bigger names that most people would follow, you're paying 25 or 30 times multiples for very little growth.'' For example, Coca-Cola trades at 26 times its earnings last year and 24 times its expected earnings for 2004.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, the S.&amp;P. 500 index dropped 16.69 points, or 1.5 percent, to 1,123.89. The technology-heavy Nasdaq dropped 31.01 points, or 1.6 percent, to 1,964.15, and the Dow Jones industrial average fell 160.07 points, or 1.5 percent, to 10,296.89.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Black and Mr. Giovine both warned against overreacting to the recent downturn</p>
        <p>Despite this week's drop, the S.&amp;P. 500 is still less than 3 percent from the high it reached in February. The Nasdaq, which rose even farther last year, has slid more sharply in the last month, dropping almost 9 percent.</p>
        <p>Stocks remain more attractive than alternative investments, Mr. Black said. With 10-year Treasury bonds yielding less than 3.8 percent, investors who buy them are taking a serious risk that inflation will eventually rise and erode their value, he said. European stocks also appear dangerous because the rise in the euro against the dollar will probably hurt Europe's economy.</p>
        <p>''There's nowhere to go,'' he said. ''What's the alternative?''</p>
        <p>Other investments, including real estate and the bonds issued by Mexico and other emerging-market counties, are also unattractive, Mr. Giovine said. And the dividend tax cuts enacted last year have contributed to stocks' allure, he said. For example, the American depository receipts of BP pay a dividend of 3.7 percent, about the same as the 10-year Treasury note, with a lower tax rate and better protection against inflation, he said.</p>
        <p>''Do I want to be in bonds, do I want to be in cash, do I want to put more money in real estate, or do I want to be in equities and buy a yield that has a tax advantage?'' he said.</p>
        <p>Richard DeKaser, the chief economist at the National City Corporation, a Cleveland-based bank, said he thought stocks were ready to slide because they have gained so steadily since March 2003. The S.&amp;P. 500 has risen in 11 of the last 12 months and four of the last five quarters.</p>
        <p>''What I see is we have a stock market that is still fairly valued,'' Mr. DeKaser said. Last year, operating profits for S.&amp;P. 500 companies rose 20 percent to 25 percent. This year they are expected to rise more than 10 percent.</p>
        <p>That level of growth can easily support the S.&amp;P. 500's price-earnings ratio, which Mr. DeKaser calculates at less than 20, excluding certain one-time charges, he said.</p>
        <p>Low interest rates also help the market, both by making bonds less attractive as an alternative investment and by enabling investors to discount future corporate profits at a lower rate.</p>
        <p>Even weak job growth is not entirely bad for investors as long as productivity is rising, Mr. DeKaser said. High productivity translates into higher output, and if job growth is weak companies will not have to share much of their extra profits with workers.</p>
        <p>''Earnings are growing rapidly,'' he said. ''And that phenomenon in many respects is the flip side of the jobless recovery.''</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>Treasury Prices Dip  By Bloomberg News</p>
        <p>Yields on United States 10-year Treasury notes rose slightly yesterday but held close to an eight-month low on expectations that low inflation and slow job growth will keep the Federal Reserve from raising interest rates this year.</p>
        <p>Yields on 5- and 10-year notes have fallen more than a quarter of a percentage point since a report on Friday showed that United States employment growth slowed in February. By late in the day, the price of the 10-year note dropped 5/32, to 1013/32. The note's yield, which moves in the opposite direction from the price, rose to 3.73 percent from 3.71 percent on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Earlier price gains were erased after demand was weaker than expected at an afternoon auction of $16 billion of new five-year notes. Here are the results of that auction:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>Price: 99.675  High Yield: 2.695  Low Yield: 2.600  Median Yield: 2.635  Total applied for: $39,573,279  Accepted: $16,000,053  Noncompetitive: $99,248  Interest set at: 2.625  The five-year notes mature March 15, 2009</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS &amp; BONDS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
