<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Marianne Wiggins And Life on the Run</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="436221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HARPERCOLLINS PUBLISHERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, CARYN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WIGGINS, MARIANNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUSHDIE, SALMAN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">BET THEY'LL MISS US WHEN WE'RE GONE (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910409T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DB173FF93AA35757C0A967958260" item-length="564" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Marianne Wiggins And Life on the Run</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CARYN JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, CARYN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"We were on the lam in Wales," Marianne Wiggins writes in a new short-story collection, and sure enough they were. Ms. Wiggins and her husband, the novelist Salman Rushdie, were in Wales in April 1989, two months after the Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini's death sentence against Mr. Rushdie sent the couple underground.</p>
        <p>That new part of the Rushdie-Wiggins puzzle is revealed with a casual stroke of the pen in the book, "Bet They'll Miss Us When We're Gone," to be published in June by HarperCollins.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"We were on the lam in Wales," Marianne Wiggins writes in a new short-story collection, and sure enough they were. Ms. Wiggins and her husband, the novelist Salman Rushdie, were in Wales in April 1989, two months after the Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini's death sentence against Mr. Rushdie sent the couple underground.</p>
        <p>That new part of the Rushdie-Wiggins puzzle is revealed with a casual stroke of the pen in the book, "Bet They'll Miss Us When We're Gone," to be published in June by HarperCollins.</p>
        <p>Each of the stories ends with the date and place it was written, which puts the couple in Wales in April and on the "Welsh Borders" in July 1989, the same month that Ms. Wiggins came out of hiding to promote the paperback release of her novel "John Dollar," and to pick up her own life.</p>
        <p>During the five months she was underground with Mr. Rushdie, the couple reportedly moved dozens of times, but their locations have never been specified beyond being in Britain. Mr. Rushdie, whose novel "The Satanic Verses" is considered blasphemous by some Muslims, is still under Government protection in a secret place. Two weeks ago Ms. Wiggins, an American who lives in London, announced they were divorcing.</p>
        <p>Though the stories in Ms. Wiggins's new collection date from 1979 through 1990 and favor invention over autobiography, the book holds some clues about her life in hiding. "Croeso i Gymru" (Welsh meaning "Welcome to Wales") is an eloquent story about how language, in the shape of Welsh words, becomes an emotional and intellectual life preserver for that narrator "on the lam," who at the story's end turns out to be named Marianne. She and her husband are in hiding, guarded by men she calls "the people that we have to live with now."</p>
        <p>Though she depicts a maddening life of constricted actions, fear of discovery and loss of privacy, the fictional Marianne never reveals more than her first name; Ms. Wiggins doesn't have to. Marianne worries that she has been recognized at a market, but the guards say she is simply conspicuous because of her American accent. She is afraid that soldiers at a nearby training camp have discovered who she is, but is told they only stared because she is a woman. One night while watching television, she writes, "I saw the president of a bankrupt desert nation speak into a microphone," and swear "to send a black arrow of revenge from that distant desert into my husband's heart."  Critical of Conversion</p>
        <p>Ms. Wiggins has refused all interviews since she was quoted recently in The Times of London describing her husband in extremely critical terms. Breaking out of what she called "a straitjacket of loyalty and public devotion," in that interview, she faulted him for focusing attention on himself rather than aligning himself with other persecuted writers, and said he "will do anything to save his life."</p>
        <p>Mr. Rushdie publicly embraced Islam in December. Ms. Wiggins was quoted as saying, "The very fact that he would go on television and announce a personal conversion shows how far his personality has been broken down."</p>
        <p>"Bet They'll Miss Us When We're Gone" had been in the works when the death threat was called down on Mr. Rushdie, but Ms. Wiggins's original title and the short autobiographical story from which it came were dropped. In less stressful days, the book had been called "Learning Urdu."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
