<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How Snap Analysis Spurred an AT&amp;T Slide</title>
    <meta content="21PLAC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Market Place" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="872622"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="Market Place"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">At&amp;t Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Salomon Brothers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Landler, Mark</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grubman, Jack B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mandl, Alex J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960821T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E5D71230F932A1575BC0A960958260" item-length="1166" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How Snap Analysis Spurred an AT&amp;T Slide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARK LANDLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Landler, Mark</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sharp drop in AT&amp;T stock spurred by Salomon Brothers analyst Jack B Grubman's snap analysis of implications of departure of president Alex J Mandl discussed; shares edged back up after Grubman, in unusual move, informed clients that his initial view might have been too negative; his close ties to Mandl noted (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In academic debates, getting the last word is crucial. But on Wall Street, where stock traders make split-second decisions based on snap impressions, the first word is often what matters.</p>
        <p>Such was the case on Monday with the startling news that the president of AT&amp;T, Alex J. Mandl, had resigned to join a tiny start-up company. Knowing that his departure would buffet its stock, AT&amp;T had prepared a statement that praised Mr. Mandl's contributions but noted that the long-distance company would move ahead swiftly without him.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In academic debates, getting the last word is crucial. But on Wall Street, where stock traders make split-second decisions based on snap impressions, the first word is often what matters.</p>
        <p>Such was the case on Monday with the startling news that the president of AT&amp;T, Alex J. Mandl, had resigned to join a tiny start-up company. Knowing that his departure would buffet its stock, AT&amp;T had prepared a statement that praised Mr. Mandl's contributions but noted that the long-distance company would move ahead swiftly without him.</p>
        <p>But at 9:02 A.M., 21 minutes before AT&amp;T released its statement and 28 minutes before the market's opening bell, a leading telecommunications analyst broke the news about Mr. Mandl in a harshly negative note to his clients that was picked up by Bloomberg Business News.</p>
        <p>The analyst, Jack B. Grubman of Salomon Brothers, wrote that Mr. Mandl's departure could cause ''major management disruption'' and ''may be an indication of deeper issues within AT&amp;T.'' He concluded, ''Needless to say, we remain cautious on the stock.''</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T's stock dropped like a stone immediately after it began trading on the New York Stock Exchange at 9:45 A.M. on Monday, and it has not yet fully made up the loss. After falling by as much as $1.875 Monday morning, the shares ended that day's trading down $1.375, or 2.5 percent, to close at $54.125. Yesterday, the company's shares bounced around before closing up slightly at $54.375.</p>
        <p>Kevin Haggerty, an equity trader with Fidelity Investments in Boston, said that Mr. Mandl's resignation was a nasty surprise, but that Mr. Grubman's early pessimistic assessment magnified the impact  on AT&amp;T's shares. ''When you get a double whammy like that, it does make the stock go down even more,'' Mr. Haggerty said.</p>
        <p>In the early afternoon, when Mr. Grubman took the remarkable step of issuing a second note to his clients, acknowledging that his initial assessment might have been overly negative, the shares began to edge back up.</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T's stomach-churning ride illustrates the power of a handful of influential analysts to affect stockholder sentiment about giant companies -- especially when the analyst scoops the company with its own news.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grubman, who was once an executive at AT&amp;T, has won high marks in annual surveys of analysts by Institutional Investor magazine. And his often-trenchant reports are must reading for money managers who invest in AT&amp;T and other telephone companies.</p>
        <p>Whatever Mr. Grubman's reputation, though, his Monday morning  comments did not win him any friends at his old company. ''Jack was way off base,'' Robert E. Allen, the chairman and chief executive of AT&amp;T, said in an interview on Monday afternoon, in an unusually heated criticism of a powerful Wall Street opinion leader. ''He was obviously acting emotionally,'' Mr. Allen added, ''It was almost as if his note was planted by someone.''</p>
        <p>AT&amp;T's chairman did not elaborate on his suspicions. And Mr. Grubman did not return repeated telephone calls Monday and yesterday  seeking comment.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Grubman has enjoyed close ties to Mr. Mandl, which date back to when Mr. Mandl was AT&amp;T's chief financial officer and handled the company's relations with Wall Street. Mr. Grubman has even spent the weekend with Mr. Mandl and his wife at their home outside Washington.</p>
        <p>And so to some people at AT&amp;T, Mr. Grubman's note seemed like a pat on the back from a friend -- at their expense. In the note, Mr. Grubman described Mr. Mandl as a ''seasoned, aggressive leader.'' He said Mr. Mandl was embarking on a ''fantastic opportunity'' in taking over Associated Communications, which owns licenses to offer wireless telephone services. In addition to a $20 million signing bonus, Mr. Mandl will get a stake in the company that will grow to 18 percent, based on its escalating market value.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandl said yesterday that he had not discussed his new job with Mr. Grubman before AT&amp;T's announcement. And while he acknowledged he was ''closer to Jack than to other analysts,'' he said he was as upset as Mr. Allen by Mr. Grubman's criticism of AT&amp;T's management team.</p>
        <p>''When Jack came out with that thing, I was very surprised and thought it was highly inappropriate,'' Mr. Mandl said. ''The last thing I wanted to have happen is for the people at AT&amp;T to be angry.''</p>
        <p>After Mr. Grubman spoke to AT&amp;T's chief financial officer, Richard W. Miller, later on Monday morning, he apparently had his own misgivings. Mr. Miller told Mr. Grubman that he was ''surprised'' by the tone of the report, particularly since Mr. Grubman had not spoken to  AT&amp;T before releasing it. Soon after Mr. Miller's call, Mr. Grubman published a second note in which he wrote, ''We perhaps were a bit harsh on AT&amp;T's remaining management.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Miller did not attribute the ups and downs of AT&amp;T's stock on Monday completely to Mr. Grubman's pronouncements. During Monday's trading session, another top analyst, Frank Governali of CS First Boston, lowered his recommendation on AT&amp;T to a ''hold'' from a ''strong buy.'' Still, Mr. Miller said, ''investors pay a lot of attention to what Jack has to say.''</p>
        <p>If AT&amp;T suffered from Mr. Grubman's strong opinions, Mr. Mandl's new employers may have benefited. Shares of the Associated Group, which owns 55 percent of Associated Communications, have jumped a total of $6.75 in the last two days, to $32.25, in Nasdaq trading.</p>
        <p>The Associated Group is controlled by Myles P. Berkman, a communications investor who made his fortune by buying and selling cable television systems and cellular telephone properties. Mr. Berkman and his family own 35 percent of the Associated Group -- which means the value of their holdings has risen roughly $44 million since Mr. Mandl's bold move.</p>
        <p>Salvatore Muoio, an analyst with Lazard Freres &amp; Company who follows Associated, said the company's licenses to offer a variety of wireless telephone and data services were ''really valuable real estate.'' But Mr. Muoio said that the company had spent years casting about for way to turn these licenses into a lucrative business.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mandl's arrival -- combined with the recent relaxation of Federal telecommunications laws -- will enable Associated to attract the capital necessary to build a wireless network, according to Mr. Muoio. Though the owners of Associated have put a private market value of $250 million on the company, Mr. Muoio said that it could raise more than $500 million in an initial public offering.</p>
        <p>For the Berkmans, who are $44 million richer today than last week, Mr. Mandl has already earned his $20 million signing bonus.</p>
        <p>Market Place</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
