<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bledsoe? Marino? This Game Is All Legs</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="722062"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MIAMI DOLPHINS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW ENGLAND PATRIOTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, TIMOTHY W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Miami Dolphins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E5DA1E3FF932A05753C1A962958260" item-length="744" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bledsoe? Marino? This Game Is All Legs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, TIMOTHY W</byline>
      <dateline>FOXBORO, Mass., Oct. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This was supposed to be a shootout between two fly boys -- Miami's Dan Marino and New England's Drew Bledsoe -- who like nothing better than filling the air with passes. In the last game between the two teams, on opening day, the two quarterbacks combined for 894 yards and 9 touchdowns through the air and the Dolphins won, 39-35.</p>
        <p>On a sunny afternoon, with a game-time temperature an unseasonably warm 75 degrees, the stage was set for another toss-fest between Marino and Bledsoe. But it soon turned into a day for the foot soldiers, primarily the Miami kicker, Pete Stoyanovich, and running back Bernie Parmalee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This was supposed to be a shootout between two fly boys -- Miami's Dan Marino and New England's Drew Bledsoe -- who like nothing better than filling the air with passes. In the last game between the two teams, on opening day, the two quarterbacks combined for 894 yards and 9 touchdowns through the air and the Dolphins won, 39-35.</p>
        <p>On a sunny afternoon, with a game-time temperature an unseasonably warm 75 degrees, the stage was set for another toss-fest between Marino and Bledsoe. But it soon turned into a day for the foot soldiers, primarily the Miami kicker, Pete Stoyanovich, and running back Bernie Parmalee.</p>
        <p>Stoyanovich kicked field goals of 44, 50 and 48 yards and Parmalee rushed for 123 yards while the Dolphins' defense virtually shut down the Patriots' high-flying offense, paving the way for Miami's 23-3 victory. The Dolphins (6-2) maintained their one-game lead in the American Football Conference East over Buffalo; the Patriots dropped to 3-5.</p>
        <p>New England entered the game averaging 397.4 yards of offense a game. They left with 188 total yards on offense. Bledsoe entered the game with 2,314 yards passing, the most of any quarterback in the National Football League. He left the game in the fourth quarter, having completed 16 of 33 passes for 125 yards and 3 interceptions.</p>
        <p>How did Miami befuddle Bledsoe, the prolific passing prodigy?</p>
        <p>"We just stayed in his face," said Tom Olivadotti, Miami's defensive coordinator. "He's a smart quarterback, and the Patriots' coaches are smart. You're not going to fool them. We came with extra hard pressure."</p>
        <p>The Dolphins' strategy was for the defensive linemen to keep pressure on Bledsoe and block his view in the passing lanes. The cornerbacks had to hold the coverage on the Patriots' wide receivers a few seconds longer to allow the pass rush to get there. Strong safety Michael Stewart drew coverage on tight end Ben Coates, who came into the game as the Patriots' leading receiver with 51 catches for 744 yards. Coates finished with 2 catches for 17 yards.</p>
        <p>"We took away everything they wanted to do," said Miami linebacker Bryan Cox. "I'm sure if you went over to their locker room, they'd tell you we outplayed and outcoached them in every phase of the game."</p>
        <p>"It's quite obvious that they're a far superior team than we are," said Patriots Coach Bill Parcells. "We continue to do things that aren't going to allow us to win."</p>
        <p>The Patriots scored first on a 48-yard field goal by Matt Bahr in the first quarter. Then, Stoyanovich booted field goals of 44 and 50 yards to give the Dolphins a 6-3 lead midway through the half. Miami capitalized on an interception by defensive end Jeff Cross at the Patriots' 29 to get a 1-yard touchdown run from Keith Byars to go up by 13-3 at the end of the first half. Byars scored his second touchdown on a 7-yard pass from Marino to cap the opening drive of the third quarter, and Stoyanovich added a 48-yarder early in the fourth quarter that made it 23-3. So much for the shootout.</p>
        <p>If nothing else, this game showed just how much the two teams have changed over the last eight weeks.</p>
        <p>The Dolphins, who have been searching for a consistent rushing attack since Terry Kirby went down with a season-ending knee injury in the fourth game of the season, have found one with Parmalee. Combining the 150 yards he had against the Raiders and the 123 yards he picked up against the Patriots, Parmalee set a Dolphins record for most rushing yards in back-to-back games, breaking a mark set by Mercury Morris (258) in 1973. Parmalee played most of the game with a dislocated right thumb that he suffered in the first quarter -- and oblivious to the fact that he could set a team rushing record.</p>
        <p>"I just felt good running it," he said. "The offensive line did a good job opening up holes. I told them to hold their blocks for a split second longer and I'd try to get through the holes as quickly as possible."</p>
        <p>The Patriots, who gave up 105 points in their first three games, decided to blitz more in an effort to cut down on the number of big plays they were allowing.</p>
        <p>"It was something we had to do," said Patriots' cornerback Maurice Hurst. "But blitzes are really scary, because you live by them or you get burned by them. When you have a quarterback like Drew that throws it 50 times a game, he's bound to hit on some big plays. And when you have a defense that blitzes 20 or 30 times a game, you're bound to give up some big plays."  PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
