<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Gulf Syndrome; Americans Decide War May Not Be Quite So Scary</title>
    <meta content="30SCHM$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Washington; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="976845"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Persian Gulf War</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kuwait</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schmitt, Eric</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hussein, Saddam (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E7D9103AF933A05752C1A961958260" item-length="1345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Gulf Syndrome; Americans Decide War May Not Be Quite So Scary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC SCHMITT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schmitt, Eric</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Opinion polls show most Americans are prepared to support extensive military strike to force Pres Saddam Hussein to allow United Nations inspectors free access to do their job; this is in stark contrast to tremulous tone of public debate in 1990, on eve of Persian Gulf War; Americans have been emboldened by victory in that war; new-found bellicosity toward Hussein seems to spring from belief that military can thwart him with unmanned missiles or bombing runs, and suffer few if any casualties; but it took tanks and infantry, not bombs, to get Iraq to withdraw from Kuwait in 1991; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THERE'S nothing like a crisis with Iraq to get American blood boiling.</p>
        <p>For the moment, diplomacy has defused the latest standoff over allowing United Nations inspectors to resume their hunt for Iraq's nuclear, chemical and biological arsenal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THERE'S nothing like a crisis with Iraq to get American blood boiling.</p>
        <p>For the moment, diplomacy has defused the latest standoff over allowing United Nations inspectors to resume their hunt for Iraq's nuclear, chemical and biological arsenal.</p>
        <p>But opinion polls show that most Americans were prepared to support an extensive military strike to force President Saddam Hussein to back down.</p>
        <p>This is in stark contrast to the tremulous tone of public debate in 1990, as America girded for war against Mr. Hussein, and it seems to suggest that Americans have finally shaken off their famous Vietnam syndrome. But a question remains: Are Americans ready to use their muscle anywhere? Or is their attitude more conflicted than that, notwithstanding their eagerness to punish Iraq?</p>
        <p>A Newsweek poll taken Nov. 13 and 14, in mid-standoff, found that 53 percent of Americans favored using force if Iraq refused arms inspections because of American participation. And the figure climbed to 82 percent if Iraq were to shoot down an American U-2 spy plane flying for the inspectors.</p>
        <p>If diplomacy failed, Congress was clamoring for an attack punishing enough to topple Mr. Hussein's regime.  ''I'd like to see him taken out,'' said Senator Trent Lott of Mississippi, the majority leader.</p>
        <p>Even liberal pundits are sounding bloodthirsty these days. Last week George Stephanopoulos, President Clinton's former senior adviser, called on his old boss to ignore a Ford-era Presidential order barring American.-sanctioned assassinations and put out a contract on Mr. Hussein. ''If we can kill Saddam, we should,'' Mr. Stephanopoulos wrote in the current issue of Newsweek.</p>
        <p>What a change from seven years ago, when Americans and their elected representatives were almost evenly divided over whether to wait longer for economic sanctions to bite or to wage war to repel Iraq's invasion of Kuwait.</p>
        <p>The stakes were different then, of course; the fact that Iraq had conquered and occupied an independent neighbor made both the urgency of ousting Mr. Hussein and the potential cost seemed to demand a great deal more debate.</p>
        <p>Still, the result seems to have emboldened Americans into replacing their old first instinct (''Don't go to war because we might lose and divide ourselves at home'') with a new one (''Let's go to war; we'll win big and unify ourselves at home'').</p>
        <p>The polls show this. The politicians are talking the talk. And there are logical reasons to explain why Americans seem to feel freer to use force now than they did in 1990.</p>
        <p>For one, people and generals everywhere tend to calculate their chances in the next war from their experiences in the last one. In 1990, the last big war was Vietnam. Now it is the Persian Gulf war.</p>
        <p>Vietnam, moreover, had been only the final convincing course in a generation-long learning experience about the limits of American power. Before Vietnam fell, there had been the stalemate in Korea, inconclusive and frightening confrontations with the Soviets and insolent challenges from teensy nations. Standoff was largely the name of the game, and it seemed prudent to put up with that fact.</p>
        <p>All of that had only begun to change in 1990; there was, in fact, still a Soviet Union, even though it was fast coming undone. Now Americans have had plenty of time to realize how different the world has become without it.</p>
        <p>But Iraq is also a special case. First of all, the United States and its allies have had seven years to demonize Mr. Hussein. And a wealth of new information surpassing nearly everyone's worst fears has emerged about the size and scope of his doomsday stockpiles. So unlike in 1990, when George Bush struggled to find an argument for defending Kuwait that resonated with the public, President Clinton can pick and choose from Iraq's terrifying array of poison gases and killer germs as a rationale to bomb away.</p>
        <p>Defense Secretary William S. Cohen, playing show-and-tell on national television a couple of weeks ago, plunked down a five-pound bag of sugar and proclaimed that if the sugar were anthrax, a deadly bacteria, it could kill half the population of Washington. In case anyone missed his point, he said last week that the United Nations believes Iraq may have produced up to 200 tons of VX nerve gas, ''theoretically enough to kill every man, woman, and child on the face of the Earth.''</p>
        <p>The public and Congress agree on the urgency of destroying Mr. Hussein's ability to inflict mass destruction. ''We cannot let stand what they are doing,'' Senator Lott said.</p>
        <p>All this demonstrates that Americans are still willing to fight to win a war that seems morally unambiguous. But the stakes have to be high enough and clearly defined, and the bad guy must be really bad. And since the end of the cold war, these clear-cut choices about what America must defend seem harder to come by.</p>
        <p>Beyond the case of Iraq, the more likely model for American military operations in the foreseeable future is peacemaking, particularly if it can be described as a humanitarian venture. Cadets at West Point train for such missions, and politicians have learned how to sell them. Recent efforts to halt civil or ethnic strife that threatened to get out of hand have included Stop the Famine in Somalia, Restore Democracy in Haiti and  End the Genocide in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>But Americans are still hesitant to get involved in these episodes.</p>
        <p>As the first American troops arrived in Bosnia two years ago, a CBS News/New York Times poll found that 55 percent of those surveyed opposed the mission, while only 40 percent supported it. Respondents said Mr. Clinton had explained the situation well enough; they just didn't feel they had a direct stake in the conflict.</p>
        <p>Today, even though no American forces in Bosnia have been killed in combat in those two years, Congress is still pressing the Administration to pull out the troops by June 1998 -- although it remains to be seen just how hard lawmakers will fight so long as the mission is going well.</p>
        <p>In Iraq, the public seems to be willing to pay a higher price -- but only up to a point.</p>
        <p>In a curious way, the thumping American military success there in 1991 is posing thorny problems for American planners now.</p>
        <p>Easy Win</p>
        <p>The new-found bellicosity toward Saddam Hussein seems to spring from a belief that the military can thwart him with unmanned Tomahawk cruise missiles or a few bombing runs, and suffer few if any casualties.  But this view doesn't take into account how many bombs were dropped on Iraq in 1991 without forcing a withdrawal from Kuwait. For that, it took tanks and infantry.</p>
        <p>Disarming Mr. Hussein's arsenal of horror weapons poses a similar problem. Mr. Clinton's generals have presented him with a plan to bomb every suspected weapons site in the country. But as the President himself is fond of pointing out, the 88,000 tons of bombs dropped on Iraq during the gulf war had less success in destroying its clandestine arsenal than have United Nations inspectors since the war.</p>
        <p>Without inspectors on the ground, the only other reliable option would be to send in ground forces. No one in the Administration wants to talk about that, mainly because of the much higher risk of casualties.</p>
        <p>And unlike Mr. Stephanopoulos, 55 percent of Americans surveyed in a recent Gallup poll opposed a plan to kill Mr. Hussein -- even though, according to another poll, 73 percent thought he should have been ousted in 1991.</p>
        <p>Even in Iraq, it seems, Americans are more comfortable with uneasy coexistence than with sending a hit man to deal with the enemy they feel should have been removed six years ago.</p>
        <p>So the the war of nerves continues.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
