<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cheap and Chic in Los Angeles</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19941109T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="722503"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <org class="indexing_service">WOLFGANG PUCK CAFE (LOS ANGELES)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ABUQUIU (LOS ANGELES RESTAURANT)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">VIDA (LOS ANGELES RESTAURANT)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ALTO PALATO (LOS ANGELES RESTAURANT)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TWIN PALMS (LOS ANGELES RESTAURANT)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">GRATIS (LOS ANGELES RESTAURANT)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ECLIPSE (LOS ANGELES RESTAURANT)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">IL PASTAIO (LOS ANGELES RESTAURANT)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">REICHL, RUTH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DA163EF931A35752C1A962958260" item-length="2203" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cheap and Chic in Los Angeles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RUTH REICHL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">REICHL, RUTH</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>RIOTS, fires, earthquakes, recession. This city has been pretty badly battered in the last couple of years. Faced with the end of the halcyon 1980's, local restaurateurs went around moaning, lamenting the big-money days and wondering if the good times would ever come back. But as catastrophe followed catastrophe something remarkable happened here: The most successful restaurateurs stopped looking backward and started facing reality. If people were reluctant to spend money, they would simply charge less. And do it with style.</p>
        <p>This change of attitude has created a virtual restaurant revolution. Many of the old favorites march on, but some have closed to be replaced by new and less expensive places.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>RIOTS, fires, earthquakes, recession. This city has been pretty badly battered in the last couple of years. Faced with the end of the halcyon 1980's, local restaurateurs went around moaning, lamenting the big-money days and wondering if the good times would ever come back. But as catastrophe followed catastrophe something remarkable happened here: The most successful restaurateurs stopped looking backward and started facing reality. If people were reluctant to spend money, they would simply charge less. And do it with style.</p>
        <p>This change of attitude has created a virtual restaurant revolution. Many of the old favorites march on, but some have closed to be replaced by new and less expensive places.</p>
        <p>The Bistro Garden, a venerable Beverly Hills institution, shut its elegant doors and was reincarnated as a fast-food souffle joint a couple of miles down the road in the Century City Marketplace. One of the city's most famous chefs, Michel Richard, turned part of his upscale Citrus into an earthy, affordable bistro. When you reserve a table, you have to specify in which part of the restaurant you want to be seated. And two other chefs, Wolfgang Puck and Celestino Drago, are busy opening inexpensive spinoffs of their big-deal restaurants.</p>
        <p>But the most interesting new restaurants in Los Angeles are those that have closed only to reopen in new incarnations. They look the same. They taste the same. But the names are new, the menus are new and, most important, the prices are new. To a person accustomed to paying New York City prices, in fact, the numbers printed on these menus look like mistakes.</p>
        <p>The new food in Los Angeles is more than merely a bargain; it also has a new spirit. In the face of the recession, food has become fun. It has silly names like "Tra La La" and "Whatcha Whatcha Want." It has outrageous combinations like scallop, apple and spinach salad with bacon vinaigrette. And it has colors that vibrate off the plate. When a dish of bright green spinach risotto framed by intense red beet risotto arrives at the table, you know you're in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Here is a look at some of the restaurants that are setting the new Los Angeles style. Each has opened in the last year. The Best Bargain</p>
        <p>"Pasta for $6.50? How does he do it?" people ask as they wander into this big, elegant room, sink into the comfortable chairs and look at the thick cloths and beautiful dishes that cover the tables at Alto Palato. "He" is Mauro Vincenti, owner of the fabulously expensive Rex, which occupies a landmark Art Deco building downtown, and former owner of Pazzia, which once occupied this space.</p>
        <p>It's a good question. Who else could offer a $6.50 plate of pasta like his spaghetti alla sorrentina? It is a bowl of beautifully chewy strands of al dente spaghetti topped with a bright green zucchini sauce. The flavors are understated and delicious with the true taste of Italy. All the food here has it, from pappardelle al ragu ($8) to a remarkable veal stew in red wine with grilled polenta ($12). There is even a grilled rib of beef for two with roasted potatoes and grilled tomatoes at $11.50 a person. The thin-crusted pizzas are superb and inventive, the gelato is a dream and nowhere in Los Angeles can you get a better cup of espresso. Even the service is special.</p>
        <p>How does he do it? ALTO PALATO, 755 North La Cienega Boulevard; (310) 657-9271; entrees, $11.50 to $17. The Most Fun</p>
        <p>Fred Eric is the bad boy of Los Angeles chefs. He trained with Joachim Splichal (Patina, Pinot, the long-lamented Max au Triangle), but then went on to create some of the city's silliest food at Flaming Colossus, a club, and the Olive, a record-industry hangout known for its attitude, noise and outrageous food. Having his own restaurant, Vida, has not slowed Mr. Eric down one bit. Just reading the menu is an indication that you are in for a wild ride.</p>
        <p>Here is where you will find "Tra La La," which turns out to be a sort of salad of crisp artichoke hearts filled with goat cheese with a basil salsa. "Whatcha Whatcha Want" has been lamentably retired from the fall menu; it was a simple plate of capellini in a chunky tomato and grilled vegetable stew. But the puns roll on: "Ty Cobb" is "crispy duck on a warm spinach salad with the traditional toppings of Cobb salad made in Thailand" and it is terrific.</p>
        <p>So is the "Okra Winfrey Creole gumbo." Smokey the fish is, despite its name, a rather complicated smoked bass in various sauces.  What's "New Yorkshire"? Steak, potatoes and Yorkshire pudding, of course.</p>
        <p>There's an impressive and inexpensive wine list and a big buzz in the room. Vida has become a hangout for Hollywood's youngest and hippest producers, who appreciate the puns, the experimental architecture and the affordable food. This may be Los Angeles's unstuffiest restaurant. Not bad for a place in the staid Los Feliz district. VIDA, 1930 Hillhurst Avenue; (213) 660-4446; entrees, $12 to $17. Cheap Chic</p>
        <p>In the early 80's Michael Roberts helped define Los Angeles style, continually moving the border of what was possible a little farther toward the edge. As chef and owner of Trumps he was fearless, putting caviar onto fried plantains and turning tostadas into dessert.</p>
        <p>Now, he has gone into partnership with Kevin Costner and moved to Pasadena. Their sprawling Twin Palms has the air of a slightly decaying Southern country club, all peeling white paint verandas and lazy ceiling fans. It is as gorgeous as a spread in an architecture magazine: you want to get your suitcase and move right in. It certainly doesn't look like a place that sells $3.50 appetizers and cassoulet for $9.75.</p>
        <p>Mr. Roberts does not seem to have lost his sense of humor -- he is the architect of that scallop, apple and spinach salad with bacon vinaigrette. But most of the food on the huge menu is more familiar. There are pizzas and burgers and sandwiches and stews. The prices are reasonable: the rotisserie chicken with roasted garlic, wilted escarole and gratin potatoes is a hefty plate for $9.50.</p>
        <p>To begin there are terrific crisp artichokes served with deep-fried caper berries and olives and sprinkled with cheese. But the best appetizer is a rich brandade of salt cod and mashed potatoes, topped with crisp slices of toast, generous enough to make a meal and so delicious it is easy to see why the $3.75 plate is so popular. "I sell more salt cod than anybody on the West Coast," Mr. Roberts says. "These days people in Los Angeles have a real sense of adventure." TWIN PALMS, 101 West Green Street, Pasadena; (818) 577-2567; entrees, $7.25 to $15.50. A Healthy Bargain</p>
        <p>Are you ready for fat-free food? Los Angeles is. People have been lining up to eat at Gratis since the day the restaurant and takeout store opened in the Brentwood section of the city. There is usually a wait to pick up food, and customers are given silent beepers that vibrate when their order is ready.</p>
        <p>The menu is completely vegetarian; some of the food is actually edible. The soft tacos with black beans, chili and cilantro-lime dressing are an awesome amount of food that is good enough to elevate eating beyond mere guiltlessness. But the pizza was gummy and the veggie cheese burger was one of the worst things I have ever tried to swallow. As for potato salad, there is probably a way to make a fat-free version, but Gratis has yet to discover it.</p>
        <p>The most famous dish at Gratis, I am told, is the triple-layered chocolate cake. (The restaurant swears it, too, is fat-free.) And you know what? It's pretty good. Good enough to warrant picking up one of those beepers. GRATIS, 11658 San Vicente Boulevard; (310) 571-2345; entrees, $4.50 to $7.95. Most Colorful</p>
        <p>If you can't get reservations at Spago or Chinois on Main, don't despair: Wolfgang Puck Cafe doesn't take reservations. You may have to wait, but you won't have to suffer the humiliation of reserving a table and then cooling your heels while celebrities waltz right in. Here it is strictly first come, first served.</p>
        <p>Open just a few weeks, the cafe that America's most famous chef named for himself is a rainbow of tiles, ceramics, paints and patterns layered in dizzying, dazzling profusion. It is a room in which it is almost impossible to feel depressed.</p>
        <p>The food, fast versions of hits from Puck's other restaurants, has no trouble competing with the setting; it is the most colorful food I have ever seen.</p>
        <p>A bright orange bowl of butternut squash soup is swirled with a puree of red peppers. Salmon is a slab of pink on a bed of grilled vegetables so gorgeous it practically begs you to eat it. Linguine with scallops and spicy Chinese black-bean sauce has multicolored peppers sprinkled through the dish. Even meatloaf, which comes wrapped in bacon and perched on an enormous pile of mashed potatoes, is framed by bright, tiny tomatoes.</p>
        <p>The most expensive item on the menu is the smoked salmon pizza ($14.50), with cream cheese, chives and slices of smoked fish. This "Jewish Pizza" is what Mr. Puck sends out to his special customers at Spago, where it has never been on the menu and is usually crowned with caviar. WOLFGANG PUCK CAFE, 1323 Montana Avenue, Santa Monica; (310) 393-0290; entrees, $9.50 to $12.50. Italy, in Technicolor</p>
        <p>"Why cook?" asks the takeout menu at Il Pastaio in Beverly Hills. At these prices it is not a bad question.</p>
        <p>Celestino Drago runs the hugely successful Drago in Santa Monica. But his newest restaurant serves only salads, antipasti, pastas and risotto, and no dish on the menu costs more than $12; few exceed $10.</p>
        <p>In the window of the simple room a woman stands making pasta. She works quickly, deftly folding a mixture of lobster and zucchini into mezzelune and stuffing tortelloni with a pumpkin mush. She turns out green and white tagliolini for the Sicilian pesto, which is made with nuts and tomatoes. Ribbons of black and white pasta run through her fingers; after they are dried they will be tossed with tiny, sweet clams and bright green leaves of arugula.</p>
        <p>This is also the home of the world's most colorful risotto. The green is so green, the red so red, it is hard to believe that these colors exist in nature. "I can never resist this spinach and pea risotto," said a woman at the next table, scooping up a forkful of bright green. Who can blame her? IL PASTAIO, 400 North Cannon, Drive, Beverly Hills; (310) 205-5440; entrees, $7.50 to $12. Most Exciting</p>
        <p>John Sedlar practically invented nouvelle Southwest cuisine when he opened the restaurant St. Estephe, and blended his New Mexican roots with his classic French training. He expanded the repertory with his next restaurant, Bikini, allowing his cooking to resonate with Italian, Asian and South American influences. Alas, the restaurant was too expensive and too experimental, and after it was damaged by the earthquake, Mr. Sedlar shut it down.</p>
        <p>He has just reopened the sleek, modern room as Abiquiu. The food, which is much more affordable, is rooted in New Mexico but still takes fliers into foreign territory. His chile relleno Bangkok, for instance, is filled with Thai shrimp and topped with a spicy peanut sauce.</p>
        <p>But the best dishes are the ones that simply refine Southwestern cuisine. Nobody makes a better tamale than Mr. Sedlar, whose Santo Pasqual is filled with chicken and topped with a clear, sharp pumpkin-seed and chile sauce. His tuna zozobra is rubbed with sharp spices and served on bright green-chile mashed potatoes. On the simpler side, trout is served with bacon, eggs and skillet hashed browns.</p>
        <p>There are lots of gorgeous desserts, including an exotic banana split. But the best is the Zuni corn souffle with passion-fruit cream. A treat at $6. ABIQUIU, 1413 Fifth Street, Santa Monica; (310) 395-8611; entrees, $12 to $18. La La Land</p>
        <p>Eclipse is like a joke about Los Angeles come to life. In the front of the crowded room three bodyguards circle nervously, talking into their watches and fiddling with their earpieces. The owner, Bernard Erpicum, trimmed down and more nervous-looking since his days as the all-powerful maitre d'hotel at Spago, confides that they are guarding the oil and real estate mogul Marvin Davis.</p>
        <p>And there he is, solid as a tank, sitting at the front table. It is clearly the best seat in the house. As soon as the Davis party departs, Steve Martin et al. take their place.</p>
        <p>With a Spago-trained chef, a Spago-trained owner and a site that was once the industry hangout Morton's (which has moved to larger quarters across the street), Eclipse came into the game with quite an edge. At the moment it is incredibly hot; people wait endlessly for one of the tables in the crowded dining room or on the (less desirable) patio.</p>
        <p>The house specialty is whole fish baked in the wood-burning oven. The menu even offers surf and turf. The chef, Serge Falesitch, is not breaking any new ground here, but it is clear that few people come for the food. The question is this: With entrees priced from $17 to $29.50, will Eclipse survive in the lean new Los Angeles world of restaurants? ECLIPSE, 8800 Melrose Avenue; West Hollywood; (310) 724-5959.</p>
        <p>Correction:  November 9, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in The Living Section last Wednesday about low-price restaurants in the Los Angeles area referred incorrectly to the Bistro Garden in Beverly Hills. It remains open.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: November 9, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>An article in The Living Section last Wednesday about low-price restaurants in the Los Angeles area referred incorrectly to the Bistro Garden in Beverly Hills. It remains open.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
