<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Short of Cash, N.A.A.C.P. Stops Paying Its Employees</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="722433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL ASSN FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF COLORED PEOPLE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E4DE163EF931A35752C1A962958260" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Short of Cash, N.A.A.C.P. Stops Paying Its Employees</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN H. CUSHMAN Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CUSHMAN, JOHN H JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, its reserves of cash depleted, has stopped paying most of its professional staff, board members of the nation's preeminent civil rights organization said today.</p>
        <p>The furlough took effect on Monday, and although officials of the group said they hoped it would last no more than a week or two, it showed the depth of the financial crisis gripping the organization after accusations of financial abuses by some of its leaders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, its reserves of cash depleted, has stopped paying most of its professional staff, board members of the nation's preeminent civil rights organization said today.</p>
        <p>The furlough took effect on Monday, and although officials of the group said they hoped it would last no more than a week or two, it showed the depth of the financial crisis gripping the organization after accusations of financial abuses by some of its leaders.</p>
        <p>The N.A.A.C.P., with a national staff of about 100 people and an annual budget of about $15 million, is facing a growing deficit that already exceeds $3.5 million, officials said. Major contributors and individual members, their confidence shaken by the group's widely publicized turmoil, have been reluctant to donate money to make up the gap.</p>
        <p>The group's local affiliates are principally volunteer organizations that raise their own money and operate under independent budgets. They are not directly affected by the national group's financial troubles.</p>
        <p>Officials at the organization's headquarters in Baltimore did not answer their telephones today, but at offices around the country members of the staff were continuing to work without pay.</p>
        <p>"Basically, we are volunteering our time," said Rob Robinson, a staff member in the New York office. "While we are having financial difficulties, we recognize the job we do is important."</p>
        <p>The only staff members who continue to be paid are those whose work is financed through special, restricted grants made for specific purposes, board members said.</p>
        <p>Several board members voiced dismay at the furlough, saying that staff members were informed of it by telephone over the weekend and that little information was available even to board members.</p>
        <p>The board members said that the group's executive committee decided on the furlough over the weekend, after auditors from the accounting firm Price Waterhouse recommended it.</p>
        <p>The accounting firm, which is not the group's regular independent auditor, was brought in on an emergency basis to review the group's finances, the board members said.</p>
        <p>They also said that the Ford Foundation, a major donor to the association, had agreed to resume financing for the organization's operations once Price Waterhouse's recommendations are put into effect.</p>
        <p>Spokesmen for the Ford Foundation and Price Waterhouse declined to disclose any details of the arrangements, which board members said were intended to allow the N.A.A.C.P. to resume normal operations, begin paying off its accumulating bills, and most critically of all, increase its fund-raising activities.</p>
        <p>But the board members conceded that raising money will be difficult.</p>
        <p>In August, the N.A.A.C.P.'s board dismissed the organization's executive director, Benjamin F. Chavis Jr., after directors learned that he had approved the spending of hundreds of thousands of dollars to settle a threatened sexual harassment suit.</p>
        <p>More recently, the syndicated columnist Carl Rowan renewed the criticisms of the group's leaders, asserting that William F. Gibson, the board chairman, may have misused his expense account, a charge that Mr. Gibson has denied.</p>
        <p>Joe Madison, an N.A.A.C.P. board member in Washington who spent 10 years as a political organizer on the group's staff, said that the furloughs might hurt the group's efforts to get voters to the polls next week, but he said that he expected most of the staff to keep working.</p>
        <p>More important, he said, is the group's efforts to restore its reputation, especially because the end of the year is the time when, for tax reasons, many individual contributors decide how much money to give to charities.</p>
        <p>"What the N.A.A.C.P. needs to do is to restore a sense of confidence in its leadership," he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gibson, the board chairman, has called for special audits of the spending of all top officials, but Mr. Madison said that in his opinion Mr. Gibson should resign. Mr. Gibson could not be reached for comment.</p>
        <p>Hazel Dukes, another board member, said that staff members were bitter about their treatment and that she had apologized to those with whom she works in New York.</p>
        <p>Another board member, who insisted on anonymity, said that senior staff members had a "heated meeting" with Earl Shinhoster, the interim leader, on Monday, complaining about the emergency measures.</p>
        <p>Only a few days ago, Mr. Shinhoster and Mr. Gibson kicked off a nationwide appeal for support with a half-hour radio broadcast from the Pittsburgh headquarters of the American Urban Radio Networks, whose 250 stations are focused on African-American audiences.</p>
        <p>The group's radio campaign, announced two weeks ago, takes as its theme: "Imagine an America without an N.A.A.C.P."</p>
        <p>Attracting new members is critical to the group's success, since nearly three-fourths of the national group's annual budget comes from memberships and individual donations.</p>
        <p>But it is the local branches, youth councils and college chapters, that actually sign up the members and funnel the money to the national headquarters. The national group focuses on politics, legal cases, and other activities that require a professional staff.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
