<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Old Haunt</title>
    <meta content="12njdine" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/12/travel/12njdine.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746141"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E06E4D61231F931A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1131" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Old Haunt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Old Haunt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CORCORAN</byline>
      <dateline>STANHOPE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Robert and Jean Duda first laid eyes on Bell's Mansion five years ago, about all it had left were a grand history and a liquor license.</p>
        <p>Built when Andrew Jackson was president, owned for more than a century by wealthy industrialists, the old mansion had long since fallen on bad times. By 2001 it had been empty for two decades -- a listing pile of bricks and rotting shingles overrun by raccoons, squirrels and if you believe the local legend, the ghosts of its former owners, the Bells and the Salmons. A plan by a more recent owner to turn it into an inn -- hence the liquor license -- had collapsed, along with much of the roof.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>STANHOPE.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Robert and Jean Duda first laid eyes on Bell's Mansion five years ago, about all it had left were a grand history and a liquor license.</p>
        <p>Built when Andrew Jackson was president, owned for more than a century by wealthy industrialists, the old mansion had long since fallen on bad times. By 2001 it had been empty for two decades -- a listing pile of bricks and rotting shingles overrun by raccoons, squirrels and if you believe the local legend, the ghosts of its former owners, the Bells and the Salmons. A plan by a more recent owner to turn it into an inn -- hence the liquor license -- had collapsed, along with much of the roof.</p>
        <p>It would be hard to imagine what the Dudas saw in the old place if it weren't for what they've made of it since. Today Bell's Mansion, on a maple-shaded rise overlooking this old mill-and-canal town, glows with the pride of renewal.</p>
        <p>The new owners gutted the place, polished every square inch to a high gloss and outfitted it with the fruits of years of relentless antiquing -- most astoundingly, a 15-foot, 1,200-piece stained-glass window, which Mr. Duda painstakingly reassembled and hung over the bar.</p>
        <p>The place is no museum, though. In part this is because many of the furnishings are more knickknacks than antiques, and in part it's because some of the rooms are rather dim and cramped. But mostly it's because Bell's is a working restaurant, a vibrant, bustling community hub. Like the old mansion, Stanhope had seen better days; Bell's has given it a welcome infusion of energy.</p>
        <p>And much of that liveliness can be found on the menu, the work of another Duda import: Roger Mora Valverde, the husband of Mr. and Mrs. Duda's daughter Tracey. (Their other daughter, Jennifer Konya, is a manager.) Mr. Mora Valverde, 32, came to New Jersey from Costa Rica at age 20 and taught himself to cook, notably in the kitchen of the Dudas' first restaurant, Muldoon's in Ledgewood.</p>
        <p>His style is as eclectic as the décor. The splendiferously antlered ''double shovel'' caribou, whose head hangs in the lobby, found an echo one recent night on the list of main-course specials: elk with a rum-and-peppercorn glaze, Asian-pear-parsnip purée, red verjuice sauce, thyme and (I'm not done) caramelized lingonberries and apples.</p>
        <p>For all its moving parts, the dish was terrific -- the elk reminiscent of venison but pleasingly gamy and liverish; the peppercorns whole, crunchy and biting; the fruits dark and sweet but far from cloying. Sometimes, though, perhaps in an effort to satisfy too many appetites (the restaurant seats 160 people), the kitchen has trouble keeping everything under control.</p>
        <p>The menu stretches on for five densely packed pages, and it would benefit from some serious editing. It's easy, for instance, to see why beef Wellington remains such a temptation to diners and chefs: a thick cut of filet mignon in an opulent mantle of puff pastry and mushroom duxelles makes a spectacular entrance every time. But too often, as here, it's weighty and dull.</p>
        <p>Seafood Fra Diablo was bland and undifferentiated, as were lobster ravioli; Yucatán salad with a market basket of ingredients (sugar-cane-grilled shrimp, Manchego cheese and avocado, to name three) was wrestled to the ground by its sweet chipotle vinaigrette; and warm Brie salad was undone by a peculiar streusel-like topping.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Mora Valverde is no dilettante. He is confident and creative across a startling range of cuisines: Italian, Asian, Latin, Southern, New American, Old American. Roasted eggplant medallions, stacked in Napoleonic layers with roasted peppers and basil pesto, were solid and satisfying. A standard shrimp cocktail was lifted by its central ingredient -- four juicy jumbo shrimps -- and by a lively assortment of dipping sauces. Seafood bisque was a little starchy, but it had plenty of flavor and plenty of seafood. Floating on its surface was a nifty little flourish, crab meat salad on a raft of fried tomato.</p>
        <p>Two other main-course specials were carefully cooked and explosively flavorful: rack of lamb with roasted potatoes, sautéed spinach and mustard sauce turbocharged by piquillo peppers; and Chilean sea bass in a crackling crust of pistachios and Vietnamese rice paper. ''Drunken duck'' sounded over the top: marinated in tequila, it came with verjuice-and-guava sauce and mascarpone polenta. But somehow all these ingredients managed to speak to one another, if not exactly in the same language.</p>
        <p>If you think you won't have room for dessert, you're right -- especially since these dishes are as exuberantly caloric as the rest of the menu. Still, if you must make the sacrifice, you'll enjoy the sweet, dark caramelized pineapple, its warmth melting a monster scoop of Mounds ice cream; the moist, rich architecture of the chocolate pyramid; and an immense, perfect pecan tart, with butter-pecan ice cream garnished with extra pecans.</p>
        <p>Service here is sweet but a bit scattered, especially on busy nights. If a long pause develops between courses, get up and wander. If you're lucky, Jean Duda, stationed at the reservation desk, will take you on a little tour of the old Bell's Mansion, in the form of photos showing the place as she and her husband found it.</p>
        <p>Close your eyes and you'll hear the wind rattling the broken shutters, the raccoons scrabbling in the bar, and the shades of departed Bells and Salmons, as pleased as you are by what's become of their old house.</p>
        <p>Bell's Mansion  11 Main Street  Stanhope  (973) 426-9977  www.bellsmansion.com</p>
        <p>GOOD</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- A massive, ancient, lovingly restored mansion with many smallish dining rooms. Always lively, and noisy when full. Smoking will be allowed in the bar until the statewide ban takes effect on April 15.  SERVICE -- Cheerful but sometimes slow.  DRESS -- Casual.  WINE LIST -- Solid and fairly priced, with a fine selection of whites and reds by the glass.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Roasted eggplant medallions, seafood bisque, shrimp cocktail; elk, rack of lamb, Chilean sea bass, drunken duck; caramelized pineapple, pecan tart, chocolate pyramid.  PRICE RANGE -- Lunch entrees, $7.99 to $13.99. Dinner: appetizers, $5.99 to $13.99; entrees, $11.99 to $28.99; desserts, $6.99 to $8.99.  HOURS -- Closed Monday. Tuesday to Thursday, from 11:30 a.m. to 11 p.m.; Friday, from 11:30 a.m. to 2 a.m.; Saturday, 4 p.m. to 2 a.m.; Sunday, 4 to 11 p.m.  CREDIT CARDS -- American Express, MasterCard, Visa.  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended. After 6 p.m. on Saturdays, reservations are accepted only for groups of six or more.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESS -- Fully accessible.  IF YOU GO -- Stanhope is in Sussex County, about a mile north of Exit 27B from Interstate 80. Follow Ledgewood Avenue (Route 183) through the Netcong traffic circle. After about four-tenths of a mile, the restaurant is on the left.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS Comments? Recommendations? E-mail: njdine@nytimes.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Comments? Recommendations? E-mail: njdine@nytimes.com.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
