<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stop the Presses (Or the Web Sites)</title>
    <meta content="12njworth-2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1746314"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="WORTH NOTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060312T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DF1031F931A25750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="325" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stop the Presses (Or the Web Sites)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN MILLER</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Did you hear about Assemblyman So-and-So? He's a drunk. Councilman Such-and-Such? Didn't pay alimony. How about the gubernatorial candidate XYZ? You don't want to know.</p>
        <p>Juicy tidbits like these are offered almost every day on Web sites, often from anonymous writers. Many times, it is the handiwork of fevered dreams and warped minds. Other times, it is true.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Did you hear about Assemblyman So-and-So? He's a drunk. Councilman Such-and-Such? Didn't pay alimony. How about the gubernatorial candidate XYZ? You don't want to know.</p>
        <p>Juicy tidbits like these are offered almost every day on Web sites, often from anonymous writers. Many times, it is the handiwork of fevered dreams and warped minds. Other times, it is true.</p>
        <p>Enter Peter J. Biondi, a Republican assemblyman from Somerset County, who said he had had enough after hearing from constituents upset about disparaging remarks they've read on the Web site Nj.com.</p>
        <p>''Geez,'' he said in an interview last week, ''What happened to civility?''</p>
        <p>So he has proposed a bill to make illegal the posting of anonymous comments online. The measure, which was introduced in the State Legislature in January, would force Web sites that post messages on public forums to have those posters ''either to be identified by legal name and address or to register a legal name and address.''</p>
        <p>Most experts say that the bill is of dubious constitutionality. Mr. Biondi said he had no intention of limiting free speech, but noted, ''You have the right to say whatever you want, until you go to far, and then it's libel.''</p>
        <p>As a poster named Tumbledry noted on the Somerset County forum on Nj.com: ''Thanks Pete for making NJ a laughing stock of the nation again! Best work since Raritan tried to ban cursing!''</p>
        <p>Joe Territo, the vice president for Advance Internet, which operates NJ.com, declined to comment.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. Biondi said that his office had been besieged by irate calls and e-mail messages, and later he seemed to scale back his intentions. ''It is becoming apparent that the bill may be too broad in scope and in reality not enforceable,'' he wrote.</p>
        <p>Though he stands behind the bill, he said, ''If it turns out that the bill is, in fact, unworkable, unconstitutional, or unenforceable, I'll certainly reconsider and withdraw it.''</p>
        <p>JONATHAN MILLER</p>
        <p>WORTH NOTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
