<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. NOW EXPECTS THE MIDEAST TALKS TO TAKE TIME OUT</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="484959"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="THE MIDDLE EAST TALKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SYRIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ISRAEL</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MADRID (SPAIN)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHARAA, FAROUK AL- (MIN)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Syria</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain/Madrid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Spain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911105T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DC133AF936A35752C1A967958260" item-length="1152" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. NOW EXPECTS THE MIDEAST TALKS TO TAKE TIME OUT</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</byline>
      <dateline>MADRID, Nov. 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>American officials said today that there would have to be a pause before reconvening the next round of direct Middle East peace talks to allow the negotiators time to consider their positions and enable the United States to find a new meeting place.</p>
        <p>And, because of the failure of Syria and Israel to make any headway in their direct talks, which ended about 3 a.m. today, officials who were part of Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d's contingent said they would probably have to come up with ideas of their own to break the impasse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>American officials said today that there would have to be a pause before reconvening the next round of direct Middle East peace talks to allow the negotiators time to consider their positions and enable the United States to find a new meeting place.</p>
        <p>And, because of the failure of Syria and Israel to make any headway in their direct talks, which ended about 3 a.m. today, officials who were part of Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d's contingent said they would probably have to come up with ideas of their own to break the impasse.</p>
        <p>Unlike the talks between Israel and the Jordanian-Palestinian delegation, which agreed to discuss Palestinian self-rule, there was no such accord between the representatives of Syria and Israel. The Optimistic Reading</p>
        <p>The only mildly encouraging development was a departure statement by the Syrian Foreign Minister, Farouk al-Sharaa, who said he believed that the Israeli people wanted peace but that their Government was blocking the way.</p>
        <p>"I think the Israelis as a people desire peace," he said. "They are looking for peace. Israel is a special case, where the Government is more hawkish than the people. In the Arab world, it is just the opposite. We are more flexible than the Arab people."</p>
        <p>The Syrian official spoke to reporters after five hours of direct talks with Israeli representatives. Both sides said that these first contacts had made no progress but also said they were committed to continuing direct talks when and if they could agree on a site.  Taking Time to Consider</p>
        <p>American aides said they would take time out from the discussions to let the Mideast adversaries digest the implications of what has happened so far, and try to hammer out a compromise on where the next round of direct talks should take place.</p>
        <p>The Israelis want discussions to alternate between towns in their country and in Arab lands. The Syrians, Palestinians, Jordanians and Lebanese want them held in Madrid, under the umbrella of this conference, or in some other neutral site outside the Mideast. It is expected that Mr. Baker will invite the negotiating parties to Washington sometime in the next month.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Sharaa's departure remarks today were considered highly polemical, Arab journalists present said they could not recall such an overture to the Israeli people from the hard-line Syrians.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharaa, however, does not seem to have been suddenly transformed by the contact with Israel here. His comments appear to have been prompted, at least in part, by the negative publicity he received in the Western press for his behavior and remarks in Madrid.</p>
        <p>The Syrian had held up an old "wanted" photograph of the Israeli Prime Minister, Yitzhak Shamir, during Mr. Shamir's underground days, and also engaged in vitriolic exchanges with the Israelis. Today, throughout his news conference, Mr. Sharaa took pains to say that his comments had been misunderstood by the Western news media.</p>
        <p>Of all the delegations in Madrid, the Syrians were the least experienced in dealing with the public and the press.  They tried to avoid calling on Israeli reporters during news conferences and often issued handwritten statements, while the Israelis, Palestinians, Jordanians and Lebanese were running off copies in several languages.</p>
        <p>Some Syrian journalists said privately that they were embarrassed, and predicted that their closed society would have to open a bit if Syria intended to compete in the game of public diplomacy with Israel and the Palestinians.</p>
        <p>On the substance of Sunday night's face-to-face contacts, Syrians and Israelis were in full agreement: Each heard nothing from the other that suggested a compromise was possible.</p>
        <p>The Syrian team was headed by an experienced former diplomat, Muwaffaq al-Allaf, while the Israelis were led by the Egyptian-born Yossi Ben Aharon, director general of Prime Minister Shamir's office, a man known for hard-line views.</p>
        <p>The Syrians said their negotiating strategy had been to keep repeating that they were not ready to discuss the substance of peace unless Israel first committed itself to withdrawing from the territories captured in the 1967 war, and particularly the Golan Heights.</p>
        <p>The Israelis said they were trying to persuade the Syrians to open direct communication outside the talks, and to discuss small, confidence-building gestures each side might take, before trying to deal with the territorial issue.  Dialogue at Cross-Purposes</p>
        <p>"It was in every respect futile," Mr. Ben Aharon said afterward, "because what they kept telling us constantly was 'When will you withdraw from the territories?'</p>
        <p>"We invited them them to Israel," he recounted. "They said no.</p>
        <p>"We asked them to establish a link between us. They said no.</p>
        <p>"We asked them to sign a peace treaty. They said no.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ben Aharon continued: "We asked if they accepted the legitimacy of Israel, even in Tel Aviv, and they said it is not a relevant issue now. They refused any other venue for the talks other than Madrid and would not go anywhere in the Middle East.</p>
        <p>"We said, 'Why don't we host you? Wouldn't you want us in Syria so your people will change their minds about us?' He kept saying that 'Once you withdraw, everything will be resolved.' "</p>
        <p>Members of the Israeli delegation described the Syrian negotiators as professional, armed with briefing papers, well versed in all the relevant United Nations documents, but extremely standoffish. There were no handshakes, and the two sides took their coffee breaks in separate rooms.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharaa, who did not personally take part in the talks, said after briefings by his negotiators that "the Israeli delegates rejected all the requirements for peace; the Israeli head of delegation talked about everything other than the land that has been occupied for 24 years."</p>
        <p>He added: "The equation in our region is very clear. The Syrian delegate spoke about both land and peace. The Israeli delegate dropped the land, kept it under the feet of their soldiers, and spoke only empty rhetoric about peace."</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, said Mr. Sharaa, "our delegates will continue to resume the bilateral talks, and, of course, we are waiting for the co-sponsors to come up with a proposal for the next venue. We don't think our presence in the peace conference or ensuing negotiations is a waste of time."</p>
        <p>American officials say the Syrian-Israeli discussion, if it is to make progress, will require the greatest amount of mediation and other intervention, since neither side has any pressing need to compromise.</p>
        <p>Secretary Baker, who left Madrid on Sunday night and flew with President Bush today to California, said: "We're encouraged that the talks took place at all. They were businesslike and carried off in a constructive atmosphere. No one walked out in the conference or the bilateral. There is a sense of engagement now that bodes well for the future."</p>
        <p>THE MIDDLE EAST TALKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
