<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Whitman's Multitudes, For Better And Worse</title>
    <meta content="18whit" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/11/18/books/18whit.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1718389"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Poetry and Poets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Public Library</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Whitman, Walt</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051118T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EEDA113EF93BA25752C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1754" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Whitman's Multitudes, For Better And Worse</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Whitman's Multitudes, for Better and Worse</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL FRANK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anniversary exhibitions built around the publication of an author's Major Work often have a dutiful air. Books in first and subsequent editions are prettily arranged in glass cases, along with relevant manuscripts, photographs and ephemera. And don't forget the lock of hair, neatly braided or twirled just so, supplying the illusion that the great man (or woman) is somehow just out of sight.</p>
        <p>You blink and imagine the hair on the head, the head on the body, the writer sprung to life, asking, as we do, why this, why now, what other than a dot on a calendar has brought us all, squinting and reverent, into this dim, sober, marbled room?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New York Public Library's exhibition commemorating the 150th anniversary of the first edition of "Leaves of Grass" has a distinct point of view.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anniversary exhibitions built around the publication of an author's Major Work often have a dutiful air. Books in first and subsequent editions are prettily arranged in glass cases, along with relevant manuscripts, photographs and ephemera. And don't forget the lock of hair, neatly braided or twirled just so, supplying the illusion that the great man (or woman) is somehow just out of sight.</p>
        <p>You blink and imagine the hair on the head, the head on the body, the writer sprung to life, asking, as we do, why this, why now, what other than a dot on a calendar has brought us all, squinting and reverent, into this dim, sober, marbled room?</p>
        <p>To the credit of Isaac Gewirtz, curator of the Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature at the New York Public Library, the exhibition he has mounted on the 150th anniversary of the first edition of Walt Whitman's ''Leaves of Grass'' is commemoration with a point of view. That is a good thing, because Whitman's poem is one of those literary mazes, with passages brilliant and tedious, through which it is possible to follow dozens if not hundreds of ideas. Even when the book is regarded merely as an object, with its nine (or more) separate editions and countless other issues in Whitman's lifetime alone, the story is a dense one.</p>
        <p>So what is driving the show ''I Am With You'' other than the nice round number of years that have elapsed since July 4, 1855, when Whitman, a former schoolteacher, printer, journalist and editor, first published his bold, unruly and groundbreaking poem? Drawing on the library's extensive holdings, Mr. Gewirtz has put on display at least one copy of every authorized American edition of ''Leaves,'' along with the separate collections of poetry that Whitman later incorporated into his work, which he expanded, rearranged and revised nearly until the day he died.</p>
        <p>He has opened these books to specific pages, written extensive labels and published an accompanying pamphlet, with the goal, he said in an interview, of bringing attention to three aspects of ''Leaves'' that he believes have gotten short shrift: the poem's spiritual message, its homosexual aspects and its author's racial views.</p>
        <p>Through these themes, Mr. Gewirtz said, ''I Am With You'' endeavors to ''modulate the image of Whitman as the 'good gray poet' and champion of democracy.'' Perhaps it doesn't matter so much that this cozy, fossilized view of Whitman is, by now, a bit of a straw man. Mr. Gewirtz brushes aside the straw and, to take the knottiest theme first, explains that salvation, in Whitman's spiritual journey, ''inheres in the journeying itself'' and ''is a process of moment-to-moment awakening.''</p>
        <p>As ever with Whitman, the goal is an open, perceiving, feeling self; he was less interested in talking about God than ''about his own Oneness experience.''</p>
        <p>Examples of Whitman's spirituality, thus defined, abound in the first edition of ''Leaves'' (in later editions he began to formulate different ideas about a personal deity):</p>
        <p>I have said that the soul is not more than the body,</p>
        <p>And I have said that the body is not more than the soul,</p>
        <p>And nothing, not God, is greater to one than one's-self is.</p>
        <p>Or:</p>
        <p>I hear and behold God in every object, yet I understand God not in the least,</p>
        <p>Nor do I understand who there can be more wonderful than myself.</p>
        <p>(The spiritual invariably seems to bring out the most epigrammatic in the poet.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Gewirtz interprets Whitman's abounding selffulness as being more Eastern than Western in sensibility. ''The 'myself' of which Whitman speaks in such contexts,'' he writes, ''is not the ego, but what the Hindu Vedas, Upanishads and other Eastern spiritual traditions call 'the higher self.' '' Since Whitman ''sees no distinction between inner and outer, all that exists is God, which makes 'God' an unnecessary concept.''</p>
        <p>A summary of a summary hardly does anyone's thinking justice -- but there is a compression to this reading that feels a bit hasty; perhaps ideas given by slant and snippet can feel no other way. The exhibition seems on much steadier ground when it seeks to convey Whitman's homosexuality, even if it has to look outside of ''Leaves'' (to diary entries and the first draft of a poem in which the object of Whitman's love, in later drafts changed to a woman, is expressly a man) for corroboration.</p>
        <p>It is important to remember that Whitman on heterosexual sex was strikingly explicit for serious literary writing in his or anyone's time, most famously in ''A Woman Waits for Me'' (''I pour the stuff to start sons and daughters fit for These States -- I press with slow rude muscle''), which belongs to ''Enfans d'Adam,'' one of the titled sequences of poems clustered together in ''Leaves.''</p>
        <p>Whitman was unprecedented, too, in the way he portrayed women as erotic beings (think of the woman in ''Song of Myself'' spying on naked male swimmers, a subject Whitman's friend Thomas Eakins later took for his painting ''The Swimming Hole''), but he did not politicize heterosexuality the way he did homosexual ''adhesiveness,'' and it is in this that Whitman is arguably at his most daring.</p>
        <p>While the actual sexual language of the Calamus cluster of poems is less explicit than its heterosexual counterpart -- ''He ahold of my hand has completely satisfied me'' is about as racy as it gets -- and was written in an era when expressions of physical affection between men were not automatically categorized as homosexual, Whitman believed that the ''manly love of comrades'' was fundamental to a truly democratic America. Men loving men would promote equality, respect and mutual admiration and thereby do away with destructive exploitation and violence.</p>
        <p>Men thus connected would cease exploiting one another and would ''make the continent indissoluble.'' Interestingly -- or is it naïvely? -- he held to this belief even during the high carnage of the Civil War:</p>
        <p>Affection shall solve the problems of Freedom yet;</p>
        <p>Those who love each other shall become invincible.</p>
        <p>''I Am With You'' takes its name from a line in the poem that came to be called ''Crossing Brooklyn Ferry'': ''I am with you, you men and women of a generation, or ever so many generations hence.'' In titling his pamphlet essay, Mr. Gewirtz amends the line to ''I Am With [Some of] You'' and in this way underlines one of the more problematic aspects of Whitman's thinking and writing, his undeniable racism. Like T. S. Eliot's anti-Semitism, Whitman's ideas about blacks present a granite-hard stumbling block, one to reckon with or (if you can) step around.</p>
        <p>Here, as in many places, Whitman was a paradox, and held ideas that changed over the years. He wrote a poem in the voice of an angry slave (''The Sleepers'') and another compassionately portraying an older female slave (''Ethiopia Saluting the Colors''), yet he also expressed sympathy for the plight of the slave owner. Because he believed that abolition would lead to an insuperable division and war in his beloved union, he was at the same time anti-abolition and antislavery.</p>
        <p>But his racial views were not merely political. While in ''Leaves'' he cushioned his sentiments, as though intuiting their unpalatable nature, he was probably never more off-putting and narrow-sighted than when it came to his conviction, expressed in writings published and unpublished, of the inferiority of blacks, whose ''intellect and caliber'' he most egregiously likened to those of ''so many baboons.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gewirtz's selection of books, manuscripts and photographs makes several ancillary, more contained points about Whitman and his poem. You can feel Whitman's experience as a printer and compositor, for example, in his cover design for the first edition of ''Leaves,'' with its gilt-stamped tendriled letters and leaf, fern and flower motifs. You can see Whitman the endless reviser at work in many places, but most notably in ''The Blue Book,'' a copy of the 1860-61 edition, thus named because it was bound in blue paper wrappers; this is the actual copy that Whitman marked up to prepare the 1867 edition.</p>
        <p>Whitman the sly promoter of his own work and life surfaces in a manuscript titled ''Analysis of Leaves of Grass''; supposedly by Richard Maurice Bucke, who published a biography of Whitman, the page on display, describing how British critics and readers appreciate Whitman's work better than their American counterparts, is actually in Whitman's hand.</p>
        <p>The exhibition's photographs tell a poignant parallel story: Whitman young (or youngish) shimmers out of a daguerreotype made at the beginning of his career, and we watch him age through successive images, with an ever more lined face and smoky, thickening swirl of beard. There is an 1864 picture of the Knickerbockers Nine, a nod to Whitman's love of baseball. (He trenchantly said that it embodied the ''snap, go, fling, of the American atmosphere.'') And there is ''Wounded Soldiers in Hospital,'' a Civil War-era photograph that sets a visual cue for one of the more compelling interludes in Whitman's biography, the four years he spent in Washington, where by his own estimate he nursed 80,000 to 100,000 of the war's wounded, an experience he summed up as ''the greatest privilege and satisfaction'' and ''the most profound lesson in my life.''</p>
        <p>And that lock of hair? It was most likely cut by Whitman himself; certainly he identified it on one side of its mounting, ''Walt Whitman/America -- Oct. 29 1891'' and on the other, ''A lock of hair/WW 73d year.''</p>
        <p>Bent into a tiny, tidy wreath, it has a surprising amount of gold in it for a fellow his age. But for Whitman, of all writers, this corporeal token seems hugely beside the point. As he wrote in a late contribution to ''Leaves'':</p>
        <p>This is no book;</p>
        <p>Who touches this, touches a man.</p>
        <p>'' 'I Am With You': Walt Whitman's 'Leaves of Grass' (1855-2005)'' remains through Jan. 8 at the New York Public Library, Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street; (212) 869-8089.</p>
        <p>Michael Frank is a short-story writer and book critic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Frank is a short-story writer and book critic.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
