<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawyers for Kaczynski Agree He Is Competent to Stand Trial</title>
    <meta content="21UNAB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Health; U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989317"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unabomb Case</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glaberson, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Sally C (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kaczynski, Theodore J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burrell, Garland Jr (Judge)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unabom Case</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4DC1E38F932A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="1496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawyers for Kaczynski Agree He Is Competent to Stand Trial</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glaberson, William</byline>
      <dateline>SACRAMENTO, Calif., Jan. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense lawyers, after reviewing sealed psychiatric evaluation by Dr Sally C Johnson, concede Theodore J Kaczynski is competent to stand trial in Unabomb case; Johnson reportedly found he suffers from serious mental illness; Judge Garland E Burrell Jr suggests he will keep current defense team in place and hold Kaczynski to accord to use mental-illness defense at least in penalty phase of trial; indicates Kaczynski's bid to represent self comes too late and only will serve to delay trial (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Theodore J. Kaczynski is competent to stand trial on charges that he is the Unabomber, defense lawyers conceded today. Then, with that issue resolved, the Federal judge in the case suggested that he would keep the current defense team in place and hold Mr. Kaczynski to an agreement to use a mental-illness defense at least in the penalty phase of his trial, which is to begin on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The judge, Garland E. Burrell Jr., suggested that Mr. Kaczynski had asked to represent himself too late and only to delay his trial. And Judge Burrell said the appointment of new lawyers would only postpone a struggle over whether Mr. Kaczynski or his lawyers should control the question of whether to portray him as mentally ill as a way to try to avoid the death penalty.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Theodore J. Kaczynski is competent to stand trial on charges that he is the Unabomber, defense lawyers conceded today. Then, with that issue resolved, the Federal judge in the case suggested that he would keep the current defense team in place and hold Mr. Kaczynski to an agreement to use a mental-illness defense at least in the penalty phase of his trial, which is to begin on Thursday.</p>
        <p>The judge, Garland E. Burrell Jr., suggested that Mr. Kaczynski had asked to represent himself too late and only to delay his trial. And Judge Burrell said the appointment of new lawyers would only postpone a struggle over whether Mr. Kaczynski or his lawyers should control the question of whether to portray him as mentally ill as a way to try to avoid the death penalty.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaczynski's protest against a psychiatric defense would resurface with almost any new lawyer, the judge said. Then, Judge Burrell said, ''we will be right back in the situation we're in right at this moment.''</p>
        <p>In his remarks today, Judge Burrell said he would make final rulings on the question of who represented Mr. Kaczynski and how at a hearing at 8 A.M. on Thursday. The jury, which has been selected but not sworn, will be instructed to appear at the courthouse here at 10 A.M. for the scheduled start of the trial.</p>
        <p>The concession that Mr. Kaczynski is competent came after defense lawyers and the judge reviewed a sealed competency evaluation filed this weekend by Dr. Sally C. Johnson, a court-appointed psychiatrist.</p>
        <p>Because prosecutors had maintained that Mr. Kaczynski met the low threshold of mental fitness to be qualified to stand trial, the concession by the defense resolved the issue without any ruling from the judge.</p>
        <p>Dr. Johnson's report, filed under seal and not released publicly, concluded that Mr. Kaczynski, while competent to stand trial, suffered from serious mental illness, including ''schizophrenia, paranoid type,'' said a lawyer who had consulted on the case and had read the report.</p>
        <p>That is the same diagnosis the defense team has suggested applies to Mr. Kaczynski. Dr. Johnson concluded that Mr. Kaczynski had delusions that he was being ''maligned and harassed by family members and modern society.''</p>
        <p>Lawyers were still evaluating the 47-page report today, and it seems certain to be the subject of much debate as efforts are under way to reopen plea-bargain negotiations, with each side trying to use Dr. Johnson's conclusions to support its positions. The Justice Department has rejected several offers by Mr. Kaczynski to plead guilty in return for avoiding the death penalty.</p>
        <p>The lawyer who read Dr. Johnson's report said it suggested a direct link between Mr. Kaczynski's mental illness and the Unabom campaign. ''Consistent with other individuals with persecutory types of delusions,'' said a report excerpt provided by the lawyer, ''he is resentful and angry and fantasizes and actually does resort to violence against those individuals and organizations that he believes are hurting him.''</p>
        <p>Judge Burrell did not make any final rulings today in the case that spiraled out of his control when Mr. Kaczynski made a public demand for control over his defense on Jan. 5, the scheduled first day of his trial.</p>
        <p>In a court hearing today, Judge Burrell said, ''Tentatively, I'm not inclined to bring in new lawyers.'' And his remarks from the bench suggested he was leaning toward barring Mr. Kaczynski from representing himself. Mr. Kaczynski sat calmly at the defense table today between the two public defenders with whom he has been warring, Quin Denvir and Judy Clarke.</p>
        <p>Some legal experts said decisions by Judge Burrell limiting Mr. Kaczynski's control over his case would undoubtedly create grounds for appeal. But some experts also said it appeared the judge had found solid legal arguments to justify rulings that would avoid the spectacle of Mr. Kaczynski's handling his own case or relying on lawyers who might try to turn the case into a political trial.</p>
        <p>The judge also said today that he was researching the legal question of whether Mr. Kaczynski had obligated himself to go along with his current lawyers' plans for a limited psychiatric defense. Judge Burrell said Mr. Kaczynski had reached such an accord in a private session with the lawyers and judge on Dec. 22.</p>
        <p>In that session, as the judge described it today, Mr. Kaczynski agreed that he would permit psychiatric testimony during a penalty phase of the trial, if he was found guilty. A penalty phase would be conducted to determine if he would be sentenced to death. He is charged here with four bombings, two of which resulted in death.</p>
        <p>After the Dec. 22 meeting, the defense submitted a formal notice withdrawing its plan to use expert witnesses to assert during the first phase of the trial that Mr. Kaczynski suffered from a ''mental defect.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kaczynski's rebellion against his lawyers accelerated a few days later when Ms. Clarke and Mr. Denvir began plans to argue that he suffered from mental illness during the first phase of the case by using evidence other than the testimony of experts. Judge Burrell indicated that he had not decided whether to force Mr. Kaczynski to accept such references to psychiatric illness in the first phase of the case.</p>
        <p>Dr. Johnson's report described Mr. Kaczynski as suffering from delusions of persecution and ''erotomanic delusions'' that included ''idealized romantic relationships with women with whom he has little familiarity or contact.''</p>
        <p>In addition to what she called a provisional diagnosis of paranoid schizophrenia, Dr. Johnson found that Mr. Kaczynski was suffering from other serious mental illnesses, including ''paranoid personality disorder with avoidant and antisocial features (premorbid).''</p>
        <p>There has been a widespread sense among lawyers and legal scholars that Judge Burrell is under pressure to avoid allowing the case to become the embarrassment to the system it might become if Mr. Kaczynski was permitted free rein.</p>
        <p>At the hearing today, the judge painstakingly worked his way through the quagmire of legal issues Mr. Kaczynski had created. As he discussed each with prosecutors and defense lawyers, Judge Burrell seemed to be methodically trying to regain power over the pace and direction of the case.</p>
        <p>First, he said, he had telephoned the office of Tony Serra, the San Francisco lawyer who has represented Black Panthers and members of the Symbionese Liberation Army. Mr. Kaczynski had said he wanted Mr. Serra to replace his lawyers.</p>
        <p>The judge said Mr. Serra's office had reported that he was not available for trial at least until next September. The chief prosecutor, Robert J. Cleary, who had urged the judge to permit Mr. Kaczynski to change lawyers, agreed that was ''untenable.''</p>
        <p>When he reached the subject of the meeting on Dec. 22, Judge Burrell telegraphed his views on a series of complex legal issues. He wondered from the bench, for example, whether the justice system would permit a defendant to meet with a judge and defense lawyers extensively, reach an agreement about how the defense would be conducted and then change his mind. ''It appears,'' Judge Burrell said, seeming to direct his remarks toward Mr. Kaczynski, ''you have wasted the judge's time and interfered with the orderly administration of justice.''</p>
        <p>The judge suggested that Mr. Kaczynski might be bound to the agreement to go along with his lawyers as long as they withdrew plans for the formal ''mental defect'' defense in the guilt phase. Judge Burrell said he was still researching whether that agreement had been ambiguous.</p>
        <p>One prosecutor, R. Steven Lapham, said he was uncertain that Mr. Kaczynski could be held to an agreement that a layperson might not have understood clearly. The prosecutors have repeatedly said they fear that Judge Burrell's ruling could result in an appeals court's overturning any guilty verdict.</p>
        <p>Some legal experts, like Prof.  Franklin E. Zimring of Boalt Hall Law School at the University of California at Berkeley, said appeals courts were likely to struggle as well to assure that a jury verdict, if there is one, stands. Appeals courts, he said, might share the view that is apparently shared by the defense lawyers and Judge Burrell that under the unique circumstances of a defendant who cannot bear to be described as mentally ill, his lawyers should control whether to use a psychiatric defense. Professor Zimring said appeals courts could rule that even if such a defense was conducted over the protest of Mr. Kaczynski, it could do no harm to him legally.</p>
        <p>''Nobody is willing to accept his own preferences to foreclose a psychiatric inquiry as the best defense against the death penalty,'' Professor Zimring said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
