<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No. 1 Suits Blue Devils Just Fine</title>
    <meta content="21MAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989367"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES: MEN'S BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EFDB1E38F932A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="780" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No. 1 Suits Blue Devils Just Fine</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Roundup of college basketball results (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DUKE 101, NORTH CAROLINA A&amp;T 66</p>
        <p>William Avery scored 11 points during a two-and-a-half-minute span in the first half as Duke rolled over North Carolina A&amp;T, 101-66, last night in Greensboro, N.C., in the Blue Devils' first game since regaining the No. 1 ranking.</p>
        <p>Trajan Langdon also added 11 of his 16 points in Duke's 57-point opening half for the Blue Devils (17-1). The Aggies, led by Jonathan Richmond's 15 points, fell to 4-10 and 0-11 career against schools from the Atlantic Coast Conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DUKE 101, NORTH CAROLINA A&amp;T 66</p>
        <p>William Avery scored 11 points during a two-and-a-half-minute span in the first half as Duke rolled over North Carolina A&amp;T, 101-66, last night in Greensboro, N.C., in the Blue Devils' first game since regaining the No. 1 ranking.</p>
        <p>Trajan Langdon also added 11 of his 16 points in Duke's 57-point opening half for the Blue Devils (17-1). The Aggies, led by Jonathan Richmond's 15 points, fell to 4-10 and 0-11 career against schools from the Atlantic Coast Conference.</p>
        <p>Duke, which was No. 1 for the first two weeks of December before losing to Michigan, made 20 of 33 shots (60.6 percent) in the opening 20 minutes to grab a 27-point halftime lead.</p>
        <p>The Blue Devils started each half with 10-0 runs and were nearly as dominant in between.</p>
        <p>The Aggies did close to 22-15 midway through the first half before Langdon converted a three-point play, made a pair of technical free throws called against A&amp;T Coach Roy Thomas, and Roshown McLeod's shot in the lane made it  29-17.</p>
        <p>PROVIDENCE 58, BOSTON COLLEGE 54</p>
        <p>Kendrick Moore hit four free throws in the closing 11.2 seconds as visiting Providence overcame a 12-point second-half deficit and downed Boston College.</p>
        <p>The Friars had trailed by 43-31 with just under 16 minutes left, but held the Eagles to only three field goals in the final 17 minutes and one in the closing 10 minutes 12. seconds</p>
        <p>Jamel Thomas led the Friars  (8-8 over all, 3-4 Big East) with 17 points. Llewellyn Cole added 15 points and 9 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Antonio Granger paced Boston College (10-9, 2-6) with 21 points and 11 rebounds, his second consecutive double-double.</p>
        <p>CLEMSON 69, VIRGINIA 52</p>
        <p>Tony Christie had a career-high 17 points as No. 25 Clemson held off visiting Virginia's second-half rally.</p>
        <p>Christie's four 3-pointers helped the Tigers (12-6, 3-3 Atlantic Coast Conference) take a 40-22 lead with 17:38 to go. But Clemson managed only two field goals in the next 10 minutes as the Cavaliers (10-9, 2-4) pulled within eight points.</p>
        <p>Greg Buckner then scored four points and Christie another three in an 14-6 run that gave the Tigers their fourth victory in five tries against Virginia. Buckner finished with 19 points.</p>
        <p>MICHIGAN 65, MINNESOTA 57</p>
        <p>Robert Traylor had 21 points and 12 rebounds as No. 16. Michigan temporarily took over sole possession of first place in the Big Ten .</p>
        <p>Maceo Baston added 15 points and 14 rebounds and Louis Bullock 10 points for the Wolverines (15-4, 5-1 Big Ten). Michigan began the night in a three-way tie for first with Michigan State and Iowa, who play tonight in Iowa City.</p>
        <p>Sam Jacobson scored 21 points and Kyle Sanden added 11 for Minnesota (7-10, 0-6).</p>
        <p>XAVIER 72, JOSEPH'S 62</p>
        <p>In Cincinnati, Gary Lumpkin and Torraye Braggs led a balanced attack by scoring 14 points apiece, and No. 19 Xavier turned up the defensive intensity as it beat St. Joseph's.</p>
        <p>Xavier (12-4, 4-2 Atlantic 10) gained control early as Lumpkin scored six consecutive points and pulled away by rattling St. Joseph's (5-8, 1-5) with its full-court press and half-court traps.</p>
        <p>James Posey and Darnell Williams added 12 points apiece for Xavier. Rashid Bey scored 16 to lead St. Joseph's, which has lost five of its last six.</p>
        <p>CINCINNATI 60, TULANE 50</p>
        <p>D'Juan Baker scored 8 straight points down the stretch as No. 21 Cincinnati held off a late Tulane rally for a Conference USA victory in New Orleans.</p>
        <p>The Bearcats (14-2, 6-0) won their 10th straight game. The Green Wave (6-11, 1-4) lost for the fifth time in six games.</p>
        <p>Cincinnati let a 23-point lead shrink to four before putting the game away at the foul line.</p>
        <p>FRESNO STATE</p>
        <p>Daymond Forney and Avondre Jones were suspended indefinitely yesterday, the latest setbacks to hit Coach Jerry Tarkanian's program.</p>
        <p>The school issued a one-sentence announcement that they were suspended for violating team rules. Officials refused further comment as to the reason.</p>
        <p>Tarkanian told one reporter that the Bulldogs would have to go on without Forney and Jones, who had been starters.</p>
        <p>COLLEGES: MEN'S BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
