<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I.B.M. Offers Profit Warning for Quarter</title>
    <meta content="Y21BLU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989274"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY REPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Far East, South and Southeast Asia and Pacific Areas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Business Machines Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hansell, Saul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EED71138F932A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="967" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I.B.M. Offers Profit Warning for Quarter</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAUL HANSELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hansell, Saul</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>IBM warns that its earnings for first quarter of 1998 will be dragged down by rising dollar, sales decline in Asia and several one-time factors, even as it reports earnings in fourth quarter of 1997 that are slightly above expectations; in fourth quarter, company earned $2.1 billion, up 3.4 percent from $2 billion a year earlier; for 1997, IBM earned $5.9 billion, up from $5.4 billion in 1996; revenue in 1997 was $78.5 billion, increase of 3 percent; chart (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I.B.M. warned yesterday that its earnings for the first quarter would be dragged down by the rising dollar, a sales decline in Asia and several one-time factors, even as it reported earnings in the fourth quarter of 1997 that were slightly above expectations.</p>
        <p>In the fourth quarter, the International Business Machines Corporation earned $2.1 billion, up 3.4 percent from $2 billion a year earlier. On a per-share basis, the earnings were up 9.3 percent, to $2.11 a share from $1.93, largely because $7 billion in stock buybacks in 1997 reduced the number of shares outstanding.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I.B.M. warned yesterday that its earnings for the first quarter would be dragged down by the rising dollar, a sales decline in Asia and several one-time factors, even as it reported earnings in the fourth quarter of 1997 that were slightly above expectations.</p>
        <p>In the fourth quarter, the International Business Machines Corporation earned $2.1 billion, up 3.4 percent from $2 billion a year earlier. On a per-share basis, the earnings were up 9.3 percent, to $2.11 a share from $1.93, largely because $7 billion in stock buybacks in 1997 reduced the number of shares outstanding.</p>
        <p>Nonetheless, the rising dollar had already undercut the company's fortunes. Over all, the company's revenue increased by 3 percent in the fourth quarter, to $23.7 billion. But if the dollar had stayed at a constant exchange rate, increasing sales overseas would have increased revenue by 8 percent.</p>
        <p>The company also had to write off $50 million to $75 million from losses in Asia, mainly related to the failure of Yamaichi Securities in Japan.</p>
        <p>The results were released after the market closed. Earlier, the company's shares rose $3.375, to $108.375, but they gave up some of those gains in after-hours trading.</p>
        <p>Speaking to analysts, Lawrence R. Ricciardi, I.B.M.'s acting chief financial officer, said the company's earnings for the first quarter of 1998 would be 10 to 15 cents a share below the $1.16 it earned in the first quarter of 1997. That represents a potential decline of as much as 17 percent, or close to $200 million, from the $1.2 billion I.B.M. earned in the first quarter of 1997.</p>
        <p>This reflects further appreciation of the dollar, a slowdown of sales in many Asian countries, and continued pressure to cut prices. Furthermore, I.B.M. will take one-time write-offs related to its $200 million acquisition of Software Artistry, a maker of help-desk software, and will have unusual expenses related to its sponsorship of the Winter Olympics in Nagano, Japan.</p>
        <p>''No one of these factors is extraordinary or unusual, but taken together, we have had an extraordinary concatenation of events,'' Mr. Ricciardi said in an interview yesterday.</p>
        <p>I.B.M., like many big companies, has tried to hedge its risk from a rising dollar, but Mr. Ricciardi said that it had not prepared for changes of the magnitude that have been seen in Asia.</p>
        <p>''With devaluations in currency anywhere from 12 percent to 66 percent, country by country, since the end of June to today, you are facing a market in which the purchasing power of local companies has been significantly reduced,'' he said. The declines are somewhat offset by lower costs from I.B.M.'s manufacturing plants in Singapore and Thailand, he said.</p>
        <p>In the fourth quarter, overall sales in the company's Asia-Pacific region were flat as gains in Australia and China were offset by declines elsewhere. The fastest-growing region was North America, which posted a 9 percent revenue increase.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ricciardi was upbeat about the company's prospects for the rest of this year, beyond the first quarter.</p>
        <p>''I am not prepared to hang any black crepe with respect to Asia,'' Mr. Ricciardi said. ''I am starting to feel that Asia may be turning back.''</p>
        <p>Analysts were surprised at Mr. Ricciardi's optimism. ''Our economists are more concerned about the serious ramifications of the Far East,'' Steven Milunovich, an analyst with Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, said. None of the other potential expenses in the first quarter particularly troubled analysts, despite the high cost of advertising and providing technology related to the Olympics.</p>
        <p>''The Olympics are an important way for I.B.M. to show their customers what they can do,'' Mr. Milunovich said. ''They had some problems last time in Atlanta, so it's good that they are not backing off.''</p>
        <p>Over all, I.B.M.'s hardware sales declined 1 percent in the fourth quarter, hurt by declines in the very largest mainframe computers sold to businesses and in personal computers sold to consumers.</p>
        <p>The company's services business, the source of much of its recent growth, slowed slightly, with revenue increasing by 18 percent in the quarter, the first time in recent years that the growth has been less than 20 percent.</p>
        <p>''We expect to grow faster than the overall services business and do it profitably,'' Mr. Ricciardi said, ''But we don't expect to grow at prior years' rates.''</p>
        <p>Software sales increased by 1 percent, with strong sales of its data base, Lotus Notes and Tivoli computer management products.</p>
        <p>Over all, the company's gross profit margin -- its sales minus the cost of the goods sold -- was 40.1 percent, down slightly from a year earlier.</p>
        <p>Expenses increased by only 1 percent, to $6.5 billion, helped by lower costs overseas. In constant currency, expenses rose by 5 percent.</p>
        <p>For the full year, I.B.M. earned $5.9 billion, up from $5.4 billion in 1996, in which the company took about $500 million in special charges. Its 1997 revenue was $78.5 billion, an increase of 3 percent.</p>
        <p>COMPANY REPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
