<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Finding on Mixing Sexes in Military</title>
    <meta content="21MILI$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Defense Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shenon, Philip</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Youngman, Judith A (Prof)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sexual Harassment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D07E1DD1E38F932A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="718" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Finding on Mixing Sexes in Military</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHILIP SHENON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shenon, Philip</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Defense Advisory Committee on Women in Services reports most members of armed services want more integration of sexes during early training; all-civilian panel says trainees believe all-male training schools foster more negative attitudes toward women; findings conflict with recent recommendation of advisory panel on sexual harassment that men and women be separated during much of training; Prof Judith A Youngman, main author of new report, comments (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only a month after one advisory committee urged the Defense Department to separate men and women during much of their military training, another Pentagon panel has found that most members of the armed services actually want more integration of the sexes during their early months in uniform.</p>
        <p>The new report by the Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services, a panel formed in the 1950's to advise the department on women's issues, said that an inspection of 12 military training schools last year showed that ''most service members from every service believed that more gender integration of training was needed than currently existed.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Only a month after one advisory committee urged the Defense Department to separate men and women during much of their military training, another Pentagon panel has found that most members of the armed services actually want more integration of the sexes during their early months in uniform.</p>
        <p>The new report by the Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services, a panel formed in the 1950's to advise the department on women's issues, said that an inspection of 12 military training schools last year showed that ''most service members from every service believed that more gender integration of training was needed than currently existed.''</p>
        <p>The investigation found that trainees from all four branches of the armed services believed that all-male training schools fostered ''more negative and prejudicial attitudes toward women,'' according to the all-civilian committee -- composed of 18 women and 2 men with academic, business and military backgrounds.</p>
        <p>The committee's findings were welcomed by the advocates of mixed-sex training, who said they hoped the report would convince Defense Secretary William S. Cohen to reject the findings of a separate committee that recommended that the Army, Navy and Air Force significantly roll back the integration of men and women in basic and advanced training.</p>
        <p>That panel -- led by former Senator Nancy Kassebaum Baker, Republican of Kansas, and created in response to a series of sexual harassment scandals involving military trainers -- found in a report made public last month that integrated training had undercut efforts to make men and women work together effectively.</p>
        <p>By separating the sexes, the panel found, the services could head off potential disciplinary problems and improve the morale of women.</p>
        <p>The principal author of the new report, Judith A. Youngman, an associate professor of political science at the United States Coast Guard Academy in New London, Conn., who was the chairwoman of the Defense Advisory Committee last year, said she had been surprised by the findings of the Kassebaum Baker panel.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't want to say that the Kassebaum Baker report was mistaken,''' Ms. Youngman said in an interview. ''But its findings were not consistent with what we heard from service members in the field or fleet. What we heard was that service members were overwhelmingly in favor of gender-integrated training. I think our report does raise questions about the Kassebaum Baker report.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman in Washington for Mrs. Kassebaum Baker said the former Senator was traveling today and unavailable for comment. The executive director of the committee, Lori E. Murray, said that even though the panel was drawn from diverse backgrounds, it still reached its conclusions unanimously.</p>
        <p>''The committee was asked for their best advice, and that's what they gave the Secretary,'' Ms. Murray said.</p>
        <p>The Defense Advisory Committee  reports directly to the Secretary of Defense and is a respected voice within the Pentagon on issues involving women in uniform.</p>
        <p>Secretary Cohen and the leaders of the four branches of the armed services will now weigh the conflicting findings of the two reports in deciding on the future of integrated military training.</p>
        <p>In a statement issued today along with the Defense Advisory Committee report, Mr. Cohen did not say whether he accepted or rejected its findings, much as he did not accept the reject the conclusions of the Kassebaum Baker panel.</p>
        <p>The number of women serving in the military has been steadily climbing over the last quarter century, reaching 14 percent of the 1.4 million troops now on active duty. But integrating men and women in basic and advanced training is still relatively new.</p>
        <p>The Army began the practice only in 1993, after conducting trials in the late 1970's and early 80's. The Navy began integrated training in 1994.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Kassebaum Baker's panel did not recommend that men and women be completely separated during training, but rather that they be kept apart at the level of core units -- the platoon in the Army, the division in the Navy and the flight in the Air Force. The recommendation would bring those services into line with the Marine Corps, which has resisted integrating men and women in basic training.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
