<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>About New York; Architecture Doesn't Stop At 96th Street</title>
    <meta content="21ABOU" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hamilton Theater (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Harlem (NYC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gonzalez, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Adams, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE0DB1138F932A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="775" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>About New York; Architecture Doesn't Stop At 96th Street</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Gonzalez, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>David Gonzalez About New York column discusses work of Michael Adams, preservationist and architectural historian devoted to protecting architectural landmarks in Harlem; his plan to restore Hamilton Theater on West 146th St discussed; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE chorus girls on Broadway stood still as statues, but they made Michael Adams's eyes dance. He craned his neck to behold the slender, bare-chested figures that flanked the windows on the old Hamilton Theater on West 146th Street.</p>
        <p>''They look like burlesque queens from Ziegfeld's Follies,'' Mr. Adams said. ''Incredible. On the front of the building the keystones over the windows have comedic masks. It always struck me how in these vaudeville houses they decided there would never be any tragedy, so they just put up the mask of comedy.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE chorus girls on Broadway stood still as statues, but they made Michael Adams's eyes dance. He craned his neck to behold the slender, bare-chested figures that flanked the windows on the old Hamilton Theater on West 146th Street.</p>
        <p>''They look like burlesque queens from Ziegfeld's Follies,'' Mr. Adams said. ''Incredible. On the front of the building the keystones over the windows have comedic masks. It always struck me how in these vaudeville houses they decided there would never be any tragedy, so they just put up the mask of comedy.''</p>
        <p>Tragedy, it turns out, wears a dust mask. Work crews were converting the lobby of this once-grand vaudeville house and movie theater in Hamilton Heights into a department store. The walls had been stripped down to the brick, where white outlines were a ghostly reminder of mirrored arches. One man sorted through a pile of clothing scattered among the plaster and paint chips, ignoring the chipped cherub that hovered above on a frieze.</p>
        <p>This raises complicated questions for Mr. Adams, a preservationist and architectural historian devoted to protecting Harlem's physical riches. An active business beats an empty, gated storefront in an area that needs more investment. But why is there no corresponding investment in protecting and landmarking the elegant structures that graced these neighborhoods, some of which have been covered with gaudy siding or slathered with stucco?</p>
        <p>While well-organized advocates rally elsewhere in the city to protect their treasures, Mr. Adams said that only 7.5 percent of Manhattan's landmarked buildings are above 96th Street.</p>
        <p>''We're not against economic development, but why is it necessary to destroy something irreplaceable?'' Mr. Adams asked. ''In SoHo or TriBeCa, those features are used to attract people. Here, it's thrown in the Dumpster like it's trash.''</p>
        <p>Or scavenged and sold to those downtown stores that recycle bits of buildings in exchange for chunks of your wallet. On 149th Street, Mr. Adams pointed to the half-peeled copper dome of a synagogue that had been turned into a Christian church. Hammered-copper lions' heads once graced the dome, but they were swiped ages ago. On the facade, cinder blocks covered what had once been windows.</p>
        <p>''I was looking at a book on urban artifacts and there was no mention of Harlem in the index,'' Mr. Adams said. ''But in caption after caption, you see fireplace mantels or doorways that used to be in Harlem.''</p>
        <p>It was enough to drive him to seek the esthetic haven of Ann Dobson's apartment. She has lived since 1956 in a stately building on Riverside Drive and 150th Street that had once been home to Marian Anderson and Ralph Ellison. Ms. Dobson's nine-room apartment features leaded windows with stained-glass details, impeccable floors and sweeping river views.</p>
        <p>HE and Ms. Dobson, a friend, commiserated over the demise of the Hamilton Theater, which she used to visit for first-run movies. That era seemed distant, a reminder of the time when apartments like hers were common, before landlords cut them up to house the thousands of immigrants that settled into upper Manhattan. Now she sometimes feels it's too painful to walk down Broadway and confront the memories stirred by aging or covered-up facades. She takes some comfort in the efforts of Mr. Adams and some of her longtime neighbors.</p>
        <p>''This is part of our history,'' she said. ''When I go to other cities in Europe, I see all these places that are 500 years old being used, still being viable. We won't have anything in this city over 100 years old if we keep on tearing it down.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Adams said he hoped to prod city officials into protecting the interior of the Hamilton Theater, which has already survived years of use as a soda and beer warehouse. He is also pushing to extend the boundaries of the Hamilton Heights Historic District, among other concerns.</p>
        <p>He knows that a lot of the new arrivals in the uptown neighborhoods may be more preoccupied with paying the rent than preserving worn-out architectural details, but he is optimistic that proposed Federal legislation offering tax credits for landmarked buildings may help some banks and investors become involved.</p>
        <p>He insists that Harlem's past doesn't have to vanish with present progress.</p>
        <p>''So many different groups of people have seen this area as the destination of their dreams,'' he said. ''You have this rich cultural and architectural heritage, like the synagogue that is now a church. This layering of culture on top of culture is like an illustration of what America is about.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
