<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cuban Church: It's Weak but Unified</title>
    <meta content="Y21CHUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Education" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="989241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Roman Catholic Church</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Niebuhr, Gustav</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pope (John Paul II)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Castro, Fidel (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Church-State Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shortages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Priests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980121T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1DA1138F932A15752C0A96E958260" item-length="1175" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cuban Church: It's Weak but Unified</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GUSTAV NIEBUHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Niebuhr, Gustav</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pope John Paul II, during Cuba visit, will find Roman Catholic Church vastly weakened under Fidel Castro's rule, shoved by Government to margins of Cuban society; experts say church, while short of priests and deprived of school system, is unified, through its bishops, determined to try to push for dialogue with Government and role in society; table; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Pope John Paul II arrives in Cuba today, he will encounter a Roman Catholic Church vastly weakened under Fidel Castro's rule, shoved by the Government to the margins of Cuban society since before the Second Vatican Council, which introduced sweeping reforms into Catholicism worldwide.</p>
        <p>It is a church short of priests and  deprived of its school system, and its bishops have been accused in the past of being counterrevolutionary by Mr. Castro, who has spoken harshly of his own religious education by Jesuits in the early 1940's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Pope John Paul II arrives in Cuba today, he will encounter a Roman Catholic Church vastly weakened under Fidel Castro's rule, shoved by the Government to the margins of Cuban society since before the Second Vatican Council, which introduced sweeping reforms into Catholicism worldwide.</p>
        <p>It is a church short of priests and  deprived of its school system, and its bishops have been accused in the past of being counterrevolutionary by Mr. Castro, who has spoken harshly of his own religious education by Jesuits in the early 1940's.</p>
        <p>Yet experts on the Cuban church  say it is unified and, through its bishops, determined to try to push for a dialogue with the Cuban Government and a role in Cuban society.</p>
        <p>As for Mr. Castro, his views on religion are perhaps more nuanced (or more opportunistic) than his declared atheism would initially suggest. He has publicly expressed admiration for the Pope, an anti-Communist who also offers a moral critique of Darwinian capitalism.</p>
        <p>Since the 1970s, Mr. Castro has been aware of the power of alliances between left-wing Christians, influenced by political forms of ''liberation theology,'' and secular revolutionaries in Latin America. He met with Christian socialists in Chile during Salvador Allende's presidency and had considerable contact with the leaders of Nicaragua's Sandinista Front, which included two priests.</p>
        <p>When he sat for a long interview with a Brazilian Dominican friar in 1985, Mr. Castro said Marx would probably have agreed with the Sermon on the Mount.</p>
        <p>The Pope's visit does not technically mark a rapprochement between the Vatican and Cuba, as Mr. Castro's Government never severed diplomatic ties with the Holy See, even while it undercut the church.</p>
        <p>Despite its nearly 500-year history,  the Cuban church never had the universal appeal Catholicism has in the Pope's native Poland. Still, the church suffered heavily when Mr. Castro's Government took over 245 Catholic schools and expelled scores of foreign priests in 1961.</p>
        <p>The Government accused the church of being reactionary and dedicated largely to the rich. Those moves, together with restrictions on religious expression outside church walls, had the effect of largely severing the church from much of society.</p>
        <p>''There's been a whole generation that has not known the church,'' said Prof. Alex Garcia-Rivera, a Cuban theologian who teaches at the Jesuit School of Theology at Berkeley, Calif. ''But they do have stories from their parents and grandparents.''</p>
        <p>What also restricts the church's reach now is a shortage of manpower. American Catholic leaders worry about an emerging shortage of priests in the United States, where there is one clergy member for approximately every 1,100 baptized Catholics. But in Cuba, the situation is far worse, with a ratio of about one priest for every 16,000 Catholics.</p>
        <p>Despite such daunting difficulties, the Cuban church is now ''a very unified church, which is often the case during oppressive regimes,'' said Thomas E. Quigley, a policy adviser with the United States Catholic Conference.</p>
        <p>The author of an essay on the Cuban church in ''Catholicism and Politics in Communist Societies'' (Duke University, 1990), Dr. Quigley said the church endured a period of ''marginalization'' in the 1960's and 1970's, a period of nearly unbroken public silence by the bishops.</p>
        <p>The Cuban church, he said, began to stir under the inspiration of a landmark Latin American bishops' conference that met in Puebla, Mexico, with Pope John Paul II in 1979. Among other things, the conference endorsed Catholics' taking a ''preferential option for the poor,'' committing themselves primarily to serving the impoverished, a theme emphasized in liberation theology.</p>
        <p>Cuban bishops and priests embarked on a period of ''renewal and reflection,'' Dr. Quigley wrote. Since that time, the Cuban bishops have felt confident enough to request talks with the Government on church-state relations.</p>
        <p>Although Dr. Quigley said the appeal has gone unanswered, the church has benefited from the recent relaxation of official hostility toward religious activities. In the early 1990's the Government declared the state to be ''secular,'' not atheist, a change that has been followed by a growth in church attendance.</p>
        <p>But one effect of the greater tolerance of religion may pose a new challenge to the Catholic Church. The Rev. Pablo Oden Marichal, a prominent Cuban Episcopal priest, said in a recent interview with Religion News Service that the number of Protestant churches in Cuba had grown by more than half since 1992, to nearly 1,700, a number that included small congregations that meet in people's homes. It made Protestantism visible, he said, especially outside the urban areas, to Cubans who were ''looking for religion.''</p>
        <p>Practicioners of Santeria, an Afro-Cuban religion involving the invoking of spirits, are more visible, too, and their rites more public, said Andres Perez y Mena, an associate professor of educational anthropology at Long Island University at Brooklyn. Because Santeria borrows heavily from Catholic symbols, it is widely assumed to have a large following among baptized Catholics. Some authorities assert that the Government has quietly encouraged its growth as a counter to the church.</p>
        <p>The immediate concern is what the church may gain as a result of the Pope's visit. Some experts say they expect Catholic leaders to seek permission for visas for more foreign priests to help rebuild the church's ''infrastructure.''</p>
        <p>In a sense, it was Mr. Castro who contributed to a greater awareness of religion, at least as an intellectual topic, in Cuba. In 1985, he gave a series of interviews to Frei Betto, a Brazilian friar, which were later published as a book, ''Fidel and Religion.'' It sold widely in Cuba, even inspiring study groups among some religious believers.</p>
        <p>In it, Mr. Castro affirmed his own atheism. But he also said religious faith could be a ''marvelous help.''</p>
        <p>The book, Dr. Quigley said, ''piqued the curiosity of a lot of people.'' Negative though it was about much of Christian life, he said, ''it legitimated or helped to legitimate the discussion of religion.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
