<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dow Rises 47.63 to Second Straight Record</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="521682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCK PRICES AND TRADING VOLUME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FAISON, SETH JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DC1639F935A25757C0A964958260" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dow Rises 47.63 to Second Straight Record</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SETH FAISON Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FAISON, SETH JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks rallied again yesterday, with the Dow Jones industrial average reaching a closing high for the second consecutive day, on a second day of upbeat earnings reports.</p>
        <p>The Dow jumped 47.63 points, or 1.4 percent, to 3,353.76. After a sharp rise at the opening, the Dow climbed gradually through morning trading, steadied itself in the early afternoon, and then shot upward in the final 30 minutes of trading. It closed near the day's high. On Tuesday, the Dow closed above 3,300 for the first time.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks rallied again yesterday, with the Dow Jones industrial average reaching a closing high for the second consecutive day, on a second day of upbeat earnings reports.</p>
        <p>The Dow jumped 47.63 points, or 1.4 percent, to 3,353.76. After a sharp rise at the opening, the Dow climbed gradually through morning trading, steadied itself in the early afternoon, and then shot upward in the final 30 minutes of trading. It closed near the day's high. On Tuesday, the Dow closed above 3,300 for the first time.</p>
        <p>Trading was heavy yesterday, with volume on the New York Stock Exchange at 229.7 million shares, compared with 231.1 million on Tuesday. Gaining stocks outnumbered losing ones by 1,111 to 651.</p>
        <p>The advance rippled through the broader market, with the Standard &amp; Poors' index of 500 issues up 3.89 points, to 416.28, nearing its record high of 420.77, set on Jan. 15. The Nasdaq Composite index was up 5.22 points, to 600.03.</p>
        <p>"This week, we've seen better-than-expected earnings at one company after another," said Ricky Harrington, director of equity investments at Marion Bass Securities. "Now we've got double-barreled action: stable, low interest rates, and improving economic signs."</p>
        <p>In Chicago, trading in the futures markets returned to near-normal conditions after two days of disruptions following flooding in the financial district that began Monday.</p>
        <p>The Mercantile Exchange held regular trading hours for the first day this week, and volume totaled an estimated 459,000 contracts, down from this year's daily average of 549,000. The Chicago Board of Trade, where workers were still pumping water from a flooded basement, reopened for a shortened, two-hour session in an annex building and in one floor of its 43-story main building.</p>
        <p>"Volume was fairly light, but at least we were open again," said Michael Oakes, manager of corporate communications for the Board of Trade. "Not everybody had their computers up, for fear of overtaxing the system." Mr. Oakes said the exchange would again be limited to two hours of trading today, and closed for the holiday on Good Friday.</p>
        <p>The gains in stocks yesterday were aided by four moderate program trades, said Philip Smyth, an analyst at Birinyi Associates. But the day's big buying, other analysts said, was fueled by positive earnings reports by Coca-Cola, A.T.&amp; T., Motorola and others.</p>
        <p>Those companies were up smartly. Motorola jumped 6, to 82; Coca-Cola rose 1 3/8, to 83 3/8, and A.T.&amp; T. rose 1/4, to 42 7/8. But the optimism caused by the earnings news also affected big companies that benefit from cyclical economic changes.</p>
        <p>International Paper, for example, was up 3 7/8, to 76 1/4; Goodyear Tire jumped 4, to 75 3/8, and Caterpillar, which agreed with the United Automobile Workers union to end a strike at its plant in Peoria, Ill., went up 4 3/8, to 53 7/8. Among over-the-counter stocks, Microsoft was a big winner, rising 11 7/8, to 128 7/8, after most of a copyright suit by Apple Computer Inc. against Microsoft was disallowed.</p>
        <p>Last week's action by the Federal Reserve Bank to lower interest rates, analysts said, was instilling confidence among investors.</p>
        <p>"The market is still responding to what the Fed did last week," said Peter G. Grennan, head of stock index futures trading at Shearson Lehman Brothers. "They sent a message that they were on top of the situation and are going to stay there. There is suddenly a lot more confidence in this market."</p>
        <p>There were some losers yesterday. Centocor Inc. fell a stunning 12 3/4, to 18 1/2, while purchase warrants for Centocor stock fell even further, losing 24, to 18 1/2. The Food and Drug Administration advised the company that there was not enough evidence to justify approval of its HA-1A drug, the company's flagship drug.</p>
        <p>Only a day earlier, the company's main rival, Xoma Corporation, was given similar news from the Government. Xoma's stock fell 4 yesterday, to 14 1/2. Together, Xoma and Centocor drove biotechnology stocks down a full 5 percent.</p>
        <p>Analysts pointed out that the rally had swept along most of the market. Among the 30 industrial stocks that make up the Dow average, only one stock is down in the five days of trading since the current rally began.</p>
        <p>Goodyear is up 13.7 percent during that period; Caterpillar has risen 12.2 percent, and Alcoa is up 11.3 percent. Woolworth, which recently reported disappointing same-store sales this year, was the only stock to fall.</p>
        <p>"This market is something like a steamroller now," Mr. Harrington said. "There is no telling how it's going to go."</p>
        <p>Other companies whose stock rose after issuing positive news reports yesteday included: Sprint, up 2 1/4, to 23 3/4; Superior Industries International up 4 5/8, to 54 1/8, and Consolidated Rail, which rose 5 1/2, to 90 1/2.</p>
        <p>Merck, which reported profits that fell short of expectations, fell 4, to 151 1/4.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
