<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Orleans Outlaws Bias By Mardi Gras Parade Clubs</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="495433"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CARNIVALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MARDI GRAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARADES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ORGANIZATIONS, SOCIETIES AND CLUBS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW ORLEANS (LA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARCUS, FRANCES FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARTHELEMY, SIDNEY (MAYOR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana/New Orleans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Louisiana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mardi Gras</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parades</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organizations, Societies and Clubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Holidays and Special Occasions</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DC1530F932A15751C1A967958260" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Orleans Outlaws Bias By Mardi Gras Parade Clubs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCES FRANK MARCUS,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARCUS, FRANCES FRANK</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS, Dec. 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The New Orleans City Council has voted unanimously to outlaw discrimination in the carnival clubs that sponsor the city's Mardi Gras parades. Mayor Sidney Barthelemy said today that the action sends a strong message "that New Orleans is an open town and everyone is recognized."</p>
        <p>The law stops clubs from excluding anyone because of "race, color, sex, sexual orientation, national origin, ancestry, age, physical condition or disability."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The New Orleans City Council has voted unanimously to outlaw discrimination in the carnival clubs that sponsor the city's Mardi Gras parades. Mayor Sidney Barthelemy said today that the action sends a strong message "that New Orleans is an open town and everyone is recognized."</p>
        <p>The law stops clubs from excluding anyone because of "race, color, sex, sexual orientation, national origin, ancestry, age, physical condition or disability."</p>
        <p>Sixty-five club leaders issued a statement Wednesday saying the proposal would be a "tragic mistake," and some city officials have said the ordinance would "kill carnival" because it would drive parades out of the city or cause clubs to cancel them. A Fixture of New Orleans</p>
        <p>The carnival, consisting of numerous parades, parties and promenades over a 12-day period that ends on Mardi Gras, or Shrove Tuesday, the last day before Lent, has been a fixture of New Orleans society since the 19th century.</p>
        <p>The Councilwoman who proposed the ordinance, Dorothy Mae Taylor, a black community worker who has been admanant that the long-segregated carnival structure must be changed, said, "As a lawmaker it's incumbent on me to do what I have to do."</p>
        <p>The City Council voted, 7 to 0, to approve the ordinance Thursday night after carnival clubs agreed to a compromise proposed by the Mayor. The compromise delays enforcement of the law for a year while the clubs and city officials try to work out their differences.</p>
        <p>The ordinance denies a parade permit to clubs that discriminate and sets penalties of $300 or five months in jail for violations.</p>
        <p>When debate on the ordinance began Thursday, carnival club leaders were determined to keep the autonomy the clubs have enjoyed in the past. Most of the clubs, which are private, are segregated by sex and most are white, but there are also prestigious black clubs.</p>
        <p>Beau Bassich, a former carnival king, said in an interview today that the law was so unpopular with club leaders that nearly half of the 27 clubs that parade in the 12 days before and on Mardi Gras might decide to cancel parades or move them outside the city. He said the compromise would give the clubs some time to decide "whether they'll have a parade."</p>
        <p>Some carnival club members said it would be easier to admit blacks to white clubs or whites to black clubs than to allow men into women's clubs or vice versa.</p>
        <p>When an 84-year-old retired leader of Iris, an organization of white women, was asked in an interview today whether men would ever be allowed to join, she replied, "Never."</p>
        <p>Another club leader, Roy E. Glapion Jr., chairman of Zulu, which produces one of the most popular parades in the city, said 20 of its 375 members are white and that he had favored the ordinance from the outset. Women as 'Associate Members'</p>
        <p>"We have been discriminated against," he said. In the past the city's white government had not given Zulu a permit to parade, and many blacks had criticized Zulu members "because we painted our faces black and wore grass skirts."</p>
        <p>Mr. Glapion said he believed the club would be willing to accept women as "associate members," and added, "If we have to accept women, we'll just have to accept women."</p>
        <p>Each Zulu member spends a minimum of $2,000 a year on club activities, he said.</p>
        <p>Lambert C. Boissiere Jr., one of the four black members of the City Council, said that in a sense Mardi Gras stemmed from exclusivity and that many clubs had sprung up because aspiring members had been barred from joining established ones. Despite the fears raised by the new law, Mr. Boissiere said, "I think more than anything it's a statement rather than an act."</p>
        <p>The Councilman also said it would be difficult to monitor the clubs for discrimination because some clubs are so exclusive they do not divulge membership."How do we enforce it?" he asked.</p>
        <p>In an interview today, Mayor Barthelemy explained why he had worked out the compromise and helped push the vote through the Council by saying, "We can't support discrimination or the perception of discrimination."</p>
        <p>Two Council members, both white, had opposed the original version; three others were undecided. One of those who had opposed the original law, Peggy Wilson, said she is opposed to discrimination but was disturbed at the tone of the debate.</p>
        <p>"I don't think I've ever seen such hatred released on the world than was unleased in the City Council last night," she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Wilson and others have said that this was not the time to initiate such a law because of David Duke's recent racially divisive campaign for governor and the fragility of the black-white coalition that defeated him. "It would have been better to have sorted this out in a more private situation," Mrs. Wilson said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
