<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trade in Auto Parts Favors Japan Despite Gains by U.S.</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="618877"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLLACK, ANDREW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0D71F31F932A35754C0A965958260" item-length="1633" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trade in Auto Parts Favors Japan Despite Gains by U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLLACK, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO, June 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Japanese automobile manufacturers appear to be on track toward reaching their target of doubling their 1990 purchases of American-made auto parts by 1994, according to executives and analysts on both sides of the Pacific.</p>
        <p>But that is not reducing the flow of auto parts Japan keeps shipping to the United States. To the chagrin of some American executives, the trade deficit with Japan in auto parts actually increased almost 10 percent last year to $10.9 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Japanese automobile manufacturers appear to be on track toward reaching their target of doubling their 1990 purchases of American-made auto parts by 1994, according to executives and analysts on both sides of the Pacific.</p>
        <p>But that is not reducing the flow of auto parts Japan keeps shipping to the United States. To the chagrin of some American executives, the trade deficit with Japan in auto parts actually increased almost 10 percent last year to $10.9 billion.</p>
        <p>Now, as Washington is pushing Japan to agree to numerical goals for buying more American products, the auto parts experience provides evidence that such an approach can open doors in Japan. Indeed, American parts are now starting to be incorporated into the designs of future Japanese autos, which could lead to bigger sales in the future.</p>
        <p>But the experience also underscores the complexities of the target-setting approach, which critics brand as managed trade.</p>
        <p>"It is true that we have increased auto parts sales," J. P. Reilly, president and chief executive of Tenneco Automotive and chairman of the Auto Parts Advisory Committee to the Commerce Department, said in a speech at a conference earlier this month in Detroit.</p>
        <p>"But we have made only marginal progress in reducing the trade deficit," he continued. "It is not because we have not tried. It is very frustrating. It seems the harder we try, the further behind we get."</p>
        <p>What is causing this to happen, he said in a later interview, is that Japanese auto makers are shifting more production to America. Even as they buy more American-made parts for their American factories, they are also importing more parts from Japan. The result: the auto parts deficit does not shrink.</p>
        <p>Americans also said that while they were happy the overall target could be reached, they had been somewhat dissatisfied with the exact nature of the purchases. To wit:</p>
        <p>*A substantial but undetermined portion of the "American" parts being purchased are made in the United States by Japanese suppliers that have set up shop in America. Such purchases, while helping Japanese-owned companies that employ Americans, do not help existing American suppliers who believe that they are locked out of the Japanese market.</p>
        <p>*Most of the American parts being purchased are for use in the American factories of Japanese auto makers. Exports of American parts to Japan are not increasing fast enough to satisfy American trade officials.</p>
        <p>*Many of the parts being purchased from American companies are simple mechanical parts as well as carpets and aluminum, rather than high-technology components like engines and electronic controls that account for much of the vehicle's value. This, however, appears to be changing.</p>
        <p>The Japanese car companies announced during President George Bush's trip here in January 1992 what they called voluntary plans that collectively would amount to purchases of $19 billion of American parts by the 1994 fiscal year, which ends in March 1995. That compared with $9 billion in the fiscal year ended March 1991.</p>
        <p>In the fiscal year that ended in March, Japanese auto companies bought $13.6 billion of American parts, up 30 percent from a year earlier, according to the Japan Automobile Manufacturers Association. If that rate of increase continues for two years, the target will be easily exceeded.</p>
        <p>The Administration is now trying to come up with proposals for what to ask Japan to do next, such as setting a new, higher target for 1996 or 1997.</p>
        <p>Japanese industry and Government officials say the purchase plan is a voluntary goal, not a promise, and that they do not want to set any more. The United States, they say, is already misinterpreting the plan as a commitment.</p>
        <p>"If we do not reach the goal we will be criticized, and if we do reach the goal the U.S. will demand a larger figure for fiscal year '95 and '96," said Hisayoshi Umemoto, manager of the auto association's parts and materials department.</p>
        <p>In any case, the United States' $31.5 billion trade deficit in autos and auto parts with Japan, which accounted for nearly two-thirds of the entire trade deficit with that country in 1992, will prove to be highly resilient. Deficit May Decline</p>
        <p>In a soon-to-be-released report, the Office for the Study of Automotive Transportation at the University of Michigan estimates that the parts deficit will range between $8.8 billion and $10.6 billion in 1996 compared with $10.9 billion in 1992. The small reduction reflects the fact that Japanese auto production in the United States is increasing, bringing in more parts from Japan.</p>
        <p>The trade deficit in autos might decline somewhat more significantly, reflecting fewer exports from Japan. The report predicts it will range from $16.6 billion to $21.08 billion in 1996 compared with $20.6 billion in 1992.</p>
        <p>Auto executives agree that the numerical target has led to a sharp increase in discussions with Japanese companies, though that has not always led to sales.</p>
        <p>"I used to go to Toyota and get shifted back and forth between international purchasing and Nummi and we couldn't get our foot in the door," said Glen Fillion, executive director of engineering for the Japanese subsidiary of the Dana Corporation. Now the Toledo, Ohio, company is supplying drive shafts for Toyota pickup truck production in both Japan and at New United Motor Manufacturing Inc., Toyota's joint venture with General Motors in California.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Japanese purchases of American parts had been rising before the target was set and would have continued rising even without a target. As more Japanese auto production has shifted to the United States, local content regulations, as well as the convenience of a nearby supplier, have worked in favor of more parts purchases from the United States. And now, with the appreciation of the yen, it makes economic as well as political sense for Japanese companies to buy American parts.</p>
        <p>But the downturn in Japan's domestic auto production has made it more difficult for the auto companies to import American parts. Japanese suppliers are hurting and starting to complain about new competition.</p>
        <p>Teiji Suzuki, executive managing director in charge of international purchasing for Nissan, recalled hearing from Mr. Reilly at the Detroit conference that American parts makers had increased their sales to Japan but not sufficiently. "I told him, 'Congratulations, Mr. Reilly, Japanese parts makers have decreased their sales to auto makers in Japan.' He didn't say anything after that." Trade Representative's Concern</p>
        <p>Mickey Kantor, the United States trade representative, said here this week that he was concerned that American exports of car parts to Japan were only $1 billion annually, or about 1 percent of Japan's $98 billion market. The 1992 purchase plan calls for $4 billion of the $19 billion in American parts purchased to be exported to Japan.</p>
        <p>Japanese officials say that imports from the United States accounted for $2.4 billion of the $13.6 billion in American parts procured last year, and that imports have more than doubled in four years. The discrepancy between the United States and Japanese figures is that the Japanese count general items like carpets and leather that are used in cars but are not classified for customs purposes as auto parts.</p>
        <p>As for the claim that they are not buying high-technology parts, Japanese companies say that such parts must be designed into the car from the outset, making it difficult to buy such parts immediately.</p>
        <p>"At the beginning, we tended to purchase parts like tires and glass that don't require joint development," said Hiroyoshi Ono, a spokesman for Toyota.</p>
        <p>Now more complex parts are being purchased, they say. Toyota recently announced it might buy cruise-control systems from the Ford Motor Company. Nissan is buying steering gears and other parts from TRW. Target Too Early</p>
        <p>Mr. Kantor, the trade representative, said Washington had already expressed its concern to the Japanese Government that much of the American parts purchased by transplant auto factories came from 400 or so Japanese-owned suppliers that had set up factories in the United States.</p>
        <p>"This is just replicating their exclusionary practices in the United States," said Lee Kadrich, director of government affairs for the Automotive Parts and Accessories Association, a trade group.</p>
        <p>But Japanese officials say that such Japanese parts factories in the United States employ Americans and often buy their components from American companies.</p>
        <p>The Japanese auto makers association will not provide figures that distinguish between American-owned and Japanese-owned factories.</p>
        <p>But a new study by the Boston Consulting Group, which was commissioned by the association to assess the quality of United States suppliers, estimates that Japanese auto factories in the United States obtain only 26 percent of their parts from traditional American suppliers. Some of the imports of American parts to Japan also come from Japanese owned companies.</p>
        <p>Still, that situation now appears to be changing as well. "Traditional suppliers have been brought into the process," Mr. Reilly said.</p>
        <p>The Boston Consulting Group said there was still a gap between American and Japanese suppliers in their ability to support Japanese auto companies.</p>
        <p>The Big Three American auto companies make 50 to 70 percent of their parts themselves and give detailed designs to suppliers for the rest. The report said American suppliers had had trouble adjusting to the system used by Japanese auto companies, which is to buy most of their parts from outside and let suppliers design those parts.</p>
        <p>Toyota established a supplier support center in Lexington, Ky., last year and is now working with 19 American suppliers on improving quality and productivity.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
