<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="01BIZD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1547419"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E4DA1F3EF932A35752C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1093" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nasdaq Led Comeback For Stocks in 2003  Stocks broke their three-year slide with robust gains last year. But the market still has a way to go to return to the heights reached during the bubble that burst in 2000. Still, the year was a great relief to investors who had lived through a recession, an anemic recovery and the worst market decline since the 1970's.</p>
        <p>For 2003, the Nasdaq composite index surged 50 percent, to 2,003.37, its third best year ever. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index climbed 26.4 percent, to 1,111.92, while the Dow Jones industrial average, which surged 6.9 percent in December, climbed 25.3 percent, to 10,453.92. [Page A1.]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nasdaq Led Comeback For Stocks in 2003  Stocks broke their three-year slide with robust gains last year. But the market still has a way to go to return to the heights reached during the bubble that burst in 2000. Still, the year was a great relief to investors who had lived through a recession, an anemic recovery and the worst market decline since the 1970's.</p>
        <p>For 2003, the Nasdaq composite index surged 50 percent, to 2,003.37, its third best year ever. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index climbed 26.4 percent, to 1,111.92, while the Dow Jones industrial average, which surged 6.9 percent in December, climbed 25.3 percent, to 10,453.92. [Page A1.]</p>
        <p>Unemployment Claims Decline  The number of Americans filing first-time applications for state unemployment benefits declined to 339,000 last week, the government said, the lowest in almost three years. Initial claims fell 15,000 in the week that ended Saturday from 354,000 a week earlier. The less volatile four-week moving average declined to 355,750 from 362,250. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Comcast Seeks Initial Share Sale  Comcast exercised an option that would allow the company to sell its stake in Time Warner's cable business in an initial public offering. Time Warner will file a registration statement with the Securities and Exchange Commission that clears the way for Comcast to sell its stake in the cable unit, according to a regulatory filing. [C3.]</p>
        <p>Auto Parts Auction Business Sold  FreeMarkets, which makes Internet-auction software, is buying the auto parts auction business of Covisint, a venture of General Motors, Ford Motor and DaimlerChrysler. Terms were not disclosed. [C2.]</p>
        <p>PPL Sells Cloning Technology  PPL Therapeutics, the company that cloned Dolly the sheep, sold the rights to its intellectual property, including cloning technology and patents, to Exeter Life Sciences for $1.35 million. Exeter is a Phoenix holding company with subsidiaries that specialize in genetic engineering of plants and animals. PPL is being dismantled after the company's scientific feats were not followed by commercial success. [World Business, Section W.]</p>
        <p>Shrimpers File Antidumping Petition  American shrimpers filed an antidumping petition against six Asian and South American countries in hopes of shoring up a fishery ravaged by competition from cheap pond-raised imports. The petition was filed by the Southern Shrimp Alliance, an eight-state group that claims the value of the United States harvest dropped by more than half from 2000 to 2002 -- to $560 million from $1.25 billion. As a result, the group says that American shrimpers are being driven out of business. [C2]</p>
        <p>Starting Small, Thinking Big  Gayle Warwick, left, an American living in London, has discovered that with barriers to trade and investment falling everywhere, she can create a mini-global empire in fine linens on a $16,000 investment and a lot of old-fashioned sweat. These days, going global is all the rage for United States entrepreneurs. Small Business. [C4.]</p>
        <p>HealthSouth Trial Rescheduled  The accounting fraud trial of HealthSouth's founder, Richard M. Scrushy, will start Aug. 23, a federal judge in Birmingham, Ala., has decided. The trial had been set to start Monday. [C5.]</p>
        <p>Avoiding Previous Blunders  Economists would be better off checking their theories against the reality of the past. A new encyclopedia of economic history can help. Virginia Postrel: Economic Scene. [C2.]</p>
        <p>Financial Markets Are Closed Today  All United States financial markets, government offices and banks are closed today in observance of New Year's Day. Most overseas financial markets are also closed. The markets will reopen tomorrow.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
