<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Wayne, Fair Housing vs. History</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="791977"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="HOUSING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WAYNE (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CHEN, DAVID W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E1D71439F932A35753C1A963958260" item-length="530" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Wayne, Fair Housing vs. History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CHEN, DAVID W</byline>
      <dateline>WAYNE</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It sounds like a familiar refrain: Old house may be demolished in favor of development. Developers want the new; historic preservationists want the old.</p>
        <p>But the case of the Kipp-Nellis farmhouse is more complicated. It involves this township's last vestige of its agricultural past, lead paint and asbestos,  fair-housing obligations and liability concerns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It sounds like a familiar refrain: Old house may be demolished in favor of development. Developers want the new; historic preservationists want the old.</p>
        <p>But the case of the Kipp-Nellis farmhouse is more complicated. It involves this township's last vestige of its agricultural past, lead paint and asbestos,  fair-housing obligations and liability concerns.</p>
        <p>Next month, a judge is to decide whether to let the township demolish the house. And already there is some jockeying over what the proper stance should be.</p>
        <p>The house was built in the 1830's by the Kipp family (for whom Kip's Bay in Manhattan) is named, as the centerpiece of a 600-acre vegetable farm. By 1973, the farm, one of the few left in Wayne, was deteriorating, and the owner, Kathryn Nellis, was aging. So the township bought the seven remaining acres of the site.</p>
        <p>Now, the eight-bedroom house is in a shambles, its hardwood floors and four fireplaces unused since the Red Cross moved out in 1985. It is boarded up, all 52 windows, with "No Trespassing" signs tacked to its white clapboard exterior.</p>
        <p>In 1993, to satisfy its fair-housing obligations under the State Supreme Court's Mount Laurel rulings, the township signed an agreement with a Roseland developer to build apartments for 95 disabled people of low to moderate income on the Nellis site. The farmhouse itself would be renovated, the contract said,  and used for social activities and administrative offices.</p>
        <p>This year, though, the township learned of the lead paint and asbestos in the house, as well as a large number of dead pigeons and their droppings. The cleanup estimates were eye-popping: $7,672 for the asbestos, up to $122,075 for  the lead.</p>
        <p>In July, the Township Council voted to amend the contract and allow demolition of the house. Next month Superior Court Judge Nicholas G. Mandak is to decide whether the amendment is valid. "We're under the gun to a certain extent," said John Fiorello, Wayne's township attorney. "If the developer pulls  out, and we can't find another developer, the township is obligated to bond $6.5 million and build it ourselves."</p>
        <p>Historic preservationists disagree -- among them Susan Pikaart, a Nellis family descendant. "We are losing our historic sites one by one," she said, "and I think somewhere you have to draw the line." And preservationists say the environmental concerns are exaggerated.</p>
        <p>"The environmental report is irrelevant," said Susan Bristol, a Rocky Hill architect who grew up in Wayne. "The building, as it's intended to be used, does not need to be remedied. In fact, the asbestos becomes more of a hazard in demolishing the building than leaving it."</p>
        <p>Indeed, environmentalists said they had not heard of any precedents where historic structured were doomed by environmental problems. Then again, they agreed that the Kipp-Nellis house was not a straightforward case.</p>
        <p>"I personally wanted to save the house," said Mayor David Waks of Wayne. "But I can't justify doing this because of the costs."</p>
        <p>HOUSING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
