<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Efforts to Restore Original Name to Park</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="792734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NAMES, GEOGRAPHICAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NATIONAL PARKS, MONUMENTS AND SEASHORES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FIRE ISLAND (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FIRE ISLAND NATIONAL SEASHORE (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MOSES, ROBERT, STATE PARK (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MOSES, ROBERT (1880-1981)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PAQUETTE, CAROLE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/National Parks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island/Fire Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Names, Geographical</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">National Parks, Monuments and Seashores</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDE1630F932A35753C1A963958260" item-length="596" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Efforts to Restore Original Name to Park</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROLE PAQUETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PAQUETTE, CAROLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN 1962 when Robert Moses resigned from the State Council of Parks, where he had been commissioner for 38 years, the council passed a resolution changing the names of three New York State parks -- Massena, Niagara and Fire Island -- to Robert Moses State Park.</p>
        <p>But the Fire Island Tourism Bureau has urged returning to the original name, to avoid confusion and to increase tourism, the organization says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN 1962 when Robert Moses resigned from the State Council of Parks, where he had been commissioner for 38 years, the council passed a resolution changing the names of three New York State parks -- Massena, Niagara and Fire Island -- to Robert Moses State Park.</p>
        <p>But the Fire Island Tourism Bureau has urged returning to the original name, to avoid confusion and to increase tourism, the organization says.</p>
        <p>"We have no problem with the name Robert Moses Causeway in honor of his accomplishments," the president of the bureau, Warren McDowell, said. "But because tourism has become Long Island's No. 1 industry the park should be called the Fire Island State Park. It would enhance the attractiveness of Long Island. It would eliminate a lot of confusion and alleviate some of the problems in the communities where they don't have public facilities by recognizing that the park is part of Fire Island."</p>
        <p>In the early 1900's, Fire Island State Park, on the western end of the barrier beach, was the lone state park on Long Island. It was on 200 acres, where in 1892 the state bought the Surf Hotel to quarantine passengers on the Normannia, which came from Europe in the midst of a cholera outbreak.</p>
        <p>Unable to manage the hotel, the state created the Fire Island State Park Commission in 1908 and financed a Boardwalk and restrooms.</p>
        <p>Ten years later a fire destroyed the restrooms, the Boardwalk and the hotel.</p>
        <p>When Moses visited the site in the early 20's he found that waves had piled sand on the western end and added 600 acres, about four miles, to the park.</p>
        <p>By 1923, Moses proposed a state park system that included Jones Beach and Fire Island State Park. A year later Gov. Al Smith appointed Moses president of the Long Island State Park Commission.  Throughout Moses' 38 years at the agency he fought Fire Island residents on his plan to build a highway across the 32-mile island that would link Ocean Parkway and the South Shore barrier beaches.</p>
        <p>"For years he was the real bogeyman of Fire Island," said Madeline C. Johnson, who wrote "Fire Island 1650's to 1980's." In the book Mrs. Johnson wrote that Moses' main argument was that the road "would preserve the island by anchoring it in place, that it would provide access to the beach for thousands now deprived."</p>
        <p>"Moses condemned his opponents as rich property owners who wanted to keep it all to themselves," she added.</p>
        <p>Perhaps selfish interests were a part of the opposition, Mrs. Johnson wrote, that a highway would have destroyed unspoiled beauty and that in cases where the spit was 500 feet wide the road would cover the entire area.</p>
        <p>Moses resigned from the park commission in 1962. In 1964, Fire Island, with 17 communities, became a National Seashore, with a state park at its western and eastern borders.</p>
        <p>Advocates of tourism are trying to reverse the name of the park on the east. "It only makes sense because it is a slap in the face to Fire Island when it was Robert Moses who had tried to put a road in that would have destroyed the communities in general," Mr. McDowell said.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Philip M. Boyle,Republican of Bay Shore, whose district includes western Fire Island, said he supported the original name. "After seeing two other state parks also called Robert Moses State Park, I think it would be a good idea," Mr. Boyle said. "We have something unique here, and people should know that."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Boyle said he had "not heard enough of an outcry."</p>
        <p>"If there is enough support," he added, "I will do something about it. It hasn't reached that point yet."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
