<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supreme Court To Weigh Gay Rights</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="792174"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMOSEXUALITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSTITUTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DISCRIMINATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND CLAIMS AGAINST GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">COLORADO</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SUPREME COURT (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Rockies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Colorado</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutional Amendments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Constitutions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06EEDF1539F932A35753C1A963958260" item-length="1211" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supreme Court To Weigh Gay Rights</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LINDA GREENHOUSE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GREENHOUSE, LINDA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Sept. 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A revolution of sorts was in progress when the Supreme Court stitched together its final 5-to-4 decisions and recessed in June. The Court's conservative wing accomplished some longstanding objectives, including curbing Federal affirmative action programs, further limiting the use of race in legislative districting and reinvigorating old notions of limits to the Federal Government's powers.</p>
        <p>So as the Justices open a new term, the question is whether the tide of fundamental change that last term battered or overturned precedents on such subjects as race and Federal authority will sweep through the Court again and find new targets among the cases on docket for the session that begins on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A revolution of sorts was in progress when the Supreme Court stitched together its final 5-to-4 decisions and recessed in June. The Court's conservative wing accomplished some longstanding objectives, including curbing Federal affirmative action programs, further limiting the use of race in legislative districting and reinvigorating old notions of limits to the Federal Government's powers.</p>
        <p>So as the Justices open a new term, the question is whether the tide of fundamental change that last term battered or overturned precedents on such subjects as race and Federal authority will sweep through the Court again and find new targets among the cases on docket for the session that begins on Monday.</p>
        <p>Some of last term's debates, most notably that over voting rights, will be carried over into the new term, which also includes important free speech and intellectual property cases. But the new case with the highest profile concerns  a subject the Court has not addressed in a decade: gay rights, in a new context  that implicates the rights not only of homosexuals but of all minority groups to seek protection within the political system.</p>
        <p>This case, which will be argued on Oct. 10, asks the Court to decide the constitutionality of an amendment to the Colorado Constitution that overrides all state and local laws and executive orders that protect homosexuals against discrimination.</p>
        <p>The amendment, titled "No Protected Status Based on Homosexual, Lesbian or Bisexual Orientation," prevents any anti-discrimination provision from being adopted or enforced in the future, unless the voters first change the constitution again. The provision, Amendment 2, was approved by the state's voters in a 1992 referendum, after a vigorous campaign in which proponents depicted homosexuals as a politically powerful special-interest group that had gained disproportionate influence on the legislative process. Denver, Boulder and several other Colorado cities had passed laws barring discrimination in housing and employment on the basis of sexual orientation.</p>
        <p>The Colorado Supreme Court struck down Amendment 2, ruling last year that because no other group faced a similar obstacle to translating its agenda into legislation, Amendment 2 violated the equal protection guarantee of the United States Constitution by restricting the ability of homosexuals to "participate equally in the political process."</p>
        <p>That approach to the case made it unnecessary for the Colorado court to declare that homosexuals as a group had a protected constitutional status, an analysis the Supreme Court would be unlikely to embrace. The Colorado court chose another route, basing its ruling on a 1969 decision by the United States Supreme Court, Hunter v. Erickson, which struck down a city charter amendment in Akron, Ohio, that had repealed existing anti-discrimination laws and required future voter approval for any local law dealing with housing discrimination. The Justices said in that case that a government could not single out any particular group for a special disadvantage in the legislative process.</p>
        <p>In its appeal in the Colorado case, Romer v. Evans, No. 94-1039, the state is arguing that the Hunter v. Erickson precedent was limited to race and was therefore inapplicable. The Colorado Supreme Court "has created out of whole cloth a new fundamental group right" that threatens principles of state sovereignty, Colorado maintains.</p>
        <p>The case has attracted wide attention, with other states lined up either for  or against Colorado's position. Numerous groups on the religious right are supporting Colorado while the gay rights groups that challenged the amendment are supported by a number of traditional civil rights organizations, as well as  the American Bar Association and the American Psychological Association.</p>
        <p>The Court has already accepted some 40 cases for decision in the new term and will add another 40 or 50 over the coming months. In that sense, the term is very much a work in progress. For example, the Court has not yet announced whether it will hear an important sex discrimination case, the Justice Department's appeal of a lower court's ruling that a separate military-style college program for women is a constitutionally adequate remedy for the state of Virginia's exclusion of women from the state-supported Virginia Military Institute.</p>
        <p>There is not yet a case that offers a target for the Court's new skepticism toward the assertions of Congress about its authority to regulate interstate commerce, although several possible candidates are in the pipeline.</p>
        <p>The 1996 election cycle will be well under way by the time the Court decides  its new voting rights cases, which will be argued in late fall. The two cases, from Texas and North Carolina, require the Court to clarify its decision last June in Miller v. Johnson, which invalidated a majority-black Congressional district in Georgia and held that the use of race as a predominant factor in drawing district lines was presumably unconstitutional.</p>
        <p>The Texas case, Bush v. Vera, No. 94-805, presents the question of how courts are to decide whether race played an illegitimate role in the drawing of district lines when the Texas Legislature also took into account considerations  of partisan advantage and incumbents' needs. A special three-judge Federal District Court in Houston invalidated three Texas Congressional districts with black or Hispanic majorities, finding them to be the product of unconstitutional racial gerrymanders.</p>
        <p>In the North Carolina case, Shaw v. Hunt, No. 94-923, a three-judge Federal District Court in Raleigh applied to the eel-like 12th Congressional District the strict scrutiny required by a 1993 Supreme Court decision and upheld the majority-black district as serving the state's "compelling interest" in complying with the Voting Rights Act. The majority in the Georgia decision last  June suggested that a broadly interpreted Voting Rights Act might be unconstitutional, so the North Carolina case could lead the Justices to confront this crucial question explicitly rather than obliquely.</p>
        <p>The Court will also revisit the punitive damages issue this year. In an Alabama case the Justices will have another chance to place constitutional limits on punitive damages. The Court has wrestled with this issue for years, but while a majority is clearly uncomfortable with large punitive damage awards  that appear to have little connection to the underlying injury, the Court has not found a constitutional theory to address the problem.</p>
        <p>This case, BMW v. Gore, No. 94-896, is a challenge to a $2 million punitive award received by a purchaser of a new BMW who sued after learning that damage to the original paint job had been repaired without disclosure. The Alabama Supreme Court held that the jury had properly taken into consideration the nationwide extent of the car manufacturer's undisclosed paint refinishing over a 10-year period.</p>
        <p>In addition, the Court's approach to a First Amendment case concerning liquor advertising could illuminate the coming constitutional confrontation over curbs  on cigarette advertising as well. The case, 44 Liquormart v. Rhode Island, No. 94-1140, is a challenge to a Rhode Island law that bars the advertising of liquor prices. The state defends the law, which was upheld by a Federal appeals  court, as holding down liquor consumption.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
