<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hillary Speaks</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="792724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="ON LANGUAGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ENGLISH LANGUAGE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BEIJING (CHINA)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNITED NATIONS (UN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, HILLARY RODHAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine/Columns/On Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">English Language</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Language and Languages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE7D91131F932A35753C1A963958260" item-length="1112" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hillary Speaks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM SAFIRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SAFIRE, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I PUT IT DIRECTLY TO the Dalai Lama, who was in Washington pressing for the protection of Tibetan culture: did Hillary Rodham Clinton's unexpectedly strong speech to the United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women, held in Beijing, help the cause of human rights in his country?</p>
        <p>"Yes," the monk in red robes replied without hesitation. "The speech will have an enormous positive impact in the long run."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I PUT IT DIRECTLY TO the Dalai Lama, who was in Washington pressing for the protection of Tibetan culture: did Hillary Rodham Clinton's unexpectedly strong speech to the United Nations Fourth World Conference on Women, held in Beijing, help the cause of human rights in his country?</p>
        <p>"Yes," the monk in red robes replied without hesitation. "The speech will have an enormous positive impact in the long run."</p>
        <p>Having elicited and reported that ringing endorsement, I feel more comfortable dissecting the speech as a piece of oratory.</p>
        <p>She made effective use of what speech writers call "the Kennedy let 'em." You will recall how J.F.K., in his Ich bin ein Berliner speech, thrice set up the straw men "some who" and demolished them with a "let them" construction: "There are some who say that Communism is the wave of the future. Let them come to Berlin."</p>
        <p>In the same way, Mrs. Clinton found "some who question the reason for this conference" and pulverized them with "let them listen to the voices of women in their homes, neighborhoods and workplaces." And what to tell "some who wonder whether the lives of women and girls matter"? "Let them look at the women gathered here."</p>
        <p>Another rhetorical device that worked was what the Greeks called epanodos, meaning "the road back," which is repetition in reverse. Shakespeare used epanodos in "Macbeth": "Fair is foul, and foul is fair." The First Lady used it in Beijing: "Human rights are women's rights. And women's rights are human rights."</p>
        <p>Epistrophe is also a Hillary specialty. That's the ending of phrases with the same term. "If women are healthy and educated, their families will flourish. If women are free from violence, their families will flourish. If women have a chance to work . . . their families will flourish." Obviously, Mrs. Clinton and her speech writer, Lissa Muscatine, decided to push alliterative epistrophe.</p>
        <p>With those positive elements noted, some constructive criticism:</p>
        <p>"Women comprise more than half the world's population." The parts do not comprise the whole; the whole comprises the parts. (A book comprises its chapters, not the other way around.) Comprise is a synonym for include, and a smaller group can never "include" the larger group; instead, smaller groups "constitute" or "form" the larger one. Our nation comprises 50 states, but the 50 states constitute, not comprise, our nation. Because "population" is the whole of which "women" are a part, the correct verb is compose or make up.</p>
        <p>Later, she got it: "Women and children make up a large majority"; they do not comprise it. (When Jimmy Carter estimated that "about 8 percent of our military forces are comprised of women," he was using an even more controversial construction: the passive "is comprised of." Even though "comprise" should not take "of," many dictionaries are now including "comprised of," sometimes labeled as a "loose usage." Substitute the synonym in that passive phrase, however, and "is included of" makes no sense; replace it with "is composed of.")</p>
        <p>I will not cavil at her use, four times, of raise in connection with the upbringing of children. We in the rear guard of usage prefer rearing children and raising cattle, but this distinction is being worn down and may have been given a powerful clop on the head by the First Lady in this formal speech to a world body. However, her locution "fast-food chefs" is an oxymoronic euphemism; the 1951 modifier fast-food, like its predecessor short-order, applies to cooks, whether they work in "greasy spoons" or "fast-food joints"; chefs (from the French chef de cuisine, meaning "head of the kitchen") carries a clear connotation of gourmet cooking.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton urges women to "take greater control over their own destinies"; I would urge them to take control of, rather than over, or to exercise greater power over. This seems like a nitpick, but if you are going to empower an entire sex, you have to give it the proper linguistic tools. Same with her use of "caretakers for most of the world's children"; since you take care of someone, the better choice would be "caretakers of." The preposition for works better with "caregivers for," because you can give "care for."</p>
        <p>She spoke of efforts to "bring new dignity" and "bring new strength" to women around the world. Bring should be used only for conveying something from somewhere else to the place of the verb's user. In this case, neither bring nor take fits; give or add would have been appropriate.</p>
        <p>Her choice of "let us not forget" places her on the side of the prescriptive and eat-your-peas rhetorician; the verbal finger-wagging is surely not incorrect, but as the Reagan speech writer Peggy Noonan pointed out, "let us remember" is the warmer and more positive form.</p>
        <p>Her use of NGO's, an abbreviation, before using the full phrase, "nongovernmental organizations," invited confusion in the minds of the worldwide audience; it's not a good idea to assume everyone knows what the local audience does. There are those for whom NGO stands for Nongovernmental Observers, Naval Gunfire Officer or National Gas Outlet.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton needs to address her also problem. "Women also are dying from diseases" suggests in the present progressive that women, as well as men, are dying. Her intended meaning, however, was that another problem facing women is disease; therefore, her word order should have been "women are also dying." Same with her use of "we also must recognize," which means "we, too, must recognize." She obviously meant "we must also recognize," which has the also modifying the recognize rather than the we.</p>
        <p>"The voices of this conference," the First Lady told the delegates, " . . . must be heard loud and clear." Everybody knows what she meant because loud and clear is a fused phrase, but the problem is with the heard. A sound may be loud when it is made, but it is not "heard" loud; either the voices should be loud and clear without the heard, or the voices should "ring out" loud and clear.</p>
        <p>Is any of this belated copy editing necessary? Wasn't it a good speech, well received by all except the repressive Chinese gerontocracy? The central message of Hillary Rodham Clinton's most important speech came across with courage and puissance (loud and clear, if cliches appeal), but when a representative of the United States steps on the world stage, he or she should pay attention to the details. "It is time for us to say here in Beijing, and the world to hear," she said, but could more clearly and forcefully have said, "and time for the world to hear." It's a little thing, good English usage in the service of oratory, but the little things add up.  ON LANGUAGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
