<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. BLOC SEEKS DELAY IN TAX CUTS</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="750833"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FEDERAL TAXES (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME TAX</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAX CREDITS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GINGRICH, NEWT (SPEAKER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, JERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Federal Taxes (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income Tax</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Credits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950325T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5DF143DF936A15750C0A963958260" item-length="894" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. BLOC SEEKS DELAY IN TAX CUTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GRAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRAY, JERRY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Agitation over the Republicans' promised tax cuts broadened today as about three dozen moderate party members in the House, joined by 23 Democrats who have consistently voted with the majority, demanded that the cuts be delayed until it was clear how they would be paid for.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, 102 House Republicans broke ranks with the leadership by urging that the proposed $500 per-child tax credit for families be scaled back. The move was partly in response to Democratic claims that the tax credit favors the rich.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Agitation over the Republicans' promised tax cuts broadened today as about three dozen moderate party members in the House, joined by 23 Democrats who have consistently voted with the majority, demanded that the cuts be delayed until it was clear how they would be paid for.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, 102 House Republicans broke ranks with the leadership by urging that the proposed $500 per-child tax credit for families be scaled back. The move was partly in response to Democratic claims that the tax credit favors the rich.</p>
        <p>The combined developments suggest trouble ahead for Speaker Newt Gingrich, who has had a string of relatively easy victories but who acknowledges that the political road will become rougher toward the end of his 100-day effort to complete the Contract With America.</p>
        <p>On the tax cut issue, lawmakers said today they would try to amend the Republican plan, which includes proposals for expanding retirement accounts and repealing the so-called marriage penalty, to guarantee that it would not take effect until Congress passed spending reductions sufficient to compensate for the lost revenue as well as to balance the budget.</p>
        <p>Individually, some Republicans staked out an even tougher position, saying that if the amendment was not approved, they would vote against their party's tax plan, one of the cornerstones of the contract.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Gingrich and the House Budget Committee chairman, Representative John R. Kasich of Ohio, have repeatedly said that the Republicans would present a plan that would reduce spending by increments toward a balanced budget by 2002 and also pay for the $189 billion in tax cuts proposed in the contract.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Gingrich's timetable calls for a vote on the tax cut first, followed by the budget, and that is the source of the latest insurrection.</p>
        <p>"A number of members said they had a problem voting on a tax package without knowing how we are going to pay for it or having a balanced budget in line," said Representative Bill Martini, a freshman Republican from New Jersey and one of the leaders of the challenge. "Their desire is to have such language as an amendment when the tax bill goes to the floor."</p>
        <p>The White House has repeatedly challenged the Republicans to reveal how they plan to balance the budget and provide a huge tax cut at the same time. Some Republicans who share that concern have asked the party leadership to spell out their plans to quiet Democratic tongues and some Republican nerves.</p>
        <p>A senior aide to one House Republican said today that a widespread worry among the caucus was that Mr. Gingrich had put "the cart before the horse" by insisting that the tax cuts come first.</p>
        <p>There are two main points to the amendment: that no tax cuts would take effect until passage of all the spending cuts to both balance the budget and pay for the tax benefits, and that the tax cuts would be "permanently revoked" if the Federal deficit exceeded a specific target.</p>
        <p>Under the proposal, the deficit target would be $150 billion in fiscal year 1996, which begins on Nov. 1, and would decrease by $25 billion a year for the next five years, achieving a balanced budget by 2002. The estimated deficit for the current fiscal year is $176 billion.</p>
        <p>The amendment's co-sponsors are Representative Michael N. Castle, Republican of Delaware, and Representative Glen Browder, Democrat of Alabama.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martini said that about 35 to 40 Republicans pledged their support today within hours of the announcement of the proposed amendment. Some in that group were among those who raised questions this week about the proposed tax credit for families with children, but Mr. Martini said most were not part of the earlier protest.</p>
        <p>Later in the day, the 23 Democrats, who form a moderate-to-conservative bloc known as the Coalition, announced that they had joined forces with the Republicans.</p>
        <p>Representative Gary A. Condit, a Democrat from California and the leader of the Coalition, said he and his colleagues would try to pressure the Republican leadership and their own party caucus to support the amendment. But he said if that effort failed, the Coalition as a bloc would not oppose the tax plan and members would be free to vote as they wished.</p>
        <p>Mr. Martini said that the issue was first raised with the House Republican leadership on Thursday night when he and three other Republican members met privately with Representative Dick Armey of Texas, the majority leader. The issue was put to Mr. Gingrich this morning when he met with about 25 freshmen Republicans, Mr. Martini said.</p>
        <p>"I can't say that they have endorsed it, but leadership is at least aware of our position," he added.</p>
        <p>So far, Mr. Gingrich has stood firm in the face of opposition within his party, holding his 230-member House majority together on a series of tough votes and scoring impressive victories with the help of Democrats who have broken ranks.</p>
        <p>On Tuesday, for example, he responded with a firm "no" to the 102 Republicans who urged a scaling back of the proposed per-child tax credit to exclude families with taxable incomes over $95,000.</p>
        <p>For political reasons and for reasons of his 100-day timetable, which ends in less than three weeks, Mr. Gingrich would be even more hard pressed to give in to the demands raised today. But he is facing a much more serious challenge than he did earlier in the week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
