<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wall Street Leads, but New York's Economy Doesn't Follow</title>
    <meta content="07WALL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="913839"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment and Job Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Kirk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E4D71030F934A35750C0A961958260" item-length="1925" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wall Street Leads, but New York's Economy Doesn't Follow</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIRK JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Kirk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York City's overall economy is not participating in big profits of booming Wall Street, breaking pattern of past; it is a major change; since days of trusts and railroad barons, Wall Street has been both a barometer of New York's economic health and a powerful job engine; economists say that what has happened is that those two historical roles largely fell away; despite blizzard of bonuses and profits and taxes, fortunes of securities industry and fortunes of New York diverged; good news of Wall Street has not been enough to bring overall prosperity; economists say that this new and evolving pattern is more volatile, is less equitable in distribution of wealth, and may be unable over long term to produce kinds of entry-level jobs on which New York has historically depended; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Over the last year, New York City's unemployment rate has climbed even as Wall Street was cheering repeated record highs. Brokers earning seven-figure bonuses shopped for summer homes while about one in 11 people looked for jobs.</p>
        <p>Through much of New York's history, those kinds of contradictions did not occur. The economic rule of thumb was that when Wall Street celebrated, New York celebrated. But there has been a fundamental shift in that chemistry in the 1990's. Because the city, the state and the securities industry are not producing jobs in ways that they used to, the good news of Wall Street has not been enough to bring overall prosperity.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Over the last year, New York City's unemployment rate has climbed even as Wall Street was cheering repeated record highs. Brokers earning seven-figure bonuses shopped for summer homes while about one in 11 people looked for jobs.</p>
        <p>Through much of New York's history, those kinds of contradictions did not occur. The economic rule of thumb was that when Wall Street celebrated, New York celebrated. But there has been a fundamental shift in that chemistry in the 1990's. Because the city, the state and the securities industry are not producing jobs in ways that they used to, the good news of Wall Street has not been enough to bring overall prosperity.</p>
        <p>Economists say that this new and still evolving pattern is more volatile, is less equitable in the distribution of wealth, and may be unable over the long term to produce the kinds of entry-level jobs on which New York has historically depended.</p>
        <p>That represents a major change. Since the days of the trusts and the railroad barons, Wall Street has been both a barometer of New York's economic health and a powerful job engine. What has happened in the 1990's, economists say, is that those two historical roles largely fell away. Despite the blizzard of bonuses and profits and taxes, the fortunes of the industry and the fortunes of New York diverged.</p>
        <p>Through most of the 1980's in particular, securities industry profits acted like a lever on the economy: in most years when profits were up, the rate of growth of personal income in New York State surpassed the national average, and in years when profits declined, New York was dragged down and trailed the nation. It was a calculus that echoed the industry's roots in lower Manhattan and its power as an employer.</p>
        <p>Since the 1987 market crash, and particularly in the last few years, however, the lever has simply not worked. Securities  industry profits reached record levels, but state growth in personal income still lagged.</p>
        <p>In short, Wall Street's health is no longer enough to compensate for erosion in other areas. The windfall of tax revenues that washed through the city and state budgets made politicians smile, but was inadequate to the task of uplifting the overall economy.</p>
        <p>''When I look at Wall Street, I don't think of it as a major growth sector for employment,'' said Rae Rosen, a senior economist at the Federal Reserve Bank of New York. ''I look at high-paying jobs, and income, but not so much employment. We're going to want to look elsewhere for a job engine.''</p>
        <p>Another result of changes in the city and in the securities industry is a heightened disparity of wealth. Between 1989 and 1995, according to the State Comptroller's office, total real wages for New York City's 3.2 million workers went up 8.4 percent when adjusted for inflation. But the majority of those gains came from one place: Wall Street.</p>
        <p>With the securities-industry contribution stripped out, wages in New York rose a paltry 3.8 percent in those six years. If the securities industry and banking are both removed, wages rose only 2.5 percent after inflation.</p>
        <p>In this new economic mix, contrary indicators have become common. Just this week, the state reported that in January, New York City's unemployment rate reached its highest level in three years. The following day, the City Comptroller's office said that the city had created more jobs in January than in any month for a decade.</p>
        <p>H. Carl McCall, the State Comptroller, said his central worry was that New York's fortunes rest on a narrower and narrower economic base that does not, in the end, provide for all New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''New York's economic problem is the creation of a wide variety of jobs,'' he said. ''We have to look to other sectors where we will get a wider job penetration.''</p>
        <p>The forces that underlie these changes are complex and still evolving. Certainly, the health of the securities industry as a whole is not in question. What has changed is the mix of jobs, and New York's greater dependence on them.</p>
        <p>In the 1990's, perhaps more than at any other time in its history, Wall Street work means white-collar work. Ten years after the 1987 market crash, there are fewer midlevel, entry-level and union jobs, and more salaried workers eligible for bonuses. Some firms have changed nearly everything about whom they employ in the city, what kind of work they do, and what they're paid.</p>
        <p>At the same time, continued declines in manufacturing, government and banking have left the city with a smaller work force, which is ever more reliant on Wall Street.</p>
        <p>In 1987, for example, the nearly 163,000 people employed in New York City securities firms made up a total of 5.1 percent of the private sector work force and earned 12.6 percent of the total private sector wages, according to state figures. By 1996, industry employment had fallen to 150,000, but that accounted for 5.3 percent of a smaller work force and 16.9 percent of the wages.</p>
        <p>Certainly, some elements of the new dynamic are unequivocally good for New York. Stock trading volume is higher than ever. The city has solidified its place as a center of global finance. Soaring stock prices have created wealth and willingness to spend money that has spilled over into retailing and real estate.</p>
        <p>After shedding more than 30,000 jobs in the city between 1987 and 1991, the securities industry has rebuilt itself: hiring about 20,000 people in the years since. New York State received $1 billion in taxes from the industry last year.</p>
        <p>And some of the changes could be positive in the long term. More high-end jobs means that New York is headquarters for the industry's glamour and brain power. Economists say upper-level jobs may be more stable, too: Wall Street usually cuts from the bottom in bad times.</p>
        <p>But the sunny headlines about the  Dow Jones average or budget-saving tax infusions have also obscured the less visible changes that leave the future of the regional economy and the industry much less certain.</p>
        <p>Between 1987 and 1995, for example, New York State lost more than 13,000 securities industry jobs, while other states gained 85,000 jobs. In that same period the state's national share of securities jobs fell from 38 percent to 30 percent, as New York became less and less the center of the universe for the business.</p>
        <p>Three major forces were at work, the first being that this decade is the era of the mutual fund investor, and the mutual fund companies are mostly not in New York. New technologies, partly driven by higher stock-trading volumes, have also kept labor needs down, while cost control pressures have pushed firms to relocate workers.</p>
        <p>Entry-level industry jobs familiar since the days of Rockefeller and Morgan have disappeared. When the $10.2 billion merger between Morgan Stanley and Dean Witter Discover was announced last month, for example, some of the first people to hear about it were the messengers and runners who shuttle documents through the organizations.</p>
        <p>But those workers are not employees of either firm. They work for Choice Courier Systems, a contractor that does in-house delivery and mailroom services. Morgan Stanley got rid of its 60 in-house messengers two years ago. Dean Witter signed on with Choice in January.</p>
        <p>Those kinds of outside arrangements -- common across corporate America -- clearly create new opportunities, but they also eliminate entry-level spots from which people might once have been promoted. Choice's founder, president and chief executive officer, Edward Katz, conceded that the health benefits for his employees were probably less generous than a giant Wall Street firm might offer. But the lower cost is also largely why he is doing well, he said.</p>
        <p>For New York politicians the implications are delicate. The city and state have spent hundreds of millions of dollars in recent years wooing and subsidizing Wall Street firms that threatened to leave the city. The apparently growing gap between rich and poor has become, at the same time, a centerpiece of the debate about government's role. In the adminstration of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, caution reigns.</p>
        <p>''I don't think you can define it either as a positive or a negative,'' said Fran Reiter, the city's Deputy Mayor for Economic Development and Planning, of the changes in the securities industry. ''It just is.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Reiter said that specific efforts were under way to try to bring back some lower-wage securities jobs, but that it was also important for the city to wean itself away from dependence on one industry.</p>
        <p>Some securities companies are also nervous. A spokesman at one large investment firm in New York, declining to comment on the record, said that the firm did not want to alienate New Yorkers by admitting that the growth of jobs was faster in areas of the firm outside New York.</p>
        <p>He also did not want to alienate people in those other places by giving the impression that New York gets only the highest-paying jobs. But as a generalization, the spokesman said, both trends are true.</p>
        <p>At Smith Barney, the transformation of jobs has occurred entirely within the city. In two years, the firm has created about 150 new technical jobs in computer programming, technical support and communications. It also eliminated about the same number of ''mundane clerical functions,'' said Melvin Taub, a senior executive vice president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Taub said that some of the displaced clerks got training and made the transition or found other jobs, so that no layoffs resulted. The new jobs are more highly paid than the old ones, he said, and are all eligible for bonuses as well.</p>
        <p>At Bowne &amp; Company, a 222-year-old financial printing company, the changes are even more stark. Ten years ago, the firm's offices on Hudson Street had clattering presses and lots of union jobs. It was a place where prospectuses and legal filings got printed.</p>
        <p>That's all gone now. During the recession, when many of the company's competitors went out of business, Bowne retooled. Its printing is now done in Secaucus; the staff has been upgraded. The Federal Securities and Exchange Commission changed to electronic filing.</p>
        <p>Between 1987 and 1996, the number of white-collar occupations at Bowne's New York office went up 127 percent while blue-collar positions fell by 69 percent. The company used to recruit at the New York High School of Graphic Communication Arts. That just won't do now, said David L. Rosenstein, a company spokesman.</p>
        <p>''They couldn't do this kind of work,'' Mr. Rosenstein said. ''Our trainees are college graduates.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
