<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Greenburgh Approves Verizon Cable Pact</title>
    <meta content="08wecableWC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1795618"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenburgh (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Verizon Communications</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cablevision Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Scharfenberg, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061008T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E0D91530F93BA35753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="433" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Greenburgh Approves Verizon Cable Pact</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID SCHARFENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Scharfenberg, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Town Council in Greenburgh, NY, has unanimously approved agreement that would allow Verizon to compete with Cablevision by offering cable television service in unincorporated part of town (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Bernsteins of Greenburgh paid $46.95 last month for their cable television package and $17.40 for their cable box. HBO was an extra $11.95, and the digital video recorder service rang in at $10. Add $45 for an Internet connection, and taxes and fees, and the family sent exactly $136.85 to Cablevision.</p>
        <p>For Robert Bernstein, a fan of the New York Giants and of Jon Stewart, it was well worth the price. But Mr. Bernstein, 51, a lawyer and longtime Cablevision customer, has had trouble with reception from time to time. Customer service has not been what he would like, he said, and he could always use a rate cut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Bernsteins of Greenburgh paid $46.95 last month for their cable television package and $17.40 for their cable box. HBO was an extra $11.95, and the digital video recorder service rang in at $10. Add $45 for an Internet connection, and taxes and fees, and the family sent exactly $136.85 to Cablevision.</p>
        <p>For Robert Bernstein, a fan of the New York Giants and of Jon Stewart, it was well worth the price. But Mr. Bernstein, 51, a lawyer and longtime Cablevision customer, has had trouble with reception from time to time. Customer service has not been what he would like, he said, and he could always use a rate cut.</p>
        <p>Now, relief could be on the way. The Greenburgh Town Council unanimously approved an agreement with Verizon on Sep. 27 that would allow the company to offer cable television service in the unincorporated part of the town, injecting a little competition into the local market.</p>
        <p>''Having two billion-dollar companies competing for our business, I think, should be a good thing,'' Mr. Bernstein said.</p>
        <p>Cablevision and Verizon are each charging about $40 a month for what they call their standard package of cable service.</p>
        <p>Westchester customers have had access to satellite television for years. But Verizon's arrival in Greenburgh will be the first head-to-head cable television competition in the county in recent memory.</p>
        <p>''I certainly hope this helps pave the way for other municipalities in Westchester to sign agreements with Verizon,'' said Francis Sheehan, the town councilman who led negotiations with the company.</p>
        <p>The Greenburgh agreement now goes to the New York State Public Service Commission for final approval. If the commission signs off on the deal, Verizon, which already offers Internet service in the county, could begin offering cable television in unincorporated Greenburgh as early as this month.</p>
        <p>Bill Powers, a spokesman for Cablevision, said he expected Greenburgh customers to keep the company's television, Internet and telephone services. ''We're always pursuing innovative ideas so we can continue to provide state-of-the-art features,'' he said, pointing to an upgrade of Internet speed in Westchester in April.</p>
        <p>John Bonomo, a spokesman for Verizon, said the company was just beginning to crack the county's sprawling market. ''This is the first in Westchester and we hope to keep rolling,'' he said. Verizon has 14 franchise agreements statewide, mostly on Long Island and in Rockland County; it now has about 100,000 television customers in New York, Massachusetts, Maryland, Florida, Texas, Virginia and California.</p>
        <p>Verizon began offering television service over its fiber optic network for the first time in Keller, Tex., in September 2005, Mr. Bonomo said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
