<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Headline</title>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="627595"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ATHLETICS AND SPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930809T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1DE133EF93AA3575BC0A965958260" item-length="879" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Headline</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TENNIS  Krajicek Edges Chang Richard Krajicek recovered from a shaky start yesterday to beat Michael Chang, 0-6, 7-6 (7-3), 7-6, (7-5) and successfully defend his Volvo-Los Angeles title. Krajicek, seeded fourth and ranked 10th, struggled to get his big serve going, allowing Chang to dictate from the baseline. In the third-set tie breaker, the ninth-ranked Chang led by 3-2 before committing two straight errors. A huge serve and overhead smash gave Krajicek a 5-3 lead. Down match point at 6-5, Chang hit a down-the-line backhand that was just wide. (AP)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TENNIS  Krajicek Edges Chang Richard Krajicek recovered from a shaky start yesterday to beat Michael Chang, 0-6, 7-6 (7-3), 7-6, (7-5) and successfully defend his Volvo-Los Angeles title. Krajicek, seeded fourth and ranked 10th, struggled to get his big serve going, allowing Chang to dictate from the baseline. In the third-set tie breaker, the ninth-ranked Chang led by 3-2 before committing two straight errors. A huge serve and overhead smash gave Krajicek a 5-3 lead. Down match point at 6-5, Chang hit a down-the-line backhand that was just wide. (AP)</p>
        <p>Ruling Factor in Graf Victory: Top-ranked Steffi Graf, who had rallied from an 0-4 deficit in the first set, capitalized on a disputed call in the third set to beat second-seeded Arantxa Sanchez Vicario, 6-4, 4-6, 6-1, yesterday in the final of the Mazda Classic in Carlsbad, Calif. Sanchez Vicario, seeking to hold service and trailing by 2-1 in the third set, became upset when a line judge ruled that a Graf shot was good at the baseline. It gave Graf a break point, and she took the game on an unforced error. Graf had an easy time after that and breezed to her fourth straight tournament title and sixth of the year. (AP) Title for Bruguera: Top-seeded Sergi Bruguera beat third-seeded Andrei Chesnokov, 7-5, 6-4, to win the Skoda Czech Open in Prague. Bruguera, ranked fifth in the world, lost his serve in the third game of the first set, but broke Chesnokov in the eighth and 12th games to win the set. (AP) GOLF Mize Rallies for Victory Larry Mize, wiping out Fuzzy Zoeller's four-stroke lead in the first four holes, shot a four-under-par 68 yesterday to win the Buick Open by one stroke. Mize, who sank a six-foot par putt on the 72d hole to avoid a playoff with Zoeller, finished at 16-under 272 at the Warwick Hills Golf and Country Club in Grand Blanc, Mich. Zoeller, the third-round leader, closed with a 73 on a day in which his putter and driver deserted him. Greg Norman was third after shooting a 65 for 274. (AP) Late Starter Senior Winner: Bob Betley, a one-time Utah motorcycle cop who began playing golf at age 28, shot a three-under-par 69 yesterday for a three-round total of 204 and a one-stroke victory in the Bank of Boston Senior Classic in Concord, Mass. It was his first major victory. Bob Murphy, the runner-up, closed with a 69 for a 205. Chi Chi Rodriguez, Gibby Gilbert and Jim Albus shared third at 206. (AP) SOCCER Bolivia Keeps Rolling Bolivia, trying to advance to the World Cup for the first time since 1950, made another strong showing yesterday with a 3-1 victory over Uruguay in South American qualifying. Erwin (Platini) Sanchez broke a scoreless duel in the 66th minute in the game at La Paz, Bolivia. Marco Antiono Etcheverry and Milton Melgar added goals in the final eight minutes as Bolivia improved to 3-0-0 in South American Group B. Ecuador moved into second place in the group by blasting Venezueala, 5-0, at Quito, Ecuador, as Eduardo Hurtado scored three goals. In Group A, two visiting teams won: Argentina beat Paraguay, 3-1, in Asuncion, and Colombia defeated Peru, 1-0, in Lima. Argentina stayed atop Group A with 4 points from two games. (AP) SWIMMING  Sixth Gold for German Franziska van Almsick won her record-tying sixth gold medal as the European swimming championships concluded yesterday at Sheffield, England. Van Almsick, a 15-year-old German who won two silver and two bronze medals at last year's Olympics, won her sixth gold in the 50-meter freestyle, winning in 25.53 seconds by edging Sweden's Linda Olofsson by 0.14 of a second. (AP) AUTO RACING Mansell Celebration Nigel Mansell, the British racing star, celebrated his 40th birthday yesterday by winning the New England 200 at Loudon, N.H., after a three-car duel with Paul Tracy and Emerson Fittipaldi. Mansell passed Tracy while the two ran in traffic on Lap 197 at the New Hampshire International Speedway and prevailed by 45-hundredths of a second, with Fittipaldi, Tracy's teammate, 8.8 seconds behind. Mansell completed 200 laps at an average speed of 130.148 miles an hour. (AP) 1993 Victory for Martin: Mark Martin, benefiting from an accident six laps from the end that took out Kyle Petty and Dale Earnhardt, won his first race of the season at the Budweiser at the Glen at Watkins Glen, N.Y. Petty's Pontiac Grand Prix pinched up against a curbing in the third turn of the 2.45-mile, 11-turn road course and began to slide. Earnhardt, chasing Petty, tried to dive past on the outside but slammed his Chevrolet Lumina into Petty. Martin got his Ford Thunderbird through the smoke and debris and went on to the eighth victory of his career. Wally Dallenbach Jr. outran Jimmy Spencer for the runner-up spot. (AP) DOG SHOW Bichon Frise Wins Ch. Beau Cheval Red Roses, a 2-year-old bichon frise owned by David Rumel and I. F. Zimmerman of Stratford, Vt., was guided by Dave Roberts to the top honors yesterday at the 37th show of the Hunterdon Hills Kennel Club, on the fairgrounds in Flemington, N.J. It was the second top award for the little white dog, who answers to the name of Casper. "He's a superb type, with great balance and a beautiful head," said Peg Walton, who judged the final.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
