<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Some optimism has been expressed on the prospects for improved demand for commercials.</title>
    <meta content="14ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/14/business/media/14ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1480873"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Viacom Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Assn of Advertising Agencies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karmazin, Mel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Karmazin, Mel</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E5DD133BF937A25757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1046" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Some optimism has been expressed on the prospects for improved demand for commercials.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Some Optimism Seen for Advertising</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <dateline>NEW ORLEANS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mel Karmazin, president and chief operating officer of Viacom, tells 2003 Management Conference of American Assn of Adveritsing Agencies that there will be robust demand for commercial time to be sold by his company's television networks despite economic uncertainty and war in Iraq; there have been fears that advertisers would trim budgets if consumers significantly cut back on shopping, whether out of nervousness or at expense of staying home to watch war coverage (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEBATE over the twin, intertwined topics of the moment  the economy and the war -- dominated the closing general session of the 2003 Management Conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies.</p>
        <p>The attendees at the conference, which ended here on Friday, seemed to breathe a proverbial sigh of relief when one speaker, Mel Karmazin, the president and chief operating officer of Viacom, predicted there would be robust demand for commercial time to be sold by his company's television networks, which include BET, CBS, MTV, VH-1 and UPN, before the start of the 2003-04 season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Debate dominated the closing session of an important advertising conference. Still, some executives offered hope for better days ahead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEBATE over the twin, intertwined topics of the moment  the economy and the war -- dominated the closing general session of the 2003 Management Conference of the American Association of Advertising Agencies.</p>
        <p>The attendees at the conference, which ended here on Friday, seemed to breathe a proverbial sigh of relief when one speaker, Mel Karmazin, the president and chief operating officer of Viacom, predicted there would be robust demand for commercial time to be sold by his company's television networks, which include BET, CBS, MTV, VH-1 and UPN, before the start of the 2003-04 season.</p>
        <p>The waxing or waning of interest among major marketers in buying commercial time in what is known as the upfront market is an important indicator of the health of the advertising economy. Since the war began, there have been divergent forecasts for the coming upfront market, expected to start in late spring. Initial predictions of record-setting sales had been called into question because of fears that advertisers would trim budgets if consumers significantly cut back on shopping, whether out of nervousness or at the expense of staying home to watch statues of Saddam Hussein topple in Iraq.</p>
        <p>''From everything we are seeing, advertising, despite the geopolitical aspects of the war, is very strong,'' Mr. Karmazin said. ''Our belief is that there's a good amount of demand.''</p>
        <p>That is particularly true for the spots to be sold during the season after January 2004, he added, because next year will bring two big events that invariably stimulate demand for commercial time: a Summer Olympics and a presidential election.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karmazin joked that he was willing to accommodate those agencies eager to buy commercial time before 2004, or even before the negotiations for the upfront market get under way.</p>
        <p>''If you'd like to buy in the preupfront, I've been authorized by Les Moonves to do any deals in the back of the room,'' Mr. Karmazin said. Mr. Moonves is chief executive at the CBS division of Viacom.</p>
        <p>Mr. Karmazin acknowledged that there was ''a little bit of a disconnect between the advertising agency business and ours.'' While Madison Avenue has struggled to emerge from its steepest downturn in years, television networks, especially broadcasters like CBS, NBC and WB, have been setting revenue records.</p>
        <p>''There's virtually no inventory available in the second quarter,'' Mr. Karmazin said, referring to commercials sold just before they run in the so-called scatter market, ''and demand looks very strong for the third quarter.''</p>
        <p>In fact, advertisers that ran commercials in the first quarter in shows that did not deliver the audiences guaranteed by CBS are being reimbursed with cash rather than ''make-good'' commercials in the second quarter, Mr. Karmazin said, because ''demand is so strong for second-quarter inventory'' that CBS can sell the spots at higher prices than the advertisers were charged for spots in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>The recent strength of the scatter market should also prime the pump for the coming upfront market, Mr. Karmazin said, because commercial time for the second and third quarters is being sold at prices that he estimated are from 10 percent to 60 percent higher than they were last spring in the upfront market for the 2002-03 season.</p>
        <p>The results of that rising tide should, sooner or later, begin to trickle down to the agencies that belong to the association, which is known as the Four A's, because when marketers are buying more commercial time, they usually need more new commercials from their agencies.</p>
        <p>''All of us want to be optimistic and get going,'' said O. Burtch Drake, the president and chief executive of the association, ''but we don't know whether advertisers will want to open the floodgates or not.''</p>
        <p>''The upfront is going to be best signal'' of whether or not that happens, he added, and the fact that Mr. Karmazin ''is reasonably bullish'' is a signal in and of itself.</p>
        <p>Still, ''a chunk of money has disappeared,'' Mr. Drake said, referring to the ad dollars that many marketers did not spend in the days immediately after the war began, ''and it's not coming back.''</p>
        <p>That is why one speaker, Keith L. Reinhard, the chairman of DDB Worldwide in New York, part of the Omnicom Group, said he thought ''we have to create our own recovery.''</p>
        <p>''Agencies must take advantage of difficult times and find bigger ideas to bring to our clients,'' Mr. Reinhard said. ''I agree with people who say you can find opportunity in every difficulty.''</p>
        <p>A colleague of Mr. Reinhard, Cleve Langton, corporate executive vice president and worldwide director for business development at DDB, predicted there would be a recovery for the agency industry late this year, accelerating into early 2004.</p>
        <p>Mr. Langton's optimistic outlook was based on a survey conducted for a presentation he made on new business. Like demand in the upfront market, the pace of account changes among advertisers can also help gauge how agencies will fare.</p>
        <p>The war was also the subject of a lively panel discussion featuring Andrew Heyward, the president of CBS News, and three of his employees: Ed Bradley, Bob Schieffer and Hannah Storm.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bradley, who covered the Vietnam War, marveled at the improvements in television technology to deliver the reports from journalists ''out with the troops in harm's way.''</p>
        <p>''We in Vietnam were almost in the Stone Age,'' Mr. Bradley said. ''I'd do what we called the three S's: Shoot it, script it and ship it, to Saigon and then to Bangkok or Hong Kong, which had the only satellite facilities. Today, you turn on the television and you're watching war as it happens.''</p>
        <p>For that reason, Mr. Schieffer said, it is important that television not sanitize the war scenes that viewers see.</p>
        <p>''If we're not reminding people of the sacrifices being made during war,'' he added, ''watching war on television becomes just another option for people who don't want to watch basketball.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
