<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Elegant Magazine, Avalanche Of Dirt</title>
    <meta content="14MASL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/14/books/14MASL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1480850"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="BOOKS OF THE TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weisberger, Lauren</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Devil Wears Prada, the (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Magazines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Vogue</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Weisberger, Lauren</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02EEDF133BF937A25757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1102" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Elegant Magazine, Avalanche Of Dirt</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Elegant Magazine, Avalanche of Dirt</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews Lauren Weisberger book The Devil Wears Prada; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA  By Lauren Weisberger  360 pages. Doubleday. $21.95.</p>
        <p>If Cinderella were alive today, she would not be waiting patiently for Prince Charming. She would be writing a tell-all book about her ugly stepsisters and wicked stepmother, taking care to position herself at the absolute center of their story. She would be dishing the dirt, wreaking vengeance and complaining all the way.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lauren Weisberger's tell-all about Vogue magazine lacks much needed self-deprecating humor and warmth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE DEVIL WEARS PRADA  By Lauren Weisberger  360 pages. Doubleday. $21.95.</p>
        <p>If Cinderella were alive today, she would not be waiting patiently for Prince Charming. She would be writing a tell-all book about her ugly stepsisters and wicked stepmother, taking care to position herself at the absolute center of their story. She would be dishing the dirt, wreaking vengeance and complaining all the way.</p>
        <p>Cinderella may have been too nice for that, but Lauren Weisberger is not. Ms. Weisberger graduated from college and began her professional life in a low-level position at the Condé Nast publishing empire. Now she has written a novel, ''The Devil Wears Prada,'' and can devote a second career to insisting that it is not exactly, precisely, entirely one long swat at the editor of Vogue.</p>
        <p>This is not to suggest that the work-and-tell genre does not have its merits. Just ask the former nannies who wrote ''The Nanny Diaries'' and who come off as the Brontë sisters next to Ms. Weisberger. Like that other disgruntled employee, Bridget Jones, they managed to be genuinely funny and ingratiating while skewering bosses whom readers had reason to hate. But Ms. Weisberger lacks the self-deprecating humor and warmth for that. And her book's sour, sarcastic, self-involved heroine is too much of a pill to be endearing.</p>
        <p>That heroine is Andrea Sachs, known as Andy and eager to prove her literary talents at The New Yorker. She reveres that magazine and expects to write for it someday. And she has enough scorn for the fictitious fashion bible Runway to wonder if she's slumming to take an editorial assistant's job there.</p>
        <p>''You don't think it's completely selling out to work at a fashion magazine, do you?'' she asks Alex, her boyfriend. He is one of several bland peripheral characters meant to represent the real world. Alex is a nice-guy college boyfriend who teaches fourth graders and runs an after-school program. He's virtuous, but can he compete with the Prince Charming whom Andy will meet via Runway? And what about Andy's best friend, Lily? Trouble for Lily is signaled with the book's typical level of subtlety: ''I briefly wondered if Lily might be drinking too much these days. After all, she did seem to be drunk pretty consistently.''</p>
        <p>''The Devil Wears Prada'' flags whenever it spends too much time in this company. The book's real interest is in life at the offices of Elias-Clark (Condé Nast right down to the cafeteria), where Andy meets her big, bad boss. This is the so-called Miranda Priestley, and she is awful. But she is the same kind of awful throughout the story, to the point at which even her arrogance turns dull.</p>
        <p>Miranda is undeniably monstrous. She is rude, imperious, snobbish, near-criminally extravagant. (The book is at its bitchiest in indicating how much of her employer's money she wastes, and how much payola she accepts.) Miranda is vague yet impossibly demanding with her employees. They quake in their boots at the very sight of her. This book always notes the designer of those boots and the height of their heels. Footwear is character here.</p>
        <p>The ordeals Andy suffers are the high points of her story. She must go pick up her boss's custom-made tennis shorts at Chanel. She must get an advance copy of a book from ''that wretched Harry Potter series'' and send it, at huge expense and inconvenience, to Miranda's ungrateful children in Paris. She must find a restaurant in New York, although the place is actually in Washington, a fact that Miranda neglects to mention. Being thanked for any of this is out of the question.</p>
        <p>Andy must race to procure Miranda's coffee and meals (''I. Want. My. Lunch. Now!''), which are the main signs that this editor is the devil of the title. Miranda eats bacon and ice cream sundaes without gaining weight. Meanwhile, at 5 feet 10 tall and 115 pounds, Andy is the Hulk Hogan of this food-phobic crowd.</p>
        <p>Faced with these tasks and some remarkable on-the-job insults (Andy is forbidden to hang her coat near Miranda's in the closet), Andy reels off such an endless series of complaints that ''The Devil Wears Prada'' would be a pamphlet without them. Eventually, she will reach the point of saying two little words (and hardly unexpected ones) to make Miranda gasp in shock. This is the book's only indication that Miranda is naïve.</p>
        <p>Contemptuous as she is of fashion, Andy spends a lot of time being scrutinized and beautified by Runway employees, Cinderella-style. The book's way of dropping names, labels and price tags while feigning disregard for these things is another of its unattractive qualities. It's fair to assume that nobody oblivious to names like Prada will be reading this story anyway.</p>
        <p>While being so dreadfully mistreated, Andy manages to be nice to the story's peasant characters, who are part of Miranda's extended support system. These folks appreciate Andy ad nauseam. (''Knock 'em dead, hottie,'' one lecherous admirer says as Andy heads to a party in her Runway finery.) Also appreciative, no doubt, is the teenage Miranda Priestly fan who writes a letter asking for a nice party dress. Andy winds up granting her wish, since the poor letter writer lives in Newark, where the Versaces are scarce.</p>
        <p>For a mean-spirited ''Gotcha!'' of a book, one that offers little indication that the author could interestingly sustain a gossip-free narrative, ''The Devil Wears Prada'' is most unseemly when it comes to literature. While Alex is parked with his fourth-grade schoolchildren, Andy catches the eye of Christian Collinsworth, a successful writer. (''The critics had gone crazy over his first book, hailing it as one of the most significant literary achievements of the 20th century,'' and ''it seemed the entire book world was eagerly anticipating his next contribution.'') He likes her. And she likes the designers of his T-shirt, belt and tasseled loafers.</p>
        <p>Christian's agent decides Andy might be famous-writer material herself. Ultimately, she wows another magazine editor, becomes ''the next new 'it' writer'' and finds her name mentioned in a gossip column. Maybe ''The Devil Wears Prada'' will do this for Ms. Weisberger.</p>
        <p>BOOKS OF THE TIMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
