<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Israelis Get the All Clear To Stow Their Gas Masks</title>
    <meta content="14ISRA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/14/international/worldspecial/14ISRA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1480917"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION AT WAR: JERUSALEM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gas Masks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Myre, Greg</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mofaz, Shaul (Min)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Jerusalem</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Masks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Protective Clothing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Israel</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Jerusalem</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03E2D8133BF937A25757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="669" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Israelis Get the All Clear To Stow Their Gas Masks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Israelis Get the All Clear to Stow Their Gas Masks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GREG MYRE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Myre, Greg</byline>
      <dateline>JERUSALEM, April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Israeli Defense Min Shaul Mofaz says danger of Iraqi missile attack has passed and citizens can put away their gas masks; most had already stopped carrying masks and dismantled sealed rooms; US troops have scoured western desert, only place from which Iraqi missiles could reach Israel, and have found nothing threatening; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israel's defense minister said today that the danger of an Iraqi missile attack had passed and citizens could put away their gas masks. Meanwhile, Israeli commentators questioned whether other regional dangers might also soon diminish.</p>
        <p>''The missile threat from western Iraq no longer exists, as far as we can tell,'' Defense Minister Shaul Mofaz said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Israel's defense minister said that the danger of an Iraqi missile attack had passed and citizens could put away their gas masks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Israel's defense minister said today that the danger of an Iraqi missile attack had passed and citizens could put away their gas masks. Meanwhile, Israeli commentators questioned whether other regional dangers might also soon diminish.</p>
        <p>''The missile threat from western Iraq no longer exists, as far as we can tell,'' Defense Minister Shaul Mofaz said.</p>
        <p>Few Israelis needed the official word. Most had already stopped carrying their army-issued gas masks and had dismantled sealed rooms, part of nationwide preparations to guard against a nonconventional Iraqi attack. During the Persian Gulf war in 1991, Iraq fired 39 Scud missiles with conventional warheads at Israel, causing extensive damage but few casualties.</p>
        <p>United States troops have scoured Iraq's western desert, the only place from which the Iraqi missiles could reach Israel, and there have been no reports that missiles or launchers were found. Still, Israel was keeping its Arrow antimissile batteries on alert, the Defense Ministry said.</p>
        <p>The Israeli news media, meanwhile, have been filled with debate on whether Saddam Hussein's swift fall in Iraq would chasten Israel's other rivals in the region, particularly Syria and the militant Shiite Muslim group it supports in Lebanon, Hezbollah.</p>
        <p>Optimistic Israeli analysts envision the American-led military operation in Iraq paving the way for a new, more moderate Middle East that would give Israel the possibility of broadening its very limited contacts in the Arab world.</p>
        <p>''A window of opportunity for Israel has opened up in Baghdad, a kind of crack in the sky, something that happens in our region perhaps once every 50 years,'' wrote Guy Bechor in Yediot Ahronot, a leading Israeli daily. ''The window could soon closed. It would be a shame not to take advantage of it.''</p>
        <p>Israel's infrastructure minister, Yosef Paritzsky, even raised the prospect of reopening a regional oil pipeline that went dry when Iraq and other Arab states began boycotting Israel at its independence in 1948. The long abandoned pipeline runs from Iraq's northern oil fields, across Jordan and to the northern Israeli port city of Haifa.</p>
        <p>But others were far more cautious, saying Israel would face the same friction points and should not expect any dramatic breakthroughs.</p>
        <p>''One has to be realistic,'' said Shlomo Avineri, a political scientist at Hebrew University. ''I don't think there will be many political and diplomatic opportunities for Israel. And a triumphal Israeli attitude will be counterproductive.''</p>
        <p>The Israelis will be looking closely for any signs of change in Syria and Lebanon. The Bush administration has been sharply critical of Syria and its young leader, Bashar al-Assad, accusing him of aiding Iraq.</p>
        <p>If President Assad seeks to avoid further confrontation with the United States, he may act to restrain Hezbollah, which periodically trades fire with Israeli forces across the Israeli-Lebanese frontier. Hezbollah, which is also backed by Iran, is on Washington's list of terrorist groups.</p>
        <p>''If the United States is telling Syria to keep things quiet, I imagine the message Syria will give to Hezbollah is, 'Be careful,' '' Mr. Avinieri said.</p>
        <p>Syria has had troops in Lebanon for more than a quarter century, is regarded as the main power broker there and has considerable influence over Hezbollah.</p>
        <p>In 2000, Israel pulled its troops out of south Lebanon, ending an 18-year occupation. The move greatly reduced the intensity of the conflict, but the shooting has not ended.</p>
        <p>Today, Hezbollah fighters fired antiaircraft rounds at Israeli warplanes flying over south Lebanon. Earlier this month, three Hezbollah antiaircraft shells, fired at Israeli planes, landed in northern Israel, but caused no injuries.</p>
        <p>Haim Barbivai, the mayor of Kiryat Shmona, the northern Israeli town often targeted by Hezbollah, called on the Israeli Air Force not to fly over southern Lebanon during the Jewish holiday of Passover, which begins this week.</p>
        <p>The planes and the resulting Hezbollah fire scare away tourists, he told Israel radio.</p>
        <p>A NATION AT WAR: JERUSALEM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
