<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For 7 Families, Relief After Weeks of Waiting</title>
    <meta content="MB012801" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1480987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION AT WAR: THE FAMILIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kuwait</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Romero, Simon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisoners of War</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2DF103BF937A25757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1015" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For 7 Families, Relief After Weeks of Waiting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SIMON ROMERO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Romero, Simon</byline>
      <dateline>ALAMOGORDO, N.M., April 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Seven families across nation weep, laugh and celebrate at word that their children and spouses have been released from capture by Iraqis; some had been shocked weeks ago by images of their relatives looking terrified in Iraqi hands; now they watch over and over cable television footage of their loved ones free in desert and boarding plane to Kuwait; some take time from their glee to remember other members of 507th maintenance unit who will not be coming home; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anecita Hudson's joy poured out in a jumble of English and her native Tagalog today, as she explained how she had always believed her son, Joseph, would survive capture by the Iraqis.</p>
        <p>''I told myself, 'Hell no, not my Joseph,' '' Ms. Hudson said here, surrounded by a half-dozen friends from the Philippines sitting on lawn chairs in her yard. ''God's going to deliver him back to me for my birthday.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anecita Hudson's joy poured out in a jumble of English and her native Tagalog today, as she explained how she had always believed her son, Joseph, would survive capture by the Iraqis.</p>
        <p>''I told myself, 'Hell no, not my Joseph,' '' Ms. Hudson said here, surrounded by a half-dozen friends from the Philippines sitting on lawn chairs in her yard. ''God's going to deliver him back to me for my birthday.''</p>
        <p>''I'm going to fatten my boy up a bit with some chicken adobo and rice when he gets home,'' she said after she learned that Specialist Joseph N. Hudson, 23, had been set free.</p>
        <p>After long weeks of waiting, seven families across the nation wept, laughed and celebrated today at word that their children and spouses had been released.</p>
        <p>Some who had been shocked by the images of their relatives looking terrified in Iraqi hands, now watched over and over the cable television footage of their loved ones free in the desert and boarding a plane to Kuwait.</p>
        <p>Some took time from their glee to remember the members of the 507th maintenance unit who would not come home.</p>
        <p>In Georgia, Kelly Lively saw the television pictures of her brother, Chief Warrant Officer Ronald D. Young Jr., 26, walking from a helicopter to a truck in blue-striped pajamas. She studied how he clapped a Marine on the shoulder and decided he could not have been tortured.</p>
        <p>''He's not totally emotionally turned down, or he wouldn't be able to touch people,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Rileys of Pennsauken., N.J., realized their son, Sgt. James J. Riley was all right when they saw Maj. Nathan Banks walk up their driveway at 9:30 this morning and give a thumbs-up sign.</p>
        <p>It was the fact that Major Banks was alone that instantly comforted Athol Riley. ''There are always two of them when someone is dead,'' he said today. [Page B3.]</p>
        <p>Whole communities exploded in joy. At the 10:15 Palm Sunday service at First United in Valley Center Kansas -- the hometown of Pfc. Patrick W. Miller -- a parishioner reported from the lectern, ''Pat Miller is in the hands of the United States Army.'' The congregation stood and clapped and cheered.</p>
        <p>The celebration spread to Fort Bliss, in El Paso, home base of the 507th Maintenance Company and of five of the prisoners of war found today. Those five were taken prisoner after a fierce firefight with Iraqi forces on May 23 near the city of Nasiriya.</p>
        <p>Col. Ben Hobson, the chief of staff at Fort Bliss, described the discovery as ''great news,'' but he also tempered his comments. ''We must not forget the other nine from the unit who were killed in action and our thoughts and prayers are with them and their families,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In a nearby neighborhood, Claude Johnson, the father of Specialist Shoshana N. Johnson, 30, another freed soldier from the 507th, said: ''We thank God for watching over them. We are grateful for all the worldwide prayers.'' Specialist Johnson was said by military officials in Kuwait to be recovering from a gunshot would in her ankle.</p>
        <p>In Mission, a city of about 50,000 in southern Texas across the border from Reynosa, Mexico, hundreds of residents exploded into a jubilant celebration, honking their horns and giving thumbs-up signs as they drove past the home of Jose and Maria de la Luz Hernandez. ''I don't know how to describe the emotions that are in my body right now,'' Ms. Hernandez, the mother of Specialist Edgar A. Hernandez, said in an interview in Spanish. ''I'm crying for joy, all of the joy does not fit in me.''</p>
        <p>In New Mexico, the Hudson family made plans for a homecoming. ''I'm not going to say anything to him or ask him anything; I'm just going to give him a hug,'' said Anthony Hudson, 19, Specialist Hudson's younger brother.</p>
        <p>When asked if he had learned anything in the three weeks since his brother was captured, Mr. Hudson replied: ''War's not so great. There's not much to learn from something like that.''</p>
        <p>About an hour's drive south, Specialist Hudson's wife, Natalie, 23, sat in her dining room in El Paso, her 4-year-old daughter, Cameron, bouncing on her knee. ''I tried to have as positive an outlook as possible but the worries were kind of bottled up inside me,'' she said. Between bites of fried chicken and puffs on a cigarette, Ms. Hudson said the stress of waiting had taken its toll. She was diagnosed with high blood pressure on a recent medical visit.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hudson, who met Private Hudson when she was 15 and he was 16 and both were students at Alamogordo High School, said she hoped life could soon take on a semblance of normalcy for her and her husband.</p>
        <p>She returned to her job as a bank teller last week in El Paso. Specialist Hudson, she said, had dreamed of working for the Border Patrol after finishing his service in the Army.</p>
        <p>A NATION AT WAR: THE FAMILIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
