<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Barkley Putting Some Spin on the Ball Off the Court</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="545974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BARCELONA: BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1992)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARKLEY, CHARLES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARATON, HARVEY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004/Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DF1738F93AA15754C0A964958260" item-length="447" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Barkley Putting Some Spin on the Ball Off the Court</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ARATON, HARVEY</byline>
      <dateline>BADALONA, Spain, July 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the day the Dream Team rested and nursed its wounds, Charles Barkley's mouth continued to run in Olympic marathon form.</p>
        <p>Angry that he has been forced by the United States Olympic Committee to discontinue a column he was writing in USA Today, Barkley claimed the U.S.O.C. is "a little jealous about how much attention we're getting."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the day the Dream Team rested and nursed its wounds, Charles Barkley's mouth continued to run in Olympic marathon form.</p>
        <p>Angry that he has been forced by the United States Olympic Committee to discontinue a column he was writing in USA Today, Barkley claimed the U.S.O.C. is "a little jealous about how much attention we're getting."</p>
        <p>Barkley proceeded to attract more attention, with his knack for the outrageous. The man who has spoken out vigorously against racial stereotyping in America, defended the elbow he threw at a 174-pound Angolan last Sunday by saying, "How did I know he didn't have a spear?"</p>
        <p>Added the rebel forward in search of a cause: "We don't think we're above the rules. We don't think we're above the Olympic committee, but they shouldn't pick on every little thing we do. We should be given our due for being a great basketball team."</p>
        <p>No problem, according to Mike Moran, a U.S.O.C. spokesman, who added that it was the International Olympic Committee which actually objected to Barkley using the Olympics to pursue a career in journalism. He added that while everyone here admires the quality of basketball being played, it is off the court that the stars from the National Basketball Association will get no preferential treatment.</p>
        <p>"The Dream Team is out of touch with the rest of the Olympic team," said Moran. "The Dream Team must abide by the rules like any other U.S. athlete."</p>
        <p>Moran also said the U.S.O.C. continues to insist that all United States medal winners wear a specially designed suit made by Reebok during medal ceremonies. Michael Jordan, who has Nike emblems on everything he wears or touches, including his golf clubs, said he will not wear anything designed by a rival company.</p>
        <p>In a world of famine, drought and war, we may expect a standoff late next week, as the U.S.O.C. is claiming a higher moral form of capitalism than Jordan.</p>
        <p>"The money we're getting from Reebok is going to assist thousands of athletes in training," said Moran.</p>
        <p>On the injury front, Magic Johnson is likely to miss the game Wednesday night against Germany (1-1) with what has been diagnosed as sprained posterior ligaments in his right knee. Johnson said he felt a pop in the back of the knee as he ran a fast break in the first half of the 103-70 victory over Croatia on Monday night.</p>
        <p>A team spokesman said Johnson is day to day. The team's other injured point guard, John Stockton, reported Monday that he is hoping to return Friday night against Brazil, although Coach Chuck Daly said he is not counting on it. Stockton has not played since the second game of the Tournament of the Americas after breaking a small bone in his right leg.</p>
        <p>BARCELONA: BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
