<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>You Want Multiculturalism? Here It Is</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="715481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="RECORDINGS VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECORDINGS (AUDIO)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">JAMES, JAMIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALEXANDER, ROBERTA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HELLER, ALFRED</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">VILLA-LOBOS, HECTOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recordings (Audio)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405EEDB103AF931A35753C1A962958260" item-length="618" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>You Want Multiculturalism? Here It Is</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMIE JAMES;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JAMES, JAMIE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE FRENCH Musicologist Pierre Vidal once described Heitor Villa-Lobos as "Bach and Beethoven rolled into one." The description is not altogether inapt. Beethoven's white-hot intensity is in evidence in the Brazilian composer's best works for orchestra; and while it is an exaggeration to ascribe to his compositions the formal perfection of Bach, there is no doubt that he was a master of counterpoint, a brilliant writer with a remarkably fluent and versatile musical mind.</p>
        <p>Yet Vidal's metaphor, generous as it is, does not go far enough, for Villa-Lobos was also a master of a musical medium that never particularly interested Bach or Beethoven: the song. He is best known for his "Bachiana Brasileira" No. 5, scored for soprano and eight cellos, which has been recorded by everyone from Victoria de los Angeles, who sang it on the composer's own recording, to Galina Vishnevskaya and Kiri Te Kanawa. But he also wrote a great body of folk songs, many of them with texts in obscure Amazon Indian languages and the Afro-Brazilian patois.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE FRENCH Musicologist Pierre Vidal once described Heitor Villa-Lobos as "Bach and Beethoven rolled into one." The description is not altogether inapt. Beethoven's white-hot intensity is in evidence in the Brazilian composer's best works for orchestra; and while it is an exaggeration to ascribe to his compositions the formal perfection of Bach, there is no doubt that he was a master of counterpoint, a brilliant writer with a remarkably fluent and versatile musical mind.</p>
        <p>Yet Vidal's metaphor, generous as it is, does not go far enough, for Villa-Lobos was also a master of a musical medium that never particularly interested Bach or Beethoven: the song. He is best known for his "Bachiana Brasileira" No. 5, scored for soprano and eight cellos, which has been recorded by everyone from Victoria de los Angeles, who sang it on the composer's own recording, to Galina Vishnevskaya and Kiri Te Kanawa. But he also wrote a great body of folk songs, many of them with texts in obscure Amazon Indian languages and the Afro-Brazilian patois.</p>
        <p>A new collection of Villa-Lobos songs by Roberta Alexander, accompanied by Alfred Heller (Etcetera KTC 1165; CD), comprises examples of the whole range of the composer's vocal literature. And what an impressive range it is: from the Indian lullabies and drinking songs that open the disk, in a playful mood reminiscent of Satie, to the sly, sensual swing of a carioca in the style of Rio de Janeiro, to suites of formal art songs.</p>
        <p>A grisly folk ballad about a water sprite, who was "very ugly, dark, fat and had a limp," has the eerie fascination and relentless pacing of Schubert's "Erlkonig." Songs from a cantata called "Forest of the Amazon," which were written for the Brazilian soprano Bidu Sayao, are haunting and complex, standing up to comparison with Ravel's evocations of the exotic, like "Sheherazade."</p>
        <p>Ms. Alexander's flexible, diaphanous voice is nearly ideal for this music, just capturing its luxuriant rainbow of colors. She appears to negotiate the half-dozen dialects effortlessly, even if few listeners will be able to gauge the authenticity of her Parici, an Indian language of the Mato Grasso, or her pronunciation of Afro-Brazilian. Mr. Heller has written an arrangement for her of the "Bachiana Brasileira" No. 5, accompanied by piano and cello, which captures the glamour and earthy vigor of the original.</p>
        <p>A student of Villa-Lobos's, Mr. Heller is not a particularly interesting pianist in his own right, but he is a good accompanist, scarcely missing a nuance of Ms. Alexander's wonderfully communicative style. He has somehow persuaded the small Dutch label Etcetera to record a series of Villa-Lobos chamber works, of which the present recording is the sixth.</p>
        <p>When Leopold Stokowski visited Rio in 1940, he was overwhelmed by Villa-Lobos's music and invited him to come to the United States. In the years that followed, Villa-Lobos became celebrated as a modern master, and his works were performed widely throughout Europe and the United States. Yet Serialism was the reigning style at that time, and the musical establishment never quite overcame its doubts that such prodigiously colorful music, rocking with racy rhythms and overflowing with sweet melodies, should really be taken seriously.</p>
        <p>Now the music world claims to have a deep thirst for music in multicultural idioms. How short is its memory: even as mediocre contemporary composers are being commissioned to write works with cosmopolitan influences, the music of Villa-Lobos, which is about as multicult as it comes, appears to be lapsing into near-obscurity. Mr. Heller and Etcetera are to be congratulated for their efforts to keep this magical music alive.  RECORDINGS VIEW Jamie James reviews musical events in New York for The Times of London.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jamie James reviews musical events in New York for The Times of London.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
