<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Powlus's Passing Prowess Propels Notre Dame to Victory</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="715794"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL: MIDWEST"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME (SOUTH BEND, IND)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">STANFORD UNIVERSITY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE0DA173DF931A35753C1A962958260" item-length="759" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Powlus's Passing Prowess Propels Notre Dame to Victory</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Notre Dame 34, Stanford 15</p>
        <p>Ron Powlus threw three touchdown passes and set up another one with a 44-yard run as Notre Dame beat Stanford, 34-15, yesterday at South Bend, Ind.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Notre Dame 34, Stanford 15</p>
        <p>Ron Powlus threw three touchdown passes and set up another one with a 44-yard run as Notre Dame beat Stanford, 34-15, yesterday at South Bend, Ind.</p>
        <p>Powlus completed 10 of his first 11 passes for 168 yards, including touchdown throws of 15, 10 and 47 yards for the Fighting Irish (4-1), who are ranked No. 8 by The Associated Press.</p>
        <p>Steve Stenstrom, closing in on Pac-10 and Stanford passing records in his senior year, was 37 of 59 for 360 yards with Mark Harris catching touchdown passes of 9 and 19 yards in the fourth quarter after the outcome was already determined.</p>
        <p>Coach Bill Walsh's Cardinal (1-2-1) took a 3-0 advantage on a 34-yard field goal by Eric Abrams after a penalty nullified a Stanford touchdown on the game's opening drive.</p>
        <p>The Irish built a 10-3 halftime advantage despite having the football only 7 minutes and 52 seconds in the half, then took command with 24 consecutive points in the second half.</p>
        <p>Two big plays were the difference for Notre Dame in the first half, which prevented Stanford from becoming only the third school this century to defeat the Irish on their home field three consecutive times.</p>
        <p>Notre Dame took the lead for good on a 15-yard touchdown strike to Charles Stafford from Powlus and added a 43-yard field goal by Scott Cengia after Ray Zellars broke loose for a 58-yard run that brought the ball to the Stanford 6-yard line. Stanford forced the field-goal attempt after the Irish lost ground on three consecutive plays.</p>
        <p>Stenstrom, who became the third player in Pac-10 history to pass for 9,000 career yards, completed 5 of his first 6 passes to move the ball from the Stanford 23 to the Irish 2 in 12 plays. He then completed a pass to wide-open Justin Armour in the end zone, but the play was nullified by a pass-interference call for an illegal pick.</p>
        <p>Stenstrom threw over the middle on the next play and Irish linebacker Justin Goheen tipped the ball. The ball popped into end zone and into the hands of Stanford's Anthony Bookman, but he failed to hold it when he was hit by Brian Magee. Michigan 29, Iowa 14</p>
        <p>Tyrone Wheatley ran for 182 yards and 2 touchdowns in his first start of the season and Michigan, ranked No. 7 by A.P., rebounded from its shocking loss to Colorado to beat host Iowa.</p>
        <p>Michigan (3-1) also got three field goals from Remy Hamilton and a touchdown run from Wheatley's backup, Tim Biakabutuka, in winning its 13th straight Big Ten opener.</p>
        <p>Iowa (2-3, 0-1) led by 7-3 after quarterback Ryan Driscoll's 1-yard touchdown run with 12:23 left in the second quarter. But the Hawkeyes didn't make another first down until the 2:23 mark in the third quarter and, by then, Michigan was in control. The Wolverines scored 10 points in the final 2 minutes of the first half to go up 13-7 and led 22-7 before Iowa finally regrouped on offense.</p>
        <p>Wheatley looked more like the player he was before separating his right shoulder in preseason practice. The injury kept him out of the first two games this year, but he came back to rush for 50 yards in 17 carries a week ago against Colorado, which won by 27-26 on a 64-yard touchdown pass on the game's final play. Michigan State 29, Wisconsin 10</p>
        <p>Turnovers did Wisconsin in again yesterday, as Duane Goulbourne scored two touchdowns and Michigan State's defense came up with four takeaways as the Spartans surprised the Badgers at East Lansing, Mich.</p>
        <p>Wisconsin (2-2, 1-1 Big Ten), ranked No. 15 by A.P., had four turnovers in a 55-17 loss at Colorado last weekend. Yesterday the Badgers lost two fumbles and two interceptions to Michigan State (2-2, 1-0). Ohio State 17, Northwestern 15</p>
        <p>Eddie George rushed for 206 yards on 39 carries Saturday as Ohio State, ranked No. 20 by A.P., rallied and then held on to beat Northwestern at Evanston, Ill.</p>
        <p>George, who rushed for more than 100 yards for the fourth straight game, would have been the goat had teammate Matt Finkes not made a saving tackle on Northwestern's 2-point conversion try with 5:01 to play in the Big Ten opener for both teams.</p>
        <p>The Buckeyes (4-1) trailed by 9-0 at halftime. IN OTHER GAMES</p>
        <p>INDIANA (4-1, 1-1 Big Ten), struggling throughout on offense, turned turnovers into second-half touchdowns by Reggie Bryant and John Paci in a 25-14 victory over visiting MINNESOTA. . . . Corey Rogers ran for two touchdowns and PURDUE stopped ILLINOIS tight end Ken Dilger on the 1-yard line on the game's final play as the visiting Boilermakers upset the Illini, 22-16. Illinois had been ranked No. 25 by A.P.  COLLEGE FOOTBALL: MIDWEST</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
