<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Sunday; One Last Toast Before a Life Of Solitude</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk;" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Second Front" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="715768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROMAN CATHOLIC RELIGIOUS ORDERS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ROMAN CATHOLIC CHURCH</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PHILLIPSON, DAVID B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINES, FRANCIS X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9507E3DC173DF931A35753C1A962958260" item-length="768" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Sunday; One Last Toast Before a Life Of Solitude</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLINES, FRANCIS X</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT? Never to hear a Letterman top-10 list again? Never to learn the O.J. verdict? Or see if the Carville-Matalin nuptials go pfffft but produce another "gosh weren't they a whacky twosome" best seller? Never to master E-mail or track the lost Harriman fortune? Never to accept fresh-ground pepper at the latest hyped bistro? Or savor that better world we all hope for when Forrest Gump recedes mercifully to video replay?</p>
        <p>"I won't miss the auto alarms," said David B. Phillipson before checking himself into a Carthusian monastery this weekend for a life of silence and solitude. "The alarms go off and they don't do anything," he noted, making his withdrawal to a severe life of godly contemplation all the more poignant in citing a few ineffectual details of city existence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT? Never to hear a Letterman top-10 list again? Never to learn the O.J. verdict? Or see if the Carville-Matalin nuptials go pfffft but produce another "gosh weren't they a whacky twosome" best seller? Never to master E-mail or track the lost Harriman fortune? Never to accept fresh-ground pepper at the latest hyped bistro? Or savor that better world we all hope for when Forrest Gump recedes mercifully to video replay?</p>
        <p>"I won't miss the auto alarms," said David B. Phillipson before checking himself into a Carthusian monastery this weekend for a life of silence and solitude. "The alarms go off and they don't do anything," he noted, making his withdrawal to a severe life of godly contemplation all the more poignant in citing a few ineffectual details of city existence.</p>
        <p>His new world unfolds inside a granite-walled cloister hidden in 6,000 otherwise untouched acres in the Vermont woods. Mr. Phillipson quit the Bronx to join one of the most threadbare religious communities, the Charterhouse of the Transfiguration, a total of 22 monks so far off the scope of progress that they cannot even learn the mushrooming extent of all they've renounced.</p>
        <p>Far from the madding superhighway the rest of us wend in search of daily data, the monks have no telephones, television or visitors. They live, pray, meditate, eat and work apart from one other. Each man chops the day's wood to heat his own cell, washes his own monk's habit of unbleached wool and freshens the straw mattress on his plywood pallet. Each manages a strict spiritual regimen with prayers at midnight, dawn and all manner of inconvenient times in between. Not the merest gleaning of a life style section is permitted.</p>
        <p>"I'LL miss the city," said Mr. Phillipson, lean and steady-eyed at 36. "You can get anything here. I was just at a Polish cafe and had borscht -- my last borscht. I had a cappuccino the other night. Loved that for the last time. A great bottle of wine the night before, red wine -- merlot, oh, yes."</p>
        <p>He worked at Fordham University for the last 10 years in a lay minister's job, setting up social outreach programs for students and scouting the poorest parts of the world from India to Appalachia. "The people of the third world have a special quality and I found myself wanting to become like them," he said, trying to explain. "To be on an equal footing with them because I saw value in how they embraced their own life situation."</p>
        <p>Whatever religion's shortage of parish clergy, individuals still gravitate toward monastic withdrawal, and the city is as great and gaudy a place as ever to encourage shunning life's tenderloin. "Maybe 10 years ago I would have said the city was godless," Mr. Phillipson said during his final hours in New York. "But I've come to love or like it a lot more. I have been able to find God here, especially among the poor and the disenfranchised."</p>
        <p>He leaves a vast throng of them behind, of course. But a mix of factors, from a taste for wilderness austerity to years of Eastern and Christian meditation studies, impelled his retreat from the city. In recent days, Mr. Phillipson said goodbye to family and friends, finding many sad, some perplexed, all well-wishing. He gave away belongings and put away a few, his prized possessions being a rocking chair from his grandmother and his stereo.</p>
        <p>"I love music, everything from Gregorian chant to the Grateful Dead," he said, smiling fondly at the defining details of a life abandoned. "It's like a paradox: I feel very free. They say in a monastery personalities flourish. With such exterior uniformity there's no longer any attempt to define who you are by what's outside of you."</p>
        <p>HE can break silence only for about an hour after the monks' common Sunday lunch, and once more for a few hours on Mondays when the holy men go outside the walls to walk the woods and mountains for recreation. Three years ago, when he returned from rafting in Alaska, he recalled "missing the solitude I experienced out there, the closeness with nature and with God."</p>
        <p>Yes, but no all-talk radio? Never learning how Whitewater or Andrew Giuliani turn out? Or whether America can disarm its children? Will Brando or Dan Quayle ever return?</p>
        <p>"I was thinking maybe I should bring a cassette of my favorite piece of music, Rachmaninoff's "Evening Vespers," Mr. Phillipson said, explaining a foolishly self-teasing moment when he was packing up and thought finally about the world's attachments and curiosities. "Time has been a concern, never feeling enough time to really experience life on its terms," he said, leaving the music and the city.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
