<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pastimes;   Camera</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="64" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="360133"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SALT HILL PHOTOGRAPHIC INSTRUMENTS INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRUNDBERG, ANDY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SALTZER, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900610T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D7113BF933A25755C0A966958260" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pastimes;   Camera</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andy Grundberg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRUNDBERG, ANDY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Those who think that the spirit of photographic invention has fled from the United States to Japan should pay a visit to Joe Saltzer's darkroom, a scant hour's drive north of New York City. You won't find the latest hybrid 35-millimeter camera there, but you will see some of the best designed and easiest to use darkroom tools ever developed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Those who think that the spirit of photographic invention has fled from the United States to Japan should pay a visit to Joe Saltzer's darkroom, a scant hour's drive north of New York City. You won't find the latest hybrid 35-millimeter camera there, but you will see some of the best designed and easiest to use darkroom tools ever developed.</p>
        <p>Those who think that the spirit of photographic invention has fled from the United States to Japan should pay a visit to Joe Saltzer's darkroom, a scant hour's drive north of New York City. You won't find the latest hybrid 35-millimeter camera there, but you will see some of the best designed and easiest to use darkroom tools ever developed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Saltzer, who is a photographer from the large-format, Zone System school, has taught and written about black-and-white printing for more than 20 years. What he doesn't know about home darkrooms probably could fit on the head of a pin. But unlike the rest of us, he was not satisfied to simply make use of existing darkroom equipment. He knew it could be better, so he set up a company to make and sell his own line of specialized darkroom products.</p>
        <p>The company is called SaltHill Photographic Instruments, Inc. Its mailing address is Wildcat Road, Chappaqua, N.Y. 10514, which is Joe Saltzer's home address. The company's research and development headquarters is located in the darkroom in the basement of his home. SaltHill is what you might call a small manufacturing and marketing firm.</p>
        <p>What does Joe Saltzer sell? For starters there is his Cross Current Archival Washer. Based on a design used by Kostiner, Zone VI and other makers of plexi-style print washers, the SaltHill version incorporates several essential improvements. Most important in terms of archival endurance is the design of the air jets that keeps prints from sticking to the plexi dividers. Unlike jets in other washers, those in Joe Saltzer's model really get unwashed prints jumping in their slots. And they do it with a minimum of water flow, which means smaller water bills and less waste.</p>
        <p>If you live in an area with really expensive water, the SaltHill washer can be connected to an aquarium pump. The pump keeps the air jets at peak performance even with a minimum of water flowing through the washer. It's not something everyone would want to do, but then Mr. Saltzer isn't designing darkroom tools for everyone.</p>
        <p>Another SaltHill washing aid is called the Vortex Wash Tray. It is basically a holding tank for unwashed prints that can also be used to wash one print at a time. The tray can handle up to a 16-by-20-inch print but also works fine with 8-by-10's. Like the washer, it is built to survive all but a direct nuclear hit. All acrylic parts are joined by something called slow-solvent welding, which Mr. Saltzer explains is less sloppy and more long-lasting than conventional epoxy gluing.</p>
        <p>SaltHill's other bombproof products include a print easel that is the best feeling and smoothest easel I've ever touched, and a forced-air print dryer that dries prints in less than an hour while maintaining archival quality. The easel is incredibly well engineered with a ''fifth blade'' for easily centering the paper under the enlarger and Teflon-impregnated railings for smooth adjustments.</p>
        <p>Like most of Joe Saltzer's designs, the Forced-Air Archival Dryer solves two problems in one blow (no pun intended). One problem has been that most print dryers are not archival; they leave residues on the print surface. Drying screens solve that problem but create two others: the prints take forever and a day to dry, and they usually curl at the edges.</p>
        <p>Saltzer's Archival Dryer protects wet prints from contamination by sandwiching them between layers of fiber webbing backed with acid-free board. A stack of these sandwiches are placed in the dryer and a fan and heating element do the rest. No curl, no overnight wait for dry prints. The dryer comes in two models, one for drying 20 11-by-14-inch prints at a time and another that handles the same number of 16-by-20's.</p>
        <p>Are these machines too arcane? I haven't even told you yet about the Salthill enlarging timer, its Trilinear Alignment Tool, or the fiber-optic densitometer that so far exists only as a non-working model. But that's the glory of entrepreneurs like Joe Saltzer: if something can be made better or easier to use, he will make it, whether there is a mass market for it or not.</p>
        <p>Besides being highly engineered and exquisitely built and finished, Joe Saltzer's SaltHill products are expensive. The 1989 catalog price for an 11-by-14-inch versions of the Cross-Current washer is $525, which is about $100 more than the competition. The smaller-sized print dryer goes for $540 and the rock-solid easel for $320. Again, that's substantially more than prices elsewhere. One consolation is that SaltHill equipment comes with a lifetime guarantee.</p>
        <p>Will Joe Saltzer make a fortune selling specialized darkroom equipment at high prices? I hope he does. But the essential point is that there are still folks around who are sufficiently devoted to photography to try to make things easier for the rest of us - not just to sell us the latest gizmo.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
