<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dining as the Nation's Founders Did</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="696437"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECLARATION OF INDEPENDENCE (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HISTORIC BUILDINGS AND SITES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CITY TAVERN (PHILADELPHIA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL PARK SERVICE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STAIB, WALTER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BANKS, DEREK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E6D6143CF93AA15755C0A962958260" item-length="2033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dining as the Nation's Founders Did</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it opened more than 200 years ago, City Tavern was Le Cirque of Philadelphia. Started by a group of 53 prominent investors, including Lieut. Gov. John Penn and several signers of the Declaration of Independence, it was decidedly clubby and, as John Adams wrote, created suppers "as elegant as was ever laid on a table." Some meetings of the Second Continental Congress were held there, as were more raucous gatherings where prodigious quantities of alcohol were consumed.</p>
        <p>Now, just in time for the Fourth of July, a refurbished City Tavern is reopening, in an incarnation that celebrates its history and the nation's food legacy. The restaurant opens to the public on June 30. On June 29 at noon, Mayor Edward G. Rendell will sit down to lunch with 60 city and business leaders. Had he been Mayor some 200 years ago, he might have done the same.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When it opened more than 200 years ago, City Tavern was Le Cirque of Philadelphia. Started by a group of 53 prominent investors, including Lieut. Gov. John Penn and several signers of the Declaration of Independence, it was decidedly clubby and, as John Adams wrote, created suppers "as elegant as was ever laid on a table." Some meetings of the Second Continental Congress were held there, as were more raucous gatherings where prodigious quantities of alcohol were consumed.</p>
        <p>Now, just in time for the Fourth of July, a refurbished City Tavern is reopening, in an incarnation that celebrates its history and the nation's food legacy. The restaurant opens to the public on June 30. On June 29 at noon, Mayor Edward G. Rendell will sit down to lunch with 60 city and business leaders. Had he been Mayor some 200 years ago, he might have done the same.</p>
        <p>City Tavern, a restaurant with lodgings, was established in 1773 but burned down in 1854. When the National Park Service decided to reconstruct the tavern in 1948, not even the foundation remained. The project was finished in time for the bicentennial in 1976.</p>
        <p>It cost $1.5 million to rebuild the tavern, a handsome five-story, Federal-style building on South Second Street at Walnut Street, not far from Independence Hall. To make it authentic, the Park Service used drawings, insurance surveys and other documents of the time and went as far as to have the bricks handmade, as they would have been in the late 18th century.</p>
        <p>The rebuilt City Tavern fitted right in with the rest of the landmarks in Philadelphia's Independence Park district. But the food failed to live up to the structure. The restaurant was run by the Canteen Corporation, which initially tried to offer food typical of the era of George Washington. But quality and authenticity eroded under the pressure to turn a profit in what became a seasonal, tourists-only venture. A subsequent operator did no better.</p>
        <p>Now, perhaps, gastronomic history will be better served. A year and a half ago, the Park Service closed the restaurant and began a search for a new operator. In February, after considering a number of proposals, it selected one from Walter Staib, a restaurant consultant in nearby Bryn Mawr, Pa. The contract required Congressional approval, and when it was granted on April 15, Mr. Staib was nervously looking at the calendar. "My dream was to open by the Fourth of July, and I began to wonder if we would make it," he said.</p>
        <p>Not to worry. The Government has in Mr. Staib, 48, a man whose vision and attention to detail operate in overdrive. "I've been working so closely and intensely with this, I sometimes feel as though I was actually here at the time, in another life," Mr. Staib said last week as he guided a visitor through the building and offered tastes of some of the dishes that will be on City Tavern's menu.</p>
        <p>As his executive chef, Mr. Staib hired Derek Banks, 29, who graduated from the Culinary Institute of America and has become nearly as passionate as Mr. Staib about the historic aspects of the project. The two had worked together before, at the Excelsior Hotel in Little Rock, Ark. "I love the history, finding out where the foods and cuisines came from," Mr. Banks said. "And I have become fascinated with Thomas Jefferson, who was definitely the food guru of the era."</p>
        <p>The menu will include smoked pheasant and trout, baked crab meat, a lush wild mushroom bisque laced with sherry, pork tenderloin in oatmeal stout, quail roasted with bread stuffing and glazed with a raisin and brandy sauce, pork pie, a seafood stew and several dishes with sausages. Some West Indian dishes like pepper pot soup were popular in 1773 and will appear on the new menu. An old-fashioned taste is suggested in a number of dishes by the addition of sherry and allspice. Main dishes at dinner range in price from $14.25 to $22.50, and at lunch, from $6.75 to $14.25.</p>
        <p>Some of the dishes seem startlingly modern -- like an appetizer of artichoke bottoms stuffed with peas, and salad dressings made with olive oil -- yet, they are historically valid. "Jefferson grew artichokes and 30 kinds of peas," Mr. Banks said. "And he loved olive oil so much he brought it back from Italy and wanted to plant trees here. That didn't work out, so he arranged for Africans to bring sesame seeds so they could be pressed for oil instead." Mr. Banks is also using a lot of marinades, he said, "because that's what they did in those days."</p>
        <p>Mr. Staib said that there is a fine line between re-creating the old and accommodating modern tastes. "If someone wants a margarita, we'll serve it, but bottles of tequila will not be visible on the bar," he said. "We have no sandwiches on the menu because they were not served in America at the time."</p>
        <p>All items on the menu, as well as the furnishings and tableware, had to be approved by Park Service historians. "They insisted on brass candlesticks because they said pewter was not used for candles in the late 18th century," Mr. Staib said. "Their historic window for this is about 1770 to 1790. They would not allow us to put flowers on the table. It's never easy when you're dealing with 50 million curators."</p>
        <p>The dinnerware reproduces an 18th-century pattern, as do the goblets, which are made with a metal alloy that looks like pewter, rather than real pewter, which contains lead.</p>
        <p>The Park Service did not permit certain historically accurate touches, like a whiff of curry in a sauce. "They were afraid spices like that would confuse the customers," Mr. Staib said. The issue of whether saffron will be acceptable has not been resolved.</p>
        <p>Mr. Staib and Mr. Banks have started working with local growers of fruits and vegetables, especially those in nearby Lancaster County, and plan to start their own herb garden behind the restaurant. "The first thing I did when I came in here was get rid of the freezers," Mr. Staib said. "We only have a small one for ice cream."</p>
        <p>The chandeliers will be dimly lit with 20-watt bulbs to simulate candlelight. "We're using large type on the menus," Mr. Staib said. He has made mostly cosmetic changes in the decor. The high-ceilinged rooms have been painted in muted colors, the wood floors are freshly scraped and the carpeting was designed from a needlepoint pattern researched by Park Service historians. Mr. Staib will use the basement rooms with fireplaces as private dining rooms.</p>
        <p>As in the past, strong drink will be sold. "We know from the data there were parties you would not believe," Mr. Staib said. "They consumed incredible amounts of sherry, port, Madeira and wine." City Tavern will be the only place serving Thomas Jefferson Ale, an amber brew with an alcohol content of 9.8 percent, twice that of most beers. It is being made by Dock Street Brewing Company in Philadelphia according to Jefferson's recipe. "We had been working on the beer, and when we saw work was being done on the tavern, we came by to try to get the account," said Peter Breslow, a sales representative for the brewery. "The coincidence was unbelievable."</p>
        <p>The beer will be served in small stemmed glasses because of its strength. It will be available in the dining rooms as well as in the bar room, whose bar is actually fitted with wooden bars to secure it. "That's the origin of the term," Mr. Staib said.</p>
        <p>City Tavern is not Mr. Staib's first encounter with American history. The Parker House Hotel in Boston and the Sagamore Hotel in upstate New York are among his previous consulting assignments.</p>
        <p>A native of Pforzheim, Germany, a town at the edge of the Black Forest, Mr. Staib began working in his parents' restaurant when he was 6. In 1969 he got a job as a chef in Chicago, and never went back to Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Staib has no partners in the City Tavern project. It is the first job in which he has invested his own money, nearly $500,000 so far.</p>
        <p>Each of the handmade costumes for the servers, from the mobcaps to the historically accurate shoes with no left or right, cost $400. He redid the kitchens and bought all the tableware. He plans eventually to open a shop to sell some of the items as souvenirs, along with baked goods and the like.</p>
        <p>Records show that Daniel Smith, the tavern's first innkeeper, a man who straddled the fence politically and ran off to England after the Revolutionary War, purchased all the fixtures and furnishings.</p>
        <p>"That even makes our expenses authentic," Mr. Staib said.</p>
        <p>Early American Cuisine: Varied, but No Sandwiches  West Indian Pepper Pot Soup  (Adapted from City Tavern)  Total time: 45 minutes  1 link Italian hot sausage  1/4 pound corned beef in one piece  1 large onion, chopped  4 scallions, chopped  1 bay leaf  2 sprigs fresh thyme  1/2 Scotch bonnet pepper or other small hot chili, seeded and minced, or hot red pepper flakes or cayenne pepper to taste  1 1/2 teaspoons whole allspice  1/2 teaspoon whole black peppercorns  6 cups beef stock  2 cups shredded callaloo, spinach, mustard greens or other greens  1 medium-size carrot, peeled and diced  1/2 pound yuca, peeled and diced  3/4 cup diced chayote or yellow squash  Salt to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Dice the sausage, place it in a 3- to 4-quart saucepan and cook over medium heat until lightly browned. Dice the corned beef, add it and continue to cook a few minutes. Add the onion, scallions, bay leaf and thyme, and continue to cook until the onion is tender. Stir in the hot chili or pepper.</p>
        <p>2. In a mortar or spice grinder, crush the allspice and peppercorns and add them to the pot. Stir, then add the stock. Bring to a simmer, and add the greens. Cook for 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>3. Add the carrot, yuca and squash and cook about 10 minutes longer. Taste, adjust the amount of pepper if necessary and season with salt. Remove the bay leaf and thyme before serving.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 200 calories, 9 grams fat, 30 milligrams cholesterol, 660 milligrams sodium (before salting), 10 grams protein, 20 grams carbohydrate. Seafood Stew  (Adapted from City Tavern)  Total time: 45 minutes  1 cup medium-dry or fruity white wine</p>
        <p>2 pounds mussels, scrubbed and debearded  1 tablespoon unsalted butter, or more to taste  1 large onion, sliced thin  1 bulb fennel, sliced thin  3 shallots, sliced thin  12 jumbo shrimp, peeled and deveined  1 pound bay scallops  1/4 cup amontillado sherry  1/2 cup heavy cream  Salt and freshly ground white pepper  A few drops lemon juice  1 tablespoon minced chives.</p>
        <p>1. Place 1/2 cup wine in a 3-quart saucepan, and bring to a boil. Add the mussels, cover and cook over medium heat until the mussels open, about 10 minutes. Use a slotted spoon to remove the mussels to a bowl. Strain the cooking liquid through a very fine strainer into a 2-cup measure. Add enough water to make 1 1/2 cups, and set aside.</p>
        <p>2. Rinse any grit out of the saucepan. Place it over medium heat to dry it; then, add the butter. Add the onion, fennel and shallots, and saute, stirring from time to time, until they are tender but not brown.</p>
        <p>3. Add the remaining wine, and cook over high heat until nearly all the wine evaporates. Add the mussel liquid. Bring to a boil, and add the shrimp. Cover, and cook about 5 minutes, until the shrimp are not quite completely pink. Stir in the scallops, cover and cook about 3 minutes. Add the mussels in their shells, cover and cook 2 minutes longer, until the mussels are reheated and the other seafood is cooked.</p>
        <p>4. Using a slotted spoon, transfer the seafood, onions and fennel to a large, warmed, shallow serving bowl. Cover the bowl.</p>
        <p>5. Bring the contents of the saucepan to a boil, add the sherry and cream and cook briskly for 5 minutes or so, until the liquid has reduced and thickened somewhat. Season to taste with salt and pepper, and add the lemon juice. Swirl in a little additional butter if desired. Pour the sauce over the seafood, sprinkle with chives and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 440 calories, 20 grams fat, 220 milligrams cholesterol, 570 milligrams sodium (before salting), 45 grams protein, 20 grams carbohydrate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
