<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Pass Can Set Up Or Start Up an Offense</title>
    <meta content="29NFLL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1035230"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TRAINING CAMP PREVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980729T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7DE1438F93AA15754C0A96E958260" item-length="1123" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Pass Can Set Up Or Start Up an Offense</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas George NFL training camp preview (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The essence of winning football is the running game. This question follows: Does the run set up the pass, or does the pass set up the run?</p>
        <p>It is a puzzle as old as the game. As National Football League training camps unfold in earnest this week, each team attempts to solidify exactly what role the passing game will play in its season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The essence of winning football is the running game. This question follows: Does the run set up the pass, or does the pass set up the run?</p>
        <p>It is a puzzle as old as the game. As National Football League training camps unfold in earnest this week, each team attempts to solidify exactly what role the passing game will play in its season.</p>
        <p>The difference in thinking on the question can be dramatic among the N.F.L.'s 30 teams. Oakland, for example, says that the deep, vertical passing game is the way to go. That approach sets up the run and breaks down defenses and keeps the opponent always on its heels. It strikes fear. Pittsburgh, however, insists that pounding the football up the middle via the run softens any defense. It makes the enemy bring its safeties up to support the run defense. Then pow. Hit 'em with the home run, the deep pass.</p>
        <p>The answer, in fact, lies somewhere in between. It is all about efficiency. Choose your strategy: run first or pass first. Simply carry it out efficiently.</p>
        <p>And when you do pass, work on improving in a few specific areas that are crucial to success.</p>
        <p>Whether you run or pass, the first essential ingredients of a productive offense are, of course, a stout and mobile offensive line and skilled players at the skill positions to make the offense click. Avoiding turnovers is critical. Avoiding dropped balls in the passing game is critical, too.</p>
        <p>Given all that, success in today's N.F.L. passing game frequently hinges on increasing average yards gained per pass attempt, allowing fewer sacks and using the short pass as a substitute for the run.</p>
        <p>If a team can master these interrelated areas, it is on its way to a successful passing offense.</p>
        <p>The numbers from the 1997 N.F.L. season say so. The teams that ranked No. 1 through No. 7 in average yards per pass attempt, with sacks included as attempts, all reached the playoffs last season. Five of those teams won 11 or more games.</p>
        <p>Oakland (No. 3), Cincinnati (No. 7), Atlanta (No. 8), Philadelphia (No. 12) and Indianapolis (No. 13) sat pretty in average yards per pass attempt without considering sacks allowed. Factor in the sacks, and their rankings dropped to 10, 9, 15, 17 and 21, respectively.</p>
        <p>One way around the puzzle of running first or passing first is to use the pass as the run.</p>
        <p>Over the past decade, San Francisco has been the champion of this tactic. How many times did Joe Montana and Steve Young play catch with tight end Brent Jones? Jones would run 4 yards, turn around, catch the ball and fall down for 3 more yards, and the result was the equivalent of a 7-yard run. The game clock kept running, too, keeping the ball away from the opponent's offense. Easy stuff. Or those swing passes the 49ers used to a variety of backs -- Roger Craig or Ricky Watters, now Garrison Hearst -- for 5 and 6 yards or a little more. Stay inbounds and the clock runs. Again, the equivalent of a running play.</p>
        <p>That is en vogue in the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>Where do we stand in the passing game, teams ask? Here are some answers. Following each team is its number of sacks allowed and yardage lost on those sacks.</p>
        <p>INDIANAPOLIS (62 sacks for 430 yards) The Colts must throw more quickly and throw more often to tight end Ken Dilger. He caught 27 balls last season and averaged 14.1 yards a catch. That's a hot average for a tight end.</p>
        <p>MIAMI (22 for 153) Dan Marino is protected well and throws it fast. The Dolphins need more speed and fewer dropped passes to take advantage.</p>
        <p>NEW ORLEANS (50 for 317) Not only 50 sacks allowed, but also 33 interceptions thrown. No wonder the Saints suffered. They must improve in both pass protection and possession time.</p>
        <p>DENVER (35 for 210) The Broncos took chances and made the gambles pay off. Last season they swung back and forth on the run-first/pass-first question: quarterback John Elway set up back Terrell Davis and then Davis set up Elway. Versatile. Makes them tough to defend. Helped make them champions.</p>
        <p>JACKSONVILLE (40 for 218) For the last two seasons this team has led the league in average yards per pass attempt with sacks included. Several teams allowed fewer sacks but lost more yardage. (Dallas, for example, allowed 39 sacks for 313 yards lost.) That says that Jaguars quarterback Mark Brunell is agile and elusive.</p>
        <p>GIANTS (32 for 238) Their average yards per pass attempt in both categories, with and without sacks, was at the bottom of the league, yet they won their division. Two things are clear: the running game was good and the defense was spectacular. For success in '98, the Giants need big improvement here.</p>
        <p>OAKLAND (58 for 530) Jeff George led the league in passing yards (3,917). He led the American Football Conference in touchdown passes (29). Yet he still spent too much time on his back, and the Raiders paid for their all-or-nothing scheme. The Raiders will tinker more with the short passing game.</p>
        <p>KANSAS CITY (32 for 236) The Chiefs ranked in the lower half of the league in average yards gained per pass, but with the free agent Derrick Alexander joining Andre Rison, they have a receiving package that can burn.</p>
        <p>ARIZONA (78 for 495) Where do you start to fix this?</p>
        <p>JETS (48 for 313) The more Glenn Foley plays, the more the Jets' passing numbers should improve. If Vinny Testaverde starts, he will have to reduce his interceptions (15 last season in Baltimore).</p>
        <p>SEATTLE (36 for 228) James McKnight led the league with 18.7 yards a catch last season. A steady mixture of deep passes to McKnight and short ones to the new Seahawk back, Ricky Watters, spells success.</p>
        <p>TAMPA BAY (32 for 196) Only six N.F.L. teams lost fewer than 200 yards when sacked. This was one. The others were Pittsburgh (152), Tennessee (199), Miami (153), Green Bay (191) and Washington (198).</p>
        <p>Does the run set up the pass or does the pass set up the run?</p>
        <p>It is a matter of choice for N.F.L. teams in the '98 season. Drops and interceptions, however, are not; they kill a passing offense. Completing big plays, avoiding sacks and using the short pass as a run bring the passing offense to life.</p>
        <p>TRAINING CAMP PREVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
