<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ways to Make the Most of the Strawberry Season</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="615134"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STRAWBERRIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fruit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930613T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE0DB173EF930A25755C0A965958260" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ways to Make the Most of the Strawberry Season</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE local strawberry crop is late this year, as it was last year, making the lush, ripe berries more welcome than ever. The season is now in full swing.</p>
        <p>Farm stands and markets throughout the region are overflowing with berries by the quart. Pickers take to the fields, and even some supermarkets have caught on and are selling locally grown strawberries from fields that perfume the air.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE local strawberry crop is late this year, as it was last year, making the lush, ripe berries more welcome than ever. The season is now in full swing.</p>
        <p>Farm stands and markets throughout the region are overflowing with berries by the quart. Pickers take to the fields, and even some supermarkets have caught on and are selling locally grown strawberries from fields that perfume the air.</p>
        <p>These are tender, fragile strawberries, best consumed within a day of picking. They should be kept refrigerated and hulled after they have been rinsed so they do not become waterlogged.</p>
        <p>Excess strawberries can be turned into jam or preserves. Sorbet and ice cream can extend their shelf life by a few days. Some cooks freeze the berries, but upon thawing they are watery and suitable only for sauce.</p>
        <p>Another approach is to dry them, a method of preserving the berries for future use that gives them an incomparably intense flavor, delicious as a snack or to add to granola, breads, cakes and sauces. In the few fancy food shops where they are sold dried, strawberries cost $15 to $18 a pound.</p>
        <p>In "How to Dry Foods" by Deanna DeLong (HP Books), the method for drying strawberries is explained in detail. Essentially, it calls for rinsing ripe strawberries, draining them well in a colander, then hulling them. They should be sliced in half vertically or, if they are very large, cut in slices at least a half-inch thick.</p>
        <p>The actual drying can be done in a regular oven or a toaster oven, but more even results are achieved by using a convection oven or an electric dehydrator.</p>
        <p>The berries should be placed cut side down on special screen or mesh drying racks. These are often sold where dehydrators are sold but can also be made using stainless-steel screening material.</p>
        <p>The recommended drying time for strawberries is about two hours at 150 degrees, initially; then this should be followed by further drying at 130 degrees until the berries are fully dehydrated.</p>
        <p>When dry, the berries should be pliable and still pinkish, but they will have no moisture. They will have a rich, jammy flavor.</p>
        <p>For safe storage over a period of several months, place the dried strawberries in airtight containers in the freezer.</p>
        <p>But so long as the season remains, there are also plenty of ways to use fresh berries at their peak. Strawberry-Watermelon Fruit Soup Total time: 30 minutes plus chilling  3 cups cubed watermelon, seeded  3 cups sliced ripe strawberries  Pinch of cinnamon  1 1/2 tablespoons superfine sugar  3/4 cup dry red wine  2 tablespoons finely slivered mint leaves.</p>
        <p>1. Place watermelon, half the strawberries, the cinnamon and sugar in food processor. Puree mixture.</p>
        <p>2. Transfer mixture to bowl and stir in wine. Refrigerate for an hour.</p>
        <p>3. To serve, divide the watermelon and strawberry puree among six soup bowls or large goblets. Spoon the remaining sliced strawberries into the soup and scatter the mint leaves on top. Serve at once.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings. Strawberry-Yogurt Roulade Total time: 1 hour plus cooling and chilling  Unsalted butter for greasing pan  3/4 cup cake flour  3/4 teaspoon baking powder  Pinch of salt  4 eggs, at room temperature  1/2 cup granulated sugar  Confectioners' sugar  1 pint ripe strawberries  3 tablespoons light brown sugar  3/4 cup plain nonfat yogurt.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 350 degrees. Butter a 10-by-15-inch jelly-roll pan; line it with a sheet of waxed paper cut to fit the width but extending a few inches at either end. Butter the paper.</p>
        <p>2. Sift together the flour, baking powder and salt. Set aside.</p>
        <p>3. Beat eggs at high speed until very thick and light, almost like softly whipped cream. Gradually beat in granulated sugar, then fold in flour mixture. Spread the batter in the pan and bake for about 20 minutes until puffed and golden brown. Quickly run a knife around the edges of the pan.</p>
        <p>4. Heavily dust a clean dish towel (but not terrycloth) or a sheet of waxed paper with sifted confectioners' sugar and invert cake, pan and all, on surface. Lift off pan, peel off waxed paper and gently roll cake up from narrow side in towel or paper. Allow to cool completely.</p>
        <p>5. Rinse and hull the berries. Slice them and fold in the brown sugar. Drain the yogurt of any excess liquid and gently fold it into the berries.</p>
        <p>6. Carefully unroll the cake and spoon the berry mixture over the surface. Slowly re-roll the cake as tightly as possible without causing the berry mixture to ooze out. Gently wrap it in foil, enclosing it completely and refrigerate it for at least an hour.</p>
        <p>7. To serve, transfer it to a serving dish and, using a serrated knife, cut slices from open ends at an angle.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
