<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arms Ban Leaves Owners Feeling Pistol-Whipped</title>
    <meta content="17BRIT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Bisley Journal" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="944254"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="Bisley Journal"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bisley (Eng)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gun Control</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970717T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9901EEDC1038F934A25754C0A961958260" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arms Ban Leaves Owners Feeling Pistol-Whipped</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>BISLEY, England, July 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Shooting enthusiasts in Bisley, Eng, for annual target shooting competition, premiere event of its kind, are upset over current and pending laws to tighten curbs on gun ownership; map; photo (M)U</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There is a sureness to this place, with its sweep of green fields, striped wind pennants fluttering from high masts and people ambling along leafy paths and lolling on the covered porches of their Victorian bungalows.</p>
        <p>And never is there more of a sense of permanence here than in July, the month that Bisley Camp is the site of the Imperial Meeting, the event that is to target shooting what Wimbledon is to tennis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There is a sureness to this place, with its sweep of green fields, striped wind pennants fluttering from high masts and people ambling along leafy paths and lolling on the covered porches of their Victorian bungalows.</p>
        <p>And never is there more of a sense of permanence here than in July, the month that Bisley Camp is the site of the Imperial Meeting, the event that is to target shooting what Wimbledon is to tennis.</p>
        <p>But this year, July has taken on a new and unsettling significance for the members of the Bisley community, causing them to focus their attention more on the present and the future than on the annual reaffirmation of traditions of their sport reaching back to archery tournaments in the 14th century.</p>
        <p>''It's a bloody disaster is what it is,'' said Roger Millard, a partner in G. E. Fulton &amp; Son Registered Gunsmiths.</p>
        <p>Starting on July 1 and continuing until Oct. 1, owners of pistols larger than .22 caliber must turn them in to police stations around the country under a law passed last year, and next summer the pistols exempted from that ban will be confiscated under a new, more stringent law now moving toward certain adoption in Parliament.</p>
        <p>Both laws tighten restrictions on gun ownership in a country with a police force famous for going unarmed and with laws that were already the strictest of any Western country's. But two nationally traumatizing events -- the killing of 14 people on the main street of the Berkshire town of Hungerford in 1987 by a man with a rifle, and the massacre of 16 schoolchildren and their teacher by a man wielding four handguns in the Scottish town of Dunblane in March 1996 -- produced a public and political demand for action.</p>
        <p>Under far-reaching laws existing at the time, machine guns, self-loading rifles and semiautomatic shotguns were illegal and others types of firearms like pistols, revolvers, rifles and shotguns required a certificate of good ''character'' and a clean record from the police renewable every five years.</p>
        <p>In both the Hungerford and Dun blane incidents, however, the killers had licensed weapons, leading to a perception that the existing laws were not sufficient.</p>
        <p>''Of course, the problem wasn't the law, it was the lack of enforcement of the law,'' said C. C. C. Cheshire, a retired lieutenant colonel in the Royal Tank Regiment and chief executive of the National Rifle Association, which has its headquarters here.  ''Neither one of those men would have had weapons if the police had done their job.''</p>
        <p>In Dunblane, the constable who had approved the killer's certificate admitted his failure and resigned from the force.</p>
        <p>Dismay and anger have taken hold of the shooting enthusiasts who flock here over what they perceive as the demonization of their sport and its membership.</p>
        <p>''We are all parents, and the fact that this was a ghastly thing to have happened sent a shock wave through this community too,'' Mr. Millard said. He spends much of his time now providing valuations of pistols to be turned in, and he warmed to a question about the nature of the people bringing in their guns for assessment.</p>
        <p>''Lawyers and lorry drivers,'' he said, ''doctors and dustmen, soldiers and solicitors, one in a wheelchair and a couple of lady shooters. What I haven't seen, and am unlikely to, is the villain in the black balaclava who wants his handgun valued before doing over the local sub post office.''</p>
        <p>Speaking to an American visitor while tattoos of small-arms fire sounded outside his window, Colonel Cheshire said: ''We're not talking about weapons made to kill people, these are for shooting paper targets. And I hope you will take this in context, but a lot of our gun culture has come from the United States over the last 40 years. Every sport has its odd'uns and the way people dress shouldn't really be an issue, but you see a fellow with a leather jacket and  two holsters on his hips, and you get scared.''</p>
        <p>Albie Fox, owner of an embroidery store catering to shooters and director of the Sportsman's Association, said, ''The gun culture in the U.K. is what people see on television from America, and that has become what people perceive us to be.''</p>
        <p>Unlike its namesake in the United States, the National Rifle Association here is not a lobby but a charity. Prince Charles is its president, and one of its missions is ''defense of the realm.''</p>
        <p>The organization says it welcomes restrictions on ownership like those proposed by an independent Government commission set up after Dun blane that would have required gun owners to keep weapons locked in one of the country's approved 2,118 clubs.</p>
        <p>''We cannot proceed here on the argument that owning a gun is a constitutional right,'' Colonel Cheshire said. ''Here it is a privilege.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Fox said his association not only wasn't against gun control, it favored creation of a firearms board to control licenses. There are 200,000 legally held handguns in Britain that will have to be turned in or taken out of the country. Estimates of illegal handguns, which will not be reached by the law, start at one million.</p>
        <p>The Government has promised compensation equal to 75 percent of the list price of weapons turned in, starting at $250 for what Colonel Cheshire called ''common garden'' pistols to more than $2,000 for guns with higher valuations because of their historical value or elaborate construction.</p>
        <p>Businesses and clubs that shut down or suffer losses will get no compensation, and some of them are planning to take their cases to European Community courts. The ultimate cost to the Government is estimated at anywhere from $250 million to $850 million.</p>
        <p>Many gun owners are taking their arms abroad, and some of the 139 pistol clubs are relocating to countries like Belgium, France and Switzerland. Target shooting with rifles, a large segment of the sport, is unaffected by the new laws, and the Government has said it will give special dispensation to foreign pistol teams coming to Manchester for the Commonwealth Games in 2002.</p>
        <p>The British national pistol team, long an Olympic force, will also be allowed to compete. But to comply with the new law, it will have to train abroad.</p>
        <p>Bisley Journal</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
