<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bensonhurst Case Ends, Satisfying Few</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="429928"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RACIAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSAULTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BENSONHURST (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAWKINS, YUSUF K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAUCCI, PASQUALE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLTZMAN, ELIZABETH (DIST ATTY)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HYNES, CHARLES J (DIST ATTY)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEELE, SHELBY (PROF)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHARPTON, AL (REV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assaults</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910314T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DA1E3BF937A25750C0A967958260" item-length="1497" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bensonhurst Case Ends, Satisfying Few</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM GLABERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GLABERSON, WILLIAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After 19 months of painful legal proceedings, the Bensonhurst case, which once transfixed New Yorkers, has ended, leaving many of those who cared most about it dissatisfied with its results and leaving unanswered many of the questions it raised about race and New York City.</p>
        <p>The end came on Tuesday, when Pasquale Raucci, the last of the Bensonhurst defendants, was cleared of murder charges but convicted of lesser counts. To some New Yorkers, Mr. Raucci's case was just another in a line of eight prosecutions that failed to properly condemn the killers of Yusuf K. Hawkins, the black teen-ager who was shot to death on an August night in 1989 while looking for a used car in the mostly white Brooklyn neighborhood.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After 19 months of painful legal proceedings, the Bensonhurst case, which once transfixed New Yorkers, has ended, leaving many of those who cared most about it dissatisfied with its results and leaving unanswered many of the questions it raised about race and New York City.</p>
        <p>The end came on Tuesday, when Pasquale Raucci, the last of the Bensonhurst defendants, was cleared of murder charges but convicted of lesser counts. To some New Yorkers, Mr. Raucci's case was just another in a line of eight prosecutions that failed to properly condemn the killers of Yusuf K. Hawkins, the black teen-ager who was shot to death on an August night in 1989 while looking for a used car in the mostly white Brooklyn neighborhood.</p>
        <p>For others, the case did not produce the vindication that they thought Bensonhurst deserved. For the prosecutors, the case was both a political embarrassment and a professional frustration -- a failed effort to hold a mob responsible for its actions.</p>
        <p>And for the city as a whole, the case ended without fully explaining what had happened.</p>
        <p>Like the Rosenberg espionage trial in the 1950's and the Scottsboro Boys rape trial in the 1930's, the Bensonhurst case came to stand for things that were bigger than the fate of the defendants, bigger even than the particular grief involved. It became an emblem of a social issue, the conflict between blacks and whites.</p>
        <p>But lawyers often caution that courts handle individual cases only according to the courts' own narrow rules, and that juries and judges therefore rarely have the chance to declare winners of social debates.</p>
        <p>Because of that, the disappointment with the verdicts was almost inevitable, said James B. Jacobs, the director of the Center for Research in Crime and Justice at New York University. "We pump a lot of symbolism into these cases," Mr. Jacobs said. "They stand for a lot of things to people, and there is no resolution that would bring closure to the symbolism, the emotions and the politics that are pumped into these trials."  Racial 'Perception Gap'</p>
        <p>Shelby Steele, the essayist on race relations who made a television documentary on the Bensonhurst case, said the case was always a surrogate for a broader debate. It exposed a "perception gap," he said, between blacks and whites about the extent of racism and racial violence in America.</p>
        <p>From the start, Mr. Steele said, two separate views of reality were being tested by the Bensonhurst case. Many blacks, he said, saw in the Hawkins killing a confirmation of their view that the oppression and even the killing of blacks remain acceptable in America. Many whites, perceiving a far more benign racial climate, he said, saw nothing more than a teen-age dispute tragically out of control.</p>
        <p>High-profile trials with race an issue have framed such debates for decades. In 1955, the acquittals of two Mississippi white men charged with killing Emmett Till, a black teen-ager who had supposedly whistled at a white woman, aroused an anger that helped give rise to the civil-rights movement. The Howard Beach assault and the rape of the jogger in Central Park were other recent cases in New York that seemed to promise answers that could not be delivered about society and its racial divisions.</p>
        <p>"We have a natural longing," Mr. Steele said, "that these court cases, somehow, will resolve this larger debate over reality: 'Is America a place where a black kid can be killed by a white mob for walking down the street? Is that true, or is it not true?' We long for the court cases to resolve that debate for us, and they really can't do that, no matter what the verdict is."  Questions of Justice</p>
        <p>Of the 30 or more young men who the prosecutors said had joined in the violence in Bensonhurst, only eight were tried and only one, Joseph Fama, was convicted of murder. Three were acquitted of all charges.</p>
        <p>Those statistics alone convinced some people that the guilty were not punished.</p>
        <p>"Yusuf Hawkins did not get justice," the Rev. Al Sharpton, an adviser to the Hawkins family, said this week as he called for a Federal civil-rights investigation into the killing.</p>
        <p>In Bensonhurst, too, the end of the case has not quelled the passions it aroused. The Rev. Al Barozzi, the associate pastor of St. Dominic Roman Catholic Church, said people there still feel the case labeled all of Bensonhurst as racist and proved only that a typical neighborhood bully incident got out of control. "This was a bad incident which people here feel has been blown up by the press," Father Barozzi said. Nothing Was Clear-Cut</p>
        <p>In the streets, the facts of the case took on a clarity that helped make it a powerful symbol. But in the courtroom, the prosecution became a case study in the ambiguities that are often exposed during hard-fought trials.</p>
        <p>The jurors who convicted Mr. Fama of murder, for example, said they were not convinced that he had fired the shots that killed Mr. Hawkins.</p>
        <p>And it turned out that it was a black Bensonhurst youth who had carried bats through the streets to what the prosecution said was a gathering race riot of young white men.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors at first said grand jury testimony had showed that one of the Bensonhurst youths encouraged Mr. Fama to fire the shots. Actually, the testimony ended up showing that the young man did the opposite: He shouted out not to shoot.</p>
        <p>The Government's star witness, Gina Feliciano, said her inviting black and Hispanic friends from outside Bensonhurst to her birthday party had infuriated her young, mostly Italian-American, neighbors. She said she had seen many of them with guns.</p>
        <p>But defense lawyers quickly caught her on a tape recording telling her sister that she lied to the police about some details. Inconsistencies and her record of drug abuse led many jurors, some of them said, to discount everything Ms. Feliciano said.</p>
        <p>While the evidence did clearly show that a band of bat-wielding white youths had gathered to confront black and Hispanic outsiders, it nevertheless clouded the image of white racists indiscriminantly hunting blacks. It showed that in the instant before the shots rang out on 69th Street, some of the young white men seemed to realize that they were making a mistake. Just when it was too late, some of them seemed to understand that Mr. Hawkins and his three friends were not the outsiders they were looking for.  Wall of Silence</p>
        <p>Mr. Hawkins's friends testified that they had heard the young white men speaking to each other just before the 16-year-old fell to the ground with two bullet holes in his chest. "Are these the guys? Are these the guys?" the young whites were saying.</p>
        <p>The prosecutors said they met a stone wall of silence from the "brothers and sisters of Bensonhurst" who refused to tell about what they saw that night. But even if much of the community had not closed ranks, legal experts say, group-violence cases are difficult to prove because the chaos of group crimes defies the orderliness required later in court.</p>
        <p>In a group-crime case, it is never enough to prove simply that someone was at the place where a crime occurred. Instead, prosecutors must prove that each defendant intended to take part in a crime and did something to help make it happen. When a mob acts, said Robert M. Pitler, a former prosecutor who is now a professor of criminal law at Brooklyn Law School, its actions are often so random that it becomes impossible to reconstruct what happened.</p>
        <p>"A lot of people like to say that a trial is a search for the truth," Mr. Pitler said. "I don't think in these riot cases you ever know exactly what happened."</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharpton and other critics have said that the prosecutors mishandled the case from the start and too easily gave up trying to pierce that wall of Bensonhurst silence. The Brooklyn District Attorney, Charles J. Hynes, and his predecessor, Elizabeth Holtzman, have defended their handling of the prosecution. But in a case that left no winners, there is little doubt that Mr. Hynes and Ms. Holtzman, both ambitious Democratic politicians, were bruised.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sharpton can claim a limited symbolic victory despite the unsatisfying result in court. The marches he led through Bensonhurst exposed the power of racism, he said, when furious whites with contorted faces hoisted watermelons in front of television cameras.</p>
        <p>Much of the frustration in the wake of the Bensonhurst case may have been unavoidable, Mr. Sharpton said. That is because there were really two Bensonhurst cases, he said -- one about the substance of what happened and another about the symbolism.</p>
        <p>"The symbolism of the case," he said, "and the substance of the case at some time begin fighting each other because, in the end, the evidence of the case is what you have to render a verdict on, and you still have to answer what the symbolism of the case is. And I don't know if you can get a verdict that will satisfy both. I don't know if that can ever be achieved in the court."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
