<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Spoiling for a Fight</title>
    <meta content="18cheer" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/18/sports/othersports/18cheer.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1827198"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="CHEERING SECTION"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Apparel</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Hunter College</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070218T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E5D6143EF93BA25751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="711" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Spoiling for a Fight</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Amateur Boxer Is Spoiling for a Fight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By VINCENT M. MALLOZZI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallozzi, Vincent M</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Camille Currie was a boxing fan before her first fight -- as a sixth grader in the girls' bathroom at Stratford Academy in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''I won that fight,'' Currie, 29, said one recent morning at Mendez Boxing Gym in Manhattan, smiling as she wrapped her hands with tape. ''Too bad I can't add that one to my record.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Camille Currie’s amateur boxing record is 3-4, a fair amount of ring work for someone who has been boxing for only 15 months and has another job as the sports information director at Hunter College.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Camille Currie was a boxing fan before her first fight -- as a sixth grader in the girls' bathroom at Stratford Academy in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>''I won that fight,'' Currie, 29, said one recent morning at Mendez Boxing Gym in Manhattan, smiling as she wrapped her hands with tape. ''Too bad I can't add that one to my record.''</p>
        <p>Alas, Currie's amateur record is 3-4, a fair amount of ring work for someone who has been boxing for only 15 months and has another career. She is the sports information director at Hunter College on the Upper East Side.</p>
        <p>''I like to think that my boxing knowledge, combined with the fact that I was fairly athletic growing up, helps me in the ring,'' Currie said as she slipped on gloves. ''I was always a sports junkie, especially where boxing is concerned, and I still enjoy studying different fighters and the techniques and styles they bring to the ring.''</p>
        <p>Currie, who grew up in Stratford spending her allowance on boxing magazines and pay-per-view events that featured the likes of Pernell Whitaker, Lennox Lewis and Kevin Kelley -- her favorites -- was inspired to cross the line that separates spectator from slugger after watching the much-hyped 2001 bout between Laila Ali and Jacqui Frazier-Lyde, the daughters of former heavyweight champions.</p>
        <p>''That fight was incredible, and even though Ali won, they both did a lot for women's boxing,'' Currie said. ''They also proved that women can do anything they want in life as long as they work hard enough.''</p>
        <p>She attended Ali's fight Nov. 11 at Madison Square Garden, a technical knockout against Shelley Burton. Currie said boxing looks a lot scarier from a corner stool in a ring than from the sofa in her Manhattan apartment.</p>
        <p>''Every time I step inside a ring, I know it's either me or my opponent, and that's a pretty scary feeling,'' she said. ''The key is learning to overcome that fear.''</p>
        <p>Last year, the 5-foot-9 Currie signed up for New York's Golden Gloves tournament, to fight in the 132-pound division. She lost her first bout, a four-round decision to Karen Chance. Currie is returning to this year's Golden Gloves, and has a fight scheduled for Feb. 28 at the Copacabana against an opponent to be named. Finalists from each weight class will fight at the Garden in April.</p>
        <p>Shedrick Jackson, Currie's trainer, said: ''Camille is very passionate about boxing, and has made an odd but natural progression from fan to fighter. She's always researching, always calling me about the strengths and weaknesses of various fighters. She's constantly studying, constantly learning.''</p>
        <p>Currie, who said her goal in the ring was to be as technically sound as the junior middleweight Floyd Mayweather and as aggressive as the lightweight Juan Diaz, has been training and sparring three or four times a week to prepare for her next bout. She also jogs in Central Park to work on her stamina.</p>
        <p>''She usually gets here at sunrise, and comes back at night, after work,'' Francisco Mendez, who owns the gym, said. ''She's very nice, but very serious.''</p>
        <p>Jackson said: ''Camille's technique has grown tremendously since she lost in the Golden Gloves last year. She's always had the physical stature. But now she has better footwork and agility, a greater mental toughness and is thinking her way through fights a lot more clearly. She's much more competitive.''</p>
        <p>Currie played basketball at Delaware State; she was a point guard for two seasons beginning in 1996. Once a public relations assistant for the New York Liberty of the Women's National Basketball Association, she began working at Hunter in October 2004.</p>
        <p>Currie has become a bit of a celebrity on campus. Each morning, students greet her with questions like, ''How did it go last night; did you knock anybody out?'' Her role as a part-time pugilist has floored at least one of her colleagues.</p>
        <p>''Since I found out about Camille being a boxer, I treat her a bit differently,'' Jeff Bernstein, New York University's assistant athletic director for sports information, said. ''Now when I call to get a roster or some statistics from one of her teams, I always remember to say please and thank you. No need for me to get on her bad side.''</p>
        <p>CHEERING SECTION E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: cheers@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
