<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kenya's Hard Line: President Gambles on Crackdown</title>
    <meta content="09KENY$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="942577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Kenya</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moi, Daniel Arap (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Kenya</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E5DD1539F93AA35754C0A961958260" item-length="1021" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kenya's Hard Line: President Gambles on Crackdown</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <dateline>NAIROBI, Kenya, July 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Kenya's Pres Daniel arap Moi is gambling that pro-democracy opposition leaders lack popular support to weather the brutal crackdown he has launched against them; is also betting that Western powers will not abandon him; apparently sees opposition as too disorganized and splintered along ethnic lines to present viable alternative to his Government (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>By violently crushing pro-democracy  demonstrations across Kenya on Monday, President Daniel arap Moi has gambled that opposition leaders seeking to rewrite the nation's Constitution do not have enough popular support to weather a brutal police campaign against them.</p>
        <p>He is also wagering that Western powers will not abandon him just  because his police tear-gassed and clubbed hundreds of protesters who were demonstrating peacefully to dilute the powers of the presidency and increase civil liberties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>By violently crushing pro-democracy  demonstrations across Kenya on Monday, President Daniel arap Moi has gambled that opposition leaders seeking to rewrite the nation's Constitution do not have enough popular support to weather a brutal police campaign against them.</p>
        <p>He is also wagering that Western powers will not abandon him just  because his police tear-gassed and clubbed hundreds of protesters who were demonstrating peacefully to dilute the powers of the presidency and increase civil liberties.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moi's calculation appears  based on the notion that the opposition is too disorganized and splintered along ethnic lines to present a viable alternative to his Government, even if its human-rights record is less than perfect.</p>
        <p>And on both counts, he is probably right, political experts and diplomats said today.</p>
        <p>On Monday, nine people were killed in clashes at rallies across the nation in the worst political violence  since 1991, when a series of similar protests finally persuaded Mr. Moi to end the one-party state and allow multi-party elections.</p>
        <p>The police hardly needed to scatter the protesters with such force.  After weeks of dire official warnings to citizens not to attend the rallies,  the organizers did not draw the huge crowds they had hoped for. Most of the rallies planned in 56 towns across the nation attracted less than a thousand demonstrators.</p>
        <p>Abroad, the response to the mayhem was muted. Several Western diplomats issued statements today deploring the violence on both sides and urging the Government to talk to the opposition about its demands.</p>
        <p>In Washington, Nicholas Burns, the State Department spokesman, said that the violence was inspired by Kenya's ''failure to take the essential concrete steps to create a free and fair electoral climate.''</p>
        <p>But no country made mention of more palpable pressure, like cutting off Kenya's lifeline of low-interest loans from the International Monetary Fund. One reason is a fear of taking sides in the elections, which Mr. Moi must call before the end of the year. Mr. Moi says he is willing to appoint a commission to consider  amending the Constitution, but not until after the voting.</p>
        <p>The streets of Nairobi and other towns returned to normal during the  day, but as darkness fell tonight,  students clashed with the police near the Nairobi University campus and gunfire was heard.</p>
        <p>For most of the day, however, businesses reopened and the roads were  full of traffic, despite the heavy presence of paramilitary police officers.  Many workers returning to their jobs  today said that while they supported the protesters in principle, they were weary of the looting and violence attending the demonstrations.</p>
        <p>''It does worry us,'' Joseph Kwasi,  43, a shop clerk. ''We have children at home, and we have to worry about them. The protesters are fighting for their rights, and this is what most Kenyans need, but the problem is, once the violence starts there is no boundary. Anybody can be hurt.''</p>
        <p>In news conferences today, opposition politicians and human rights advocates vowed to step up their campaign of civil disobedience on Wednesday after a period of mourning for the people who were killed. Police officials, however, said that it was unlikely that demonstrators  would turn out in large numbers.</p>
        <p>One problem for the opposition is that the violence has alarmed many middle-class Kenyans who might otherwise support them. Each time the police have broken up protests in the last two months, the demonstrators -- their ranks swelled by college students angry about high tuition costs -- have turned quickly to looting shops and stoning cars.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people in the middle class are getting, I think, disillusioned with the fact that none of this violence is achieving any of its objectives,'' Anthony Nzuya, a Nairobi businessman, said. ''The way to get these reforms on the table is not through street violence.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Moi has skillfully exploited these fears, repeatedly portraying the opposition leaders as bent on sowing anarchy and violence. Thus he has neatly sidestepped the fact the police have been brutal.</p>
        <p>In addition, there are some cracks within the coalition of churches, human-rights groups and opposition party leaders who are pushing for  reforms. While the clergy and human-rights advocates are trying to roll back repressive laws limiting civil liberties, the opposition politicians have another motive. They want to change electoral rules in the  Constitution that make it hard for them to win. For instance, one proposed amendment would require a presidential candidate to get a simple majority, or face a run-off election. At present a President can be elected with less than half the vote, as long as he gets a quarter of the vote in five of the country's eight  provinces. The provision, added in 1992, served to weaken the two largest ethnic groups, the Kikuyu and the Luo, whose members are crammed into two districts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moi, who comes from a small ethnic group, was able to get only about 38 percent of the popular vote in 1996. He won only because most of the Luo and Kikuyu were split along ethnic lines among three candidates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Moi has other enormous advantages the coalition wants to end. He controls the official radio and television broadcasts. The electoral commission, which registers voters, is stacked with his appointees. Security laws left from the British colonial era give him sweeping powers to detain political enemies and break up public meetings and protests.</p>
        <p>But these issues do not resonate with the vast majority of Kenyans,  who are struggling with a sluggish economy, low wages, high education costs and widespread poverty.</p>
        <p>Despite today's calm, the atmosphere remains explosive. If the opposition continues to call marches, and Mr. Moi sticks to his hard line, some diplomats fear a conflagration.</p>
        <p>''There are three million people in Nairobi, most of them poor,'' said  one diplomat in Nairobi, who spoke on condition of anonymity. ''How many sparks do you need until something gets out of hand?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
