<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trainer Hitches Sulky To Steinbrenner Again</title>
    <meta content="09PACE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HARNESS RACING" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="942588"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="HARNESS RACING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Harness Racing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Meadowlands Pace</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jockeys, Drivers and Trainers</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kellner, Jenny</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gallagher, Bill</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinbrenner, George M 3d</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970709T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E1DB1539F93AA35754C0A961958260" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trainer Hitches Sulky To Steinbrenner Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNY KELLNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kellner, Jenny</byline>
      <dateline>WEST ORANGE, N.J., July 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on harness trainer Bill Gallagher notes that he is training George Steinbrenner's colt, Rod's Deal, for upcoming $1 million Meadowlands Pace (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bill Gallagher is not the first harness trainer to have an on-again, off-again relationship with an owner. When that owner happens to be George Steinbrenner, one cannot help wondering how many ons and how many offs that relationship will eventually have.</p>
        <p>''Well, you can never get too comfortable,'' Gallagher said, smiling, after Steinbrenner's colt, Rod's Deal, drew post position No. 3 for Friday night's $1 million Meadowlands Pace. ''He doesn't like to be second. And he doesn't like to lose.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bill Gallagher is not the first harness trainer to have an on-again, off-again relationship with an owner. When that owner happens to be George Steinbrenner, one cannot help wondering how many ons and how many offs that relationship will eventually have.</p>
        <p>''Well, you can never get too comfortable,'' Gallagher said, smiling, after Steinbrenner's colt, Rod's Deal, drew post position No. 3 for Friday night's $1 million Meadowlands Pace. ''He doesn't like to be second. And he doesn't like to lose.''</p>
        <p>For that matter, neither does Gallagher. At age 33, the Saginaw, Mich., native already has been twice hired, once fired by Steinbrenner, for whom he started working four years ago. The relationship began in Florida when Gallagher, who started training on his own in 1984, was asked by another trainer to ready a horse of Steinbrenner's for sale. After a short time in Gallagher's care, the colt fetched 10 times Steinbrenner's original asking price.</p>
        <p>Impressed, the owner sent Gallagher another horse to sell, then another. Within 18 months, Gallagher, who grew up as a Detroit Tigers fan and an avid Yankee hater, worked his way up from the minors to training a half-dozen horses for Steinbrenner on the East Coast, splitting his time between Pompano Park in Florida in the winter and his Meadowlands base at nearby Gaitway Farm in Englishtown, N.J., during the summer.</p>
        <p>''It's such a thrill to train for Steinbrenner,'' said Gallagher, who at age 13 began grooming standardbreds even as he was playing third base in the Saginaw Little League. ''I mean, if you can't play on his team, you might as well train his horses.''</p>
        <p>Taking his own advice to heart, Gallagher never took his position as Steinbrenner's trainer for granted. So it was no surprise to him last spring when, after several less-than-sparkling stakes performances by his horses, including the fine filly Personal Banner, Steinbrenner informed Gallagher he was changing trainers.</p>
        <p>''He wasn't happy with the way things were going, and frankly, neither was I,'' Gallagher said. ''It was a cordial parting and we even kept in contact. I didn't like seeing 75 percent of my stable leave, but that's business.</p>
        <p>Four months later, the phone rang in Gallagher's barn -- it was Steinbrenner, asking him to take Personal Banner back. And the others, as well.</p>
        <p>''Of course, I said yes,'' Gallagher said.</p>
        <p>Steinbrenner, who has owned several horses who have run in the Kentucky Derby, has been involved in standardbred racing since he was a child and takes an active personal interest in his trotters and pacers, even going so far as to exercise them on occasion.</p>
        <p>''I can't exercise my thoroughbreds, but I can get in a sulky and drive,'' Steinbrenner said in a conference call from Florida. ''I drove in an amateur series in 1987, and I can tell you I've been in some big athletic events in my life, but I had my stomach in my throat when we came up to the gate.''</p>
        <p>Friday night's race, in which Rod's Deal is one of the longer shots in the 10-horse field of 3-year-olds, will be the first Meadowlands Pace in which Steinbrenner and Gallagher have participated. Neither owner nor trainer is particularly thrilled with the way Rod's Deal has been performing recently. He finished fourth in his elimination race at the Meadowlands but made the final field when the third-place horse was taken down for interference.</p>
        <p>''He's got talent, but he's a head case,'' Gallagher said.</p>
        <p>''Like his owner,'' chimed in Steinbrenner.</p>
        <p>Red Bow Tie, driven by Bill Fahy, and Arturo, with Luc Oulette in the sulky, were made the 5-2 and 7-2 top choices after drawing posts No. 8 and No. 2, respectively.</p>
        <p>The rest of the field, from the rail out, includes Dream Away (Ron Pierce), 4-1; Rod's Deal, 10-1; Western Dreamer (Mike Lachance) and Park Place (Wally Hennessey), both at 6-1; J K Outlaw (Jack Moiseyev), 4-1; His Mattjesty (Doug Brown), 12-1; Village Jasper (Paul MacDonell), 15-1, and At Point Blank (John Campbell), 20-1 from the outside.</p>
        <p>''I don't know if we belong in there with these horses,'' Steinbrenner said. ''But I do know I need the money. Irabu pitches Thursday night and I'm hoping Friday night to come up with his paycheck.''</p>
        <p>HARNESS RACING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
