<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Giants, Tied for Best N.F.C. Mark at 7-2, Have Even Gaudier Possibilities</title>
    <meta content="08GIAN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/11/08/sports/08GIAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1245506"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Giants</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Rams</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Vikings</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pennington, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Minnesota Vikings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/St. Louis Rams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001108T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E7DB1139F93BA35752C1A9669C8B63" item-length="1013" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Giants, Tied for Best N.F.C. Mark at 7-2, Have Even Gaudier Possibilities</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL PENNINGTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pennington, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Speculation on possible post-season play for New York Giants, who are tied for best record in National Football Conference, 7-2, with Minnesota Vikings and St Louis Rams; article says Giants are on pace to have best year running since 1985, that defense against running game is superb and that turnovers are not a factor; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's a snowy, mid-January day at Giants Stadium, where a dull sky seems shaded gray to match the blunted, ashen outer walls of the big oval stadium set in the Meadowlands parking lots.</p>
        <p>The wind howls, the field is hard, the football crowd is bundled.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's a snowy, mid-January day at Giants Stadium, where a dull sky seems shaded gray to match the blunted, ashen outer walls of the big oval stadium set in the Meadowlands parking lots.</p>
        <p>The wind howls, the field is hard, the football crowd is bundled.</p>
        <p>It's a scene from a conference championship nearly 14 years ago, rendered for those Giants fans who can't remember that far back -- and to tease those who can.</p>
        <p>It doesn't much matter that it's still impractical to expect such a scene to be replicated two months from now.</p>
        <p>In a season of unrelenting serendipity for the Giants, this much is true:</p>
        <p>If the National Football League season ended today, the Giants would not only have a bye in the postseason, not only play host to a second-round playoff game, but also if they won that game, the National Football Conference championship game would be at Giants Stadium on Jan. 14.</p>
        <p>The Giants, who haven't had a winning season since 1997 and who entered the 2000 season losers in six of their last eight games, currently hold the edge in obtaining the home field throughout the conference playoffs.</p>
        <p>Though the 7-2 Giants are tied for the best record in the N.F.C. with Minnesota and St. Louis, the Giants have the advantage in the tie-breaker system because of a 6-1 conference record. Minnesota has a 4-2 conference record and St. Louis is 4-1. The first tie breaker is head-to-head play, but the teams haven't played each other yet.</p>
        <p>The Rams play at Giants Stadium on Sunday. St. Louis also plays Minnesota on Dec. 10, but the Giants will not face Minnesota in the regular season.</p>
        <p>With seven games to play in the season, any number of possibilities could play out -- including the Giants' not making the playoffs at all. The Washington Redskins or the Tampa Bay Buccaneers could end up with the top conference record, but if the Giants keep winning -- and a victory Sunday could be pivotal to the tie-breaking system -- the Giants can hold a commanding advantage.</p>
        <p>If it is unfathomable, it is also worth looking at how the Giants got in this position because a lot has changed from last year's 7-9 team. Among the factors contributing to the Giants' success this season:</p>
        <p>*The Giants are on a pace to have their best year running the football since 1985. With an average of 143.6 rushing yards a game, the Giants have been gaining 55.6 more yards a game than last year's team. The 1985 team averaged 153.2 yards a game. The drafting of Ron Dayne and the expanded use of Tiki Barber have allowed the Giants to return to their rushing roots. Dayne's 515 rushing yards and Barber's 621 rushing yards are more than last season's leading rusher, Joe Montgomery, who had 348 yards.</p>
        <p>*The Giants have balance offensively. For all the production on the ground, the Giants have passed the football nearly as much as they have run it, which keeps them unpredictable and harder to defend. The Giants have 285 pass attempts and 308 rushing attempts through nine games. They have scored 11 touchdowns through the air and 9 on the ground. Last season, the Giants threw the football 603 times and ran it 430 times.</p>
        <p>*Running against the Giants defense has been virtually impossible. Eddie George of Tennessee has been the only ball carrier to have a 100-yard rushing game against the Giants, who rank second in the league in rushing defense. Four opposing teams have had fewer than 50 yards rushing. Last year's opponents averaged 97.5 rushing yards against the Giants; this year, they average 67.9 yards.</p>
        <p>The biggest change has been the second-round draft pick Cornelius Griffin, a defensive tackle who has played better than anyone expected. Combined with the starting defensive linemen Michael Strahan, Christian Peter, Cedric Jones and Keith Hamilton, this group just dominates the line of scrimmage early in games. That's when seven of nine opponents have abandoned trying to run the ball.</p>
        <p>*The Giants aren't killing themselves with turnovers. This year's turnover ratio is plus-5; last year it was minus-8. This is largely because of the play of quarterback Kerry Collins, who has 11 touchdown passes but just 7 interceptions. The Giants' turnover ratio is the second highest in the conference. The Giants have also converted 40.3 percent of their third downs into first downs. The percentage increase over last season is 4.1 percent, which might seem small, but it has limited the number of three-and-out Giants possessions.</p>
        <p>*The revamped offensive line has become the most dependable part of the offense. The play of the new linemen, center Dusty Zeigler, left guard Glenn Parker and left tackle Lomas Brown, along with right guard Ron Stone and Luke Petitgout, who was moved to right tackle, has been the biggest surprise of the season. This is a unit with remarkable personality, poise and confidence. Contrast that with last year's line, which was unsure of itself, was prone to penalties and gave up 42 sacks.</p>
        <p>The Giants are on a pace to give up just 28 sacks. Moreover, momentum-killing holding and false-start penalties have been rare.</p>
        <p>All of which leaves the Giants in a most unexpected position in early November -- first in the N.F.C. East and leading in the conference postseason tie-breaking system. If the Giants can maintain that standing, it will be only the second time in the modern history of the franchise.</p>
        <p>Fifty-two days until the playoffs.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>It is not likely that center DUSTY ZEIGLER will be available to play in Sunday's game against the Rams. Not because of the knee ligament Zeigler strained last weekend but because of the left ankle he also sprained. His backup is DEREK ENGLER, who is experienced and played well in Zeigler's absence against Cleveland.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
