<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vilma Is Man in Middle for Jets</title>
    <meta content="02JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/02/sports/football/02JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1578695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vilma, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D9123DF931A35756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="842" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vilma Is Man in Middle for Jets</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Vilma Is Man in Middle for Jets</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., May 1</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Jets draft pick linebacker Jonathan Vilma will be cornerstone of defense (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The play came on the first day of practice for the rookie linebacker.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Vilma, a middle linebacker from the University of Miami and the Jets' first-round draft selection, was supposed to blitz the quarterback. The offense lined up a tight end wide, but the player who was supposed to come down to cover the tight end did not recognize the call quickly enough. Vilma saw that the tight end was uncovered, waved off a teammate and covered the tight end himself.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last week, the Jets made Jonathan Vilma the cornerstone of an infusion of youth and speed that they hope will pull the defense out of three seasons of torpor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The play came on the first day of practice for the rookie linebacker.</p>
        <p>Jonathan Vilma, a middle linebacker from the University of Miami and the Jets' first-round draft selection, was supposed to blitz the quarterback. The offense lined up a tight end wide, but the player who was supposed to come down to cover the tight end did not recognize the call quickly enough. Vilma saw that the tight end was uncovered, waved off a teammate and covered the tight end himself.</p>
        <p>''When a rookie can do that right out of the box, that's pretty impressive,'' Coach Herman Edwards said.</p>
        <p>The Jets' linebacking corps had grown old and slow last season, so much so that in Miami, Vilma realized there would probably be a job opening for him here, months before the Jets released Mo Lewis and Marvin Jones. Last week, the Jets made him the cornerstone of an infusion of youth and speed that they hope will pull the defense out of three seasons of torpor.</p>
        <p>The change was noticeable almost immediately when Vilma joined the Jets for his first practice Friday.</p>
        <p>''Vilma stood out to me a couple of times today,'' cornerback Ray Mickens said. ''Just his speed and awareness. I saw him covering a couple of receivers in the open field -- that caught my eye. I haven't seen that here in a while.''</p>
        <p>There is nothing subtle about the shift the Jets hope to make with Vilma in the middle. He will be counted on to provide the sideline-to-sideline pursuit that has long been absent, to cover running backs and tight ends and to take control of a defense that the coordinator Donnie Henderson vows will be more aggressive in getting to the quarterback. That defense will feature multiple fronts and coverages.</p>
        <p>For Vilma, this is familiar ground. He played on every down while at Miami. Last year, he had 127 tackles.</p>
        <p>''I'm just used to it now,'' Vilma said. ''It's what I do. I'm able to cover. I'm able to run. Plug the holes, fill the gaps. I don't see why I wouldn't be an every-down linebacker.''</p>
        <p>Vilma has been adamant since draft day that he intends to be the starter for the season opener. The veteran linebacker Sam Cowart, who has been switched to the middle after two underwhelming seasons on the weak side, said he felt out of sorts on the weak side, as if his name had been changed after 28 years.</p>
        <p>Still, the drafting of Vilma can be viewed as a no-confidence vote for Cowart, who barely survived a salary-cap purge and who will have to learn an entirely new defense with his job on the line. Cowart, however, has not felt slighted by Vilma's arrival.</p>
        <p>''I was 22 coming into the league, and the Bills had Chris Spielman,'' Cowart said. ''You have to look ahead. I'm 29 and Vilma's a young guy. He's the future.''</p>
        <p>The Jets raved that Vilma was the most instinctive linebacker in the draft, but at Miami those instincts were helped by two hours of film study each day, at least one hour a day on his own. Vilma did this while being named an academic all-American as a finance major.</p>
        <p>On Friday night, Vilma stayed up late in his hotel room, studying his new playbook. Still, when Henderson performed his usual test in a defensive meeting Friday -- announcing a scenario and demanding that a player spit out the appropriate call quickly -- Vilma stumbled, citing only part of the call. Henderson threw his arms up, signaling that the opponent would have score a touchdown if Vilma had made the same mistake in a game.</p>
        <p>When the season starts, there will be far greater pressure on Vilma to make the correct call. That is when he expects his studies to become more important than his instincts, but until then he will rely on the dominant part of his game.</p>
        <p>''I hustle best,'' he said.</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>At the end of last season, Coach HERMAN EDWARDS vowed to talk to his offensive coordinator, PAUL HACKETT, about ways to shake up the offense. The Jets have had problems with clock management, and last season they struggled to score when they got inside their opponents' 20. Edwards wants to be more aggressive and less predictable. This year, the Jets will sprinkle in a no-huddle and a fast-huddle offense to change the tempo of the game. There is also a new rule: no timeouts are to be called in the first and third quarters except under extreme conditions. Last season, the Jets called five timeouts in the first and third quarters and five early in the fourth.</p>
        <p>The Jets will also give quarterback CHAD PENNINGTON the authority to call his own plays in the huddle on occasion and to audible at the line of scrimmage. The Jets have also streamlined communications among coaches, with Edwards and the senior offensive assistant DICK CURL managing the clock on the sideline. The Jets have rehearsed down-and-distance options so there are fewer delays in play-calling.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
