<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italian (and More) in a Stylish Setting</title>
    <meta content="02CTDINE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1578486"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="DINING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Olio (Groton, Conn, Restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lyness, Stephanie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040502T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E7DF173DF931A35756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="849" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italian (and More) in a Stylish Setting</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHANIE LYNESS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lyness, Stephanie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stephanie Lyness reviews Olio restaurant in Groton, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I FIRST met Olio one miserably cold night last winter while I was driving around, lost, looking for a restaurant in New London. Having overshot my exit, I pulled off the highway into a large, semi-deserted, commercial-looking parking lot with a restaurant at the edge of it. That was Olio.</p>
        <p>I went in to use the phone and found a stylish room with a bar, clothed in downtown-chic black and white. It was the beginning of the evening and Olio was just revving up for the dinner service. I got the impression of a sophisticated, urban, modern Italian restaurant. I remember fervently wishing that I had made reservations there that night.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I FIRST met Olio one miserably cold night last winter while I was driving around, lost, looking for a restaurant in New London. Having overshot my exit, I pulled off the highway into a large, semi-deserted, commercial-looking parking lot with a restaurant at the edge of it. That was Olio.</p>
        <p>I went in to use the phone and found a stylish room with a bar, clothed in downtown-chic black and white. It was the beginning of the evening and Olio was just revving up for the dinner service. I got the impression of a sophisticated, urban, modern Italian restaurant. I remember fervently wishing that I had made reservations there that night.</p>
        <p>So I went back. Olio is a rather sophisticated restaurant and I guess one could say that it is Italian: the menu is full of pizzas, pastas, balsamic vinegar and Gorgonzola cheese. But non-Italian foods are represented as well, particularly amongst the appetizers where you'll find a satay, a quesadilla, shrimp tempura and truly excellent fried oysters (mild and sweet, with a crisp cornmeal crust) with a chile-sesame dipping sauce. The house drink is a martini, with a page of variations.</p>
        <p>There are restaurants where the chef seems to be stretching to create a new culinary vision; it is often exciting but we can't always tell what he or she intends. And there are other restaurants, like Olio, where the food -- more connected to tradition -- is in a kind of ''groove.'' Whether we like the execution or not, a sureness of intention and concept comes through in the cooking.</p>
        <p>For example, a dish I like very much at Olio is the grilled chicken breast, served (as are many of the entrees) with mashed potatoes. The breast (a little overcooked one night) is permeated with the taste of rosemary, the mashed potatoes are rich and buttery, and a basil oil drizzled around the plate freshens things. You can tell that the chef achieved what he or she was looking for. The veal française, on the other hand, is a little heavy for my taste, but it is a traditional rendition of the classic dish. (Crab cakes, however, are ill-conceived: far too much bread.)</p>
        <p>My favorite appetizers were the crisp calamari served with both a marinara sauce (a nice balance of sweetness and acidity) and an addictive chipotle mayonnaise (anything chipotle is mostly for me anyway); a lobster-stuffed artichoke (warm, perfectly seasoned bread crumbs); a special summer squash soup garnished with caramelized scallops, the taste of which sweeten the soup. (Who knew that summer squash could have that much flavor?) Pizza crusts are thin and crisp; I prefer the cheesy Pomodoro-style pizza to the pizza salad. (The night I had it, it was too much of a mish-mash of flavors.)</p>
        <p>Pastas are good across the board. One night, a plate of ravioli was stuffed with a moist truffle duxelles, rich with truffle flavor and finished with a drizzle of buttery sauce. Open-faced lasagna with seafood is thin squares of pasta, layered with seafood, served with a tasty cream sauce. The Bolognese lacks a little punch, though, and the gnocchi could be lighter.</p>
        <p>Two things that don't work for me at Olio: the chef goes a little heavy on the butter sometimes -- a steak bruschetta seemed excessively rich with melted butter as did the linguine with white clam sauce -- and I wish the desserts were a bit more in some traditional ''groove.'' A crisp, layered chocolate dessert is just too rich; the tiramisù a bit too bland. Crème brûlée wasn't creamy enough. But the banana split with its warm chocolate sauce and perfectly ripe bananas was excellent.</p>
        <p>I've been to Olio on the weekends and I've been there with large parties -- five one night, seven another. There is hardly a restaurant I've been to recently in Connecticut that could handle either successfully. Weekends at Olio are noisy, but service is excellent and if the food suffered, it wasn't noticeable. The bread is homemade and warm, the wine list is reasonable, and the sweet lemon martini is really something.</p>
        <p>Olio  33 King's Highway, Groton  (860)445-6546</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE -- Large restaurant with bar; modern, informal, but classy.  NOISE LEVEL -- Moderate; loud on weekends.  SERVICE -- Very good.  RECOMMENDED DISHES -- Olio house salad, baked goat cheese salad, fried calamari, trio of tempura shrimp, grilled quesadilla with asparagus, fried oysters, lobster-stuffed artichoke, Pomodoro-style pizza, all the pastas, grilled filet mignon, grilled chicken with mashed potatoes, banana split.  PRICE RANGE -- Appetizers: $7.95 to $10.95; main courses: $13.95 to $18.95; desserts: $6. (Lunch prices are slightly cheaper.)  CREDIT CARDS -- All major cards accepted.  HOURS -- Monday through Thursday, 11:30 a.m. to 9 p.m., Friday and Saturday until 10 p.m.; Sunday, 4:30 p.m. to 9 p.m..  RESERVATIONS -- Recommended.  WHEELCHAIR ACCESSIBILITY -- Good.  Reviewed by The Times May 2, 2004.  Ratings -- Extraordinary, Excellent, Very Good, Good, Satisfactory, Fair, Poor. Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
