<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Receives Assurance From Japan on Beef Exports</title>
    <meta content="15MADC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/15/national/15madcow.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1680388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Livestock</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Japan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Agriculture Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050615T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06EEDE163BF936A25755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="904" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Receives Assurance From Japan on Beef Exports</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Receives Assurance From Japan on Beef Exports</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEXEI BARRIONUEVO and DONALD G. McNEIL Jr.</byline>
      <dateline>CHICAGO, June 14</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The United States Agriculture Department won assurance from the Japanese government on Tuesday that a second potential case of mad cow disease found on American soil would not affect negotiations to resume beef exports to Japan, the top American export market.</p>
        <p>But critics of the department's mad cow testing program said the case underscored the need for more intensive testing to determine how prevalent the fatal, brain-wasting disease was in the American herd.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Japanese government told the U.S. that a second potential case of mad cow disease found on American soil will not affect negotiations to resume beef exports to Japan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The United States Agriculture Department won assurance from the Japanese government on Tuesday that a second potential case of mad cow disease found on American soil would not affect negotiations to resume beef exports to Japan, the top American export market.</p>
        <p>But critics of the department's mad cow testing program said the case underscored the need for more intensive testing to determine how prevalent the fatal, brain-wasting disease was in the American herd.</p>
        <p>The Agriculture Department said Friday that it had found bovine spongiform encephalopathy, or mad cow disease, in an animal that had tested negative last November. It would be the second case of the disease to be found in the United States, and the fifth in North America, since 2003.</p>
        <p>On Monday Taiwan, which had resumed imports of American beef two months ago, and South Korea, which had been negotiating to restart them, expressed concern about the new case. Taiwanese officials said that if a final round of testing confirmed the disease that it would cease importing American beef. The news helped sink cattle future prices to their lowest level in 13 months.</p>
        <p>But beef prices recovered slightly on Tuesday after Japanese officials said the latest discovery would not derail plans to restart exports to Japan, which imported $1.4 billion worth of American beef in 2003, or 36 percent of all American exports.</p>
        <p>''This incident will not have any impact on our process,'' Shin Yokoyama, Japan's agriculture counselor to the United States, said in an interview about the negotiations. Mr. Yokoyama said his government was not bothered by the discovery because the animal was older than 20 months, the cutoff age for accepting beef into Japan.</p>
        <p>''If this cow is born in the United States and raised in the United States it still doesn't matter,'' Mr. Yokoyama said. ''As long as it is old.'' Japan, which has been testing all its cattle since September 2001, has found 20 cases, the most recent on June 6.</p>
        <p>American agriculture officials said more tests would be conducted on the small amount of remaining brain tissue from the animal at a laboratory in Ames, Iowa, and at the world's premier mad cow testing facility, in Weybridge, England. The process could take up to two weeks.</p>
        <p>Taiwan, Japan and South Korea were among 53 countries that banned American beef after mad cow was discovered in December 2003 in a dairy cow in Washington State. Through intense lobbying, the Bush administration has restored about one-third of its beef exports.</p>
        <p>American officials have emphasized that there is no risk to humans from the animal that tested positive on Friday because it was destroyed and did not get into the animal or human food supply. The cow found in Washington had been sold as hamburger.</p>
        <p>So far, officials have released little else about the latest potential case, other than that the cow was at least eight years old and was most likely not imported.</p>
        <p>The cow's origin could prove critical to efforts to restore the American beef trade. In trying to bless the American herd as mad cow-free, American officials have emphasized that the Washington cow was born in Canada before a 1997 feed ban. The United States banned live cattle from Canada after mad cow was discovered in a Canadian cow in May 2003.</p>
        <p>In the latest American case, the cow tested positive only after the Office of Inspector General, an independent watchdog group within the Agriculture Department, required the use of a second type of test on three suspect animals first tested in November.</p>
        <p>Critics of the Agriculture Department asked Tuesday why the department had refused for more than six months to perform the tests, called Western blot.Michael K. Hansen, a senior research associate at Consumers Union, produced copies of letters he wrote in January to the department's chief veterinary officer and in February to the new secretary of agriculture, Mike Johanns, asking the department to use the Western blot test on the cow's brain. He said the newest test, used in Europe and Japan, where more mad cow cases have surfaced, is 1,000 times more sensitive than the test used by the Agriculture Department, the immunohistochemistry test.</p>
        <p>In a letter dated March 18, an agriculture official replied that the department did not think a Western blot test ''would have enhanced the result of our November 2004 testing,'' and did not think that confirmatory testing in England was necessary.</p>
        <p>In the past, the Agriculture Department has repeatedly called its immunohistochemistry test the ''gold standard'' for detection. But tests in Belgium and Japan have shown, Dr. Hansen said, that it missed some cases. Ed Loyd, an Agriculture Department spokesman, said the department made use of both tests but usually used the Western blot test only when samples began to degrade. ''This is an instance where we had a very good sample.''</p>
        <p>Since the discovery of the first mad cow case in 2003 the department enhanced its surveillance program, testing 375,000 cattle, up from fewer than 20,000, and testing high-risk ''downer'' cattle that are struggling to walk. But discussions are underway to end the testing program, Mr. Loyd said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
