<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Serbs Pour Over Border to Join Fighting in Bosnia</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="559428"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA-HERZEGOVINA (YUGOSLAVIA)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SERBIA</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">COHEN, ROGER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KARADZIC, RADOVAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">IZETBEGOVIC, ALIJA (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920928T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D91F3BF93BA1575AC0A964958260" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Serbs Pour Over Border to Join Fighting in Bosnia</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROGER COHEN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COHEN, ROGER</byline>
      <dateline>ZVORNIK, Bosnia and Herzegovina</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the morning bus from Belgrade to the Bosnian front paused at the border here, Brano Tadic leaped off and started running. A few minutes later he returned with a big grin on his unshaven face, a Zastava machine gun clasped in his right hand and a couple of grenades strapped to his belt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tadic, a 25-year-old Serb who was a waiter in Sarajevo before the Bosnian war started in April, said he had been in Belgrade for a week visiting family. But immediately after crossing from Serbia into Bosnia and Herzegovina, he was transformed from a civilian into a warrior for the Bosnian Serbs, flaunting his weapons and proclaiming war without end on the Muslims of Bosnia.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When the morning bus from Belgrade to the Bosnian front paused at the border here, Brano Tadic leaped off and started running. A few minutes later he returned with a big grin on his unshaven face, a Zastava machine gun clasped in his right hand and a couple of grenades strapped to his belt.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tadic, a 25-year-old Serb who was a waiter in Sarajevo before the Bosnian war started in April, said he had been in Belgrade for a week visiting family. But immediately after crossing from Serbia into Bosnia and Herzegovina, he was transformed from a civilian into a warrior for the Bosnian Serbs, flaunting his weapons and proclaiming war without end on the Muslims of Bosnia.</p>
        <p>His sudden switch illustrates why the war in Bosnia has remained so intractable to those seeking a peaceful solution. Although the Serbian Government of President Slobodan Milosevic in Belgrade has insisted for some time that no fighters or weapons cross the border between Serbia and Bosnia, visits to Bosnia suggested that the frontier remains so open as to have little significance as a barrier. Diversity Handicaps Leader</p>
        <p>A few days ago, for example, a medical evacuation helicopter in the Bosnian town of Sokolac could be seen taking wounded Bosnian Serbian soldiers to the Yugoslav Army hospital in Belgrade.</p>
        <p>Moreover, the ability of Radovan Karadzic, the leader of the Bosnian Serbs, to deliver on any promises he makes in peace negotiations appears to be limited because of the extreme diversity of the Serbian forces in Bosnia, which range from former Yugoslav Army officers with sophisticated training to former waiters like Mr. Tadic with none.</p>
        <p>Although the force that calls itself the army of the Serbian Republic of Bosnia and Herzegovina seems to be making progress in imposing discipline, Serbian forces in Bosnia remain splintered. Machine guns and other weapons are now carried mainly by officers and soldiers in uniform, but also by bearded youths wearing leather jackets, jeans and Reeboks.</p>
        <p>"When the war started we got all our weapons from the various barracks of the Yugoslav Army in Bosnia, and now there's no way of controlling all the weaponry," Mr. Tadic said with evident pride.</p>
        <p>Asked which military unit he fights in, he pointed to a skull and crossbones badge on his fatigues and said "Chetniks" -- a reference to the Chetnik guerrillas who fought for Serbia in World War II. There is no official Chetnik unit in the army of Serbs in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>Officers of this army, commanded by a former Yugoslav Army general, Ratko Mladic, appear increasingly embarrassed and irked by the mention of such irregulars, who flip back and forth between Serbia and Bosnia. The leaders say they are well on their way to eliminating the irregulars.</p>
        <p>"The Serbian Army in Bosnia is in a period of formation and all these para-military groups which sprang up spontaneously are now coming under our control," said Col. Ljuba Kosovac, who commands the Lukavica Barracks near Sarajevo. "The orders are: either disarm these people or recruit them."</p>
        <p>Colonel Kosovac is a Bosnian who was previously a Yugoslav Army officer. He said that when the country and army splintered, he was offered the choice of going to Serbia as an officer in the army of the rump Yugoslav state or joining the emerging Serbian Army in Bosnia. He chose the latter.</p>
        <p>"All the officers here are former Yugoslav Army officers," he declared, adding that there are close to 100,000 soldiers in the Serbian Bosnian Army. This figure is higher than estimates of United States analysts in Belgrade, who say there are about 70,000 Serbs fighting in Bosnia, equally split between army soldiers and militiamen with varying degrees of independence from the army.  Militia Leader Arrested</p>
        <p>There is evidence that a drive to eliminate the Serbian irregulars or recruit them is indeed taking place. For example, on Sept. 22 a prominent Serbian militia leader widely known as "Major Ceko," who had been operating at the Gorazde front in Bosnia from a base in Pljevjla in Yugoslavia, was arrested. Major Ceko, whose real name is Misko Dacevic, claimed to control about 3,000 men.</p>
        <p>Throughout Serbian-held Bosnia, as this process continues, it seems that a degree of military discipline is beginning to take hold. Roadblocks are now all manned by soldiers in uniform, and robberies, which were commonplace, have declined. Nonetheless, many militia commanders continue to operate independently.</p>
        <p>For the Government in Belgrade, it is important that the irregulars -- especially those using Serbia as a base -- be eliminated. In arguing for the removal of United Nations sanctions, it is essential to the Yugoslav authorities to be able to portray events in Bosnia as outside their control.</p>
        <p>"We withdrew our entire armed forces from Bosnia last May, and the only people from Serbia still fighting there are outlaws and criminals who will be arrested," said Oskar Kovac, the Deputy Prime Minister of what remains of Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>Gen. Zivota Panic, the Chief of Staff of the Yugoslav Army, added that every Yugoslav soldier was out of Bosnia on May 19 and "we now look at Bosnia like another country."</p>
        <p>On the ground, however, it is clear that while much effort is going into building formal divisions between Serbs in Bosnia and the truncated Serbian-dominated Yugoslav state, contacts remain strong. Indeed, the bus route between Belgrade and the Bosnian Serbian capital of Pale, near Sarajevo, is regularly packed with fighters going back and forth.</p>
        <p>As for the Muslims loyal to President Alija Izetbegovic, they are heavily outgunned and their military prospects appear slight in the absence of a Western military intervention.</p>
        <p>"Serbs own 65 percent of the property in Bosnia and we are fighting to liberate and protect this land," said Colonel Kosovac, the Bosnian Serbian officer. "After a number of casualties, hatred has escalated, and the only possibility for peace is a total division of Bosnia."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
