<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Postwar Skimp: Cozy, if Ghastly</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="406564"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERIOR DESIGN</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LONDON (ENG)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEFFRYE MUSEUM (LONDON)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUCCO, TERRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England/London</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interior Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD1731F935A35751C1A966958260" item-length="1121" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Postwar Skimp: Cozy, if Ghastly</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TERRY TRUCCO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">TRUCCO, TERRY</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUCH of the new British film "The Krays" unfolds in a narrow East London sitting room. Ronnie and Reggie Kray, the twin gangsters who terrorized London in the 1950's and 60's, come of age amid brown and yellow wallpaper, worn brown sofas, scrubbed lace curtains and crocheted tea cozies. Their mother's careful decorating -- the film's metaphor for the banality of evil -- raises a question for interior design enthusiasts who see the film: why did so many British sitting rooms of the 50's look like this?</p>
        <p>Some answers can be found in two new rooms that went on permanent display on Dec. 4 in the East End of London at the Geffrye Museum, which specializes in the history of British furniture. The sitting rooms -- one modeled after a room in a modest house in the London suburbs, the other after a room in a London public housing unit called a council flat -- recall thousands of British homes during the scraggy postwar years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUCH of the new British film "The Krays" unfolds in a narrow East London sitting room. Ronnie and Reggie Kray, the twin gangsters who terrorized London in the 1950's and 60's, come of age amid brown and yellow wallpaper, worn brown sofas, scrubbed lace curtains and crocheted tea cozies. Their mother's careful decorating -- the film's metaphor for the banality of evil -- raises a question for interior design enthusiasts who see the film: why did so many British sitting rooms of the 50's look like this?</p>
        <p>Some answers can be found in two new rooms that went on permanent display on Dec. 4 in the East End of London at the Geffrye Museum, which specializes in the history of British furniture. The sitting rooms -- one modeled after a room in a modest house in the London suburbs, the other after a room in a London public housing unit called a council flat -- recall thousands of British homes during the scraggy postwar years.</p>
        <p>The rooms offer a concise look at interior design as seen through the prism of social history rather than esthetics. They are bluntly realistic, authentic instead of attractive. No anachronistic colors or objects are on view to make them pretty or sophisticated. Nothing has been idealized or sanitized. In short, design students will be appalled by these rooms, though sociologists and nostalgia buffs should love them.</p>
        <p>The council flat's walls are cream-colored trimmed in battleship gray, the era's Government-issue hues. The so-called Utility furniture, also Government issue, dates from the war, when only newlyweds and bombing victims were allowed to buy it. A wedding picture is on the sideboard, next to a birdcage holding a parakeet.</p>
        <p>The colors of the suburban house scream: ivy-patterned wallpaper, gray and yellow furniture and long, heavy curtains in a red, cream and black print. The fireplace has do-it-yourself tile work in hospital green.</p>
        <p>"It's ghastly, but comfortable," said Jan Graffius, the deputy curator who worked on the rooms. "People will no doubt say, 'Gosh, scholarly work went into that?' "</p>
        <p>The rooms are, in fact, a result of several years of research, including interviews with dozens of ordinary Britons who set up housekeeping in the 1950's. "We didn't invent anything in these rooms, but designed them on the recollections of different people with similar experiences," Mrs. Graffius said.</p>
        <p>After advertising in national publications for people who might share their memories of the era, the museum was deluged with fabric swatches, wallpaper samples, wedding photographs and reminiscences. A picture emerged of a nation hampered by rationing and shortages but eager to make something from the little available.</p>
        <p>"No one mentioned Elvis or pink Cadillacs, the things young people here today associate with the 50's," Mrs. Graffius said.</p>
        <p>The two sitting rooms were originally seen in "Putting on the Style," an exhibition of seven 1950's British rooms at the museum earlier this year. The show included a modest kitchen, a newlyweds' bedroom (postwar housing shortages meant that young couples often lived with parents) and a shabby furnished room (known in Britain as a bed-sit) that was the only type of housing available to most Caribbean immigrants in the 1950's.</p>
        <p>Visitors to "Putting on the Style" who were over the age of 30 were given ballots and asked to select the rooms they thought belonged in the museum's permanent collection. The council flat and suburban home won by a landslide.</p>
        <p>"This is the most cohesive, comprehensive room on view, albeit a bit too middle class," wrote a suburban-room fan. A visitor who liked the council flat termed it "believable" and praised it for reflecting "the simplicity and economy of the period."</p>
        <p>Another voter, in spidery script, wrote: "The rest of the museum concentrates on the aristocratic/upper-middle-class experience. The council flat would represent the working-class experience."</p>
        <p>Objects that record the working-class experience in this century are gaining a greater place in Britain's museums, led by successes like Glasgow's Tenement House, a preserved workers' home, with gaslights, that opened to the public in 1982. In part, the Thatcher Government's efforts to make museums less dependent on Government support was responsible. With the number of visitors increasingly important, museums are scrambling to offer exhibitions that are popular as well as scholarly. "Putting on the Style" proved extremely popular, Mrs. Graffius said.</p>
        <p>There is also an effort to do away with old-style idealized display methods in favor of believable exhibits, even when it means ivy-patterned wallpaper. The Geffrye's move toward all-out authenticity began in earnest a couple of years ago, when the museum's 1930's room was renovated. Conceived as a modest London sitting room, it included the era's heavy brown furniture and an Art Deco sideboard from the Queen Mary.</p>
        <p>When visitors complained that the sideboard was too posh for the room, the curators removed it and promised that future exhibitions would be consistent in matters of style, economics and class. They also decided to consult visitors, many from the museum's working-class neighborhood, when an interior was "within living memory," as Mrs. Graffius put it.</p>
        <p>The museum's two new rooms owe their distinctive appearance to postwar economics as much as taste. Rationing continued well into the 1950's, new furniture was scarce and people lucky enough to move into their own homes were often stuck with whatever was on the walls.</p>
        <p>Mary Gwyther, who runs the Geffrye's coffee shop, was married in 1950 and recalled workers' offering council tenants a few wallpaper samples, probably prewar, in washed-out green and brown florals. "You were so glad to have a bit of color," she said.</p>
        <p>White was the only color of paint widely available, so Mrs. Gwyther added red food coloring to get the pink she wanted for her bedroom walls.</p>
        <p>Years of skimping bred conservative taste in decoration. Efforts by the Socialist Government of the 1950's to encourage the development and sale of simple, modern furniture were mostly rejected by homemakers, who wanted suites of furniture similar to those in the suburban home -- or in the sitting room of Mrs. Kray.</p>
        <p>In 1952, Britain's Design and Industries Association conducted a survey asking suburban dwellers which of two model rooms they preferred. One was dark and traditional, with overstuffed sofas and a fringed floor lamp. The other was light and modern, with blond Danish armchairs and a pale rug.  People admired the modern but didn't want to live in it.</p>
        <p>As a secretary wrote: "The room is ideal, but my family would have a fit. They'd think I'd gone quite mad and all arty."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
