<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No, Burrowing Can't Undermine the Yanks, Either</title>
    <meta content="13YANK$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1038782"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Minnesota Twins</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Minnesota Twins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980813T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E2D9123AF930A2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1097" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No, Burrowing Can't Undermine the Yanks, Either</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees defeat Minnesota Twins, 11-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Defeating the Yankees these days requires more than a simple combination of good hitting, pitching and defense. Defeating the Yankees requires a secret weapon, and unwittingly, Minnesota deployed the size 13 1/2 right foot of LaTroy Hawkins yesterday -- a big foot that oddly provided the Twins with their best chance for victory in the three-game series.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, David Cone recovered from the impact of Hawkins's right foot and the Yankees covered the Twins with a flood of late-inning runs to win, 11-2, before 47,841 at Yankee Stadium.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Defeating the Yankees these days requires more than a simple combination of good hitting, pitching and defense. Defeating the Yankees requires a secret weapon, and unwittingly, Minnesota deployed the size 13 1/2 right foot of LaTroy Hawkins yesterday -- a big foot that oddly provided the Twins with their best chance for victory in the three-game series.</p>
        <p>Ultimately, David Cone recovered from the impact of Hawkins's right foot and the Yankees covered the Twins with a flood of late-inning runs to win, 11-2, before 47,841 at Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>The Yankees once again have a .750 winning percentage, having won 87 of 116 games, including their last seven. At 87-29, they have won 58 games more than they have lost, the first Yankee team to do so since 1939.</p>
        <p>''We've been waiting all year to get everyone clicking together on all cylinders,'' Cone said. ''I think we're starting to do that.''</p>
        <p>But the other games on their current homestand were a lot easier. The Yankees were in jeopardy yesterday; Cone was in trouble. There were moments in the opening innings when the Twins could have broken open the game with one hit, when they could have knocked out Cone, when they could have finally had the Yankees reeling, if only for one day.</p>
        <p>And Hawkins's big right foot played a major part in creating this opportunity. In the first inning, Cone, already out of sorts, was rushing his delivery, his body moving forward with his arm dragging behind. His control was affected, his fastball sailing high, his curveball and slider imprecise. Two hits and a hit batsman loaded the bases for Minnesota, and the Twins scored their first run on a groundout. Cone returned to the dugout feeling fortunate.</p>
        <p>Hawkins shut out the Yankees in the bottom of the first, and when Cone returned to the mound, he found that Hawkins had dug an unusually large hole in front of the rubber, where pitchers plant their back foot as they drive forward in their release.</p>
        <p>Cone excavated and kicked at the gash, working to fix it to his liking. But, he said later, his balance was affected, he felt awkward. He walked Ron Coomer on four consecutive pitches to lead off the second; he was unable to throw any of four fastballs over the plate, and he was missing badly.</p>
        <p>Cone tried slowing his delivery, aiming intently at the mitt of catcher Joe Girardi -- and the more he tried aiming the ball, the more dysfunctional his delivery became. Javier Valentin stood and watched Cone throw four more fastballs out of the strike zone.</p>
        <p>Girardi went to the mound. ''Be patient, I'll figure it out,'' Cone said, digging at the hole with his size 10 shoes.</p>
        <p>Manager Joe Torre watched, and although he says he believes Cone when the pitcher tells him he feels great, he was seeing the classic signs of a pitcher with a tired or injured arm: Cone, whose control has been spectacular, simply could not throw a strike.</p>
        <p>Mike Jerzembeck began throwing in the Yankees' bullpen, as Cone fell behind Denny Hocking, Minnesota's No. 9 hitter, three balls and no strikes. ''I can't remember a time when I threw 11 straight balls,'' Cone said after the game. He saw Jerzembeck warming up and assumed that he was in danger of being replaced.</p>
        <p>He threw a strike to Hocking, and Yankee Stadium erupted with mock cheers. Cone fired another fastball, and Hocking popped up to short center field, the runners forced to hold. Later, Hocking and Cone would point to this as a pivotal moment. ''I was thinking we might bunt in that situation,'' Hocking said, ''but you've got to make the guy throw strikes.''</p>
        <p>Otis Nixon lined a single to right, but the ball was hit so hard and reached Paul O'Neill so quickly that Coomer stopped at third. Bases loaded, one out, infield back, Jerzembeck nearly ready in the bullpen.</p>
        <p>Brent Gates hit a bouncer to first baseman Tino Martinez, who was in position to make the play only because the bases were loaded and he wasn't holding the runner. Martinez gloved the ball and threw to second, where Derek Jeter caught the ball for a forceout and returned a throw to first for an inning-ending double play.</p>
        <p>Cone returned to the dugout and with both hands grabbed his teammate David Wells, joking: ''How are you throwing strikes? Let it rub off on me.''</p>
        <p>Cone said later: ''At that point, I breathed a sigh of relief. I knew I could settle down.''</p>
        <p>The Twins scored another run in the third inning, but Cone, who would pitch seven innings for his major league-leading 17th victory, was making adjustments on the fly, adjusting to the hole, adjusting his release, gradually gaining control of his fastball and slider. Minnesota, only 1 for 6 with runners in scoring position in the first three innings, would not get any more runs.</p>
        <p>And eventually, the Yankees came back. Four runs in the fourth, including two on Girardi's hit-and-run double; three runs in the seventh, with home runs by Bernie Williams and Scott Brosius, and three more in the eighth, including two on a double by Brosius that gave him five runs batted in for the game.</p>
        <p>Hawkins's foot had opened a hole, but the Twins couldn't get through quickly enough.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>The Yankees have held a lead in each of their last 41 games, eclipsing the previous best of 40 games, set by the 1932 Yankees, according to the Elias Sports Bureau. . . . The Yankees have outscored opponents by 66-14 during this unbeaten homestand, and they have hit homers in 14 consecutive games, their longest such streak since they homered in 16 straight games in 1994. Their 45-8 home record is the best in franchise history after 53 games. . . . BERNIE WILLIAMS increased his hitting streak to 14 games and leads the American League with a .352 batting average.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
