<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cases of Lethal New Illness Rise Sharply in Interior Region</title>
    <meta content="Y15CHI$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/15/science/sciencespecial/15CHIN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1481127"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="A RESPIRATORY ILLNESS: CHINA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (Sars)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Shanxi Province (China)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Guangdong Province (China)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hong Kong</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Taiyuan (China)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Beijing (China)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">World Health Organization</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckholm, Erik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/SARS (Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Guangdong Province</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Beijing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">SARS (Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Respiratory Diseases</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">China</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E3DE113BF936A25757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1243" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cases of Lethal New Illness Rise Sharply in Interior Region</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Cases of Lethal New Illness Rise Sharply in Interior China</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIK ECKHOLM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eckholm, Erik</byline>
      <dateline>BEIJING, April 14</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report last week that 32 people in China's Shanxi Province have been diagnosed with severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) heralds possible spread of disease through country's vast, medically underserved hinterlands; until now disease has been concentrated in prosperous, urbanized southeastern province of Guangdong and in neighboring Hong Kong, with small numbers of cases appearing in other Chinese cities; worry deepens when Chinese ministry of health reports 47 more cases in Shanxi; Shanxi cases are concentrated in provincial capital of Taiyuan, where SARS was apparently introduced several weeks ago by traveler returning from Guangdong; World Health Orgn team seeking to clarify situation in Beijing is making what team members describe as slow, steady progress; say they have still not gained access to any of city's military hospitals; photo; map (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reported cases of severe acute respiratory syndrome rose sharply today in an interior province of northern China, heralding the possible spread of the disease through the country's vast, medically underserved hinterlands.</p>
        <p>A report last week that 32 people in Shanxi Province, a region of coal mines and factory towns, had been diagnosed with the disease, known as SARS, had already raised concerns among health experts. The disease, which has been fatal in about 4 percent of cases, has been concentrated in the prosperous, urbanized southeastern province of Guangdong and in neighboring Hong Kong, with small numbers of cases appearing in other Chinese cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Reported cases of SARS rose sharply in an interior province of north-central China, heralding the possible spread of the disease.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Reported cases of severe acute respiratory syndrome rose sharply today in an interior province of northern China, heralding the possible spread of the disease through the country's vast, medically underserved hinterlands.</p>
        <p>A report last week that 32 people in Shanxi Province, a region of coal mines and factory towns, had been diagnosed with the disease, known as SARS, had already raised concerns among health experts. The disease, which has been fatal in about 4 percent of cases, has been concentrated in the prosperous, urbanized southeastern province of Guangdong and in neighboring Hong Kong, with small numbers of cases appearing in other Chinese cities.</p>
        <p>The worry deepened today when the ministry of health, in its daily update to the World Health Organization, said 47 more cases had been reported from Shanxi on Sunday.</p>
        <p>''We're very concerned about what may be happening out in the provinces,'' Henk Bekedan, director of the W.H.O. office here, said in an interview.</p>
        <p>The Shanxi cases are concentrated in the provincial capital of Taiyuan, where SARS was apparently introduced several weeks ago by a traveler returning from Guangdong.</p>
        <p>The new figures bring reported cases in the Taiyuan area to 79. This is a small number in a metropolitan region of 3.3 million, but it is more than double the 37 cases reported as of today here in Beijing, the capital, with a metropolitan area population of about 14 million. Public fears are being expressed here that the government says are overblown.</p>
        <p>Nationwide, China now has reported 1,418 cases of the disease, with 64 deaths, out of a worldwide total of 3,619 cases and 144 deaths.</p>
        <p>In the last few days, in what international officials call a helpful step, China's top leaders have expressed strong new concern about SARS and called for greater openness and stronger control measures.</p>
        <p>In weekend meetings that were featured in news reports today, Prime Minister Wen Jiabao described the threat of SARS as ''grave'' and called for all-out efforts to overcome it. He did not describe the disease as ''under effective control'' -- as senior health officials had last week in an effort to reassure the public and head off the mass cancellation of foreign tourist and business visits to China.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bekedan said the surge in Shanxi might reflect an expectable second wave of infections as the initial patients exposed others before they were diagnosed and isolated. What happens next will depend on the effectiveness of control measures introduced by local officials.</p>
        <p>He said the jump might also reflect more effective or honest reporting from Taiyuan after central authorities sent a special team there last week to strengthen the effort against SARS.</p>
        <p>Reached by telephone, officials at the national health ministry and the health departments of Shanxi Province and Taiyuan city all declined to comment on the increasing caseload in Shanxi. The ministry is to issue new national data on Tuesday.</p>
        <p>Adding to the concern of health experts are the often substandard quality of health facilities and surveillance in much of interior China. Millions of workers from the relatively prosperous coastal areas made trips home to these interior provinces during the lunar new year holidays in February -- just when the epidemic was reaching a peak in Guangdong.</p>
        <p>''Our assumption is that most of China's provinces will have cases,'' Mr. Bekedan said today.</p>
        <p>Second to Shanxi in reported cases, among the inland regions, is Inner Mongolia, which as of Sunday had reported 17. Smaller numbers of cases have been detected in several other provinces, but the vast majority of victims are still in Guangdong, with more than 1,250 reported cases though a declining curve of new victims.</p>
        <p>A World Health Organization team seeking to clarify the situation in Beijing has visited a few hospitals and pored over records, making what team members described as slow, steady progress.</p>
        <p>But by the end of the fourth day of what is planned as a six-day mission, the investigators had still not gained access to any of the city's military hospitals, apparently because of foot-dragging by military administrators who are not under the health ministry's control.</p>
        <p>Last week, in a blow to the credibility of Beijing's disease reports, a prominent military surgeon said that the city's military hospitals alone might hold 100 SARS patients. City and military officials have denied this.</p>
        <p>The international experts, based on their limited work, say they are impressed by Beijing's careful care of patients in specially designated hospitals, and its strengthened efforts to trace and isolate those who have been in close contact with SARS patients.</p>
        <p>But it appears unlikely that the team, in the short time planned for this visit, can allay public skepticism about the true extent of SARS in Beijing, especially because the government has so far refused to provide data on suspected cases and people who are quarantined for observation. Scores or hundreds of people, some experts guess, may be in isolation in hospitals now, possibly helping to explain the rampant rumors and conflicting accounts.</p>
        <p>Health experts are also worried by the coming May 1 holiday, when many Chinese normally take trips. In recent years, the government has extended the holiday to a full week and encouraged travel in hopes of stimulating the economy.</p>
        <p>The widespread movement of people, especially in planes and crowded trains and buses and without stringent precautions, could hasten the spread of SARS, which is believed to be passed by close contact with sick people, including the inhalation of droplets from their coughs.</p>
        <p>So far, no campaign has been started to discourage travel, even to and from the center of infection in Guangdong, or to require the screening of passengers for fever and other signs of illness.</p>
        <p>In Hong Kong, health officials said tonight that there had been 40 more cases there, and 7 more deaths. The number of deaths in Hong Kong, a special administrative region of China, has jumped lately. But Dr. Ko Wing-man, the acting chief executive of the Hong Kong Hospital Authority, said at a news conference that it was unclear whether the mortality rate had risen or whether there were simply more patients infected with the disease.</p>
        <p>Malaysia's consulate in Hong Kong announced on Saturday the temporary suspension of a ban on the issuance of most visas to people from Hong Kong, Vietnam and Canada. But Malaysia's health minister, Chua Jui-meng, seemed to contradict this position at a news conference today in Kuala Lumpur, saying, according to a Reuters report, that policy had not changed and that most visas would not be issued.</p>
        <p>Mr. Chua also said the Malaysian cabinet might consider broadening the visa restrictions to other countries.</p>
        <p>A RESPIRATORY ILLNESS: CHINA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
