<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSH SAYS IRAQIS AREN'T YET ABLE TO QUELL REBELS</title>
    <meta content="21PREX$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/12/21/politics/21prexy.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1636427"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="THE CONFLICT IN IRAQ: THE PRESIDENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sanger, David E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stevenson, Richard W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Warner, John W (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Homeland Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/National Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20041221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B04EFDA1330F932A15751C1A9629C8B63" item-length="1586" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSH SAYS IRAQIS AREN'T YET ABLE TO QUELL REBELS</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Bush Says Iraqis Aren't Yet Able to Quell Rebels</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. SANGER and RICHARD W. STEVENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sanger, David E; Stevenson, Richard W</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 20</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pres Bush acknowledges that United States has had only 'mixed' success in training Iraqi troops to secure country and says it is 'unacceptable' that some Iraqi units have fled as soon as they faced hostile fire, news conference; his public criticism of Iraqi performance reflects mounting concern in White House, Pentagon and Capitol Hill that strategy for training 125,000 Iraqi forces to secure country is failing; he makes no effort to argue with assessment of Iraqi security forces made by Sen John Warner, who called them 'bottom level'; Bush also acknowledges that insurgents' bombings in Iraq are 'having an effect' in sowing terror among Iraqis; says he will not let continued violence deter him from his stated goal of bringing democracy to Iraq; his comments amount to his broadest acknowledgement yet that rebuilding Iraq's security forces has run into severe difficulties, issue he resisted discussing during re-election campaign; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush acknowledged Monday that the United States had achieved only ''mixed'' success in training Iraqi troops to secure the country, and said that it was ''unacceptable'' that some Iraqi units had fled as soon as they faced hostile fire.</p>
        <p>With the first elections in Iraq six weeks away, Mr. Bush's public criticism of how the Iraqis had performed reflected mounting concern, voiced from the White House, the Pentagon and Capitol Hill, that the strategy for training 125,000 Iraqi forces to secure the country is failing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>President Bush acknowledged that the U.S. had encountered only "mixed" success in training Iraqi troops to secure the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>President Bush acknowledged Monday that the United States had achieved only ''mixed'' success in training Iraqi troops to secure the country, and said that it was ''unacceptable'' that some Iraqi units had fled as soon as they faced hostile fire.</p>
        <p>With the first elections in Iraq six weeks away, Mr. Bush's public criticism of how the Iraqis had performed reflected mounting concern, voiced from the White House, the Pentagon and Capitol Hill, that the strategy for training 125,000 Iraqi forces to secure the country is failing.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, Senator John W. Warner, the Virginia Republican who serves as the chairman of the Armed Services Committee, said a recent trip to the country convinced him that the Iraqi forces were ''bottom level'' and still had no effective leadership 20 months after the fall of Saddam Hussein.</p>
        <p>Several other Republicans, and many Democrats, have been highly critical of Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld for his conduct of the war and how he dealt with questions from soldiers two weeks ago about the absence of effective armor to protect them from improvised explosives. But Mr. Bush used his news conference to express confidence in his secretary of defense. ''I know Secretary Rumsfeld's heart,'' Mr. Bush said. ''Beneath that rough and gruff, no-nonsense demeanor is a good human being who cares deeply about the military and deeply about the grief that war causes.'' [Page A19.]</p>
        <p>At his news conference in the Eisenhower Executive Office Building on Monday morning, expected to be his last before he leaves for vacation at Camp David and then his Texas ranch, Mr. Bush made no effort to argue with Senator Warner's assessment of the Iraqi security forces. He said that in a meeting last week with the two military leaders in charge of the 148,000 American troops in Iraq, Gen. John P. Abizaid and Gen. George W. Casey Jr., he learned that the problem extended well beyond shortcomings in training.</p>
        <p>''They've got some generals in place and they've got foot soldiers in place, but the whole command structure necessary to have a viable military is not in place,'' Mr. Bush said. ''And so they're going to spend a lot of time and effort on achieving that objective.'' [Excerpts, Page A16.]</p>
        <p>He also acknowledged that ''no question about it, the bombers are having an effect'' in sowing terror among Iraqis and said that they were trying to shake the will of Iraqis and of Americans who saw scenes of the resulting carnage on their television sets almost nightly. ''Car bombs that destroy young children or car bombs that indiscriminately bomb in religious sites are effective propaganda tools,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Bush said he would not let the continued violence deter him from his stated goal of bringing democracy to Iraq, declaring that ''we must meet the objective, which is to help the Iraqis defend themselves, and at the same time have a political process to go forward.''</p>
        <p>Taken together, Mr. Bush's comments amounted to his broadest acknowledgement yet that rebuilding Iraq's security forces, a central task in remaking Iraq, had run into severe difficulties -- problems he resisted discussing during his re-election campaign.</p>
        <p>The numbers alone released by the administration tell a story of a training program that has slowed to a halt. The State Department's weekly assessment of Iraqi security forces shows that the number of newly trained troops has stayed level since early November at about 114,000, and that more of those troops are being channeled to the police, to try to restore order to the streets of major cities.</p>
        <p>Administration officials acknowledged that it was a measure of how bad things had become that an assassin photographed while killing three election workers on Sunday on a street in Baghdad did not even feel the need to cover his face.</p>
        <p>Asked about a ''move away from democracy'' by President Vladimir V. Putin of Russia, Mr. Bush conspicuously passed up an opportunity to criticize Mr. Putin for cracking down on civil liberties and centralizing power. Though Mr. Bush's aides have been highly critical of Mr. Putin, with some of them reassessing their earlier, favorable impressions of his intentions, Mr. Bush sidestepped the issue, reminding reporters that ''Vladimir Putin and I have got a good personal relationship.''</p>
        <p>''It's important for Russia and the United States to have the kind of relationship where if we disagree with decisions, we can do so in a friendly and positive way,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also declined to state his position in an internal debate within his own administration about whether the United States should be promoting a change of leadership in North Korea and Iran. He said again that ''diplomacy must be the first choice'' in ending the nuclear standoffs with both nations.</p>
        <p>But he acknowledged that in Iran's case, ''we're relying upon others, because we've sanctioned ourselves out of influence with Iran.''</p>
        <p>He repeated his warnings to Iran and Syria not to interfere with Iraq's coming election. ''When I said the other say that I expect these countries to honor the political process in Iraq without meddling, I meant it,'' he said. ''And hopefully, those governments heard what I said.''</p>
        <p>The issue of the training of Iraqis is hardly a new one for Mr. Bush, but it is one he has been reluctant to talk about publicly. In September, speaking in the Rose Garden with Prime Minister Ayad Allawi of Iraq, he talked of training 125,000 troops by year's end. But the numbers mean relatively little, said Barak A. Salmoni, who has studied the training process at the Naval Postgraduate School in Monterey, Calif. ''There have been some improvements in recent months that are worthy of study and emulation,'' he said. ''But the numbers tend to reflect who is on payrolls, not who is showing up the next day, or who is ready to fight.''</p>
        <p>Even as he parried questions on foreign policy, Mr. Bush reiterated his intention to push for an array of domestic initiatives starting in January.</p>
        <p>The president signaled that he intended to disclose more details in coming months about his approach to Social Security, saying he would ''propose a solution at the appropriate time.'' But he dodged repeated questions about what those details might be.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush has called for adding personal investment accounts to Social Security but has not specified what other steps he would support to address the retirement system's financial problems. When asked why he did not refer in public to the likelihood that any plan would require painful steps like benefit cuts, Mr. Bush acknowledged that dealing with the issue ''requires difficult choices.''</p>
        <p>He said his emphasis for now would be on convincing lawmakers that a ''crisis is upon them'' with regard to Social Security, because without that sense of urgency, Congress might not summon the will to act. Many Democrats agree that Social Security's finances are sufficiently shaky that some action should be taken to ensure the system's long-term health, but a growing number of liberal groups are taking exception to the administration's assertion that there is a crisis that demands wholesale changes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush also made it clear that he intended to push ahead with his proposal to rewrite some of the nation's immigration laws, despite considerable opposition from conservative Republicans in Congress. His plan would grant some illegal aliens the right to work in the United States, in jobs that no Americans wanted, but would not grant them citizenship and would ultimately require them to return to their home countries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush vowed to meet his pledge to cut the budget deficit in half within five years. Administration officials said that pledge would mean reducing by half the $521 billion level that White House projections said it would reach in the last fiscal year, which ended Sept. 30. The deficit never actually got that high, coming in at $413 billion for the year.</p>
        <p>A group of senior Democrats immediately challenged Mr. Bush to include in the budget he will submit to Congress in February the costs of continued military operations in Iraq and Afghanistan, a category of spending that the White House had left out of the budget in the past.</p>
        <p>Getting the budget back on track ''has to begin with a realistic estimate of the deficit, and no estimate is realistic if it omits the enormous cost of our efforts in Iraq and Afghanistan,'' the senior Democrats on the House and Senate Budget and Armed Services Committees said in a letter to Mr. Bush.</p>
        <p>THE CONFLICT IN IRAQ: THE PRESIDENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
