<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: CBS and QVC Announce Their Marriage;Merger Accord Proves Popular On Wall Street</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="696717"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">CBS INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">QVC NETWORK INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TISCH, LAURENCE A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DILLER, BARRY  BARRYDILLER</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAURENCE A TISCH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940701T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E0DD1739F932A35754C0A962958260" item-length="1707" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: CBS and QVC Announce Their Marriage;Merger Accord Proves Popular On Wall Street</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE;</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CBS may have lost some luster since its days as the "Tiffany network," and stock in Barry Diller's QVC Inc. may have skidded in the wake of its failed Paramount takeover bid, but all that was forgotten yesterday.</p>
        <p>Laurence A. Tisch, chairman of CBS, and Mr. Diller, QVC's chairman, confirmed that they had reached a tentative agreement to merge the two companies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CBS may have lost some luster since its days as the "Tiffany network," and stock in Barry Diller's QVC Inc. may have skidded in the wake of its failed Paramount takeover bid, but all that was forgotten yesterday.</p>
        <p>Laurence A. Tisch, chairman of CBS, and Mr. Diller, QVC's chairman, confirmed that they had reached a tentative agreement to merge the two companies.</p>
        <p>The deal would mark the end of the powerful Tisch family's dominance of CBS, reducing both the family's stock holdings and Mr. Tisch's management role.</p>
        <p>But in Mr. Diller and QVC, Mr. Tisch has found an heir apparent and created a combined cable and broadcast television operation.</p>
        <p>Shares of CBS Up $50</p>
        <p>The pending alliance was applauded on Wall Street. CBS's stock jumped $50 a  share, or 19 percent, to close at $313, regaining almost all the value it had shed in the last six weeks since it lost eight television affiliates to the Fox  Television Network.</p>
        <p>Stock in QVC, the home shopping channel company, rose $5.625, or 18.8 percent, to $38 a share.</p>
        <p>"It is a win for CBS shareholders to take cash out of the company, yet they get to invest in a new entity that is run by arguably the best programmer in the business," said John Tinker, who follows media for Furman Selz &amp; Company. "You combine both network and cable assets. The new company has a low level of debt,  and the flexibility to experiment with new businesses."</p>
        <p>CBS and QVC have agreed to a complex stock and cash merger in which each CBS  shareholder will get $175 in cash and about four-tenths of a share of stock in a newly formed company. QVC shareholders will get roughly one-twentieth of a share of common stock and roughly one-fifth share of nonvoting preferred stock in the  new company. When the dust settles, CBS holders will own 53.6 percent of the new company and QVC holders will own the balance.</p>
        <p>Using yesterday's closing stock prices, Jeffrey Lodgson, a media analyst at the Seidler Company, put the value of the deal to CBS shareholders at $344 a share, and the value to QVC shareholders at about $40 a share. But he noted that the final value to shareholders depended on the price of CBS stock when the deal closed, as well as on subjective valuations of QVC's preferred stock.</p>
        <p>The 71-year-old Mr. Tisch said that he had been motivated to merge CBS with QVC because he liked the idea that "Barry could be part of this company" because of Mr. Diller's track record as a programming executive. Mr. Tisch added: "I had no intention of trying to stay forever. The question was how could you insure that your constituencies are served well?"</p>
        <p>Mr. Diller described CBS as "being in damn good shape, terrific shape," but was careful to shy away from saying anything about specific changes he might make at the network after the completion of the deal, which is planned for the fall. Mr. Diller seemed to relish the chance to get back in the business he likes best -- network programming -- where he had his biggest successes, first at ABC and then in building the Fox network.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tisch's well-known fascination with trading was evident even during yesterday's interview. He took frequent phone calls and reported enthusiastically on Wall Street's reaction to the merger as CBS's stock climbed. .</p>
        <p>But even as Mr. Tisch tracked his stock, some media experts began to wonder whether the Walt Disney Company or other bidders might not attempt to make a competing offer for CBS. A spokesman for the Disney company declined to comment  on rumors.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Tisch and Mr. Diller dismissed a rival bid as unlikely. They said it would be difficult because transferring ownership of a network has a number of regulatory hurdles and is a difficult and lengthy process.</p>
        <p>A Vindication</p>
        <p>If the deal goes through, it would represent a vindication for Mr. Diller, whose company lost a bitter and protracted battle earlier this year with Viacom  Inc. for Paramount Communications Inc.</p>
        <p>As the deal is currently structured, there would be roughly 12.6 million shares of the new company outstanding. The result would be that the Loews Corporation, the Tisch-controlled conglomerate that holds the family's CBS stock, would find its stake reduced from 20 percent of CBS to 9.4 percent of the new company, which would keep the CBS name. Mr. Diller would take over the positions as chief executive and head of the executive committee from Mr. Tisch, who would remain chairman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tisch has four sons, and his brother Robert Tisch has two sons and a daughter. Though the family is extremely close knit, Laurence Tisch denied that  he had ever encouraged his sons to go into the network business and said that none of them had ever indicated to him an interest in doing so.</p>
        <p>Nor was he disappointed at not being able to bring his children into the television business. "I only care that they are happy in what they are doing."</p>
        <p>Indeed, one of his sons, Daniel Tisch, who heads Mentor Partners, a risk arbitrage investment firm, apparently played a role in the merger of CBS and QVC, along with Martin Lipton of Wachtell, Lipton, Rosen &amp; Katz, the law firm that represents both QVC and Loews.</p>
        <p>'Lot of Sense'</p>
        <p>"At the time of the Paramount transaction when they were both -- QVC and Viacom -- going after Paramount, I said to Marty that a CBS transaction makes a  lot of sense," Daniel Tisch said in a telephone interview yesterday. "If Paramount does not succeed, it makes a lot of sense to look at CBS as a transaction."</p>
        <p>Mr. Lipton did not return telephone calls yesterday. However, Herbert Allen of Allen &amp; Company, the investment bankers representing QVC, described Mr. Lipton as the architect of the deal. Apparently Mr. Lipton spoke to both Mr. Diller and Laurence Tisch, suggesting an alliance.</p>
        <p>Mr. Diller said yesterday that he had called Laurence Tisch about a month ago and the two men had met alone at CBS's headquarters.</p>
        <p>The talks took off from there.</p>
        <p>James Tisch, another of Laurence Tisch's sons and an executive vice president at Loews, recalled that the talks had come unraveled once, but that Mr. Lipton put them back on track. He added that he was too busy at Loews to want to give that up.</p>
        <p>When Laurence Tisch was asked whether he might have been more receptive to the idea of stepping aside because of the challenges raised by CBS's loss of affiliates to Fox, he said it was not an issue.</p>
        <p>Daniel Tisch said that his father had never had either "an entry or an exit plan at CBS."</p>
        <p>'Catching the Winds'</p>
        <p>"Larry is very good at catching the winds," he said. "He likes to take advantage of opportunities. There was no thought that he would go in and run the company."</p>
        <p>Daniel Tisch added: "He got involved at age 63 or 64. CBS has never had his signature on it. The board has never changed significantly. Larry never viewed it as his company."</p>
        <p>Of course, Daniel Tisch initially suggested buying CBS stock in 1985. As a trader, he views the deal as a long one: "Eight years is longer than I usually trade for," he said.</p>
        <p>Laurence Tisch was quick to emphasize yesterday that he was not selling the company, and that Loews would own 9.4 percent after the deal was completed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Diller will own less than 2 percent of CBS, although he has options that  would let him acquire as much as 5 percent Clearly, his role as chief executive  of the new entity was critical to the agreement.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Diller will not have as much voting control of the stock as he had at QVC. After he left Fox, Mr. Diller said that he was seeking more autonomy. When he joined QVC, he insisted on voting parity with his leading partners, the Comcast Corporation and Liberty Media, a cable company controlled  by the cable entrepreneur John Malone. Mr. Tisch was quick to note that "Barry will be the boss." And Mr. Diller said he was very excited about his new position.</p>
        <p>But there are already obvious tensions among the new shareholders.</p>
        <p>Mr. Tisch has been a bitter rival of Mr. Malone's in various cable and broadcast battles. Yesterday, however, he sought to smooth that friction, referring to his adversary as "brilliant," but adding, "That is not a sentiment; it is a fact."</p>
        <p>The proposed CBS-QVC deal is not likely to face significant regulatory obstacles, according to communication lawyers in Washington. CBS is prohibited under current Federal regulations from owning newspapers or cable television systems in markets where it also owns a television station, but QVC is merely a  provider of programming and not a system operator. And although QVC is owned in  part by two cable companies, Tele-Communications Inc. and Comcast, those companies are not expected to own more than 5 percent of CBS, and are therefore  not expected to constitute a problem.</p>
        <p>In the event that another bidder sought control of CBS, the Federal Communications Commission would have to approve the transfer of television and radio licenses. That could prove complicated, because CBS was granted special "grandfather" exemptions to rules that bar a company from owning a television and radio station in the same market.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
