<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pavin Scorches Memorial Opener</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="446000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PAVIN, COREY</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MEMORIAL GOLF TOURNAMENT</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910517T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE4D9113AF934A25756C0A967958260" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pavin Scorches Memorial Opener</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAIME DIAZ,</byline>
      <dateline>DUBLIN, Ohio, May 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Corey Pavin, the leading money and tournament winner on the PGA Tour this year, continued his superlative play today with a six-under-par 66 to take the first-round lead of the Memorial Tournament.</p>
        <p>The slightly built, 5-foot-7-inch Pavin, whose victories this year came in playoffs at the Bob Hope and last week at Atlanta, used his shot-making creativity to post six birdies and no bogeys on a fast and tricky Muirfield Village Golf Club. Pavin has now shot in the 60's in 9 of his last 10 rounds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Corey Pavin, the leading money and tournament winner on the PGA Tour this year, continued his superlative play today with a six-under-par 66 to take the first-round lead of the Memorial Tournament.</p>
        <p>The slightly built, 5-foot-7-inch Pavin, whose victories this year came in playoffs at the Bob Hope and last week at Atlanta, used his shot-making creativity to post six birdies and no bogeys on a fast and tricky Muirfield Village Golf Club. Pavin has now shot in the 60's in 9 of his last 10 rounds.</p>
        <p>Dave Rummells is one shot back with a 67, while veterans Tom Watson and Fuzzy Zoeller shot 68. A total of 32 players broke par of 72, a record for the first round in this tournament, including 71's by tournament host Jack Nicklaus and Greg Norman, who was playing his first tournament since the Masters. Power Game Superfluous</p>
        <p>Pavin has had only one top-10 finish in six previous appearances at this Nicklaus-designed course, where the elevated greens and 7,014-yard course length work against his relatively short-hitting, low-ball game. But warm, dry weather has created firm fairways that gave up as much as 60 yards in roll to well-hit drives, making Muirfield Village more a position than a power course.</p>
        <p>"It's nice to come to a golf course like this and really test your game out," said Pavin, who holed a 10-foot par putt on the 18th. "You had to play point-to-point golf out there today, and it makes it fun to have to hit a lot of different types of shots."</p>
        <p>Rummells's explosive round included eight birdies of lengths ranging from a foot to 25 feet. His round was marred by a double bogey at the 410-yard par-4 ninth hole, where he pushed his 7-iron approach into the water hazard that guards the green, and a bogey on the par-5 11th hole, where he hit a 1-iron approach into a creek. No Speed Limit on Greens</p>
        <p>Rummells said the key to his round was keeping his birdie putts below the hole on the sloping, often lightning fast greens. But Rummells also said that because putting is one of his strengths, he expects to perform well on them all week even when his ball striking is not as precise.</p>
        <p>"If the greens are fast, it favors a guy like me," said Rummells. "It doesn't bother me to get above the holes because my touch is so good."</p>
        <p>If Rummells sounded somewhat cocky, there is a good reason. After an abysmal 1990, Rummells was forced to return to the PGA Tour's qualifying school to retain his exempt status for this year. In the sixth and final round, Rummells came to the final hole needing no worse than a bogey to qualify for the last spot. He hit his approach to the par-4 hole into the water, but recovered on his next shot, hitting an 8-iron from 153 yards to within 5 feet and sinking the putt for the crucial bogey.</p>
        <p>"I was playing so bad, but I just gutted it out with sheer guts," said Rummells, who has yet to win in six seasons on the PGA Tour.</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
