<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place;   Thorny Issues in S.&amp; L. Seizure</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="382210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DECISIONS AND VERDICTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCOUNTING AND ACCOUNTANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FRANKLIN SAVINGS ASSN</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">RESOLUTION TRUST CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORRIS, FLOYD</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB173DF934A3575AC0A966958260" item-length="1284" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place;   Thorny Issues in S.&amp; L. Seizure</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NORRIS, FLOYD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: A Federal judge's ruling that the Government acted illegally in seizing the Franklin Savings Association has raised questions about the Government's ability to regulate - and avoid huge losses at - institutions that use highly sophisticated investment strategies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: A Federal judge's ruling that the Government acted illegally in seizing the Franklin Savings Association has raised questions about the Government's ability to regulate - and avoid huge losses at - institutions that use highly sophisticated investment strategies.</p>
        <p>At issue beyond the immediate issue of who should control Franklin is how well the Government can regulate institutions as complicated as Franklin. The ruling could make regulators afraid to move against institutions that can find experts willing to defend their practices and accounting, even if the regulators believe they are not safe.</p>
        <p>In the end, of course, the taxpayers will pay the bill if an institution that should be closed is allowed to continue operating.</p>
        <p>Judge Saffels ruled that some Federal regulators who had inspected Franklin ''appeared to lack adequate training and understanding to evaluate the nature of Franklin's operation.'' While qualified experts disagreed on a variety of important issues, he said, he found the experts called by Franklin to be more impressive. That conclusion played an important role in his ruling.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Fleischer and Franklin ultimately prevail, then the , institution based in Ottawa, Kan., will be able to stay in business, with the hope that its future complicated strategies will be more successful than its recent ones.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, if the strategies are not successful, then the losses could grow.</p>
        <p>An Unusual Institution</p>
        <p>Franklin has always been an unusual institution, largely because it has engaged in complicated and sophisticated strategies involving financial futures that were intended to hedge it against losses brought on by fluctuating interest rates.</p>
        <p>But the strategies resulted in losses, which led the Government to take over the institution. There are no allegations of improper transactions, as there have been at some ailing savings and loan associations.</p>
        <p>Nor are bad loans a large part of the dispute, although a subsidiary issue in the case involves the size of the loss the association should take on an unsuccessful commercial property transaction.</p>
        <p>At the heart of the dispute is the method of accounting for futures contracts and other sophisticated financial instruments, when those contracts are bought not for speculation, but to hedge against a company's business risks. Under certain circumstances, losses or profits from such investments can be deferred for several years, to be taken at the same time as the institution reports profits or losses from the business that is being hedged.</p>
        <p>Franklin, like most savings institutions, has a large block of short-term deposits, on which interest rates can change rapidly, depending on the level of rates in the economy. It also has mortgage loans that will be outstanding for many years. If interest rates rise, Franklin could find itself squeezed, as it must pay high rates for money that is being lent out at lower rates.</p>
        <p>Franklin set up an elaborate hedge, which it frequently changed, involving zero-coupon bonds, futures and options contracts, and an esoteric type of mortgage security known as principal-only contracts. The holders of those contracts get all principal payments from mortgages, while others get the interest payments.</p>
        <p>In an interview yesterday, Mr. Fleischer said the institution had set out to hedge against the possibility that the rates it pays on deposits would increase. In fact, rates fell, and the hedges lost $119 million. He said the institution's view of accounting rules, which was accepted by Judge Saffels, was that the loss could be reported over seven years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Fleischer said the institution no longer had such a hedge in effect, but he said that should not affect its ability to defer the losses. Now, he said, the institution is hedging against fluctuations in the value of its assets, the mortgages and mortgage-backed securities it owns. He said the overall effect of the hedges was similar.</p>
        <p>Whether Franklin's accounting for hedges conforms to generally accepted accounting principles was a dispute in the trial before Judge Saffels. Accountants called by Franklin, among them Chester B. Vanatta, a former managing partner of Arthur Young &amp; Company, said it did. Accountants testifying for the Government said it did not.</p>
        <p>Judge Saffels said one Government witness, Alfred Schrott, a partner in Spicer &amp; Oppenheim, was ''extremely conservative'' in his accounting, and the judge decided his testimony was less persuasive than that of the Franklin witnesses.</p>
        <p>For the public, the more important issue would seem to be whether Franklin's assets are worth more than its liabilities. Generally accepted accounting principles can often produce misleading answers, since they do not require many assets to be carried at market value. Judge Saffels found, however, that the ''economic value'' of the company was not less than the accounting book value shown by the company of $387 million on Dec. 31, 1989.</p>
        <p>In reaching that conclusion, the judge said he placed great weight on the testimony of Samuel Stewart, the president of Wasatch Inc., an investment firm, who put the value of Franklin as a going concern at $250 million to $700 million.</p>
        <p>The judge ruled that testimony from Government witnesses, setting a much lower value based on liquidation values, was not ''relevant or meaningful'' because the other testimony convinced him that there was no need to liquidate the institution.</p>
        <p>While taking the loss from the hedging tranasctions would not, in itself, have left the institution insolvent, it would have left it with insufficient capital under Federal rules, John Scowcroft, Franklin's vice chairman, said.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately for Franklin, that would leave it in apparent violation of a covenant in bonds that Franklin had issued. Those bonds provide that if Franklin's capital falls below required levels, it must sell certain securities that secure the bonds and replace them with Treasury securities. Mr. Scowcroft said that such a move would have cost the company about $180 million, enough to cause the Government to conclude it was insolvent.</p>
        <p>Although Franklin is controlled by Mr. Fleischer, some of its stock is publicly traded. Howard Kay, a trader at Rodman &amp; Renshaw in Kansas City, Mo., which makes a market in the over-the-counter stock, said the closing price yesterday was $2 bid, $2.75 asked, up from $1.25 bid, $1.75 asked, before Judge Saffels's decision was released Wednesday.</p>
        <p>The appeals court's ruling came after trading ended yesterday. It temporarily stayed the lower court ruling pending further review by the appellate judges.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
