<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: EAST RIVER PARK: The Ups and Downs (and Ups) of a 57-Acre Dream Park; Park on Respirator Breathes New Life</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="711404"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PARKS AND OTHER RECREATION AREAS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTORATION AND REHABILITATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST RIVER PARK (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOWER EAST SIDE (NYC)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940911T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE3DC1F38F932A2575AC0A962958260" item-length="501" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: EAST RIVER PARK: The Ups and Downs (and Ups) of a 57-Acre Dream Park; Park on Respirator Breathes New Life</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARVINE HOWE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Opened as a grand esplanade along the new East River Drive in 1939, the East River Park had slowly deteriorated. Only four pedestrian walks cross the six-lane drive to link the 1 1/4-mile strip of park to Alphabet City and the Lower East Side. Budget cuts prevented anything more than piecemeal renovations.</p>
        <p>But a clarion call for help was heard a few years ago, when inspections showed that the tides were wearing away the seawall that supports the park's esplanade. "Major reconstruction was needed to keep the park from sliding into the sea," said Robert Redmond, a Parks Department spokesman.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Opened as a grand esplanade along the new East River Drive in 1939, the East River Park had slowly deteriorated. Only four pedestrian walks cross the six-lane drive to link the 1 1/4-mile strip of park to Alphabet City and the Lower East Side. Budget cuts prevented anything more than piecemeal renovations.</p>
        <p>But a clarion call for help was heard a few years ago, when inspections showed that the tides were wearing away the seawall that supports the park's esplanade. "Major reconstruction was needed to keep the park from sliding into the sea," said Robert Redmond, a Parks Department spokesman.</p>
        <p>Since then, several renovation projects have been completed -- some structural, and mainly invisible, others delightfully practical and cosmetic -- in the 57 acres of park that stretch from just above the Manhattan Bridge to 12th Street.</p>
        <p>And next weekend, the Parks Enforcement Patrol, a wing of the City Park Rangers, plans to move into a refurbished station at Corlears Hook Park, part of the East River Park. A dozen officers, formerly based at Battery Park, will work out of Corlears Hook and cover a score of other parks south of 42d Street.</p>
        <p>"This will mean more attention for East River Park," said Alexander R. Brash, chief of the Urban Park Service. But the park -- which even during the heaviest of the reconstruction work, continued to draw devotees ranging from T'ai Chi adepts to tennis players -- is generally peacefully shared. Chief Brash said the biggest problem for the patrol officers was keeping vehicles out of the park but a new emergency parking lot should take care of this.</p>
        <p>Isidora Risi sat watching her son and daughter go though exercises at the Brian Watkins Tennis Club (named for the slain Utah tourist slain whose family is suing the city). "I grew up in this park and love it, especially the children's tennis lessons," Mrs. Risi said, referring to the free youth program, started in 1991 as part of the $1.7 million renovation of the 12 public tennis courts.</p>
        <p>Officer David Bentham and his partner, Michael Accurso, slowly patrolled the East River esplanade recently. Neither officer could remember any violent incidents in the two-and-a-half years they have been patrolling there.</p>
        <p>"It's a family-oriented park," said Officer Bentham.</p>
        <p>At the north end of the park, the officers pointed to the fenced-off area where works on the seawall have begun, a $1.4 million project financed by the Mayor's executive budget. All the pilings have already been replaced at the southern end of the park, at a cost of $1.7 million.</p>
        <p>Nearby, a new basketball court and a new children's playground are both busy, even on a weekday afternoon. They cost $450,000 and were paid for by City Council member Antonio Pagan's capital fund.</p>
        <p>The changes aren't over yet. Near 10th Street a $550,000 comfort station is to be built this fall and a barbecue and picnic tables costing $100,000 will be set up next year, also financed by the council member's fund. MARVINE HOWE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
