<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Jury Is Told Chief Backed Shifts in Enron Accounting</title>
    <meta content="01enron" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/01/business/businessspecial3/01enron.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1743362"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enron Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Skilling, Jeffrey K</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lay, Kenneth L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Delainey, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barrionuevo, Alexei</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Accounting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accounting and Accountants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Securities and Commodities Violations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Enron Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Skilling, Jeffrey K</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EED61631F932A35750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1242" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Jury Is Told Chief Backed Shifts in Enron Accounting</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Jury Is Told Chief Backed Shifts in Enron Accounting</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEXEI BARRIONUEVO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barrionuevo, Alexei</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, Feb. 28</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Enron Energy Services division head David Delainey testifies that former Enron chief executive Jeffrey Skilling signed off on controversial accounting shift involving troubled trading contracts; says there was no business purpose but to hide losses at energy unit and that he knew it was not proper; says Skilling and Kenneth Lay went to great lengths to mislead analysts that Enron was not high-risk trading company at its core in order to protect company's high stock price; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former Enron executive on Tuesday gave the strongest testimony yet in the five-week-old trial that Jeffrey K. Skilling, the company's former chief executive, signed off on a controversial accounting shift involving troubled trading contracts.</p>
        <p>David W. Delainey, who headed the Energy Services division at Enron, said that he initially resisted the idea of shifting losses from his unit to the wholesale division, an accounting move that he concluded was improper and misled investors. But, he said, he went along with the move after Mr. Skilling accepted the idea as a way to continue the fiction that the energy unit was profitable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former Enron executive gave the strongest testimony yet that Jeffrey K. Skilling signed off on a controversial accounting shift involving troubled trading contracts.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former Enron executive on Tuesday gave the strongest testimony yet in the five-week-old trial that Jeffrey K. Skilling, the company's former chief executive, signed off on a controversial accounting shift involving troubled trading contracts.</p>
        <p>David W. Delainey, who headed the Energy Services division at Enron, said that he initially resisted the idea of shifting losses from his unit to the wholesale division, an accounting move that he concluded was improper and misled investors. But, he said, he went along with the move after Mr. Skilling accepted the idea as a way to continue the fiction that the energy unit was profitable.</p>
        <p>Mr. Delainey recounted a meeting on March 29, 2001, in Mr. Skilling's office where, he said, Mr. Skilling assented to the move after Mr. Delainey initially got ''cold feet.''</p>
        <p>''There was no business purpose but to hide the loss and I knew that was not proper,'' he testified.</p>
        <p>Mr. Delainey, 40, provided other testimony on Tuesday in the trial of Mr. Skilling and Enron's founder, Kenneth L. Lay, who are accused of conspiring to defraud Enron investors. Mr. Skilling and Mr. Lay say that there was no conspiracy and that any wrongdoing at Enron was confined to a small group that did not include them. They also say that Enron's failure was tied to a market panic and not to portrayals of its finances.</p>
        <p>Mr. Delainey testified that Mr. Skilling and Mr. Lay went to great lengths to mislead analysts that Enron was not a high-risk trading company at its core, in order to protect the company's high stock price.</p>
        <p>Mr. Delainey also said Mr. Skilling tried to allay Mr. Delainey's initial concerns about using hedging vehicles as a place to park ''orphan assets'' and hide potential losses while booking huge earnings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Delainey is yet another former Enron manager who is testifying after pleading guilty to crimes and agreeing to cooperate with the government. He has pleaded guilty to insider trading that netted him $4.3 million and faces a maximum prison term of 10 years. He made $11 million while working at Enron and forfeited $7.9 million of that to the federal government, he said.</p>
        <p>During questioning, Mr. Delainey recounted how top managers at the meeting on March 29, 2001, discussed a plan by Richard A. Causey, the chief accounting officer. At the time the retail unit faced having to book almost immediate losses of $200 million from a surcharge being added to retail power in California during the state's energy crisis. Mr. Delainey said a decision was made to move all the money-losing operations from the energy services unit into wholesale ''and to justify it as an operational change.''</p>
        <p>While Mr. Delainey conceded that at first he found that idea ''clever,'' he soon lost his nerve. ''We were using an efficiency change to hide at least $200 million in losses,'' he said, in describing how Enron planned to justify the action.</p>
        <p>''I said we didn't need to do this and we could just write it off, and it lacked integrity,'' Mr. Delainey recalled saying at the meeting. Mr. Causey reacted angrily, he said, saying it was a ''bona fide operational change.'' Then Mr. Skilling turned to Mr. Delainey and said, ''What do you want to do?''</p>
        <p>''What did you take that to mean?'' asked Kathryn H. Ruemmler, a prosecutor.</p>
        <p>''Get in line,'' Mr. Delainey responded.</p>
        <p>About three weeks later, on April 17, Enron reported income for the retail group of $40 million in the first quarter of 2001 -- a lie, Mr. Delainey said, since the unit had not reported some $300 million in losses. Mr. Skilling cited the division's ''explosive growth'' to analysts, and Mr. Lay said in August of that year that retail ''just keeps banging away and growing at a tremendous rate.''</p>
        <p>None of that was true, Mr. Delainey said. When Enron declared bankruptcy in December 2001 the energy services unit had never turned a profit in its core business, he said.</p>
        <p>In the April 17 earnings press release, Enron claimed that its ''risk management activities'' were being managed by its wholesale unit and that this had been the case since the beginning of 2001. But as of that day in April, the change had yet to be carried out, Mr. Delainey said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Delainey said that Mr. Lay previously signed off on an idea Mr. Delainey floated in January of 2001: to shift about $1 billion in energy bills owed by failing California utilities from ''the little bucket'' of retail energy to ''the big bucket'' of wholesale. Mr. Lay said it ''sounded like a good idea.'' Once done, the potential trading losses were contained at about $500 million.</p>
        <p>Also on Tuesday, Mr. Delainey offered the first evidence that Mr. Skilling was aware of the plans to use the Raptor accounting vehicles to move underperforming assets and hundreds of millions of dollars of debt off Enron's books.</p>
        <p>In the spring of 2000, when Mr. Delainey was heading Enron's wholesale group, he went to Mr. Skilling with concerns about using Enron's stock to hedge the value of the assets being placed in the vehicles. He said he asked Mr. Skilling if he supported their use. ''He said it was approved and 'what are you worried about?' '' Mr. Delainey recounted. ''I took that as an affirmation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Delainey later proposed putting some 40 assets into Raptors, which he saw as a ''bookkeeping exercise.'' A true sale of the assets, he said, would have taken ''one and a half years, at least.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Delainey also recounted how managers, including Mr. Skilling and Mr. Lay, discussed efforts to falsely portray Enron as a ''logistics and services'' company with predictable earnings, when most profits were derived from risky speculative trading.</p>
        <p>He said by late 2000 the profit-and-loss swings grew extreme: the wholesale unit lost $551 million on trading in one day, Dec. 12, which was more than the $500 million in profits of the wholesale unit's North American division in all of 1999.</p>
        <p>The fat profits in the wholesale division were looked upon as a reservoir that could ''fill gaps for other divisions that were not making as much,'' Mr. Delainey said.</p>
        <p>Use of so-called Schedule C reserves was ''standard operating procedure at Enron,'' Mr. Delainey said. ''My experience at Enron in Houston was that we tended to be pretty fast and loose with the rules.''</p>
        <p>The volatility in California's energy markets became a boon for Enron, and by the fall of 2000 ''we were knocking the cover off the ball,'' Mr. Delainey said.</p>
        <p>He said that at a meeting on Oct. 16, 2000, Mr. Skilling was overwhelmed with emotion when Mr. Delainey told him that the wholesale unit had $200 million to $300 million in ''reserves'' that would give Enron ''flexibility for a few quarters.''</p>
        <p>''He gave me a hug,'' Mr. Delainey recalled.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
