<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two Are Charged in Money-Laundering Scheme</title>
    <meta content="14MOB.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1309186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Money Laundering</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Longshoremen's &amp; Warehousemen's Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genovese Crime Family</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bellomo, Liborio S</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cafaro, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rashbaum, William K</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Organized Crime</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Racketeering and Racketeers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Extortion and Blackmail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E3D6123BF937A25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="430" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two Are Charged in Money-Laundering Scheme</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM K. RASHBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rashbaum, William K</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Liborio S Bellomo, reputed member of Genovese crime family now serving prison term on extortion conviction, and Thomas Cafaro are charged with conspiring to launder money they siphoned from International Longshoremen's Association benefit fund between 1996 and 1997; charges are added to earlier indictment that is among several that charge more than two dozen crime family figures with racketeering and other crimes (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Federal prosecutors in Brooklyn announced money-laundering conspiracy charges yesterday against a man they identified as the former acting boss of the Genovese crime family.</p>
        <p>The man, Liborio S. Bellomo, 44, was charged in an indictment handed up Thursday in United States District Court in Brooklyn. Prosecutors said the charges arose from efforts by Mr. Bellomo and another man to launder money they siphoned from the International Longshoremen's Association benefit funds between 1996 and 1997.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Federal prosecutors in Brooklyn announced money-laundering conspiracy charges yesterday against a man they identified as the former acting boss of the Genovese crime family.</p>
        <p>The man, Liborio S. Bellomo, 44, was charged in an indictment handed up Thursday in United States District Court in Brooklyn. Prosecutors said the charges arose from efforts by Mr. Bellomo and another man to launder money they siphoned from the International Longshoremen's Association benefit funds between 1996 and 1997.</p>
        <p>Charged with Mr. Bellomo, who is known as Barney and who is serving a prison term for an earlier extortion conviction, was Thomas Cafaro, 42. Prosecutors said Mr. Cafaro was an Genovese crime family associate.</p>
        <p>The accusations against the two men were added to an earlier indictment handed up in April, which was among several that charged more than two dozen crime family figures with racketeering and other crimes. While Mr. Cafaro was charged in the earlier indictment, Mr. Bellomo was not. The earlier indictment named several other men, identified by prosecutors as mid-level managers in the Genovese family.</p>
        <p>In 1997, Mr. Bellomo, of Pelham Manor, N.Y., was sentenced to 10 years in prison after pleading guilty to extorting payoffs from a construction union and a garbage hauling company. At the time, he was the Genovese family's acting boss, prosecutors said. Murder and racketeering charges against him were dropped as part of a plea agreement.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cafaro, of Boca Raton, Fla., is the son of Vincent Cafaro, a capo in Genovese family known as the Fish who became a government witness nearly two decades ago. Vincent Cafaro's move led his son to offer to carry out a standing contract for his father's killing, law enforcement officials said, adding that he never tried to make good on the offer.</p>
        <p>The charges yesterday were the result of an investigation by the Police Department, the F.B.I. and the office of United States attorney in Brooklyn, Alan Vinegrad.</p>
        <p>A lawyer for Mr. Cafaro, Michael Rosen, said his client had pleaded not guilty to the earlier charges and ''pleaded not guilty, louder'' to the new indictment. He called the claim that Mr. Cafaro had offered to kill his father a ''government fiction.''</p>
        <p>Calls to Mr. Bellomo's lawyer were not returned.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
