<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Strain of Fourth-Grade Tests Drives Off Veteran Teachers</title>
    <meta content="14GRAD" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/14/nyregion/14GRAD.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1301536"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodnough, Abby</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Standards and Standardization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Teachers and School Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Principals (School)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Council of Supervisors and Administrators</org>
        <org class="online_producer">United Federation of Teachers</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E5D91F3EF937A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1453" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Strain of Fourth-Grade Tests Drives Off Veteran Teachers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ABBY GOODNOUGH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodnough, Abby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Growing number of veteran New York City teachers shun fourth grade, citing strain of administering high-stakes state tests; leave assignments for least experience teachers; principals fear trend could depress test scores, key factor in rating schools and principals; teachers complain they are being held responsible for results, even though tests measure skills students have been learning since kindergarten, interviews; note focus on testing takes emotional toll on students (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A growing number of fourth-grade teachers in New York City are seeking other assignments, saying they cannot stand the pressure of administering the high-stakes state tests that have become a defining feature of fourth grade, school officials around the city say.</p>
        <p>And since tenured teachers can generally choose their assignments within a school, fourth-grade classes are increasingly being entrusted to the least experienced educators, a trend that principals fear could depress the scores for the grade.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A growing number of fourth-grade teachers in New York City are seeking other assignments, saying they cannot stand the pressure of administering the high-stakes state tests that have become a defining feature of fourth grade, school officials around the city say.</p>
        <p>And since tenured teachers can generally choose their assignments within a school, fourth-grade classes are increasingly being entrusted to the least experienced educators, a trend that principals fear could depress the scores for the grade.</p>
        <p>Principals say they are troubled by these developments because the fourth-grade exams are the most crucial factor in rating elementary schools and even deciding whether they are added to the state's list of low-performing schools. The fourth-grade scores also play a major role in determining whether principals stay in their posts and, starting this year, receive merit bonuses.</p>
        <p>In interviews over the last month, many fourth-grade teachers questioned why they should stay in a job that revolves around preparation for new state exams in reading, mathematics and science. They said that school administrators were holding them responsible for poor results, even though the tests measure skills that students should have been learning since kindergarten. They also said that the intense, sometimes single-minded focus on testing was taking an emotional toll on fourth graders, increasing their stress levels in a way the teachers said they could not abide.</p>
        <p>''The whole school is looking at how our kids are going to do, so the pressure is enormous,'' said Brian Davis, a fourth-grade teacher at Public School 57 in the Bronx who has asked to teach first grade next year. ''The test-prep books have basically become our curriculum.''</p>
        <p>It is impossible to know just how many teachers are leaving the fourth grade in New York City because the Board of Education does not track the movement of teachers from grade to grade. But in interviews, about two dozen teachers and principals around the city confirmed that the problem not only exists, but is worsening at their schools.</p>
        <p>The principals say that they cannot keep experienced teachers in fourth grade, or transfer them there, because of a provision in the teachers union contract that gives teachers with seniority significant leeway in choosing their assignments from year to year. Unlike many teachers contracts elsewhere in the state, the New York City contract requires principals to send out ''preference sheets'' to teachers in May, on which they list their top three assignment choices for the next school year.</p>
        <p>Although principals technically can veto a senior teacher's top choice, most do not out of fear that the teacher will file a time-consuming grievance, according to officials at the Council of Supervisors and Administrators, the union representing city principals.</p>
        <p>''It is absolutely a hindrance,'' said the principal of a Staten Island elementary school where two fourth-grade teachers, both veterans, have requested new assignments. Given the high stakes and the growing acrimony over the tests, most of the teachers and principals interviewed, including this one, spoke on the condition of anonymity. ''If it were an informal survey asking the teachers what job they would prefer, that would be fine,'' he said. ''But holding my feet to the fire is a problem because it ruins my creativity in filling the most challenging jobs.''</p>
        <p>Officials at the teachers union said that eighth-grade teachers, whose students also take new state exams in English, math and other subjects, are also complaining about the pressure to raise test scores. But fewer of those teachers are seeking new assignments, the officials said, possibly because they teach only one subject and are responsible for only one test. New York City also tests third, fifth, sixth and seventh graders in reading and math, but those exams do not carry the same weight as the fourth-grade exams.</p>
        <p>''The buck now stops with the fourth-grade teacher and it's terribly unfair,'' said Randi Weingarten, president of the United Federation of Teachers, the city teachers union. ''Instead of using these tests diagnostically to assess where kids are, they've too often become an off-with-your-head tool.''</p>
        <p>New York State introduced new fourth-grade exams in English and mathematics in 1999 to hold students accountable to rigorous new academic standards. Fourth graders also take a state science test. The English exam, which is given over three days in January and tests students' reading, writing and listening skills, is considered the most difficult of the fourth-grade tests and the one whose results say the most about how a school is doing. Only 43.9 percent of New York City students passed the exam this year, compared with 69.4 percent in the rest of the state.</p>
        <p>To be sure, the majority of fourth-grade teachers are not jumping ship, and even many of those who wish the tests did not carry such high stakes say that they approve of standardized testing. Debbie Campbell, who volunteered to teach fourth grade next year at Public School 198 on the Upper East Side, said she thought the state English test in particular was a valuable measure of whether students were meeting standards.</p>
        <p>''These are basic things that children need to know,'' she said. 'Teachers who are confident and prepare their students properly have nothing to feel bad about.''</p>
        <p>Most principals interviewed said they were loath to put rookie teachers in the fourth grade because of the public scrutiny of fourth-grade scores, which are published in newspapers, and because preparation for the language arts and mathematics tests requires skills that many novices lack.</p>
        <p>Some principals said they were creating incentives to persuade experienced teachers to take fourth-grade classes: one Brooklyn principal found the money to put extra computers in fourth-grade classrooms and to create a new fourth-grade classroom next fall so that each teacher would have fewer students.</p>
        <p>Even with such inducements, the principals say, fourth grade is a hard sell.</p>
        <p>''They tell me it's giving them health problems and high blood pressure,'' the Brooklyn principal said of teachers who want out of fourth grade. ''I have to cajole and beg. They don't want the embarrassment and humiliation of knowing that if they don't produce good results, it's published in the newspaper.''</p>
        <p>Many principals said they routinely meet with fourth-grade teachers at the beginning of each school year to analyze each new fourth grader's test scores from the previous year and set targets for improvement. One new teacher in the Bronx described a meeting last September in which his principal told the fourth-grade teachers exactly how many students she expected to pass the English test. The principal warned that if teachers did not meet the established targets, they would be ''letting the children down,'' according to the teacher.</p>
        <p>''She set goals for each of us, saying, 'This is where I want you to be, number-wise,' '' the teacher said. ''It was almost theatrical the way she said it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Davis of P.S. 57 in the Bronx said he had been mulling leaving the fourth grade for several years, but when his school was added to the list of failing schools in December he quickly made up his mind.</p>
        <p>''I need to not feel that intense pressure that if the kids don't improve, our school will be closed down,'' Mr. Davis said. ''I need a break so I can recover my strength.''</p>
        <p>A first-year teacher who was given one of the most challenging fourth-grade classes in a low-performing Brooklyn school said that she was leaving the profession, partly because of the pressure from administrators to raise her students' scores.</p>
        <p>''It is all around you, it is constant, it never lets up,'' the teacher said of the focus on improving test scores. ''It is criminal to give a first-year teacher a fourth-grade job.''</p>
        <p>Unlike teachers at low-performing schools, those at schools where most students pass the tests said their biggest concern was the psychological impact of the test culture. A teacher in Queens who is a 25-year veteran of the school system said that she had asked to leave fourth grade after 10 years because of what the tests ''are taking away from the children.''</p>
        <p>She said that for her the last straw came this spring, when her school asked the fourth-grade teachers to spend the month of June preparing their students for a new state social studies test that they will take early in fifth grade. Until now, she said, June has been the only month of the school year in which teachers and students can forget about standardized tests.</p>
        <p>''It hits them like a bomb the minute they walk into fourth grade,'' the teacher said. ''It's way too early to put this amount of pressure on them. I don't want to play a part in it anymore.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
