<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Finds No Allergies to Altered Corn</title>
    <meta content="Y14STAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/06/14/business/14STAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1301507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Corn</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Environmental Protection Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aventis Cropscience</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pollack, Andrew</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetic Engineering</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corn</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Grain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food Contamination and Poisoning</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Genetics and Heredity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tests and Testing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetables</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010614T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE4DC1F3EF937A25755C0A9679C8B63" item-length="828" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Finds No Allergies to Altered Corn</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">U.S. Finds No Allergies to Altered Corn</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pollack, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention scientists say they have found no evidence that any people had had allergic reactions to genetically modified StarLink corn; findings could dispel public concern that corn represents threat to public health; results could also clear way for Environmental Protection Agency to permit small amounts of corn to be present in food without leading to recalls, something that would relieve farmers, grain processors and food companies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Government scientists said yesterday that they had found no evidence that any people had had allergic reactions to the genetically modified StarLink corn.</p>
        <p>The findings could dispel public concern that the corn, which spread through the nation's food supply even though it was never approved for human consumption, represents a threat to public health.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Government scientists said that they had found no evidence that any people had had allergic reactions to the genetically modified StarLink corn</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Government scientists said yesterday that they had found no evidence that any people had had allergic reactions to the genetically modified StarLink corn.</p>
        <p>The findings could dispel public concern that the corn, which spread through the nation's food supply even though it was never approved for human consumption, represents a threat to public health.</p>
        <p>The results, announced by the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, could also clear the way for the Environmental Protection Agency to permit small amounts of the corn to be present in food without leading to recalls, something that would greatly relieve the farmers, grain processors and food companies.</p>
        <p>The C.D.C. and the Food and Drug Administration tested the blood of 17 people who had reported suffering allergic reactions ranging from upset stomachs to potentially fatal anaphylactic shock after eating products they thought contained StarLink corn.</p>
        <p>The agencies looked to see if the blood contained antibodies to the protein in the corn that was considered the possible allergen. No such antibodies were found, an indication that none of the people had had immune reactions to the corn protein.</p>
        <p>''We do not have any positive results whatsoever,'' said Carol S. Rubin, a research scientist at the National Center for Environmental Health at the C.D.C. Still, the report prepared by the centers says that there is some possibility that people could be allergic without having antibodies in their blood.</p>
        <p>StarLink contains a bacterial gene that permits the corn to produce a protein that kills the corn borer, a major pest. But that protein, known as Cry9C, has some characteristics of an allergen, mainly that it is not digested easily in the stomach.</p>
        <p>Because of those concerns, the corn was approved for use as animal feed but not for human consumption. But it leaked into the human food supply, causing huge recalls of taco shells and other products, hurting American grain exports, forcing grain elevators and food companies to test incoming shipments of corn, and raising new concerns about the possible health effects of genetically engineered foods.</p>
        <p>Now, the biotechnology industry, which said all along that there was little threat to public health from the corn, may breathe a bit easier. ''We are pleased, but not the slightest bit surprised,'' said L. Val Giddings, vice president for food and agriculture of the Biotechnology Industry Organization, a trade group.</p>
        <p>Critics of genetically modified food said the testing was insufficient. ''These tests are not proof that StarLink corn is safe for human consumption,'' said Matt Rand, a spokesman for Genetically Engineered Food Alert, a coalition of environmental groups. ''This is not a thorough investigation.''</p>
        <p>He said the government did not test the hundreds of people who complained to food companies about reactions instead of to the F.D.A. He also said it appeared that the test might have been performed using Cry9C made by bacteria, which might be different from the protein made in the corn.</p>
        <p>Dr. Rubin said she could not comment on the specifics of the antibody test because it was designed by the F.D.A. An F.D.A. spokeswoman said her agency would not comment.</p>
        <p>Dr. Marc E. Rothenberg, the section chief for allergy and immunology at Children's Hospital in Cincinnati and an adviser to the E.P.A. on this issue, said that antibody tests were more likely to report false positives than false negatives. Just because a person has antibodies to a protein does not mean she suffered an allergic reaction, he said. But if there are no antibodies, he said, there is only a tiny chance that the person had an allergic reaction.</p>
        <p>The results of the blood tests will be used by the E.P.A. to decide whether to permit small amounts of StarLink in human food. Aventis CropScience, the company that developed StarLink, has asked the  agency to permit such a small presence for four years, so the food industry would be spared the costs and disruptions of testing and food recalls. The E.P.A. has scheduled a meeting of its scientific advisory panel for next month to discuss the issues.</p>
        <p>Aventis, which declined to comment on the results announced yesterday, has asserted that since most of the StarLink grown has been collected by the company and the government, there is so little in the food supply that it would not cause any public health problems even if Cry9C were found to be an allergen.</p>
        <p>The C.D.C. and the F.D.A. reviewed the cases of 51 people who had told the agency about allergic reactions they thought were connected to StarLink. Of those, 28 people were considered to have had some sort of allergic reaction, while the rest were judged to have had some other health problem.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
