<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Trade Data Spur a Big Stock Drop</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="713405"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DOW JONES STOCK AVERAGE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK STOCK EXCHANGE (NYSE)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMERCE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dow Jones Stock Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940921T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DD163AF932A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Trade Data Spur a Big Stock Drop</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY RAMIREZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RAMIREZ, ANTHONY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>America's mounting trade deficit was bad news for the dollar yesterday, and that, in turn, meant bad news for the stock market. Its fall accelerated by high-speed computer-guided trading near the end of the session, the Dow Jones industrial average lost all its hard-won gains since Aug. 30 and slipped below 3,900.</p>
        <p>The Dow index of 30 blue-chip stocks, the best-known measure of stock performance, lost 67.63 points to close at 3,869.09, and the other leading indexes also fell. The broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500 stock index fell 7.49 points, to 463.36, and the smaller-company Nasdaq composite index fell 9.98 points, to 766.74.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>America's mounting trade deficit was bad news for the dollar yesterday, and that, in turn, meant bad news for the stock market. Its fall accelerated by high-speed computer-guided trading near the end of the session, the Dow Jones industrial average lost all its hard-won gains since Aug. 30 and slipped below 3,900.</p>
        <p>The Dow index of 30 blue-chip stocks, the best-known measure of stock performance, lost 67.63 points to close at 3,869.09, and the other leading indexes also fell. The broader Standard &amp; Poor's 500 stock index fell 7.49 points, to 463.36, and the smaller-company Nasdaq composite index fell 9.98 points, to 766.74.</p>
        <p>Stock prices usually fall because traders dislike a stock or are pessimistic about the economy, or both. But sometimes, as happened yesterday with the computer selling, factors that have little to do with market fundamentals or the world economy also play a large role.</p>
        <p>Traders were dumping stocks all day after the release of worse-than-expected figures concerning the July trade deficit, which at $10.99 billion was the second highest in the nation's history. Then, a huge computer-guided "sell" program further reduced leading stock indexes at 3:36 P.M. Minutes later, when the Dow fell 50 points, the program activated the New York Stock Exchange's "circuit breaker" rules, which are intended to curb the computerized trading known as index arbitrage.</p>
        <p>The probable identity of the computer trader will not be clear until the exchange publishes its computerized trading figures later this month. Nor was it clear why the trader was selling stocks in a falling market, when bargain hunting might have seemed more likely.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey Rubin, a market analyst at Birinyi Associates, which tracks such trading, estimated that the sell program involved some 28 million shares in 360 S.&amp; P. 500 stocks. It reduced the Dow by 20.10 points and the S.&amp; P. 500 by 2.49 points, he said.</p>
        <p>Christine A. Callies, an equity market strategist at Brown Brothers Harriman, said the market had risen too high on technical factors, rather than market sentiment. "This just wipes the slate clean," she said.</p>
        <p>The market had been rising for three weeks, partly because of such factors as "short covering," by which traders who had sold borrowed shares betting that stock prices would fall were forced to buy shares when prices unexpectedly rose. Traders also bid up stocks because they believed that the Federal Reserve, which raised short-term interest rates by half a percentage point on Aug. 16, would not act again until after the November elections.</p>
        <p>But now, that consensus has melted away. Yesterday's near-record low for the dollar versus the Japanese yen in the currency markets worried stock traders. That prompted the leading stock indexes to retreat from further assualts on their records for the year. The Dow's high this year is 3,978.36 points on Jan. 31. The S.&amp; P. 500's high is 482.00 points on Feb. 2, and the Nasdaq's peak is 803.93 points on March 18.</p>
        <p>The immediate cause of yesterday's fall was the Commerce Department's trade report. Wall Street economists had expected the deficit would total a worrisome $9.8 billion. When it exceeded that by a startling $1.19 billion, and included a wider deficit with Japan, the dollar fell to a New York close of 97.65 yen, just a fraction above the closing low set on July 12 of 97.40 yen after hitting a post-World War II low of 96.60 yen in intraday trading.</p>
        <p>Japanese are paid in dollars for Japanese goods they sell in the United States, and then exchange those dollars for yen or other major currencies. The resulting glut of dollars has pushed the dollar's value to the lowest point in nearly 50 years. A weak dollar means foreign investors are less likely to buy stocks and bonds because gains will be cut when converted to their own currencies.</p>
        <p>Amid the general retreat, some stocks advanced. Magma Power, which operates geothermal power plants, rose 7 1/4, to 34 3/4, after receiving an $840 million takeover bid from a rival, the California Energy Company. Shares of the 3Com Corporation, a computer company, rose 1 1/8, to 38 3/8, after it said its first-quarter profit had more than doubled.</p>
        <p>Shares of First Alert and American Sensors, the two principal makers of carbon-monoxide detectors, rose on expectation of higher sales after reports that Vitas Gerulaitis, the former tennis star, died accidentally from carbon-monoxide poisoning. First Alert rose 2, to 27, and American Sensors rose 1 3/8, to 20 1/4.</p>
        <p>Volume on the New York Stock Exchange was far above average, with 326.1 million shares changing hands, about 14 percent above this year's average of 286 million shares.</p>
        <p>The New York Stock Exchange composite index fell 3.72 points, to 255.91, with declining stocks far outpacing advancers, 1,812 to 492. The American Stock Exchange market value index fell 2.98 points, to 458.15.</p>
        <p>Of the 30 component stocks that make up the Dow industrials, 28 fell, led by E.I. du Pont de Nemours, which gave up 1 3/4, to 57 3/4.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
