<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ex-Student Denies Killing Levin and Tells of Gunmen</title>
    <meta content="08LEVI$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="942385"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sullivan, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arthur, Corey</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Levin, Jonathan M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Robberies and Thefts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E4DF1439F93BA35754C0A961958260" item-length="811" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ex-Student Denies Killing Levin and Tells of Gunmen</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sullivan, John</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Corey Arthur is arraigned for murder of Bronx high school teacher Jonathan M Levin; Arthur says two armed men forced him to tie up Levin while he was visiting his former teacher in his Manhattan apartment and that he had fought with men before managing to escape; says he was making delivery of crack cocaine to Levin (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A former student accused of murdering Jonathan M. Levin told the police that two armed men forced him to tie up Mr. Levin while he was visiting the teacher in his Manhattan apartment and that he had fought with the men before managing to escape, according to court papers filed yesterday during the suspect's arraignment.</p>
        <p>The suspect, Corey Arthur, 19, told the police that he had visited Mr. Levin to make a delivery of crack cocaine to the teacher. Mr. Arthur said that Mr. Levin had smoked the crack immediately before the attack, and that he had fled the apartment before Mr. Levin was killed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A former student accused of murdering Jonathan M. Levin told the police that two armed men forced him to tie up Mr. Levin while he was visiting the teacher in his Manhattan apartment and that he had fought with the men before managing to escape, according to court papers filed yesterday during the suspect's arraignment.</p>
        <p>The suspect, Corey Arthur, 19, told the police that he had visited Mr. Levin to make a delivery of crack cocaine to the teacher. Mr. Arthur said that Mr. Levin had smoked the crack immediately before the attack, and that he had fled the apartment before Mr. Levin was killed.</p>
        <p>Anthony Ricco, a lawyer for Mr. Arthur, said yesterday, however, that a toxicology report by the Medical Examiner's office showed that tests did not find the presence of ''basic drugs'' in Mr. Levin's body. But Mr. Ricco said that despite the report the defense would conduct its own toxicology tests of hair and blood samples.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors declined to comment on the toxicology report yesterday. The judge in the case has repeatedly warned lawyers for both sides that they must be extremely careful in any public comments they make about it.</p>
        <p>But prosecutors said previously that a backpack found at Mr. Levin's Upper West Side apartment contained empty crack vials and belonged to Mr. Arthur. They also have said that Mr. Arthur used his relationship with Mr. Levin to gain entry to his apartment, where, the police said, Mr. Arthur killed his former teacher for his bank card.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Ricco said police documents turned over to the defense yesterday also indicated that the police had found a crack pipe in Mr. Levin's apartment. And he said the documents indicated that the pipe had not been tested for drugs, which he said he found ''quite unusual.''</p>
        <p>The statements giving Mr. Arthur's account were filed after he was charged with first-degree murder and robbery. At his arraignment yesterday before Supreme Court Justice Marcy L. Kahn, Mr. Arthur pleaded not guilty to both charges.</p>
        <p>The Manhattan District Attorney, Robert M. Morgenthau, has not said whether he will seek the death penalty for the first-degree murder charge. Under state law, he has 120 days to make a decision after the arraignment.</p>
        <p>In the statements, Mr. Arthur said he was visiting his former teacher's apartment when the two men burst in and forced him to bind Mr. Levin with tape. Mr. Arthur said he fought with the men and was stabbed in the hand before escaping.</p>
        <p>''These guys came into the apartment with guns,'' detectives said Mr. Arthur told them during his June 7 arrest. ''They put a gun to my head and put me on the floor. This guy with the gun forced me to tie the teacher, Mr. Levin, with tape. I was there and you could take me to see some photos. I can show you who these guys are.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Arthur's co-defendant, Montoun Hart, has already pleaded not guilty to second-degree murder and robbery. Mr. Hart, who claims he was present during the murder but not a participant, has told the police that Mr. Arthur murdered Mr. Levin during a robbery.</p>
        <p>Mr. Arthur's portrayal of Mr. Levin as a crack smoker is in stark contrast with descriptions given by others who knew the young teacher. Friends and colleagues at William Howard Taft High School described Mr. Levin as a dedicated man who only recently told students that he was the son of Gerald M. Levin, the chief executive of the Time Warner media conglomerate. Students described him as friendly and outgoing.  In part because of his popularity at the school, the police began a citywide manhunt after Mr. Levin was found dead on May 30. Investigators said he had been bound and slashed with a knife in an attempt to discover his A.T.M. card code, and then shot once in the head. Mr. Hart and Mr. Arthur were arrested eight days after the murder.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hart told the police that he and Mr. Arthur had gone to Mr. Levin's apartment to rob him. He said that Mr. Arthur shot Mr. Levin after binding him with duct tape.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Arthur said he had gone to make a drug delivery and was surprised by the two armed men. He also told the police that he did not report the crime because he was afraid that he would be blamed. He also told them he had been ''running away from community service'' on a fare-beating charge.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
