<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Woman Caring for Nephew Is Killed in Hammer Attack</title>
    <meta content="15sitter" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/08/15/nyregion/15sitter.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1695000"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050815T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E4DE123EF936A2575BC0A9639C8B63" item-length="522" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Woman Caring for Nephew Is Killed in Hammer Attack</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Woman Caring for Nephew Is Killed in Hammer Attack</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WILSON and ANAHAD O'CONNOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A 21-year-old woman baby-sitting for her nephew was beaten to death with a hammer in Brooklyn yesterday morning by a companion of the child's mother, the police said.</p>
        <p>It was unclear yesterday what provoked the attack on the woman, Sharlene Francis, of 540 Kosciusko Street in Bedford-Stuyvesant, the police said. The only witness to the attack may have been her 2-year-old nephew, the police said. The companion, Richard Thorne, 34, was arrested after he opened his door for officers and they saw blood on him, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A woman was beaten to death with a hammer in Brooklyn by a companion of her nephew's mother, the police said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A 21-year-old woman baby-sitting for her nephew was beaten to death with a hammer in Brooklyn yesterday morning by a companion of the child's mother, the police said.</p>
        <p>It was unclear yesterday what provoked the attack on the woman, Sharlene Francis, of 540 Kosciusko Street in Bedford-Stuyvesant, the police said. The only witness to the attack may have been her 2-year-old nephew, the police said. The companion, Richard Thorne, 34, was arrested after he opened his door for officers and they saw blood on him, the police said.</p>
        <p>Officers were called to Mr. Thorne's home, at 1162 Stanley Avenue in East New York, about 7 a.m., the police said. They found Ms. Francis, beaten but still alive, and arrested Mr. Thorne, the police said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Francis had been there baby-sitting for her older brother's son, a family friend said. Ms. Francis was taken to Brookdale University Hospital and Medical Center, where she was pronounced dead later in the morning, the police said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thorne was treated for minor injuries and charges were pending last night, said a spokesman for the Brooklyn district attorney's office.</p>
        <p>The police said Mr. Thorne had been arrested for shoplifting in North Carolina and New Jersey, and was charged with robbery once in Harlem, the police said. The status of those cases was not available as of last night. Ms. Francis was studying accounting in college, according to a friend who identified herself only as Connie. Ms. Francis lived with her mother, identified as Darlene Francis, and her younger half-brother.</p>
        <p>''She would always be outside in the yard playing Double Dutch with my kids,'' Connie said, adding that Ms. Francis' mother was devastated. ''That was her only daughter. It's unbelievable. She was a good person. She never bothered anyone. I can't imagine anybody would do something like that to her.''</p>
        <p>Another relative, who gave his name only as Shaheim, said, ''She was a fantastic individual. She was gorgeous. She was beautiful and I'm going to miss her.''</p>
        <p>A neighbor, Cecilia Sosa, said Ms. Francis helped her organize a trip to a march for women's rights, and helped with her son's recent birthday party. ''She did many things with me. I was very close to her. She did a lot of special things. I consider her a very loving, courageous, intelligent, strong young woman. She was destined to be something great.''</p>
        <p>Kenneth West, 24, who lives nearby, said he met Ms. Francis on Saturday, when he saw her in a nearby park. ''I thought she was pretty, so I went up and started talking to her. She was baby-sitting one child.''</p>
        <p>She gave him her telephone number and the two had planned to meet yesterday, Mr. West said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
