<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Liberated by His Conscience</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="411801"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHULMAN, MARSHALL D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SAKHAROV, ANDREI D</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MOSCOW AND BEYOND: 1986 TO 1989 (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDB1538F933A05751C1A966958260" item-length="1442" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Liberated by His Conscience</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Marshall D. Shulman; Marshall D. Shulman is the Adlai E. Stevenson Professor Emeritus of International Relations at Columbia University's Harriman Institute for Advanced Study of the Soviet Union.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHULMAN, MARSHALL D</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MOSCOW AND BEYOND  1986 to 1989. By Andrei Sakharov. Translated by Antonina Bouis. Illustrated. 168 pp. New York: Alfred A. Knopf.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MOSCOW AND BEYOND  1986 to 1989. By Andrei Sakharov. Translated by Antonina Bouis. Illustrated. 168 pp. New York: Alfred A. Knopf.</p>
        <p>JUST a year ago, on Dec. 14, 1989, the great, courageous heart of Andrei Sakharov stopped. He was 68 years old.</p>
        <p>But his voice, as the conscience of his countrymen and of the world, has not been stilled. His memoirs continue his clarion call to "make good the demands of reason and create a life worthy of ourselves and of the goals we only dimly perceive," as he wrote in his speech accepting the Nobel Peace Prize in 1975. (The speech was read for him by his wife, Yelena Bonner, since he was not permitted by the Soviet authorities to travel to Oslo.)</p>
        <p>This slim book, the second and final volume of his memoirs, completed shortly before his death and ably translated by Antonina Bouis, sketches the events of the last three years of Sakharov's life, from his return to Moscow from exile in Gorky to his last speech before the Congress of People's Deputies on June 9, 1989. Read in conjunction with the heftier first volume, published in June of this year, "Moscow and Beyond" carries forward the account of the evolution of his reformist thought and actions under the changed circumstances of Mikhail S. Gorbachev's perestroika.</p>
        <p>That evolution began in the mid-1960's, when Sakharov began to emerge in public from his world of highly classified military research -- he is regarded as the father of the Soviet thermonuclear bomb -- as a thoughtful social critic, with articles on the Soviet educational system, genetics, the rehabilitation of Stalin and the trials of dissident writers. In 1968, he came to international attention with the publication in the West of his essay "Reflections on Progress, Peaceful Coexistence, and Intellectual Freedom," where he called for freedom of thought and world government.</p>
        <p>It was clear from the start that his was a remarkable voice. A personal note: when "Reflections" was published, I wrote in The Saturday Review that "his essay is in the great tradition of the moral conscience and sense of social responsibility of the Russian intellectual, and it is a thrilling experience to come upon an expression of this tradition today, like a seedling breaking through the cement of a city pavement with its vital force."</p>
        <p>From that time, Sakharov continued to evolve, deepening his campaign against the overmilitarization of his society and the dangers of nuclear war, and particularly expanding his efforts in behalf of human rights. He became the tireless tribune of all those who were persecuted for their political beliefs, and was himself banished from Moscow by Leonid Brezhnev in 1979 for his opposition to the war in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>Characteristically, Sakharov's response to Mr. Gorbachev's telephone call permitting him to return to Moscow in 1986 to continue his "patriotic work" was to appeal for the release of all "prisoners of conscience."</p>
        <p>And thus began a new stage in Sakharov's struggle. From Mr. Gorbachev's point of view, to bring Sakharov back to Moscow as a sign of the seriousness of his commitment to glasnost was a gamble, since he did not know if the famous dissident would be willing to mute his criticisms. Sakharov, however, had no intention of being co-opted; he lent his support to Mr. Gorbachev's reforms, but he remained independently critical of their shortcomings, and increasingly so to his last days.</p>
        <p>There lies the high drama between the two men that is the heart of this book -- one, the uncompromising idealist, the other, the pragmatic political tactician. Doggedly, stubbornly, inconveniently persistent, Sakharov continued his struggle for the immediate and complete realization of his goals for the democratization of the country, for the rule of law, for full freedom of speech, of thought and of conscience. "Only a radicalization of perestroika can overcome the crisis without a disastrous move into reverse," he writes here. Mr. Gorbachev, pursuing politics as the art of the possible, accepted compromises in order to feed the reforms, step by step, into a resisting system. To the Soviet leader, such compromises were a necessary part of the political process. To Sakharov and many others of the liberal (or radical) intelligentsia, they were a betrayal. (It may occur to readers of a certain age that there is a faint parallel to the relationship between Franklin D. Roosevelt and Norman Thomas. Does the process of political change require both kinds of reformers -- the political tacticians and the idealists?)</p>
        <p>The two Russians appear to have regarded each other with a mixture of respect and exasperation. Frequently, Mr. Gorbachev gave Sakharov the floor at the Congress of People's Deputies immediately on seeing his hand raised, despite the noisy opposition of the conservatives. But at the concluding session, Mr. Gorbachev showed visible irritation and shut off the microphones when Sakharov, determined to get his entire program out before the delegates, exceeded the allotted five-minute time limit.</p>
        <p>Sakharov describes Gorbachev, after their first face-to-face encounter, as "intelligent, self-possessed, and quick-witted in discussion, and the policies he was pursuing at the time impressed me as consistently liberal, fostering a gradual growth of democracy by means of fundamental reforms." But, speaking of Mr. Gorbachev's "half-measures" and "several seemingly retrograde actions," he writes: "I attributed these failings mainly to the constraints that inhibit every leader, especially a reformer, and to the rules of the game prevailing in the milieu in which Gorbachev had made his career and in which he was still operating."</p>
        <p>"I just can't see an alternative to Gorbachev at this critical juncture," Sakharov writes (in May of last year). "Even though his actions may have been prompted by historical circumstances, it has been Gorbachev's initiatives that have completely altered the country and the psychology of its people in just four years. At the same time, I don't idealize him, and I don't believe he's doing all that's needed. Furthermore, I think it's extremely dangerous to concentrate unlimited power in the hands of a single man. But none of this changes the fact that there is no alternative to Gorbachev." (Events have moved so rapidly that one cannot be sure what Sakharov's view might be today.)</p>
        <p>Sakharov's central message is that the reforms of his own country and all other countries must above all be committed to moral principles. On the few occasions when I met him, he impressed me as a saintly man.</p>
        <p>But he was also, as "Moscow and Beyond" reveals, exquisitely human. He acknowledges mistakes. He settles old scores with, among others, Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, and seems to forget nothing, not only of his unspeakable encounters with the K.G.B. (which twice destroyed the manuscripts for his memoirs) but of arguments with other reformers. He particularly lashes out against the many who attacked him through his wife, and pays her tribute for prompting him "to understand much that I would otherwise miss because of my restrained personality."</p>
        <p>Sakharov is surely an authentic hero of our times. For him, perhaps the most fitting tribute is the quotation from Goethe's "Faust" with which he prefaced "Reflections on Progress, Peaceful Coexistence, and Intellectual Freedom": "He alone is worthy of life and freedom / Who each day does battle for them anew."</p>
        <p>INSULTED BY SOLZHENITSYN</p>
        <p>I called  [ Solzhenitsyn ]  from Newton in the morning. His wife, Natalya, answered the phone. We spoke for several minutes before she called Solzhenitsyn, noting that this was an exception, since he almost never comes to the phone himself. . . . I said a few words about the importance of his work as a writer, and then added, "Alexander Isayevich, there should be nothing left unsaid between us. In your book 'The Oak and the Calf' you hurt me deeply, insulted me. I'm speaking of your pronouncements about my wife, sometimes explicit and sometimes without naming her, but it's perfectly clear whom you mean. My wife is absolutely not the person you depict. She's an infinitely loyal, self-sacrificing, and heroic person, who's never betrayed anyone. She keeps her distance from all salons, dissident or otherwise, and she's never imposed her opinions on me."</p>
        <p>Solzhenitsyn was silent for several seconds -- he probably wasn't accustomed to direct rebukes. Then he said, "I would like to believe that it is so." By ordinary standards, that wasn't much of an apology, but for Solzhenitsyn it was apparently a major concession. From "Moscow and Beyond."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
