<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New York City Seeks to Protect Funds</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="411892"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BANKS AND BANKING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUINT, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DC103CF933A05751C1A966958260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New York City Seeks to Protect Funds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL QUINT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">QUINT, MICHAEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New York City has begun studying ways to protect up to $400 million it has in uninsured accounts at 28 local banks used by city agencies and departments.</p>
        <p>Because of the city's size and myriad agencies, each of which manages its own bank accounts, officials say they cannot eliminate bank deposits above the $100,000 maximum eligible for Federal deposit insurance. But they are considering whether local banks should be required to provide collateral, such as Treasury securities, to cover those deposits if the bank should fail. The practice is common in other parts of the country, and required by law for local governments in 39 states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New York City has begun studying ways to protect up to $400 million it has in uninsured accounts at 28 local banks used by city agencies and departments.</p>
        <p>Because of the city's size and myriad agencies, each of which manages its own bank accounts, officials say they cannot eliminate bank deposits above the $100,000 maximum eligible for Federal deposit insurance. But they are considering whether local banks should be required to provide collateral, such as Treasury securities, to cover those deposits if the bank should fail. The practice is common in other parts of the country, and required by law for local governments in 39 states.</p>
        <p>Robert E. Huber, an assistant commissioner in the Finance Department, said that last month's failure of Freedom National Bank led to the review of the practice of keeping unsecured deposits. "The banking market is spongy," he said. "We don't anticipate any failures, but at this time prudence would dictate that we examine our policy."  Exempt From State Law</p>
        <p>The city is exempt from a state law requiring that certificates of deposit and checking accounts of counties and cities be backed by collateral.</p>
        <p>In the past, officials were content to monitor the safety of banks holding city funds through reviews of those banks prepared by private rating services. The city has not lost any money from its uninsured checking accounts because of a bank failure since the creation of Federal deposit insurance in 1933.</p>
        <p>At Freedom National, which held about $300,000 in city funds when it failed last month, the city was protected because its funds were backed by collateral provided by the bank. The deposits were collateralized because they were in certificates of deposit, not checking accounts.</p>
        <p>Elinor B. Bachrach, the Deputy State Comptroller for New York City, said she was surprised to learn how much money the city held in accounts which were uninsured and not backed by collateral. "It's certainly an issue and something we should look into," she said.</p>
        <p>Earlier this month, L. William Seidman, chairman of the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation, warned that many of the bank failures he expects in the coming year will be in the Northeast. Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Rhode Island and Vermont are among the states which do not require that banks pledge collateral to back deposits of local governments.  Deposits in 28 Banks</p>
        <p>The city keeps accounts with 28 banks, but most of the checking-account funds are in Chase Manhattan Bank, Chemical Bank and Manufacturers Hanover Trust Company. Earnings at all three banks have suffered recently from loan losses, particularly for commercial real estate projects, and their financial condition has deteriorated. All three are rated Prime-2 by Moody's Investors Service, a rating that is below the top-notch Prime-1 rating but still high enough to be considered a prudent investment.</p>
        <p>According to a comptroller's report covering the year that ended June 30, 1990, the city had bank balances of $486 million on June 30, of which $371 million was uninsured and uncollateralized. Another $37.8 million in investment accounts for entities like pension funds was also uninsured and uncollateralized.</p>
        <p>The comptroller's report said that the $371 million in uninsured funds held at banks did not fluctuate much during the year.</p>
        <p>Most of the city's uninsured deposits are "compensating balances" that pay the city no interest because the banks they are in provide various services to the city, such as issuing or cashing payroll checks or providing quick collection of real estate taxes.</p>
        <p>To obtain collateral for the uninsured deposits, city officials expect that they would have to pay a fee to banks for handling the securities transfers and record-keeping. National Trend</p>
        <p>According to David Chanko, manager of bank contracts and compliance in the treasury bureau of the Department of Finance, the city pays about $40 million a year for bank services. About half the payments are in the form of fees, he said, and half are in the form of non-interest-bearing deposits kept at banks. He said there are cases in which such deposits are unavoidable, despite the city's preference for investing surplus funds to earn interest.</p>
        <p>Girard C. Miller, a vice-president at Fidelity Investments Institutional Services in Boston, said other cities generally pay a fee for collateral equal to about one-fourth of 1 percent of the amount covered. A fee of one-fourth of 1 percent would equal $1 million for $400 million of uninsured deposits.</p>
        <p>"The trend nationally is for local governments to pay for bank services through fees rather than through deposits," Mr. Miller said. "They can often earn more on investments than the banks give them credit for by holding deposits."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
