<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Haven Drops Mall Plan After 5 Years</title>
    <meta content="14MALL$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/14/nyregion/14MALL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1255156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Haven (Conn)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Destefano, John Jr (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Zielbauer, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut/New Haven</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001214T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DD1E3FF937A25751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="977" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Haven Drops Mall Plan After 5 Years</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL ZIELBAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zielbauer, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>NEW HAVEN, Dec. 13</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Haven shelves plan for $500-million shopping mall to revive economy, after nearly five years of talk and millions of dollars in marketing and environmental studies; rendering; Mayor John DeStefano, formerly enthusiastic, now likens Galleria at Long Wharf project to Vietnam quagmire; says city will contrate on high-tech, citing $1 billion in new investments by biotechnology companies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A grand plan to build a $500 million shopping mall to revive this city's economy has been shelved after nearly five years of talk and millions of dollars in marketing and environmental studies.</p>
        <p>Until this week, New Haven's mayor, John DeStefano, had spent a significant chunk of political capital defending the plan to build a ''super-regional'' shopping center just west of downtown on Long Island Sound, a project that he said would breathe some economic life back into a city whose downtown has been dormant for years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A grand plan to build a $500 million shopping mall to revive this city's economy has been shelved after nearly five years of talk and millions of dollars in marketing and environmental studies.</p>
        <p>Until this week, New Haven's mayor, John DeStefano, had spent a significant chunk of political capital defending the plan to build a ''super-regional'' shopping center just west of downtown on Long Island Sound, a project that he said would breathe some economic life back into a city whose downtown has been dormant for years.</p>
        <p>But in disclosing his decision about the mall to The New Haven Register on Tuesday, the mayor sounded more like the mall's worst critics, comparing it to a quagmire like the Vietnam War.</p>
        <p>Backers of the project, which was to have been known as the Galleria at Long Wharf,  envisioned constructing 1.2 million square feet of retail space and eventually adding $7 million in annual property taxes and 3,000 jobs to New Haven's economy. But its opponents, including 130 downtown merchants, said the mall would pulverize local retailers and turn the city into a suburb of the mall itself.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. DeStefano, who did not respond to several calls seeking comment, publicly cited several reasons for the decision, including the $1 billion in investments the city has gained from biotechnology companies.</p>
        <p>Andrea Comer, Mr. DeStefano's spokeswoman, said those investments were ''something we didn't have when we first put our support behind the project.''</p>
        <p>The mayor also tried to assure residents that the city had other major development plans for downtown, plans that in time would reduce the project to little more than a forgettable distraction.</p>
        <p>He said New Haven would be focusing its development efforts on increasing the number of high-tech and other new companies that have opened in the downtown area in recent months.</p>
        <p>Those new companies have created optimism among City Hall and business leaders, and the view that after years of decline, New Haven may be poised to take advantage of the digital age.</p>
        <p>By contrast, building a shopping mall seemed an old idea tied to the 1980's, less economically promising and decidely less glamorous, city officials said. ''It was easier to let that go knowing we had this tremendous direction for the city,'' Ms. Comer said.</p>
        <p>The mayor said he began thinking of dropping the mall project in recent weeks after reading newspaper reports that one of the mall's anchor stores, Nordstrom's, might pull out. Such a move, he said, could easily have caused withdrawals by other retail anchors, including Filene's, Macy's and Lord &amp; Taylor, and cause the entire project to unravel.</p>
        <p>Last week, Mr. DeStefano met with top executives of the company that was planning to build the mall, New England Development Corporation, based in Newton, Mass., and told them that the city wanted out.</p>
        <p>''I don't think that the city would have gotten out of the project,'' Ms. Comer said about the mall, ''if we had felt there was something sustainable for us.''</p>
        <p>The conciliatory words and the quick retreat from the project, however, contrast greatly with New Haven's aggressive defense of the mall project in recent months against a legal and public relations barrage from its opponents, including some state legislators and a mall developer that controls an existing mall in nearby Milford.</p>
        <p>When a state representative, James A. Amann, of Milford, where Westfield America has a mall, denounced New Haven's project during a floor debate in the State House in March, Mr. DeStefano was waiting outside the chamber afterward to tell reporters why the New Haven mall deserved public support.</p>
        <p>When Westfield America, the competing mall developer, filed more than a dozen legal challenges to the mall earlier this year, Mr. DeStefano fired back, suing Westfield in State Superior Court and accusing it of using the courts to try to kill the project.</p>
        <p>But today all that appeared to be in the past, as delighted downtown merchants and the mayor focused on the city's dream of using biotechnology and eager high-tech entrepreneurs to fire its economy.</p>
        <p>''I'm extremely pleased the mayor pulled the plug on this project,'' Mr. Amann said today, citing the $28 million in tax subsidies that the state had agreed to give New England Development to build the mall. ''This was a bad project for the region.''</p>
        <p>Gov. John G. Rowland said he spoke to Mr. DeStefano by telephone Tuesday about the demise of the project and said he supported the mayor's plans to redirect the city's efforts away from retail shopping and toward fostering more high-tech business.</p>
        <p>''The bottom line is, the mall has been a very difficult project to bring to finality,'' Mr. Rowland told reporters in his office today, citing the legal headaches and some critics' predictions of traffic gridlock. ''I think at this juncture, now with all the lawsuits, the focus can and should be on the biomedical research possibilities.''</p>
        <p>Referring to the 19.5-acre site where the mall was to be built, he added, ''I'm certain that that piece of property is conducive to research and development.''</p>
        <p>Westfield America, based in Los Angeles, has offered to buy the site from its two owners, New England Development and Fusco Corporation  of New Haven, and to drop all court actions against them, a spokeswoman said today.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
