<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers Stay With the Sabres, But Can't Hang On in Overtime</title>
    <meta content="27rangers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/27/sports/hockey/27rangers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1807768"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Buffalo Sabres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Rangers</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Buffalo Sabres</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Drury, Chris</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Straka, Martin</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E2DA103EF934A15752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="728" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers Stay With the Sabres, But Can't Hang On in Overtime</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rangers Stay With the Sabres, but Can’t Hang on in Overtime</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNN ZINSER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Zinser, Lynn</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the end of an up-and-down night, after the final dip sent them off the ice with a 3-2 loss in overtime to the Buffalo Sabres, the Rangers tried to paint a happier face on the defeat. They said they were glad to earn a point for taking the game to overtime. They took heart in playing a feisty game against the best team in the league.</p>
        <p>But no matter what they said, they could not quite make the paint stick. Not far under the surface, the Rangers were angry about the winning goal. They were angry at the officials for several of their 10 penalties, which forced them to kill 20 minutes of power play.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Rangers are moving closer to the top teams in the league, but they could not quite match the speed and teamwork of the Sabres on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the end of an up-and-down night, after the final dip sent them off the ice with a 3-2 loss in overtime to the Buffalo Sabres, the Rangers tried to paint a happier face on the defeat. They said they were glad to earn a point for taking the game to overtime. They took heart in playing a feisty game against the best team in the league.</p>
        <p>But no matter what they said, they could not quite make the paint stick. Not far under the surface, the Rangers were angry about the winning goal. They were angry at the officials for several of their 10 penalties, which forced them to kill 20 minutes of power play.</p>
        <p>And they were disappointed that they had come back from a 2-0 deficit but could not pull ahead of the Sabres at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>''If it would happen to them, they would be down, 2-0, and they would tie it, 2-2, and I think they would jump on us and they would beat us,'' said Jaromir Jagr, the Rangers' captain. ''That's not us. We don't have it yet. We're not a good team yet. Good teams, when they have the momentum, they go for it.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers (13-9-2) played stubbornly in this game, falling agonizingly short of a fourth consecutive victory. They had finally erased the Sabres' lead when Martin Straka scored his second goal with 4 minutes 53 seconds left in the third period to tie the score at 2-2.</p>
        <p>But the final turn came 1:30 into overtime, when Chris Drury deflected a shot by defenseman Teppo Numminen past Rangers goalie Henrik Lundqvist to give Buffalo the victory.</p>
        <p>On paper, it did seem the least bit unusual. At 19-3-2, Buffalo has the best record in the league, riding a wave of confidence that began with a 10-game winning streak to start the season. Drury, the Sabres' captain, who has built a career on clutch performances, has 14 goals this season.</p>
        <p>''I was able to get a tip,'' Drury said, almost shrugging off the effort. ''The goalie was squared up to Numminen's shot. It was just one of those things. I was able to get a tip on it and found a hole.''</p>
        <p>Lundqvist, who played valiantly through the penalty kills and made some spectacular stops among his 28 saves, was helpless as the redirected puck tumbled past his glove.</p>
        <p>But the Rangers were fuming about the face-off that preceded Numminen's shot. Rangers center Matt Cullen lost the face-off, then Sabres forward Jason Pominville jumped in front of Rangers wing Brendan Shanahan, who was trying to skate over to block Numminen's shot.</p>
        <p>Shanahan screamed for an interference call, but the officials did nothing. He had the heartbreaking view of Numminen's shot, from behind a player screening him.</p>
        <p>''At the beginning of the year, we all get sent video on what certain calls are and how they are going to be called, and there was a call in overtime that no question might be the best footage you can have of face-off interference,'' Rangers Coach Tom Renney said.</p>
        <p>Shanahan was further angered by the referees' refusal to explain to him why they did not make the call. But even he tried to make the best of the situation after venting to the officials.</p>
        <p>''I wouldn't say it came down to one call,'' Shanahan said. ''On the positive side, there was a lot of fight and a lot of determination to get back from a 2-0 deficit to one of the better teams in the league. Considering we killed off the better part of 10 penalties, the penalty killing was great.''</p>
        <p>The Rangers felt tantalizingly close to a breakthrough. One night earlier, they won their third game in a row, defeating Pittsburgh when Straka scored with 2.2 seconds left in overtime.</p>
        <p>The Rangers are enjoying a great streak by Straka, whose goals against Buffalo gave him 13 this season. He has had four goals and three assists in the past four games.</p>
        <p>Straka did not take much consolation in that, but he tried to find a positive side.</p>
        <p>''Definitely, we showed a lot of character to come back against a team like this,'' he said. ''It is huge. I think we should be proud of the point against a team like that.''</p>
        <p>Pride, however, struggled to elbow aside the anger.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
