<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prices Decline Ahead of Data On Economy</title>
    <meta content="11BOND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="CREDIT MARKETS" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="914755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Treasury Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hurtado, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E7D81439F932A25750C0A961958260" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prices Decline Ahead of Data On Economy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HURTADO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hurtado, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prices of US Government securities slip; 30-year bond is down 2/32, to price of 97 19/32, to yield 6.81 percent, unchanged from close on March 7; graph (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prices of Government securities slipped yesterday, with few investors willing to buy ahead of economic data to be reported this week, for fear that if the news is too robust, the Federal Reserve will raise interest rates to avert inflation.</p>
        <p>While most market participants expect the Fed to wait until May to tighten credit, some are beginning to suspect that it will come this month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prices of Government securities slipped yesterday, with few investors willing to buy ahead of economic data to be reported this week, for fear that if the news is too robust, the Federal Reserve will raise interest rates to avert inflation.</p>
        <p>While most market participants expect the Fed to wait until May to tighten credit, some are beginning to suspect that it will come this month.</p>
        <p>''Chairman Greenspan is inching closer to a pre-emptive strike,'' said Sung Won Sohn, senior vice president and chief executive of the Norwest Corporation in Minneapolis. ''The tight labor market and above-trend economic growth have raised the probability of tighter monetary policy, but hikes in interest rates will be limited,'' he added, because the inflation picture looks good, and the dollar's appreciation is equivalent to monetary tightening.</p>
        <p>The 30-year bond was down 2/32, to a price of 97 19/32 to yield 6.81 percent, unchanged from Friday's close. With a lack of new data to influence the market's direction, trading was  mostly on technical factors.</p>
        <p>''Given the market's renewed inflation anxieties,'' Anthony Chan, a vice president and the chief economist at Banc One Investment Advisors Corporation in Columbus, Ohio, ''financial market investors are likely to focus this week on Friday's release of the Producer Price Index, with Thursday's retail sales report for February as the second most important number for the week.'' He added, ''Investors will also be holding their breaths in anticipation of the Fed's beige book report, another part of the puzzle.''</p>
        <p>''Nonetheless,'' Mr. Chan said, ''our view suggests that the employment report on Friday failed to provide the smoking gun needed to put to rest any or all doubts about a possible Fed tightening at the March 25 policy meeting. So we are sticking with our view that a May rate hike has a better chance, barring any negative surprises from either the P.P.I. on Friday or the Consumer Price Index next week.''</p>
        <p>Greg Jones, an economist with Briefing.com, a market analysis firm in Menlo Park, Calif., said investors could draw two conclusions about the market outlook if the Fed tightened on March 25: that yields will move higher and that the yield spread between the short end of the market and the long end will narrow. ''A typical spread for the two-year note versus the Federal funds rate is 50 basis points when Fed policy is viewed to be on hold indefinitely,'' he said. ''At present the spread is about 82 basis points.'' (A basis point is a hundredth of a percentage point.)</p>
        <p>''Bulls might argue that this spread already incorporates a 25-basis-point tightening, so the market is well priced for the policy outlook,'' Mr. Jones added. ''However, we can guarantee that if the Fed tightens  there will be an immediate consensus that another 25-basis-point tightening will be seen at the May 20 meeting. With the first tightening, the spread will narrow to 57 basis points if the two-year remains steady. If another is expected, the spread will be in the 75-basis-point-to- 100-basis-point range.''</p>
        <p>Interest rates declined slightly at yesterday's Treasury bill auction, as the results were in line with expectations. The rate for a three-month bill declined four basis points, to 5.06 percent, and the six-month bill fell one basis point, to 5.18 percent, as investors showed a little more demand for the shorter maturity.</p>
        <p>The following are the results of yesterday's Treasury auction of new three-month and six-month bills:</p>
        <p>(000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>3-Mo. Bills  6-Mo. Bills  Average Price  98.721  97.381  Discounted Rate  5.06%  5.18%  Coupon Yield  5.20%  5.39%  High Price  98.726  97.391  Discounted Rate  5.04%  5.16%  Coupon Yield  5.18%  5.37%  Low Price  98.721  97.381  Discounted Rate  5.06%  5.18%  Coupon Yield  5.20%  5.39%  Accepted at low price  38%  41%  Total applied for  $52,643,473  $40,214,577  Accepted  $12,068,408  $12,117,497  Noncompetitive  $1,379,626  $1,147,402</p>
        <p>Both issues are dated Mar. 13, 1997. The three-month bills mature on June 12, 1997, and the six-month bills mature on Sept. 11, 1997.</p>
        <p>CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
