<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Flamenco, as Itself and as It's Been Tidied Up</title>
    <meta content="11FLAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="MUSIC REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="914724"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Brooklyn Philharmonic</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kozinn, Allan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Linares, Carmen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DD1439F932A25750C0A961958260" item-length="651" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Flamenco, as Itself and as It's Been Tidied Up</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALLAN KOZINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kozinn, Allan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Allan Kozinn reviews flamenco performances by Brooklyn Philharmonic; photo of singer Carmen Linares (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nationalist schools of composition have always been defined by their crossbreeding of folk styles with classical forms, but in most cases the classical side is unquestionably dominant. Typically, in fact, composers have used folk elements to temper either modernist or distinctly individualistic styles with recognizable, earthy roots. Bartok and Stravinsky did this; so did Gershwin and Copland.</p>
        <p>For the Spanish nationalist composers -- or, for that matter, for non-Spanish composers who wanted to evoke Spain -- flamenco was the obvious motherlode. Yet composers like Falla, Albeniz, Granados and Turina did not want merely to mine flamenco as a local flavoring. They hoped to elevate it to classical stature, and to that end, they poured its vital dance rhythms, its Eastern-tinged melodies with their Gypsy, Arabic and Sephardic Jewish influences, and their modal harmonies, into the refined timbres and symmetrical forms favored by composers elsewhere in Europe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nationalist schools of composition have always been defined by their crossbreeding of folk styles with classical forms, but in most cases the classical side is unquestionably dominant. Typically, in fact, composers have used folk elements to temper either modernist or distinctly individualistic styles with recognizable, earthy roots. Bartok and Stravinsky did this; so did Gershwin and Copland.</p>
        <p>For the Spanish nationalist composers -- or, for that matter, for non-Spanish composers who wanted to evoke Spain -- flamenco was the obvious motherlode. Yet composers like Falla, Albeniz, Granados and Turina did not want merely to mine flamenco as a local flavoring. They hoped to elevate it to classical stature, and to that end, they poured its vital dance rhythms, its Eastern-tinged melodies with their Gypsy, Arabic and Sephardic Jewish influences, and their modal harmonies, into the refined timbres and symmetrical forms favored by composers elsewhere in Europe.</p>
        <p>Flamenco, both on its own terms and filtered through the sensibilities of the nationalist composers, was the subject of a series last weekend at the Brooklyn Philharmonic. The Brooklyn orchestra has been undertaking musicological adventures of this sort for the last few seasons, and it has the concept well in hand. A thick, nicely illustrated program book, with informative historical notes by Pablo Zinger and Brook Zern, proved a useful tour guide; lectures and a panel discussion offered further (if spottier) enlightenment. And films of flamenco singers, captured at work in taverns and living rooms in the 1960's, put the live performances in perspective.</p>
        <p>The Saturday evening installment (which had also been performed on Friday) was mostly orchestral, with dance and traditional flamenco singing providing a link between the raw and processed forms. Robert Spano conducted the orchestra in bright, outgoing accounts of Turina's ''Orgia,'' with its Puccini-like wind scoring, Carlos Surinach's vibrant ''Sinfonietta Flamenca'' and Roberto Gerhard's ''Alegrias.''</p>
        <p>Actually, the most compelling performances on both Saturday evening and Sunday afternoon were those of Carmen Linares, a flamenco singer who was accompanied by two guitarists, Paco and Miguel Angel Cortes. Ms. Linares's voice has the gritty quality one hears in blues singing, in Portuguese fado and in some Middle Eastern forms. It is not beautiful in the operatic sense, but its expressive power is extraordinary. There was also a superb interaction between her singing and the wonderfully detailed playing of the Cortes brothers. Flamenco guitars are lighter in timbre than classical models, and where classical players try to minimize string noise in favor of pure tone, their flamenco counterparts use the brash attacks of nails against strings as a percussive overlay.</p>
        <p>The dance component of flamenco was represented both days by Pilar Rioja, who demonstrated a variety of flamenco styles, from the pictorial (she gave a vivid impression of the bullfighter in Turina's ''Oracion del Torero'' on Saturday) to the seductively abstract. She was at her most compelling in a traditional set on Sunday afternoon, with Jose Luis Negrete and Antonio Munoz accompanying her on guitars. Here, she was Ms. Linares's equal in her ability to convey in movement, as Ms. Linares did through vocal shading, the deep-seated, soulful pain that lies at the heart of so many traditional flamenco texts.</p>
        <p>The centerpiece of the Saturday concert brought together the currents of traditional and orchestrated flamenco that were under the microscope all weekend. Mr. Spano led a shapely performance of Falla's ''Amor Brujo,'' with Ms. Linares as the vocal soloist and sections danced by Ms. Rioja.</p>
        <p>A program of chamber pieces on Sunday afternoon was less consistently polished, but included spectacular readings of Infante's ''Variations on 'El Vito' '' and Falla's ''Fantasia Betica'' by Martin Soderberg, a pianist.</p>
        <p>MUSIC REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
