<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where Ladies Lunched, and Boys Grew Up</title>
    <meta content="29ESKI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/29/arts/29ESKI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1515401"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="MY MANHATTAN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eskin, Blake</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Urban Areas</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Police Academy</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Bayview Correctional Facility</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDC1E39F93AA1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="2562" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where Ladies Lunched, and Boys Grew Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Where Ladies Lunched, and Boys Grew Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BLAKE ESKIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Eskin, Blake</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Blake Eskin My Manhattan essay on spending most of his life on 20th Street; photos; chart; map (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On this island it is easy enough to find a native. Still, some people who moved here as adults treat me like a rare specimen when I tell them I grew up in Manhattan. Their voices will rise in pitch, and then the inevitable question, ''Where?'' For such newcomers, I have discovered, no answer is too specific: ''Downtown'' or ''the East Side'' will simply trigger another ''Where?'' It is not as if they want to send my parents a fruit basket, but I surrender to their curiosity: ''20th Street,'' I tell them, ''between Second and Third Avenues.''</p>
        <p>A few years ago I refined my answer, explaining that I grew up halfway between Gramercy Park and Stuyvesant Town. Though geographically vaguer, that response is an attempt to get at what I suspect is their underlying interest in the street map's socioeconomic overlay. Stuyvesant Town, gradually emerging from rent limits, has begun advertising its vacancies as luxury rentals, but even the extensive renovations under way can't alter its red-brick uniformity or roots. Built for the families of World War II veterans, it still stands in sharp contrast to the exclusive surroundings of the only private park in Manhattan, Gramercy Park, created by Samuel Ruggles in 1831.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>In less than two miles, 20th Street in Manhattan slices through Gramercy Park, the Ladies' Mile and Chelsea, and shows many faces.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On this island it is easy enough to find a native. Still, some people who moved here as adults treat me like a rare specimen when I tell them I grew up in Manhattan. Their voices will rise in pitch, and then the inevitable question, ''Where?'' For such newcomers, I have discovered, no answer is too specific: ''Downtown'' or ''the East Side'' will simply trigger another ''Where?'' It is not as if they want to send my parents a fruit basket, but I surrender to their curiosity: ''20th Street,'' I tell them, ''between Second and Third Avenues.''</p>
        <p>A few years ago I refined my answer, explaining that I grew up halfway between Gramercy Park and Stuyvesant Town. Though geographically vaguer, that response is an attempt to get at what I suspect is their underlying interest in the street map's socioeconomic overlay. Stuyvesant Town, gradually emerging from rent limits, has begun advertising its vacancies as luxury rentals, but even the extensive renovations under way can't alter its red-brick uniformity or roots. Built for the families of World War II veterans, it still stands in sharp contrast to the exclusive surroundings of the only private park in Manhattan, Gramercy Park, created by Samuel Ruggles in 1831.</p>
        <p>This in-between answer also allows me to avoid repeating myself when asked where I live now. Because when I'd say 20th Street again, they'd give me that gentle smile reserved for people in their 30's who have never left home.</p>
        <p>In fact, I spent a half-dozen years after college in the East Village, but in the fall of 1999 I moved into a fifth-floor walk-up at 222 West 20th Street, between Seventh and Eighth Avenues. This cramped three-room apartment, where I resided between bachelorhood and marriage, was a rent-stabilized compromise, arrived at after months of negotiating with the woman who is now my wife; though also a lifelong Manhattanite, she would have preferred to experiment with cohabitation in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>At first our location seemed to have no connection to the past; it is impossible, after all, to arrive in the realm of childhood after a 20-minute stroll. But just as last year's date finds its way onto a September check, every once in a while I put the old address on the top left corner of an envelope. And the constant, casual police presence from the station house of the 10th Precinct a few doors down at No. 230 has been oddly reassuring, less out of personal safety than familiarity.</p>
        <p>My old apartment building, where my parents still live, is next to the Police Academy, and the block and corner coffee shop would often fill up with dozens of recruits with their light blue shirts, dark pants and heavy black leather bags, nightsticks tucked under the handles. They had all gone on to tackle the real world, and some had been assigned for now to 20th Street. So, I suppose, had I.</p>
        <p>Now that Rachel and I have finally decided to follow most of our peers out to Brooklyn, my thoughts have frequently flowed east with the traffic. Instead of packing, I've walked back and forth, from Stuyvesant Cove Park, another promising stage in the revitalization of the East River waterfront, to the Bayview Correctional Facility, a medium-security women's prison abutting the West Side Highway. In less than two miles, 20th Street shows many faces. It slices through three historic districts -- Gramercy Park, the Ladies' Mile and Chelsea -- but for me the more prosaic stretches amid the remnants of 19th-century splendor can sometimes stir up more feeling.</p>
        <p>Windy and Desolate</p>
        <p>East of First Avenue, 20th Street runs two ways, serving as a conduit to the Franklin D. Roosevelt Drive, and a boundary between Stuyvesant Town and its slightly better-endowed younger sister to the north, Peter Cooper Village. Built by Metropolitan Life at the end of World War II, this dual attempt at urban renewal replaced part of the Gashouse District, a malodorous slum named for the storage tanks that dotted the riverbank.</p>
        <p>For these 80 developed acres, only 20th Street still respects the urban grid. Tree-lined, windy and desolate because stores are few and most buildings open onto internal paths, this stretch is best experienced from the window of the M23 crosstown bus, which, along with the rest of the westbound traffic, turns right at First Avenue.</p>
        <p>Keep walking, however, and you arrive in the institutional borderlands where I grew up. Though I attended neither of the schools between First and Second Avenues, I spent many afternoon hours outside, graduating from the swings of Public School 40 to the asphalt softball field and basketball courts outside Junior High School 104. Farther west, past Second Avenue, sirens from the emergency entrance of Cabrini Medical Center, named for St. Frances Xavier Cabrini, the Roman Catholic patron saint of immigrants, will interrupt any illusions of having arrived yet at Gramercy Park.</p>
        <p>On my way home from school I would sometimes linger by the door of the Police Academy gymnasium when it was propped open for ventilation and watch the officers-in-training do sit-ups or handcuff drills. Twice a day the recruits line up like soldiers in strict formation in the cavernous ground-floor courtyard -- a procedure called muster, I learned recently from Sgt. Ben Pape, a compact man with a mustache, who was assigned to show me around. I was glad to learn that the academy had not dispensed with my favorite moment of each term, which came when the recruits swarmed their instructors' cars in clusters of eight or a dozen, filling out practice tickets.</p>
        <p>The eight-story Police Academy, at No. 235, was built in 1962 of gray-speckled brick and black granite, making it feel a bit like an old high school, with tiled walls and displays of mementos from ethnic clubs and visiting delegations. It used to house the New York City Police Museum, now near the South Street Seaport, and I remember running around in the gym once or twice as a boy.</p>
        <p>Since Sept. 11, however, the Police Academy has become a more secure building. When the attack on the twin towers also destroyed the city's bunker in the sky at 7 World Trade Center, the Office of Emergency Management took over the academy's sixth-floor library, and Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani gave his first news conference that afternoon beneath the clock at the back of the academy's auditorium downstairs. Even after the command center shifted to a pier on the West Side, the block remained on high alert. Chain-link fence replaced the hedgerow, concrete barriers have been stationed on the sidewalk, and for months sharpshooters stood at the end of the street, blocking cars and pedestrians. I was unnerved the day my father had to come to the corner and vouch for me before I could step onto the block.</p>
        <p>Before settling down at No. 237, next to the Police Academy, my parents lived at 32 Gramercy Park, a high-rise on the corner of Third Avenue and 20th. I spent the first 18 months of my life there, but I can't recall much beyond the park privileges that outlasted our stay and an August 1989 steam-pipe explosion that spewed asbestos-laced mud everywhere, killing three people and blanching the beloved orchid collection of our friend Judith.</p>
        <p>Elevator Dreams</p>
        <p>The ornate brick-and-terra-cotta building at No. 34, however, holds a more cherished spot. A friend from Gramercy Park lived there, and until 1994 it had the city's last hydraulic elevator, powered by pressure from a water main. Though I never wanted to be a policeman when I grew up, I did dream of operating that elevator, which the doormen controlled by pulling on a velvet rope. My friend and I lost touch around the same time my parents gave up the key to the park in the late 1970's. I may envy those with access, but it still lifts my spirits to wander by, particularly in the spring, when the dogwoods and the tulips bloom.</p>
        <p>Twentieth Street has the distinction of having the homes of two men who sought the White House, one a Democrat who came close, one a Republican who got there. The National Arts Club, at 15 Gramercy Park South, was once the private residence of Samuel Tilden, the reform-minded governor who won the popular vote in 1876, but lost in the electoral college to Rutherford B. Hayes after disputes involving four states, including Florida. After the Civil War draft riots, Tilden had Calvert Vaux, one of the architects of Central Park, remodel the house, complete with a secret tunnel that would permit him to flee out the back should any subsequent violence break out on the block.</p>
        <p>And between Park Avenue and Broadway, at No. 28, the National Park Service gives tours of Theodore Roosevelt's birthplace -- or, rather, a replica of it. The original house, which the Roosevelts left when the future president was 14, was torn down in 1916, only to be recreated seven years later and furnished with his low velvet chair, an exercise bicycle from the White House and the horns of a kudu that Roosevelt shot on a hunting trip in Africa and presented to his attorney general.</p>
        <p>The Roosevelt birthplace finds itself on a block dense with fashionable restaurants, including Patria, La Pizza Fresca and Gramercy Tavern, whose sparkling rhubarb cocktail has inspired recent attempts to concoct a potable version at home. The Tavern's no-reservations front room has come to the rescue on more than one special occasion, and passing by always reminds me of an avuncular family friend who so enjoyed eating there that, when he died, his wife and children seriously considered furtively sprinkling his ashes outside.</p>
        <p>It is also on this block, between Park Avenue and Broadway, that the Ladies' Mile Historic District begins. Lord &amp; Taylor occupied the southwest corner of 20th and Broadway from the Civil War to World War I, and Stanford White designed buildings on two of the other three corners. I've watched the upscale retailers come back to Broadway -- Villeroy &amp; Boch now occupies the original Lord &amp; Taylor building at No. 901 Broadway. The professional photo shops west of Fifth Avenue, meanwhile, seem to be in retreat, and the bright glow outside the Limelight, the erstwhile nightclub in the former Church of the Holy Communion, has dimmed for good.</p>
        <p>Much changed in the four years that I lived on West 20th Street. The gas-station lot on the southeast corner of Seventh Avenue, like every other underutilized space in Chelsea, has been filled with a luxury high-rise. Next door to us, Other Books, which specialized in psychoanalytic titles and was gracious enough to accept our overnight mail, has been replaced by a spa, even as the Grandiosa, a dull tenement across the street at No. 219, endures, rusting metal door and all.</p>
        <p>The architectural charm of Chelsea does not become apparent again until Eighth Avenue, though before crossing the street I'd advise a left turn and a half-block detour downtown to Havana Chelsea, at 190 Eighth Avenue, for a $5 pressed Cuban sandwich at the lunch counter. Halfway to Ninth Avenue is St. Peter's Episcopal Church, which ministers to the neighborhood's gay residents, and nearby is a Gothic Revival building, No. 336, which has been transformed into the Atlantic Theater, the 182-seat main stage of the company devoted to the acting technique developed by its founders, David Mamet and William H. Macy. Renovations have kept the theater dark this summer; previews for Jez Butterworth's ''Night Heron'' begin on Sept. 16.</p>
        <p>A Serene Courtyard</p>
        <p>And between Ninth and Tenth, the General Theological Seminary, which Clement Clarke Moore carved out of his sprawling estate, occupies the full north side of the block. The serene, tree-lined courtyard of this Episcopal institution, with Gothic buildings from the 1830's, opens to the public for a few hours every afternoon. The block's literary pedigree goes beyond Moore, author of an early American Hebrew lexicon (though perhaps not of ''A Visit From St. Nicholas,'' the Christmas poem for which he is best known).</p>
        <p>The British novelist Hugh Walpole lived as a youth in a Greek Revival town house at No. 412 while his father taught dogmatic theology at the Episcopal seminary, and Jack Kerouac banged out ''On the Road'' in his mother's house at No. 454, near 10th Avenue. The liberal laptop policy of La Bergamote, a patisserie on the southwest corner of Ninth, where the French counterwomen are as dependably sour as the croissants are fresh, has attracted a new generation of writers; I did a little work on my book there.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, I wasn't on 20th Street long enough to acquire a taste for La Bergamote's signature confection, a pale, translucent candy infused with the oil of bergamot, a pear-shaped citrus fruit. To say that one of the shop's bergamotes de Nancy is like a cold cup of Earl Grey minus the tea doesn't suffice; it's more like eating perfume, which I have no intention of doing any time soon. Not to worry, though; my parents will provide plenty of reasons to stop back on 20th Street, as will friends in Peter Cooper Village and Chelsea.</p>
        <p>And though I'm trying to embrace Eastern Parkway as my new axis, you never know where the future will lead you. The third time, as they say, is the charm.</p>
        <p>Grand to Gritty  Sites in Blake Eskin's article on 20th Street in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>Attractions</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC THEATER COMPANY, 336 West 20th Street, (212) 645-8015. The 2003-4 season begins with Jez Butterworth's ''Night Heron''; previews begin on Sept. 17.</p>
        <p>GENERAL THEOLOGICAL SEMINARY, 175 Ninth Avenue, at 20th Street, (212) 243-5150. Hours: Courtyard open Monday through Friday, noon to 3 p.m.; Saturday, 11 a.m. to 3 p.m. Free.</p>
        <p>NATIONAL ARTS CLUB, 15 Gramercy Park South, (20th Street), (212) 475-3424. ''Counter Culture,'' a group show of artists affiliated with New York Central Art Supply, through Sept. 9. September exhibitions include ''Pastel Society of America,'' Sept. 3 to 28; ''Fred Rosenberg,'' Sept. 15 to 28; ''Deborah Chapin,'' Sept. 15 to 28; ''Simon Levenson,'' Sept. 22 to Oct. 6; visits by appointment. Beginning Sept. 15, a program of staged readings with lunch; tickets, $42; information, (212) 362-2560.</p>
        <p>POLICE ACADEMY, 235 East 20th Street, (212) 477-9727 Groups by appointment only.</p>
        <p>ST. PETER'S EPISCOPAL CHURCH, 346 West 20th Street, (212) 929-2390.</p>
        <p>THEODORE ROOSEVELT BIRTHPLACE, 28 East 20th Street, (212) 260-1616. Hours: Tuesday through Saturday, 9 a.m. to 5 p.m. Tours on the hour from 10 a.m. to 4. p.m. Admission: $3; free for children under 16.</p>
        <p>Dining</p>
        <p>GRAMERCY TAVERN, 42 East 20th Street, (212) 477-0777.</p>
        <p>HAVANA CHELSEA, 190 Eighth Avenue, between 19th and 20th Streets, (212) 243-9421.</p>
        <p>LA BERGAMOTE, 169 Ninth Avenue, at 20th Street, (212) 627-9010.</p>
        <p>LA PIZZA FRESCA, 31 East 20th Street, (212) 598-0141.</p>
        <p>PATRIA, 250 Park Avenue South, at 20th Street, (212) 777-6211.</p>
        <p>Shopping</p>
        <p>VILLEROY &amp; BOCH, 901 Broadway, at 20th Street, (212) 505-1090.</p>
        <p>MY MANHATTAN Blake Eskin is the author of ''A Life in Pieces: The Making and Unmaking of Binjamin Wilkomirski.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Blake Eskin is the author of ''A Life in Pieces: The Making and Unmaking of Binjamin Wilkomirski.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
