<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Programs for Gifted Favor Whites, Study Says</title>
    <meta content="18ACOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gifted Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Acorn (Advocacy Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sengupta, Somini</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hispanic-Americans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifted Students</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4D8113DF93BA25755C0A96E958260" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Programs for Gifted Favor Whites, Study Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SOMINI SENGUPTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sengupta, Somini</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Report by Acorn, advocacy group based in Brooklyn, finds that black and Hispanic parents continue to be less likely than white parents to be offered classroom tours and meetings with educators about programs for gifted children; says little has changed since similar survey was conducted in 1996 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Black and Hispanic parents continue to be less likely than white parents to be offered classroom tours and meetings with educators about programs for gifted children, according to a report released yesterday by Acorn, an advocacy group based in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>For the survey, modeled after housing discrimination tests, volunteers posed as parents and visited 26 schools during the last two months. The report says that little has changed since a similar survey was conducted two years ago. In that report, released in April 1996, the group accused the school system of denying black and Hispanic parents equal access to classes for the gifted by failing to provide information.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Black and Hispanic parents continue to be less likely than white parents to be offered classroom tours and meetings with educators about programs for gifted children, according to a report released yesterday by Acorn, an advocacy group based in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>For the survey, modeled after housing discrimination tests, volunteers posed as parents and visited 26 schools during the last two months. The report says that little has changed since a similar survey was conducted two years ago. In that report, released in April 1996, the group accused the school system of denying black and Hispanic parents equal access to classes for the gifted by failing to provide information.</p>
        <p>The group filed a complaint with the civil rights arm of the United States Department of Education. That and other complaints have prompted a Federal civil rights investigation into the city's programs for the gifted.</p>
        <p>Schools Chancellor Rudy Crew cited his own concerns last year about the possible exclusion of minority and immigrant children. He prohibited admissions and testing fees, which at least 2 of the city's 32 community school districts were charging. He also ordered school district officials to post information about their programs in each school and asked district superintendents to explain in writing what kinds of admissions criteria they used and why.</p>
        <p>Yesterday, in a brief statement, Dr. Crew said the latest Acorn study ''glosses over the substantial efforts'' he has undertaken in recent years. ''Since becoming Chancellor, I have continually called for greater publicizing of these programs,'' the statement said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Crew's spokesman, J. D. LaRock, said yesterday that most districts have moved away from relying solely on I.Q. tests and are looking at examples of students' work and at teacher referrals. Dr. Crew also pointed to the Math/Science Institute, a coaching program established last year to prepare more black and Hispanic students for the city's most competitive high schools.</p>
        <p>In an agreement with the civil rights office of the Department of Education, the school board has promised to post information about programs for the gifted at every school and district office.</p>
        <p>The Acorn report criticized the board for having failed to post the information. But city and Federal education officials maintained yesterday that the signs are not required to be posted until this fall.</p>
        <p>Representatives for Acorn, formally known as the Association of Community Organizations for Reform Now, said yesterday that they planned to file another complaint with the Federal agency.</p>
        <p>In their survey, the testers were instructed to try to talk to teachers and principals about classes for the gifted at each school and to request class tours. Only 12 percent of the African-American and Hispanic testers were able to talk with a teacher or another educator familiar with the school's gifted programs, compared with 45 percent of the non-Hispanic white testers, the report said. About 13 percent of the black and Hispanic testers were allowed to look in on a class, compared with 40 percent of the whites.</p>
        <p>The report also found that middle schools in which most of the students were black and Hispanic failed to provide advanced math and science classes required for entrance to the city's competitive high schools.  Moreover, the report said that in some federally financed programs that were intended to integrate schools with large minority concentrations, white students were overrepresented in the classes for the gifted.</p>
        <p>For instance, at Intermediate School 54 on the Upper West Side, the report said, white students made up only 13 percent of the student body but 40 percent of the gifted students, while black and Hispanic children,  more than 80 percent of the student body, made up roughly 55 percent of the gifted students.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
