<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PUBLIC LIVES</title>
    <meta content="18PUBL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025441"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Urban Justice Center</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bennett, Tony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barron, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Friedwald, Will</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Negron, Jon-Erik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Negron, Ray</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Randall, Tony</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Randall, Heather</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Good Life, The (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Public Lives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9803E2DA113DF93BA25755C0A96E958260" item-length="975" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PUBLIC LIVES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES BARRON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barron, James</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Tony Bennett is writing his autobiography, The Good Life, with co-author Will Friedwald; Jon-Erik Negron, 13-year-old son of former New York Yankees' batboy Ray Negron, was recently batboy for a day at Yankee Stadium; notes that Urban Justice Center will auction script for last episode of Seinfeld sitcom at upcoming benefit; Tony Randall's wife Heather gives birth to 7-pound, 2-ounce boy; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bennett's Ballad To a 'Good Life'</p>
        <p>You can learn a lot about yourself by reading your own autobiography.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bennett's Ballad To a 'Good Life'</p>
        <p>You can learn a lot about yourself by reading your own autobiography.</p>
        <p>''I said, 'Wait a minute, this is a good read,' '' declared TONY BENNETT, who left the writing to WILL FRIEDWALD, the author of ''Sinatra! The Song Is You: A Singer's Art'' (Da Capo, 1997).</p>
        <p>And that was only the opening of ''The Good Life,'' which Pocket Books is scheduled to publish in the fall. Mr. Friedwald is still working on the manuscript. ''He's now in the 1970's,'' Mr. Bennett said. ''He interviews almost everybody I've ever met.''</p>
        <p>And dredges up things that Mr. Bennett was too busy living his life to pay attention to; for example, that he received a Presidential citation in the 1950's. ''I was the G.I. who went the farthest with my education under the G.I. Bill of Rights,'' Mr. Bennett said. ''That just knocked me out.'' (He attended the American Theater Wing, later known as the Actors Studio. ''The best bel canto teacher, the best coach for teaching popular singing and jazz, and Stanislavsky's secretary, who performed with Stanislavsky, as an acting coach,'' Mr. Bennett said.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Bennett said that becoming a co-author was not his own idea. ''They called me,'' he said of the editors at Pocket Books. ''I'm at the right age. I'm going on 72. It's just naturally a time when you start reflecting, even though you don't like to retrogress. It's a time when you can see a story in all the different things that have happened.''</p>
        <p>Then the Boss, Always the Boss</p>
        <p>GEORGE STEINBRENNER saw five teen-agers spray-painting graffiti on Yankee Stadium.</p>
        <p>''I was the one with the can,'' RAY NEGRON recalled yesterday. ''He's telling me he's going to have me arrested, damaging Yankee Stadium, sacred ground, etc. They had a holding cell downstairs. He's telling me he's taking me there, a little police station. I'm begging him to give me a chance. He asks me, why should I give me a chance? I said, 'Because my mother's going to kill me.' He makes a quick about-face. He takes me to the Yankee clubhouse. The door opens up, he pushes me in and says, 'Give this guy a uniform. He's got damage he's got to work for.' ''</p>
        <p>That was 25 years ago. Mr. Negron was a batboy for a couple of seasons, then played with the Pittsburgh Pirates organization. Later, he returned to the Yankees, working with REGGIE JACKSON and, more recently, DWIGHT GOODEN. He left the Yankees in January to work for the Cleveland Indians.</p>
        <p>But he still has the boss's telephone number, which is how Mr. Negron's 13-year-old son, JON-ERIK, came to be a batboy for a day at Yankee Stadium last Sunday.</p>
        <p>''He did great,'' Mr. Negron said. ''People love to trash George. But think about it: That was a million-to-one shot that George Steinbrenner was going to catch me. I hope this doesn't start a whole flurry of kids doing graffiti at Yankee Stadium. Look out. People don't realize George was a track star in school.''</p>
        <p>'Seinfeld' and Ford Benefit Charities</p>
        <p>Old ''Seinfeld'' scripts keep surfacing. The Urban Justice Center, a nonprofit advocacy organization for the homeless, said it would auction a script for the last episode of the long-running sitcom at a benefit next week. The center got the script from one of its directors, PHYLLIS LOUIS-DREYFUS, the stepmother of JULIA LOUIS-DREYFUS, who played Elaine on the show. ''It has a silver cover, very fancy,'' said ANN VERMES, the center's director of development. ''I'm guarding it with my life.'' A script from the final episode of the show about nothing is worth something: Ms. Vermes said she had read on the Internet that a similar script sold for $9,100 on the night the final episode was broadcast last month. . . . ANNE FORD, a daughter of Henry Ford II and a great-granddaughter of the founder of the Ford Motor Company, is pledging $1 million to the National Center for Learning Disabilities, a Manhattan group of which she is chairwoman. Her commitment is personal: her daughter, ALLEGRA FORD, was diagnosed with severe learning disabilities 20 years ago. ''I determined, back when my daughter was very young,'' she said, ''that I must help all those parents like me, who feel helpless in a world where misunderstandings about learning disabilities can devastate you. Parents still feel uncomfortable about it.''</p>
        <p>Another Randall At Center Stage</p>
        <p>TONY RANDALL got his wish.</p>
        <p>Last week, his public relations agency sent out faxes saying that Mr. Randall, 78, was ''pacing with anxiety.'' His wife, Heather, 28, was pregnant, and Mr. Randall hoped the baby would be born on a Monday, ''because in his 60 years onstage, Tony Randall has never missed a performance.''</p>
        <p>As if on cue, JEFFERSON SALVINI RANDALL was born at Beth-Israel Hospital on Monday, Mr. Randall's day off from ''The Sunshine Boys'' with JACK KLUGMAN at the Lyceum Theater. The 7-pound, 2-ounce boy is the second child for the Randalls.</p>
        <p>''Who could write such a story?'' Mr. Randall said yesterday. ''I always thought my father was too old to have children. I guess it's repeating family history. I think my father was in his 60's when we were born.''</p>
        <p>The baby was named for two 19th-century performers. ''One was a comedian, one was a tragedian,'' Mr. Randall said. ''He'll be the master of them all.''</p>
        <p>JAMES BARRON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
