<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public Eye; More Than Just Money</title>
    <meta content="18EYE.$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025376"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Karrie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E3D8103DF93BA25755C0A96E958260" item-length="798" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public Eye; More Than Just Money</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Karrie Jacobs</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Karrie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Design of new euro banknotes, which will replace currencies of most European nations by 2002, is ecumenical but dull; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ABOUT a month ago, as preparations began for printing the 10 billion new euro banknotes that will replace the currencies of most European nations by 2002, a French anti-counterfeiting hologram vanished. The disappearance, which could prompt changes in the design,  occurred on a flight from France to Germany, where it was to be tested by a  printer in Nuremberg. Officials speculated that it had been stolen by well-informed thieves who understood what the device was.</p>
        <p>An alternative theory --  totally unofficial -- is that the hologram was snatched by an unhappy esthete who understands the damage the euro will do to the continent's reputation as a place where the design of everyday things matters.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ABOUT a month ago, as preparations began for printing the 10 billion new euro banknotes that will replace the currencies of most European nations by 2002, a French anti-counterfeiting hologram vanished. The disappearance, which could prompt changes in the design,  occurred on a flight from France to Germany, where it was to be tested by a  printer in Nuremberg. Officials speculated that it had been stolen by well-informed thieves who understood what the device was.</p>
        <p>An alternative theory --  totally unofficial -- is that the hologram was snatched by an unhappy esthete who understands the damage the euro will do to the continent's reputation as a place where the design of everyday things matters.</p>
        <p>The seven euro banknotes created by Robert Kalina, a designer for the Austrian Central Bank, were selected in a 1996 competition in which  entrants from all over the continent were asked to depict the ''ages and styles of Europe.'' Mr. Kalina took those instructions to heart and fashioned a veritable art history lesson with textbook examples of the Romanesque, the Gothic, the Baroque and the Modern. The bridges and windows pictured are deliberately detached from any particular place or building, so images of structures that look very familiar, but that you cannot quite place, are shown on banknotes, which are redolent of the Deutsche mark, the Dutch guilder or the Swedish krona, but are less . . . well, specific. The euros depict Europe as you might see it on a seven-countries-in-seven-days bus tour, a swirl of landmarks devoid of culture or context.</p>
        <p>Obviously, the aim was to avoid glorifying or insulting anyone. Unfortunately, the banknotes, in striving for the ecumenical look, make Europe  seem a very dull place, more homogenous, even, than the United States.</p>
        <p>In an economic analysis of the euro, attention is generally focused on the Germans and the almighty mark or the Italians and the shrinking lira, but from a graphic design standpoint, the most significant event in the change-over is the loss of the Dutch guilder. While the guilder is not among the world's powerhouse currencies, the Netherlands Bank produces money that is so innovative -- and lovely -- that it should have been the model for the euro.</p>
        <p>From the mid-1960's to the mid-1980's, a graphic designer named R. D. E. Oxenaar applied a personal esthetic to his nation's currency, and in doing so demonstrated that the specific could be universal. In his designs, Mr. Oxenaar used sunflowers, lighthouses and birds and surrounded them with a kaleidoscopic mix of patterns that please the eye and protect the money from counterfeiting. The Oxenaar tradition was carried forward by a designer of television graphics, Jaap Drupsteen, who created a new series of guilder notes covered with vivid, eye-catching motifs as hypnotic as the drawings of M. C. Escher.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Oxenaar and Mr. Drupsteen were unsuccessful entrants in the competition to design the euro. For that reason, Mr. Drupsteen is reluctant to give his opinion on the new notes, but Mr. Oxenaar, now retired, readily offers an assessment: ''Really miserable.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Oxenaar mentioned that each competitor was sent a package of ''a safe range of historical'' images chosen by art historians, ''a kind of European salad.''</p>
        <p>''I threw them all in the dust bin,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Clearly, Mr. Kalina did not.</p>
        <p>It was a ''lost chance to do something interesting,'' said Lo Breier, a partner in the graphic design and advertising agency Buro X, based in Vienna and Hamburg. Mr. Breier, an Austrian, says the competition should have been a chance to reflect on what being European means.</p>
        <p>Mr. Breier was one of a handful of designers invited by Der Spiegel to perform an unauthorized redesign of the euro coins. The coins show maps of the continent (sans the two non-members Switzerland and Norway). Each  member mints its own euro coins and can put whatever it chooses on the flip side. The German coins have the Brandenburg Gate and an updated version of their federal eagle. The editors of Der Spiegel, dismayed by the predictability, asked Mr. Breier and three others for alterations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Breier recommended drilling two holes in the coins so they could double as buttons, a way to give the coins practical value in case they turn out to be worthless.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
