<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At a Tribute to Herb Ellis, A Contrast With Old Heroes</title>
    <meta content="18ELLI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1025390"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="JAZZ FESTIVAL REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Jvc Jazz Festival</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellis, Herb</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ratliff, Ben</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews/Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Jazz</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980618T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EFD7103DF93BA25755C0A96E958260" item-length="479" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At a Tribute to Herb Ellis, A Contrast With Old Heroes</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN RATLIFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ratliff, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Ratliff reviews JVC Jazz Festival tribute to jazz guitarist Herb Ellis at Kaye Playhouse (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Postwar guitarist-heroes in jazz, those following Wes Montgomery, Joe Pass and Herb Ellis, are unostentatious form-followers. Their Queen's English is a language of quiet, rapid, single-note lines in a watery tone, and two baseball teams full of them played at the Kaye Playhouse during a JVC Jazz Festival tribute to Mr. Ellis on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Even for guitar freaks, it was a long show -- three and a quarter hours -- and performances eventually had to be cut short. Being reduced to a one-song walk-on prompted one musician, Joe Diorio, to turn confessional. ''I never really wanted to be in show business,'' he lamented. ''I don't have the nerves for it. I always just wanted to paint pictures.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Postwar guitarist-heroes in jazz, those following Wes Montgomery, Joe Pass and Herb Ellis, are unostentatious form-followers. Their Queen's English is a language of quiet, rapid, single-note lines in a watery tone, and two baseball teams full of them played at the Kaye Playhouse during a JVC Jazz Festival tribute to Mr. Ellis on Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>Even for guitar freaks, it was a long show -- three and a quarter hours -- and performances eventually had to be cut short. Being reduced to a one-song walk-on prompted one musician, Joe Diorio, to turn confessional. ''I never really wanted to be in show business,'' he lamented. ''I don't have the nerves for it. I always just wanted to paint pictures.''</p>
        <p>From the outside, most of the music had little to do with Mr. Ellis, who is most famous for his role in the Oscar Peterson Trio of the mid-1950's. But there was some good music. Ron Affif, the youngest of the group, was smartly put first: he set an excitement level with Earl May on bass and Winard Harper on drums that took some time to subside. He's a driving, intense player, and he jumped into the maw of rhythm right after his themes. On ''Cheek to Cheek,'' he first phrased slow and dreamily, then tightened up and focused his notes into little blades; Mr. Harper responded with cracking snare-drum beats and hard, dampened crashes of his cymbal.</p>
        <p>Gene Bertoncini played a solo ''Body and Soul'' on his nylon-stringed guitar that folded strange, upside-down chords into the patterns. Andy Summers, once of the Police, timidly played a few standards, his guitar treated with effects and his rhythms blunt. When Mr. Ellis came out at the end of the first half to play with two other guitarists, Charlie Byrd and Mundell Lowe, he sounded gutbucket soulful by comparison with much that had gone before. He used bent notes and provocative silences for syncopated effects and avoided single-string soloing; his ideas had rhythmic tooth to them.</p>
        <p>In the second half Martin Taylor, a Scottish guitarist more in line with Chet Atkins than with Wes Montgomery, has a tone as pure as water. His bottom-string notes purred sensually where his colleagues' were inky smudges. In ''I Got Rhythm,'' he brought the crowd to its feet by playing a walking eighth-note bass line and the melody chords simultaneously at great speed. Mr. Diorio was excellent in the opposite direction, a subtle weaver of great blanketing harmonic ideas without the overt, flamelike technique. Finally, Jack Wilkins and Jimmy Bruno improvised fast counterpoint together in ''All the Things You Are,'' and then Mr. Ellis came out again to join them, his economy and soul once more shining through.</p>
        <p>JAZZ FESTIVAL REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
