<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Italian Mainstays With Unexpected Touches</title>
    <meta content="26ctdine1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/26/travel/26ctdine1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1749922"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="DINING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">cantina sforza (westport, conn, restaurant)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brooks, Patricia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Connecticut</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02EEDE1430F935A15750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Italian Mainstays With Unexpected Touches</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Italian Mainstays With Unexpected Touches</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brooks, Patricia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Patricia Brooks reviews Cantina Sforza restaurant in Westport, Conn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Connecticut diner's appetite for Italian food is seemingly insatiable. Counting on this is Cantina Sforza, a recent arrival on the Post Road in Westport near the Norwalk line. Its older sibling, Via Sforza, is a few blocks southwest on the same road in Norwalk.</p>
        <p>The specialty at this attractive newcomer is northern Italian fare and the kitchen, on my visits, proved itself capable of dishing up any number of tantalizing examples. While some restaurants list every ingredient in a dish to ''romanticize'' it, Cantina Sforza takes another direction.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Connecticut diner's appetite for Italian food is seemingly insatiable. Counting on this is Cantina Sforza, a recent arrival on the Post Road in Westport near the Norwalk line. Its older sibling, Via Sforza, is a few blocks southwest on the same road in Norwalk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Connecticut diner's appetite for Italian food is seemingly insatiable. Counting on this is Cantina Sforza, a recent arrival on the Post Road in Westport near the Norwalk line. Its older sibling, Via Sforza, is a few blocks southwest on the same road in Norwalk.</p>
        <p>The specialty at this attractive newcomer is northern Italian fare and the kitchen, on my visits, proved itself capable of dishing up any number of tantalizing examples. While some restaurants list every ingredient in a dish to ''romanticize'' it, Cantina Sforza takes another direction.</p>
        <p>In an order of pappardelle with pancetta in a luscious creamy goat cheese sauce, I detected bits of something else: cooked chestnuts. Could it be? I inquired. Yes, the waiter said, after consulting with the chef. Imagine! An ingredient as intriguing and rich as marron in a dish, and it isn't even mentioned. I was impressed.</p>
        <p>So many dishes are equally impressive, beginning with a rich and robust appetizer of polenta Fiorentina -- soft polenta with duck sausage and forest mushrooms in a light tomato sauce, topped with grana Padano cheese.</p>
        <p>Fried calamari's light crust of Arborio rice flour and semolina gave it a crunch and flavor different from the usual fried calamari. The tomato dip, with red-hot pepper seeds on top, added freshness to an old favorite.</p>
        <p>Even a menu cliché like vongole casino had verve. Six clams, baked in their shells in a bath of garlic, butter, lemon and roasted pepper, were blanketed with crisply fried pancetta. And tri-colori salad, another old-timer, was a lively mix of arugula, radicchio and endive, tossed with toasted walnut halves, Gorgonzola and pear slices, in a light truffle vinaigrette.</p>
        <p>Most entrees, which came with a side dish of snow peas and a small roasted potato ''boat,'' were just as ingratiating. Among them, veal Marsala, with forest mushrooms in a subtle Marsala sauce, and veal scalloppine Pepe Sforza were notable for their fine quality, tender veal. The Pepe Sforza, in a port wine sauce, topped with spinach, bresaola and Gorgonzola, was especially delectable.</p>
        <p>Don't overlook the pasta dishes. A second pappardelle pasta, with duck sausage caressed by a cream-rich truffle and grappa sauce, was memorable.</p>
        <p>My only disappointment was one of the wood-roasted pizzas: the vegetariana. While its toppings of diced fresh tomatoes, fresh asparagus bits, portobello mushrooms and goat cheese were first rate, the thin crust had no flavor. To add to my disappointment, it arrived cold. Our waiter was accommodating in returning it for reheating, but unfortunately, that didn't improve the crust.</p>
        <p>Desserts were appealing, with one exception. The tiramisù was a flawless blend of espresso, Marsala wine and mascarpone mousse, elegant and satisfying. Almost as tasty was the panna cotta with a top layer of rich chocolate ganache. Torta al cioccolato was decadent dark chocolate, and the few gelatos on the menu had the intensity of flavor one expects of good gelato (especially the espresso flavor). Only the torta di formaggio dolce (Italian cheesecake) was disappointing. Served in a round pudding bowl, the dessert was more of an extremely dense pudding than a cake. And as such it was bland and boring.</p>
        <p>Cantina Sforza is as serious about its wines as its menu. The well-selected list includes a variety of wines from several countries, including Italy. There are also California wines. A 2003 David Bruce pinot noir from the Santa Clara mountains was an expansive, glowing companion to our many diverse courses.</p>
        <p>In making reservations, if you would like to feel transported to Italy, request the stone-walled cellar room. It is in the rear of the main dining room, but feels like a wine cellar (except it isn't cold). It is quiet, cozy and the next best thing to being tucked into the wine cellar of a charming Tuscan inn.</p>
        <p>Cantina Sforza</p>
        <p>243 Post Road West, Westport  (203) 454-4444</p>
        <p>Very Good</p>
        <p>Atmosphere -- Handsome free-standing brick-and-fieldstone building, with a dining room with saffron stucco walls hung with colorful Italian plates, evocative of an Italian trattoria; in the entrance a bar with a few tables and a wood-burning pizza oven.</p>
        <p>Noise Level -- Acceptable.</p>
        <p>Service -- Friendly and professional, with a few misses (no table clearing and crumbing before dessert).</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes -- Fried calamari, vongole casino, tri-colori salad, wild mushroom and carmelized onion soup, polenta Fiorentina, veal Marsala, pappardelle della Cantina, pappardelle with pancetta, gamberoni ripieni, panna cotta, tiramisù.</p>
        <p>Price range -- Lunch: appetizers $6 to $10, entrees $12 to 18; dinner: appetizers $7 to $11, entrees $16 to $30, desserts $5 to $8.</p>
        <p>Credit cards -- American Express, MasterCard, Visa.</p>
        <p>Hours -- Lunch noon to 3 p.m. Tuesday to Friday; Dinner: 5 to 10 p.m. Tuesday to Friday, 5 to 10:30 p.m. Saturday; 2 to 9:30 p.m. Sunday. Closed Monday.</p>
        <p>Reservations -- Accepted, recommended on weekends.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility -- Street level; restrooms the same.</p>
        <p>Reviewed by The Times -- March 26, 2006.</p>
        <p>The Ratings -- Excellent. Very Good. Good. Satisfactory. Poor. Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction primarily to food, with ambience and service taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
