<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rutgers Takes On Tennessee. So Soon?</title>
    <meta content="26rutgers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1749939"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL: CLEVELAND REGIONAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ncaa Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Tennessee</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Litsky, Frank</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060326T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E4DD1430F935A15750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="636" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rutgers Takes On Tennessee. So Soon?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANK LITSKY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Litsky, Frank</byline>
      <dateline>CLEVELAND, March 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rutgers University women's basketball team prepares to face Tennessee University in NCAA tournament Round of 16 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>C. Vivian Stringer is angry and Pat Summitt is not exactly happy. And they're not going to take it anymore. Or at least, they are trying to make sure they won't have to.</p>
        <p>Those two are Hall of Fame women's basketball coaches, Stringer at Rutgers and Summitt at Tennessee. When the N.C.A.A. tournament's Cleveland Regional begins Sunday, these old friends will see their teams bump heads. Too soon, they said, at separate news conferences Saturday. Too illogical. Too bad.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>C. Vivian Stringer is angry and Pat Summitt is not exactly happy. And they're not going to take it anymore. Or at least, they are trying to make sure they won't have to.</p>
        <p>Those two are Hall of Fame women's basketball coaches, Stringer at Rutgers and Summitt at Tennessee. When the N.C.A.A. tournament's Cleveland Regional begins Sunday, these old friends will see their teams bump heads. Too soon, they said, at separate news conferences Saturday. Too illogical. Too bad.</p>
        <p>In this regional, North Carolina (31-1), Tennessee (30-4) and Rutgers (27-4) are seeded one, two and three. This is easily the most loaded of the four regionals. Summitt said she thought Tennessee should have been seeded No. 1 somewhere. Stringer said her team should not be meeting a power like Tennessee as early as the Round of 16.</p>
        <p>''I have to laugh,'' said Stringer, who was smiling but not laughing. ''I could guess that was going to happen. It didn't surprise me, but it was disappointing. I don't know what anybody was looking at. Tennessee is one of the best defensive teams in the country. So are we. North Carolina is the best offensive team in the country.''</p>
        <p>The seeding for the 64 tournament teams was done by a committee of athletic directors and other college officials. Stringer said she and Summitt and Coach Sylvia Hatchell of North Carolina had talked about the seeding situation here.</p>
        <p>''We want to make it better for other schools in the future,'' Stringer said. ''People didn't do this intentionally, but the whole system has to be evaluated.''</p>
        <p>Summitt, who has won six national championships, was more philosophical. ''You always think you are in the toughest regional,'' she said. ''Is it good that this one is so strong? It's good for you.''</p>
        <p>Shanna Zolman, Tennessee's senior point guard, seemed to have command of the situation. ''At first, we felt disappointed,'' she said, ''but we're trying to channel our anger. I've never played with this much talent in a regional.''</p>
        <p>The reality is that the team that wins the tournament must beat six opponents over three weeks. As Cappie Pondexter, the star point guard for Rutgers, said, ''it doesn't matter who you play; you just have to take on the challenge.''</p>
        <p>Pondexter, a 5-foot-9 senior, poses the biggest challenge to Tennessee. Candace Parker, Tennessee's 6-4 freshman wonder, is the one Rutgers must stop. In a sport in which women's dunks used to come a decade apart, Parker dunked twice against Army in the first round last weekend. Summitt seemed relieved, saying: ''I'm glad to get it over with. I've seen her do it in practice every day. It is not a pressure issue.''</p>
        <p>Rutgers is not saying how it will try to stop Parker. Kia Vaughn, the 6-4 freshman center, will surely be part of the plan, but the main defender may be Essence Carson, a 6-foot sophomore who plays physically.</p>
        <p>Parker, ever candid, did not seem concerned. ''We have so many weapons,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Rutgers has only one main weapon: Pondexter. Summitt said she was working on a plan to contain her.</p>
        <p>''She is the heartbeat of their game,'' Summitt said. ''She's going to dictate the tempo. She makes the big shot. She defends and she anticipates. You're not going to stop her, but hopefully you'll contain her.''</p>
        <p>How do you that?</p>
        <p>''You've got to mix it up,'' Summitt said. ''I'm not going to give you our game plan or tell you who will guard her, but I'll tell you this: I won't be guarding her.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>The Round of 16 began Saturday with two games in Albuquerque and two in San Antonio. It continues Sunday with two games in Bridgeport, Conn., and the two in Cleveland: Tennessee against Rutgers and North Carolina against No. 4 Purdue (26-6).</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL: CLEVELAND REGIONAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
