<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Racist and Killer Or Just Misunderstood?</title>
    <meta content="11CHAM$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="26" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="FILM REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="882507"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="FILM REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grisham, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hackman, Gene</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunaway, Faye</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Donnell, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Foley, James</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Maslin, Janet</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Chamber, The (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E1D9123EF932A25753C1A960958260" item-length="660" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Racist and Killer Or Just Misunderstood?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JANET MASLIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Maslin, Janet</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Janet Maslin reviews film The Chamber, directed by James Foley and based on John Grisham novel; Gene Hackman, Chris O'Donnell and Faye Dunaway co-star; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Timing does no favors for ''The Chamber,'' the John Grisham death row drama that arrives on the heels of a better death row film (''Dead Man Walking'') and a better Grisham adaptation (''A Time to Kill''). But this film's also-ran aspects are partly offset by Gene Hackman's superlative performance as a wily old racist whose grandson is determined to save him from execution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hackman plays Sam Cayhall of the Ku Klux Klan, sentenced to death for a Mississippi bombing that killed the two young sons of a Jewish civil rights lawyer. When confronted about this by his nice young grandson, Adam Hall (the family name has been changed to escape Sam's ignominy), Sam proudly spouts the same racist and anti-Semitic slurs that got him into trouble in the first place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Timing does no favors for ''The Chamber,'' the John Grisham death row drama that arrives on the heels of a better death row film (''Dead Man Walking'') and a better Grisham adaptation (''A Time to Kill''). But this film's also-ran aspects are partly offset by Gene Hackman's superlative performance as a wily old racist whose grandson is determined to save him from execution.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hackman plays Sam Cayhall of the Ku Klux Klan, sentenced to death for a Mississippi bombing that killed the two young sons of a Jewish civil rights lawyer. When confronted about this by his nice young grandson, Adam Hall (the family name has been changed to escape Sam's ignominy), Sam proudly spouts the same racist and anti-Semitic slurs that got him into trouble in the first place.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hackman makes himself startlingly hateful, then does an expert job of evolving, however predictably, into a more palatable character. During one long monologue describing the workings of the gas chamber, as he lets Sam's bravado give way to quiet fear, Mr. Hackman demonstrates beautifully understated acting without a trace of the self-congratulatory. Condemned killers like Sam may not go to heaven, but they do turn up at the Oscar show.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hackman's co-star is Chris O'Donnell as Adam, and comparisons with other films become inevitable at this point. Mr. O'Donnell is capable and photogenic, but he makes a blandly lightweight lawyer and doesn't match the swagger of Matthew McConnaughey in ''A Time to Kill.''</p>
        <p>And ''The Chamber,'' the more recent of the two Grisham books, is by far the more padded and less credible. While the screenwriters, William Goldman and Chris Reese, dispense with subplots and diversionary tactics that fill out the book, they don't do much about the story's convenient coincidences or its suggestion that a murderous third-generation Klansman is not necessarily evil. Maybe he's just misunderstood.</p>
        <p>James Foley's brand of Grisham is more brittle than Joel Schumacher's (''The Client'' and ''A Time To Kill''), with more overripe hints of a Southern gothic style. When Adam's aunt Lee (Faye Dunaway, looking extravagantly rejuvenated) recalls a traumatic incident, Mr. Foley does more than let her tell the story; he brings Lee to the scene of the crime and throws in impassioned flashbacks, too. As the date of Sam's planned execution draws closer, even the placards outside the penitentiary reflect the film's overheated tone. Among the signs: ''Suck gas, evildoer'' and ''Roast in Peace.''</p>
        <p>As ''A Time to Kill'' did, ''The Chamber'' brings on a babe as the hero's not-quite-romantic interest, for reasons that have practically nothing to do with advancing the plot. So Lela Rochon flounces prettily but gratuitously through the tacked-on role of the governor's legal aide. In a film whose women are mostly window dressing, there's a brief but solid performance from Millie Perkins as the dead boys' mother, still grieving nearly 30 years after the crime.</p>
        <p>''The Chamber'' is rated R (Under 17 requires accompanying parent or adult guardian). It includes racist slurs and profanity, along with several abrupt, violent scenes.</p>
        <p>THE CHAMBER</p>
        <p>Directed by James Foley; written by William Goldman and Chris Reese, based on the novel by John Grisham; director of photography, Ian Baker; edited by Mark Warner; music by Carter Burwell; production designer, David Brisbin; produced by John Davis, Brian Grazer and Ron Howard; released by Universal Pictures. Running time: 110 minutes. This film is rated R.</p>
        <p>WITH: Chris O'Donnell (Adam Hall), Gene Hackman (Sam Cayhall), Faye Dunaway (Lee Bowen), Lela Rochon (Nora Stark) and Millie Perkins (Ruth Kramer).</p>
        <p>FILM REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
