<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Aetna to Cut 4,400 More Jobs As It Shifts to Managed Care</title>
    <meta content="11INSU$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="882612"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Health Maintenance Organizations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Aetna Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">US Healthcare</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freudenheim, Milt</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Health Insurance and Managed Care</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E4D8133EF932A25753C1A960958260" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Aetna to Cut 4,400 More Jobs As It Shifts to Managed Care</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MILT FREUDENHEIM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freudenheim, Milt</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Aetna Inc, in one of largest job cutbacks in health care and insurance industries, says that it will reduce its work force by 4,400 jobs, or 13 percent of its 33,700 employees; says it will lay off 8,200, but some of those people will be retrained for 3,800 new positions that it will create; decision brings number of overall layoffs planned by Aetna this year to over 10,800; about 1,000 jobs will be cut in Connecticut; Aetna's downsizing reflects company's struggle to transform itself from provider of traditional insurance and financial services into leader in managed health care; Aetna announced in April that it would spend $8.18 billion to acquire US Healthcare (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Aetna Inc., in one of the largest job cutbacks in the health care and insurance industries, said yesterday that it would reduce its work force by 4,400 jobs, or 13 percent of its 33,700 employees. It was Aetna's fourth big layoff announcement this year.</p>
        <p>The company, based in Hartford, said it would lay off a total of 8,200, but some of those people would be retrained for 3,800 new positions that it will create. The decision brought the number of overall layoffs planned by Aetna this year to more than 10,800. About 1,000 jobs will be cut in Connecticut.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Aetna Inc., in one of the largest job cutbacks in the health care and insurance industries, said yesterday that it would reduce its work force by 4,400 jobs, or 13 percent of its 33,700 employees. It was Aetna's fourth big layoff announcement this year.</p>
        <p>The company, based in Hartford, said it would lay off a total of 8,200, but some of those people would be retrained for 3,800 new positions that it will create. The decision brought the number of overall layoffs planned by Aetna this year to more than 10,800. About 1,000 jobs will be cut in Connecticut.</p>
        <p>Aetna's relentless downsizing -- exceeded this year only by AT&amp;T's announcement in January that it would cut 40,000 jobs -- reflects the company's struggle to transform itself from a provider of traditional insurance and financial services into a leader in managed health care.</p>
        <p>In April, Aetna announced that it would spend $8.18 billion to acquire U.S. Healthcare, a major health maintenance organization concentrated in New York, New Jersey and Pennsylvania. At that time, when many big corporations were being assailed politically and in the news media over a wave of downsizings, Aetna's chairman, Ronald E. Compton, suggested that the number of jobs lost in the merger would probably be minimal, though he allowed that ''as we streamline, there are bound to be some.''</p>
        <p>Yesterday, an Aetna spokeswoman, Joyce Oberdorf, said the employees to be laid off would be offered retraining and priority in the new hiring, but it was clear that most of the new jobs would be situated far from those being dropped.</p>
        <p>Mr. Compton said yesterday that the sweeping reorganization would help Aetna carve out a major role in the highly competitive world of managed health care -- at a time when all H.M.O.'s are under intense pressure to prevent costs from rising.</p>
        <p>''Over the long term,'' he said, ''we believe this growth will result in more job opportunities.''</p>
        <p>The job cuts include 7,500 in health care -- mainly from the Aetna side  -- and 700 in the life insurance, pensions and financial services unit, Aetna Retirement Services.</p>
        <p>The company said Aetna U.S. Healthcare, its health benefits subsidiary, would add 3,500 new positions, for a net reduction of 4,000. Retirement Services will add 300 new slots for a net loss of 400.</p>
        <p>In Connecticut, the 1,000 lost jobs will come on top of the elimination of 875 positions in Hartford and Middletown earlier this year. The rest of the cuts will be spread across the country in 43 offices that Aetna plans to combine in six regional centers and at roughly nine other locations.</p>
        <p>''Aetna paid a price far greater than most people would ever want to pay for U.S. Healthcare,'' said Mark Puccia, a managing director with Standard &amp; Poor's, the credit rating firm. ''Now they have to justify it. They have to look for cost reductions to get their earnings up.''</p>
        <p>The combination with U.S. Healthcare made Aetna the country's biggest medical benefits company, but analysts said the merger, completed in July, brought together two companies that had been far apart in methods and philosophy.</p>
        <p>''U.S. Healthcare had the best operating systems in the business,'' said Margo Vignola, a health care analyst with Merrill Lynch. ''The big question is whether these two organizations can be readily integrated.''</p>
        <p>U.S. Healthcare, which was known for its Norman Rockwell-style advertising, has long been seen within the health industry as one of the strongest practitioners of tough cost controls, paying doctors a fixed fee for each patient and relying on a computerized system that closely monitored the services provided by its doctors and hospitals. By contrast, Aetna's health care business was a vast paper-shuffling organization that consisted mostly of insuring traditional fee-for-service health care providers.</p>
        <p>The insurance industry, with its huge armies of white-collar workers, is in the midst of a major consolidation that has forced companies to eliminate tens of thousands of jobs. Hartford, one of the capitals of the insurance business, has been particularly hard hit.</p>
        <p>In some of the biggest insurance downsizings in the last three years, the CNA Corporation eliminated 6,000 jobs, Prudential cut 3,500 employees, Travelers laid off 3,300 and the Continental Corporation cut 2,000 positions, according to Challenger, Gray &amp; Christmas, an executive placement firm based in Chicago.</p>
        <p>Aetna has been struggling to reshape itself for the last four years. It eliminated 4,800 jobs in 1992 and 1993 and cut 4,000 more in 1994.</p>
        <p>Last year the company sold its property and casualty business, which had 11,000 employees, to Travelers for $4.1 billion. In addition to  475 headquarters jobs eliminated earlier this year as part of that deal, Aetna has also announced the demise of 1,700 jobs processing claims for the Federal Medicare insurance program, and 500 more in health technology.</p>
        <p>Aetna said yesterday that it would write off $307 million in after-tax earnings this year to cover the costs of the latest job cuts, including $167 million in payments to people leaving the company. They will get a severance package that includes a minimum of 13 weeks' pay for regular employees and 30 weeks for executives. Employees will also receive additional payments, depending on the number of the years they have worked at the company.</p>
        <p>Ms. Oberdorf, the Aetna spokeswoman, said the company did not expect to take any additional charges for restructuring moves ''in the foreseeable future.''</p>
        <p>In trading on the New York Stock Exchange, shares in Aetna declined 87.5 cents, closing at $66.875.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
