<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ford Places Top Designer On the Leadership Track</title>
    <meta content="11FORD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="882597"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bradsher, Keith</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nasser, Jacques A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hagenlocker, Edward E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E1D9133EF932A25753C1A960958260" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ford Places Top Designer On the Leadership Track</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bradsher, Keith</byline>
      <dateline>DEARBORN, Mich., Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ford Motor Co names Jacques A Nasser to head its North American and European automotive operations, clearing the way for Nasser to become Ford's top operating officer someday; Nasser, who had been group vice president in charge of vehicle development, will take rank of executive vice president when his promotion takes effect on Nov 1; Ford also announces that it is separating its many auto parts businesses from core automotive operations that Nasser will oversee; executive vice president Edward E Hagenlocker is named vice chairman with responsibility for overseeing new auto parts division; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company today named Jacques A. Nasser, 48, to head its North American and European automotive operations, clearing the way for the urbane car designer to become the auto maker's top operating officer someday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasser, who had been a group vice president in charge of vehicle development, will take the rank of executive vice president when his promotion takes effect on Nov. 1.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Ford Motor Company today named Jacques A. Nasser, 48, to head its North American and European automotive operations, clearing the way for the urbane car designer to become the auto maker's top operating officer someday.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasser, who had been a group vice president in charge of vehicle development, will take the rank of executive vice president when his promotion takes effect on Nov. 1.</p>
        <p>His rise through the ranks partly reflects Ford's growing emphasis on international experience. Born in a remote mountain village in Lebanon and raised in Australia, Mr. Nasser speaks several languages fluently and is a former chairman of Ford's European subsidiary and a former president of its Australian unit.</p>
        <p>While the current president of Ford's automotive operations, Edward E. Hagenlocker, has worked from an office at the company's headquarters here, Mr. Nasser will remain at Ford's sprawling vehicle development campus several miles away. Some senior marketing executives and other managers will also move there, a further indication of the powerful role that Mr. Nasser will now play at the No. 2 auto maker.</p>
        <p>Ford also announced today that it was separating its many auto parts businesses from the core automotive operations that Mr. Nasser will oversee. The new automotive products operations division has annual sales of $14.3 billion and 75,000 employees; its profitability was not disclosed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hagenlocker, a 56-year-old executive vice president, was named a vice chairman today with responsibility for overseeing the new auto parts division.</p>
        <p>Alex Trotman, Ford's 63-year-old chairman and chief executive, said at a news conference today at Ford's headquarters here that Mr. Hagenlocker would conduct a broad review of whether to sell or otherwise overhaul existing businesses and whether to invest in new auto parts operations, possibly through joint ventures.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview this afternoon, Mr. Trotman said that Mr. Hagenlocker and Mr. Nasser would both have a lot of responsibility in the coming years and declined to discuss who might eventually replace him. Auto analysts said that today's management move, while expected, gave Mr. Nasser the inside track to become the top operating officer at Ford.</p>
        <p>William Clay Ford Jr., 39, the chairman of the Ford board's finance committee, is considered the front-runner to be the next chairman, partly because the Ford family still controls 40 percent of the voting power at the company.</p>
        <p>Today's reshuffling of senior management ''does not necessarily determine who will be the next chairman, it identifies the next No. 1 operating person at Ford, Jacques Nasser,'' said Maryann N. Keller, an auto analyst with Furman Selz. ''The job is his to lose right now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Nasser, a favorite of the Ford family, has long been expected to go farther than Mr. Hagenlocker, a  physicist who does not seem as comfortable as Mr. Nasser at making speeches and other public appearances. While Mr. Hagenlocker has received some of the credit for the highly successful redesign last winter of the F-series pickup trucks, the nation's best-selling vehicle, he has also taken some of the blame for the less successful redesign last year of the Ford Taurus sedan.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trotman hinted today that he would be interested in staying on as chairman of Ford beyond his 65th birthday if the board will let him. ''You'd like to live to be 100 years old and work in the auto business, it's just not realistic,'' he said.</p>
        <p>If the automotive operations run into trouble, Mr. Nasser could easily run into competition for the top job.</p>
        <p>John M. Devine, the 52-year-old chief financial officer and a favorite of Wall Street because of his consistent candor, was also picked today to become an executive vice president. He gave up his responsibility over land development to Mr. Hagenlocker but kept his position as chief financial officer.</p>
        <p>W. Wayne Booker, the 62-year-old executive vice president who oversees Ford's operations in emerging markets, was also chosen today to become a vice chairman. But neither Mr. Hagenlocker nor Mr. Booker will become members of the board. All of the management moves are scheduled to take effect on Nov. 1.</p>
        <p>Mr. Trotman said that part of Mr. Hagenlocker's job would involve figuring out how to make use of Ford's new labor contract with the United Automobile Workers.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
