<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 AFGHAN FACTIONS SIGN PACT TO FIGHT NEW KABUL RULERS</title>
    <meta content="11AFGH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="882643"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Parwan Province (Afghanistan)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Taliban (Afghan Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Burns, John F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dostum, Abdul Rashid (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Massoud, Ahmad Shah</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Khalily, Abdul Karim</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shiite Muslims</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961011T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E1D7133EF932A25753C1A960958260" item-length="1655" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 AFGHAN FACTIONS SIGN PACT TO FIGHT NEW KABUL RULERS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Burns, John F</byline>
      <dateline>KHINJAN, Afghanistan, Oct. 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gen Abdul Rashid Dostum and Ahmad Shah Massoud, last two military commanders holding out against Muslim Government in Afghanistan, sign formal military alliance; they vow to set up non-fundamentalist government in nine northern provinces under their control; pact is also signed by Abdul Karim Khalily, leader of Shiite Muslim minority in Afghanistan; Government proclaimed by Taliban Islamic movement in Kabul controls all other 19 provinces, except part of Parwan Province that is held by Massoud forces; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The last two military commanders holding out against the new rigorously Muslim Government in Afghanistan forged a formal military alliance here today. They vowed to set up a non-fundamentalist government in the nine northern provinces under their control.</p>
        <p>Gen. Abdul Rashid Dostum and Ahmad Shah Massoud, military commander in the Government that fell when the Islamic movement called the Taliban captured Kabul two weeks ago, signed a document creating the new alliance. They met for the first time in three years, at an old Soviet guesthouse in the Hindu Kush mountains.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The last two military commanders holding out against the new rigorously Muslim Government in Afghanistan forged a formal military alliance here today. They vowed to set up a non-fundamentalist government in the nine northern provinces under their control.</p>
        <p>Gen. Abdul Rashid Dostum and Ahmad Shah Massoud, military commander in the Government that fell when the Islamic movement called the Taliban captured Kabul two weeks ago, signed a document creating the new alliance. They met for the first time in three years, at an old Soviet guesthouse in the Hindu Kush mountains.</p>
        <p>The pact was also signed by Abdul Karim Khalily, a leader of the Shiite Muslim minority in Afghanistan, whose forces control a 10th province.</p>
        <p>The Government proclaimed by the Taliban in Kabul, the capital, controls all the other 19 provinces,  except part of Parwan Province north of Kabul that is held by the  Massoud forces.</p>
        <p>But events today in the area immediately north of Kabul, where Taliban forces came under attack for the second time in three days, with dozens of Taliban casualties, underscored the uncertainties surrounding the Taliban's ability to consolidate power in Kabul.</p>
        <p>One of those waiting outside the guesthouse during the meeting was the Russian Consul General in Mazar-i-Sharif, Oleg Nevelayev, whose presence signaled the strong diplomatic support that General Dostum and Mr. Massoud have received from Russia.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nevelayev said Russia was determined to oppose the Taliban, whose control of Afghanistan he described as fraught with miseries for Afghans and for the country's neighbors. ''It will be worse than a second Iran,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Moscow has reacted with hostility to the prospect of Taliban rule close to Russia's southern borders. It has been joined in its support for the Taliban's opponents by India and Iran, whose Shiite Muslim leaders distrust the Sunni Muslim leadership of the Taliban.</p>
        <p>$(In Washington, the State Department's spokesman, Nicholas Burns, called on all sides in Afghanistan to stop fighting and seek a political solution. ''The United States will not support any one faction or group of factions against another,'' he said. ''We're neutral.''</p>
        <p>$(On the question of Russia's support, he said, ''We don't think any of Afghanistan's neighbors should intervene in this conflict to promote a continuation of the civil war.''$)</p>
        <p>Russian backing for the new alignment appeared to be reflected in some of the new equipment displayed at the Khinjan meeting by Dostum troops. In addition to what appeared to be brand-new trucks carrying antiaircraft guns to protect the meeting from possible Taliban air attacks, many of the Dostum fighters wore what appeared to be brand-new uniforms and boots of the kind worn by Soviet troops when they occupied Afghanistan in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>The alliance proclaimed at the meeting at Khinjan, 100 miles north of Kabul on the northern side of the Hindu Kush, opened a new chapter in the 18 years of war in Afghanistan.</p>
        <p>The alignment appeared to mean that the Taliban, instead of facing two enemy forces that have been divided, will now face a common front, controlling an area of tens of thousands of square miles, and united by their hostility toward the rigorous form of Islam that the Taliban have imposed in areas they control.</p>
        <p>The document signed here committed the three leaders to establishing, without any stated deadline, ''a permanent government'' for Afghanistan that will apparently be based, at least at first, at the north-central town of Mazar-i-Sharif, the military stronghold of General Dostum.</p>
        <p>The document also pledged the leaders to the formation of a Supreme Defense Council of Afghanistan, and bound all three groups, and any others that may join them, to come to the defense of each other if attacked by the Taliban. ''If any party continues to attack any of the signatories to this accord, the other signatories pledge themselves to come to the aid of the signatory under attack,'' the document said.</p>
        <p>The accord appeared to remove any doubt about the intentions of General Dostum, the former Communist who survived the collapse of the Soviet-installed Government in Kabul in 1992, becoming a powerful northern warlord in the civil war among rival Muslim guerrilla groups that followed.</p>
        <p>Taliban leaders had repeatedly appealed for General Dostum to remain neutral while they moved their troops against Mr. Massoud, one of the most formidable of the former guerrilla commanders, whose forces have retreated into the Panjshir Valley northeast of Kabul.</p>
        <p>But the alliance held out the possibility of something more threatening to the Taliban than a stiffening of Mr. Massoud's defenses against the onslaught in the Panjshir: the possibility of two Afghanistans.</p>
        <p>One of these would be the one controlled by the Taliban, where  stern decrees have spread a deepening chill, especially for women, who have been barred from working; for girls, who have been prohibited from  going to school, and for offenders against Islamic laws, who have been threatened with punishments that include stoning to death and amputation of hands and feet.</p>
        <p>The other would be the more moderate Muslim state in northern and central Afghanistan that seemed to be foreshadowed by the pact today.</p>
        <p>The three leaders who met here  represent three of the largest ethnic minorities in Afghanistan, the Hazara, Tajik and Uzbek groups, which  together account for about 5 million of the country's 16 million people.</p>
        <p>In General Dostum, an Uzbek, Mr. Massoud, a Tajik, and Mr. Khalily, a  Hazara, the new alliance has formidable military forces, and a territory, stretching from Faryab Province in the northwest to Badakhshan  Province in the northeast, and south to central province of Bamyan, that has a natural shield in the form of the Hindu Kush range. The mountains  rise above 16,000 feet and divide Taliban areas in the south from the alliance forces in the north.</p>
        <p>But even short of the consolidation of a new rival state, the Taliban were confronted after today's meeting by the prospect of far stiffer military resistance in their drive to control the parts of the country that have so far escaped their control.</p>
        <p>If the Taliban fail to break through in the Panjshir, and in their drive against General Dostum up the Salang Highway through the Hindu Kush, where their advance has stalled just as it has in the Panjshir, they could eventually face a counterattack on Kabul by the combined Dostum and Massoud forces.</p>
        <p>This would join the conventional military power of General Dostum's Soviet-trained forces and the guerrilla wiliness of the Massoud troops.</p>
        <p>Neither General Dostum nor Mr. Massoud responded directly when two Western reporters present at the Khinjan meeting asked whether they planned to mount a counterattack to take Kabul. ''We will decide that in the future,'' said Mr. Massoud, who appeared more subdued at the meeting than the bullish General Dostum.</p>
        <p>The two men had not met since 1993, when their forces, briefly united behind the first guerrilla-installed Government in Kabul, fell into enmity and fought a battle for control of the capital that killed tens of thousands of people and destroyed large parts of the city.</p>
        <p>The two opposition military commanders, and Mr. Khalily, the Shiite leader, whose forces are too small to have much bearing on the outcome of the war, met over bowls of raisins and grapes in a building beside the Salang Highway that was used as a guesthouse by Soviet engineers who built the highway in the 1960's. The Soviets maintained it during their  military occupation of Afghanistan in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>The two-hour meeting ran into the  twilight, with the document creating the new alliance finally being signed by the glow of a kerosene lamp.</p>
        <p>But the nervous arrangements for the meeting showed how fragile the new alliance could be. Officials for General Dostum and Mr. Massoud, who made the trip from the Panjshir in a military helicopter inherited years ago from the occupying Soviet forces, tried to keep the meeting secret, to the point of telling reporters to travel north to Mazar-i-Sharif to meet General Dostum.</p>
        <p>For the moment, the Taliban appeared preoccupied by the setbacks they have encountered in the south, close to Kabul.</p>
        <p>The Taliban thrust into the gorge that commands access to the Panjshir Valley, then stalled under a heavy Massoud counterattack earlier this week, and that blow has been followed by two more.</p>
        <p>The attack on Taliban forces before dawn today at the town of Bagram, 40 miles north of Kabul on the dusty plain that separates the southern flank of the Hindu Kush from the capital, followed an ambush by Massoud forces on Tuesday on Taliban forces pushing up the Salang Highway. Dozens of Taliban fighters died.</p>
        <p>What happened at Bagram was unclear, since Taliban roadblocks prevented Western reporters from reaching the area.</p>
        <p>Taliban officials in Kabul said there had been ''an uprising'' among local villagers, and some reports said the villagers had been armed only with old rifles.</p>
        <p>Other accounts said there had been a new ambush by Massoud forces. In either case, it seemed clear from reports of Taliban vehicles moving south to Kabul with dozens of new casualties, including many dead, that the Taliban had suffered yet another sharp blow.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
