<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Maximum Justice</title>
    <meta content="01ELLIST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="892757"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ellis, Joseph J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Smith, Jean Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">marshall, john</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">John Marshall: Definer of A Nation (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DEED8173DF932A35751C1A960958260" item-length="1452" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Maximum Justice</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Joseph J. Ellis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ellis, Joseph J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Joseph J Ellis reviews book John Marshall: Definer of a Nation by Jean Edward Smith; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>John Marshall</p>
        <p>Definer of a Nation.</p>
        <p>By Jean Edward Smith.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 736 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $35.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>John Marshall</p>
        <p>Definer of a Nation.</p>
        <p>By Jean Edward Smith.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 736 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Henry Holt &amp; Company. $35.</p>
        <p>Between 1801 and 1835, while five Presidents came and went, Chief Justice John Marshall came and stayed. ''He hit the Constitution much as the Lord hit the chaos,'' wrote one observer, ''at a time when everything needed creating.'' An essential feature of Marshall's genius, however, was to claim that he was not creating anything. As Lord Bryce put it, ''the Constitution seemed not so much to rise under his hands to full stature, as to be gradually unveiled by him till it stood revealed in the harmonious perfection of the form which its framers had designed.''</p>
        <p>More than anyone else, Marshall made the Constitution a binding contract among the American people rather than a compact among sovereign states. Almost single-handedly, he transformed the Supreme Court from the weakest and most problematic branch of the Federal Government to the Olympian presence we now take for granted. He was already a legend in his own time, and even the gods seemed to regret his passing: When he died in July 1835 and they rang the great Liberty Bell in Independence Hall in his honor, the bell cracked, never to ring again.</p>
        <p>A man of such stature might be expected to attract his full complement of biographers. Thomas Jefferson, Marshall's lifelong antagonist (Marshall called him ''the great Lama of the mountains''), is the subject of several hundred biographies. But the last serious study of Marshall's life is out of print and 80 years old. Now Jean Edward Smith has produced a wholly satisfying modern biography that immediately establishes itself as the authoritative life. Given the fact that Mr. Smith is neither a historian nor a constitutional scholar -- he teaches political science at the University of Toronto and his previous books have focused on 20th-century military topics -- the appearance of ''John Marshall'' is an unexpected event, as if Noah's ark suddenly floated ashore in Canada. But here it is.</p>
        <p>The great temptation presented by a life like Marshall's is to regard the pre-Court years as a mere prologue. Then, in the triumphant phase, those magisterial Marshall opinions come marching forward in stately procession -- Marbury v. Madison on judicial review, the Dartmouth case on the sanctity of contract, McCulloch v. Maryland on Federal sovereignty. The life, in effect, is subordinated to the law.</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith's approach is just the opposite. The law is subordinated to the life. The classic Court decisions are treated as the fulfillment of moral and political lessons that Marshall had internalized years earlier and that he derived more from experience than reading. As a result, some constitutional scholars are likely to be disappointed, since the exegesis of the landmark cases offered here is neither original nor aligned with the kind of precedent-seeking questions that preoccupy the legal profession. On the other hand, if you want a straightforward synthesis of the current scholarly wisdom on Marshall's judicial opinions rendered in clear English prose, which is, after all, in the spirit of Marshall's own judicial style, this is the place to find it.</p>
        <p>The story Mr. Smith tells in truly loving detail focuses on the experiences that made Marshall an ardent nationalist. It begins in the foothills of the Blue Ridge Mountains of Virginia in 1755, where Marshall grew up isolated from the tobacco-and-slaves culture of the Tidewater region. The seminal experience of his life was the American Revolution. Marshall led an elite company of backwoods riflemen through many of the major battles of the war and suffered through the winter at Valley Forge with George Washington, who became his lifelong hero. And much like Washington, he developed a deep distrust of the local and state governments that so often failed to provide promised support once the war moved beyond their own borders. As Marshall recalled, ''I was confirmed in the habit of considering America as my country and Congress as my government.'' His war experience forever inoculated Marshall against the Virginia-writ-large version of the nation that Jefferson embodied. This difference, plus Marshall's unspoken resentment toward Jefferson's avoidance of military service, laid the foundation for their mutual animosity.</p>
        <p>Throughout the 1780's and 1790's Marshall's political experience added further layers of confirmation over this nationalistic foundation. Like James Madison, Marshall was convinced by his service in the Virginia legislature that the provincialism of the state governments required the discipline of Federal law if the American republic was to endure. In the 1790's, he served a term in the Federal Congress, went abroad as part of a three-member delegation charged with the impossible task of negotiating with Talleyrand and the French Directory (the occasion for what became known as the XYZ Affair), and eventually, in 1800, during the final months of John Adams's Presidency, became Secretary of State. By the time Marshall was appointed to the Supreme Court by Adams in 1801, he had developed a keen sense of how bedevilingly hard it was to control the boisterous energies released by the American Revolution.</p>
        <p>It is impossible to overestimate Jefferson's resentment of the Marshall Court, which he described as ''a subtle corps of sappers and miners constantly working underground to undermine the foundations of our confederated fabric.'' The crowning insult was Marshall himself, sitting nonchalantly in his scruffy black robe with his disheveled hair, nubbing his quill pens as he listened with endless patience to lawyers arguing both sides of a case, the artful embodiment of the understated Virginia style that Jefferson considered his own special province.</p>
        <p>Even Jefferson admitted that Marshall was truly formidable. When conversing with Marshall, he acknowledged, ''I never admit anything. So sure as you admit any position to be good, no matter how remote from the conclusion he seeks to establish, you are gone. So great is his sophistry you must never give him an affirmative answer or you will be forced to grant his conclusion. Why, if he were to ask me if it were daylight or not, I'd reply, 'Sir, I don't know. I can't tell.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Smith does not deploy any elaborate psychological theories to explain Marshall's personality. Instead we simply observe him leading troops at Brandywine, caring for Polly, his semi-invalid wife, and their 11 children, jousting with Jefferson in Marbury v. Madison and again in the trial of Aaron Burr, riding circuit in Virginia and North Carolina and chatting up unsuspecting fellow travelers, who never realize they are speaking with the Chief Justice of the United States. Though he had a very clear constitutional agenda, Marshall struck most observers as a man so comfortable with himself that he lacked any personal agenda at all. ''I love his laugh,'' wrote his friend and judicial colleague Joseph Story, ''it is too hearty for an intriguer.''</p>
        <p>Indeed, on the basis of the evidence presented here one could argue that Marshall's convivial temperament, even more than his steel-trap mind, had a decisive effect on American law. Jefferson developed the theory that Marshall was some kind of wizard or hypnotist, because new appointments to the Court who were expected to generate dissent within chambers invariably came under Marshall's mysterious spell and ended up sustaining his opinions. Because the justices lived and boarded together when the Court was in session, their deliberations occurred as Marshall presided over meals and after-dinner Madeira. The consensual judgments reached under Marshall's benign prodding were then announced to the world with one voice, usually Marshall's.</p>
        <p>Of course, much of Marshall's extraordinary influence was also a matter of timing. He came at the beginning and therefore shaped the terms of the long argument over the proper allocation of power between the Federal Government and the states. Mr. Smith's splendid biography deserves a large readership mostly because it has recovered Marshall the man. But of late the long argument has itself been recovered, most recently in the proposal to return control of welfare to the states. Efforts to conjure Marshall up as a participant in the current constitutional context are probably futile, like trying to plant cut flowers. All that one can say with confidence is that if Marshall were here today the Court's decisions would almost surely be unanimous.  Joseph J. Ellis, the Ford Foundation Professor of History at Mount Holyoke College, is the author of the forthcoming ''American Sphinx: The Character of Thomas Jefferson.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Joseph J. Ellis, the Ford Foundation Professor of History at Mount Holyoke College, is the author of the forthcoming ''American Sphinx: The Character of Thomas Jefferson.''</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
