<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Go Ahead, Make My Day</title>
    <meta content="SRAGOW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="892789"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sragow, Michael</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schickel, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eastwood, Clint</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Clint Eastwood: A Biography (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E1DE113DF932A35751C1A960958260" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Go Ahead, Make My Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Michael Sragow</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Sragow, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Sragow reviews book Clint Eastwood: A Biography by Richard Schickel; drawing (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CLINT EASTWOOD</p>
        <p>A Biography.</p>
        <p>By Richard Schickel.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 557 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $27.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CLINT EASTWOOD</p>
        <p>A Biography.</p>
        <p>By Richard Schickel.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 557 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>Alfred A. Knopf. $27.50.</p>
        <p>Richard Schickel's telling of Clint Eastwood's life is as long and tortured as the lanky action hero's climb from a bit part in ''Revenge of the Creature'' (1955) to superstardom in ''Dirty Harry'' (1971) and from the cheap thrills of his film-making debut, ''Play Misty for Me'' (1971), to directorial eminence in ''Unforgiven'' (1992). Mr. Schickel, a film critic for Life from 1965 to 1972, and for Time since then, admits in ''Clint Eastwood'' that ''as a reviewer I had been as wary of him initially as any of my colleagues.'' But nearly two decades of friendship with the actor-director and the proselytizing of Mr. Eastwood's champions have worked their magic. He now calls the occasional poster boy for the .44 Magnum ''one of the great ironists of the age.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schickel presents himself as a Hemingwayesque figure (The Old Man and the Cinema?), a salt-of-the-earth American and movieland veteran who's the right guy to net a notoriously elusive big fish. In the quasi-autobiographical mode he too often falls into, he writes, ''What we knew -- Clint and I and others of our kind and time -- about that most vexed of topics, being male, had been shaped by forces always cautioning us that real men don't talk about real manhood.'' He asserts that Mr. Eastwood's ''manner of representing maleness -- with a sort of conscious un-self-consciousness -- is the largest source of his strength.'' Agonized phrases like ''conscious un-self-consciousness'' permeate the thesis that Mr. Eastwood's perilously thin persona and movies are actually full of ''humorous self-awareness,'' even ''subversion.''</p>
        <p>The first third of the book has some momentum as it traces young Clint's rise: from his middle-class boyhood and adolescence in the Oakland, Calif., area and his post-high-school drifter days; through his Korean War-era Army experience supervising the swimming pool at Fort Ord in Monterey and his move to Los Angeles and entrance into acting; to his television celebrity on ''Rawhide'' and his international breakthrough in Sergio Leone's deliriously entertaining spaghetti westerns (''Fistful of Dollars,'' ''For a Few Dollars More,'' ''The Good, the Bad, and the Ugly'').</p>
        <p>But Mr. Schickel can't restrain himself from bland talk and gassy moralizing about his generation (''The virtue of being seen but not heard, much stressed in those days, seemed to be good advice''). And he covers all-too-familiar ground: Mr. Eastwood's laconic independence and efficiency, his empathy for fellow actors, his love for jazz and his ability to reshape himself as star and film maker, alternating between eccentric projects and conventional ones so that audiences can accept him in different lights (cool killer, slapstick comedian, conscience-stricken veteran). Mr. Schickel gingerly handles a personal matter that would never make it into the kind of hagiographic ceremonies that present Mr. Eastwood with lifetime achievement awards: namely, his self-estimated 30 years of promiscuity (during and after his first marriage). Mr. Schickel finds much to admire even in the star's casual acceptance of his ''need to have many women'' and in the ''discretion'' of what Mr. Schickel revealingly terms his ''romantic transactions'': ''no public unpleasantness, certainly no scandal, attached to them until his famous falling-out with Sondra Locke in 1989.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Eastwood's smartest ''transaction'' as a producer-director-star was making his award-winning film ''Unforgiven.'' Part of its power comes from its chilling reversal of the dramatic values in his previous westerns and cop movies. If Mr. Eastwood's corpse-laden productions often cue audiences to cheer the hero's fits of vengeance, ''Unforgiven'' compels them to feel his murderous rage as a moral defeat. Mr. Schickel views the film both as a change in tenor and as the flowering of an oeuvre -- which unfortunately permits him to give blow-by-blow accounts of the entire mottled roster of Clint Eastwood productions, from ''Play Misty for Me'' to that pallid tear-jerker ''The Bridges of Madison County.''</p>
        <p>Critics who turn themselves into evangelists often struggle to uphold rickety work; Mr. Schickel writes as if he had a .44 Magnum to his head. He criticizes Don Siegel's unpretentious and enjoyable ''Coogan's Bluff'' for a rape scene that occurs only in Mr. Schickel's imagination. But in Mr. Eastwood's leaden ''High Plains Drifter'' the protagonist actually does rape a woman (she loves it), and Mr. Schickel ultimately excuses the scene as an expression of ''anarchic unpredictability.'' He doesn't note the coincidence that the best of Mr. Eastwood's American westerns were scripted by talented writers with substantial non-Eastwood credits -- David Webb Peoples (''Unforgiven'') and Philip Kaufman (the final drafts of ''The Outlaw Josey Wales''). Indeed, his description of Mr. Kaufman's firing as the director of that film relies on accounts by Mr. Eastwood and his associates and on a couple of journalistic items; Mr. Kaufman says Mr. Schickel never called him for his version of the story.</p>
        <p>Nor, according to Pauline Kael, did he contact her to check Mr. Eastwood's contention that she once apologized for hectoring him, saying (in what Mr. Schickel concedes is the actor's paraphrase), ''I'm just a dumpy little movie critic.'' Ms. Kael denies the conversation ever took place, but Mr. Schickel needs some friction to heat up his book, and one of his steadiest sources is the ongoing duel he conjures up between Ms. Kael and Mr. Eastwood. The first of many allusions or direct references to her appears on page 4, the last on page 498, and the book's index includes six entries alone under the heading ''Kael, Pauline, animus against Eastwood.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Schickel must believe that history is on his side. There's a victors-taking-the-spoils feeling to the entire volume, from its Eastwood-centric view of the star's peccadilloes and squabbles to its rendering of him as a bloodied but unbowed role model for 60-somethings. Yet Mr. Schickel's faith doesn't translate into either insight or passion. ''Clint Eastwood'' reads not as a labor of love, but as just plain labor.  Michael Sragow reviews new movies for SF Weekly and old movies for The New Yorker.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Michael Sragow reviews new movies for SF Weekly and old movies for The New Yorker.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
