<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Solved! Prof. Plum and Cohorts in the Clear</title>
    <meta content="01PRAT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="893060"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Clue (Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Waddington's (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Robert Mcg Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pratt, Anthony E</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961201T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E4DD123CF932A35751C1A960958260" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Solved! Prof. Plum and Cohorts in the Clear</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT McG. THOMAS Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thomas, Robert Mcg Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anthony E Pratt, British law clerk who invented classic board game Clue, died in obscurity near Birmingham in 1994; he was 90; his death did not become general knowledge until after Waddington's, company that first published game in 1948, issued public appeal to find its creator; ceremonies were being planned to commemorate impending 150-millionth worldwide sale of game, known in Britain as Cluedo; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A British law clerk who whiled away his time on World War II fire patrol in England dreaming up a board version of a popular parlor game died in such obscurity two years ago, it was learned last week, that not even Colonel Mustard or Miss Scarlet had a clue.</p>
        <p>They, of course, along with Professor Plum, Mrs. Peacock, Mrs. White and Mr. Green, owe their very existence to the clerk, Anthony E. Pratt, who linked them together in a nine-room Victorian mansion as the perennial murder suspects in the classic game Clue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A British law clerk who whiled away his time on World War II fire patrol in England dreaming up a board version of a popular parlor game died in such obscurity two years ago, it was learned last week, that not even Colonel Mustard or Miss Scarlet had a clue.</p>
        <p>They, of course, along with Professor Plum, Mrs. Peacock, Mrs. White and Mr. Green, owe their very existence to the clerk, Anthony E. Pratt, who linked them together in a nine-room Victorian mansion as the perennial murder suspects in the classic game Clue.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pratt, who was 90 and had dropped out of sight a decade ago, died in 1994 near Birmingham, England. But this did not become general knowledge until after Waddington's, the company that first published the game in 1948, issued a public appeal to find its creator. Ceremonies were being planned to commemorate the impending 150-millionth worldwide sale of the game, known in Britain as Cluedo.</p>
        <p>What the British press termed Clue's final mystery was solved when the company, which had set up a hot line, received a call from Gillian Lewis, the superintendent of the Bromsgrove Municipal Cemetery, 12 miles from Birmingham. He said Mr. Pratt had been buried there in April 1994.</p>
        <p>The company, which knew that several men named Anthony Pratt had died in recent years but hoped that the inventor was still alive, accepted that it had traced the right one when Mr. Lewis reported that the marble headstone bore the inscription ''Inventor of Cluedo.''</p>
        <p>As Mr. Pratt once explained to a British newspaper, he was walking his beat as a fire warden in Leeds in 1943, musing on a pastime that had been popular a few years earlier, when he had a brainstorm.</p>
        <p>''Between the wars,'' he said, ''all the bright young things would congregate in each other's homes for parties at weekends. We'd play a stupid game called Murder, where guests crept up on each other in corridors and the victim would shriek and fall on the floor.''</p>
        <p>With the help of his wife, who designed the familiar nine-room layout of the murder house, Mr. Pratt obtained a provisional patent on the game. But it was not until 1948, when he made a deal with Waddington's, a major British game publisher, that Colonel Mustard and his associates became household names.</p>
        <p>Since then, the murder mystery that is at the heart of the game has been solved tens of millions of times. Players, who are dealt cards representing suspects, weapons and rooms, take turns rolling a die to move from room to room, summoning suspects and weapons to determine by process of elimination which of the 324 possible combinations of 6 suspects, 6 weapons and 9 rooms figured in the murder.</p>
        <p>Still ranked among the top 10 games in annual sales, Clue is marketed in the United States by Parker Brothers, now a Hasbro subsidiary.</p>
        <p>The game, which inspired a 1985 movie and has recently been introduced in a CD-ROM version, sells about 3 million copies a year in 73 countries. And if its cast of characters is not universally recognized, that is at least partly because Clue's nomenclature varies somewhat from country to country.</p>
        <p>The murder victim, for example, is Dr. Black in England, Herr Kludo in Switzerland, Senor Lemon in Spain and, wincingly, Mr. Boddy in the United States.</p>
        <p>Mr. Green, originally the Rev. Green in Britain, is Dr. Olive in France; Professor Plum is Professor Black in Brazil; Mrs. Peacock is Baronesse von Blauw in Norway. And, in a change that would make a proper British officer twirl his mustache in fury, the Swiss, who do after all have something of a pacifist tradition, call Colonel Mustard Madame Curry.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pratt, a Birmingham native, made enough from the game to give up his work as a law clerk and become a touring concert pianist.</p>
        <p>One reason the company lost track of him was that in the mid-1950's, after originally receiving royalties amounting to 5 percent of British sales, he sold Waddington's his rights for a lump sum. He later complained that at the time of the transaction, the company did not tell him the game had become a best seller in the United States and elsewhere. Because of postwar production problems in England, it had until that point enjoyed only modest success.</p>
        <p>In the end, the obscurity of his death might be attributed to the standards of headline violence his game helped establish.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pratt, a widower who is survived by a daughter, Marcia, was not, for example, bludgeoned to death by Mr. Green or Mrs. Peacock with the candlestick in the ballroom, billiard room or study. He was not shot to death by Mrs. White or Miss Scarlett with the revolver in the dining room or kitchen, or stabbed to death by Professor Plum or Colonel Mustard with the knife in the library or lounge. Nor was he done in by anybody in the conservatory, or anywhere else.</p>
        <p>Instead, the man who made mayhem into a children's game died peacefully of natural causes in a nursing home.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
