<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Against Patriots' Brady, Jets Face the Unknown</title>
    <meta content="30JETS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="S" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/30/sports/football/30JETS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1347197"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Jets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New England Patriots</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Battista, Judy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New England Patriots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Jets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Jets</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Lewis, Mo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Brady, Tom</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DE123DF933A05752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="858" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Against Patriots' Brady, Jets Face the Unknown</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Against Patriots' Brady, Jets Face Unknown</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JUDY BATTISTA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Battista, Judy</byline>
      <dateline>HEMPSTEAD, N.Y., Nov. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses New York Jets preparations for game against New England Patriots (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Jets linebacker Mo Lewis knocked New England quarterback Drew Bledsoe out of the first meeting between the teams on Sept. 23 with a sheared blood vessel, and perhaps out of his Patriots career, Bledsoe was not the only one hoping he would return for this Sunday's game.</p>
        <p>The Jets' defense has had an unusual amount of success against Bledsoe, sacking him 10 times and intercepting him 5 times in their last three meetings. So the promotion of Tom Brady, young and inexperienced though he may be, is not necessarily welcome news for the Jets.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The promotion of Tom Brady to starting quarterback for the Patriots is not welcome news for the Jets, who have had an unusual amount of success against Drew Bledsoe.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Jets linebacker Mo Lewis knocked New England quarterback Drew Bledsoe out of the first meeting between the teams on Sept. 23 with a sheared blood vessel, and perhaps out of his Patriots career, Bledsoe was not the only one hoping he would return for this Sunday's game.</p>
        <p>The Jets' defense has had an unusual amount of success against Bledsoe, sacking him 10 times and intercepting him 5 times in their last three meetings. So the promotion of Tom Brady, young and inexperienced though he may be, is not necessarily welcome news for the Jets.</p>
        <p>''If you're doing good with one person, why do you want to face someone different?'' cornerback Aaron Glenn said. ''Hopefully, we can apply as much pressure on Brady as we do on Bledsoe.''</p>
        <p>That is, of course, the prescription for success against any quarterback, but pressuring Brady may be particularly important. He is 6-3 as a starter this season and his 93.5 quarterback rating is second in the American Football Conference and fourth in the National Football League. He is more mobile than Bledsoe and tries to minimize mistakes. He has thrown just 7 interceptions, compared to 16 touchdown passes. The Jets are impressed that Brady does not try to do too much.</p>
        <p>''That's what separates Brady from other young quarterbacks,'' safety Damien Robinson said. ''He's smart enough to take the check-down receiver rather than force it to the wide receiver.''</p>
        <p>Brady's one shortcoming seems to be a susceptibility to fumble. He has done so six times while being sacked since his second start of the season, in Week 4. In that unofficial category, Brady leads the league's quarterbacks. Brady has been sacked 26 times, and the Patriots' rookie tackle, Matt Light, is about to go against the best pass-rusher he will face this season, John Abraham, who, with seven sacks in his last four games, was named today the A.F.C.'s defensive player of the month.</p>
        <p>''You could be the most confident quarterback in the league, but if you get hit and see hands in your face, it makes you think,'' Glenn said. ''Right now, Brady is throwing darts. We have to rough him a little bit.''</p>
        <p>So prepare for a wave of blitzing, right? Not so fast. The defensive coordinator, Ted Cottrell, is not fond of blitzing because it opens holes in the secondary.</p>
        <p>''If you blitz a lot, sometimes you don't get there and it could be a big play,'' Jets Coach Herman Edwards said. ''You don't want to get out of character. If you're not a big blitz team, why are you going to start blitzing all of a sudden? It could backfire. I'm not saying we're not going to blitz him, because we'll blitz him.''</p>
        <p>For the first time since Curtis Martin left New England for New York in 1998, the Jets will also have to concern themselves with a Patriots running game. Antowain Smith has rushed for more than 100 yards in three of his last four games, all Patriots victories. He is seventh in the A.F.C. with 721 yards.</p>
        <p>In their four-game winning streak, the Jets have yielded more than 100 yards on the ground to a team only once, when they gave up 108 to the Saints. No individual rusher has had more than 71 yards. The Jets hope that they will not have to stack the box with eight defenders to stop Smith because that will allow them to keep their regular pass coverage.</p>
        <p>''We've got to stop the run,'' Edwards said. ''If you look at us, that's what we've been able to do. It's a cliché. You want to make a team one-handed. It puts a lot of pressure on the passing game.''</p>
        <p>EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Defensive end JOHN ABRAHAM refused to talk to reporters today after he was named the A.F.C.'s defensive player of the month, even after the defensive coordinator, TED COTTRELL, implored him to. Why? Because Abraham is superstitious and thinks he does not play well the game after he talks to reporters. He did release a statement saying he was proud he won the award. . . . Offensive guard RANDY THOMAS (ankle) is still questionable, but he practiced today for the first time since missing three games with a high ankle sprain, which he has been told will take six to eight months to heal. Thomas said it hurt when he ran. ''I've got to see how much pain I can play with,'' Thomas said. ''This is not going to heal. I'm going to use common sense. I'm not going to hurt myself.'' . . . Coach HERMAN EDWARDS gave players with five or more years of experience a vote about which surface to practice on in the rain today. The choice: the artificial turf in the bubble.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
