<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dinkins Moves to Shore Up Plans To Scatter City Homeless Shelters</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="492921"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOMELESS PERSONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PUBLIC OPINION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PURDUM, TODD S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homeless Persons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DB143CF933A25751C1A967958260" item-length="947" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dinkins Moves to Shore Up Plans To Scatter City Homeless Shelters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TODD S. PURDUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">PURDUM, TODD S</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Mayor David N. Dinkins says that he will seek to build a broader consensus on how his administration should handle the problems of the homeless before he begins scattering homeless shelters in neighborhoods across the city.</p>
        <p>The Mayor said his approach would be to find the "common ground and build from there" on an issue that has left his administration besieged with criticism from communities and their elected officials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Mayor David N. Dinkins says that he will seek to build a broader consensus on how his administration should handle the problems of the homeless before he begins scattering homeless shelters in neighborhoods across the city.</p>
        <p>The Mayor said his approach would be to find the "common ground and build from there" on an issue that has left his administration besieged with criticism from communities and their elected officials.</p>
        <p>"We must turn down the rhetorical heat while turning up the substantive discussions," Mr. Dinkins said in a statement. Wait for Recommendations</p>
        <p>Mr. Dinkins said he would defer submitting formal proposals on two dozen sites until a mayoral commission headed by Andrew Cuomo makes comprehensive recommendations on homeless policy late next month. That is precisely what the City Council and other politicians have been urging since before Mr. Dinkins released his plan in October.</p>
        <p>His aides said this new stance was effectively an acknowledgment that their proposal for breaking up large shelters for single men and women and building smaller ones with better services -- many in middle-class areas -- had unleashed such an uproar, and in their view been so misunderstood, that it was for all practical purposes paralyzed.</p>
        <p>No real progress could be made, they reasoned, until the whole issue was hashed out, specifically in Mr. Cuomo's commission. Mr. Dinkins he had asked Mr. Cuomo to hold four more hearings, the first of them at City Hall today.</p>
        <p>Senior mayoral aides were quick to play down the announcement, saying it stated the obvious, and would have little practical impact since they had never intended to begin land-use reviews until next spring anyway. They said they were not scrapping the thrust of their plan to improve care for single men and women, generally considered the most troubled part of the homeless population because many of them are mentally ill or suffer from addictions.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dinkins first announced his new stance in a written statement issued over the weekend. He elaborated on it in a letter yesterday to Peter F. Vallone, the City Council Speaker.</p>
        <p>"It does not mean we're going to revamp the whole plan," said Deputy Mayor Bill Lynch. "We're not." He said the administration was moving forward to solicit alternative proposals for sites in a 90-day comment period that ends next month.</p>
        <p>But other officials have not offered alternatives, and the political significance of the Mayor's move seemed aimed at breaking a political logjam because Mr. Vallone has bitterly opposed the plan and urged the Mayor to rethink it. Even Mr. Cuomo has raised doubts about just how such shelters would work and who would run them. The Mayor's statement seemed a tactical retreat aimed at soothing such concerns and giving both Mr. Vallone and himself some political cover, which was one of the reasons for appointing a blue-ribbon commission in the first place.  Open to Criticism</p>
        <p>Mr. Vallone and the Mayor's critics have said the administration left itself open to trouble by releasing the list of 35 potential sites without adequate explanation of the treatment programs at them. Yesterday, Mr. Vallone said the Mayor's statement was "a healthy sign that a cooperative effort can be achieved."</p>
        <p>The Mayor's plan is meant to conform with legal requirements for a five-year blueprint for sheltering the homeless. It comes as the onset of winter aggravates the problems of the homeless and as transit officials are themselves grappling with new policies to keep the homeless from loitering in subway stations and bus terminals.</p>
        <p>In his statement yesterday, Mr. Vallone welcomed "the Mayor's decision to postpone any further action" until the Cuomo commission reports. That prompted the Mayor to issue a clarifying letter to Mr. Vallone last night, stressing that he had asked for more hearings to insure "that our proposal has been informed by the broadest possible public input before the sites are submitted" for review by the Council.</p>
        <p>"However, this neither requires nor implies a delay," Mr. Dinkins's letter said, since the formal review was not to begin until spring.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cuomo, the Governor's son, who runs a nonprofit group that builds housing for the homeless, said: "The more substantive the dialogue, the greater the process. There's been enough rhetoric on the issue to last us for quite some time. The Mayor's trying to say, 'Put substance over rhetoric. Let cooler heads prevail.' "</p>
        <p>In a sign of the stress he is under on the topic, Mr. Dinkins gave vent to a rare burst of public temper with a knot of hecklers who repeatedly interrupted his remarks at a ceremony on the steps of City Hall yesterday honoring human rights. As the Mayor recounted the privations he saw in squatter camps on his recent trip to South Africa, a handful of squatters from the area around Tompkins Square Park, where the city recently bulldozed shanties, asked why he did not express more concern for the homeless here.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Dinkins tried to explain, the hecklers kept yelling and finally Mr. Dinkins shouted back, "Just shut up a minute!" as the crowd of about 50 ministers there for the rights ceremony cheered.</p>
        <p>"If you are as committed as you claim to be, listen a minute," the Mayor told the hecklers, who carried a sign reading, "Lord Mayor Dinkins visits South African shantytowns because none exist in New York, God Bless America."</p>
        <p>"If you would direct your attention where it belongs, if you would recognize that the Federal Government has abandoned our cities, instead of trying to disrupt a legitimate effort about apartheid in South Africa, you might get more support for your effort."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
