<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; A Bleak Season For Natural Gas</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="492974"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GAS (FUEL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUTURES TRADING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEATHER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EASTERN STATES (US)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAYES, THOMAS C</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gas (Fuel)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19911210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3D8153EF933A25751C1A967958260" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; A Bleak Season For Natural Gas</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Thomas C. Hayes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAYES, THOMAS C</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE futures market for natural gas and the market for shares of natural gas companies have both just about written off the winter of 1991-92 as another disappointment for the long-depressed industry.</p>
        <p>The contract for January gas in the spot market fell again yesterday, by 4 cents, to $1.94 for one million British thermal units, from a peak of $2.33 on Oct. 15. The plunge has coincided with several weeks of unusually warm weather in the East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE futures market for natural gas and the market for shares of natural gas companies have both just about written off the winter of 1991-92 as another disappointment for the long-depressed industry.</p>
        <p>The contract for January gas in the spot market fell again yesterday, by 4 cents, to $1.94 for one million British thermal units, from a peak of $2.33 on Oct. 15. The plunge has coincided with several weeks of unusually warm weather in the East.</p>
        <p>And after a selloff in the last month, shares of a group of large independent natural gas producers, including Enron Oil and Gas, Anadarko Petroleum, Burlington Resources and Cabot Oil and Gas, are up 8 percent for the year, compared with an increase of 14 percent in the Standard &amp; Poor's index of 400 industrial company stocks.</p>
        <p>Two years ago, many analysts and producers figured that the end was near for a period of gas oversupply dating from the early 1980's. The dominant view is that gas prices are likely to remain depressed, with the yearly average spot price not rising much above $2 for one million B.T.U.'s before 1995, from about $1.40 this year.</p>
        <p>Timothy J. Curro, energy analyst at UBS Securities in New York, said, "I don't think a very strong case can be made for the price of natural gas for the next three or four years."</p>
        <p>Ronald J. Barone, a managing director and analyst at Kidder, Peabody in New York, said, "This is the worst year for gas prices in a long, long time."</p>
        <p>Rising output from areas like the Gulf of Mexico, the Mobile Bay region of Alabama and the Anadarko Basin in Arkansas and Oklahoma helps explain the ample supply. So do the recession and warm winters, which have curbed demand.</p>
        <p>Advances in drilling technology, including seismic studies that give geologists a clearer gauge of likely reserve sites and improvements in completing wells, are another factor. Production is up, even though the number of rigs drilling for gas plunged to 299 in the week ended Dec. 6, from 495 a year earlier, according to Baker Hughes Inc.</p>
        <p>Also, big inventories remained in pipelines and storage tanks this fall after one of the warmest winters of the century last year.</p>
        <p>Supplies also increased as a result of tax credits that Congress approved last year for gas drillers. Drillers are now receiving credits of 87 cents for one million B.T.U.'s of gas produced from coal layers, called coal-seam gas. Another tax credit, equal to 52 cents for one million B.T.U.'s, has sharply expanded drilling in tight-sands areas, where gas is locked in dense rock formations.</p>
        <p>William A. Johnson, president of the Jofree Corporation, an energy consulting firm in Houston, forecast last month that tax-subsidized gas produced in the United States would rise to 5 percent of total gas output in the next few years, from 2.4 percent this year. Subsidized gas "is a major culprit currently driving down prices" and could send spot prices below $1 next summer, he said.</p>
        <p>The prevailing gloom among gas producers is a striking reversal from the optimism of 1989, when the shares of many independent producers soared by more than 50 percent. The popular view then was that production would gradually fall, especially in the abundant Gulf of Mexico fields, and that demand would be raised by the Clean Air Act and new gas-fired electricity plants being built.</p>
        <p>"We were very bullish on prices a few years ago," said Robert W. Harvey, head of domestic natural gas consulting at McKinsey &amp; Company in Houston. His view is a centrist one in the debate over gas supplies and future prices. He sees prices rising barely above $2 in 1993.</p>
        <p>"A couple of years ago, people acted on the belief that the gas bubble's demise was imminent, and they drilled more," he said. "We've seen a complete reversal on the score. The bearish view that has swept the industry today may be the first sign that a correction is possible in gas prices over the next two to four years."</p>
        <p>Some analysts are more bullish. Paul R. Leibman, a principal at Petrie, Parkman &amp; Company in Denver, said that falling drilling rates should cut into supplies within the next three years. "We actually see a tight gas market in the '93-'95 period," he said, with prices rising to $2.50 per million B.T.U.'s.</p>
        <p>Indeed, some independent producers like Tom Brown Inc. in Midland, Tex., have acquired gas reserves at bargain prices in the last few years in the hope that prices will rebound.</p>
        <p>"I want to be there with a big pile of reserves when the market turns," said Donald L. Evans, chairman and chief executive. "But with a recession and what looks like a mild winter, there is not a lot of reason to feel like gas prices will move to higher levels soon. We're hoping for '92, but it might not be before '94."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
