<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Many Airlines Not Worried By Boeing-McDonnell Deal</title>
    <meta content="19BOEI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="896446"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Boeing Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mcdonnell Douglas Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Airlines Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bryant, Adam</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crandall, Robert L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brace, Jake</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961219T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A07E0DE1731F93AA25751C1A960958260" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Many Airlines Not Worried By Boeing-McDonnell Deal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM BRYANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bryant, Adam</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Airline executives say they do not oppose merger of Boeing Co and McDonnell Douglas Corp, which would shrink number of commercial jet makers to two from three; American Airlines chairman Robert L Crandall and United Airlines aide Jake Brace comment (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even though the proposed merger of the Boeing Company and the McDonnell Douglas Corporation would  shrink the number of commercial jet aircraft makers to two from three, several airline executives said yesterday that they did not oppose the deal.</p>
        <p>Their opinions matter because they are likely to be consulted by Federal agencies scrutinizing the deal for potentially anti-competitive effects.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even though the proposed merger of the Boeing Company and the McDonnell Douglas Corporation would  shrink the number of commercial jet aircraft makers to two from three, several airline executives said yesterday that they did not oppose the deal.</p>
        <p>Their opinions matter because they are likely to be consulted by Federal agencies scrutinizing the deal for potentially anti-competitive effects.</p>
        <p>Robert L. Crandall, the chairman of American Airlines, which is one of the largest users of McDonnell Douglas aircraft, said yesterday that the marketplace lesson of the proposed merger was that the capital demands of the aircraft-building business were so great that there was no room for more than two big manufacturers, Boeing and Airbus Industrie, the European consortium.</p>
        <p>The merger, he added, would largely guarantee that American, a unit of the AMR Corporation, will have a steady supply of parts for its McDonnell Douglas planes, much better than McDonnell Douglas failing on its own.</p>
        <p>''What's occurred is about as favorable a situation as you can have,'' he said. He added that he did not believe that prices of aircraft would, over the long term, rise as a result of the merger. ''If you take the waste out of the system, and assume that the presence of two producers will continue to provide adequate price discipline, you may end up paying less,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Jake Brace, vice president of financial analysis for United Airlines, said that ideally three competitors were better than two. But given the shrinking role in recent years of McDonnell Douglas, he said its absorption into Boeing was a nonevent. ''We are not losing any sleep over it,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Steven C. Sunshine, a former deputy assistant attorney general in charge of merger enforcement at the Justice Department, said that the agency that reviews the proposed merger -- either the Justice Department or the Federal Trade Commission -- would need the support of airline executives if it goes to court to try to block the deal.</p>
        <p>Another important customer that could protest the merger is the Pentagon, the primary customer for the military-related businesses of Boeing and McDonnell Douglas. Thus far, the Pentagon has said nothing publicly beyond acknowledging that consolidation in the military industry is inevitable and necessary in light of the declining military budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sunshine said he believed that Boeing and McDonnell Douglas probably checked first with Pentagon officials whether they were likely to have major objections to their merger. ''I would be shocked if the merger had been announced publicly if there had not been some favorable indications,'' he said.</p>
        <p>As a group, airlines often do not speak with one voice on various public policy issues. And some airlines have not yet decided whether the Boeing-McDonnell Douglas merger will be good or bad for business. Delta Air Lines, for example, has assigned a team to study the question.</p>
        <p>But many other airlines say that because McDonnell Douglas did not offer a full range of aircraft, and because it had said publicly that it planned to narrow its role to a niche player, its merger with Boeing was not likely to affect the prices they pay for new planes.</p>
        <p>''The No. 1 maker is Boeing and No. 2 is Airbus -- that's where the main competitive arena is,'' Mark Abels, a spokesman for Trans World Airlines, said. ''I wouldn't see this as a Coke and Pepsi merger.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
