<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Citigroup Says It Will Cut 10,400 Jobs</title>
    <meta content="Y16CIT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19981217T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1070106"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Citigroup Inc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Brien, Timothy L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Banks and Banking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E4DD123DF935A25751C1A96E958260" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Citigroup Says It Will Cut 10,400 Jobs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY L. O'BRIEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">O'Brien, Timothy L</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Citigroup plans to eliminate about 10,400 jobs, or about 6 percent of its work force, well beyond several thousand positions it suggested would be cut as recently as October; undisclosed but substantial number of jobs cuts will involve layoffs; Citigroup says 65 percent, or about 6,760, of the cuts will be overseas; about 3,640 positions will be in US; Citigroup employees in New York will not bear brunt of US cutbacks; chart (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citigroup, one of the country's largest financial services companies, said yesterday that it planned to eliminate about 10,400 jobs, or about 6 percent of its work force, well beyond the several thousand positions it suggested would be cut as recently as October.</p>
        <p>An undisclosed but substantial number of the job cuts will involve layoffs. Citigroup said 65 percent, or about 6,760, of the cuts would be overseas. The rest, about 3,640 positions, will be in the United States.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Citigroup, one of the country's largest financial services companies, said yesterday that it planned to eliminate about 10,400 jobs, or about 6 percent of its work force, well beyond the several thousand positions it suggested would be cut as recently as October.</p>
        <p>An undisclosed but substantial number of the job cuts will involve layoffs. Citigroup said 65 percent, or about 6,760, of the cuts would be overseas. The rest, about 3,640 positions, will be in the United States.</p>
        <p>When Citicorp and Travelers Group Inc. announced in April that they planned to merge, the companies focused on the financial benefits of the merger and said that cost-cutting and layoffs were not the reasons for the deal. But global financial markets have been pummeled since late summer, forcing Citigroup to adopt less ambitious goals.</p>
        <p>''They've wanted the world to believe that this merger was about revenue enhancement and cross-selling,'' said John Keefe, president of Keefe Worldwide, a financial services consulting firm in New York. ''But having a big layoff like this is at cross-purposes with revenue enhancement, particularly if your goal is cross-selling. More and more, the logic of the deal appears to be cost-cutting.''</p>
        <p>Citigroup employees said that New York, where the company is based, would not bear the brunt of the cutbacks in the United States. Citigroup noted that its telephone call centers, which support businesses like credit cards, would have cutbacks. Call centers abroad would be hardest hit, according to employees involved in the moves. Citigroup's main call centers in the United States are in Jacksonville, Fla.; San Antonio; Las Vegas, Nev.; Sioux Falls, S.D.; Hagerstown, Md.; Kansas City, Mo.; St. Louis, and Erlanger, Ky.</p>
        <p>Citigroup comprises a consumer business, which includes operations like traditional loans, savings accounts and credit cards, and a corporate business, which includes operations like investment banking, lending to big companies and trading.</p>
        <p>Citigroup said it expected to cut about $525 million in costs from its consumer business and about $350 million from its corporate business.</p>
        <p>Citigroup said the largest portion of the job cuts would occur in the consumer business. ''These include regional consolidation of call centers and other back-office functions worldwide, reduction of management layers, sales force restructuring and integration of overlapping marketing and product management groups,'' Citigroup said in yesterday's announcement.</p>
        <p>On the corporate side, Citigroup has already been scaling back its trading operation. It said yesterday that it would also make cutbacks in ''emerging markets, global relationship banking and investment banking, as the company rationalizes its presence in countries with multiple operations.''</p>
        <p>Investors cheered the moves. In trading yesterday on the New York Stock Exchange, shares of Citigroup jumped $2.6875, or 5.8 percent, to $48.75.</p>
        <p>Many big Wall Street firms have been announcing layoffs in response to financial turmoil overseas, which has eaten into those companies' profits. Even so, Citigroup has repeatedly played down how large its cutbacks would be.</p>
        <p>In October, a Citigroup spokesman, John Morris, said that the bank planned no further job cuts beyond the several thousand that the company had announced in September. Mr. Morris said yesterday that the size of the cutback was determined by Citigroup managers who were told to analyze their operations in September and then determine how many jobs could be cut.</p>
        <p>''The businesses have come back with more than had been anticipated at that time,'' Mr. Morris said yesterday.</p>
        <p>Citigroup declined to be more specific yesterday about which businesses or which geographic regions would face cutbacks, although it said it planned to drop ''several nonstrategic operations'' in both the consumer and corporate businesses.</p>
        <p>Citigroup executives have called such unwanted businesses ''hobbies'' because, in their view, the company lacks either the size or the competence in those arenas to be competitive. It was unclear, however, which operations are about to be abandoned, although Citigroup certainly does not enjoy the advantage of size in businesses like mortgage lending and student loans. There are also some European consumer businesses that may be on the block.</p>
        <p>Citigroup has also been forecasting a big fourth-quarter charge for reorganization in recent weeks, and the company said yesterday that it would incur an after-tax charge of about $900 million, ''the bulk of which'' would be taken in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>Although Citigroup said at the time of the merger that it expected after-tax savings of about $1 billion a year, it said yesterday that after-tax savings in 1999 would be only about $442 million and that after-tax savings in 2000 would be only about $634 million.</p>
        <p>Analysts said that Citigroup might have to be more aggressive about cutbacks if it intended to meet some of its goals.</p>
        <p>''This restructuring charge is chump change when you look at the $40 billion cost base of the company,'' said Diane Glossman, an analyst with Lehman Brothers Inc. ''It's just not a big percentage.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 17, 1998, Thursday  A chart in Business Day yesterday listing layoffs announced this year at major financial institutions misstated the figure for Merrill Lynch. It is 3,400, not 4,300.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 17, 1998, Thursday</p>
        <p>A chart in Business Day yesterday listing layoffs announced this year at major financial institutions misstated the figure for Merrill Lynch. It is 3,400, not 4,300.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
