<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Helmsley's Last Legal Bid to Elude Prison Fails</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="521672"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAX EVASION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HELMSLEY, HARRY B</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HELMSLEY, LEONA M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DERSHOWITZ, ALAN M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, RONALD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920415T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEFD91030F936A25757C0A964958260" item-length="629" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Helmsley's Last Legal Bid to Elude Prison Fails</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SULLIVAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, RONALD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Leona M. Helmsley's final legal move to avoid prison failed yesterday when a Federal appeals court in Manhattan upheld an order for her to surrender today to the Federal Medical Center in Lexington, Ky.</p>
        <p>Underscoring her desperate attempt to remain free, her lawyer, Alan M. Dershowitz, said outside the courtroom that Mrs. Helmsley would give her hotel holdings to New York City for housing the homeless in exchange for escaping prison. She and her husband, Harry, own the New York Helmsley and the Park Lane and have interests in the other Helmsley hotels, including 51 percent of the Helmsley Palace.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Leona M. Helmsley's final legal move to avoid prison failed yesterday when a Federal appeals court in Manhattan upheld an order for her to surrender today to the Federal Medical Center in Lexington, Ky.</p>
        <p>Underscoring her desperate attempt to remain free, her lawyer, Alan M. Dershowitz, said outside the courtroom that Mrs. Helmsley would give her hotel holdings to New York City for housing the homeless in exchange for escaping prison. She and her husband, Harry, own the New York Helmsley and the Park Lane and have interests in the other Helmsley hotels, including 51 percent of the Helmsley Palace.</p>
        <p>"She has offered to solve the city's problem of the homeless singlehandedly," Mr. Dershowitz said. But Mrs. Helmsley's spokesman, Howard J. Rubenstein, said later that she had not authorized such an offer and that the proposal was more of "a metaphor" used in bargaining for her freedom than a concrete proposal. 'Buy Your Way Out'</p>
        <p>Mayor David N. Dinkins's press secretary, Leland T. Jones, said that the idea "was broached some time ago," but that "It didn't go anywhere, because the assumption was it was between the judge and Mrs. Helmsley."</p>
        <p>Even Mr. Dershowitz said he knew of no legal rule that would allow the appeals court to entertain such a proposal. And Stephen Gillers, a law professor at New York University, said: "You can't buy your way out of prison. It's something the courts simply cannot accept."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Helmsley had sought a sentence of performing community service for her conviction on income-tax fraud. Mr. Dershowitz said yesterday that she "was not prepared to go to prison." But when Mrs. Helmsley was informed of the court's ruling at her residence in the Park Lane Hotel on Central Park South, she said through Mr. Rubenstein, "I accept the court's judgment, and I'm prepared to abide by the law."</p>
        <p>Mr. Rubenstein said Mrs. Helmsley's husband, Harry, who was also indicted for tax fraud but was ruled incompetent to stand trial, took the news of his wife's impending imprisonment "very hard." At Least 16 Months</p>
        <p>Barring any last-minute development, like another admission to New York Hospital, where she was taken last month after losing in court, the 71-year-old self-styled hotel queen will begin her four-year sentence on the day of the Federal income tax filing deadline and two and one half years after she was found guilty.</p>
        <p>She must serve at least 16 months before becoming eligible for parole.</p>
        <p>Federal prosecutors say they expect that Mrs. Helmsley will fly in her private jetliner to Lexington and then be driven by limousine through the rolling bluegrass countryside to the front entrance of the prison, which is reserved for female inmates who require either hospitalization or medical treatment.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dershowitz, arguing yesterday before the United States Court of Appeals for the Second Circuit, contended that because of what he described as Mrs. Hemlsley's deterioriating cardiovascular condition, her imprisonment amounts to a death sentence for both her and for her ailing 83-year-old husband, who Mr. Dershowitz said would die without her.</p>
        <p>Her lawyer also said Mrs. Helmsley had received death threats from a group he described as Aryan Brotherhood, a splinter group of the Ayran Nation, to be carried out after she is imprisoned. Janet Jacobson, a spokeswoman for the prison, said any threat would be investigated and "appropriate measures would be taken if necessary."</p>
        <p>Mrs. Helmsley was convicted of evading $1.7 million in Federal income taxes. Both she and her husband were indicted on charges that they purchased furnishings and decorations for their Greenwich, Conn., home and for their Park Lane residence and fraudulently deducted them as business expenses for the Helmsley hotel chain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
