<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Florio, a Budget Proposal And an Election Platform</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="589233"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNORS (US)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAY, JERRY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LYNCH, JOHN A (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FLORIO, JAMES J (GOV)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D81439F933A25751C0A965958260" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Florio, a Budget Proposal And an Election Platform</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERRY GRAY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRAY, JERRY</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, Feb. 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a year in which both he and all 120 members of the State Legislature face re-election, Gov. Jim Florio used much of his annual budget address today to trumpet the successes of his first term in office and to set the platform on which he is expected to seek a second term.</p>
        <p>Leading politicians agreed that it was definitely an election-year presentation, although they disagreed about whether that was good or bad. Mr. Florio's speech and his budget won cautious praise from the Republicans who control the Legislature, which must approve the spending plan, though it came under immediate attack from two candidates for the Republican nomination for governor -- Christine Todd Whitman and Cary Edwards.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a year in which both he and all 120 members of the State Legislature face re-election, Gov. Jim Florio used much of his annual budget address today to trumpet the successes of his first term in office and to set the platform on which he is expected to seek a second term.</p>
        <p>Leading politicians agreed that it was definitely an election-year presentation, although they disagreed about whether that was good or bad. Mr. Florio's speech and his budget won cautious praise from the Republicans who control the Legislature, which must approve the spending plan, though it came under immediate attack from two candidates for the Republican nomination for governor -- Christine Todd Whitman and Cary Edwards.</p>
        <p>More surprisingly, the budget was criticized by the State Senate minority leader, John A. Lynch, the second most powerful elected Democrat in state government, after Governor Florio. Mr. Lynch's attack today was driven by anger that the proposed budget did not fully restore the homestead rebate program that gives tax refunds to some homeowners and renters. The program was cut in half, to $350 million, last year. 'Fiscal Gimmicks'</p>
        <p>"It's clearly an election-year budget -- high on promises but low on problem-solving," Mr. Lynch said in a statement that was distributed to reporters as Mr. Florio delivered his speech. "A budget backed by $4 billion in fiscal gimmicks and $412 million in Medicaid reimbursements should have enough money in it to restore the homestead rebate program to what it was before the Republicans cut it last year."</p>
        <p>The proposed budget that Mr. Florio released on Monday for the 1994 fiscal year is a $15.6 billion spending plan shaped largely by political deal-making -- from collaboration with the Republican legislative leaders on major spending to the last-minute infusion of $412 million in Medicaid reimbursements with the help of President Clinton.</p>
        <p>Today, Mr. Florio went before a joint session of the Republican-controlled Legislature to outline his broad budget goals: guaranteed health-care coverage for all New Jersey residents, tougher law-enforcement programs, a program to train youths for high-tech jobs. Awkward Position</p>
        <p>With the coalition of Mr. Florio and the Republican legislative leadership seemingly in accord on the budget, it left the Republican gubernatorial candidates and Mr. Lynch, the Senate Democratic leader, in the awkward position of hitting their own party members with the political arrows intended for their traditional enemies, and it left the Senate President, Donald T. DiFrancesco, a Republican, in the even odder position of defending Mr. Florio.</p>
        <p>"Governor Florio's budget is great electioneering but lousy economics," said Mrs. Whitman, who held an impromptu news conference in one corner of the State House corridor as Mr. Edwards held a competing news conference several yards away.</p>
        <p>But Mr. DiFrancesco said, "This is a good election-year budget," adding that the Republican legislative leaders had agreed on 85 to 90 percent of the budget, including spending on education, health and jobs creation. 'Months of Discussions'</p>
        <p>In his speech, Mr. Florio said: "No one wants to see a repeat of the budget hell of last year. This budget I submit today is based on months of discussions I've had with the leaders of this distinguished body."</p>
        <p>Mr. Florio, in the final year of his first four-year term in office, has yet to announce for re-election, but much of his speech today had the ring of a politician on the stump.</p>
        <p>"You know, when I was a kid growing up in Brooklyn, my Uncle Tom Florio got me one of my first jobs -- shoveling up after the horses at a stable in Prospect Park," Mr. Florio said. "At that time, I thought I was lucky to have a little pocket money. I never imagined it would be such a good apprenticeship for being Governor."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
