<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="13DIGE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1009430"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E00E3D7103DF930A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="584" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Citicorp and Travelers Face A Tangle of Technology  The synergies that Citicorp and Travelers promise will result from the huge merger the two companies announced last week may be a while coming. That is because it is likely to be a decade, at least, before their computer systems can be fully integrated. Citicorp itself has tried for 10 years to merge the computers in its banks in 100 countries into one happy family, a task that remains far from complete.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Citicorp and Travelers Face A Tangle of Technology  The synergies that Citicorp and Travelers promise will result from the huge merger the two companies announced last week may be a while coming. That is because it is likely to be a decade, at least, before their computer systems can be fully integrated. Citicorp itself has tried for 10 years to merge the computers in its banks in 100 countries into one happy family, a task that remains far from complete.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the computers holding Travelers insurance policies are barely on speaking terms with those at the company's brokerage and credit units. [Page D4.]</p>
        <p>Talk Radio: A Dash Past Rush  A new survey says the talk-radio personality Rush Limbaugh has fallen behind two rivals, Dr. Laura Schlessinger and Howard Stern. Radio experts say the change reflects a broad shift away from political talk radio as the strong economy and the public's weariness with scandal dull its interest in Washington. [D7.]</p>
        <p>Fresh Hostilities at Cantor  Two years ago, Howard W. Lutnick, the chief executive of Cantor Fitzgerald, settled a bitter legal dispute over control of the firm with Iris Cantor, the wife of the firm's founder, as her husband was dying. Now, however, Cantor Fitzgerald is suing Mrs. Cantor, accusing her of violating the partnership agreement that came out of the settlement. [D4.]</p>
        <p>Hawking Documentaries in Cannes  Cannes may be the last place one would expect to find a serious documentary producer, but that is where Brian Lapping was last week, hawking the rights to his film ''The 50 Years War: Israel and the Arabs.'' He joined 10,000 buyers and sellers at the Marche International des Programmes de Television, the leading international trading market for television programs. [D7.]</p>
        <p>Cyberspace Bet For TV Veteran  With two broadcasting companies built and sold, Bert Ellis is making the biggest bet of a high-stakes career. Lured by low entry costs and the potential for astronomical growth, he embraced the Internet. His two-year-old iXL Holding has quickly become a budding interactive communications conglomerate, luring top industry talent like Lara Stein. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Privacy Wars on the Web Intensify  Nowhere is the conflict between traditional and electronic commerce clearer than in the war between privacy champions and the companies that sell personal data. Consumers indifferent to junk mail on the front stoop fanatically guard their personal information on line, a fact lost on Web vendors gathering it. Denise Caruso: Digital Commerce. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Programmers Extol Free Software  A dozen of the nation's best-known software designers, who met last week to promote the idea of freely sharing the underlying code of their products, say that such sharing is the most effective way to improve the quality of software. [D5.]</p>
        <p>Broadcasters Focus on Digital TV  Digital television was on the tongue of nearly everyone as 105,000 broadcasters gathered at the industry's annual convention in Las Vegas, Nev., last week. Broadcasting. [D7.]</p>
        <p>Many Overseas Markets Closed  Many financial markets overseas -- including those in Britain, France, Germany and Hong Kong -- are closed today in observance of holidays. But the American and Japanese markets are open.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
