<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boxing; Tyson's Next Bout: Legal Case With His Manager</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="157526"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOXING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEAVYWEIGHT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERGER, PHIL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TYSON, MIKE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CAYTON, BILL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880629T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6DF103CF93AA15755C0A96E948260" item-length="1106" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boxing; Tyson's Next Bout: Legal Case With His Manager</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PHIL BERGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERGER, PHIL</byline>
      <dateline>ATLANTIC CITY, June 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Mike Tyson's 91-second fight with Michael Spinks Monday night, as it turned out, was far less complicated than life after Spinks is likely to be for the heavyweight champion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Mike Tyson's 91-second fight with Michael Spinks Monday night, as it turned out, was far less complicated than life after Spinks is likely to be for the heavyweight champion.</p>
        <p>Mike Tyson's 91-second fight with Michael Spinks Monday night, as it turned out, was far less complicated than life after Spinks is likely to be for the heavyweight champion.</p>
        <p>Despite making preparations over the weekend for his next defense, against Frank Bruno in London in September, Tyson left some doubts about whether he would fulfill the obligation against Bruno.</p>
        <p>''As far as I know,'' Tyson said after knocking out Spinks, ''this fight might be my last.'' That, however, seems unlikely. For even before the fight began Monday night, moves were being made on Tyson's behalf to position him for a boxing future without Bill Cayton, the surviving partner of the co-managers with whom Tyson began his career. The other manager, Jim Jacobs, died in March. As Cayton sat at ringside waiting for his fighter to enter the ring, he was served with a lawsuit filed by Tyson earlier in the day. Battle for Control</p>
        <p>Since Tyson's marriage to the actress Robin Givens in February, Cayton, on the one hand, and Givens and her mother, Ruth Roper, on the other, have been at odds. In that conflict for control of Tyson, the fighter's promoter, Don King, has allied himself with the women, and Tyson's trainer, Kevin Rooney, has backed Cayton.</p>
        <p>''In essence,'' Thomas Puccio, Cayton's lawyer, said today, ''it's an attempt to set aside the contract by accusing Jimmy Jacobs of fraud. Mike Tyson is saying he was defrauded by a dead man, someone not in a position to defend himself.''</p>
        <p>Puccio, who also represents Jacobs's widow, Loraine, said both of his clients were ''disappointed and distressed'' with Tyson.</p>
        <p>Tyson's attorney, Michael Winston, differed with Puccio, contending that Jacobs and Cayton had not notified Tyson of the terminal nature of Jacobs's illness. He said not informing Tyson would constitute a basis for breaking the contract. Contract at Issue</p>
        <p>''The other issue,'' said Winston, ''is that the contract that my client entered into did not contain a specific term.'' He added that a contract with no stated term could be terminated at will.</p>
        <p>The latest contracts in a series involving Tyson, Jacobs and Cayton were dated Feb. 12, 1988 - about a month before Jacobs's death. The contracts were attached as exhibits to Tyson's suit, which was filed in New York State Supreme Court. One of those contracts, which Tyson signed, said that if Jacobs died and Cayton survived him, Cayton would be Tyson's manager. Jacobs and Cayton also signed contracts giving each other's widow 50 percent of the surviving manager's share if one should die.</p>
        <p>The New York State Athletic Commission forbids managerial contracts of longer than four years. In the contract signed by Tyson and Cayton in February, on the line where the duration would normally go, the words on the contract form were crossed out. A typed line was added saying the contract would run until the expiration of the Tyson-Jacobs contract dated Feb. 12, 1988. That contract was for four years, so this one would run to Feb. 12, 1992. Whether this would constitute a duration for the contract is what the suit is basically about. Tyson Sends Cayton a Letter</p>
        <p>As for Puccio's comment about his client's distress with Tyson, Winston said: ''My client is quite disappointed that things have gotten to this point. He's disappointed that his wife has been attacked, that his mother-in-law has been attacked, that his own intelligence has been attacked. My client has tried to resolve this amicably with very little cooperation from Mr. Cayton.''</p>
        <p>Last Friday, Tyson sent a short letter to Cayton that in effect dismissed him as manager. It said, among other things, ''You are to take no action on my behalf as a boxing manager.''</p>
        <p>''I'm very disappointed in Mike,'' Cayton said at a news conference in Puccio's office at a Wall Street law firm. ''I thought Mike had far greater respect for Jim's memory. I'm outraged.''</p>
        <p>While the legal maneuvering was beginning Monday afternoon, Tyson was visited by Roberto Duran, one of his heroes.</p>
        <p>Tyson had heard that Duran was unable to get a ticket for his heavyweight title fight with Michael Spinks and gave Steve Lott, his assistant manager, $1,500 to buy Duran a ringside seat. Some Hero-Worshipping</p>
        <p>When Duran showed up at Tyson's boardwalk apartment before the fight, Lott walked into Tyson's bedroom and told him, ''There's a guy here that wants to fight you.''</p>
        <p>For just a second Tyson missed the joke. ''Mike got this mean look on his face,'' said Lott. ''He was lying there wrapped in a towel. Then he saw Duran. They'd never met. Mike jumped up out of bed and hugged him. They began talking.'' Tyson, who is a rabid boxing fan, asked Duran in detail about his career. But Duran was as eager to impart to Tyson a few words about the fight against Spinks.</p>
        <p>''Stay calm,'' Duran told him, speaking through an interpreter. ''You don't have to chase him. Spinks will be very nervous. Just walk to him. You'll catch him.''</p>
        <p>As it turned out, Duran was a prophet of the first order.</p>
        <p>The opening bell had barely rung when Tyson began bouncing right hands off Spinks's head. For the rest of Spinks's abbreviated night's work, it would not get any easier for him. Spinks's Tactical Mistake</p>
        <p>For whatever reasons, Spinks decided that he would stand his ground and make a fight of it, as he had promised in prefight remarks. It was a tactical mistake.</p>
        <p>Tyson knocked Spinks to his knees with a left uppercut and right to the body. Spinks got to his feet quickly, by the count of 3, although he took a mandatory 8 count. Then Tyson wasted no time in finishing. A big right hand sent Spinks flat onto his back. The referee, Frank Capuccino, knelt beside Spinks, shouting the count. Spinks tried to get up, rolling to his side, but that was as far as he could get by the time Capuccino's count reached 10.</p>
        <p>As Capuccino was counting, Tyson looked toward Butch Lewis, Spinks's promoter, and ran his gloved hand across his throat. A Prefight Controversy</p>
        <p>Lewis was at the center of a prefight controversy that had delayed the start of the bout. Lewis objected to the procedures for taping Tyson's hands, and it was only after Larry Hazzard, the New Jersey State boxing commissioner, intervened that Spinks headed to the ring.</p>
        <p>''Everyone was screaming,'' said Greg Fritz, a Tyson spokesman who was in the dressing room at the time Lewis entered to protest.</p>
        <p>''As for Mike, you could just see him begin to boil,'' said Fritz. ''He was seething. When Butch Lewis left, Mike began hitting the dressing room walls with his gloves. A series of two, three punches. Then he circled and paced the room.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
