<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Paris Open May Spawn Battle for No. 1 Ranking</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="47" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="397787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="TENNIS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TENNIS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ASSOCIATION OF TENNIS PROFESSIONALS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STOUT, NICK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Tennis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tennis</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE3DF1430F930A35752C1A966958260" item-length="496" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Paris Open May Spawn Battle for No. 1 Ranking</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NICK STOUT, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STOUT, NICK</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, Nov. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It can be argued that something must be askew when the Association of Tennis Professionals Tour's computer awards the top world ranking to a man -- Stefan Edberg, in this case -- who could not get past the first round of the French or United States Opens this year.</p>
        <p>It is indeed being argued that something will definitely be askew if the No. 1 ranking passes to someone -- in this case, Boris Becker -- who failed to claim a winner's trophy at any of this year's Grand Slams: the Australian, the French and the United States Opens and Wimbledon.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It can be argued that something must be askew when the Association of Tennis Professionals Tour's computer awards the top world ranking to a man -- Stefan Edberg, in this case -- who could not get past the first round of the French or United States Opens this year.</p>
        <p>It is indeed being argued that something will definitely be askew if the No. 1 ranking passes to someone -- in this case, Boris Becker -- who failed to claim a winner's trophy at any of this year's Grand Slams: the Australian, the French and the United States Opens and Wimbledon.</p>
        <p>The 24-year-old Edberg has been No. 1 since Aug. 13 after winning at Cincinnati. The Swede, who outdueled Becker to win Wimbledon, has six tournament championships to his credit this year. Good enough, the computer says, for No. 1.</p>
        <p>But the computer says the 22-year-old Becker is within a few of his famous red hairs of being designated the best player in the world. Faulty Programming?</p>
        <p>Ivan Lendl, whom the computer has demoted from No. 1 to No. 3, sees some faulty programming at play. He believes the computer cannot be working properly if it vaults someone without a Grand Slam title to No. 1. And Becker has supported Lendl on this.</p>
        <p>"There is a possibility that I can be No. 1 without winning one Grand Slam, and in a way that's wrong," Becker said the other day when asked to comment on Lendl's remarks.</p>
        <p>The A.T.P. ranks its players according to their best 14 tournaments. Because Edberg has played in 19 so far this year, the Grand Slam lapses in Paris and New York don't really count against him. The number of computer points awarded for Grand Slam excellence is not in proportion to the prestige of the events, so a Grand Slam victory is not essential for a No. 1 ranking. Suspense for the Rivals</p>
        <p>The Edberg-Becker rivalry has put some suspense into the final weeks of the A.T.P. season. After quarterfinal victories Thursday in the Paris Open, the two are on course for a showdown in the final Sunday.</p>
        <p>A victory by Becker here on a fast surface at the Palais Omnisports -- he is the defending champion -- would make the eight-player A.T.P. Championships in Frankfurt, beginning Nov. 13, decisive for the top ranking. Becker holds a career edge, 17-9, over Edberg.</p>
        <p>These aggressive serve-and-volley specialists seem to be at their best when the game is genuine lawn tennis; for three years running, the Wimbledon final has been theirs alone. Becker won Wimbledon in 1985, 1986 and 1989, first against Kevin Curren and then against Lendl and Edberg. Edberg defeated Becker in 1988 and 1990.</p>
        <p>Today, Becker beat his compatriot Michael Stich, 6-1, 6-2, to set up a semifinal match with Jonas Svensson, who defeated Emilio Sanchez, 7-5, 6-4. Edberg stopped Jakob Hlasek, 6-3, 6-4, and, in a curious twist of fate, will play Sergi Bruguera of Spain. The last time the two met, five months ago at the French Open on the other side of town, Bruguera sent Edberg packing after the first round.</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
