<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Those Clapboards! Those Downspouts!</title>
    <meta content="17NJPERSO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1665516"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="IN PERSON"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bergen County (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rankin, Betty</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rockland, Kate</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/Regions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E5DA103EF934A25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1348" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Those Clapboards! Those Downspouts!</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KATE ROCKLAND</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rockland, Kate</byline>
      <dateline>TENAFLY</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of and interview with Betty Rankin, 70, who specializes in bringing together homeowners and their houses, mostly in Bergen County, NJ, with film companies that shoot movies and television commercials; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BETTY RANKIN wants to make you a star. Well, really, she wants to make your house a star. Think of her as the Swifty Lazar of real estate.</p>
        <p>Working mostly in Bergen County, Ms. Rankin specializes in bringing together homeowners and their houses with film companies that are shooting movies and television commercials. The studios on her speed dial include Paramount and Screen Gems.Darting about her ''studio zone'' recently, checking on her properties like a hunter checking traps, Ms. Rankin, who is 70, was swathed in purple, including purple eye shadow and purple lipstick. But don't let the lavender or her Mary Poppins sweetness fool you; her work ethic is pure Trump-like steel. Without irony, she calls this ''ruling with a velvet glove.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BETTY RANKIN wants to make you a star. Well, really, she wants to make your house a star. Think of her as the Swifty Lazar of real estate.</p>
        <p>Working mostly in Bergen County, Ms. Rankin specializes in bringing together homeowners and their houses with film companies that are shooting movies and television commercials. The studios on her speed dial include Paramount and Screen Gems.Darting about her ''studio zone'' recently, checking on her properties like a hunter checking traps, Ms. Rankin, who is 70, was swathed in purple, including purple eye shadow and purple lipstick. But don't let the lavender or her Mary Poppins sweetness fool you; her work ethic is pure Trump-like steel. Without irony, she calls this ''ruling with a velvet glove.''</p>
        <p>Maureen O'Connor's 19th-century farmhouse in Demarest is one of the staples of Ms. Rankin's stable. The farmhouse has appeared in more than 40 television commercials since Ms. O'Connor signed on with Ms. Rankin, who has upward of 350 houses on her roster and is always looking for more.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Connor says her house is now ''an inch thicker on all the walls due to how many times they've been painted for different shoots.''</p>
        <p>And what kinds of commercials get shot? Think back to all those warm, cozy family settings in ads that feature cellphones, pizza deliveries and professional athletes serving up corny public service messages. They were filmed by directors who passed up on fake sets because they wanted to get that deep feeling of family togetherness. Or, as Ms. Rankin puts it, they wanted a set that already felt ''lived in.''</p>
        <p>As a young woman living in Tenafly many years ago, Ms. Rankin's life couldn't have been further from the glamour of Hollywood and the bustle of Madison Avenue. She admits, though, that she has ''always been starstruck,'' and has watched ''Gone With the Wind'' more times than she can count just to see the house used in it. And she recalls the open archways and furnishings used in the family saga ''Giant'' (1956) as if she were describing her own living room.</p>
        <p>While raising two daughters, Ms. Rankin worked as a volunteer at her church and at Englewood Hospital. But when her best friend, Judy Mettler, died, Ms. Rankin began helping Ms. Mettler's daughter run the family business: finding homes to be used in movie shoots. When the daughter wanted to move on, Ms. Rankin bought the business in 1984.</p>
        <p>These days, Ms. Rankin can often be found either whipping around Tenafly in her Volvo wagon on the way to solving some filming mishap, or up to her elbows in dirt with her garden club. Her 10-year-old cocker spaniel, Tucker, (''He's 10 years young!'') is permanently perched on the passenger seat.</p>
        <p>A typical day for Ms. Rankin starts with a call from a studio, telling her what kind of set they need. ''Saturday Night Live'' recently called, asking for a hunting lodge with dead animals on the walls. ''They're so crazy'' Ms. Rankin, said, laughing. Next, she mentally flipped through her homes. ''I have a fantastic memory,'' she added. In the old days, studios would have to take a look at portfolios that Ms. Rankin kept in New York. Now, they can access her Web site, bettyrankin.com, to take a look at photographs of potential shooting sites.</p>
        <p>To visit the Web site is to live the vicarious suburban dream: kitchens, living rooms and houses that wouldn't be out of place on ''Desperate Housewives.''</p>
        <p>She suggests homes, and sets about calling owners to let them know that location scouts will drop letters in their mailboxes and ring doorbells. If they are willing to have their home used, they are added to a list the director will flip through and decide if the property is ''shoot accessible.'' This means that the floors can support thousands of pounds of equipment, the neighbors will not complain and the town has agreed to issue a permit.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rankin has an innate sense of how each town will react to a shoot. ''If a community wishes not to let studios film, they charge such a large permit fee to the studios the studios take their business elsewhere,'' she said. ''We have to keep the neighbors happy.'' And why would residents of Bergen County towns like Englewood, Tenafly and Demarest agree to let the studios wreak havoc on their azaleas? ''It's recognition that you own this beautiful house,'' one Englewood resident said. Then there's the roughly $3,000 a day. That's serious extra money for college tuitions, family vacations, or a new roof.</p>
        <p>Some families are so used to the chaos that filming brings that they have created noise-free rooms where their children do homework after school. The rooms come complete with fold-out beds, should the shoot go deep into the night and the children can't get upstairs to their bedrooms.</p>
        <p>Ms. O'Connor's teenage daughter, Devon, is a pro: ''We started doing this when I was in the third grade,'' she said. ''So to me, it's normal. Now when I'm on the phone with my friends, I'm like, 'Yeah, there are some dudes downstairs shooting a Verizon commercial.' And they'll be like, 'What?'''</p>
        <p>Over the decades, Ms. Rankin has developed a keen eye for trouble. She once had to suggest to a movie studio that it fire a male scout who made improper advances toward a female homeowner.</p>
        <p>She also knows her clients' limits. ''If a family only wants their first floor used,'' she said, ''I make sure the director knows the second floor is not to be used.'' Before studios outlawed smoking on set, she would drive to her houses and tack up ''No Smoking'' signs.</p>
        <p>''You really have to understand the business because it is not fair to the homeowner if you don't,'' Ms. Rankin said.</p>
        <p>The relationship between Ms. Rankin and her army of homeowners is special. They trust her to bring only reliable studio crews. And the studios trust her to not suggest nervous nellies who hover. ''I've had to drop friends of mine from my roster,'' Ms. Rankin said, ''because they made ridiculous demands on the crews, such as insisting they use the family's vacuum to clean up the place.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Rankin says she tries to only uses families who are very laid-back, given the unpredictable nature of the entertainment business.</p>
        <p>And what about on the movie star side of the ledger? She admitted that Robert DeNiro was something of a prima donna: ''He was doing something for 'Saturday Night Live,' and they wanted him in a garage setting. I found him this fabulous four-car garage in Englewood that was just perfect, but he wouldn't come. He said New Jersey was too far away.''</p>
        <p>As the day wound down, Ms. Rankin pulled up to her own house, once the setting of an ADT ad where a ''thief'' repeatedly climbed into her windows and ruined a perfectly good pair of her curtains. As Ms. Rankin shook her head over that incident, a large buck suddenly materialized from the woods and silently watched her and Tucker.</p>
        <p>''Woody Allen acted just like that deer when he was scouting for a house in Englewood to film 'Annie Hall''' Ms. Rankin said in a stage whisper. ''He'd just stand at the edge of people's driveways surrounded by his entourage and stare.''</p>
        <p>IN PERSON</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
