<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Taxes Must Be Paid, But Why All at Once?</title>
    <meta content="17WETAX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1665497"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="MUNICIPALITIES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Greenburgh (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feiner, Paul (Supervisor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Medina, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050417T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D05E1DD103EF934A25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="706" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Taxes Must Be Paid, But Why All at Once?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER MEDINA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Medina, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Supervisor Paul Feiner of Greenburgh, NY, suggests making higher taxes more palatable by changing date when local taxes are due or, better yet, spreading county, fire, sewer and town taxes over two payments, the way school taxes are paid, and allowing local governments to hire outside companies to collect payments online; changing date would require action from Board of Legislators (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>JUST as the federal income-tax checks are mailed off, the latest property-tax bills are arriving at homes across Westchester County. Meanwhile, several towns are considering their budgets. Not surprisingly, many include hefty tax levies. Larchmont, Tarrytown, Irvington and in Port Chester are facing double-digit increases -- in Port Chester, it may be as much as 19.9 percent. A 9.5-percent tax increase is on the table in Briarcliff Manor. That's enough to make anyone's wallet feel lighter.</p>
        <p>But Supervisor Paul J. Feiner of Greenburgh has come up with an idea that he suggests will make higher taxes more palatable: Why not change the date when local taxes are due? Better yet, Mr. Feiner says, why not spread out county, fire, sewer and town taxes over two payments, the way school taxes are paid? Think of it as a tax plan on layaway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>JUST as the federal income-tax checks are mailed off, the latest property-tax bills are arriving at homes across Westchester County. Meanwhile, several towns are considering their budgets. Not surprisingly, many include hefty tax levies. Larchmont, Tarrytown, Irvington and in Port Chester are facing double-digit increases -- in Port Chester, it may be as much as 19.9 percent. A 9.5-percent tax increase is on the table in Briarcliff Manor. That's enough to make anyone's wallet feel lighter.</p>
        <p>But Supervisor Paul J. Feiner of Greenburgh has come up with an idea that he suggests will make higher taxes more palatable: Why not change the date when local taxes are due? Better yet, Mr. Feiner says, why not spread out county, fire, sewer and town taxes over two payments, the way school taxes are paid? Think of it as a tax plan on layaway.</p>
        <p>Mr. Feiner might have a reputation for slightly over-the-top ideas, but his other tax-related proposals have caught on in the county.</p>
        <p>Last year, Greenburgh became one of several towns in Westchester to allow residents to pay taxes online. Yonkers is following suit this year, joining a growing list of municipalities nationwide.</p>
        <p>''For a lot of people, having so many of the same obligations is tough,'' Mr. Feiner said. ''Having this in another month when there aren't so many bills wouldn't be a big deal for the government.'' Changing the due date for county taxes would require action from the Board of Legislators. Bill Ryan, the legislature's chairman, said that he is more concerned with stemming tax increases than changing the dates when payments must be made.</p>
        <p>''The idea is always to create some kind of taxpayer relief,'' Mr. Ryan said. ''But I think that comes more with lowering taxes than splitting the overall bill.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Feiner said that he proposed the same idea when he was on the board more than two decades ago. ''The concept didn't go anywhere, but it wasn't a big deal then, when local taxes weren't as significant,'' he said. ''Now we're talking about a big dollar amount.''</p>
        <p>But no county legislation is necessary for local governments to hire an outside company to collect payments online. Link2Gov, the Nashville-based company that Yonkers hired, says that the number of local governments using its service has more than doubled in the last two years.</p>
        <p>''This is the new wave,'' said Deputy Mayor William Regan of Yonkers. ''It makes it easier for us to collect and easier for them to pay. It's a convenience thing, really.'' Within the next several months, the city plans to make it possible for residents to pay water bills and parking tickets through the Web site, he said.</p>
        <p>Because there is no wait for bank checks to clear, the online process allows governments to collect the money more quickly and saves time on paperwork, officials say. And most major credit cards are accepted, usually with a 3 percent fee on the total payment.</p>
        <p>Although the Town of Eastchester has allowed residents to pay tax bills online by credit card for the last five years, only a handful have done so, said Bert Abrams, who has been the town's receiver of taxes since 1972.</p>
        <p>''I don't think it's the greatest thing in the world,'' he said. ''When you start getting into fees that high, you're going to get people in trouble.''</p>
        <p>Still, in an era when everything from phone and electricity bills to books and video rentals are paid for online, such payments may appeal most to those who welcome any chance to avoid writing a check and affixing a postage stamp.</p>
        <p>In Greenburgh, about $230,000 had been collected from online payments during the first week in April, officials said. ''People have to pay their taxes,'' Mr. Feiner said, ''but if there's a way to make it easier, we should do that.''</p>
        <p>MUNICIPALITIES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
