<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Dinkins Encourages Council to Retain His Key Programs</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="657540"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINDER, ALAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FINDER, ALAN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DINKINS, DAVID N (MAYOR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GIULIANI, RUDOLPH W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DF113AF931A15751C1A965958260" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Dinkins Encourages Council to Retain His Key Programs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FINDER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FINDER, ALAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Striving to define and protect his legacy, Mayor David N. Dinkins appealed to the City Council yesterday to preserve the liberal programs he initiated from what he called "the very different ideology and philosophy" of Mayor-elect Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>In a speech before the Council -- his last formal address before he leaves office in nine days -- Mr. Dinkins was by turns conciliatory and biting. He appealed to New Yorkers to put aside the racial and political divisiveness of the mayoral campaign and to Mr. Giuliani to bring the city together and "make us proud."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Striving to define and protect his legacy, Mayor David N. Dinkins appealed to the City Council yesterday to preserve the liberal programs he initiated from what he called "the very different ideology and philosophy" of Mayor-elect Rudolph W. Giuliani.</p>
        <p>In a speech before the Council -- his last formal address before he leaves office in nine days -- Mr. Dinkins was by turns conciliatory and biting. He appealed to New Yorkers to put aside the racial and political divisiveness of the mayoral campaign and to Mr. Giuliani to bring the city together and "make us proud."</p>
        <p>He also chided the Mayor-elect, in an indirect reference to the incident last week in which Mr. Giuliani argued forcefully with the supervisor of an ambulance crew over where to take a young patient. Mr. Dinkins said it was important for the city to rely on experts and to learn from them. "To be a good hands-on mayor, you've got to know when to take your hands off," Mr. Dinkins said.</p>
        <p>For most of his unusual 20-minute farewell address, the Mayor concentrated on stating his broad political philosophy and laying out what he views as the prime accomplishments of his four-year tenure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dinkins, a Democrat, told the overwhelmingly Democratic Council members, who greeted him with a standing ovation, that he was counting on them to preserve programs that he thinks constitute his legacy. These include the police expansion, known as Safe Streets, Safe City, the creation of new primary-care health clinics in poor neighborhoods, called Communicare, the all-civilian police review board and the awarding of more city contracts to companies owned by women and minority-group members.</p>
        <p>"We've shared goals," the Mayor told the Council. "We've shared dreams. We've shared solutions.</p>
        <p>"I'd like to think that the same will be said for the next four years. But the chances are, the same will not be said. The fact is, New York City has elected a mayor with a very different ideology and philosophy than any we have seen in City Hall in recent decades. Now more than ever, New Yorkers will look to their Council to protect the most proudly progressive government on God's earth."</p>
        <p>Clearly concerned that Mr. Giuliani -- a Republican-Liberal who was elected on a promise to shrink significantly the size of city government and to change the way it does business -- would dismantle much of the liberal social agenda Mr. Dinkins helped to create, the Mayor called repeatedly on the Council to resist what he called "change for the sake of change." Moving Forward With Caution</p>
        <p>"It's up to you to move our city forward, without unraveling past success," Mr. Dinkins said at one point.</p>
        <p>"If I've made mistakes -- and I know I have -- then I want my successor to correct those mistakes, as I tried to correct the mistakes of my predecessor," he said a few minutes later. "But the greatest disservice we can do is to dismantle a good and effective program -- to uproot a careful investment in our children, and our future -- simply because it bears the imprint of David Dinkins."</p>
        <p>The Mayor also encouraged the Council to protect the members of municipal unions, whose leaders he infuriated on Monday when he declined to press for a bill to slow down anticipated efforts by Mr. Giuliani to contract out some city services to private companies.</p>
        <p>And Mr. Dinkins, New York's first black mayor, asked Council members to help insure that black and Hispanic New Yorkers, as well as gay and lesbian and disabled residents, continue to be drawn into a city government so that "our government looks like the people we govern." 'No Overwhelming Mandate'</p>
        <p>While he seldom said so directly, the Mayor appeared determined to alert the Council to what he sees as the likelihood that Mr. Giuliani will want to undo much of what Mr. Dinkins has done. The Mayor suggested that the results of the close mayoral election should provide Democratic Council members with the political muscle to preserve the city's liberal political tradition.</p>
        <p>"You see, there was no overwhelming mandate -- of defeat or of victory," he said. "Our electorate was divided -- by ideology and by race.</p>
        <p>"But you, the City Council, can help to see that the city is not divided. You can help to insure that our leadership spends less time appealing to those who already support them, and more time reaching out to those who did not."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
