<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Washington Wines Get to the Big City</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="657577"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON (STATE)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931222T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDC153CF931A15751C1A965958260" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Washington Wines Get to the Big City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD G. GOLDBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDBERG, HOWARD G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN Christopher Camarda is not waiting on tables five nights a week at Il Bistro, a restaurant in the Pike Place Market in Seattle, he makes wine, mostly red. If things continue to go right, within a year he'll just do wine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Camarda's boutique winery in Seattle is named Andrew Will, after his nephew and his son. His production is tiny -- 1,800 cases a year -- and the word has got around Seattle that his Bordeaux-like cabernet sauvignon and his merlot are fine. "The '90 cabernet and '91 merlot sold out within a few months," he said on Monday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN Christopher Camarda is not waiting on tables five nights a week at Il Bistro, a restaurant in the Pike Place Market in Seattle, he makes wine, mostly red. If things continue to go right, within a year he'll just do wine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Camarda's boutique winery in Seattle is named Andrew Will, after his nephew and his son. His production is tiny -- 1,800 cases a year -- and the word has got around Seattle that his Bordeaux-like cabernet sauvignon and his merlot are fine. "The '90 cabernet and '91 merlot sold out within a few months," he said on Monday.</p>
        <p>The word hasn't got to New York, although his '90 cabernet has. Wines from Washington's small producers often pass unnoticed in the glutted New York market. Too bad. They taste good.</p>
        <p>Since the late 1980's, New Yorkers' ideas about Washington wines have been shaped by such familiar brands as Arbor Crest, Barnard Griffin, Chateau Ste. Michelle, Columbia, Columbia Crest, Covey Run and Hogue. But together with such excellent small houses as Leonetti and Woodward Canyon, known mainly to buffs, they form only a part of the 25-year-old story of the state's wine industry.</p>
        <p>Evidently, bottles from very few of Washington's 74 small wineries can be found in New York effortlessly. The wines from five producers that are nearly invisible here and one that enjoys cult status were tasted this week, with pleasure.</p>
        <p>The producers are Andrew Will; Hedges Cellars (medium-sized, with 38,000 cases a year); L'Ecole No. 41 (5,000); Silver Lake (8,000) and Waterbrook (28,000). The producer whose cabernet sauvignons have a cult following is Quilceda Creek (1,400), made by Alex Golitzin, a chemical engineer, and his son, Paul. The elder Golitzin's uncle and adviser is the legendary California enologist Andre Tchelistcheff.</p>
        <p>The six represent a cross section of winery sizes, and were chosen because their distributors are listed in a catalogue that merchants and restaurateurs use. Of 31 varietals and blends tasted, the following were standouts. Prices are listed only for available wines; the unpriced wines will arrive in coming months.</p>
        <p>WHITE -- Hedges, 1992 fume-chardonnay ($11) and '92 Red Mountain Reserve White Wine; L'Ecole No. 41, 1992 chardonnay; Silver Lake, 1992 regular and reserve chardonnays, '91 regular ($11) and reserve chardonnays, '89 chardonnay reserve ($15), '92 dry riesling ($7) and '91 sauvignon blanc ($8), and Waterbrook, 1992 regular ($10) and reserve chardonnays and '91 sauvignon blanc ($9).</p>
        <p>RED -- Andrew Will, 1990 cabernet ($28); Hedges, 1992 cabernet-merlot ($11) and '89 Red Mountain Reserve Red Wine ($14); L'Ecole No. 41, 1990 cabernet ($21); Silver Lake, 1990 merlot and '89 cabernet reserve; Waterbrook, 1991 merlot, and Quilceda Creek, 1990 cabernet ($30).</p>
        <p>With 11,500 acres of European wine grapes in production, Washington produces the second largest quantity of vinifera wine in the United States after California.</p>
        <p>Washington's whites and reds have identifiable personalities that distinguish them from those of California and Bordeaux. A buoyant fruitiness comes through unless misguided cellar methods submerge the flavors in the oakiness of new barrels.</p>
        <p>The normally high acidity gives a mouth-watering snap to the wines, and the typically heady alcohol (over 13 percent) tends to leave an afterburn on the palate and lips. These effects are buffered if Washington wines are harmonized with food.</p>
        <p>A number of small brands are likely to turn up in New York soon. Since 1984, out-of-state sales have grown steadily, dipping only in 1992 because of a meager 1991 harvest, said Simon Siegl, executive director of the Washington Wine Commission, a trade association. Retailers who do not stock Washington wines can obtain them within a day or two from distributors.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
