<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fireworks in Deep Space as Two Galaxies Collide</title>
    <meta content="T22AST$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="24" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="967070"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hubble Space Telescope</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hubble Space Telescope</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stars and Galaxies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telescopes and Observatories</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9902E2DD153EF931A15753C1A961958260" item-length="854" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fireworks in Deep Space as Two Galaxies Collide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New pictures from Hubble Space Telescope give astronomers striking views of birth of millions of stars triggered by collision of two nearby galaxies (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New pictures from the Hubble Space Telescope have given astronomers striking views of stellar birth triggered by the collision of two nearby galaxies -- and perhaps a glimpse of what could be in store for the  Milky Way galaxy in about five billion years.</p>
        <p>The telescope, which orbits Earth, has produced the most detailed pictures yet of a galactic collision, showing the blue light of hot stars bursting to life like the brilliant finale to a Fourth of July fireworks display. As the two galaxies -- called the Antennae -- come together, the merging of gravitational forces compresses clouds of hydrogen gas, which then collapse into dense spheres glowing with thermonuclear energy: stars, millions of them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New pictures from the Hubble Space Telescope have given astronomers striking views of stellar birth triggered by the collision of two nearby galaxies -- and perhaps a glimpse of what could be in store for the  Milky Way galaxy in about five billion years.</p>
        <p>The telescope, which orbits Earth, has produced the most detailed pictures yet of a galactic collision, showing the blue light of hot stars bursting to life like the brilliant finale to a Fourth of July fireworks display. As the two galaxies -- called the Antennae -- come together, the merging of gravitational forces compresses clouds of hydrogen gas, which then collapse into dense spheres glowing with thermonuclear energy: stars, millions of them.</p>
        <p>Astronomers reported yesterday that they had counted more than a thousand clusters of newborn stars in the center of the merging galaxies. The brightest of the clusters probably contains at least one million young stars. Ground-based telescopes are able to see only the brightest of these clusters and cannot see any detail.</p>
        <p>''The sheer number of these young star clusters is amazing,'' said Dr. Bradley Whitmore, an astronomer at the Space Telescope Science Institute in Baltimore. He and Dr. Francois Schweizer of the Carnegie Institution of Washington announced the findings at a news conference at the National Aeronautics and Space Administration in Washington.</p>
        <p>They and other astronomers said the observations should provide insights into the turbulent early history of the universe and the evolution of large structures like galaxies, congregations of billions of stars.</p>
        <p>Before these pictures, said Dr. Bruce Margon, an astronomer at the University of Washington in Seattle, scientists relied primarily on computer simulations to depict the turbulent forces and creation of new structures that result from galactic mergers. The Hubble pictures showed a surprisingly chaotic environment, he said, that ''tells us how naive the computer simulations were.''</p>
        <p>Other Hubble telescope pictures have shown nearly one-third of the most distant galaxies, the ones that existed earliest in time, undergoing similar mergers. That is not surprising because the universe was denser then and has been expanding since.</p>
        <p>But most of these galactic mergers have occurred too far away to be studied in detail, and collisions are rarer in the more attenuated universe today. Still, astronomers focused the Hubble on two nearby colliding groups of stars, in galaxies that are called the Antennae because the pair of long tails of luminous matter formed by the collision resembles an insect's whiskery antenna. The Antennae are close by cosmic standards, 63 million light-years away in the southern constellation Corvus. Dr. Schweizer said the observations should help clarify how especially large star clusters, known as globular clusters, formed from giant hydrogen clouds. Most globular clusters appear to be among the oldest objects in the universe. Now it seems that some are emerging out of recent galactic collisions.</p>
        <p>Examining the new pictures, astronomers could not resist the notion that they might be seeing into the distant future. They have long known that the Milky Way and the neighboring Andromeda galaxy could be moving on a collision course.</p>
        <p>''It's pretty speculative,'' Dr. Whitmore said in an interview. ''But there's a reasonable chance that it might happen, and we should know in about 10 years.''</p>
        <p>The Milky Way and Andromeda are approaching each other with a speed of 300,000 miles an hour. They are now 2.2 million light-years apart, which is roughly 20 times the diameter of the Milky Way. Andromeda appears as a smudge of light in the northern autumn sky.</p>
        <p>Whether the two eventually collide depends on the angle at which Andromeda is heading this way. If it is coming straight at the Milky Way, there will be a head-on collision in five billion years. A direct collision would lead to a grand merger between the two galaxies that would take several billion years to complete. If its course is not straight-on, Andromeda might only sideswipe the Milky Way or miss it altogether.</p>
        <p>In 2005, NASA plans to launch the Space Interferometry Mission, a spacecraft carrying an array of telescopes that should quickly determine, among other things, the exact angle of Andromeda's approach.</p>
        <p>Not that an impending galactic smash-up would ever be a matter of urgency for humans. By then, the Sun would have burned out and the Earth reduced to a lifeless cinder. With their wide separations, stars and any of their planetary systems might escape direct hits.</p>
        <p>But the sky would change, astronomers said. New stars would flare, but their lives would probably be short, as they self-destructed in a few million years, with supernovas popping off like firecrackers. New patterns of stars and dust clouds would take shape, and gone would be the familiar arc of dust and light in the night sky, a major belt of the Milky Way. The old and new stars of the two galaxies, once spiral-shaped like pinwheels, would become a single elliptical-shaped galaxy.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
