<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I.B.M. Reports a Loss but Its Shares Rise</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="799565"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY REPORTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS MACHINES CORP (IBM)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOTUS DEVELOPMENTCORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMPAQ COMPUTER CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ZUCKERMAN, LAURENCE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAN, G RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Statistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19951018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E5D61039F93BA25753C1A963958260" item-length="903" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I.B.M. Reports a Loss but Its Shares Rise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURENCE ZUCKERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ZUCKERMAN, LAURENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I.B.M. reported disappointing third-quarter results yesterday, but its stock  surged anyway, fueled both by a rally in technology stocks and by a surprisingly strong performance by G. Richard Thoman, the company's new chief financial officer, at a meeting of Wall Street analysts.</p>
        <p>After a $1.8 billion charge for the acquisition of the Lotus Development Corporation last summer, the International Business Machines Corporation posted  a net loss of $538 million, or 96 cents a share. Excluding that charge, income for the quarter was $1.3 billion, or $2.30 a share, up from $710 million, or $1.18 a share, in the corresponding period last year, but below the average estimate of $2.42 a share made by 19 analysts surveyed by First Call Inc.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I.B.M. reported disappointing third-quarter results yesterday, but its stock  surged anyway, fueled both by a rally in technology stocks and by a surprisingly strong performance by G. Richard Thoman, the company's new chief financial officer, at a meeting of Wall Street analysts.</p>
        <p>After a $1.8 billion charge for the acquisition of the Lotus Development Corporation last summer, the International Business Machines Corporation posted  a net loss of $538 million, or 96 cents a share. Excluding that charge, income for the quarter was $1.3 billion, or $2.30 a share, up from $710 million, or $1.18 a share, in the corresponding period last year, but below the average estimate of $2.42 a share made by 19 analysts surveyed by First Call Inc.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, the company's stock gained $2.875, to $96.875, on the New York Stock Exchange, still well below its high of $114.625 reached two months ago.</p>
        <p>The Compaq Computer Corporation also posted disappointing quarterly results early yesterday, but its shares surged as well, gaining $3, to $51.375, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>Addressing the slide in I.B.M.'s share price, Mr. Thoman told the analysts at the meeting and others listening in by telephone that the company was misunderstood by investors and vowed to do a better job of promoting its strengths. It didn't take long.</p>
        <p>"The call turned the stock around," said James J. Cramer, a money manager based in New Yorkwho listened to Mr. Thoman's presentation. "The stock was pretty much in free fall before the meeting began. He did a very good job."</p>
        <p>The meeting was Mr. Thoman's first appearance before analysts since replacing Jerome B. York, the respected cost-cutter who left I.B.M. last month to help the billionaire investor Kirk Kerkorian wring more value out of his large stake in the Chrysler Corporation.</p>
        <p>I.B.M.'s stock had been on an upward course during the summer, and news of Mr. York's departure sent it plunging; yesterday, investors appeared to be reassured that the company had found a worthy successor.</p>
        <p>An overall rally in technology stocks also helped the stock.</p>
        <p>I.B.M.'s third-quarter performance was weakest in the key area of hardware sales. After showing substantial growth in the first half of the year, hardware  revenue was virtually flat in the quarter that ended Sept. 30. Sales of mainframe computers were pinched by a shortage of a key power supply unit. A forthcoming makeover of the company's highly profitable AS/400 mid-range computers delayed potential buyers, and the company's troubled personal computer business continued to lose market share.</p>
        <p>Revenue from the company's fast-growing service businesses took up some of the slack, but the quarterly earnings still came in at the low end of Wall Street's estimates, even after most analysts lowered their forecasts following strong hints from the company that business was off.</p>
        <p>I.B.M, based in Armonk, N.Y., said it would take a charge of $800 million next quarter to defray the costs of further job reductions and the consolidation of office space and other sites.</p>
        <p>Mr. Thoman declined to say how many jobs would be eliminated and added that the company did not plan any plant closings. Nevertheless, the charge appeared to assure analysts that he would be as serious about reducing expenses as was his hard-charging predecessor.</p>
        <p>Many analysts said that Mr. Thoman appeared to be more self-effacing and thoughtful than Mr. York, and that those traits seemed better suited to the company's new emphasis on revenue growth now that most of the painful cuts have  been made.</p>
        <p>But not every analyst was sold by the presentation, which contained more promises than details. "He is bothered by fact that I.B.M. stock carries a low valuation and thinks it is a public relations problem," said William J. Milton,  an analyst at Brown Brothers Harriman. "Show us how you are going to sustain a rate of growth approaching that of the industry, and we will give you a higher multiple."</p>
        <p>Compaq, based in Houston, apparently had similar luck convincing analysts and investors to look forward rather than back. The company reported that its net income rose 21.9 percent, to $245 million, or 89 cents a share, up from $201 million, or 75 cents, in the comparable quarter in 1994. Wall Street had expected the company to earn 92 cents a share, based on a survey by First Call.  Gross profit margins were also disappointing, falling slightly below the company's target of 23 to 24 percent.</p>
        <p>Executives said the weaker-than-expected performance resulted from a delay in getting the company's new LTE 5000 high-end laptop computer to market during the quarter. Relatively poor sales in Europe, where Compaq can command higher profit margins than in other parts of the world, also hurt, they said.</p>
        <p>But the company said that demand for the rest of the year was strong and that it was poised to cash in on a strong holiday season with a new line of multimedia home computers. "We are carrying over a very healthy backlog into the fourth quarter," David J. Schempf, vice president and corporate controller and treasurer, said in an interview. "We're optimistic."</p>
        <p>COMPANY REPORTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
