<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Captains Import Players for Nationals</title>
    <meta content="11CARD$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1374888"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="BRIDGE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Truscott, Alan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Crossword and Games/Bridge</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridge (Card Game)</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020311T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E7DB1639F932A25750C0A9649C8B63" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Captains Import Players for Nationals</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alan Truscott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Truscott, Alan</byline>
      <dateline>HOUSTON, March 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alan Truscott Bridge column notes nine top seeds in American Contract Bridge League's Vanderbilt Knockout Teams competition are foreigners; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Invaders from Europe are sure to carry off some booty at the American Contract Bridge League's Spring Nationals here this week. In the Vanderbilt Knockout Teams which begins today, the nine top seeds include players from Poland, Russia, Italy, Norway and Britain, although all the teams are led by Americans.</p>
        <p>These teams, by captain, are:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Invaders from Europe are sure to carry off some booty at the American Contract Bridge League's Spring Nationals here this week. In the Vanderbilt Knockout Teams which begins today, the nine top seeds include players from Poland, Russia, Italy, Norway and Britain, although all the teams are led by Americans.</p>
        <p>These teams, by captain, are:</p>
        <p>First: Jack Coleman of San Francisco</p>
        <p>Second: Nick Nickell of Manhattan</p>
        <p>Third: George Jacobs of Burr Ridge, Ill.</p>
        <p>Fourth: James Cayne of Manhattan</p>
        <p>Fifth: Steve Robinson of Arlington, Va.</p>
        <p>Sixth: Richard Schwartz of East Elmhurst, Queens</p>
        <p>Seventh: Rose Meltzer of Los Gatos, Calif.</p>
        <p>Eighth: Rita Shugart of Pebble Beach, Calif.</p>
        <p>Ninth: Reese Milner of Los Angeles</p>
        <p>The Norwegians struck first, with a victory in the Open Pairs on Saturday night. The standings were:</p>
        <p>First: Joergen Molberg and Boerre Lund of Trondheim, Norway, 2,125.68 match points</p>
        <p>Second: David Berkowitz of Old Tappan, N.J., and Larry Cohen of Boca Raton, Fla., 2,092.3</p>
        <p>Third: Nickell and Richard Freeman of Atlanta, 2,044.63</p>
        <p>The diagramed deal, from the earlier North American Pairs Championship, offered a difficult test for a defender. Lyle Poe of Columbia, Md., sitting South, landed in six diamonds after his partner had made a negative double of a three-spade overcall.</p>
        <p>He won the opening spade lead with dummy's ace and immediately led a low heart. This put East to the test, and he snatched his heart king. This normal play was fatal. A spade return was ruffed in dummy and two rounds of trumps were drawn with the king and queen. A heart was played to the queen and ace. The heart nine was led, and a club discarded when East played low. Another heart was led, and a ruff removed East's 10.</p>
        <p>Dummy was entered with a diamond to the ace, removing the last trump, and a club was discarded on a heart winner. The club finesse gave South his slam.</p>
        <p>After the opening spade lead, there were ways to make six diamonds without a defensive error. For example, South could have led the club queen for an immediate winning finesse. Then he could have cashed the king and queen of diamonds, ruffed a spade, and led a heart to the ace with a heart to follow. If West won this trick, he would have been endplayed: a spade return would permit a club discard from the dummy. And if East took his king, collecting his partner's queen, he would have been exposed to a ruffing finesse to establish two heart tricks in the dummy.</p>
        <p>The Charity Game of the American Contract Bridge League will be played on Wednesday at clubs throughout North America, including these in the New York metropolitan area:</p>
        <p>Manhattan: Honors, 115 East 57th Street</p>
        <p>Manhattan, 27 West 72nd Street</p>
        <p>Staten Island: Bridge Club of Staten Island, 444 Manor Road</p>
        <p>Richmond County Country Club, 135 Flagg Place</p>
        <p>Long Island: FrankLin, 340 Dogwood Avenue, Franklin Square</p>
        <p>Westchester-Rockland: Bridge Deck, 313 Central Avenue, Scarsdale</p>
        <p>Rockland, 27 Kennedy Drive, Spring Valley</p>
        <p>New Jersey: Glen Rock, 230 West Passaic Street, Maywood</p>
        <p>Plaza, 257 Prospect Avenue, West Orange</p>
        <p>BRIDGE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
