<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Long After Pitch 162, Leiter Finds His Way</title>
    <meta content="26LEIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1027457"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Toronto Blue Jays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9403EED71F3CF935A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1066" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Long After Pitch 162, Leiter Finds His Way</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JASON DIAMOS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Al Leiter walks to the mound at Shea Stadium tonight in the emotionally charged atmosphere of a house packed with Mets and Yankees fans, he will be excited as ever.</p>
        <p>But not because of some vendetta Leiter has against the Yankees, the team that traded him to the Toronto Blue Jays nine years ago after a 162-pitch outing in damp weather that Leiter believes contributed to his ensuing arm trouble.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Al Leiter walks to the mound at Shea Stadium tonight in the emotionally charged atmosphere of a house packed with Mets and Yankees fans, he will be excited as ever.</p>
        <p>But not because of some vendetta Leiter has against the Yankees, the team that traded him to the Toronto Blue Jays nine years ago after a 162-pitch outing in damp weather that Leiter believes contributed to his ensuing arm trouble.</p>
        <p>The 32-year-old left-hander simply gets pumped up every time he takes the mound.</p>
        <p>''I want to stick it to every team I pitch against, not just the Yankees,'' said Leiter, who will bring an earned run average of 1.60, the best in the major leagues, into tonight's opener of this much-anticipated three-game series.</p>
        <p>If this were 1989, or even some time in the early 1990's, Leiter admitted, he might feel differently.</p>
        <p>Leiter, from Toms River, N.J., was touted as the next Ron Guidry or Dave Righetti when he made his major league debut in Yankee pinstripes in 1987 as a skinny 21-year-old who was prone to blisters on his pitching hand. Since then, he has been through so much that he has put behind him that cold spring evening in 1989 when Dallas Green, then the Yankee manager, left him out for 162 pitches.</p>
        <p>After one more start as a Yankee, Leiter was dealt to the Blue Jays for Jesse Barfield. After another start, Leiter began to develop the arm troubles that derailed his career for the next three years.</p>
        <p>Leiter said: ''I could say, 'I shouldn't have stayed in that game. I should have mentioned something to the pitching coach.' But I really try to base my life on right now, today. And I think I've always been that way.''</p>
        <p>Since then Leiter has won three World Series rings: two with the Blue Jays, one last season with the Florida Marlins, when he started Game 7 and gave his team a chance to win -- which it did in extra innings. He has pitched a no-hitter. He has pitched in an All-Star Game.</p>
        <p>His redemption extends beyond the baseball field. Leiter has also watched his older brother, Mark, recover from the devastating tragedy of losing an infant son in the spring of 1994 to resurrect his career as the Phillies' current closer at the age of 35. It was Al Leiter who helped resuscitate his older brother's career when he persuaded the Yankees to take a look at Mark and give him his second chance in baseball after Mark, too, had arm troubles. ''By all rights, he's lucky to be playing,'' said the younger brother. ''And here he is having a career year.''</p>
        <p>They both are. Leiter not only leads the majors in e.r.a., but he also takes a 9-3 record and a six-game winning streak into tonight's game.</p>
        <p>In all, Leiter has faced the Yankees nine times in his career. And he has more than a little mixed emotions about the storied organization that he began his career with and that he will face again tonight.</p>
        <p>''I feel so far removed from my initial signing with that team,'' Leiter said. ''It's a bit more of a job to me now. I look at it like a professional. I don't feel like they dissed me or like it was any kind of raw deal. If anything, I don't feel like I did as well as you are supposed to do as a Yankee.''</p>
        <p>He dismissed the pressure that will inevitably be present when he takes the mound against the best team in baseball in such a highly visible game.</p>
        <p>''I'm starting a game, Friday night against the Yankees, and I'm going to be as excited,'' he said. ''If there was pressure, there's no more pressure than to start Game 7 of the World Series. Here I was, a guy who really didn't have a good year. Our ace pitched Game 6 and lost. And three-quarters of the media and fans were thinking we had no chance because I was pitching.</p>
        <p>''It's not a game in midseason against a very good team. And then you bring in what my brother's been through, come on. It's a baseball game.''</p>
        <p>Leiter's future with the Mets is uncertain. Obtained by the Mets during the Marlins' off-season dismantling, Leiter is in the final year of a three-year, $8.6 million contract that will pay him $3 million this season. His representatives, Alan and Randy Hendricks, are in New York through the weekend.</p>
        <p>''If a team really wants a player, don't let him go through the free agent market,'' Leiter said. He recalled what he told the Blue Jays: '' 'Had you guys come to me in August, I would have signed with you guys.' I went from a first-time ever free agent making $900,000 to teams offering me $3 million. I would have signed for less in August.''</p>
        <p>As for the Mets, Leiter said: ''I don't know what they're thinking. I would like for it to work here. You just never know.''</p>
        <p>Leiter has major league pitches; that was never an issue. But until this season he had never really harnessed his control, not even in 1996, when he went 16-12 with a 2.93 e.r.a.</p>
        <p>A knee injury dogged Leiter all of last season. But after that Game 7, when he decided to use other pitches and all of the plate, Leiter has blossomed into a complete pitcher and not just a thrower. He will almost certainly be named to his second All-Star Game in less than two weeks.</p>
        <p>''I guess I could think of what could of been,'' said Leiter, when asked if he ever looks back to the years of arm trouble and when he sometimes could not find home plate. ''But the two most wasted emotions are regret and worry. Neither deals with the present moment.''  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
