<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Another Slam, More Renewal For the Mets</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="355841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES DODGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Dodgers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900523T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DD173EF930A15756C0A966958260" item-length="772" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Another Slam, More Renewal For the Mets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL MARTINEZ, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MARTINEZ, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: By the time their charter flight rose into the afternoon sky today, the only thing the Mets could remember about the trip was its conclusion. They had dismissed being swept in San Francisco and being in disarray in San Diego, and when they left for home, all they seemed to have packed away was sudden contentment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: By the time their charter flight rose into the afternoon sky today, the only thing the Mets could remember about the trip was its conclusion. They had dismissed being swept in San Francisco and being in disarray in San Diego, and when they left for home, all they seemed to have packed away was sudden contentment.</p>
        <p>By the time their charter flight rose into the afternoon sky today, the only thing the Mets could remember about the trip was its conclusion. They had dismissed being swept in San Francisco and being in disarray in San Diego, and when they left for home, all they seemed to have packed away was sudden contentment.</p>
        <p>That good feeling returned Monday night and then continued this afternoon when the Mets set down the Los Angeles Dodgers, 8-3, to take both games of a series and leave for New York with a sense of renewal and a 19-19 record.</p>
        <p>Two days ago, the Mets were on the verge of mass hysteria. But a players-only clubhouse meeting on Monday was followed by a 12-3 victory in the evening and by today's triumph, the result of Bob Ojeda's return to the pitching rotation and Mike Marshall's robust day at the plate.</p>
        <p>First Victory Since Sept. 19</p>
        <p>Ojeda, making his first start since he replaced Ron Darling in the pitching rotation, gave up one run in six innings and won for the first time since last Sept. 19. Marshall, playing in the stadium where he spent his first eight seasons in the major leagues, knocked in six runs with a sacrifice fly, a single and a sixth-inning grand slam. And like that, a trip that started at 1-5 turned respectable. ''We salvaged it,'' said Ojeda, who retired 16 of the first 19 batters he faced today. ''It ended on a good note, but the best thing we can do is not look back on what happened before.''</p>
        <p>What happened was enough to send the team behind closed doors. They convened Monday, spoke openly about their concerns and then broke out grandly against the Dodgers, outscoring them by 20-6 and outhitting them by 31-14 in the two games. Their 17 hits today - including 4 by Kevin Elster and 3 by Keith Miller - were a season high.</p>
        <p>''When you start 0-4, then come back and win three of four, it's a good vital sign,'' said the Mets' manager, Dave Johnson, whose future wavered with the team's recent slump. ''The trip wasn't all that bad. The most consistent we've been is consistently bad, but we haven't played like we're capable and the teams ahead of us are stumbling, too. So this is a sign of good things to come.''</p>
        <p>The Mets began the day as the worst National League team in hitting (.233 average) and fielding (42 errors), but they had their best day at the plate and they did not make an error. It was only the second time in eight games they were flawless afield.</p>
        <p>How much good did the meeting do? Some, they said. ''When you look back at the San Francisco series and then this,'' Howard Johnson said, ''there's been such a different attitude, from batting practice to the game. It's like night and day. Now we've got to keep going out and burying other teams.''</p>
        <p>Error by Hartley</p>
        <p>They didn't dispatch the Dodgers until the sixth, and even then they needed help from an error by the Los Angeles pitcher, Mike Hartley. They had a 2-1 lead through five innings but left eight runners stranded in that span. ''It looked like it would be a 12-hit, two-run kind of day,'' Johnson said, ''and then Mike decided to take things into his own hands. That's what we need from the big guys in the middle of the lineup.''</p>
        <p>Marshall, who had only 13 runs batted in, went to bat after a throwing error by Hartley and an infield single by Darryl Strawberry that had pushed the lead to 3-1. Then he hit an 0-and-2 pitch to left-center and the day was essentially over.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure he wanted to come inside with the pitch or just miss with it,'' Marshall said of Hartley. ''But he caught too much of the plate. I was as surprised as anybody.''</p>
        <p>In the ninth, Elster led off with a home run off John Wetteland, his fifth homer of the season. At the start of the day, the Met shortstop was hitting .143.</p>
        <p>And what had his teammates said to him after his big day? Elster smiled. ''Frank Viola told me, 'Congratulations, now you're hitting higher than me,' '' he said.</p>
        <p>Dwight Gooden, who suffered a hairline fracture in the middle toe on his left foot Saturday, said he had some soreness after pitching five innings Monday. But he said the day off Wednesday would likely give him enough time to recover so he could make his next start on Sunday. . . . Kevin McReynolds, who left Monday's game with slight inflammation in his right knee and did not play Tuesday, is expected back Thursday against the Padres. . . . Marshall now has seven career grand slams, tying him with Jack Clark for third among active players. Eddie Murray has 14, Gary Carter 11. . . . The grand slams on consecutive days by McReynolds and Marshall marked the first time a Mets team had accomplished the feat.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
