<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Staten Island Team, History Is on Its Side</title>
    <meta content="16staten" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/16/sports/baseball/16staten.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1783311"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Little League World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Little League World Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Little League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Staten Island (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401EEDE143EF935A2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="813" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Staten Island Team, History Is on Its Side</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">History Is on Their Side for a Little League Title</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team of Staten Island boys departed for Williamsport, Pa., yesterday. Their bus ride spanned 198 miles. Their journey crossed several generations.</p>
        <p>The Mid-Island Little League team on Staten Island secured a berth in the Little League World Series on Monday with a 2-1 victory over Livingston American of New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Forty-two years ago, the Mid-Island team on Staten Island won the Little League World Series championship  a feat this year's team is hoping to duplicate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A team of Staten Island boys departed for Williamsport, Pa., yesterday. Their bus ride spanned 198 miles. Their journey crossed several generations.</p>
        <p>The Mid-Island Little League team on Staten Island secured a berth in the Little League World Series on Monday with a 2-1 victory over Livingston American of New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Their cheering section included parents, siblings and -- genealogically speaking -- their baseball forefathers.</p>
        <p>Forty-two years ago, the Mid-Island team won the Little League World Series championship -- a feat no New York City team has duplicated. Two members of that 1964 squad, Jeff Paul and Don Quattrochi, were in the stands Monday in Bristol, Conn., serving as unofficial advisers to their Staten Island scions.</p>
        <p>When Frank Smith clinched the World Series berth with a game-ending home run, no one was more pleased than Dan Yaccarino, perhaps the most renowned Little Leaguer in Staten Island history.</p>
        <p>Yaccarino, who tossed a no-hitter in the 1964 championship game, watched with pride as the Staten Islanders danced across his television set in Palm Beach, Fla.</p>
        <p>''When the kid hit the home run, I had chills going down my arm,'' Yaccarino said by telephone.</p>
        <p>Parents of the Mid-Island team were deluged with congratulatory phone calls yesterday. Bars and restaurants quickly promoted themselves as the place to watch the World Series. At a local grocery store, a news clipping with the headline ''Dream Team'' was taped above a cash register.</p>
        <p>''We're kind of blown away,'' said Gordon Shea, whose son Adam plays center field.</p>
        <p>Only four other New York City teams have played in the Little League World Series, and the city's most recent entries were tarnished by scandal. In 2002, a team from Harlem was accused, but later cleared, of using players who lived outside league boundaries. In 2001, a team from the South Bronx had its third-place finish nullified because its star pitcher, Danny Almonte, was determined to be 14 -- two years beyond the eligibility age.</p>
        <p>In contrast, the 2006 Mid-Island team has won admirers at every stop. Some Little League fans in Haverstraw, N.Y. -- the site of the state tournament -- traveled to Bristol to show their support, Shea said. A vendor in Bristol gave him a free lobster. Regis Philbin has been talking about the youngsters on television.</p>
        <p>''It just seems that as we go through these towns, people like us, they're drawn to us,'' Shea said.</p>
        <p>Joe Calabrese pitched his team to victory Monday night, then threw an extra curve afterward. Midway through a celebratory lap around the field, Calabrese stopped his team and invited the New Jersey players to join in. They did.</p>
        <p>''It was just a great gesture of sportsmanship,'' said his father, Joe Calabrese Sr. ''This is what you dream of your whole life.''</p>
        <p>That gesture of sportsmanship had to be a welcome image for Little League officials, who have been dealing with a pair of embarrassing incidents.</p>
        <p>On Sunday, a New Hampshire team won a regional game by forfeit because its Vermont opponent failed to follow a Little League rule about using every player for a minimum number of outs. In the final inning, with his team leading by 9-8, the Vermont manager realized his mistake and tried to extend the game by ordering his pitcher to throw wild pitches. The New Hampshire manager responded by ordering one of his players to intentionally strike out and end the game.</p>
        <p>Earlier this summer, a Little League team in Utah pitched around its opponent's best hitter in order to pitch to a cancer survivor.</p>
        <p>''You see so much negativity with youth sports, to see this just kind of reinforces the goodness of youth sports,'' Shea said.</p>
        <p>The emotional high comes with a heavy price tag, however. Parents of the Mid-Island team said they will have spent $4,000 to $5,000 each by the time the World Series run ends. Most of them spent 10 days in Bristol for the regional tournament, after spending several days in upstate New York for the state tournament.</p>
        <p>''We're a poor league,'' said the Mid-Island Little League president, Bob Johnson. ''We're a blue-collar league. I need corporate sponsors to help us out. That's my biggest concern now.''</p>
        <p>''Most of us are just middle-class people who are just getting by,'' said Maria Elena Davis, a teaching assistant. Her son, Matt, hit a game-ending home run in the regional semifinal game, which she attended with the financial help of her parents.</p>
        <p>''This is every child's dream,'' Davis said. ''How do you not make it happen for your kids?''</p>
        <p>Jeff Paul and Don Quattrochi, the 1964 players, plan to travel to Williamsport, where the Mid-Island team opens play Saturday. Yaccarino said he hoped to join them there.</p>
        <p>Forty-two years ago, they were honored with a ticker-tape parade up Broadway. Now they are imparting every bit of wisdom they can muster to their Little League descendants, in hopes of another parade.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
