<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Funeral for a Slain Teenage Car Detailer</title>
    <meta content="16fight" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/16/nyregion/16fight.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1783279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Funerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Death and Dying</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Long Island (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6DE143EF935A2575BC0A9609C8B63" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Funeral for a Slain Teenage Car Detailer</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Funeral for a Slain Teenage Car Detailer</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COREY KILGANNON; Angela Macropoulos and Julia C. Mead contributed reporting for this article.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kilgannon, Corey</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The summer rain pelted the well-waxed white hood of Daniel Cicciaro Jr.'s 2004 Ford Mustang Mach 1 and beaded into a thousand droplets.</p>
        <p>The sports car, with its black details, tinted windows and gleaming wheel rims was parked yesterday outside St. Sylvester's Roman Catholic Church in Medford, N.Y., while a funeral Mass was being said inside for its owner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Daniel Cicciaro Jr. was fatally shot last week by the father of another teenager in a confrontation that had its beginning at a local birthday party.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The summer rain pelted the well-waxed white hood of Daniel Cicciaro Jr.'s 2004 Ford Mustang Mach 1 and beaded into a thousand droplets.</p>
        <p>The sports car, with its black details, tinted windows and gleaming wheel rims was parked yesterday outside St. Sylvester's Roman Catholic Church in Medford, N.Y., while a funeral Mass was being said inside for its owner.</p>
        <p>The car was immaculate, much like the many other Mustangs parked nearby, which had been painted, cleaned and polished by Mr. Cicciaro for display at car shows and in parking lots of Suffolk County and the strip malls and fast-food joints where the Blackout car club held sway.</p>
        <p>The club was headed by Mr. Cicciaro, a teenager who was fatally shot last week by the father of another teenager in a confrontation that had its beginning at a local birthday party. Mr. Cicciaro was white; the man who shot him is black, and his lawyer says that racial epithets were used.</p>
        <p>''When tragedy strikes, we either become bitter or we become deep,'' said the Rev. Edward J. Kealey during the funeral Mass, as he urged the Cicciaro family and friends to look past the shooting and become ''as deep as we possibly can.''</p>
        <p>In life, God is in the details, he said, invoking St. Augustine's teachings that ''the smallest grain of sand contains the whole of the universe.'' In such manner, he said, did Mr. Cicciaro find meaning in the intricate upkeep and detailing of cars -- ''beyond the polish, beyond the painting, beyond all of those things.''</p>
        <p>The victim's godfather, Gregg Sarra, 45, also told mourners of Mr. Cicciaro's ''need for speed,'' whether driving his all-terrain vehicle or one of his three sports cars.</p>
        <p>''He loved to feel the wind in his face,'' said Mr. Sarra, a sports editor for Newsday. ''He felt the wind in his face one last time. It was as the angels carried him swiftly to Heaven.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Cicciaro's last night alive began with a birthday party in Sound Beach with a teenage crowd.</p>
        <p>According to court documents and the Suffolk County Police, a black teenager, Aaron White, 19, arrived. A girl at the party became upset and told guests that Mr. White had posted an Internet message threatening to rape her. Mr. White was told to leave the party, and did, but he and Mr. Cicciaro began arguing by cellphone. Mr. Cicciaro's friends told the police that Mr. White challenged him to come to his house in nearby Miller Place to settle the dispute.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Cicciaro and four friends arrived in cars at Mr. White's house around 11 p.m., Mr. White and his father, John White, walked out of the house holding guns and ordered them to leave.</p>
        <p>''I'm going to kill you,'' John White screamed repeatedly at Mr. Cicciaro, who challenged him, ''Go ahead and shoot me!'' according to the police.</p>
        <p>Then John White shot him in the face at point-blank range, the police say. Mr. Cicciaro's friends pulled him into their car -- an immaculately detailed BMW -- and he died in a nearby hospital.</p>
        <p>Mr. White was arraigned on a second-degree murder charge and is being held without bail in protective custody in Suffolk County Jail in Riverhead. No charges have been filed against his son.</p>
        <p>Daniel T. Driscoll, a lawyer for Mr. White, said yesterday that Mr. White had asked the teenagers to leave and that they had refused. He said that his client felt threatened, was trying to protect his son, and that racial epithets were directed at them.</p>
        <p>After yesterday's service, relatives and friends scoffed at allegations of racism.</p>
        <p>''There were no racial overtones whatsoever,'' Mr. Sarra said. ''The White family is playing the race card.''</p>
        <p>He described Daniel as an intelligent and ambitious teenager who was headed to college and planned to take over his father's car repair business, Dano's Auto Clinic in Port Jefferson Station.</p>
        <p>At the funeral Mass, the father, Daniel Cicciaro Sr., stood next to his son's coffin wearing a tank top bearing the name of his shop and the slogan, ''Tony Soprano sends all his friends to Dano's.'' On the back, under an image of shot bodies, was the motto, ''Some pass inspection, some don't.''</p>
        <p>The father said he wore the shirt as a message to his son, whom he buried yesterday a week before his 18th birthday.</p>
        <p>''This is how we went to work together every day,'' he said, adding that his son began rebuilding car engines when he was 8.</p>
        <p>''Our future was planned,'' he said, standing near his son's coffin in Washington Memorial Park cemetery in Mount Sinai. His Mustang was parked near his coffin, as was his all-terrain vehicle, displayed on the bed of a pickup truck.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
