<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>6 Counties That Shine In Ratings For Bonds</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="553876"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATINGS AND RATING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LOCAL GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BERGEN COUNTY (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLESEX COUNTY (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MORRIS
COUNTY (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SOMERSET COUNTY (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION COUNTY (NJ)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LUECK, THOMAS J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Local Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920902T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEED61138F931A3575AC0A964958260" item-length="1189" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>6 Counties That Shine In Ratings For Bonds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS J. LUECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LUECK, THOMAS J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although fiscal success stories are hard to find in the New York region, they do exist: 6 of the nation's 28 most credit-worthy county governments, for example, are in the suburbs of New York City.</p>
        <p>These counties have had sound credit ratings for more than a decade. But experts say their fiscal strength is remarkable now because of the recession, which has been longer and deeper in the New York region than in most of the nation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Although fiscal success stories are hard to find in the New York region, they do exist: 6 of the nation's 28 most credit-worthy county governments, for example, are in the suburbs of New York City.</p>
        <p>These counties have had sound credit ratings for more than a decade. But experts say their fiscal strength is remarkable now because of the recession, which has been longer and deeper in the New York region than in most of the nation.</p>
        <p>"There is an institutionalized conservativeness in these counties," said Michael Johnston, a vice president of Moody's Investors Service Inc., which has given its highest rating, Aaa, to the bonds issued by Westchester County in New York and Bergen, Middlesex, Morris, Somerset and Union counties in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>"These are mature, well-managed counties that have seen recessions come and go," Mr. Johnston said. "They prepare for them."</p>
        <p>They also tend to be rich counties, where tax revenue comes primarily from homeowners rather than from businesses. And they often have governments that have been under the firm control of a single party for many years, thus avoiding the fiscal uncertainty of partisan budget battles. The Westchester Model</p>
        <p>Among all New York-area counties, Westchester fits that mold best, with homes that sell for an average of $325,000, and several enclaves where values exceed $1 million. The county also benefits from taxes paid by more than a dozen large corporate headquarters. Moreover, its Board of Legislators has been in the hands of one party, the Republicans, for two decades.</p>
        <p>Westchester has received triple-A ratings from both Moody's and Standard &amp; Poor's since 1971. But Stephen V. Reitano, the county's Commissioner of Finance, said that maintaining the rating had not been simple. Hoping to shift costs to private industry, thus strengthening its own finances, he said, the county turned over its bus system and garbage-burning plant to private companies in the 1980's.</p>
        <p>Westchester, with a 1991 budget of $1.1 billion, had a cash surplus of $22 million for that year, he said, up from $17 million in 1990.</p>
        <p>Analysts said each of the most fiscally sound counties has maintained cash surpluses -- often building them up in times of economic expansion as an insurance policy against recessions. They also hold borrowing to a minimum.</p>
        <p>In Union County, N.J., which has maintained its Aaa rating from Moody's since 1978, officials said they had struggled to maintain a surplus as insurance against unforeseen shortfalls, increasing the county's reserve from $4.5 million in 1990 to $7 million last year.</p>
        <p>"The rating agencies expect to see a rainy-day fund, and we've got it," said Ann Baran, the Union County Manager. The Exception</p>
        <p>But in Union, as elsewhere, retaining the highest rating has not been easy during the recession. Among measures Union has taken in the last year are a reduction of 100 county employees, bringing the work force down to 3,100, and an increase in fees for use of its golf course and parks.</p>
        <p>Unlike most of the highest-rated counties, Union, which adopted an appointive, county-manager system of government in 1976, has had frequent shifts of control between Republicans and Democrats on its elected Board of Freeholders. But maintaining its Aaa rating has been a consistent priority.</p>
        <p>"No one wants to be the one in office when a bond rating is lowered," said Lawrence M. Caroselli, the county's director of finance.</p>
        <p>In Morris County, which has maintained its Aaa rating since 1975, officials employ an unusual form of self-policing of their credit standing. To maintain a cash surplus, the county's budget planning process each year deliberately fails to account for interest payments it is assured of receiving on certificates of deposit and other investments, and when the interest checks are received they are deposited in an account set aside as surplus.</p>
        <p>Morris County officials said the method was not foolproof. Indeed, because interest rates have plummeted this year, the county's income -- and its surplus -- will be smaller than the $13.1 million it had in the bank at the end of 1991. Glenn Roe, the county's assistant treasurer, estimated that the year-end surplus would be about $8 million, still enough to protect its high credit rating.  The Price of Squabbling</p>
        <p>If wealth, stability and conservatism are the keys to a high credit rating, the two counties on Long Island offer lessons in how not to do things. Both are wealthy but have been plagued by political turmoil of late, and both have turned to short-term borrowing to deal with large budget gaps.</p>
        <p>Suffolk, for example, has held a Baa1 rating from Moody's and a BBB rating from Standard &amp; Poor's on and off for four years.</p>
        <p>Although neither of the rating agencies advise investors not to buy the bonds of any government, Wall Street has traditionally considered a rating of BBB from Standard &amp; Poor's or Baa1 from Moody's to be only slightly above the minimum required to be "investment grade," or reasonably safe.</p>
        <p>"Suffolk has historically had a volatile political environment," said Mr. Johnston. He added that the low rating had resulted from periods of fiscal excess, which have left the county without a cash reserve, and the problems faced by the Grumman Corporation, its largest private employer.</p>
        <p>Amid much political maneuvering, Suffolk is addressing its budget crisis by raising its sales tax a half percentage point, to 8.5 percent, the maximum allowed by state law, and it is deliberating borrowing $36.5 million to close the 1991 budget gap. The Nassau Nightmare</p>
        <p>The problems in Nassau have been even more stark.</p>
        <p>After years of affluence and one-party control of government, by Republicans, a crisis developed last fall when a budget shortfall of more than $100 million loomed in a budget of $1.9 billion. Rather than raise property taxes 24 percent, as proposed by the County Executive, Thomas S. Gulotta, the county Board of Supervisors opted to make across-the-board budget cuts. But the cuts and related layoffs proved so unpopular that further layoffs were rescinded without any compensating budget cuts or tax increases.</p>
        <p>In January, saying Nassau was in "the most serious financial stress in years," Moody's lowered its rating from A1 to A. Now, according to county officials, Nassau may be downgraded again.</p>
        <p>"We feel we are fiscally strong, but we are greatly concerned," said Kenneth Cynar, a spokesman for Mr. Gulotta. "The problem is that we are bogged down in political bickering."</p>
        <p>In the latest move to solve the county's budget problems, the Board of Supervisors last week authorized $675,000 in short-term borrowing to cover the payrolls of certain departments through Oct. 31. But the vote followed heated partisan debate. Although the measure did not result in a further downgrading of Nassau's credit rating, it clearly made the county more vulnerable.</p>
        <p>"The need to develop and implement a long-term restructuring plan and find a less fractious decision-making process remains the principal issue" for Nassau, Moody's said in an advisory to its clients issued last week.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
