<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Duties on Japanese Screens For Laptops Cleared by U.S.</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="467342"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DUMPING (TRADE TERM)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERSONAL COMPUTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL TRADE COMMISSION (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLLACK, ANDREW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910816T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFDE1331F935A2575BC0A967958260" item-length="724" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Duties on Japanese Screens For Laptops Cleared by U.S.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLLACK, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Aug. 15</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The International Trade Commission cleared the way today for anti-dumping duties to be placed on imports of certain types of computer and television screens from Japan.</p>
        <p>The decision was a victory for small American manufacturers of such screens and a blow to American manufacturers of laptop and notebook computers, which now import their screens from Japan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The International Trade Commission cleared the way today for anti-dumping duties to be placed on imports of certain types of computer and television screens from Japan.</p>
        <p>The decision was a victory for small American manufacturers of such screens and a blow to American manufacturers of laptop and notebook computers, which now import their screens from Japan.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department decided last month to impose 62.67 percent duties on screens that use a technology that is considered the wave of the future.</p>
        <p>The action was taken because the department determined that the Sharp Corporation, the Hosiden Corporation and other Japanese companies were dumping such screens, or selling them at unfairly low prices, in the United States. The Commerce Department sets the duty percentage after an analysis of the manufacturing cost.</p>
        <p>But the duties could not take effect until the International Trade Commission, a separate agency, determined that American manufacturers of such flat panel displays were actually being injured by the dumping. By a 3-to-1 vote, the commission decided today in Washington that they had been, clearing the way for the Customs Service to begin collecting the duties in about a week.</p>
        <p>Today's decision is, "in effect, an eviction notice from the U.S. Government to the fastest-growing part of the U.S. computer industry," said Michael Dutton, a spokesman for the International Business Machines Corporation. If American manufacturers of notebook and laptop computers move their manufacturing offshore, they can avoid the duties by importing entire computers instead of just screens.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. has a joint venture with Toshiba in Japan to make screens using active matrix liquid crystal displays, the type of screen subject to the 62.67 percent duty. Mr. Dutton did not say what I.B.M. would do, but added, "We certainly don't intend to bear the burden of such a punitive duty, that's for sure."</p>
        <p>The American computer companies, led by I.B.M., Apple Computer and Compaq Computer, have said they must buy Japanese screens because American suppliers do not make the types they need.</p>
        <p>However, dumping duties are not likely to have much immediate effect on the notebook computer industry because active matrix screens, while considered the technology of choice for the future are still not widely used. Such screens, which provide sharp images that can change quickly, are expensive and extremely difficult to manufacture. The simpler passive matrix liquid crystal displays, the type now used in almost all notebook computers, are not subject to anti-dumping duties.</p>
        <p>American manufacturers of flat screens, which had brought the anti-dumping case against the Japanese manufacturers last year, hailed the decision.  Survival Fears</p>
        <p>"Without this, I would have feared for the survival of this industry," said Paul C. Rosenthal, a Washington lawyer representing the Advanced Display Manufacturers of America, a coalition of about 10 American companies.</p>
        <p>American manufacturers of active matrix liquid crystal displays include OIS Optical Imaging Systems of Troy, Mich. and Standish Industries of Lake Mills, Wis. Manufacturers of other types of flat panel displays include Planar Systems Inc., Beaverton, Ore. and Plasmaco of Highland, N.Y.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosenthal said the duties would allow American manufacturers to earn more revenues and to attract investors. "It will let investors know that they can invest and not face the prospect that their investment will be wiped out by predatory pricing by the Japanese," he said.  Success Not Certain</p>
        <p>In addition a 7.02 percent duty was imposed on electroluminscent screens, another type of display.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosenthal conceded however, that the dumping decision alone would not insure the success of the American display manufacturers, which generally have not been able to raise enough money to begin large-scale manufacturing. He and others said investors might continue to believe competition with the Japanese electronics giants would remain difficult, even with the dumping duties.</p>
        <p>Moreover, most of the American manufacturers use technology other than liquid crystal displays. Computer manufacturers say these other technologies are not suitable for use in battery-powered notebook computers, which are now the biggest market for flat panels.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
