<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Macon Aims to Go Higher This Time Around</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="431739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL: N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLAYOFF GAMES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL COLLEGIATE ATHLETIC ASSN (NCAA)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TEMPLE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">OKLAHOMA
STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, TIMOTHY W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MACON, MARK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Playoff Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910322T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CEEDE1738F931A15750C0A967958260" item-length="944" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Macon Aims to Go Higher This Time Around</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIMOTHY W. SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, TIMOTHY W</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With the Temple Owls trying to play their way into the Final Four in the East Region this weekend, Mark Macon is faced with the possibility of having a set of dubious bookends to his basketball career at the university.</p>
        <p>Temple (23-9), seeded No. 10, will play third-seeded Oklahoma State (24-7) in the second semifinal game tonight at Byrne Arena in East Rutherford, N.J. The winner will face the winner of the first semifinal game, between North Carolina and Eastern Michigan, in the East Regional final on Sunday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With the Temple Owls trying to play their way into the Final Four in the East Region this weekend, Mark Macon is faced with the possibility of having a set of dubious bookends to his basketball career at the university.</p>
        <p>Temple (23-9), seeded No. 10, will play third-seeded Oklahoma State (24-7) in the second semifinal game tonight at Byrne Arena in East Rutherford, N.J. The winner will face the winner of the first semifinal game, between North Carolina and Eastern Michigan, in the East Regional final on Sunday.</p>
        <p>The last time the Owls reached the round of 16 was in 1988, and they played in East Rutherford. Macon was a brillant 6-foot-5-inch freshman shooting guard on a senior-dominated team, and was averaging 20 points a game heading into that final against Duke. Forgettable Performance</p>
        <p>The ride to the Final Four came to a crashing halt as Macon ran into Billy King, the Blue Devils' defensive stopper.</p>
        <p>Macon scored 13 points, hitting only 6 of 29 shots from the field in a performance he has tried to purge from his memory over the last three years.</p>
        <p>"The only thing I remember is that we all tried to play as hard as we could that day," he said. "Every time, in and out, I tried to do my best."</p>
        <p>Three years later, more experienced, less heralded, but still no less confident in his abilities, Macon wants to help take his team farther than he did as a freshman. He does not want his career to be marked by losses in the finals of a regional as a freshman and a senior.</p>
        <p>"I'm a whole lot different as a player now than I was then," Macon said. "I've grown so much since my freshman year in my ability and as far as my knowledge of the game.</p>
        <p>"I was playing on raw talent then, on a team that knew what to do. It was so easy to do the things that I was doing."</p>
        <p>Macon's raw talent at guard was allowed to flourish on that team, because he was surrounded by experienced inside players, like senior forward Tim Perry and senior center Ramon Rivas. That team, which was ranked No. 1 in the nation for nine weeks, finished the season with a 32-2 record.</p>
        <p>"This time I'm bringing the experience and leadership that we need," Macon said. "That's what we need the most in this tournament and that's what I can contribute the most." Senior Stands Alone</p>
        <p>Macon, who leads the team in scoring with an average of 21.6 points a game, is the lone senior starter on the team. He is surrounded by skilled big men, Donald Hodge, a 7-1 junior center, and Mark Strickland, a 6-9 junior forward. Offensively, Macon is complemented by an equally adept scorer in swingman Mik Kilgore and Vic Carstarphen, a smooth sophomore point guard who transferred from the University of Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>Macon said this team had the ingredients to make a winning formula.</p>
        <p>"This year everything is coming around at the right time," Macon said. "The guys are stepping up, answering the call and showing that they're ready to play hard and they're ready to win, wanting to win. They're going to go out and do what is necessary to win."</p>
        <p>He said he didn't know much about Oklahoma State.</p>
        <p>"I know they're a very strong team that likes to play physical," he said. "I know they have some pretty big guards."</p>
        <p>Oklahoma State Coach Eddie Sutton said he expected to see a lot of zone defense and variations of zone defense when the two teams play. Sutton said it didn't matter what defense Temple played, Oklahoma State would try to counter with motion.</p>
        <p>"Against any defense, man-to-man or zone, you have to move the basketball and you have to move people," Sutton said. "We'll attack their defense as we would anybody else." The First Game</p>
        <p>North Carolina, top seeded in the East Region and considered a heavy favorite to advance to the Final Four, will meet Eastern Michigan in the first game at 7:32 P.M.</p>
        <p>Eastern Michigan Coach Ben Braun said his team was not awed by North Carolina.</p>
        <p>"Our team has done a good job this year focusing in on our own potential," Braun said. "Good teams play up to their own potential."</p>
        <p>King Rice, the Tar Heels' senior point guard, said the team wasn't underestimating Eastern Michigan.</p>
        <p>"I watched film of them yesterday and they're a very talented team," Rice said. "If we don't play well against them, we could be in trouble."</p>
        <p>For Macon, who expects to graduate in December with a degree in elementary education, this tournament is his last shot at fulfilling the promise that he displayed as a freshman. Buildup Isn't a Letdown</p>
        <p>Macon's career never matched the hoopla that surrounded him as a freshman, when he shot a career-best 45.4 percent from the field. Macon said he didn't ask for the buildup, therefore he doesn't feel like his career has been a disappointment.</p>
        <p>"I don't tend to listen to what others have to say about me," Macon said. "It doesn't matter to me what people say about my career."</p>
        <p>The waning minutes of the second-round game between Temple and Richmond last week was a microcosm of the last three years of Macon's career with the Owls.</p>
        <p>After the Spiders, the sentimental favorite of the crowd at Maryland's Cole Field House, had fought back from a 10-point deficit to cut the Owls' lead to 59-57, Macon hit a 3-pointer to help re-ignite his team. Temple won, 77-64, and advanced to the semifinals in East Rutherford.</p>
        <p>Macon has a much different view of his career and himself as a player than the popular view.</p>
        <p>"I feel like I've always been an offensive threat and defense is my game," he said. "People have always tended to see the parts of my game that they wanted to see and ignore the other parts for whatever reason."  COLLEGE BASKETBALL: N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
