<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Puzzling Over the Intentions On a Bumpy Road to Heaven</title>
    <meta content="03HEAV" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="41" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1180869"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">La Mama Etc</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wright, Damon</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bruckner, D J R</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mr Baldwin Goes to Heaven (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000303T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E7D91E39F930A35750C0A9669C8B63" item-length="540" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Puzzling Over the Intentions On a Bumpy Road to Heaven</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By D. J. R. BRUCKNER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bruckner, D J R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>D J R Bruckner reviews Damon Wright's play Mr Baldwin Goes to Heaven, presented by La MaMa; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It would be unfair to challenge viewers leaving ''Mr. Baldwin Goes to Heaven'' to say what the play is about. But it is a safe bet there would be almost as many answers as members of the audience.</p>
        <p>On the surface it is about the ascent to heaven of the black writer James Baldwin, in the company of a most unlikely guardian angel: a white pornography star called Jake, whose foul-mouthed taunts wring a declaration from Baldwin that acknowledging his homosexuality is the one form of salvation he is certain of. But in this play the journey is everything, the destination nothing, and the twists and turns can leave one totally bewildered.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It would be unfair to challenge viewers leaving ''Mr. Baldwin Goes to Heaven'' to say what the play is about. But it is a safe bet there would be almost as many answers as members of the audience.</p>
        <p>On the surface it is about the ascent to heaven of the black writer James Baldwin, in the company of a most unlikely guardian angel: a white pornography star called Jake, whose foul-mouthed taunts wring a declaration from Baldwin that acknowledging his homosexuality is the one form of salvation he is certain of. But in this play the journey is everything, the destination nothing, and the twists and turns can leave one totally bewildered.</p>
        <p>In part that is because one is not sure it is complete. Its author, Damon Wright, who worked for The New York Times for 10 years, died in 1998, and before that the piece had been performed only in a workshop production in 1996, directed by Terrell Robinson. Mr. Robinson had collaborated with Wright on productions of several other plays by him, and he directs the current revival of ''Mr. Baldwin'' at La Mama with the kind of energy and imagination that make it a tribute to this playwright.</p>
        <p>But did Wright mean it as a tribute to Baldwin? It would hardly seem so. The Baldwin of the play is easier to warm up to, and to like, than the real man was. But as Jake challenges Baldwin's whole life and character -- even his well-known courtesy, diffidence and almost pathological privacy -- Baldwin's achievements, including the brilliance of his writing and his role in the civil rights movement, begin to disintegrate, corroded by his own doubts and hesistations.</p>
        <p>What counts here is the dialogue, occasionally brilliant and often haunting. Kenyon Farrow as Baldwin can appear and sound so fragile, he can make you want to rock him to sleep, as Jake does. But just when he seems most lost, he can turn his voice into a rumble worthy of the torrents of eloquence in Baldwin's books.</p>
        <p>Spencer Aste as Jake has a tougher assignment. His coarse badgering and the crudity of his sexual banter can be physically revolting. But he convinces the audience that his devotion to Baldwin is the only emotion he never feigns; it defines him.</p>
        <p>Together Mr. Robinson and these actors make this 80-minute exploration of the private side of a public figure a rough trip but a fascinating one. Parts of it are likely to leave anyone upset and some people offended. By the end, where it has led one does not seem terribly important. One is even willing to forget that no one involved in the production has figured out how make these two characters move around the stage naturally, as though they were going somewhere.</p>
        <p>MR. BALDWIN GOES TO HEAVEN</p>
        <p>By Damon Wright; directed by Terrell Robinson; sets by Mark Tambella; lighting by Daniel Ordower; sound by Jacob Burckhardt; costumes by John McKinnon; dramaturge, Maxine Kern; stage manager, Betty Howe; production manager, Ron Jones. Presented by La MaMa E.T.C, in association with Dance Giant Steps Inc. At 74A East Fourth Street, East Village.</p>
        <p>WITH: Kenyon Farrow and Spencer Aste.</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
