<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Lesson For Sutton: Treat Golf As an Art</title>
    <meta content="16GOLF$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1017279"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gte Byron Nelson Classic</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sutton, Hal</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2DC1130F935A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="643" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Lesson For Sutton: Treat Golf As an Art</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE DRAPE</byline>
      <dateline>IRVING, Tex., May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Hal Sutton takes one-shot lead in GTE Byron Nelson Classic, Irving, Texas; photo (M)5</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A simple conversation with a legend did what equipment and psychologists could not: reinvigorate Hal Sutton's golf game.</p>
        <p>Sutton took a one-shot lead in the GTE Byron Nelson Classic today after sinking a twisting birdie putt from 15 feet on the final hole to move to 9-under. Moments later, Sutton, a  laconic Louisianan, explained that he had been through six sets of irons this year and a couple of visits with sports shrinks, but finally found what he was looking for when he visited Jack Burke, the winner of the 1956 Masters and P.G.A. Championship, this week in Houston.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A simple conversation with a legend did what equipment and psychologists could not: reinvigorate Hal Sutton's golf game.</p>
        <p>Sutton took a one-shot lead in the GTE Byron Nelson Classic today after sinking a twisting birdie putt from 15 feet on the final hole to move to 9-under. Moments later, Sutton, a  laconic Louisianan, explained that he had been through six sets of irons this year and a couple of visits with sports shrinks, but finally found what he was looking for when he visited Jack Burke, the winner of the 1956 Masters and P.G.A. Championship, this week in Houston.</p>
        <p>''He reminded me you need to play the game, instead of work at it so hard,'' Sutton recalled. ''He reminded me this is an art. It's a game of feeling. You got to love it,'' said Sutton of his visit with Burke, the folksy Texan.</p>
        <p>Sutton's 65 tied Robert Damron for low score on a day when blistering sunshine burned away the smoke and haze from brush fires in Central America and opened the Cottonwood Valley and TPC Four Season courses up to swirling winds and slippery greens. His fifth birdie of the day  knocked one of the area's native son's and tour rookie, Harrison Frazar, into second place.</p>
        <p>The sudden sunshine and blend of wind nettled competitors for most of the day. Tiger Woods, the defending champion, managed only a one-over  71 and remained five shots back. The local favorite, Justin Leonard, shot a 69 and is six back.</p>
        <p>It was Leonard's former University of Texas roommate and high school rival, Frazar, who excited the home folks. The two shared the same golf club and same teacher, Randy Smith, but Leonard was quicker to find his professional game. But the 26-year-old Frazar has looked comfortable on a course he frequently played in high school.</p>
        <p>Though he joked that he was lucky to score 6 on the par-4 No. 3 hole back then, he has put up a 68 to go with his first round 64 in front of more than 50 friends and family members who are at the core of his gallery.</p>
        <p>''It's been a lot of fun to do it in front of them. If I shoot 78 or 62 tomorrow, they're still going to be happy. They'll like me either way,'' Frazar said.</p>
        <p>''But I was a far different player. Back then I was happy to make a 6,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Another sometime Dallas resident, Couples, returned from a 12-day layoff to shoot a 67 to continue a brilliant run of golf that begin with his heartbreaking second-place finish at the Masters and a third at the Shell Houston Open. He feels he is in position to win.</p>
        <p>''Whoever is going to win here will shoot a 63 or 64 in the next two days,'' he said. ''I'm in good shape to make a few more birdies and get there.''</p>
        <p>But so is Sutton, who also counts Texas as an excellent place to get his mind right. He has been a pupil of Burke's ever since his amateur days when he played at Burke's Champions Country Club. Theirs is a cerebral relationship that has nothing to do with swings, grips or mechanics.</p>
        <p>Sutton did decide on his own a month ago to play with a set of Hogan irons. It did not matter to Burke, who watched him hit just 10 balls in a three-hour visit. ''The rest of the time we just sat at his desk and talked,'' Sutton said. ''I'll tell you what. I've never left him without being a lot smarter than when I got there.''</p>
        <p>GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
