<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Manetta Begins Searching For Next Coach at St. John's</title>
    <meta content="16STOR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1017315"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">St John's University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Popper, Steve</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fraschilla, Fran</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CEFD81130F935A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="517" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Manetta Begins Searching For Next Coach at St. John's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE POPPER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Popper, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>St John's University begins search for new basketball coach following messy departure of Fran Fraschilla (S)6</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The phones are ringing in Ed Manetta's office.</p>
        <p>Two days after the messy departure of Fran Fraschilla, Manetta, the St. John's athletic director, has received calls from hopeful prospects while compiling his list of candidates. With the help of Lou Carnesecca and the Rev. James J. Maher, who travels with the team, Manetta has been calling athletic directors for permission to speak with prospective coaches.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The phones are ringing in Ed Manetta's office.</p>
        <p>Two days after the messy departure of Fran Fraschilla, Manetta, the St. John's athletic director, has received calls from hopeful prospects while compiling his list of candidates. With the help of Lou Carnesecca and the Rev. James J. Maher, who travels with the team, Manetta has been calling athletic directors for permission to speak with prospective coaches.</p>
        <p>In a conference call yesterday, he refused to rule out candidates without New York ties or previous head coaching experience, but he has made it clear since Fraschilla's departure that there is still a belief at St. John's that it is one of the top jobs in the nation and therefore should interest the highest level of coach.</p>
        <p>''I asked Father Maher to help because he's traveled with the team and has a good knowledge of the players,'' Manetta said. ''I think Father Maher will represent the players' interests. He has a great relationship with them. Input is great from everybody. Our athletes are mature enough, they'll make their input known. And having Lou, who was involved last time, too, believe me, makes life a lot easier.''</p>
        <p>Among the candidates thought to be of interest to the Red Storm are coaches with impressive credentials, promising futures and also intriguing New York pasts. One is Vanderbilt Coach Jan van Breda Kolff, the son of Butch van Breda Kolff, who coached at Hofstra and Princeton. Growing up in the metropolitan area, the younger van Breda Kolff is familiar with the city game, previously serving as an assistant coach at Cornell and Princeton, before compiling a 90-66 record in five seasons at Vanderbilt. He said he has not yet heard from the Red Storm ''It's all hypotheticals right now,'' he said. ''But the school and Madison Square Garden have been the pinnacle of basketball.''</p>
        <p>Matt Doherty, an assistant coach at Kansas for the past six years, attended Carnesecca's summer camp when he was in sixth grade, growing up just 20 minutes from the campus. He went on to play at North Carolina for Dean Smith, winning a national championship. ''I'm flattered that I'm being mentioned,'' said Doherty, who has resisted other offers to remain at Kansas. ''But until I'm contacted, it is speculation. I'd be flattered to be considered a candidate. I think it would be a great situation to pursue if there is an interest on their part.''</p>
        <p>Also thought to be on their list are Richmond Coach John Beilein, who previously coached at Canisius and led the Spiders to an opening round upset of No. 2-seeded South Carolina in the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament this year; Davidson Coach Bob McKillop, who once coached at Long Island Lutheran; Siena's Paul Hewitt; Florida's Billy Donovan; the former Texas coach Tom Penders; St. Joseph's Phil Martelli; Dave Leitao, the Connecticut associate head coach who previously had the head coaching job at Northeastern, and Bradley Coach Jim Molinari, who worked with Manetta at Bradley before Manetta joined St. John's.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
