<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New Delhi Premier Indicates Resolve to Produce Nuclear Weapons</title>
    <meta content="16INDI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980517T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1017319"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="NUCLEAR ANXIETY: IN INDIA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">India-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nuclear Tests</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">India</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Group of Seven</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vajpayee, Atal Bihari (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Summit Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nuclear Tests</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980516T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7D71130F935A25756C0A96E958260" item-length="1354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New Delhi Premier Indicates Resolve to Produce Nuclear Weapons</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN F. BURNS</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, May 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Prime Min Atal Bihari Vajpayee indicates that India will not hesitate to deploy nuclear arms, magazine interview; Pres Clinton, at Birmingham, Eng, economic summit meeting, wins accord on firm statement criticizing India, but fails to mobilize other nations to take punitive action; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Only 48 hours after India ended a series of five underground nuclear tests that stunned the world, Prime Minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee indicated today that India would not hesitate before deploying the nuclear weapons the tests were designed to perfect.</p>
        <p>''We do not want to cover our action with a veil of needless ambiguity,'' Mr. Vajpayee said in an interview with India Today, a news magazine. ''India is now a nuclear weapons state. We have the capacity for a big bomb now, for which a necessary command-and-control system is also in place. Ours will never be weapons of aggression.'' Both the magazine and the Government released transcripts of the interview.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Only 48 hours after India ended a series of five underground nuclear tests that stunned the world, Prime Minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee indicated today that India would not hesitate before deploying the nuclear weapons the tests were designed to perfect.</p>
        <p>''We do not want to cover our action with a veil of needless ambiguity,'' Mr. Vajpayee said in an interview with India Today, a news magazine. ''India is now a nuclear weapons state. We have the capacity for a big bomb now, for which a necessary command-and-control system is also in place. Ours will never be weapons of aggression.'' Both the magazine and the Government released transcripts of the interview.</p>
        <p>Indian nuclear experts said the ''big bomb'' Mr. Vajpayee mentioned was apparently a reference to the largest explosion, on Monday, of what India described as a ''thermo-nuclear device,'' meaning a weapon with many times the explosive power of the atomic bombs that the United States dropped on Japan in 1945.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vajpayee's remarks, which took the form of written responses to questions from India Today, did not  indicate that India had already deployed nuclear missiles, or even that  deployments were imminent. Rather, he seemed to emphasize that India, having demonstrated the ability to detonate nuclear warheads designed to be mounted on missiles, would not now be persuaded to stop short of producing them when it is ready.</p>
        <p>The remarks appeared to close off a crucial avenue for diplomacy that American officials had hoped to explore as they seek to persuade Pakistan, India's arch-rival, not to respond with tests of its own. A delegation sent by President Clinton arrived today in Islamabad, Pakistan's capital, and met with Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif and other top officials, who indicated they had not yet decided whether to conduct a test and suggested they might still be dissuaded.</p>
        <p>And at a summit meeting in Birmingham, England, Mr. Clinton won agreement on a firm statement criticizing India, but failed to mobilize other nations to take punitive action against New Delhi.</p>
        <p>In the interview, Mr. Vajpayee, leader of a Hindu nationalist party that came to power at the head of a 14-party coalition Government only two months ago, was alternately blunt and conciliatory. He said the blasts proved that ''we mean business'' about becoming a full-fledged nuclear power, and vowed that India would not be ''cowed down'' by economic sanctions from the United States, Japan and half a dozen other nations. ''India has the sanction of her own past glory and future vision to become strong,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The Prime Minister called India's critics, including the United States,  ''hypocritical,'' adding: ''Some of the countries which have talked of sanctions, or have otherwise criticized our action, have themselves not only conducted far more nuclear tests than we have done, but they have also built huge stockpiles of nuclear weapons and delivery systems. Many of them are enjoying the shade provided by somebody else's nuclear umbrella.''</p>
        <p>But the harsh words were accompanied by reassurances regarding India's resolve to be a responsible member of the ''nuclear club'' it gate-crashed with its tests.</p>
        <p>''I would like to assure the people of the world, especially in our part of the world, that there is no cause for worry at all, much less any alarm, on account of India's action,'' he said. ''All that India has done is conduct five nuclear tests. You place this fact in the context of the hundreds of nuclear tests that have been carried out by several countries so far, and it becomes obvious that India's action does not in the least warrant consideration of worst-case scenarios.''</p>
        <p>American officials had hoped that even if Pakistan did stage a nuclear test, they could still head off an arms race by persuading India and Pakistan to forgo military deployments of nuclear weapons. Mr. Vajpayee's remarks today did not ultimately exclude that option, since his Government or a successor could conceivably change India's policy as the economic sanctions begin to bite.</p>
        <p>Another possible avenue of appeal appeared to have been closed off when Sonia Gandhi, leader of the Congress Party, India's main opposition group, announced that the party supported the tests. In remarks that were reported today, Mrs. Gandhi abandoned the equivocal stand that had been taken by other party officials earlier in the week.</p>
        <p>''The nuclear question is a national matter, not a partisan one,'' she said. ''On this, every Indian stands united.''</p>
        <p>Western weapons experts have estimated that it could take India anywhere from months to several years to deploy nuclear-tipped missiles in any numbers. Starting in 1993, India  has test-fired three versions of the Agni missile, designed to become an intermediate-range nuclear missile, able to hit targets up to 1,500 miles away. A shorter-range missile, the Prithvi, with a range of 250 miles, has been more extensively tested, and Indian forces also have artillery capable of firing nuclear-tipped shells at battlefield range.</p>
        <p>Together, these weapons would give New Delhi the power to hit targets anywhere in Pakistan and in southern regions of China, the country Mr. Vajpayee identified as India's primary security concern. Shortly before the tests, India's Defense Minister, George Fernandes, described China as India's ''potential No. 1 enemy,'' and said some of China's fast-growing arsenal of nuclear missiles were targeted on India.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vajpayee confirmed the role that national pride played in the decision to carry out the tests. His Bharatiya Janata Party, or Indian People's Party, leads a movement that has worked for 70 years to persuade Indians that an assertive Hindu pride is the solution to India's problems. That stance has alarmed India's minority of 120 million Muslims, as well as Pakistan, a Muslim state created out of the partition of British India in 1947.</p>
        <p>''India has never considered military might as the ultimate measure of national strength,'' Mr. Vajpayee said. ''It is a necessary component of overall national strength. I would, therefore, say that the greatest meaning of the tests is they have given India shakti, they have given India strength, they have given India self-confidence.'' Shakti is a Hindi word meaning power, commonly used when referring to Hindu gods.</p>
        <p>He noted that Hindu nationalists had been advocating ''the cause of India going nuclear'' for 40 years, and had done so because of ''a stark regional and global reality,'' meaning that China and other major powers had nuclear weapons stockpiles and showed no sign of abandoning them.</p>
        <p>''The world knows the truth about the progress -- or rather, the lack of it -- made by the nuclear powers in the direction of nuclear disarmament,'' he said. ''The world community should appreciate the fact that India, the second most-populous country on earth, waited for five decades before taking this step.''</p>
        <p>He said his Government, like all Indian governments since the 1950's, preferred a ''nuclear-free world,'' but had concluded that efforts by the United States and other nuclear powers to prevent the transfer of nuclear technology were ''singularly ineffective.'' This was a reference to reports, confirmed by United States intelligence, that China has transferred missile-building and bomb-making technology to Pakistan. As a result, he said, India's tests were ''a minimal response necessary'' to protect India's security.</p>
        <p>Mr. Vajpayee renewed his Government's pledge to ''discuss certain provisions'' of the Comprehensive Test Ban Treaty that 149 nations, but not India or Pakistan, have signed.  But he said the treaty should require  nuclear powers to abandon their nuclear weapons programs, a condition certain to be rejected.</p>
        <p>On the effect of sanctions, Mr. Vajpayee was dismissive. ''Yes, our action has entailed a price,'' he said. ''But we should not worry about it. India has an immense reservoir of resources and inner strength. If we tap this reservoir, this benefit will be a hundred times more than any price that we may have to pay in the short term.''</p>
        <p>NUCLEAR ANXIETY: IN INDIA  Correction:  May 17, 1998, Sunday  Because of a production error, the opening paragraphs of an article yesterday about the Indian Prime Minister's determination to produce nuclear weapons were omitted from some copies. (The article was erroneously labeled a continuation from page A1.) The article, by John F. Burns from New Delhi, reported that Prime Minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee said there should be no ambiguity about the nation's plans: ''India is now a nuclear weapons state. We have the capacity for a big bomb now.'' Readers wishing a copy of the entire article may write to Pro duction Quality Control, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036, or telephone (212) 556-1992. E-mail: quality@nytimes.com. (Include a postal return address.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: May 17, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>Because of a production error, the opening paragraphs of an article yesterday about the Indian Prime Minister's determination to produce nuclear weapons were omitted from some copies. (The article was erroneously labeled a continuation from page A1.) The article, by John F. Burns from New Delhi, reported that Prime Minister Atal Bihari Vajpayee said there should be no ambiguity about the nation's plans: ''India is now a nuclear weapons state. We have the capacity for a big bomb now.'' Readers wishing a copy of the entire article may write to Pro duction Quality Control, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036, or telephone (212) 556-1992. E-mail: quality@nytimes.com. (Include a postal return address.)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
