<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>With Turbulence Over, Mets Are Flying High</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="696972"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO PADRES  NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREY, JENNIFER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/San Diego Padres</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940702T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4DA1739F931A35754C0A962958260" item-length="948" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>With Turbulence Over, Mets Are Flying High</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER FREY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREY, JENNIFER</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, July 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The homestand was hideous five losses, one rainout and two failed drug tests  -- combining to send the Mets out of town with an ugly losing streak and their best-loved pitcher in seclusion somewhere in New York.</p>
        <p>The plane ride, too, was a nightmare, given that the Mets sat on an airport runway for more than two hours, then bumped and bounced through bad weather that made it impossible to sleep.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The homestand was hideous five losses, one rainout and two failed drug tests  -- combining to send the Mets out of town with an ugly losing streak and their best-loved pitcher in seclusion somewhere in New York.</p>
        <p>The plane ride, too, was a nightmare, given that the Mets sat on an airport runway for more than two hours, then bumped and bounced through bad weather that made it impossible to sleep.</p>
        <p>But the Mets have no complaints thus far about their visit to the West Coast.</p>
        <p>Early Offensive Barrage</p>
        <p>With an early offensive barrage and a strong start from Bobby Jones, New York defeated the San Diego Padres, 10-7, tonight at Jack Murphy Stadium for their second victory in as many games on this 11-day trip.</p>
        <p>Bobby Bonilla, Kelly Stinnett and Jim Lindeman each blasted two-run homers and John Cangelosi had three hits and three runs scored as the Mets jumped to an early 8-0 lead.</p>
        <p>"Pretty obviously, it was a pretty good night to score runs," said Mets Manager Dallas Green, "and we needed them."</p>
        <p>And Jones -- who got his eighth victory of the season -- was marvelous until  the seventh inning, when the Padres vaulted on the scoreboard with four runs.</p>
        <p>Jones set up that disaster, but he did not seal it -- that job went to the reliever Roger Mason. After holding the Padres to two hits across the first six  innings, Jones gave up a leadoff single to Phil Plantier in the seventh, then issued back-to-back walks to Eddie Williams and Ricky Gutierrez.</p>
        <p>That was enough for Green, who came to the mound and took the ball from Jones, who had slammed it into his glove in disgust.</p>
        <p>"I felt good early in the game, and I felt great in the seventh also," said Jones. "I don't know if I got out of rhythm or something else was off. I was just trying to throw strikes, and the ball wasn't delivering." One pitch later, Mason gave up a grand slam to catcher Brian Johnson, a rookie with one home run and six runs batted in this year. That home run gave Jones three earned runs on three hits for his start.</p>
        <p>Jones Cruises Early On</p>
        <p>Bip Roberts singled off Jones to lead off the first inning and advanced to second on Gwynn's one-out grounder to the mound. After that, though, Jones did not allow another hit until Johnson managed an infield single with two outs in the fifth.</p>
        <p>Plowing methodically through the Padres' lineup, Jones walked just three batters, and Roberts was the only Padre to get past first base in the pitcher's  first six innings of work. When Plantier singled to center to lead off the seventh, Jones had faced four more than the minimum with two walks and seven strikeouts.</p>
        <p>Jones's performance made Bill Krueger's Padre debut all the more embarrassing. Krueger, signed by the Padres after his release by Detroit earlier this season, was called up from San Diego's Class AAA franchise in Las Vegas prior to tonight's game in order to give the Padres a left-hander in their rotation.</p>
        <p>A journeyman pitcher, Krueger last won a baseball game on Oct. 2, 1993, when  he led Detroit to victory against the Yankees. He didn't have a chance with the  stuff he was throwing tonight. It took Krueger 36 pitches and 19 minutes to get  through the top of the first inning, and he gave up four hits and three runs in the process.</p>
        <p>Homers by Bonilla and Stinnett</p>
        <p>The big blow in the first inning was a two-run homer by Bonilla, his 13th of the season. The big blow in the second was a two-run homer by Stinnett, his second. Padres Manager Jim Riggleman did not bother to let Krueger go to the mound for the third.</p>
        <p>San Diego's first reliever, Tim Mauser, inherited a 5-0 deficit and, briefly, it looked as if he might not aid in Krueger's effort to pad the Mets' batting averages.</p>
        <p>That hope lasted one inning. In the fourth, Mauser walked Luis Rivera, gave up a run-scoring single to Cangelosi and let Lindeman take him over the wall for the Mets' third two-run homer of the game. Mauser then struck out the side in the fifth.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>PAUL WILSON, the top pick in the June free-agent draft, will start Sunday for the Mets' Gulf Coast team in Port St. Lucie, Fla. Wilson, a right-hander, will be making his debut in the Mets' system. . . . DALLAS GREEN rested JOSE VIZCAINO and gave LUIS RIVERA his second start of the season at shortstop. Green also benched JEFF KENT, who has a sore foot, after four and a half innings and put FERNANDO VINA at second. . . . By earning his eighth victory Thursday night, BRET SABERHAGEN has surpassed his victory totals for each of his first two seasons with the Mets. Saberhagen won three games in 1992 and seven in 1993. . . . JASON JACOME will make his major league debut Sunday night when he faces the Padres' ANDY ASHBY. Jacome, a left-hander, was 7-4 with a 2.63 earned run average for the Mets' Class AAA franchise in Norfolk, Va.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
