<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Newcomers' Retreat</title>
    <meta content="19TVNO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="TV Notes" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="916645"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="TV Notes"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Abc Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Broadcasting Co (NBC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carter, Bill</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Er (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Prince Street (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Law and Order (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Nypd Blue (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ratings and Rating Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CEFDB1038F93AA25750C0A961958260" item-length="559" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Newcomers' Retreat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL CARTER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carter, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>TV networks' decision to put new program in time slot occupied by hit show has been a failure; after coming up with strategy to move NBC's solid police drama Law and Order to ER time period, Thursday at 10 PM, for four weeks, while filling vacancy on Wednesday at 10 with new police drama, Prince Street, NBC saw its overall weekly audience drop precipitously without ER; then it saw Prince Street founder in the ratings; NBC has canceled Prince Street after two weeks; Law and Order will go back to Wednesday and repeats of ER wil be back a week early; ABC drama The Practice, in Tuesday night time slot of NYPD Blue, is suffering low ratings; ABC has no plans to yank The Practice (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Something happened to the networks' plan to use the two months between the February and May ratings sweep periods as a laboratory for developing new shows: Most of the experiments have blown up.</p>
        <p>No result was messier than NBC's effort to find a way to give its monster hit ''E.R.'' a rest this spring. After coming up with a strategy to move its solid police drama ''Law and Order'' to the ''E.R'' time period, Thursday at 10 P.M., for four weeks, while filling the vacancy on Wednesday at 10 with a new police drama, ''Prince Street,'' NBC saw its overall weekly audience drop precipitously without ''E.R.'' Then it saw ''Prince Street'' founder in the ratings.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Something happened to the networks' plan to use the two months between the February and May ratings sweep periods as a laboratory for developing new shows: Most of the experiments have blown up.</p>
        <p>No result was messier than NBC's effort to find a way to give its monster hit ''E.R.'' a rest this spring. After coming up with a strategy to move its solid police drama ''Law and Order'' to the ''E.R'' time period, Thursday at 10 P.M., for four weeks, while filling the vacancy on Wednesday at 10 with a new police drama, ''Prince Street,'' NBC saw its overall weekly audience drop precipitously without ''E.R.'' Then it saw ''Prince Street'' founder in the ratings.</p>
        <p>NBC yanked that show from its schedule after just two weeks and curtailed the ''E.R.'' experiment. Now ''Law and Order'' will go back to Wednesday and repeats of ''E.R'.' will be back a week early.</p>
        <p>ABC has had little more success with its plan to give -- temporarily -- a promising new drama, ''The Practice,'' the time slot on Tuesday night at 10 owned by its hit drama ''N.Y.P.D. Blue.'' After good ratings the first night, ''The Practice'' sank alarmingly in its second week. But Jamie Tarses, the president of ABC Entertainment, said the network had no plans to bail out of ''The Practice.''</p>
        <p>''If you really believe in a show,'' she said, ''you've got to stay with it more than two weeks. We believe in 'The Practice.' We think once it gets a little more press and word of mouth, it'll be all right.''</p>
        <p>But the strategy of replacing existing hits with new entries is undergoing some serious rethinking. ''I think the networks are going to be less inclined to take a hit off next spring,'' said a network program executive who spoke on condition of anonymity. ''The show you replace it with has to be very special, or the audience is going to desert you.''</p>
        <p>Among the reasons these experiments have not worked, this executive said, were the confusion and resentment that all the schedule changes have caused among viewers.</p>
        <p>Ms. Tarses said that overall this spring ''has definitely been a lean one.'' No new series on any network has given a strong indication that it will break through as a hit, and many have been crashing disappointments.</p>
        <p>Leading that list is the ABC comedy ''Arsenio,'' which has declined each of the last two weeks against not especially difficult competition.</p>
        <p>The most promising new series may be an entry from one of the fledgling networks, WB. A new comedy-drama called ''Buffy the Vampire Slayer'' has received the best Monday night ratings for that would-be network for two straight weeks.</p>
        <p>The network program executive said the success of ''Buffy'' might be one more indication that ''in order to break through, you have to be a show that's a little different.''</p>
        <p>BILL CARTER</p>
        <p>TV Notes</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
