<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="09CLAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="986290"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1DC1E30F93AA35752C0A96E958260" item-length="4354" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CLASSICAL MUSIC AND DANCE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the New York metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''CAPRICCIO,'' Metropolitan Opera. Richard Strauss's last opera, ''Capriccio,'' which received its premiere at the Munich National Theater in 1942, in the depths of World War II, is a curiosity that Strauss himself called a ''conversation piece.'' Its rather talky libretto is by the composer and his friend and champion, the conductor Clemens Krauss. Set in Paris during the 1780's, the story tells of the widowed Countess Madeleine, who is being courted by two suitors, a composer and a poet. The rivalry frames a wry aesthetic debate about which art holds priority, words or music, when they are combined. Still, the opera is strangely engrossing, and has some glorious musical moments, including the countess's final scene, which is autumnal Strauss at his most rapturously beautiful. The soprano Kiri Te Kanawa, who will sing the role in the Met's first production of the opera, would seem ideally suited to it. Andrew Davis conducts. Tonight at 8, Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000. Tickets: $96 to $150; standing room tickets, at $11 and $15, are available two hours before the performance (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing by critics of The Times of new or noteworthy opera, classical music and dance events this weekend in the New York metropolitan region.</p>
        <p>Opera</p>
        <p>''CAPRICCIO,'' Metropolitan Opera. Richard Strauss's last opera, ''Capriccio,'' which received its premiere at the Munich National Theater in 1942, in the depths of World War II, is a curiosity that Strauss himself called a ''conversation piece.'' Its rather talky libretto is by the composer and his friend and champion, the conductor Clemens Krauss. Set in Paris during the 1780's, the story tells of the widowed Countess Madeleine, who is being courted by two suitors, a composer and a poet. The rivalry frames a wry aesthetic debate about which art holds priority, words or music, when they are combined. Still, the opera is strangely engrossing, and has some glorious musical moments, including the countess's final scene, which is autumnal Strauss at his most rapturously beautiful. The soprano Kiri Te Kanawa, who will sing the role in the Met's first production of the opera, would seem ideally suited to it. Andrew Davis conducts. Tonight at 8, Metropolitan Opera House, (212) 362-6000. Tickets: $96 to $150; standing room tickets, at $11 and $15, are available two hours before the performance (Anthony Tommasini).</p>
        <p>''THE MIKADO,'' New York Gilbert and Sullivan Players. For dedicated Savoyards, the short season presented by this group every winter is a highlight of the concert season. The troupe, founded in 1974 by Albert Bergeret, who still directs it, presents these sparklingly witty works in modest but attractive stagings, with good casts, fine choral singing and choreography that suits both the music and story line. Having just presented an attractive and touching production of a comparative rarity, ''The Yeomen of the Guard,'' the company turns this weekend to one of the most popular works in the Gilbert and Sullivan canon, ''The Mikado.'' The company performed ''Yeomen'' without updating or topicality, but there is a long tradition of such tinkering with the text of ''The Mikado,'' which, after all, skewers government corruption and other timeless social ills. Some would argue that the work should be allowed to stand as it is, but Mr. Bergeret is not of that school, so the question is not whether topical jokes will be interpolated, but whether they will work. In any case, Gilbert's own puns and patter, and Sullivan's elegant Victorian music have proved durable enough to withstand almost anything. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 3 and 8, and Sunday at 3, Symphony Space, Broadway at 95th Street, (212) 864-5400. Tickets: $25 to $45 (Allan Kozinn).</p>
        <p>Classical Music</p>
        <p>AMERICAN COMPOSERS ORCHESTRA. What would we do without them? This time Dennis Russell Davies conducts a classic, Roger Sessions's First Symphony, along with the first performances of Augusta Read Thomas's ''Brass Axis'' and Hale Smith's ''Ritual and Incantations.'' Philip Glass's Concerto for Saxophone Quartet, with the Rascher Quartet, completes the program on Sunday at 3 P.M. At Carnegie Hall, (212) 903-9750. Tickets: $9 to $40 (Paul Griffiths).  BRIAN ASAWA. There are almost as many fine countertenors emerging on the scene these days as there are mezzo-sopranos. One countertenor is Brian Asawa, who has a sweet-toned yet vibrant voice, fine technical control and charisma. He was particularly impressive as Puck on last year's new Philips recording of Britten's ''Midsummer Night's Dream'' conducted by Colin Davis. Mr. Asawa will sing a program of Elizabethan songs, and arias and songs by Mozart, Alessandro Scarlatti, Caldara, Medtner and Villa-Lobos on Sunday afternoon at 2, Alice Tully Hall, Lincoln Center, (212) 875-5050. Tickets: $32 (Tommasini).  THE CHAMBER MUSIC SOCIETY OF LINCOLN CENTER. In ''Musical Evolutions,'' the third of its annual January ''celebrations'' -- minifestivals that focus on composers or historical themes -- the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center is exploring the stylistic ferment of the late 19th and early 20th centuries, specifically in the years between 1887 and 1920, when Romanticism gave way to early modernism. The series begins with a lecture tomorrow morning by Bruce Adolphe, the society's education director and music adviser, about the meaning of tonality and atonality, and continues in the afternoon with a lecture on ''Pierrot, Petrushka and the Ethics of Clowning'' by Rose Subotnik, a culture critic and professor of music at Brown University. The music gets under way on Sunday afternoon when the Orion String Quartet plays the Ravel Quartet as well as the Faure Piano Quintet with the pianist Andre-Michel Schub and the Dvorak Quintet in E flat with Ida Kavafian playing the second viola line. Lectures are tomorrow at 11 A.M. and 2 P.M., Rose Rehearsal Studio, the Rose Building at Lincoln Center, Admission is free. The concert is on Sunday at 5 P.M. at Alice Tully Hall. (212) 875-5788. Tickets: $25 to $35 (Kozinn).  RUTH LAREDO. The American pianist Ruth Laredo, who celebrated her 60th birthday late last year, plays with a rhapsodic flair that in some repertory can seem almost out of control. But her temperament is ideally suited to the visionary, ruminative and incandescent piano music of Scriabin. Her recordings of the composer have helped spark interest in his works in America, and her 1970 recordings of the complete 10 sonatas and selected etudes have recently been remastered and reissued on a two-disk Nonesuch set. Her all-Scriabin recital at the Metropolitan Museum should be rewarding. Tonight at 7, Metropolitan Museum of Art, Fifth Avenue at 82d Street, (212) 879-5500. Tickets: $25 (Tommasini).  NEW JERSEY SYMPHONY. Better late than never? It remains to be seen whether the New York region needs another complete survey of four Brahms symphonies just now, with the Berlin Philharmonic and the New York Philharmonic having covered that already familiar ground before and during the Brahms anniversary year just past. Zdenek Macal and the orchestra will put the proposition to the test over three weeks, beginning with the Second Symphony, and they offer considerable added value with Garrick Ohlsson, who should be an ideal Brahmsian, in the Second Piano Concerto. Tomorrow at 8 P.M. and Sunday at 3 P.M. at the New Jersey Performing Arts Center, 1 Center Street, Newark, (800) 255-3476. Tickets: $10 to $48 (James R. Oestreich).  NEW YORK PHILHARMONIC. Tchaikovsky's First Piano Concerto, with Grigory Sokolov, a winner of the Tchaikovsky Piano Competition in Moscow, as soloist, will undoubtedly be the attraction for most listeners, and it may well be fine. But for anyone with even an ounce of adventure, the prospect of Stravinsky's ''Rite of Spring,'' conducted by Valery Gergiyev, who has produced striking results with the philharmonic in Russian music, must be even more appealing. Today at 11 A.M., and tomorrow at 2 P.M., Avery Fisher Hall, (212) 721-6500. Tickets: $16 to $70 (Oestreich).  FREDERICK RENZ AND THE ENSEMBLE FOR EARLY MUSIC. Frederick Renz and his Ensemble for Early Music have developed a repertory of interesting productions based on medieval mystery plays. Mr. Renz's goal in these works seems not to be the straightforward revival of ancient dramas, but their adaptation for modern presentations using period instruments and techniques. ''Herod and the Innocents,'' for example, is a combination of two tellings of the Christmas story from the Fleury Playbook, a manuscript compiled during the 12th century at the Benedictine Abbey of St. Benoit-sur-Loire, in France. Mr. Renz and his musicians -- the instrumentalists typically take vocal roles as well -- have offered this production with considerable success, but it has been six years since it was last seen in New York City. Tonight at 8, and tomorrow at 2 and 8, Church of St. Mary the Virgin, 145 West 46th Street, Manhattan,  (212) 749-6600. Tickets: $24 to $28 (Kozinn).  ST-X ENSEMBLE. In previous concerts and in recordings, this group, conducted by Charles Borstein, has set the standard by which performances of Iannis Xenakis's high-powered music have to be judged. Another all-Xenakis program is an exciting prospect. Tonight at 8 at the Kitchen, 512 West 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 255-5793. Tickets: $15 (Paul Griffiths).  ZOOM: COMPOSERS CLOSE-UP. New music, at its best, can be bracing and fresh. But it can also be perplexing, and, usually, listeners hearing a new piece have no way to explore their confusion. On Saturday, however, the estimable Lark String Quartet, as part of the Zoom: Composers Close-Up series, will perform the premiere of the Second String Quartet by the notable American composer Aaron Jay Kernis, and the performance will be followed by a panel discussion. As a musical event, it may strike some as a bit lecturelike. But this should be a stimulating way to hear a new piece and ask the composer some questions about it. Tomorrow at 9 P.M., Merkin Concert Hall, 129 West 67th Street, Manhattan, (212) 501-3330. Tickets: $8.50 (Tommasini).</p>
        <p>Dance</p>
        <p>ALTOGETHER DIFFERENT. This annual panorama of up-and-coming dance companies allows theatergoers to see three varied groups in a single weekend. Kevin O'Day fuses martial arts, balletic elegance and gymnastic bravura in his creations for O'Day Dances. Mark Dendy Dance and Theater revels in wit, dexterity and choreographic surprises. Among the surprises will be Mr. Dendy's ''Rite of Spring.'' ''Fire and Ice,'' Irene Hultman's moody dance-drama for her troupe, Irene Hultman Dance, juxtaposes tragedy with humor and reflects her Swedish background. Tonight at 8 (O'Day); tomorrow night at 8 (Dendy), and Sunday at 2 and 7:30 P.M. (Hultman), Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Avenue at 19th Street, Chelsea, (212) 242-0800. Tickets: $18 (Jack Anderson).  AVODAH DANCE ENSEMBLE. There are not too many practicing choreographers of dance based on religious themes in these godless days. In her quiet way, JoAnne Tucker is one of the most persistent and one of the best, creating simple, luminous and heartfelt dances based on Jewish traditions. In a rare concert, Avodah will present ''Suit Yourself,'' a second work for the company by Linda Kent, formerly with the Alvin Ailey and Paul Taylor companies. Ms. Tucker will present a work in progress inspired by Alicia Ostriker's new poem on Jephthat's daughter, which the poet will read from at the performance. Other guest artists will include Brady McDonald, of the Jose Limon Dance Company, the vocalist Jeannine Otis and the percussionist Newman Baker. The program, completed by dances on Abraham's near-sacrifice of Isaac and on the healing impact of friendship and community, is being presented in conjunction with ''Rage/ Resolution: From Family Violence to Healing in the Works of Israeli and American Woman,'' a free exhibition at the institute through Jan. 30. Sunday at 2 P.M., Hebrew Union College-Jewish Institute of Religion, 1 West Fourth Street, Greenwich Village. (201) 659-7072. Tickets: $8; $5 for students and the elderly (Jennifer Dunning).  YOSHIKO CHUMA AND THE SCHOOL OF HARD KNOCKS. Virtuoso string players collide with skilled dancers in ''Unfinished Symphony,'' and the result is a combination of precision and chaos, order and eccentricity. Tonight, tomorrow and Sunday at 8:30, St. Mark's Church, Second Avenue and 10th Street, East Village, (212) 674-8194. Tickets: $12 (Anderson).  DANCE THEATER OF HARLEM. A last chance, before the company leaves on tour next week, to see some of its most exciting dancers in excerpts from a wide range of ballets. Among them are Kellye A. Saunders and Donald Williams in choreography by Alonzo King, Alicia Graf and Duncan Cooper in the sizzling pas de deux from George Balanchine's ''Prodigal Son,'' and Andrea Long and Ronald Perry in a pas de deux from John Taras's ''Firebird.'' Three promising youngsters from the company's Dancing Through Barriers Ensemble will also perform, with Arthur Mitchell as host. Sunday at 3 P.M., 466 West 152d Street, (212) 690-2800. Tickets, which go on sale on Sunday at 1:30 P.M. at Dance Theater of Harlem, are $6 for adults; $2 for children and the elderly (Dunning).  NEW YORK CITY BALLET. Gone are the Sugar Plums of ''The Nutcracker,'' replaced by teen-age gangsters and lovers, regiments of flag saluters and jewels in toe shoes in the company's return to its winter repertory. ''Jewels'' (tomorrow night) and ''Stars and Stripes'' (Sunday matinee) suggest the transformative simplicity of George Balanchine and his choreography, in ballets that sidestep the shameless advertisements for Van Cleef and Arpels and American jingoism they might so easily have resembled. The City Ballet dancers will also get a chance to let down their hair in Jerome Robbins's ''West Side Story Suite'' (tonight and tomorrow afternoon), with Nikolai Hubbe singing with all the aplomb of a Broadway gypsy. There will also be role debuts by some of the company's most interesting dancers, among them Peter Boal, that sumptuous classicist, performing in Balanchine's truly hokey ''Duo Concertant'' for the first time at tomorrow's matinee. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 2 and 8, and Sunday, 3 P.M., New York State Theater, Lincoln Center, (212) 870-5570. Tickets: $15 to $68 (Dunning).  KRAIG PATTERSON. Catch a promising, witty and thought-provocative modern-dance choreographer on his way up with ''Bopi's Black Sheep,'' a program of new works with live musical accompaniment; Mr. Patterson has danced with Mark Morris and choreographed for Mikhail Baryshnikov. Tonight and tomorrow at 8, and Sunday at 7, Pace Downtown Theater, Spruce Street between Park and Gold Streets, just south of City Hall, lower Manhattan, (212) 399-1715. Tickets: $15 (Dunning).  THUNDERBIRD AMERICAN INDIAN DANCERS. Thirty-five dancers will celebrate the troupe's 35th anniversary with a powwow that features dances of 10 tribes from across the country. The festivities will also include pageantry, crafts displays and traditional foods like venison, corn soup and wild rice. Tonight and tomorrow at 8, and Sunday at 2 and 5 P.M., Theater for the New City, 155 First Avenue at 10th Street, East Village, (212) 254-1109. Tickets: $10; $1 for children under 12 for Sunday matinee (Anderson).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
