<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge Wins Mostly Praise for His Low-Profile Style</title>
    <meta content="09JUDG$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="986415"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Oklahoma City (Okla)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Thomas, Jo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Matsch, Richard P (Judge)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nichols, Terry Lynn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Oklahoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Plains</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oklahoma</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Oklahoma/Oklahoma City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sentences (Criminal)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E0D91F30F93AA35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1005" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge Wins Mostly Praise for His Low-Profile Style</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JO THOMAS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Thomas, Jo</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, Jan. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Some families of victims of Oklahoma City bombing lashed out at Judge Richard P Matsch, calling him weak man who gave too much leeway to defense; in Denver, Matsch is considered tough judge and stickler for law, who is not afraid of controversy; his photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a Federal jury deadlocked over the sentencing of Terry L. Nichols, some families of the victims of the Oklahoma City bombing lashed out at the judge, Richard P. Matsch, calling him a weak man who gave too much leeway to the defense.</p>
        <p>But in Denver, Judge Matsch (pronounced maytch) of Federal District Court, who will make the final decision in the sentencing of Mr. Nichols for conspiracy in the 1995 bombing, is considered a tough judge and a stickler for the law, who is not afraid of controversy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a Federal jury deadlocked over the sentencing of Terry L. Nichols, some families of the victims of the Oklahoma City bombing lashed out at the judge, Richard P. Matsch, calling him a weak man who gave too much leeway to the defense.</p>
        <p>But in Denver, Judge Matsch (pronounced maytch) of Federal District Court, who will make the final decision in the sentencing of Mr. Nichols for conspiracy in the 1995 bombing, is considered a tough judge and a stickler for the law, who is not afraid of controversy.</p>
        <p>After they were dismissed, some jurors said they were surprised when Judge Matsch took the case out of their hands, but such decisiveness was vintage Matsch.</p>
        <p>For many years, Judge Matsch, who is 67, presided over a court-ordered school busing program in Denver, not yielding to the complaints of the city's whites or later of its minority leaders.</p>
        <p>Six years ago, he ruled that the Ku Klux Klan had a right to speak at the state Capitol on the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.'s birthday. And 10 years ago, he sentenced two members of the paramilitary group, the Order, who murdered a Jewish talk show host in Denver, to terms of 150 years each for violating the host's civil rights.</p>
        <p>His hero, his friends say, is Atticus Finch, the lawyer protagonist of the novel ''To Kill a Mockingbird,'' who stands up for justice.</p>
        <p>''This is not theater,'' Judge Matsch announced on the first day of the trial of Timothy J. McVeigh in the Oklahoma City bombing. ''This is a trial.''</p>
        <p>Judge Matsch asked for appropriate demeanor and warned the spectators not to cry. In the months that followed, when wrenching testimony from bombing victims at the trials of Mr. McVeigh and later, Mr. Nichols, left even the lawyers, the Federal agents and the journalists in tears, Judge Matsch never allowed his face or his voice to betray his own emotions, or that he had lost a daughter to a terrible and early death.</p>
        <p>''Judges have lives outside of courthouses, too -- although it might seem strange for you to realize that -- and families,'' Judge Matsch told the jury hearing Mr. Nichols's case as he warned them not to talk about the trial during Christmas holidays. ''And you know, people that I come in contact with say, 'Well, how is it going down there?' And, of course, I have to say, 'Well, I can't talk about it; you know that.' ''</p>
        <p>It was the only glimpse he ever gave either jury of his life or his feelings, other than an occasional remark about the shortcomings of computers in modern life.</p>
        <p>The judge's Federal District Court colleague, Judge John Kane, calls him a hero.</p>
        <p>''I don't mean a hero like John Wayne,'' Judge Kane said, ''but he lives by a standard that is essentially heroic, in the sense that he believes in the time-honored virtues of integrity and courage and loyalty and patriotism. It makes him, in a sense, somewhat of an anachronism because we live in an age where heroes are scarcely tolerated.''</p>
        <p>''Discipline is probably the strongest word you could use to identify him,'' Judge Kane continued. ''The hardest thing about judging, the thing the public understands least, is to control your own emotions and secondly to control your own thoughts and views -- that's not what juristic thought is about.''</p>
        <p>Judge Matsch and his wife of 38 years, Elizabeth, lived for many years in Cherry Hills, a fashionable neighborhood near downtown. Later, when their five children were grown, the Matsches moved to a 30-acre farm near Boulder.</p>
        <p>''Lib is very good with horses,'' said Thomas C. Seawell, a friend for 30 years. ''He had a lot of struggle with those horses. It was always his job to clean out the barn. I think he did it every morning at 5:30 A.M.  That's the farm boy in him. So what if you were a Federal district judge?  It didn't mean you didn't have chores.''</p>
        <p>Judge Matsch's father, William, owned a grocery store in Burlington, Iowa. The family lived upstairs, and the four sons worked in the store.  Richard Matsch, the youngest son, attended the University of Michigan, graduating in 1951, and graduated from the University of Michigan Law School in 1953. He served in an Army counterintelligence unit in Korea for two years, then moved to Denver and joined a private law firm.</p>
        <p>From 1959 to 1961, he was a Federal prosecutor for the District of Colorado, and then became Deputy City Attorney for the City and County of Denver from 1961 to 1963. He was a bankruptcy judge from 1965 until 1974, when President Richard M. Nixon appointed to Federal District Court. He assumed his duties on March 15, 1974 and became Chief Judge of the District of Colorado 20 years later, on June 1, 1994.</p>
        <p>In 1992, Judge Matsch's daughter, Betsy, was killed when she slipped into a cleft at Hawaii Volcanoes National Park and became trapped in a chamber filled with steam about 20 feet below ground.</p>
        <p>''The news of his daughter's death came over a weekend,'' recalled Mimi Wesson, a professor of law at the University of Colorado and former Federal prosecutor. ''Everyone assumed he would cancel his class for the following Friday. The dean's office kept expecting a call from someone on behalf of the judge. The call did not come. On Friday afternoon, he showed up and taught his class. To me, this was an example of how valiant the man is.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
