<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>FIGURE SKATING ; Upheaval at the Top: Kwan Nearly Perfect As Lipinski Tumbles</title>
    <meta content="09SKAT$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="986403"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="FIGURE SKATING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Figure Skating Championships</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Olympic Games (1998)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Winter Games (Olympics)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kwan, Michelle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipinski, Tara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Longman, Jere</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Figure Skating</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D01E7D91F30F93AA35752C0A96E958260" item-length="930" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>FIGURE SKATING ; Upheaval at the Top: Kwan Nearly Perfect As Lipinski Tumbles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JERE LONGMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Longman, Jere</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Jan. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Figure skater Michelle Kwan finishes first in short program at US figure skating championships; defending champion, Tara Lipinski, finishes in fourth place; only winner at championships is guaranteed to receive one of three American berths in Winter Olympics at Nagano, Japan; other two skaters will be determined by their performances over past two years; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After a fitful night of tossing and turning, Michelle Kwan slept through her early-morning training session today. The spark of her absence kindled a bonfire of speculation. Had she withdrawn from the Olympic trials with a toe injury? No, she had not. Not only did Kwan later skate the short program, but seven of the nine judges also rated her presentation as perfect.</p>
        <p>While the defending champion, 15-year-old Tara Lipinski, fell on a triple flip and tumbled sobbingly to fourth place, Kwan delivered a refined, joyful, liberating performance that was judged as the greatest by a woman in the short program at the national championships, which serve as the Olympic trials.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After a fitful night of tossing and turning, Michelle Kwan slept through her early-morning training session today. The spark of her absence kindled a bonfire of speculation. Had she withdrawn from the Olympic trials with a toe injury? No, she had not. Not only did Kwan later skate the short program, but seven of the nine judges also rated her presentation as perfect.</p>
        <p>While the defending champion, 15-year-old Tara Lipinski, fell on a triple flip and tumbled sobbingly to fourth place, Kwan delivered a refined, joyful, liberating performance that was judged as the greatest by a woman in the short program at the national championships, which serve as the Olympic trials.</p>
        <p>No American woman had ever received one perfect mark of 6, much less seven of them, in this part of the program at the nationals. Kwan's scores were surpassed only by the eight 6's that Brian Boitano received for his short program presentation at the 1988 trials.</p>
        <p>Only the winner here is guaranteed to receive one of three American berths in the Winter Olympics next month at Nagano, Japan. The other two skaters will be determined by their performances over the past two years. As the 1997 world champion, Lipinski is virtually certain to be chosen, which could cause a controversy should she finish fourth or lower.</p>
        <p>For Kwan, all the uncertainty of the past two months evaporated in the two and a half minutes of her short program. She was the 1996 world champion but had not competed since early November because of a stress fracture in the second toe of her left foot.</p>
        <p>''At the end, I said, 'Now I can enjoy this moment, now I can breathe,' '' said Kwan, who is 17. ''When I heard the 6's, I said, 'Am I hearing this right?' ''</p>
        <p>After a controlled, almost cautious, beginning to her program, Kwan appeared to gain restorative confidence as an athlete and an artist with her feathery jumps, elegant spirals, balletic grace and fierce determination. She skated to a Rachmaninoff piano concerto that helped build a churning tension as she approached the triple flip. The jump replaced a triple toe loop that causes stabbing pain when she plants her left toe pick.</p>
        <p>Twice in the past two days, Kwan had fallen while rehearsing the triple flip. Today, her thoughts seemed to linger in indecision before the jump. Later she confessed that her left foot felt encouraging and that she almost attempted the triple toe except that her coach, Frank Carroll, would ''kill me.'' So she stuck with the flip, which she landed with precision and relief.</p>
        <p>''I've had it since I was 11,'' Kwan told herself. ''Why not do it now when it counts.''</p>
        <p>A resurgent, theatrical Nicole Bobek finished second and a stolid Tonia Kwiatkowski took third. Even Kwiatkowski found herself clapping for Kwan's first-place skate, one that came after weeks of speculation about her injury and her uncertain confidence.</p>
        <p>Kwan missed three weeks of training in November, and as late as Christmas she wondered whether she could compete effectively here.</p>
        <p>''I thought it was one of her best moments, not so much for what she did, but the way she did it,'' said Carroll, who coaches Kwan in Lake Arrowhead, Calif. ''She had a wonderful look of ease on her face and confidence, a performing aura rather than just a technical aura. When you are under a lot of pressure, to make it come out with great ease is difficult to do.''</p>
        <p>Lipinski, who last year became the youngest world champion ever at age 14, was perhaps bothered by the pressure of defending her national title. She let her open spin wander, landed a flawed lutz on her combination jump then made a rare fall on the triple flip. She rushed the jump, did not attain sufficient height and crumpled to the ice.</p>
        <p>Later, Lipinski began crying. Her coach, Richard Callaghan, called the mistake ''drastic'' because it came in such an important competition. Had this been the Olympics, the fall would most likely have cost her any chance at a gold medal.</p>
        <p>Today's short program, which consisted of eight required elements involving spins, jumps, footwork and spirals, counted for one-third of the scoring. Saturday's long program will count for two-thirds. For Lipinski to defend her national title, she must win the long program while Kwan finishes third or lower. Lipinski said she remained encouraged because her fall was ''not a doubting mistake or a technical problem.''</p>
        <p>''I'll do a clean long,'' she said. ''I believe I'll do a great long.''</p>
        <p>If Lipinski or Kwan were to finish lower than third over all, the United States Figure Skating Association would face a difficult decision. Since the teen-agers appear assured of earning spots on the Olympic team, either Bobek or Kwiatkowski would very likely be left off. Neither sounded happy about that prospect. ''Whoever places what, they should be sent,'' Bobek said. Said Kwiatkowski: ''I'd be very upset. I'm not saying I'd accept it.''</p>
        <p>''I hope it doesn't happen,'' Morry Stillwell, president of the skating federation, said of the possibility of Lipinski finishing fourth. ''I'd die.''</p>
        <p>All that is speculation. Bobek and Kwiatkowski are erratic long-program skaters. The only thing for certain is, this competition is Kwan's to lose.</p>
        <p>FIGURE SKATING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
