<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Festival Review/Theater; Dilemma: Perform or Die</title>
    <meta content="16ADAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032102"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lincoln Center Festival '98</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Gesher Theater of Israel</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Marks, Peter</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chervinsky, Alexander</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arye, Yevgeny</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Adam Resurrected (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=980DE6DF1630F935A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="1053" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Festival Review/Theater; Dilemma: Perform or Die</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PETER MARKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Marks, Peter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Peter Marks reviews Gesher Theater production of Adam Resurrected, play by Alexander Chervinsky; it is directed by Yevgeny Arye and is staged in Damrosch Park as part of Lincoln Center Festival '98; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The show must go on, even in a death camp. Adam Stein, formerly a Berlin circus star, is ordered to perform for the concentration camp commandant. Told to play a clown, he plays a clown. Ordered to impersonate a dog, he does that, too.</p>
        <p>''What a Jew won't do,'' the commandant sneers, ''for a bone.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The show must go on, even in a death camp. Adam Stein, formerly a Berlin circus star, is ordered to perform for the concentration camp commandant. Told to play a clown, he plays a clown. Ordered to impersonate a dog, he does that, too.</p>
        <p>''What a Jew won't do,'' the commandant sneers, ''for a bone.''</p>
        <p>Crowd-pleasing acts of humiliation are what the degraded, taunting Nazi is after in ''Adam Resurrected,'' a lavishly hallucinatory rendering, by the Gesher Theater from Israel, of one man's Holocaust odyssey, from a sheltered existence as a popular German entertainer to his postwar confinement in an Israeli psychiatric hospital.</p>
        <p>Subtlety is not the Gesher's strong suit: to illustrate the depth of Adam's moral dilemma, for example, the director, Yevgeny Arye, has him walk a tightrope that extends the length of the stage. And yet, overall, the company's treatment of this dense and abstracted material, adapted from a 1968 novel by the Israeli author Yoram Kaniuk, is frequently ingenious and occasionally inspired. Staged in an air-conditioned tent adjacent to the Metropolitan Opera House, the nearly three-hour production is a wildly evocative excursion through the three houses of the absurd in which Adam spends much of his life: a circus, a concentration camp and an asylum.</p>
        <p>The three staging grounds are reflections of aspects of Adam's tortured psyche, where, in a sense, all of ''Adam Resurrected'' takes place. It is not a play told in conventional style, but through the re-creation of the kind of interior narrative everyone composes in the course of their lives, that highly personal assortment of analytical musings, warm and traumatic memories and recurring nightmares, that amount to a running existential conversation with some idea of God.</p>
        <p>What gives order to this chaotically conceived life story are the difficult ethical issues posed by the novelist and his adapter, Alexander Chervinsky. After the terrible complicity forced upon him in the camp, where he entertained the inmates, including his own wife, as they were herded into gas chambers, can a man like Adam reclaim his humanity? Is he worth the time and attentions of a nation filled with so many victims of less dubious standing?</p>
        <p>Mr. Arye's central image for the joyless events of ''Adam Resurrected,'' presented as part of Lincoln Center Festival '98, is that of the circus ring, which may not be the most original metaphor, but it is nonetheless useful here in releasing the Gesher's creative energy. Through the center of the ring, inventively realized by Elena Stepanova, runs a set of railroad tracks onto which the troupe places the rolling stock of props, from hospital beds, prison cells and animal cages, to Adam's performance platforms and the Nazi officer's black leather couch. The tracks, of course, are also a monument to death, the skeletal remains of the cattle cars that transported millions of Jews to the camps.</p>
        <p>The production, in Hebrew with simultaneous English translation, is a panorama of oppressiveness. Nazis in black patent-leather raincoats and fishnet stockings, performing innocent-sounding novelty numbers about springtime in the Fatherland and, even more menacingly, cutting off granny's long braids, are refugees from the Kit Kat Klub; the nod to ''Cabaret'' in general and Sam Mendes's outrageous revival in particular, seems conscious, even if it isn't. The Jews, meanwhile, wear the faded stripes of the camps, whether they are inmates of the camp or the Israeli hospital, where the patients are under the pathetically misguided delusion that Adam is the Messiah.</p>
        <p>Adam, played vigorously by Igor Mirkurbanov -- the vibrant Gesher Theater, a seven-year-old company, is made up primarily of Russian Israelis -- vaults from country to country and era to era on the high-flying trapeze and the other apparatus that Mr. Arye and Ms. Stepanova supply. Mr. Mirkurbanov, sleek and agile, wanders pitiful and ashen-faced across the landscape of his own life (he begins the play in clown's makeup), unsure whether his fate is to be counted among the Nazis' martyred victims or their soulless collaborators.</p>
        <p>In a world of ambiguity, he turns for advice to the play's most bizarre character, Mrs. Seizling, a garish American Jew portrayed in drag by the excellent Vladimir Halemsky. Having given $6 million to the psychiatric hospital in memory of the six million dead, she is anything but conflicted over the Holocaust. For now that she, too is dead, she is hoping that the donation will make her a favorite when the Messiah does return.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Seizling, who pops up in the strangest places, is a touchstone figure, the real clown of ''Adam Resurrected,'' and the embodiment of the most trivial aspects of Holocaust memorialization. The play itself, however, never sinks to triviality. A smart and empathetic ensemble, led by Mr. Mirkurbanov and also featuring other such expressive performers as Israel (Sasha) Demidov, Yevgenya Dodina and Nelly Gosheva, brings a deep sense of passion and commitment to this mini-epic under the big top. And they effortlessly surmount barriers of culture and language that could have made a mess of this extreme and ambitious material.</p>
        <p>Some playgoers may be put off by the overwrought qualities in the writing and the stagecraft. But given the subject matter, it's hard not to forgive a theater company, forged in the Jewish homeland by Russian refugees, for going overboard now and again.</p>
        <p>ADAM RESURRECTED</p>
        <p>By Alexander Chervinsky; based on the novel by Yoram Kaniuk; directed by Yevgeny Arye; assistant director, Elena Krendlin; sets and costumes by Elena Stepanova; music by Avi Benjamin (Nedzvetsky); lighting by Niv Sade; choreography by Valentine Menuhin; stage manager, Tatyana Suchanova; company manager, Victor Sokolov. Gesher Theater. Presented by Lincoln Center Festival '98. At Damrosch Park.</p>
        <p>WITH: Igor Mirkurbanov (Adam Stein), Yevgenya Dodina (Gretchen Stein), Maria Gamburg (Ruth Stein), Israel (Sascha) Demidov (Commandant Klein and Dr. Gross), Vladimir Halemsky (Mrs. Seizling), Nelly Gosheva (Elder Schwester) and Natalia Voltulevich-Manor (Fraulein Klopfer).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
