<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Stuff By Irabu Is Back On Display</title>
    <meta content="16YANK$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1032241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Yankees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Detroit Tigers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Olney, Buster</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980716T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DC1730F935A25754C0A96E958260" item-length="984" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Stuff By Irabu Is Back On Display</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Olney, Buster</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, July 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Yankees beat Detroit Tigers, 11-0; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hideki Irabu loves sushi of all kinds, tuna and whitefish, and the night before each of his starts for the Yankees, in his own ritual, he goes for the soft stuff.</p>
        <p>On the mound, however, Irabu is back to the hard stuff.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Hideki Irabu loves sushi of all kinds, tuna and whitefish, and the night before each of his starts for the Yankees, in his own ritual, he goes for the soft stuff.</p>
        <p>On the mound, however, Irabu is back to the hard stuff.</p>
        <p>He has rediscovered his good fastball, and with it he pitched eight scoreless innings as the Yankees thrashed the Detroit Tigers, 11-0, tonight. It was the Yankees' 16th victory in their last 18 games, and their fourth shutout in their last eight games.</p>
        <p>After flirting with demotion last week, Irabu, who raised his record to 8-3, once again is firmly entrenched in the rotation.</p>
        <p>''Tonight I was able to get the stuff back I had before,'' Irabu said through an interpreter.</p>
        <p>The Yankees slammed three home runs in the eighth inning; Chuck Knoblauch hit one of those, his third homer in his last six games. The Yankees have outscored the Tigers by 44-15 in six games against Detroit this season.</p>
        <p>The Yankees (67-21) continue to match the 1902 Pittsburgh Pirates stride for stride: the teams now share the mark for the best 88-game record in major league history. If the Yankees win only half of their remaining 74 games, they will finish the year with 104 victories, the most since they won 104 in 1963.</p>
        <p>The odds are pretty good they will do better than that; once the Yankees complete the final 4 games of this 11-game trip, they will play 42 of their remaining 70 games at Yankee Stadium, where they have won 33 of 39 games this season.</p>
        <p>Before his start on July 10, Irabu concentrated on correcting his arm angle -- which had dropped from 12 o'clock, on the hands of a clock, to about 11 o'clock -- and the velocity of his fastball increased somewhat. Afterward, Yankee Manager Joe Torre said that he thought Irabu had improved, but that there was still work to be done.</p>
        <p>So in his bullpen session last weekend, Irabu continued to refine his fastball and also addressed his diminished command of his split-fingered fastball. When he is most effective, Irabu gets ahead in the count with his fastball and then throws his split-fingered fastball in the dirt, forcing hitters to chase.</p>
        <p>Facing a team tonight that he routinely overmatches, Irabu was at his best, back to the form he had in April and May.</p>
        <p>The scouts' radar guns behind the plate brightened with glowing red numbers like 93 and 94. Dale Sveum, the utilityman who made a rare start tonight, asked teammates if Irabu seemed to be throwing harder than he has, and they agreed.</p>
        <p>''Tonight it was like he threw the ball at the beginning of the season,'' Knoblauch said.</p>
        <p>Irabu threw strikes with all of his pitches, getting ahead in the count enough to keep the hitters honest and then throwing his split-fingered fastball, which had more movement than at any time since the summer solstice, and a changeup.</p>
        <p>Irabu pitched into trouble only once, walking Geronimo Berroa on four pitches with two outs, before Gabe Alvarez pulled a double down the third-base line. Berroa stopped at third base. Irabu spun a curveball with his first pitch to the next batter, Paul Bako, and it broke over the plate -- too low, according to the plate umpire, Marty Foster. Jorge Posada, the catcher, threw the ball back to Irabu, who caught it head-high and held his glove in place for a moment or two, glaring at Foster.</p>
        <p>Irabu beat himself at times in this manner last year, obsessing on the mound over ball-strike interpretation. Tonight, Irabu climbed up the mound, paused, and then stepped to the back, picking up the resin bag, juggling it a bit, looking down.</p>
        <p>Moving to the rubber again, Irabu dropped the bag to the side -- last year, he would have fired it down -- and returned to the business of pitching to Bako. Irabu threw another curve, this for a strike, pumped a fastball past Bako and then dropped a curve over again for a called Strike 3, perhaps the first time this season Irabu has finished off a hitter with his curveball. End of inning, and perhaps for Irabu, the end of his in-season crisis.</p>
        <p>Irabu allowed five hits, walking three and striking out one. Irabu usually averages as many fly balls as ground balls, but because he kept his fastball down in the strike zone, he generated 13 ground-ball outs, an unusually high number for him. His fastball, Detroit's Bobby Higginson said, tends to tail away and sink, something you do not notice when you see him pitch on television. Irabu allowed at least one home run in each of his six starts since June 4, a total of 12 home runs in that span. But he did not give up a home run tonight.</p>
        <p>''He's just got it back,'' Torre said.</p>
        <p>Hard stuff, and soft.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>After the Yankees bashed three home runs in the eight, the Detroit reliever DEAN CROW hit TINO MARTINEZ with a fastball in the hip. Martinez, who has been hit numerous times this year in suspicious circumstances, glared at Crow and walked slowly to first, before being removed for a pinch-runner. Martinez was not hurt, but he is furious about the number of times he has been hit, and he is not sure if Crow hit him on purpose (Crow said he did not). ''I don't know what to do,'' Martinez said. ''What are your options -- charge the mound, get suspended, get somebody on your own team hurt? Or go to first base?''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
