<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Lawmaker's Aide Indicted on Fraud Charges</title>
    <meta content="Y10IND$05" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1008715"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Congress (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">House of Representatives (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stout, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eppard, Ann</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shuster, Bud (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, Vernon A</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE1D9153DF933A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Lawmaker's Aide Indicted on Fraud Charges</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STOUT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stout, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 9</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ann M Eppard, aide to House transportation committee chmn Bud Shuster, is indicted on charges that she illegally collected over $200,000 by using her position to help two businessmen whose property lay in way of huge Boston construction project; Washington lobbyist Vernon A Clark also is indicted; Shuster is under Federal investigation to determine whether he has wielded improper influence in connection with project (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An associate of the House transportation committee chairman was accused today of illegally collecting more than $200,000 by using her position to help two businessmen whose property lay in the way of a huge Boston construction project.</p>
        <p>A grand jury in Boston indicted Ann M. Eppard, a longtime aide to Representative Bud Shuster, on seven charges that include defrauding the Internal Revenue Service and accepting unlawful gratuities. If convicted, Ms. Eppard faces up to five years in prison and a $250,000 fine on each count, the United States Attorney's office in Boston said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An associate of the House transportation committee chairman was accused today of illegally collecting more than $200,000 by using her position to help two businessmen whose property lay in the way of a huge Boston construction project.</p>
        <p>A grand jury in Boston indicted Ann M. Eppard, a longtime aide to Representative Bud Shuster, on seven charges that include defrauding the Internal Revenue Service and accepting unlawful gratuities. If convicted, Ms. Eppard faces up to five years in prison and a $250,000 fine on each count, the United States Attorney's office in Boston said.</p>
        <p>The indictment did not address the status of Mr. Shuster himself. It has been known for months that the Congressman, a Pennsylvania Republican, was under Federal investigation to determine whether he had wielded improper influence in connection with the ''Big Dig,'' the multibillion-dollar road-and-tunnel project through downtown Boston and under the city's harbor. Amy Rindskopf, a spokeswoman for the United States Attorney's office in Boston, had no comment today on that issue. She said the investigation was continuing.</p>
        <p>Indicted on similar charges was Vernon A. Clark, a Washington lobbyist who the prosecutors said lives in Nevada. The indictment said that Mr. Clark represented the two businessmen whose property was in the way of the project and sought help from Ms. Eppard to get them favorable settlements.</p>
        <p>Ms. Eppard's lawyer, Richard Leon of Washington, declined to comment this evening, but in the past he has described his client's business dealings as legal and aboveboard. Mr. Clark could not be reached immediately through his Washington office.</p>
        <p>Ms. Eppard, who lives in the Washington area, has worked closely with Mr. Shuster since he was elected to Congress in 1972. She was his chief of staff and helped to run his campaigns, until the 1994 elections swept the Republicans into power and made him chairman of the House Transportation and Infrastructure Committee.</p>
        <p>She then left Mr. Shuster's office and started a lobbying business, which became lucrative almost overnight, largely because she has represented transportation interests. She has also continued to help raise money for Mr. Shuster's campaigns, partly by soliciting contributions from those interests.</p>
        <p>Mr. Shuster is under investigation by the House ethics committee, which is looking into his personal, political and financial ties to Ms. Eppard. He has insisted for months that he has reported his campaign contributions properly and that there is nothing improper in his dealings with Ms. Eppard.</p>
        <p>Tonight, Mr. Shuster called the charges ''a political indictment, pure and simple,'' and said Ms. Eppard was ''one of the finest, most decent and dedicated persons I have ever known.''</p>
        <p>No one disputes Mr. Shuster's enormous power as head of the transportation committee, and Ms. Eppard's considerable influence because of her association with him.</p>
        <p>United States Attorney Donald K. Stern said that Ms. Eppard had used her positions on Mr. Shuster's campaign committee and in his Congressional office ''to enrich herself,'' and that her actions ''represented a breach of public trust.'' He said the crimes were committed from 1989, when Ms. Eppard was still in Mr. Shuster's office, through spring 1995.</p>
        <p>The indictment describes a tangle of transactions that it says funneled money to Ms. Eppard in the guise of loans, ''consulting fees'' and, in at least one instance, a so-called loan to one of her relatives to enable him to buy a car dealership. On some occasions, the relative acted as a conduit to relay money from Mr. Clark to Ms. Eppard, the indictment said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
