<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Courtly Bow to Tradition And Those Who Revere It</title>
    <meta content="10JOHN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="40" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1008596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="ART REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Academy Museum and School of the Fine Arts (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Ken</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980410T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B07EEDB143DF933A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="685" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Courtly Bow to Tradition And Those Who Revere It</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEN JOHNSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnson, Ken</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ken Johnson reviews 173d annual exhibition of art at National Academy Museum and School of Fine Arts; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At the National Academy Museum, you won't find the fundamental tenets of Western Civilization interrogated, deconstructed or otherwise insulted by upstart ideologues. Here, the continuity of tradition is assumed and honored; the skillful practice of known modes of art-making trumps the avant-garde.</p>
        <p>That's not necessarily bad. Sometimes one wishes the downtown art world had a little more of the technical virtuosity and connection to the past found in the best National Academy-style work. But one wishes, too, that the academy's traditionalism could be stirred up occasionally by a little more esthetic or intellectual adventurism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At the National Academy Museum, you won't find the fundamental tenets of Western Civilization interrogated, deconstructed or otherwise insulted by upstart ideologues. Here, the continuity of tradition is assumed and honored; the skillful practice of known modes of art-making trumps the avant-garde.</p>
        <p>That's not necessarily bad. Sometimes one wishes the downtown art world had a little more of the technical virtuosity and connection to the past found in the best National Academy-style work. But one wishes, too, that the academy's traditionalism could be stirred up occasionally by a little more esthetic or intellectual adventurism.</p>
        <p>The academy's 173d Annual Exhibition, which was open this year to nonmembers, as it is every other year, steers safely away from anything too novel. Sixteen jurors picked 180 works from 2,000 entries, a collection of almost suffocating familiarity. Only one piece really departs from tradition, a sculpture by Thedra Cullar-Ledford consisting of a cubic assemblage of paperback books capped by a slab of concrete. Called ''5,000 Trashy Romance Novels,'' it looks as if someone delivered it to the wrong museum.</p>
        <p>What's bothersome about the exhibition, however, is not its conservatism but its uneven quality. Way overcrowded, it has the feel of a regional art fair. It's loaded with hackneyed illustrative paintings, abstractions in styles from 20 to 30 years ago, and absurdly anachronistic sculptures, like Michael Keropian's faux-marble rendition of a pair of plunging dolphins supporting a crouching female nude.</p>
        <p>That said, the show is still fun to visit, and you will find good examples of the sorts of things you rarely see in the cutting-edge galleries of SoHo or Chelsea. There is, for example, a lovely, masterly aquatint by Wilfred Loring depicting billowing, light-splashed laundry in a suburban backyard; or Jennifer Brennan French's subtle purple-toned mood painting of a lone coffee mug on a shadowed table, ''Working at Night No. 2.''</p>
        <p>Something especially to be valued is the National Academy's belief in the figure. Among the most arresting works in this show are a number of paintings, sculptures and drawings that not only are technically impressive but also represent the human body with vivid palpability. In Robert Braczyk's dark bronze-colored, nearly life-size sculpture of a naked, 60-ish man in a half-sitting posture,  there's an empathic realism that puts to shame the pretentious, Rodinesque bronzes that Eric Fischl unveiled a few months ago.</p>
        <p>The figure is rendered with poignant narrative simplicity in Judith Wyer's small picture of a young man in a sweatshirt seated on a subway train; seen through the train's open door, bathed in a hazy yellow light, he seems angelic. Of course, the figure can be sexually provocative, too, as in Sigmund Abeles's painting of a voluptuous young woman slouching naked, lap-forward, on the black-leather cushion of a heavy wood armchair; she holds a lipstick in one scarlet-nailed hand and offers a come-hither gaze.</p>
        <p>Eroticized men are in short supply, for some reason; Paul Cadmus's drawing of a seated male nude is a comparatively tame exception. Notwithstanding Steven Assael's intensely penciled full-frontal image of a beautiful naked woman whose body is visibly pierced in four strategic spots, in general there's not much socially or morally challenging figurative imagery. The show has a feeling of pastoral distance from the pressures and conflicts of modern experience.</p>
        <p>In any case, the most affecting works tend to be the less sensational ones, the ones that don't try to bowl you over through showy technique or flamboyant imagery. Jonathan Redmond's compact view of sunlighted brick houses is a slightly blurred, Hopperesque reverie; Wendy Lewis gives her own face a plain yet sensuously painterly immediacy. In such works, alert looking and deft execution make visible the poetry of ordinary things.</p>
        <p>The 173d Annual Exhibition continues at the National Academy Museum, 1083 Fifth Avenue, at 89th Street, through April 26.  ART REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
