<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Metropolitan Diary</title>
    <meta content="23DIAR$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="997544"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metropolitan Diary</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EED9163EF930A15751C0A96E958260" item-length="1151" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Metropolitan Diary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Ron Alexander</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>A bumper sticker spotted on a car at the Belleayre Ski Center in the Catskills: ''Practice random acts of senseless kindness and unexpected generosity.''</p>
        <p>And on the other side of the same bumper: ''My kid beat up your honor student.''</p>
        <p>ROBERT W. THUSS Jr.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>DEAR DIARY:</p>
        <p>A bumper sticker spotted on a car at the Belleayre Ski Center in the Catskills: ''Practice random acts of senseless kindness and unexpected generosity.''</p>
        <p>And on the other side of the same bumper: ''My kid beat up your honor student.''</p>
        <p>ROBERT W. THUSS Jr.</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>There have been a lot of upscale coffee houses opening in my neighborhood. I realized that my favorite haunt wasn't trying to compete when I saw a sign advertising a new coffee called 30-Flavor Blend: ''30 different flavored beans delicately and indiscriminately blended for the nondiscerning coffee drinker.''</p>
        <p>SANKAR MUKHOPADHYAY</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Here's one of those ''only in New York'' stories: one evening I made plans with a friend of a friend whom I'd met once before, three years earlier. Mark was to meet me outside one of the exits for the subway stop at Broadway and 86th. Our friend had given me a refresher description of Mark, and said he'd be wearing a blue outfit.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, I was terribly late. When I finally arrived, Mark had a funny story to tell. He'd been waiting when a young woman fitting my description walked out of the subway. Mark approached her, and the two shared a friendly hug.</p>
        <p>He asked how the trip was. She said it was O.K., apologized for being late, and explained she had been tied up transferring from across town.</p>
        <p>Mark then realized this young woman wasn't me because he knew I wouldn't be coming from across town. He asked if she was Debbie. She said no, and abashedly walked away.</p>
        <p>Mark then watched this young woman approach another young man, as tall and brunet as he is, who was also standing at the corner. This time the young woman hooked up with the right date and the pair disappeared down Broadway.</p>
        <p>DEBORAH GUBB</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Riding on a Madison Avenue bus recently, I overheard a conversation between a mother and her 2-year-old daughter.</p>
        <p>''Talia,'' the mother said, ''you know that your brothers are boys, your father is a boy, and your grandfathers are boys, and that you and I and grandma are girls. Now, tell me what are you?''</p>
        <p>And the little girl answered, ''I'm cute.''</p>
        <p>ILENE A. COWEN</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I was walking on Fifth Avenue in the Village when I heard a panhandler sitting on a box in front of the First Presbyterian Church saying, ''Change, change, change.''</p>
        <p>A youngish man in a business suit strode by and replied, ''I'm trying, I'm trying.''</p>
        <p>GENE SECUNDA</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>I took my 5 1/2-year-old adopted nephew, Ian, ice skating at the Sky Rink at Chelsea Piers not long ago. Afterward, while untying his double-knots, he asked me to completely unlace his skates. When I told him that he was just being lazy, he replied, ''I'm not being lazy; this is just what I consider good service.''</p>
        <p>ANDREW J. CHEN</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>Strolling down First Avenue on a recent afternoon, I observed a threesome of young boys, bulging book bags hanging down their backs, engaged in intense conversation. ''And you know,'' said one of the lads, ''I've known my mother for eight years.''</p>
        <p>BETTY DAVID</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>When I was a boy, my mother decided that one of the lessons a New York child needed to learn was how to spot an out-of-towner. Pointers would be administered periodically, usually when we were Downtown, as the area between 34th and 59th Streets was then called.</p>
        <p>One day I was informed that the wearing of very bright clothes Downtown was a tip-off. Another time it was explained that if one saw a couple casually walking up Madison Avenue arm in arm in the middle of the work day (''at 2 o'clock on a Tuesday afternoon'' was the expression, if I remember correctly), they were most probably out-of-towners.</p>
        <p>How eagerly my mother would have seized on a car I spotted in Greenwich Village recently. Although it had New York license plates, it had a bumper sticker proclaiming the charms of what is no doubt a lovely -- albeit a definitely out-of-town -- beauty spot. It read, ''Bellevue is Beautiful.''</p>
        <p>CHARLES POTTER</p>
        <p>Dear Diary:</p>
        <p>A 61-year-old woman finds her way through a northeaster to a famous New York steak house where she's meeting a gentleman for dinner. She's a few minutes early and asks the host if Mr. Shelley has arrived.</p>
        <p>She isn't sure if the host heard, so she repeats Mr. Shelley's name two or three times, questioningly. Our host asserts firmly that he has not arrived yet and offers to take her to a table to wait.</p>
        <p>Seating the woman at a small table against the wall near the kitchen, he gestures to the empty chair across from her. ''A lady friend?'' he asks. Stunned, she reminds him that she is waiting for Mr. Shelley.</p>
        <p>''O.K., or a gentleman,'' he says as he walks away.</p>
        <p>''This is what happens when you're a woman of a certain age,'' she remarks to a waiter standing by, her enthusiasm for dinner suddenly dampened.</p>
        <p>Twenty minutes later, the woman asks the waiter to call the restaurant's branch across the street, where Mr. Shelley is discovered waiting. She pays for the glass of wine she ordered and crosses the street in the rain. The other restaurant is nearly empty, the booth spacious, the waiters warm and welcoming. Mr. Shelley has brought a birthday present of Tuscan memoirs that feature wonderful food.</p>
        <p>They settle in for lobster and the northeaster blows away.</p>
        <p>JOANNA BULL</p>
        <p>The Circus</p>
        <p>Amid the familiar music</p>
        <p>You can hear the crack of the ringmaster's whip</p>
        <p>The cacophony of the elephants</p>
        <p>Marching stem to stern</p>
        <p>The banter of the clowns</p>
        <p>With big feet and squirting flowers</p>
        <p>And the laughter of children</p>
        <p>With cotton candy smiles</p>
        <p>Gaining memories to last a lifetime.</p>
        <p>ELLEN FUCHS</p>
        <p>While waiting in the lobby of the Lunt-Fontanne Theater, Susan B. Nashel overheard a mother explaining to her daughter and three young friends that this version of ''The Titanic'' was not like the movie version.</p>
        <p>The girls were oblivious, so the mother repeated herself that the Broadway musical would be different from the movie. After yet another reminder, one of the girls turned to her and asked incredulously, ''You mean Leonardo DiCaprio is not going to be in it?''</p>
        <p>Observations for this column may be sent to Metropolitan Diary, Style Department, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York 10036. Please include your name, address and daytime telephone number; upon request, names may be withheld in print. Letters become the property of The Times and cannot be returned. They may be edited, and may be republished in all media.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
