<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The 10 Biggest Little Stories of 1997; Hey, Whose Face Is It?</title>
    <meta content="FEAT4" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="983698"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nineteen Hundred Ninety-Seven</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewine, Edward</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">History</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E1DB1631F93BA15751C1A961958260" item-length="741" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The 10 Biggest Little Stories of 1997; Hey, Whose Face Is It?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD LEWINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewine, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Comment on ubiquitous film crews on streets of New York, as reported in 1997; movie and television industry spent about $2.2 billion, paid about ten percent of that in taxes, and employed more than 70,000 New Yorkers in 1997 (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As news goes -- the big single events that chill spines, get the pulse racing and last for weeks -- it was not the busiest of years.</p>
        <p>Not that the big news did not exist. There was Abner Louima and the awful brutality against him and the plight of the deaf Mexicans in horrific conditions in Queens. These stories seemed to capture deeper urban truths. But the mayoral election, part political funeral, part coronation, was largely a dud, devoid of the kind of psychological venting a mayoral race can provide. Even the shooting rampage atop the Empire State Building, with its potential for intense symbolism, was a tribute to one individual's madness, providing little illumination, and it passed from notice quickly.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As news goes -- the big single events that chill spines, get the pulse racing and last for weeks -- it was not the busiest of years.</p>
        <p>Not that the big news did not exist. There was Abner Louima and the awful brutality against him and the plight of the deaf Mexicans in horrific conditions in Queens. These stories seemed to capture deeper urban truths. But the mayoral election, part political funeral, part coronation, was largely a dud, devoid of the kind of psychological venting a mayoral race can provide. Even the shooting rampage atop the Empire State Building, with its potential for intense symbolism, was a tribute to one individual's madness, providing little illumination, and it passed from notice quickly.</p>
        <p>Crime continued to drop; tourists continued to come; a Metropolitan Transportation Authority surplus led to new fare structures. But to understand the year it might be better to look at the city as it unfolded day to day, beyond the biggest headlines -- its tiny dramas; its newest playthings; the neighborhoods that grew; the great desire for order that seemed to grip many neighborhoods; the degree of commercial vitality.</p>
        <p>So instead of the biggest stories of 1997, we examine the biggest little ones.</p>
        <p>ONE dull mid-November morning, the residents of Tiemann Place in Morningside Heights awoke to what they saw as a challenge to their rights. The makers of a Fiona Apple video being shot had posted signs warning passers-by that they were ''irrevocably'' consenting to having their image used ''worldwide, for any purpose whatsoever in perpetuity.''</p>
        <p>Residents, who jokingly call their street ''Little Hollywood,'' say film crews are common on this block, but many were angered by the signs, which seemed to suggest that average people didn't have the right to their own image. ''It was patently offensive,'' said Jeff Berry, a resident.</p>
        <p>How fitting, in a year when film, television and the news media have burnished New York's image to a gleam, that some New Yorkers were fighting what they saw as the hijacking of their images by a film crew. It was the quintessential push and pull of a city that benefits from film production even though it can cause headaches.</p>
        <p>It isn't certain yet exactly how much local film production there was in 1997, because the Mayor's Office of Film, Theater and Television won't release those numbers until February. But Julianne Cho, a spokeswoman, did say 1997 would probably equal or surpass 1996, which was a record year. ''We are at least on par with '96,'' Ms. Cho said.</p>
        <p>That means that around 21,000 days worth of filming took place in the city in 1997, including feature and student films, television, commercials and videos. The industry spent around $2.2 billion, paid about 10 percent of that in taxes, and employed more than 70,000 New Yorkers. Not to mention all of that great public relations.</p>
        <p>The city is like a celebrity on a success high. It is hard not to get caught up in the sheer narcissism of living in a place that is featured live every day on NBC's ''Today'' show and David Letterman, that appears on seven network series and that starred in many feature films this year, including ''Men in Black.''</p>
        <p>Of course many see a negative side to the city's second career as an actor. Even nice film crews requisition precious parking spaces, make fumes and noise, shine bright lights at night and order locals around. What makes it worse is that most New Yorkers feel that their local streets belong to them. That opinion is not shared by all. ''If you choose to live in a city as big as ours than this is what you will get,'' Ms. Cho said.</p>
        <p>As for the imbroglio on Tiemann Place. Well, the film company took the signs down (the city said it had already decided to try to issue fewer permits to film there in the future). Many of the people on the block who had been complaining were mollified. That is, except for some of the young Fiona Apple fans who were sad Ms. Apple was leaving.</p>
        <p>''Our parents don't like it,'' said 11-year-old Lana Kalaitzis about all the filming on Tiemann. ''But who really cares?''</p>
        <p>EDWARD LEWINE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
