<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Bliss of the Big City</title>
    <meta content="14KERMODT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="957745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kermode, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lessing, Doris</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Walking in the Shade (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E6DC1230F937A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="2681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Bliss of the Big City</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Frank Kermode</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kermode, Frank</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Frank Kermode reviews book Walking in the Shade: Volume Two of My Autobiography, 1949-1962 by Doris Lessing; drawing (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walking in the Shade</p>
        <p>Volume Two of My Autobiography, 1949-1962.</p>
        <p>By Doris Lessing.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 404 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $27.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Walking in the Shade</p>
        <p>Volume Two of My Autobiography, 1949-1962.</p>
        <p>By Doris Lessing.</p>
        <p>Illustrated. 404 pp. New York:</p>
        <p>HarperCollins Publishers. $27.50.</p>
        <p>Doris Lessing is evidently serious about her autobiography, which is already over 800 pages. Volume 1 begins with an account of her family from around 1827, a researcher having been hired to ferret out the ancestral facts. Volume 2 ends around the time of ''The Golden Notebook,'' a novel now 35 years old, which, as she herself is willing to admit, has long since achieved classic status.</p>
        <p>At the end of ''Walking in the Shade'' she is still in her early 40's, with something like half a remarkably full life to go. The statesmanlike length of the book is probably justified by the extraordinary variety of her achievements, her exceptional memory and her facility as a writer. Volume 1, ''Under My Skin,'' tells first of an unusual childhood, and does so with such easy power that it lends support to the generalization about literary autobiographies: that the childhood bits are likely to be the best. Born in Persia of English parents shortly after the end of World War I, this child was taken home to England via Russia, a most unusual route, and was then transferred, a middle-class refugee from depressed England, to Southern Rhodesia. She still thinks of that war as the catastrophe from which we have never recovered, and clearly regards the life of her sick and embittered father as a symbol of the damage it inflicted directly on a whole generation and indirectly on its successors. That her bourgeois English parents should be homesteading, under very difficult circumstances, in southern Africa was only one consequence of the great disaster.</p>
        <p>Remembering the usual fate of humanity in historical toils of this kind, Lessing sometimes wonders why it is that people continue to expect so much for themselves, as they surely would not if they remembered ''how things were,'' and presumably how they fundamentally still are. We always seem to think that everything will get better, and that this is what we deserve. How wrong we are! But since remembering is what she is very good at, she cannot help reporting her own early days as quite privileged, if not without tolerable hardship. Africa is exotic but acceptable: trees, snakes, horses, donkeys, servants and compulsory, hated siestas.</p>
        <p>The siestas are rendered with a specificity that probably originates in the moment of writing rather than in raw memory, ''fond memory, fond lying memory'' (insofar as they can be distinguished, and autobiographers know they can't, really), but the writing of the moment is itself memorable: ''On my back, arms stretched, I took possession of my cool body, that thudded, pulsed and trickled with sounds. I flexed my feet. I tested my fingers, one by one, all present, all correct, my friends, my friend, my body. I sniffed my fingers where smells of roast beef and carrots lingered. The golden syrup of the steamed pudding sent intense sweetness into my brain, and made my nostrils flare. My forearm smelled of sun. The minute golden hairs flattened as I blew on them, like wind on the long grasses along the ditches. Silence. The dead. full, contented silence of midday in the bush.''</p>
        <p>Here a peculiar sentience is registered, as modified by the foreign colonial environment, all the more distinctive in that it is compounded with the smells of English suburban food -- just as the men who ground out livings on the edge of the bush became, in their intervals of leisure, parodies of hard-drinking, macho stay-at-homes. The physical intensity of the girl's self-perceptions, and her sense of the place, are entirely relevant to the character of the writer she was to become.</p>
        <p>Few writers could keep that style up indefinitely -- perhaps Joyce does, in ''A Portrait of the Artist'' -- and in any case Lessing has far more to write about than disparate epiphanies. In this alien setting she did at least some of the things her mother (remembered with respect but little affection) required. She read the right books -- her father was Eeyore, her mother Kanga, herself Tigger, a bouncy good sport. But conformism didn't last long; twice married and a single mother with a small son before she was 30, she also got involved with the left, and eventually with the Communist Party, associations described in great and credible detail. Then, after long years of waiting, she went off to London with her son.</p>
        <p>''Volume One is being written without snags and blocks of conscience, she says presciently. ''But Volume Two, that is, from the time I reached London, will be a different matter, even if I follow the example of Simone de Beauvoir, who said that about some things she had no intention of telling the truth. (Then why bother? -- the reader must be expected to ask.) I have known not a few of the famous, and even one or two of the great, but I do not believe it is the duty of friends, lovers, comrades, to tell all. The older I get the more secrets I have, never to be revealed.''</p>
        <p>In fact Volume 2 has plenty to say about the famous and the great, about friends, lovers and comrades, though it says nothing as purely interesting as that account of a childhood siesta. Still, it is excellent on the London of 1949, bleak, bombed and rationed it seemed forever, where she was clinging to existence ''with her fingertips,'' though still able to make the acquaintance of an extraordinary number of famous and even great persons. ''I have far too much material for this second volume,'' she vivaciously announces, and so cannot, she thinks, make it well shaped.</p>
        <p>There were several reasons for this abundance. One was politics, the New Left and the Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament, the latter adherence responsible for an unhappy encounter with the ancient, deluded Bertrand Russell, as well as for less daunting experiences, including the first Aldermaston antinuclear march -- now, if it is generally remembered at all, believed incorrectly to have proceeded from, rather than to, Aldermaston, which annoys those of us who were there with our threatened babes in our arms, watching the gate and listening to the bellowings of leaders of the patriotic opposition, whose car and bullhorn suffered some unpacifistic damage -- deplored, though perhaps only a little, by the marchers.</p>
        <p>Lessing had left Southern Rhodesia, where the right-wing opposition was rougher and potentially more violent, a convinced radical, and remained one in her new and unfamiliar environment. There is much here about the postwar English class system -- ''the working classes, the lower classes, have 'internalized' their station in life'' -- about the follies and oddities of the Communist Party, and, by hindsight, about the damage it did to writers convinced of their ''revolutionary duty.'' As an example of the ruined writer she specifies the talented Jack Lindsay. There is nothing halfhearted about her later detestation of Communism. She is very severe on the geneticist J. B. S. Haldane, in his way a great man, but, she says, ''People like these were originals, and, like all their kind, shared the characteristic that when they talked about the Soviet Union, every word was rubbish.''</p>
        <p>Another reason for the abundance of material was her social success. Although she hated meetings of every kind, she allowed herself to be planted on the management committee of the Society of Authors: ''They expected from me the dishonesty and double-dealing characteristic of the comrades.'' She remained suspicious of the English and claimed to know little about them. But she soon learned how to deal with publishers, whom as a tribe she distrusted, not least because they seemed to have so little interest in books. She was quickly at her ease in literary London, and was often a guest at the eccentric Scottish house of Haldane's sister, Naomi Mitchison. There were trips to Spain, Germany and Russia. The list of interesting acquaintances, friends and lovers continued to grow: from Clancy Sigal to the Royal Court Theater set, Ken Tynan, John Wain, Vanessa Redgrave, and, more marginally, Mikhail Sholokhov and Paul Robeson.</p>
        <p>''The bliss of big cities is knowing people who may not care to know each other, and only those who have had to live in the provinces -- like Salibury, Southern Rhodesia -- can appreciate the freedom of it,'' Lessing writes. Here was a woman who, for all her lingering distrust of the English, lived in London as Yeats said Verlaine lived in Paris, like a fly in a honeypot. And the experience yields some good anecdotes.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most interesting of her London adventures in those earlier years were the night walks. Avoiding the big streets ''because I felt them to be alien, with a hard self-sufficiency that excluded me,'' she gloried in the unfamiliar, in the ''frightful immensities'' of the city. Not that London was convivial; in those days everything was closed at midnight, nothing passed but the late night buses and helpful policemen. No fear of rape; and she wonders why ''contemporary women scream or swoon at the sight of a penis they have not been introduced to, feel demeaned by a suggestive remark and send for a lawyer if a man pays them a compliment.''</p>
        <p>This boldness did not banish the sense of exclusion; she did not understand what she was seeing: ''If, suddenly, a light had come on in a house where the windows had been reflecting a dim streetlight, then it had been as if the place had raised its eyes to look at me: Who are you?'' There are several passages of this kind, written with an admirable easy force. One such is on the business of writing itself:</p>
        <p>''Work begins. I do not sit down but wander about the room. I think on my feet, while I wash up a cup, tidy a drawer, drink a cup of tea, but my mind is not on these activities. I find myself in the chair by the machine. I write a sentence . . . will it stand? . . . And so it goes on. I walk and I prowl, my hands busy with this and that. You'd think I was a paragon of concern for housekeeping if you judged by what you saw. I drop off into sleep for a few minutes, because I have wrought myself into a state of uncomfortable electric tension. I walk, I write. . . . And so it goes on, all day, until it is time to fetch the child from school or until he arrives at the door.''</p>
        <p>This is very good writing though not obviously so, yet it is not on the face of it very different from a good deal of rather gray prose, passages where you feel she is just typing on to complete a stint, and perhaps not looking it over later: ''Maureen Prior was sent the play and loved it so much she staggered from her sickbed, where she was ill, and came out in a bitter wind to the cold theater to audition.'' There are a good many blots of this kind. ''Isaac Deutscher thought Lenin, one of history's most ruthless murderers, was the Perfect Man. Interesting, that: it is a concept from spiritual traditions.''</p>
        <p>Yet one of Lessing's most firmly held beliefs is precisely that what has been written requires energetic scrutiny as an indispensable part of the process, and that failure to follow through in this way is a fundamental failure of talent. She mentions having read in manuscript some 30 novels, many produced in trying circumstances. She found that they were all ''nearly good,'' and this tempts her to an interesting generalization: ''All writers . . . go through the stage when what we write is nearly good: the writing lacks some kind of inward clinching, the current has not run clear. We go on writing, reading, throwing away not-quite-good-enough work, and then one day something has happened, a process has been completed, a step forward has been taken: these cliches are here because it is hard to say what has happened. But the process of writing and rewriting, and of reading the best, has at last succeeded. Professional writers all know this period of apprenticeship. Amateur writers cling to their early uneven drafts and won't let them go. Every one of the novels I was sent was the work of a talented person. Every one needed to be rewritten, or put away and another attempted.''</p>
        <p>So, after much sacrifice, all this buried talent was wasted, and none of the writers was heard of again, simply for want of letting go or pushing on at the right moment. It is a sad but instructive anecdote, though it may not be applicable to the greatest talents -- one cannot imagine Joyce or Proust letting go, for both had what Lessing calls the ''my-novel syndrome.'' On the other hand, there are those among our younger novelists, Jim Crace or Tim Parks, for instance, who let go so completely between novels that it is quite hard to see their works as all from the same hand. Lessing makes the further point that all 30 books were about ''small, sensible, decent, hopeful lives, with no aspirations to be fashionable or sensational,'' and claims to believe we need more writing about ''that England.'' Perhaps the lack of power either to drive on or let go is another aspect of the small, sensible, decent, hopeful lives of those who choose to write about just such lives.</p>
        <p>The epithet ''small'' can't possibly be applied to Lessing's own life, which has been energetic, ambitious and full of achievement. In 1958 she was making</p>
        <p>Frank Kermode's latest book is ''Not Entitled,'' a memoir.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Frank Kermode's latest book is ''Not Entitled,'' a memoir.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
