<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEHIND THE WHEEL/1998 Honda Accord; Ex-Champ Returns to Center Court</title>
    <meta content="14AUTO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="957425"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Honda Motor Co</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krebs, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00E0DE1139F937A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="1399" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEHIND THE WHEEL/1998 Honda Accord; Ex-Champ Returns to Center Court</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE KREBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krebs, Michelle</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michelle Krebs article on 1998 Honda Accord sedan; photo (M)m</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE high-stakes market for midsize sedans is not unlike an intensely competitive tennis tournament.</p>
        <p>Every year, a new model charges onto the court, driving a forceful serve that challenges its opponents to return it.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE high-stakes market for midsize sedans is not unlike an intensely competitive tennis tournament.</p>
        <p>Every year, a new model charges onto the court, driving a forceful serve that challenges its opponents to return it.</p>
        <p>The Honda Accord reigned supreme until Ford's Taurus stole the title of America's best-selling car. Along came the Toyota Camry, setting new standards for the class, followed by a modified Accord. A new Taurus aimed at the Camry as a benchmark, but double-faulted. A less-expensive Camry hit the showrooms and moved into first place in sales.</p>
        <p>All the while, numerous wannabes have scrambled to gain a piece of this bread-and-butter segment that experts say could amount to four million sales a year. Among them, General Motors has thrown its considerable weight into fielding a new team that moves it closer to the top rankings.</p>
        <p>Each year, with each new entry, the caliber of play ratchets up a notch, and 1998 will be no exception. The American Honda Motor Company is preparing to introduce a 1998 Accord that is bigger, more powerful and better equipped, but is priced about the same. It looks like the top seed in this year's tournament of champions.</p>
        <p>Honda calls the 1998 makeover of its high-volume Accord the most significant in the model's 22-year history.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the Accord has grown a full size, based on the passenger volume classifications of the Environmental Protection Agency: It's now a midsize, not a compact. With seven additional cubic feet of interior space, the new Accord is strikingly roomier than the Camry and roughly comparable to the Taurus. One big plus is the additional leg room in the back seat.</p>
        <p>While bigger than before, the deep trunk, at 14.1 cubic feet, matches that of the Camry but is considerably smaller than the cargo compartments of midsize G.M. cars like the import-fighting Oldsmobile Intrigue.</p>
        <p>The extra space was created without significantly changing the Accord's overall dimensions, so the car still feels maneuverable and easy to park. The 106.9-inch wheelbase is unchanged, though the car is slightly longer, wider and taller.</p>
        <p>The Accord platform will be used for a range of vehicles sold around the world, including a large mini-van and a big sport utility vehicle that will be available in the United States in future years. The Japanese, who shunned the previous Accord, are getting a shorter, narrower version packed with electronic gadgets, and Europeans will receive yet another Accord that is smaller and firmer-riding than the American version.</p>
        <p>But the big news for now is the difference between the sedan and the coupe. Though all-new, the four-door continues to be conservatively styled. The distinctive coupe shares a family resemblance, but it looks more like a cousin than a fraternal twin.</p>
        <p>While the sedan's basic shape is much the same, its designers borrowed some sharp-edged touches from the wedge-shaped Acura CL, another Honda product. Two creases run from the taillamps to the headlamps -- one just below the window sills and another at the mid-door level, easing over the wheel wells. The pattern is repeated in the hood. The creases produce the refined finish of well-pressed trousers. Still, buyers seeking more styling flair might prefer the Intrigue or the soon-to-come 1998 Chrysler Concorde or Dodge Intrepid.</p>
        <p>The interior, while obviously freshened, is familiar. The gathered leather on the doors and seats, complemented by wood-look panels on the doors and around the shifter, gave the top-of-the-line EX test car a softened, elegant finish.</p>
        <p>Controls and gauges are presented in Honda's usual straightforward, logical fashion. The dash is simple and clear. The knobs and buttons are pleasing to the touch and operate with precision.</p>
        <p>Interior changes are subtle, like the slight upward angle of the center-dash control panel. The buttons for the premium sound system, which includes a front-loading compact disk player, are large and widely spaced, making it easy to make selections while wearing gloves.</p>
        <p>Storage is bountiful. All four doors and the backs of the front bucket seats have pockets. The deep bin under the center armrest can hold the optional compact disk changer with space left over for CD's. Another open-faced bin at the front of the console is sloped and lined with rubber to prevent objects from flying out. The glove box, similarly deep and angled, is ample, though at the expense of front-passenger knee room. An overhead compartment stores sunglasses or a Home Link system (standard on the EX V6) that can be programmed to open a garage door or security gate. Two side-by-side cup holders are positioned in front of the center armrest. An indent alongside the shifter holds a pen.</p>
        <p>In contrast to the center rear-seat armrest of the Buick Regal that I recently tested, the Accord's lays flat so that its two cup holders (one small, one larger) are truly usable. The rear seat also has what I, my children and their car-pool friends have come to believe is vital -- a shoulder-lap belt for the center occupant. Until now, the Camry was  virtually alone in offering such a belt.</p>
        <p>The rear seat also has a pass-through that can be used for skis and locked when not in use. The rear seat folds down and also locks.</p>
        <p>The Accord EX seats, with power adjusters, are far more comfortable than Honda seats of the past, though the seats of the LX model I also drove were less so, particularly lacking lumbar support for tall drivers.</p>
        <p>The Accord's 2.3-liter four-cylinder engine comes in three versions. The base DX model uses a 135-horsepower version. A VTEC version that produces 150 horsepower satisfies California's low-emission standards. And Californians who buy the top-line EX four-cylinder with an automatic transmission will be driving the first mass-produced car that meets their state's even more stringent Ultra-Low Emission Vehicle standards.</p>
        <p>This year, for the first time, the Accord borrows its V6 -- a 3-liter, 200-horsepower power plant -- from the Acura 3.0CL coupe.</p>
        <p>While Honda is promoting this new Accord, especially the coupe, as sportier than its predecessor, it is making a stick shift available only on four-cylinder models. The Camry offers a five-speed manual with either engine.</p>
        <p>Having driven all the various versions of the new Accord, I'd save some money and some fuel by opting for the four-cylinder VTEC. This is a very peppy engine, especially when mated to the five-speed manual. The V6 is smooth and powerful, but doesn't stand out from the competition's similar engines. Honda does plan to cut the rather steep price of V6 Accords, though final prices have not been announced.</p>
        <p>The Accord's ride leans toward the soft side. The car glides over pavement cracks, tar strips and small potholes without incident. Its ride and handling, like those of other high-volume sedans, are tuned toward people who simply want to commute in relative peace.</p>
        <p>In addition to more room and more power, the Accord comes with more equipment in every model. This approach contrasts with Toyota's, which cut corners -- most of them not noticeable to the consumer -- to keep prices down.</p>
        <p>Since the Accord is the No. 1 choice of car thieves everywhere, Honda has made standard on all models an anti-theft system that immobilizes the engine unless a key is used that contains the correctly coded chip.</p>
        <p>While prices will not be announced until closer to the sedan's Sept. 25 on-sale date (the coupe goes on sale Oct. 25), four-cylinder Accords are expected to cost about the same as before. The lowest base price of a 1997 sedan is $15,495. V6 models, which now start at $25,100, will fall by about $1,000.</p>
        <p>The Camry, the current champion among midsize sedans, is on track to be the best-selling car in America for 1997. But its reign could be short-lived if Honda can turn out more than the 375,000 coupes and sedans it plans to build annually.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK: Advantage, Accord. Next serve, please.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
