<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Bald Eagles to Housing Starts</title>
    <meta content="14ALMA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="957365"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="JERSEYANA"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Demographics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, George</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">New Jersey Almanac (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F05E1DA1339F937A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="585" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Bald Eagles to Housing Starts</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE JAMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">James, George</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on newly published New Jersey Almanac; list; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There were 12 bald eagle nests in New Jersey in 1995, up from only one in 1975, and 7,988,000 people last year, up 3.3 percent from 1990.</p>
        <p>The most popular names for babies last year (of people, not eagles) were Samantha, Jessica, Nicole, Emily and Amanda for girls and, for boys, the perennial Michael, followed by Matthew, Christopher, Nicholas and Joseph.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There were 12 bald eagle nests in New Jersey in 1995, up from only one in 1975, and 7,988,000 people last year, up 3.3 percent from 1990.</p>
        <p>The most popular names for babies last year (of people, not eagles) were Samantha, Jessica, Nicole, Emily and Amanda for girls and, for boys, the perennial Michael, followed by Matthew, Christopher, Nicholas and Joseph.</p>
        <p>Chances are their families drive a Ford, which seems to be the car of choice among New Jersey motorists.</p>
        <p>These disparate items of information along with many more dealing with heavier matters like employment, income, taxes and state and local government can be found in a new book, ''The New Jersey Almanac.''</p>
        <p>The 364-page, 8 1/2-by-11-inch paperback is published by the Public Affairs Research Institute of New Jersey Inc. of Princeton. The need for such a book has been evident for years, said Don Linky, president of the institute, an independent, non-profit organization supported by business and nonprofit organizations that provides research, information and analysis on trends and issues affecting New Jersey.</p>
        <p>''We've always found it difficult to find information about New Jersey from one convenient source,'' said Mr. Linky, who even had the problem as a member of Gov. Brendan T. Byrne's administration from 1975 to 1982, as the first director of the Governor's office on policy and planning and later as chief counsel.</p>
        <p>Making the problem more acute has been a cutback in publishing by the state government in recent years as a result of overall budget reductions, he added.</p>
        <p>During the actual writing of the almanac, which took about six months, he and two staff members, Joan Ponessa and Gwenyth Russo, drew on data bases the institute had been building for years.</p>
        <p>''We tried to get a selection of interesting facts and statistics which give people an overview of different areas,'' Mr. Linky said. As for items of lesser import, like Ford leading in new passenger car registrations in 1994 with 52,560, or the most popular baby names, he said, ''I think it's fun to lighten things up a little.''</p>
        <p>Like any almanac, this one contains information on many subjects: tax rates and population, largest employers, comparative tax rates with other states, employment figures, retail sales, exports, consumer price trends, personal income and tax burden by income level, to name only a few.</p>
        <p>The initial printing was 300 books. The price is $85 plus shipping for a total of $94.10.  The response so far has been ''very strong,'' Mr. Linky said.</p>
        <p>Kenneth French, head librarian of the New Jersey room of the Jersey City Library, recalled that the last time a complete volume about New Jersey facts was published was in the mid-1960's. It too was called ''The New Jersey Almanac.''</p>
        <p>''In terms of one complete, overall volume, this is the first in 30 years,'' said Mr. French, who is often asked esoteric questions about the state that are difficult to find answers for. ''I think it is excellent and will be invaluable.'' Then he said, ''It's actually a little drier than I thought it would be. It's a little more statistical.'' But not meaning to offend, he quickly added that for librarians and historians, the more statistics the better.</p>
        <p>''Dry is good,'' he said.</p>
        <p>JERSEYANA</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
