<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Amanda Beesley, Nicholas Weinstock</title>
    <meta content="14VOWS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Society Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="51" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="957466"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="WEDDINGS: VOWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WEDDINGS AND ENGAGEMENTS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BEESLEY, AMANDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINSTOCK, NICHOLAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Columns/Vows</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style/Weddings and Celebrations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weddings and Engagements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2DD1139F937A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="771" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Amanda Beesley, Nicholas Weinstock</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOIS SMITH BRADY</byline>
      <dateline>CHILMARK, Mass.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON Sept. 6, Amanda Beesley and Nicholas Weinstock were married outside the bridegroom's family home on Martha's Vineyard, in a yard full of gnarly, weather-beaten scrub oaks with branches growing sideways like flags in a strong wind.</p>
        <p>As 160 guests gathered on wooden chairs that looked as if they had come from a schoolhouse, the bride walked down the long, sandy driveway in a tiara and a poufy, bouncy knee-length dress designed by Mary Adams, a downtown couturiere.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON Sept. 6, Amanda Beesley and Nicholas Weinstock were married outside the bridegroom's family home on Martha's Vineyard, in a yard full of gnarly, weather-beaten scrub oaks with branches growing sideways like flags in a strong wind.</p>
        <p>As 160 guests gathered on wooden chairs that looked as if they had come from a schoolhouse, the bride walked down the long, sandy driveway in a tiara and a poufy, bouncy knee-length dress designed by Mary Adams, a downtown couturiere.</p>
        <p>''Everything about Amanda is fun,'' said Marisa Wolsky, who met the bride when they were students at Barnard College. ''Amanda is the kind of person who would get up on a table and dance. And she's got a great laugh. I find I'm funnier when I'm around her.''</p>
        <p>The bride, 29, and the bridegroom, 27, met almost four years ago, when Ms. Beesley was a literary agent at ICM and Mr. Weinstock was an assistant editor at Random House. For months, the two had talked on the phone almost daily, discussing authors and manuscripts, but never met in person.</p>
        <p>''I pictured him as really literary and nerdy,'' the bride said. ''I thought he looked like Woody Allen.''</p>
        <p>When they finally made an appointment for lunch, she hoped until the last minute that he would cancel. To her surprise, lunch went well, their first date even better. Mr. Weinstock showed up not with flowers but with homemade beer, which made her laugh.</p>
        <p>''We went out to dinner and then to hear music at CBGB's,'' she recalled. ''On the way home, it was slushy and wet and we came up to one of those huge New York vats of slush, and Nicky picked me up and carried me over it. I was very impressed. I'm always impressed when someone can pick me up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Weinstock tried to impress her in other ways as well. Ms. Beesley, who lived at the time in a tiny apartment overlooking a basketball court on Houston Street and the Avenue of the Americas, began spotting him outside.</p>
        <p>''Nicky used to play basketball under her window,'' recalled Nicky Davidoff, a friend of the bridegroom. ''Whenever he played anybody on that court, he would decimate them.''</p>
        <p>Recently, the bride and the bridegroom left their jobs to write novels. ''It was very romantic to quit together,'' said Mr. Weinstock, whose first book, a work of nonfiction, ''The Secret Love of Sons'' (Putnam), came out in the spring. ''When you're in publishing, everyone thinks you're crazy if you decide to write full time. Why would you leave the seat of power and the office of decision-makers to be one of the scramblers?''</p>
        <p>Standing outdoors, under an archway made of bent saplings and pink roses, the couple were married before the Rev. Arlene Bodge, a United Methodist minister. Like an adobe house in the Southwest, the weathered gray Weinstock home blends into the scenery to the point of camouflage. At the wedding, you almost had to search for the low-key decorations, such as a pot of flowers sitting in the branches of one tree like a cat.</p>
        <p>''Unlike Southampton, Martha's Vineyard has not gotten to the point where it's only investment bankers,'' said Bruce Davidson, the photographer, who was a guest. ''There's a pickup softball game every Sunday on the island, and the third baseman is one of the richest men in America, the pitcher is a psychiatrist and out of control most of the time and a 90-year-old rabbi is the umpire. He can't see, but he has a sense of fairness.''</p>
        <p>In some ways, that was the tenor of the wedding, a casual mix of guests, some well known, like the cartoonist Jules Feiffer, and some not. Many dressed down since, as Mr. Davidson said, the Vineyard is a place where old clothes and old cars are still appreciated. Later that night, the couple left in their getaway car -- a beat-up black Jeep with high-top sneakers and Diet Coke cans dragging behind.</p>
        <p>WEDDINGS: VOWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
