<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Enemy of Our Enemy</title>
    <meta content="14PLAVSIT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="58" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="957224"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Bosnia and Herzegovina</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Plavsic, Biljana (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Karadzic, Radovan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rubin, Elizabeth</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970914T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00EFD81739F937A2575AC0A961958260" item-length="3374" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Enemy of Our Enemy</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Elizabeth Rubin</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rubin, Elizabeth</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Elizabeth Rubin profile of Biljana Plavsic; ardent Serb nationalist helped unleash bloodshed in Bosnia, but has since become Radovan Karadzic's foe and is now supported by US as best hope of holding tenuous peace together; photos; 67-year-old former biology professor, interviewed, exudes earnestness about creating state of law in Serb Bosnia and abiding by Dayton agreement; as new elected president, she is using access to official archives to reveal deep corruption and black-marketeering of Karadzic's rogue state, telling her countrymen that it is not NATO, Muslims or Croats but their own leaders who are destroying their lives (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>This summer bosnian serbs were telling a new joke, about a group of astronauts from the former Yugoslavia. Two Serbs, two Bosnian Muslims and two Croats land on Mars. The Croats say that the barren landscape so resembles their homeland that the planet must be Croat. The Muslims say that the craters are the twins of Bosnia's mountain valleys, so the planet must be Bosnian. One of the Serbs takes out a gun, shoots the other Serb and says, ''Since Serb blood has been spilled here, this is now Serb land.'' Recently a new version of the joke has made the rounds; it has Radovan Karadzic, the indicted wartime leader, pulling the trigger on his former comrade in arms, the Bosnian Serb President, Biljana Plavsic.</p>
        <p>Throughout the war in Bosnia, Karadzic as President and Plavsic as Vice President of the self-proclaimed Republika Srpska inspired their people to take up arms against their Muslim and Croat neighbors with the slogan ''Only Unity Saves the Serbs.'' But in late June, Plavsic -- who was elected President after Karadzic was deposed under the terms of the Dayton peace accord -- shed her image as his marionette, publicly accusing him and the ruling party bosses of state-sponsored corruption. Her rebellion has sparked a crisis that is proving to be not only a contest for the soul of Republika Srpska but also, with NATO throwing its weight behind her, a critical turning point for Washington and the European allies.</p>
        <p>By refusing to arrest Karadzic and deliver him to the Hague, the NATO forces have enabled him to remain the shadow commander and mafia king of the Bosnian Serb republic from his mountain home in Pale. Now, with Plavsic on the offensive in the city of Banja Luka, less than 100 miles away, the crescent-shaped Bosnian Serb territory has been effectively cut in two. There are two police forces, two governments, two state medias and an undecided army. And municipal elections scheduled for this weekend throughout Bosnia are unlikely to mend the split.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>This summer bosnian serbs were telling a new joke, about a group of astronauts from the former Yugoslavia. Two Serbs, two Bosnian Muslims and two Croats land on Mars. The Croats say that the barren landscape so resembles their homeland that the planet must be Croat. The Muslims say that the craters are the twins of Bosnia's mountain valleys, so the planet must be Bosnian. One of the Serbs takes out a gun, shoots the other Serb and says, ''Since Serb blood has been spilled here, this is now Serb land.'' Recently a new version of the joke has made the rounds; it has Radovan Karadzic, the indicted wartime leader, pulling the trigger on his former comrade in arms, the Bosnian Serb President, Biljana Plavsic.</p>
        <p>Throughout the war in Bosnia, Karadzic as President and Plavsic as Vice President of the self-proclaimed Republika Srpska inspired their people to take up arms against their Muslim and Croat neighbors with the slogan ''Only Unity Saves the Serbs.'' But in late June, Plavsic -- who was elected President after Karadzic was deposed under the terms of the Dayton peace accord -- shed her image as his marionette, publicly accusing him and the ruling party bosses of state-sponsored corruption. Her rebellion has sparked a crisis that is proving to be not only a contest for the soul of Republika Srpska but also, with NATO throwing its weight behind her, a critical turning point for Washington and the European allies.</p>
        <p>By refusing to arrest Karadzic and deliver him to the Hague, the NATO forces have enabled him to remain the shadow commander and mafia king of the Bosnian Serb republic from his mountain home in Pale. Now, with Plavsic on the offensive in the city of Banja Luka, less than 100 miles away, the crescent-shaped Bosnian Serb territory has been effectively cut in two. There are two police forces, two governments, two state medias and an undecided army. And municipal elections scheduled for this weekend throughout Bosnia are unlikely to mend the split.</p>
        <p>Shortly before the crisis erupted into violence, I met Biljana Plavsic late in the evening at her grand Austro-Hungarian-era offices in Banja Luka. Dressed in a loose, yellow floral dress and surrounded by religious icons of Orthodox Serbian saints and miniatures of the royal Serbian dynasties, the 67-year-old Plavsic, a former biology professor, hardly projected the manner of someone in a battle for survival. With a serene air, she claimed that her break from Karadzic and his cronies in Pale relieved her of a great moral burden. ''I feel free as a bird now,'' she said, lifting her arms with a laugh.</p>
        <p>This was a peculiar choice of words, given that she was practically under siege. But it was consistent with a tactic that Plavsic has found politically expedient -- to wave reality away and cut herself loose from any responsibility for the bloodshed she helped unleash during the war.</p>
        <p>For weeks, Serb soldiers with AK-47's and special police had been posted throughout the presidential residence to protect Plavsic and her small cabinet. Earlier in the summer, local NATO troops thwarted an attempted coup by Karadzic's henchmen, and police loyal to Plavsic raided a hotel room across the street, where they discovered surveillance equipment set up to spy on her. Under the circumstances, her legal adviser, Milan Dupor, was calling her Banja Luka headquarters the O.K. Corral. He told me that he was afraid of leaving the building. ''Not that they'll kill me,'' he said, ''just torture me.''</p>
        <p>Plavsic admits to no such fears. ''They can do as they like to me,'' she said. Throughout our conversation she exuded earnestness about wanting to create a state of law in Republika Srpska and abide by the Dayton agreement, which calls for a unified Bosnia. Hence the rift with Karadzic, who has by all accounts found a rogue state and a rogue economy perfectly suited to black marketeering. As President, Plavsic suddenly had access to government archives and the aid of a police force fed up with a corrupt regime. She discovered that the two companies monopolizing imports of fuel, cigarettes, alcohol, building supplies, timber and food were paying no import duties or sales taxes. They were run by Karadzic and Momcilo Krajisnik, Karadzic's ally and the Serb member of the Bosnian collective presidency. ''I have documents that there is crime and corruption, and it is destroying the state,'' she told me. ''It is clear that the Ministry of Internal Affairs is involved by order of Radovan Karadzic.''</p>
        <p>She pulled out a document titled ''Instructions of S.D.S. From July 18, 1997'' -- S.D.S. is Karadzic's Serbian Democratic Party -- and pointed to a passage in the text. ''They are openly saying that their goods are going on the Federation $(Croat-Muslim$) market without paying any customs or taxes to our state,'' she said, referring to Karadzic and Krajisnik. ''It says here, 'That export is very lucky for us,' '' she added in disbelief. ''Can you imagine? Lucky for who?'' She laughed. ''Not for the population, because our budget is empty. We cannot pay salaries. We cannot pay pensions. We cannot provide money for the army.''</p>
        <p>As she took off her stylish, half-moon reading glasses and looked at me in astonishment, it was hard to believe her expressions of outrage: you don't need access to the government archives to question what Karadzic and his friends have been up to the last six years. Yet Plavsic's campaign of moral outrage is playing well with the public. Since early July, she has been stumping from city to city, drawing sizable crowds and broadcasting speeches on television, delivering a simple but previously unthinkable message: It is not NATO, it is not the Muslims and Croats, it is your cherished leaders in Pale who are destroying your lives.</p>
        <p>Ninety percent of the 900,000 Bosnian Serbs are unemployed. Most teachers, doctors, engineers and pensioners have not received salaries in months. Serb refugees from Croatia and other parts of Bosnia who lost their homes in the last months of the Balkan population shuffle sleep in trailers, garages and shelters. Of course you'd never know it from Pale's TV broadcasts, which say things like, ''The successes achieved by our state, both in the field of economic survival and struggle against crime, are a matter of envy.'' Close your eyes and you might think you're in North Korea.</p>
        <p>Karadzic and Krajisnik are intent on keeping it that way. By controlling the black market, they essentially control the economy, and they have a formidable power base within the army, which is on their payroll. Given the realities of Bosnian Serb politics, Plavsic should have no chance of survival at all. As Richard C. Holbrooke, the U.S. negotiator on Dayton, observes, ''She's up against a business mafioso and a Communist party structure.'' But in the last several weeks, she has been developing her own base of support, and with the arrival of a new NATO commander, the American general Wesley K. Clark, the West has once again stepped up its rhetoric against Karadzic. Her crusade against corruption also seems to be gaining ground: Serbian Democratic Party leaders are starting to walk out on Karadzic to join the Plavsic camp.</p>
        <p>With Plavsic eagerly embracing the West to defeat Karadzic, Pale has counterattacked with a propaganda campaign more fevered than anything seen since the war against the Muslims. This summer, Pale television was portraying the NATO peacekeeping forces as foreign occupiers against a backdrop of footage of Nazis marching into Yugoslavia in World War II, and vilifying Plavsic as a traitor for selling the Serbian soul for a handful of dollars -- that is, desperately needed economic aid. (With the influx of Western election monitors, posters have been going up calling on the Serb people to urinate in all food served to foreigners.)</p>
        <p>In courting Washington's support, Plavsic has proved to be a clever student of American foreign policy. When Holbrooke and the special envoy Robert Gelbard paid her a visit in August, she was quick to say, ''I am a nationalist, but I'm also a democrat.'' Washington, for the moment, has decided to take her conversion at face value. Whether by serendipity or design, Plavsic's boldness has coincided with the NATO allies' decision to get tough on the Dayton agreement. There have been some 35,000 NATO troops and 1,600 international police stationed around the country and dozens of European and American diplomats flying in and out to kick some life into the paralyzed peace accords. Yet until Plavsic turned defiant of her erstwhile bosses, no one had dared take on the mafia in Pale.</p>
        <p>But as NATO troops are getting dragged into the middle of this power struggle, analysts in Washington are divided on just how much force they should use to back her up. Many officials are frustrated that NATO hasn't gone further to act like an occupying force. ''We should arrest Karadzic, seize all the television transmitters and freeze foreign assets,'' said one State Department hand. And even if Plavsic does come out on top, in the long run the West could have a bigger problem. An unrepentant nationalist, Plavsic could become a monster not unlike Franjo Tudjman, the unyielding Croatian President whom Washington also courted to defeat the hard-line Serbs.</p>
        <p>Biljana Plavsic was born in 1930, into a wealthy merchant family from Visoko, a leather-producing town not far from Sarajevo. Her father, director of natural sciences at Sarajevo's museum, was a biologist, and Plavsic followed in his footsteps. She studied botany and plant viruses in Zagreb and went to New York in the early 1970's as a Fulbright scholar. After a brief, childless marriage to a prominent Sarajevo lawyer, she devoted herself to teaching, and her students at Sarajevo University remember her as an excellent professor, always elegantly dressed. She is also unanimously described as cold, tough and aloof. As dean of the natural sciences faculty, she earned the name Iron Lady. Enjoying her first taste of power, she was flattered by the comparison with Margaret Thatcher and looked forward to assuming the biology chair at the Academy for Arts and Sciences. When she was rejected for the post in 1990, she turned to nationalism, becoming a prominent member of the newly formed Serbian Democratic Party.</p>
        <p>Momo Kapor, a Serbian nationalist writer, once remarked, ''The Coco Chanel suits of Biljana Plavsic did more for the image of this little republic than all the numerous diplomatic delegations which traveled to the world.'' Yet even within Pale's macho cabal, Plavsic managed to distinguish herself by her bellicosity. Nearly a year before the first shots were fired in Sarajevo, she attended the exhumation of a mass grave of Serbs in Bosnia who were killed by the Croatian Ustashe in World War II. Plavsic seized the opportunity to salt old wounds and arouse the martial spirit. ''Why do they force us to negotiate?'' she demanded over the dead Serbs' remains. ''In history, states were never created around a negotiating table but always with a saber!'' And few Bosnians can forget that it was Plavsic who once said: ''There are 12 million Serbs in the former Yugoslavia. We can afford to lose 6 million on the battlefield.''</p>
        <p>Yet the troops adored her. They called her Empress Biljana and emblazoned their tanks with her name. ''She was always visiting the front lines even under fire, while Karadzic was gambling in Belgrade,'' a former soldier in Banja Luka told me. While Vice President of the breakaway Serb republic, Plavsic played her role brilliantly as the Pasionata of the Serb cause -- ethnic partition and a pure Serb state. With echoes of the biology lecture hall, she offered a warped Darwinian defense of ethnic cleansing as ''a natural phenomenon'' and denounced the international community for having ''termed it a war crime.''</p>
        <p>Despite such monstrous statements, Plavsic's former academic colleagues, who survived the siege of Sarajevo at the receiving end of her party's bombs, still put her in a class apart from Karadzic and his loyalists. I often heard her described as ''an unskilled politician'' and ''stubbornly principled,'' but never as a crook. Some of her students wanted to believe that her fanatical saber rattling was driven by deep faith in the larger, historical cause of the Serbs. A Bosnian Croat physics professor who worked with Plavsic before the war credited her with saving his life when she arranged for his safe-conduct through Serbian lines to Sarajevo.</p>
        <p>''I would say she put her life in danger for me,'' he said, adding that she had protected several Muslim families as well. But he couldn't explain her. ''She wishes to protect her people,'' he said, closing his eyes. ''But on the other side, she's involved in the idiotic politics of this tragic war, and that I cannot reconcile with the Biljana Plavsic I knew.''</p>
        <p>What seemed to gall Plavsic's former colleagues and students most was that a woman acted as she did. Many recalled her heartless rebuke to a group of Serb women mourning lost sons and husbands: Don't weep, this is only the beginning. Ljubomir Berberovic, a professor and a Serb who chose to remain a part of multiethnic Sarajevo, remembers Plavsic as always having been politically ambitious. ''I think it had to do with some kind of personal frustrations,'' he told me. ''There was always a bit of the lonely wolf in her character.''</p>
        <p>In person, with a sturdy white teddy bear perched on a nearby settee, Plavsic plays the mad but well-meaning professor quite well. But finally, she comes across as the consummate political animal. When I asked her about her political alliance with Ljubisa Savic, a.k.a. Mauzer -- the Serbian commander of the notorious Panther army unit, which terrorized Muslims during the war -- she assumed the air of a naive schoolmarm, took a sip of orange juice, looked over the rim of her glasses and said, ''As far as I know, Mauzer was an ordinary soldier.'' To all questions about ethnic cleansing she responds with a simple answer: everything is the fault of the Bosnian Muslim leader, Alija Izetbegovic. Offering a markedly revisionist account of recent history, she accused Izetbegovic of forcing the Pale leadership into a corner by refusing to negotiate a way out of the war. War crimes? ''I already told you,'' she replied, snapping into scolding professor mode. ''I cannot blame Karadzic for anything,'' she said, adroitly shifting the burden from herself to her former boss and current rival. ''He really made a lot of effort to avoid war. But once it started, war is a special situation. And you know, the mechanism of war is always awful.''</p>
        <p>As I watched Plavsic at a rally in the rural town of Dubica in July, I remembered the words of a Belgrade psychology professor, Zarko Korac: ''Do not underestimate her.''</p>
        <p>''In the Balkans, bravado in politics always brings dividends,'' he said. ''If a woman has this macho bravado, she will get even more points than a man.''</p>
        <p>Standing before the crowd, President Plavsic chastised Radovan Karadzic's regime. ''When they've drawn the last drop of blood from you, they'll collect their money and go to Cyprus, Greece or wherever they wish. But I am not planning to go anywhere. I have everything here. And you have no place else to go.''</p>
        <p>The message was hardly news to her audience, but it struck a raw nerve. Karadzic's defiance of the Dayton agreement has lost them all but the minimum economic aid from the allies; only 2 percent of the $1 billion set aside for all of Bosnia last year went to the Serbs.</p>
        <p>''They say, 'The President is making contact with the international community,' '' she said. ''But who else will contact them if not me? Are we going to make a reservation of Republika Srpska so all the European countries will have an example of how people lived in the 19th century?'' Heads nodded agreement throughout the crowd. A few middle-aged women in tears held hands. ''They tell you not to think, but you have to. We are not slaves!'' Plavsic cried, and the crowd broke into applause. ''God gave us minds. You have a right to use that gift to argue, to say what you think.''</p>
        <p>Glaring back at Plavsic from the windows of the bombed-out buildings surrounding the square were hundreds of posters bearing the smirking face of Radovan Karadzic. Below were the words, in English, ''Don't Touch Him,'' ''He Means Peace,'' ''He Is Freedom.''</p>
        <p>Plavsic's wartime credentials and undiminished nationalist fervor are the keys to her popular support and have buoyed her in her crusade against the Pale mafia. As she made sure to explain to me, her complaint is not with Karadzic's war crimes but with Karadzic as an obstacle to the peacetime Serbian cause. And she has found a constituency among the diehard nationalists. Outside the Pale post office, where an old chain-swing merry-go-round provides one of the only forms of entertainment, a few unemployed men were sitting on the grass. When I asked one of them what he thought of the conflict within the Government, he said that he supported Plavsic. ''They told us we got a state. That was a lie. Now we can lose even this which we got from the war,'' he said, rolling up his pants to show me his prosthetic lower leg, which he grabbed, lifted into the air and threw back down on the grass.</p>
        <p>While Pale persists in portraying the international community as the evil oppressor, Plavsic has had the wits to grasp that Dayton can actually insure the survival of Republika Srpska, and she has successfully presented herself to Washington as the Serb who can salvage Dayton from total failure. In response, the international community recently pledged $9 million in reconstruction aid to the Banja Luka area and $60 million in loans for private businesses. ''Compared with Pale there's much more hope with her. She says she strongly supports the concept of a single Bosnia and the return of refugees,'' Gelbard said. ''We certainly have nothing to lose by supporting her.''</p>
        <p>Yet it's hard to imagine that Plavsic's dream is what Gelbard has in mind. ''I have had a deep feeling since I was a child that a good solution for Serbs is a restoration of the monarchy,'' she told me at the end of our conversation, asserting that the reign of King Peter I, before World War I, was the most democratic in Europe at that time. She grew wistful and seemed to wander off into her past. ''The first time I met the late Peter II was in Sarajevo when I was a child and he was about 12 years old. He visited the museum where my father was director, and I remember that I took some flowers from the garden and gave them to him. I never saw him again.'' She said that in recent years she had reconnected with the royal family and remains in close contact with them.</p>
        <p>Judging from Plavsic's vision for the Serbian people, she has never converted, she has simply become patient. ''In Serbia they are fed up with their leaders,'' Plavsic said. ''With a parliamentary monarchy, each four years you can change the prime minister, but there is always stability in the state. Now there is one stable roof over the Serb people, our church. Why not have the other roof, a monarchy?''</p>
        <p>In a Serbian kingdom, she conjectured, the current crisis would have no place. ''Now ordinary people are disturbed and talking about politics too much. Of course they have a right to be worried. But in a situation where you had this solid roof, they would be protected. That would be the best solution for Serbs. That is my opinion.''  Elizabeth Rubin is a contributing editor of Harper's Magazine. Her article on policing Haiti appeared in the Times Magazine in May.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Elizabeth Rubin is a contributing editor of Harper's Magazine. Her article on policing Haiti appeared in the Times Magazine in May.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
