<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sometimes, the Collectible Is Mightier Than the Sword</title>
    <meta content="25PENS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="SundayBusiness" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/25/business/yourmoney/25pens.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1599239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="SUNDAY MONEY: SPENDING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pens and Pencils</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">berrett, dan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Collectors and Collections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Equipment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Writing and Writers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040725T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D6163DF936A15754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1090" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sometimes, the Collectible Is Mightier Than the Sword</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Sometimes, the Collectible Is Mightier Than the Sword</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BERRETT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">berrett, dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Spending column on buying new or vintage fountain pens; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR Ron Lussier, 43, of Sausalito, Calif., the obsession started innocuously enough -- with a few gifts.</p>
        <p>More than a decade ago, his partner gave him two fountain pens -- a Parker Centennial and a Mont Blanc Ernest Hemingway -- and his father gave him a third. Over the years, as he moved into new homes, the pens were packed away, out of reach.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although some fountain pens are collected as works of art, others are acquired because they transform the mundane task of writing into something special.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR Ron Lussier, 43, of Sausalito, Calif., the obsession started innocuously enough -- with a few gifts.</p>
        <p>More than a decade ago, his partner gave him two fountain pens -- a Parker Centennial and a Mont Blanc Ernest Hemingway -- and his father gave him a third. Over the years, as he moved into new homes, the pens were packed away, out of reach.</p>
        <p>But he never forgot about them, and, one day last year, his interest was rekindled. While surfing the Internet, he found what he called the most beautiful pen he had ever seen: the Bexley Kensaki, with its ivory barrel and a cap with a curved gold clip. ''I have to have this,'' he remembered saying to himself.</p>
        <p>He saved his earnings as a computer programmer and bought it for $1,090 from an online seller; its retail price was $1,750. Since then, Mr. Lussier's collection has grown to 100 pens.</p>
        <p>What's going on here? Fountain pens, after all, were replaced long ago by ballpoint pens and keyboards for almost all writing tasks. And the fountain pen can be an impractical writing tool; at any moment, you may need to stop and fill it with ink -- a sort of 19th-century variation on remedying a computer crash.</p>
        <p>But some people are attracted by the pens' artistry -- both in their design and in the way they can express a writer's personality. Some pens, like the high-end collectibles made by Krone, based near Chicago, are designed to be conspicuous. According to the company's Web site, Krone pens are intended to ''evoke discussion and even controversy.'' Krone's first pen, created nearly a decade ago, did just that. Called the Abraham Lincoln and priced at $1,650, it has in its cap an amethyst stone that has been embedded with a crystallized form of Lincoln's DNA, reproduced from a strand of his hair. Since then, Krone has sold pens like the Marilyn Monroe ($5,500), which has a gold cap infused with lipstick scraped from her compact, and the Moses ($9,000), an oversized pen with biblical scenes painted by hand onto its mother-of-pearl barrel. The company made just over 1,000 of the Lincoln pens and almost 300 each of the Marilyn and the Moses.</p>
        <p>Although some fountain pens are collected as works of art, others are acquired because they transform the mundane task of writing into something special.</p>
        <p>''Many people look to fountain pens as an oasis, as a more personal and expressive way to communicate,'' said Bruce Willox, director of marketing and communications at A.T. Cross, a company in Lincoln, R.I., that has made fountain pens since 1846.</p>
        <p>Because a fountain pen responds to the lightest pressure as it dispenses ink through its nib, or tip, it reflects more accurately the quirks of a writer's handwriting style, many fans say.</p>
        <p>Some people prize fountain pens because they embody an ethos of individuality in an increasingly mass-produced world. ''They are high-touch items,'' said Marie Picon, editorial director of Pen World International, an 18-year-old magazine devoted to fountain pens. She compared fountain pens to old-fashioned, nondigital watches. The pens ''are thought of as an antidote to high tech,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Moreover, not all fountain pens cost as much as a down payment on a new car. Pens that sell for as little as $30 may perform just as well.</p>
        <p>When shopping at either end of the spectrum, some general rules apply. Assuming that the pen is for writing, not display, shopping for a new or vintage pen should be based on characteristics like length, thickness, weight, the size and material of the nib and the way the pen feels in the hand.</p>
        <p>''Don't buy a brand just because it's prestigious or pocket jewelry,'' said Richard Binder, a pen restorer in Nashua, N.H., whose skill at customizing nibs has transformed his name into a verb in the pen world: aficionados brag that their pens have been Binderized.</p>
        <p>Ms. Picon says pen shoppers should ''never buy a fountain pen without writing with it.''</p>
        <p>Most sellers let prospective buyers dip the nib in ink before testing, though a pen's true performance can be gauged only by filling the barrel with ink. Shoppers should buy only from reputable dealers who are willing to replace products if they are defective. One of the most respected shops, pen lovers say, is the Fountain Pen Hospital in Lower Manhattan, which has been in business since 1946.</p>
        <p>No matter why they are bought, fountain pens incite intense passions, even though they account for less than 2 percent of the $2.3 billion annual trade in writing implements, which also include ballpoints, roller pens, markers and pencils, according to the most recent statistics from the Writing Instrument Manufacturers Association.</p>
        <p>But an interest in fountain pens can quickly become an insatiable thirst. The Fountain Pen Hospital says it receives weekly calls from pen lovers on the prowl for the latest model. ''It's a habit for some people,'' said Terry Wiederlight, the store's president.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lussier lives with that habit daily. ''It's a constant temptation,'' he said of the frequent deals offered on pen chat lists. There is, he said, the romantic appeal (''the whole '18th century writing letters in longhand' thing'') and the artistry (''it's like collecting sculpture on a small scale''). But there is also something more basic.</p>
        <p>''The pens make me feel good whenever I see them,'' he said. ''Aesthetically, they warm me.''</p>
        <p>QUICK READ  Here are some considerations in buying a new or vintage fountain pen.</p>
        <p>KNOW why you want to buy. Will the pen be displayed as part of a collection, or will it be used for everyday writing?</p>
        <p>If you plan to use the pen, DECIDE what features are important to you: length, thickness, weight, feel, and the material and size of the nib, or tip. Ask how the ink barrel is refilled.</p>
        <p>WRITE with a pen before buying it, if possible.</p>
        <p>BUY from a reputable seller. Ask about warranties and whether parts can be replaced easily.</p>
        <p>REMEMBER that ink costs extra.</p>
        <p>BE PREPARED to take proper care of your pen. A pen intended for display, for example, should have its ink flushed out with cool water and be kept out of the light.</p>
        <p>SUNDAY MONEY: SPENDING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
