<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>7th Ave. Pastrami Feud Is a Test of Allegiances</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="163603"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CELEBRITIES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">CARNEGIE DELICATESSEN (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">STAGE DELICATESSEN (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLLINS, GLENN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED9123EF931A15754C0A96E948260" item-length="943" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>7th Ave. Pastrami Feud Is a Test of Allegiances</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GLENN COLLINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">COLLINS, GLENN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: War is hell. But a pastrami war, well, it's a real pickle. The tribal rivalry between the Carnegie and Stage Delicatessens is again spicing up Seventh Avenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: War is hell. But a pastrami war, well, it's a real pickle. The tribal rivalry between the Carnegie and Stage Delicatessens is again spicing up Seventh Avenue.</p>
        <p>War is hell. But a pastrami war, well, it's a real pickle. The tribal rivalry between the Carnegie and Stage Delicatessens is again spicing up Seventh Avenue.</p>
        <p>Charges about ''Secaucus pastrami'' are being leveled. A legendary ''comedian's table'' has been replaced by a cake stand. The so-called table comics are sniping at one another. Formerly free lunches are actually being billed.</p>
        <p>The tumult involving the two venerable Seventh Avenue establishments, each a half-block from 54th Street in the heart of the Deli Country in Manhattan, occurs after a period of ascendancy for the Carnegie.</p>
        <p>Once the Stage had the greater reputation. But in 1979, the Carnegie pastrami was judged better by The New York Times, and its image was burnished in 1984 by Woody Allen's movie ''Broadway Danny Rose.'' 'Living Off Our Overflow'</p>
        <p>But recently, ''quite a few regular customers who used to go to Carnegie come here now,'' said the co-owner of the Stage, Louis Auerbach, 63 years old.</p>
        <p>''Them?'' a co-owner of the Carnegie, Milton Parker, 69, responded. ''They're living off our overflow.'' Mr. Parker, 69, took command of the Carnegie Delicatessen after a co-owner, Leo Steiner, died last Dec. 31 at the age of 48. Mr. Steiner is missed by many. ''It's not the same kind of warm haimish feeling since Leo passed away,'' said Corbett Monica, the comedian, who was featured in the ''table-comic'' scenes of ''Broadway Danny Rose.''</p>
        <p>The ebullient Mr. Steiner was as famed for his corned beef and pastrami, cured in the Carnegie cellar, as for his cornball humor. Mr. Steiner was eulogized by Henny Youngman as ''the deli lama,'' a man who ''made New York taste good.'' 'It's Just Not Happening'</p>
        <p>''The Carnegie used to be a party every afternoon, and the reason was Leo Steiner,'' said Mark Simone, a disk jockey at WNEW-AM who visits both the Carnegie and Stage. ''You could go there any afternoon and sit with celebrities. Now it's just not happening. And a lot of those people are coming to the Stage.''</p>
        <p>Among the defectors is Mr. Steiner's wife, Irma Birnbaum. It is as if a Hatfield started sitting at table with the McCoys. ''Since Leo died, I don't feel right about going to the Carnegie,'' she said.</p>
        <p>One reason is that Ms. Birnbaum is involved in a protracted struggle over the value of Mr. Steiner's stock from his estate. Mr. Steiner and Mr. Parker each owned 40 percent of the Carnegie, and he and the surviving partners are in the process of buyng Mr. Steiner's shares.</p>
        <p>At stake is more than just chopped liver. In a town where dozens of delicatessens are vying for supremacy, a schmaltzy reputation is worth millions around the country in places where nova does not mean an exploding star. Water and the Pastrami</p>
        <p>The Carnegie has three other stores, in Secaucus, N.J.; Atlantic City and Vienna, Va. Last December, the Stage opened a restaurant in Los Angeles, and it will open another, Aug. 15 in Boston.</p>
        <p>The most stunning accusation from the Stage is that Secaucus pastrami is being imported into the Carnegie.</p>
        <p>''We know they're making their pastrami in New Jersey with Secaucus water, not New York water!'' said Mr. Auerbach. ''New York water is the only thing to use! It gives a fuller flavor.'' Water is used in the curing brine.  Mr. Parker acknowledged that most of his restaurant's pastrami originated in the Carnegie commissary in Secaucus. But, he said:</p>
        <p>''New Jersey's got great water! Our pastrami is a better product, because we make it ourselves, from our recipe. And they buy theirs.'' Devotees and Feuds</p>
        <p>Mr. Auerbach said the Stage pastrami was cured in Manhattan, with city water, by Ben Feldman Inc. on East 2d Street, according to the store's specifications. ''It's the best,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Our pastrami is better,'' Mr. Parker said. ''And our sandwiches are bigger than ever.''</p>
        <p>Many Carnegie old-timers maintain their devotion.</p>
        <p>''It's my second home since I lost my wife last year,'' Mr. Youngman said. ''I think the Carnegie is doing just as well as it ever did. It's the best food in New York.''</p>
        <p>Other former regulars would drop dead before going there.</p>
        <p>''The Stage is now doing what the Carnegie did under Leo,'' Jackie Mason said. ''I go to the Stage now.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mason has been feuding with the Carnegie since last May, when Mr. Parker would not close the restaurant for the reopening night party of ''The World According to Me!''</p>
        <p>''I was crazy about Leo. I loved hanging out there,'' Mr. Mason said. ''This man, I gave him $10 million worth of free publicity.'' #4-Tier Revolving Cake Stand The pastrami war even has some of the ''table comics'' spritzing one another. ''I never cared for him,''Mr. Youngman volunteered about Mr. Mason. ''All those guys for years stole all my jokes - the Buddy Hacketts, the Jan Murrays, the Jack Carters. Look, it was public domain. Anybody could do it.''</p>
        <p>Now the ''table comics'' have no large front table to sit at. It has been replaced by a brilliantly lighted four-tier revolving cake stand, ''to show that we offer three times the number of homebaked cakes we used to,'' said Mr. Parker.</p>
        <p>There have been other changes. Mr. Parker acknowledged that when he took charge, he discharged several employees, including Mr. Steiner's brother Sam, a manager who helped to corn the beef. ''Leo had an entourage.'' Mr. Parker said. ''I let several people go who were unnecessary.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Parker also said he had been ''much more selective'' about picking up the check and handing out linen napkins, signs of celebrity at the Carnegie. But Mr. Auerbach said he was ''generously'' picking up celebrity tabs at the Stage. All is fair in love and pastrami wars.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
