<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>American Fare and a Gospel Brunch</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="693012"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="DINING OUT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESTAURANTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">RESTAURANT MICHE MACHE (STAMFORD, CONN)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROOKS, PATRICIA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE1D9123AF931A25755C0A962958260" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>American Fare and a Gospel Brunch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICIA BROOKS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BROOKS, PATRICIA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MICHE MACHE, which enjoyed considerable success in South Norwalk, has recently relocated in the former Country Tavern in North Stamford. The new place has a much larger dining room and smaller, informal Tack Room (in the bar area), each with a different menu (with some overlap). The old barn-red building resembles a rustic tavern, with an interior of buff-yellow stucco and barn siding walls, wood floors and old barn beams. A corner fireplace in the bar adds a cozy touch.</p>
        <p>New American cooking dominates the new menu (as it did the old), but this time around there seems a greater emphasis on dishes with a Southwest accent. This worked best in a starter of herb-fried calamari (a heaping portion chock-full of crispy legs) with a coriander-mayonnaise dip, and a sharply spiced jabanero relish. Texas wild boar chili had fire and heat, with the smoky tang of moist, shredded pork, but the huge bowl of meat, with infinitesimal bits of corn, tomato and carrots simmered with it, became monotonous midway through. Some contrasting texture -- or a smaller serving -- was sorely needed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MICHE MACHE, which enjoyed considerable success in South Norwalk, has recently relocated in the former Country Tavern in North Stamford. The new place has a much larger dining room and smaller, informal Tack Room (in the bar area), each with a different menu (with some overlap). The old barn-red building resembles a rustic tavern, with an interior of buff-yellow stucco and barn siding walls, wood floors and old barn beams. A corner fireplace in the bar adds a cozy touch.</p>
        <p>New American cooking dominates the new menu (as it did the old), but this time around there seems a greater emphasis on dishes with a Southwest accent. This worked best in a starter of herb-fried calamari (a heaping portion chock-full of crispy legs) with a coriander-mayonnaise dip, and a sharply spiced jabanero relish. Texas wild boar chili had fire and heat, with the smoky tang of moist, shredded pork, but the huge bowl of meat, with infinitesimal bits of corn, tomato and carrots simmered with it, became monotonous midway through. Some contrasting texture -- or a smaller serving -- was sorely needed.</p>
        <p>The menu features three Miche Mache platters priced and designed for two. We chose the Mixed Bag Miche, which could have served three easily. It was a mixed grill of sausages and chicken pieces, a whole portobello mushroom, two tamales and a bundle of wide, flat and floppy noodles (premises-made with sweet corn, chervil and chicken fat). Dabs of coriander pesto may have been intended for the unadorned mushroom or the noodles, but they came astride the sausage slices and were neutralized by the sausage spiciness. Though generous, the platter was disparate and motley. Far more appealing were several non-Southwest dishes, starters such as baked artichoke and oven-roasted vegetable Rockefeller (an enormous artichoke stuffed with lentils, other vegetables and garlic, topped with spinach au gratin), a thick, zesty clam and fire-roasted corn chowder and broiled portobello pepped up with sliced scallion, diced pancetta and warmed Stilton.</p>
        <p>Broiled-seared salmon with fresh dill dumplings in vine-ripe tomato cream looked beautiful and was as fresh, moist and lightly cooked as we had requested.</p>
        <p>Other entrees were less satisfying. Garlic-seared tuna over a wild mushroom broth with leek crisps produced a surprisingly bland fish and thickly battered strips of leek. A special of deep-fried softshell crabs provided two monster-large crabs, which might have been terrific except for a thick and overwhelming batter. Oven-roasted vegetable (an oversupply of zucchini) and lentil turnover in a crisp, golden brown phyllo dough was inconsequential except for a delicious roasted onion gravy. Our conclusion: chef-owner Michel Nishan, who knows how to cook expertly, may need to rethink his new menu and drop some of the gimmicky combinations.</p>
        <p>Desserts were breathtaking in both artistry and taste. Chocolate and white chocolate checkerboard (a visual masterpiece), raspberry sorbet Napoleon (superb layers of crisp, nutty chocolate cookie-Napoleon), a piquant lemon tart and strawberry- banana tart in a honey mint sauce (inspired flavor contrasts), all were exquisite.</p>
        <p>Miche Mache's Sunday gospel brunch is back in force, held in the Tack Room by the bar. It is Miche Mache at its exuberent best. A buffet of Southern favorites -- cornmeal fried catfish, smothered pork chops over pepper rice, fried chicken, cheese grits (needing more cheese), biscuits and sausage gravy, collard greens, fresh corn cooked with molasses (not as sweet as it sounds), blackeyed peas with ham hocks -- all encouraged overindulgence. A dessert table included additional temptations, the most seductive of which was an intensely rich flourless chocolate cake. The gospel songs by Jean Cheek and Faces From New York were irresistibly rousing.</p>
        <p>It seems ungrateful to complain about generosity, but the portions at Miche Mache, as at so many area restaurants, seem designed for sumo wrestlers. It is probably a futile wish to think that restaurateurs could trim their portions and their prices. In any case, a three-course dinner for two at Miche Mache cost $49.55 before tax, tip and drinks. A medium-size wine list of mostly French, Italian and California vintages ranges from $19 to $30. Miche Mache fills handily the niche for a place that serves hearty helpings of well-prepared food in friendly, casual environs.</p>
        <p>Restaurant Miche Mache</p>
        <p>Good</p>
        <p>2635 Long Ridge Road (between Erskine and Old Long Ridge Roads), Stamford. 322-2953.</p>
        <p>Atmosphere: An old red barn with barn siding and rustic country tavern interior.</p>
        <p>Service: Friendly, but sometimes haphazard.</p>
        <p>Recommended dishes: Broiled portobello mushroom, herb-fried calamari, baked artichoke, broiled-seared salmon, raspberry sorbet Napoleon, checkerboard, strawberry-banana tart, lemon tart.</p>
        <p>Price range: Lunch entrees $8 to $16, dinner entrees $13.71 to $23.44, Sunday gospel brunch $25 (including entertainment).</p>
        <p>Credit cards: American Express, Mastercard, Diners Club and Visa.</p>
        <p>Hours: Noon to 5:30 P.M. Monday through Saturday, 5:30 to 9:30 P.M. Monday through Wednesday, 5:30 to 11 P.M. Thursday, Friday and Saturday, 5 to 9:30 P.M. Sunday, Sunday brunch noon to 2:30 P.M.</p>
        <p>Reservations: Accepted.</p>
        <p>Wheelchair accessibility: Ground-level access.  DINING OUT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
