<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Club Where Flamboyance Is Queen; The Barracuda Welcomes the Outré, From Tammy Faye to Tonya</title>
    <meta content="01LOUN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/01/arts/01LOUN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1313741"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Barracuda Lounge (NYC Nightclub)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nightclubs and Cabarets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Celebrities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Broadway</location>
        <location class="online_producer">East Village (New York)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Buckley, Betty</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010801T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E7DD1F3DF932A3575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1600" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Club Where Flamboyance Is Queen; The Barracuda Welcomes the Outré, From Tammy Faye to Tonya</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Barracuda Lounge: A Club Where Flamboyance Is Queen</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Barracuda Lounge, gay bar and club in Chelsea area of Manhattan, has been attracting celebrities, record executives, Broadway show promoters and perfume designers in search of elusive 'holy grail of cool'; has become unlikely refuge for performers who defy convention and second-chance cafe of sorts for entertainers in need of a third; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The man who prefers to be called Cashetta is pacing the stage in a sparkly black frock and a waterfall of a wig, waiting for a first glimpse of the latest sweetheart of Barracuda Lounge.</p>
        <p>Below him, men are vying for space in this cramped Chelsea club decorated in the frantic 1970's spirit of the Partridge Family on acid. Glowing red orbs illuminate clusters of patrons who are called to order by Cashetta's booming voice and a ritual reading of past Barracuda entertainers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lounge lizards may debate why, but celebrities, record executives, show promoters and others in search of the elusive holy grail of cool continue to flock to this neighborhood gay bar</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The man who prefers to be called Cashetta is pacing the stage in a sparkly black frock and a waterfall of a wig, waiting for a first glimpse of the latest sweetheart of Barracuda Lounge.</p>
        <p>Below him, men are vying for space in this cramped Chelsea club decorated in the frantic 1970's spirit of the Partridge Family on acid. Glowing red orbs illuminate clusters of patrons who are called to order by Cashetta's booming voice and a ritual reading of past Barracuda entertainers.</p>
        <p>''We brought Eartha Kitt to the stage!'' he yelled. ''Tammy Faye Bakker! Betty Buckley! Mackenzie Phillips! Charo!</p>
        <p>''All right, enough,'' he snapped. ''Today they've brought someone special for you to meet. Ladies and gentlemen, put your hands together for the only woman who has worse taste in men than I do -- Tonya Harding!''</p>
        <p>Lounge lizards may debate how a former bad girl of the ice and survivor of an Olympics scandal stumbled into the Barracuda, an unadorned white brick storefront on a leafy block of West 22nd Street that lacks a sign or even an address.</p>
        <p>But somehow this neighborhood gay bar keeps drawing celebrities, who often appear free, along with record executives, Broadway show promoters and perfume designers in search of the elusive holy grail of cool.</p>
        <p>The club, with its ever changing flea-market-retro décor, is an unlikely refuge for performers who defy convention and a second-chance cafe of sorts for entertainers in need of a third.</p>
        <p>There was the fabled lounge appearance of Australia's Queen of Yodeling, Mary Schneider, who presided over the club until 4 a.m. after singing a powerful version of ''The William Tell Overture.'' The former television evangelist Tammy Faye Bakker Messner came calling last year to promote a documentary about her life and mingled onstage with a drag queen interviewer. Ms. Buckley sent an emissary to ask if she could sing and then took the tiny stage, which is no bigger than a conference table, to perform an a capella version of ''Memory.''</p>
        <p>Then last week Ms. Harding, 30, emerged, surrounded by a protective retinue of middle-aged women, and submitted to an interview onstage, where she disclosed, among other revelations, that she was not skating and that she held a day job in auto detailing.</p>
        <p>''The overall philosophy behind Barracuda is that it always be fun and unexpected,'' said Robert Pontarelli, who started the club in 1995 with his business partner, Stephen Heighton. ''We look for events that are extraordinary in the true sense of the word. Tammy Faye Bakker and Charo are cult icons. Everything but the Girl and Marc Almond are pop legends. Eartha Kitt is one of a kind.''</p>
        <p>Barracuda does not charge entry fees, and most of the performers are not paid, with some exceptions, like Ms. Harding. But record executives said they valued the lounge appearances and parties to promote new music because they gave them an opportunity to build attention for artists at the street level.</p>
        <p>''The benefit is the most valuable avenue of promotion -- word of mouth,'' said Peter Galvin, a vice president for product development at Atlantic Records, whose company has organized more than 25 events at the club, like an appearance of Duncan Sheik, a singer who signed autographs and answered questions.</p>
        <p>''The strange thing is that it is a taste-maker,'' Mr. Galvin added. ''It's strange because it's been around, and it's a neighborhood bar, and usually with gay bars and clubs and restaurants, their trendiness and taste-maker status is finite. It's sort of the best of both worlds. It's not too cold and hip for its own good. You feel comfortable being there.''</p>
        <p>Broadway promoters have also used the little club to build exposure for plays. They have held parties and live performances at Barracuda by cast members from shows like ''One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest,'' ''The Donkey Show,'' ''The Rocky Horror Show'' and ''Naked Boys Singing.''</p>
        <p>''In the Broadway community, we understand that the gay and lesbian market is one of the biggest ticket-buying groups, and if you can be somewhere that is considered a cool and hip place, then you've gone a long way to getting your word out about your shows,'' said Scott Walton, whose company, the Walton Group, is a marketing and promotion agency for entertainment. ''I always kind of go there a little nervous. It's totally up in the air how it's going to turn out. In general there are always people there, but you sometimes don't know who is going to interview the performers.''</p>
        <p>That mood of the unexpected is one that Barracuda's co-owners work to preserve. Every six months, for example, the club décor changes, incorporating some flea-market finds that were discovered by Mr. Heintz and stored in a warehouse for the next transformation. In its club life Barracuda has evolved from a tiki hut lounge with colored lights and cloudy blue skies to a log cabin living room with a fake fireplace and deer antlers looming overhead.</p>
        <p>''The design and the entertainment are equally important,'' Mr. Pontarelli said. ''We're sort of obsessed with it.''</p>
        <p>The flea-market scouring has taken the owners to a barn in the Connecticut woods and a Miami Beach hotel. A new designer, Jim Foster, is putting the finishing touches on the latest transformation, which he sums up in pop speak: ''It's sort of East Village meets Palm Springs meets Frank Sinatra. This incarnation will be 70's Vegas with a 40-foot-long undulating leather couch.''</p>
        <p>The quirky, eclectic look applies to the lineup of entertainers and performers as well. Mr. Pontarelli, who for years handled public relations for American Ballet Theater, said he was constantly brainstorming with his staff about unusual ideas. He dreamed up the idea of inviting Ms. Harding; he would like to approach Imelda Marcos.</p>
        <p>Advertising for the events is carefully focused, a plan that is also an advantage to record and Broadway promoters. Ads for the Harding event appeared in HX magazine, a gay publication that declared, ''Hey, isn't there a little Tonya in all of us?''</p>
        <p>''Tonya Harding is larger than life,'' Mr. Pontarelli said of the invitation. ''She's a hugely well known figure that crossed over into the public consciousness. The Olympic incident was six years ago, and she has a story to tell. Sure it's edgy and a little controversial, but it's also kind of camp and outrageous.''</p>
        <p>But the danger of the unexpected is that not even Barracuda's owners are quite sure how an event will turn out. One night the singer Thelma Houston strolled onto the stage and interrupted a drag queen to sing her version of ''Don't Leave Me This Way.'' The hosts of events are ordered to deploy humor and a loud microphone if question-and-answer sessions with celebrities veer from whimsical to cruel.</p>
        <p>Ms. Harding, whose skating career was derailed by the publicity over a conspiracy to attack her Olympic rival Nancy Kerrigan, and who last year served three days in jail after hurling a hubcap at her boyfriend and his motorcycle, could have been an easy target during her appearance in the smoke-filled club just before midnight on Thursday.</p>
        <p>She arrived the same day on a flight from Washington with Linda L. Lewis, her manager. ''Miss Harding accepted the invitation to appear at the Barracuda, as she has many fans that write to her, and want to see her,'' Ms. Lewis said. ''The person that contacted me about her appearing there was very nice and said that she has a huge following among the clientele that visit the Barracuda.''</p>
        <p>Dressed in a miniskirt and with a relentless, sometimes awkward smile, Ms. Harding sat onstage on a stool and for the most part genially answered a brief series of questions from Michael Musto, the night-life reporter for The Village Voice, who made a mock plea to her that drew hisses from the crowd: ''Don't hit us. No, I'm kidding. Kidding.''</p>
        <p>When a woman in a beehive wig and a lace dress rose from the audience to inquire bluntly whether Ms. Harding had had her breasts enlarged, a second host, Cashetta, moved in: ''No more questions.''</p>
        <p>The mood shifted again when a Polaroid camera was produced and Ms. Harding began posing for dozens of snapshots with fans, who paid $10 each for signed photos. There were $25 CD's to sell, featuring Ms. Harding singing an a cappella version of ''Amazing Grace.''</p>
        <p>''Tonya, you're beautiful,'' screamed a middle-aged fan as he clutched two prized snapshots that grew more vivid in the crimson light.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
