<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Venting Ideas, Then Hiding Them, Turns Out to Be a Tall Order</title>
    <meta content="15blocks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/15/nyregion/15blocks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1702214"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="BLOCKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Blocks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Cahill, John P</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03E7D61131F936A2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="974" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Venting Ideas, Then Hiding Them, Turns Out to Be a Tall Order</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Venting Ideas, Then Hiding Them, Turns Out to Be a Tall Order</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By David W. Dunlap</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FOR a moment, don't think of the World Trade Center memorial plaza as hallowed ground. Or as ground at all.</p>
        <p>Think of it as a roof.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The underground complex planned at the World Trade Center site will require enormous vents, which, for security reasons, must be 40 feet high.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FOR a moment, don't think of the World Trade Center memorial plaza as hallowed ground. Or as ground at all.</p>
        <p>Think of it as a roof.</p>
        <p>That is how the memorial plaza will function; as the roof of an enormous underground complex including memorial galleries, the memorial museum, loading bays, passageways, cooling equipment and the PATH terminal.</p>
        <p>That will require a lot of ventilation shafts. And not just simple grilles set into the pavement. For security reasons, these vents generally must be 40 feet high -- that is, as tall as a four-story house.</p>
        <p>An idea of their dimension can be had in the Hudson River Park, at Morton Street, where two 46-foot shafts emerge from the PATH tunnels below. Though architectural imagination went into cloaking these shafts and park visitors gravitate to the shade and seating around them, they are still big and forbidding.</p>
        <p>Imagine the memorial plaza filled with a dozen such structures and you can understand why planners at ground zero are working hard to find alternative locations for the shafts there.</p>
        <p>''My expectation, my hope is that we'll remove all these encumbrances from the site,'' said John P. Cahill, Gov. George E. Pataki's chief of staff and the top-ranking downtown development official. ''The soul of our rebuilding efforts is the memorial.''</p>
        <p>Arguably, this behind-the-scenes engineering and design effort has a greater bearing on the integrity of the future memorial -- designed by Michael Arad of Handel Architects and Peter Walker &amp; Partners, in association with Davis Brody Bond -- than the current fight over the tenancy of the cultural building.</p>
        <p>The memorial plaza is envisioned as a ''flat plane interrupted only by two reflecting pools,'' filled with swamp white oak and sweet gum trees, said Stefan Pryor, president of the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation. ''All parties remain committed to that vision.''</p>
        <p>Until recently, however, that vision was competing with the possibility that vent shafts would rise directly upward from the underground complex. Citing security, officials would not discuss the exact location, number or dimensions.</p>
        <p>Government guidelines for securing buildings from chemical, biological and radiological attacks emphasize that air intakes must be high above ground, preferably four stories, to lessen the chance that a terrorist could lob a device in. They also urge that the area around shafts be kept clear of anything -- like trees -- that could give terrorists a foothold or obscure security guards' views of the structures.</p>
        <p>Not that plantings near the shafts would have been desirable, anyway. ''They vent cold air in summer and hot air in winter,'' said Anne Papageorge, senior vice president of the development corporation, ''so it creates microclimates that are not necessarily the best climate for the health of the trees.''</p>
        <p>Images of 40-foot shafts have never appeared on any rendering of the memorial that the public has seen. Officials had begun studying ways to move the shafts but a model prepared for internal use, showing the plaza peppered with vents, helped focus their attention. They now estimate that 80 to 90 percent of the potentially intrusive shafts have been relocated.</p>
        <p>Some shafts will be incorporated within -- and disguised by -- structures like the cultural building at the northeast corner of the plaza and the museum entrance pavilion on the west. Others might sit on the West Street-Route 9A median. Because there are no structures at the southeast corner of the plaza, relocating the shafts there has posed the greatest challenge, Mr. Cahill said.</p>
        <p>Planners are therefore casting their eyes to parcels outside the memorial quadrant. Some shafts might run through the commercial buildings known as Tower 3 and Tower 4 on Church Street. There is also a possibility of running them through Tower 5, on the site of the former Deutsche Bank building, at 130 Liberty Street, said Charles J. Maikish, the executive director of the Lower Manhattan Construction Command Center.</p>
        <p>And Kenneth J. Ringler Jr., the executive director of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, said the PATH terminal might house some ventilation shafts.</p>
        <p>Each solution carries its own complications. Costs increase as the route of the ductwork grows longer and more tortuous. If located in other buildings, the shafts would take floor area away from museum space or revenue-generating commercial space.</p>
        <p>ONE way or another, however, they must be accommodated. ''When you think about the thousands of people who could be below grade at any particular moment,'' Mr. Cahill said, ''the ability to provide for their public safety is of utmost importance.''</p>
        <p>Though the agencies may have begun with differing objectives -- the authority sought the most straightforward engineering solution, the corporation sought the most pristine plaza -- they are now ''working fantastically well together,'' Mr. Cahill said, adding, ''That has not always been the case.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ringler said he expected that Anthony G. Cracchiolo and Steven P. Plate of the authority's priority capital programs office would find a way to relocate the last shafts from the plaza in the next few weeks.</p>
        <p>''I turn to my miracle workers,'' Mr. Ringler said. ''I say that half-jokingly, but there's no question it's a challenge.''</p>
        <p>At the corporation, Mr. Pryor sounded hopeful, too. ''Each of the parties,'' he said, ''is now engaged in that part of the process labeled 'trust but verify.'''</p>
        <p>BLOCKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
