<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hopeful Words; On Taking Responsibility</title>
    <meta content="15thu1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/09/15/opinion/15thu1.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1702225"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Editorial"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricane Katrina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hurricanes and Tropical Storms</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Emergency Management Agency</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050915T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B03EED61131F936A2575AC0A9639C8B63" item-length="508" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hopeful Words; On Taking Responsibility</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Hopeful Words: On Taking Responsibility</hl2>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When President Bush addresses the country from New Orleans tonight, he will have the opportunity to build on the good beginning he made earlier this week, when he took responsibility for the federal government's failures in responding to Hurricane Katrina. In an administration that has hated to acknowledge that it ever does anything wrong, it was refreshing to hear Mr. Bush freely admit that Katrina demonstrated that there is a question about whether the nation is really prepared to respond to a terrorist attack or another natural disaster. It is only by squarely acknowledging past failure that the country will be able to do better in the future.</p>
        <p>The wording of the president's statement on Tuesday was important, and at least a bit worrisome. Mr. Bush accepted responsibility ''to the extent that the federal government didn't fully do its job right,'' which may suggest that he thinks the jury is still out on what the federal government's role should have been. Obviously, it will take time to completely analyze all of the federal system failures, and no one imagines that the city and state were perfectly prepared for the disaster. But we certainly hope that the president was not taking responsibility for a government that he doesn't really think was responsible.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's critical that President Bush acknowledge that the federal government is where the responsibility for disaster management rests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When President Bush addresses the country from New Orleans tonight, he will have the opportunity to build on the good beginning he made earlier this week, when he took responsibility for the federal government's failures in responding to Hurricane Katrina. In an administration that has hated to acknowledge that it ever does anything wrong, it was refreshing to hear Mr. Bush freely admit that Katrina demonstrated that there is a question about whether the nation is really prepared to respond to a terrorist attack or another natural disaster. It is only by squarely acknowledging past failure that the country will be able to do better in the future.</p>
        <p>The wording of the president's statement on Tuesday was important, and at least a bit worrisome. Mr. Bush accepted responsibility ''to the extent that the federal government didn't fully do its job right,'' which may suggest that he thinks the jury is still out on what the federal government's role should have been. Obviously, it will take time to completely analyze all of the federal system failures, and no one imagines that the city and state were perfectly prepared for the disaster. But we certainly hope that the president was not taking responsibility for a government that he doesn't really think was responsible.</p>
        <p>Localities have plenty of duties that are uniquely their own, and if a building catches on fire or a sewer pipe breaks, no one blames the president if the response isn't adequate. But no one community, or even any one state, can protect against hurricanes or vast flooding, any more than a city or state can protect itself against international terrorism.</p>
        <p>It would be wonderful if the president would take the opportunity tonight to endorse an independent inquiry into the Katrina disaster, similar to the 9/11 commission's work. It would also be heartening if Mr. Bush announced that from now on, the federal government, which pays the bill for flood control projects, would make sure that the most important priorities were taken care of first -- even if it required the kind of commission used to arbitrate Pentagon base closings to make sure that Congressional pork didn't trump necessity. It would be amazing if Mr. Bush really showed his sense of responsibility for this disaster by apologizing for stuffing the Federal Emergency Management Agency with inexperienced political appointees.</p>
        <p>None of these possibilities are very likely -- particularly the last one. But it's critical that the president at least acknowledge, clearly, that the federal government is where the responsibility for disaster management rests. Real accountability begins by stressing that the buck stops in Washington.</p>
        <p>Editorial</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
