<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Ewing's Absence, the Knicks Turn to Larry Johnson</title>
    <meta content="01KNIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="984424"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Knickerbockers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roberts, Selena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ewing, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnson, Larry</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B05E7D61031F932A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="722" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Ewing's Absence, the Knicks Turn to Larry Johnson</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SELENA ROBERTS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roberts, Selena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Larry Johnson has been most consistent New York Knick in three games since Patrick Ewing's season-ending injury; Johnson's statistics boom is hard to miss; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Larry Johnson is becoming more than a paper clip or a rubber band for the Knicks, more than just a temporary method of holding everything together in Patrick Ewing's absence.</p>
        <p>Johnson is starting to transform himself into a permanent support. He has been the most consistent Knick in the three games since Ewing's season-ending injury, slipping into place nicely as the team's best low-post threat. His statistics boom is hard to miss. Johnson is shooting 60.4 percent from the field, averaging 21 points a game and is 3 of 4 from 3-point range. Before Ewing's fall in Milwaukee, Johnson had been averaging 11.8 points a game, and shooting 45 percent.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Larry Johnson is becoming more than a paper clip or a rubber band for the Knicks, more than just a temporary method of holding everything together in Patrick Ewing's absence.</p>
        <p>Johnson is starting to transform himself into a permanent support. He has been the most consistent Knick in the three games since Ewing's season-ending injury, slipping into place nicely as the team's best low-post threat. His statistics boom is hard to miss. Johnson is shooting 60.4 percent from the field, averaging 21 points a game and is 3 of 4 from 3-point range. Before Ewing's fall in Milwaukee, Johnson had been averaging 11.8 points a game, and shooting 45 percent.</p>
        <p>If any Knick has responded well to the post-Ewing scenarios, it has been Johnson. He has embraced the opportunity to move back to power forward -- his natural position, which he played for Charlotte -- when the matchups call for it. And, without the looming presence of Ewing, Johnson has not been reluctant to make his voice heard.</p>
        <p>''There are certain roles guys are going to have to take on with this team, with Patrick or without Patrick,'' said Johnson, who scored a team-high 26 points in the face of Orlando Magic double-teams in the Knicks' road victory Tuesday night. ''If I can take on a leadership role like that, it's no problem. It's something I welcome and something I feel good doing.''</p>
        <p>He just wants to do his part, not wanting this season to go down as the one that fell apart without Ewing. But Johnson is not a superstar down low. He lacks the explosive moves that he once had, and has a tendency to slide sideways when he shoots.</p>
        <p>And yet, the Knicks do not need the spectacular. They need Johnson's multiple talents, like his passing, his low-post game and his defense. The Knicks, lacking consistency all season, are counting on Johnson to be a steadying influence. ''Larry was a big key for us tonight,'' Buck Williams said, referring to Johnson's game against the Magic. ''He made some big shots, passed the ball. He did it all, even broke the press. He's really a sound player. He doesn't have to score 30 points a night to be effective for us. Tonight, he just made all the right plays.''</p>
        <p>John Starks made the eye-catching ones. So there are times when Johnson's efforts are going to get lost in the flashbulbs that can surround Starks after a game. But Johnson does not seem to mind. ''I just play the game,'' Johnson said. ''Stats aren't a big issue with me. I've been around six or seven years, and I've had stats in this league. I've had individual accomplishments. To me, it's overrated. My main goal is to win me a championship. We had a setback with the big fella out, but our season isn't over, yet.''</p>
        <p>REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>CHRIS DUDLEY was listed as day to day after his nose was broken against the Magic Tuesday night. The former Knick, DEREK HARPER, who was trying to foul Dudley and put him on the free-throw line in the fourth quarter, popped him in the nose and was called for a flagrant foul. Dudley was fitted with a mask yesterday at Beth Israel Hospital North, and will wear it indefinitely. . . . The Knicks' next game is against the Nets at Continental Arena on Friday. The Nets have been threatening to nudge the Knicks from their standing in the Atlantic Division the entire season. ''They've been sort of like the whipping boys over there, so they're going to come with a lot of energy,'' JOHN STARKS said. ''It's going to be up to us to come out and match their effort.'' . . . Several Knicks are nearing milestones. ALLAN HOUSTON needs 15 points for 5,000 career points. CHARLES OAKLEY needs 33 points for 10,000 career points. And BUCK WILLIAMS needs just 10 rebounds for 12,943 in his career, a number that would put him into the league's career top 10 rebounders, ahead of JERRY LUCAS.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
