<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judiciary Report: Congress Is Prodded</title>
    <meta content="01TEXT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="984456"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Federal District Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Judges</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rehnquist, William H (Chief Justice)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Text</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Judges</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E0DC1131F932A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="999" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judiciary Report: Congress Is Prodded</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Dec. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from Chief Justice William Rehnquist's year-end report on Federal judiciary (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the 1997 Year-end Report on the Federal Judiciary by William H. Rehnquist, Chief Justice of the United States:</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Following are excerpts from the 1997 Year-end Report on the Federal Judiciary by William H. Rehnquist, Chief Justice of the United States:</p>
        <p>As I review the state of the judiciary this year and compare it with the 11 previous years I have served as Chief Justice, I am impressed by the degree to which our relations with Congress have dominated 1997. Congressional responses and initiatives on judicial issues ranging from funding to salaries, and from Federal jurisdiction to judicial vacancies, all have had a significant influence on the judiciary over the past year.</p>
        <p>The results have been mixed, which is scarcely surprising, and therefore we will face some of the same challenges in 1998 that confronted us in 1997. Despite the work that remains to be done, I am encouraged by the judiciary's ability to perform its essential role in our constitutional structure of Government. . . .</p>
        <p>I first would like to express my gratitude to Congress for its financial support of the judiciary. In a time of scarce resources, Congress responded favorably to the careful financial plan adopted by the executive committee of the Judicial Conference of the United States. These moneys will be used wisely and economically. The judiciary supports fully the national goal of eliminating the budget deficit and has instituted a formal process to identify and implement initiatives to reduce or avoid costs. . . .</p>
        <p>In general, Congress has declined to eliminate the disparity between resources and workload in the Federal judiciary by an expansion of the number of judges. There have been instances, however, in which Congress wisely has acted to reduce this disparity by enacting laws that in effect decrease the number of potential filings in Federal court. In 1996, Congress enacted the Antiterrorism and Effective Death Penalty Act, which streamlined habeas corpus procedures for both state and Federal prisoners, and the Prison Litigation Reform Act (P.L.R.A.), which did the same for prisoners' civil rights actions. . . .</p>
        <p>With limited degree of hindsight available to us -- and keeping in mind that there are many variables that could affect the future rate of prisoner filings in Federal court -- the Effective Death Penalty Act and P.L.R.A. appear to be promising examples of how Congress can reduce the disparity between resources and workload in the Federal judiciary without endangering its distinctive character.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately, Congress's effort to enact legislation of this type have been sporadic and inconsistent. I therefore call on Congress to consider legislative proposals that would reduce the jurisdiction of Federal courts. For many years, diversity of citizenship cases have been identified as one such area in which Congress could enact some very useful reforms.</p>
        <p>Should Congress, conversely, consider expanding the jurisdiction of the Federal judiciary, it should do so cautiously and only after it has considered all the alternatives and the incremental impact the increase will have on both the need for additional judicial resources and the traditional role of the Federal judiciary.</p>
        <p>If Federal jurisdiction remains at its current level -- or, worse, increases -- judicial vacancies will aggravate the problem of too few judges and too much work. Currently, 82 of the 846 Article III judicial offices in the Federal judiciary -- almost 1 out of every 10 -- are vacant. Twenty-six of the vacancies have been in existence for 18 months or longer and on that basis constitute what are called 'judicial emergencies.' In the Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit, the percentage of vacancies is particularly troubling, with over one-third of its seats empty.</p>
        <p>Judicial vacancies can contribute to a backlog of cases, undue delays in civil cases, and stopgap measures to shift judicial personnel where they are most needed. Vacancies cannot remain at such high levels indefinitely without eroding the quality of justice that traditionally has been associated with the Federal judiciary. Fortunately for the judiciary, a dependable corps of senior judges has contributed significantly to easing the impact of unfilled judgeships.</p>
        <p>The institutions that have the constitutionally assigned powers of nominating and confirming judicial nominees bear some of the responsibility for the current situation, but structural aspects of the appointment process also contribute to the existing high level of vacancies. For example, a larger judiciary increases the average number of retirements per year and the corresponding number of nominees. The additional burdens placed on the appointment process by such an increase may slow it down.</p>
        <p>An appointment process that might work well to fill the vacancies of the 700-member judiciary might struggle with a judiciary of 800 or 850 members.  Accordingly, increasing the size of the Federal judiciary so that it can handle expanded workloads might have the unintended effect of increasing the vacancy rate, perhaps leaving unaffected the gap between resources and workload that motivated the initial increase in the number of judges. This ironic result strongly supports the common-sense conclusion that, in this country, a bigger Federal judiciary is not necessarily a part of a solution for every public-policy question.</p>
        <p>Whatever the size of the Federal judiciary, the President should nominate candidates with reasonable promptness, and the Senate should act within a reasonable time to confirm or reject them. Some current nominees have been waiting a considerable time for a Senate Judiciary Committee vote or a final floor vote. The Senate confirmed only 17 judges in 1996 and 36 in 1997, well under the 101 judges it confirmed during 1994.</p>
        <p>The Senate is, of course, very much a part of the appointment process for any Article III judge. One nominated by the President is not ''appointed'' until confirmed by the Senate. The Senate is surely under no obligation to confirm any particular nominee, but after the necessary time for inquiry it should vote for him up or vote him down. In the latter case, the President can then send up another nominee.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
