<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Brick Scavenger Is Killed When a Wall Collapses</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="675066"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUILDINGS (STRUCTURES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ABANDONMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">BRONX (NYC)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Child Abuse and Neglect</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02E2DA1F3DF93BA25750C0A962958260" item-length="515" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Brick Scavenger Is Killed When a Wall Collapses</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RONALD SULLIVAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One of four men who were scavenging bricks -- at 15 cents apiece -- from an abandoned building in the Bronx was killed yesterday when a wall collapsed and crushed him.</p>
        <p>The police said that the four men were being paid by a construction company. It is common in the poorest areas of the city, officials said, for the bricks of abandoned and partially destroyed buildings to be taken for recycling into patios in the suburbs or decorator fireplaces in the city's more expensive neighborhoods.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One of four men who were scavenging bricks -- at 15 cents apiece -- from an abandoned building in the Bronx was killed yesterday when a wall collapsed and crushed him.</p>
        <p>The police said that the four men were being paid by a construction company. It is common in the poorest areas of the city, officials said, for the bricks of abandoned and partially destroyed buildings to be taken for recycling into patios in the suburbs or decorator fireplaces in the city's more expensive neighborhoods.</p>
        <p>Although police officials declined to estimate the extent of the scavenging, one officer at the scene of the collapse at 1123 Nelson Avenue, in the High Bridge section, said taking bricks from abandoned buildings in the area is "a common, everyday thing -- part of the neighborhood economy."</p>
        <p>Captain Tom Purtell of the 44th Precinct said the three surviving scavengers were not being charged. "We don't think there's any criminality involved here," he said, "But we are not overlooking that possibility." The victim was not immediately identified. 15¦ a Brick</p>
        <p>One neighborhood resident, Freddie Rodriguez, said he had been offered 15 cents a brick to help the four others. He said he turned down the offer, which he said came from a local company that hired the four others.</p>
        <p>Police officials said last night that they did not know who owned the abandoned building -- which was burned out and already partially collapsed -- or if the construction company had permission to remove the bricks.</p>
        <p>Neighbors said the company, called American, had an office in a building two doors away. But when reporters rang the bell there was no answer.</p>
        <p>The neighborhood, where many buildings are abandoned, and some of them gutted, is a half mile south of the abandoned building where Police Officer Sean McDonald was posted when he was shot to death trying to stop a robbery Tuesday night.</p>
        <p>According to an executive of a large brick company not involved in the case, the New York area offers a highly lucrative market for old bricks because of the desirability of their antique patina. Emil Puswald, an official of the Long Island City Building Building &amp; Mason Supply Company, said he was attempting to fill two orders of 8,000 bricks each for decorating two Manhattan apartments.</p>
        <p>He said such bricks sold for from 25 to 30 cents a piece.</p>
        <p>While one brick company official said old bricks were banned in some areas for new construction, many contractors, decorators, apartment and home owners used them for sidewalks, patios, and interior redecorating.</p>
        <p>"There's quite a market for them," Mr. Puswald said. "People want that look."</p>
        <p>According to the police, the three-story building was destroyed by a fire 18 months ago. Last week, they said, parts of the building collapsed and that it was amid the rubbled inside that the four men were working in yesterday afternoon, chipping bricks, one by one, from the rear wall, much of which was still standing.</p>
        <p>At 3:40 P.M., however, the wall fell inward, crushing one of the workmen, who was removed about two hours later and pronounced dead.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
