<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hong Kong to Try 5 Beijing Foes; Charge: Illegal Use of Megaphones</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="367079"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICAL PRISONERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HONG KONG</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">CHINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">WUDUNN, SHERYL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FUNG CHI-WOOD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China/Hong Kong</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Political Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD6143AF933A25754C0A966958260" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hong Kong to Try 5 Beijing Foes; Charge: Illegal Use of Megaphones</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHERYL WuDUNN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WUDUNN, SHERYL</byline>
      <dateline>HONG KONG, July 9</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In a few days, the British Government will put on trial five prominent pro-democracy campaigners accused of using hand-held megaphones without a permit at demonstrations here. Critics say that the move is an attempt to appease the Government in Beijing.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In a few days, the British Government will put on trial five prominent pro-democracy campaigners accused of using hand-held megaphones without a permit at demonstrations here. Critics say that the move is an attempt to appease the Government in Beijing.</p>
        <p>In a few days, the British Government will put on trial five prominent pro-democracy campaigners accused of using hand-held megaphones without a permit at demonstrations here. Critics say that the move is an attempt to appease the Government in Beijing.</p>
        <p>In a similar case last Wednesday, Fung Chi-wood, who is an Anglican priest and well-known democracy campaigner, was convicted of another offense - not presenting his identification card to a police officer and collecting money without a permit.</p>
        <p>The issue has come up as the British authorities in Hong Kong face accusations of acting as Beijing's agent to suppress anti-Communists or pro-democracy activities in the territory during the approach to 1997, when London will return Hong Kong to Beijing.</p>
        <p>The Hong Kong authorities have already banned some prominent Chinese exiles from entering the territory, censored films critical of the Communists and turned away a radio ship funded by exiles who wanted to broadcast propaganda toward the mainland.</p>
        <p>Creating a Public Nuisance</p>
        <p>The ordinance under which the five democracy campaigners are being tried is a statute enacted in 1900 to punish people for a creating a public nuisance.</p>
        <p>The ban on megaphones has been applied only once before, the defense says, about three months ago, when another democracy campaigner used a megaphone to call people to a demonstration.</p>
        <p>The offenses for which the democracy campaigners are being tried took place when they were leading rallies in January and February related to the Basic Law, the document that will guide Hong Kong's future. Chinese officials criticized the protests.</p>
        <p>Since the crackdown in Beijing in June 1989, Hong Kong democracy protesters - students, scholars and professionals - have become much more active in the territory. Small demonstrations take place regularly.</p>
        <p>'Pressure From the Chinese'</p>
        <p>''I think it faced pressure from the Chinese,'' Mr. Fung said of the British Government about his prosecution and conviction. ''It wants to suppress the political activities of the democracy activists in Hong Kong.''</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman at the attorney general's office would not comment on the cases. Still, Hong Kong officials deny that they are trying to suppress democracy, but say that they must preserve stability in the territory, and that the territory must live with the reality that it has a powerful northern neighbor, whom it will not help to offend.</p>
        <p>In May, leaders of Hong Kong's democracy movement were making plans to commemorate the first anniversary on June 4 of the suppression of pro-democracy demonstrations in Beijing. Nearly 100,000 people took to the streets to commemorate that day.</p>
        <p>Two of the defendents, Albert C. Y. Ho and Yeung Sum, are vice chairmen of the United Democrats of Hong Kong, the territory's first political party, which was formed in April.</p>
        <p>On several days recently in the busy central district in Hong Kong, hand-held megaphones were seen used by tour guides, movie crews, and even a small group of demonstrators who said they knew nothing of a permit.</p>
        <p>Sought Megaphone Permit</p>
        <p>Mr. Fung sought a permit to use a megaphone but was told by the police that he could ''adequately pass on your views and opinions by speaking to people individually.''</p>
        <p>In both cases, conviction carries a fine of less than $10 or three months in jail.</p>
        <p>What is unusual about the case of the megaphones is that the British Government had suggested earlier that the law being invoked contravened a Government-backed Bill of Rights that has been proposed for the territory, which will be voted on soon.</p>
        <p>In a letter to legislators on May 2, the Government included a list of Hong Kong laws that it said could be challenged as incompatible with the Bill of Rights. The law banning megaphones without a permit was among them.</p>
        <p>The Government has proposed a two-year freeze on the bill, after it is adopted so inconsistent laws can be revised to conform with the Bill of Rights. But the megaphone case has critics worried that the law might be applied through the period of the moratorium, even if the freeze were cut to one year.</p>
        <p>''I think it wouldn't be right for the Government to enforce that law,'' said Daniel R. Fung, who is leading the defense in the megaphone case. ''Because that would conflict with the Bill of Rights and be contrary to the spirit of the moratorium.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
