<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Region; A New Source of Money for the City, but at What Price?</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week In Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="424039"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">MUNICIPAL ASSISTANCE CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROHATYN, FELIX G</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HOLTZMAN, ELIZABETH (COMPTROLLER)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARBANEL, JOSH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DE1E3DF934A25751C0A967958260" item-length="1363" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Region; A New Source of Money for the City, but at What Price?</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BALANCING the budget, on time and under sound accounting principles, has been an article of faith in New York City since 1975, when it nearly went bankrupt from borrowing billions to pay for operating expenses.</p>
        <p>Now Felix G. Rohatyn, one of the architects of the plan that rescued the city, has suggested that New York may be better off borrowing than making draconian cuts to balance its budget next year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BALANCING the budget, on time and under sound accounting principles, has been an article of faith in New York City since 1975, when it nearly went bankrupt from borrowing billions to pay for operating expenses.</p>
        <p>Now Felix G. Rohatyn, one of the architects of the plan that rescued the city, has suggested that New York may be better off borrowing than making draconian cuts to balance its budget next year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rohatyn, a senior partner at the Lazard Freres investment firm, is chairman of the state's Municipal Assistance Corporation, known as M.A.C. and set up in 1975 to borrow money for the city when it was shut out of the credit markets.  He estimates that M.A.C. could realize as much as $400 million a year for the next three years for the city by refinancing bonds and postponing the payment of principal for up to 18 years.</p>
        <p>City Comptroller Elizabeth Holtzman and other critics view Mr. Rohatyn's offer as an invitation to the sort of deficit financing that caused the fiscal crisis in 1975. She said it was "too seductive" and could discourage city officials from making tough fiscal choices.</p>
        <p>Following are excerpts from interviews by Josh Barbanel with Mr. Rohatyn and Miss Holtzman. 'Just Too Seductive'  Bond Ratings Would be Lowered</p>
        <p>Q. Any homeowner knows that if you borrow against your house to pay today's bills, you could get in trouble in the future. Is the city heading for trouble under your plan?</p>
        <p>FELIX ROHATYN: No. When a homeowner gets into difficulties because either he's being laid off or his income is being cut back, he can go to the bank and stretch out his mortgage, stretch out the principal payments. That is a perfectly classical way to finance and has nothing to do with the suggestion of open-ended deficit borrowing for operating expenses.</p>
        <p>I don't believe that this is deficit financing, and no business person I know would define this as deficit financing. I also believe that it is consistent with generally accepted accounting principals. It is a method of dealing with a temporary downturn by deferring the pay down of debt that might be too rapid at this point.</p>
        <p>Q. Is it possible for Mayor Dinkins to solve the city's problems without any special help or deficit financing?</p>
        <p>A. Well, until additional cuts were imposed by the state, I thought they were capable of doing it. But if this economy continues to be weak, then it's questionable whether the city can close its budget gap next year solely with taxes and layoffs without inflicting really dramatic long-term damage to the economic and social structure of the city.</p>
        <p>Q. So will the corporation be able to step in and solve the city's problems?</p>
        <p>The reason I raised the question of M.A.C. possibly helping would be to deal with what I hope to be a temporary cyclical deficit that will occur over and above the structural deficit as a result of the, hopefully, temporary depression. Even that we couldn't do alone; it would have to be part of an overall city plan.</p>
        <p>M.A.C. refundings would benefit the city over a period of two or three years. There could be other temporary measures, wage deferrals by municipal unions, surcharge or other methods of reducing costs or increasing revenues.</p>
        <p>But as I said earlier, I don't think any of this is meant to suggest by any way, shape or form that I would in any way support open-ended deficit financing. M.A.C could be an important part of alleviating the cyclical deficit, but cannot in any way play a major, or any kind of a role in dealing with a permanent deficit.</p>
        <p>Q. So how much could M.A.C. provide?</p>
        <p>A. With the city facing a deficit of perhaps $3 billion to $3.5 billion next year, M.A.C. could do no more than help with 10 or 15 percent of that.</p>
        <p>Q. You are an adviser to Governor Cuomo, who recently asked you to stay on as corporation chairman. If your plan gives the city more money, wouldn't that make it easier for the Governor to cut aid to the city?</p>
        <p>A. I know people find it hard to believe that there aren't conspiracies, but it isn't the case here. In 15 years as chairman of M.A.C., I have tried to help the city and the state, and if that is defined as conspiring with the Governor or trying to influence the city, I plead guilty. Money From M.A.C. Just Like Streching A Mortgage</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. Rohatyn has likened the city to a homeowner in deep financial straits who goes to a bank and seeks to stretch out the payment of his mortgage. Do you agree?</p>
        <p>ELIZABETH HOLTZMAN: If a homeowner did this, and he wanted to borrow for other things, like keeping a business going or paying for his kids' college education or doctor bills, the banks wouldn't lend him more money.  The proposal is premised on a catastrophic scenario for New York City. We are not there yet. I'm not going to say that there are not severe problems. They are severe and they are serious. But that doesn't mean that the budget can't be balanced without resorting to deficit financing.</p>
        <p>We have to examine how this could be done without decimating the city. We would have to take greater advantage of attrition, and find more budget relief through productivity improvements. Only 5 percent of the budget closing measures are productivity improvements. We estimate that between $150 million and $200 million could be found through a much tougher attrition program, not replacing people who resign or retire, or leave city employment.</p>
        <p>Q. Mr. Rohatyn said that he remains opposed to deficit financing, but is prepared to pump hundreds of millions of dollars into the city's operating budget by stretching out the terms of M.A.C. bonds.</p>
        <p>A. That is precisely what deficit financing is. Rolling over the deficits from year to year will simply impose additional burdens on New Yorkers for years to come. Let me give you an example. In the fiscal crisis, the city accumulated an operation deficit of $4 billion that was rolled over. Here we are in 1991 still paying roughly $250 million to $300 million a year of interest to pay off the accumulated deficits of 1975 and prior years.</p>
        <p>That could, more or less, offset the entire state cut for education, and allow us to avoid layoffs and serious school cuts next year. We are talking about serious adverse consequences to New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>Q. Wouldn't the Rohatyn plan be worth it, to avoid severe disruptions in city services?</p>
        <p>A. While it may provide some temporary relief, it could have some very serious consequences.</p>
        <p>For one thing, it will cause a downgrade of the city's bonds. We have been told and the public has been told that any deficit financing will cause a downgrade of the city's bonds. That will mean that many people, particularly institutional investors, who now buy city bonds will not be able to do so. That will be extremely disruptive, to say the least.</p>
        <p>Q. Could the city have trouble selling its bonds?</p>
        <p>A. We may have difficulty selling the bonds we need. That could have a drastic impact under the capital budget, on the city's ability to repair schools, bridges and roads. Interest rates will become much higher and the spending on debt service will compete with spending on social programs.</p>
        <p>I want to give you an example of how interest on the city's debt aversely affects the city's ability to pay for other necessary services. The interest on the debt is going to increase from $1.8 billion to $2.7 billion in 1992. That means almost half of the budget gap the city has identified in 1992 is due to the increase in debt service. We have been piling more interest on more interest on more interest. Right now, we are having to cut back on other services because of these interest payments.</p>
        <p>Q. Would the M.A.C. plan take the pressure off Mayor Dinkins to balance his budget?</p>
        <p>A. It just becomes too seductive. I would hope the answer is no, because the adverse consequences of deficit financing are just far too serious. I don't think that we should give up hope that the city administration will balance its budget in a responsible manner.</p>
        <p>There is no reason not to demand of the city that it come up with a credibly balanced budget. We are still five months away from the final adoption of a budget for 1992. There will be plenty of time.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
