<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Preserving Bath Tiles</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="424196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIRS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BATHROOMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WARDE, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bathrooms and Toilets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Home Repairs and Improvements</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DC1631F934A25751C0A967958260" item-length="866" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Preserving Bath Tiles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN WARDE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WARDE, JOHN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CERAMIC-TILED bathroom walls are attractive and durable, but vulnerable to moisture. Frequent cleaning will preserve their appearance; careful maintenance will insure long life.</p>
        <p>For regular cleaning, which is usually necessary about every two weeks, use any nonabrasive household cleaner or a cleaner made for ceramic tile. Never use steel wool or powdered cleansers containing abrasives; they can scratch tile and also damage grout. To lengthen intervals between regular cleanings, dry tiled walls with a towel after showering.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CERAMIC-TILED bathroom walls are attractive and durable, but vulnerable to moisture. Frequent cleaning will preserve their appearance; careful maintenance will insure long life.</p>
        <p>For regular cleaning, which is usually necessary about every two weeks, use any nonabrasive household cleaner or a cleaner made for ceramic tile. Never use steel wool or powdered cleansers containing abrasives; they can scratch tile and also damage grout. To lengthen intervals between regular cleanings, dry tiled walls with a towel after showering.</p>
        <p>Household and regular-duty tile cleaners will generally remove thin soap film from tile, but to remove hard-water deposits, thick soap film and rust stains, use a cleaner formulated for these jobs that contains a mild acid.</p>
        <p>When applying all cleaners, follow the manufacturer's instructions. With acid products, protect the eyes, wear rubber gloves with cuffs and provide ample ventilation.</p>
        <p>To rid tile of mildew stains, bleach rather than acid is needed. Mildew appears as black spots, usually on grout and on caulk surrounding faucets and fixtures. To remove mildew, wash the area with a solution of one cup of either borax or household bleach and one gallon of water. Leave the solution on the area for at least two minutes, then rinse it off with clear water.</p>
        <p>Commercial mildew removers can also be used.</p>
        <p>In all cases, take the same precautions as with acid cleaners. Never mix bleach or mildew removers with any other chemical, including acidic cleaners and ammonia. That can produce poisonous fumes.</p>
        <p>After the tile is cleaned with an acidic cleaner or a mildew remover, or after every five or six cleanings with ordinary household cleaners, it can be given two coats of silicone sealer to preserve its shine and protect it from staining.</p>
        <p>Maintaining tile consists chiefly of making sure that no water can seep behind it. Deteriorated caulk commonly allows that to occur. When you notice cracked or loose caulk, replace it with new silicone caulk, often labeled silicone tub and tile sealer.</p>
        <p>When inspecting caulk, be sure to check the areas beneath decorative covers, or escutcheons, surrounding spouts and faucets.</p>
        <p>To replace caulk, pry out the old material with an ice pick or by slicing it away with a single-edge razor blade. Scrub the area with a bristle brush dipped in mineral spirits to remove residue, and then wipe the area dry.</p>
        <p>Caulk comes in squeeze tubes and in cartridges for use in a caulking gun. Slice off the tip of the tube or cartridge at a 45-degree angle, and then hold the tube or loaded gun against the seam at the angle of the tip. Next, push the tube or gun along the seam while squeezing caulk out at an even rate. Afterward, where caulk will be visible, smooth and compact the seam with a finger (gloved to prevent skin irritation) dipped in mineral spirits.</p>
        <p>Cracked, loose or missing grout also have to be promptly repaired or replaced. First determine the cause of the damage; otherwise, the repair may be ineffective and damage to the wall may worsen. The most common culprits are leaks behind tiles and the settling of bathtubs and associated construction.</p>
        <p>To repair cracked grout that is not loose, scrub it thoroughly with an old toothbrush dipped in a household cleaner or stronger one. Dampen the area with water and apply ready-mixed grout or powdered grout mixed with water, using a gloved finger.</p>
        <p>Press the grout firmly into the seam. Wait 15 minutes for the grout to stiffen, dampen a sponge with clean water, and carefully wipe away excess grout from the tiles, using diagonal strokes. Rinse the sponge in a bucket of water after each stroke. Do not let grout go down the drain; it may harden in the pipes.</p>
        <p>Wait another 15 minutes, or as the instructions specify, for the grout to harden further. Then polish away any haze still on the tiles, using a dry nylon scouring pad followed by a soft cloth. The shower or tub can be used 24 hours after applying grout, but do not apply silicone sealer until fresh grout has been dry for 72 hours.</p>
        <p>Loose grout has to be removed. Use a grout saw, consisting of a short coarse-toothed blade attached to a curved handle, or a carbide-tipped scoring knife designed for cutting cement backer board, which is used as a base beneath ceramic tile.</p>
        <p>Rake out loose grout to a depth of at least a quarter-inch. Scrub the seams with cleaner and refill them with new grout.</p>
        <p>Regrouting areas of several square feet or more can be a major undertaking. Around a tub or shower, start by closing the drain and covering the bottom with a dropcloth.</p>
        <p>After scraping out loose grout and scrubbing seams with cleaner, apply new grout to one four-foot-square section at a time. Dampen the tiles first, then spread the grout over the section's entire surface with a hard-rubber grout float held at a shallow angle to the surface. Make several passes, pressing hard to fill the seams and to force as much liquid as possible from the grout. When the seams are filled, hold the float nearly perpendicular to the tiles and scrape excess grout by moving the float diagonally across the seams.</p>
        <p>Finish removing excess grout with a sponge. Then polish the tiles and apply sealer.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
