<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Peckinpah's Messy Vision, A Little Less Truncated</title>
    <meta content="08CHOI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/08/movies/08choi.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1663156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="CRITIC'S CHOICE/FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dargis, Manohla</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Peckinpah, Sam</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Major Dundee (Movie)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Peckinpah, Sam</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Heston, Charlton</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Coburn, James</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Harris, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9802E7DC173EF93BA35757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1008" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Peckinpah's Messy Vision, A Little Less Truncated</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Peckinpah's Messy Vision, a Little Less Truncated</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MANOHLA DARGIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dargis, Manohla</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Manohla Dargis Critic's Choice column reviews recut version of Sam Peckinpah's 1965 film Major Dundee, which is opening in New York; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Yes, they cut a lot of it,'' the famously unruly director Sam Peckinpah said about his famously butchered 1965 western, ''Major Dundee.'' ''They left out what it's about.'' The ''they'' was Columbia, the studio that hired Peckinpah to direct ''Major Dundee,'' then grabbed the movie and cut it so grievously that the director tried to have his name removed from the credits. One of the many films sacrificed on the altar of the studio bottom line, ''Major Dundee'' has now been returned to the big screen in a form that is meant to bring this strange, messy work closer to Peckinpah's original vision.</p>
        <p>Written by Peckinpah and Oscar Saul, who overhauled Harry Julian Fink's script (the three share screenwriting credit), the film stars Charlton Heston as a cavalry officer nearly undone by his own obsessions. It's 1864 and Major Dundee, assigned to a New Mexico garrison, is an embittered and disgraced Civil War combatant-turned-prison warden, determined to right a career gone soul-crushingly wrong. After Apaches wipe out a nearby settlement, taking some children as captives, Dundee sees his chance for resurrection and assembles a posse. Because of understaffing, he is forced to draw upon an unlikely pool of men including an untested officer (Jim Hutton), a grizzled tracker (James Coburn with a glued-on beard and waving a phony-looking stump), black soldiers and a handful of Confederate inmates recently returned to jail after a failed prison break.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Sam Peckinpah's famously butchered 1965 western, "Major Dundee," has been returned to the big screen in a form that is closer to the director's original vision.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Yes, they cut a lot of it,'' the famously unruly director Sam Peckinpah said about his famously butchered 1965 western, ''Major Dundee.'' ''They left out what it's about.'' The ''they'' was Columbia, the studio that hired Peckinpah to direct ''Major Dundee,'' then grabbed the movie and cut it so grievously that the director tried to have his name removed from the credits. One of the many films sacrificed on the altar of the studio bottom line, ''Major Dundee'' has now been returned to the big screen in a form that is meant to bring this strange, messy work closer to Peckinpah's original vision.</p>
        <p>Written by Peckinpah and Oscar Saul, who overhauled Harry Julian Fink's script (the three share screenwriting credit), the film stars Charlton Heston as a cavalry officer nearly undone by his own obsessions. It's 1864 and Major Dundee, assigned to a New Mexico garrison, is an embittered and disgraced Civil War combatant-turned-prison warden, determined to right a career gone soul-crushingly wrong. After Apaches wipe out a nearby settlement, taking some children as captives, Dundee sees his chance for resurrection and assembles a posse. Because of understaffing, he is forced to draw upon an unlikely pool of men including an untested officer (Jim Hutton), a grizzled tracker (James Coburn with a glued-on beard and waving a phony-looking stump), black soldiers and a handful of Confederate inmates recently returned to jail after a failed prison break.</p>
        <p>An extended game of cat and mouse in which the mouse surfaces fairly infrequently, the mission takes the Americans deep into Mexico and the story deep into Major Dundee's mania. As the chase party hunts the Apaches, who are being led by the shadowy Sierra Charriba (Michael Pate), they end up fighting one another more than their stated enemy, with most of the battles taking place between Dundee and the ranking Confederate officer, who is also his former friend, Capt. Benjamin Tyreen. Played with enormous, charming flair by a mustachioed Richard Harris, Tyreen is at once Dundee's truest enemy and closest companion, the only one who knows the man behind the bravado. Like Dundee, he is also a soldier committed to an irrational, finally insupportable cause steeped in blood.</p>
        <p>''Major Dundee'' was the third feature Peckinpah directed, following the critical success of one of his great westerns, ''Ride the High Country.'' The new film proved a far less happy affair. The studio slashed both the budget and the shooting schedule days before production commenced, and Peckinpah and Saul failed to complete the screenplay. The lack of a finished script was particularly damaging. For all the time that Mr. Heston spends on camera and the attention given Dundee's quest, which Peckinpah likened to that of Ahab in ''Moby-Dick,'' Dundee remains a blur. A great movie star, Mr. Heston is not the kind of performer who can improve a screenplay by virtue of his acting talent, and neither he nor Peckinpah managed to transform Dundee into a character worthy of so much noise and confusion.</p>
        <p>Not that ''Major Dundee'' is a failure. Rather, it weighs in as a fascinating, periodically exciting hybrid of a Sam Peckinpah movie and a mid-1960's Hollywood western. The studio meddling is most conspicuous in the original-release version, with its overblown score (Mitch Miller's Sing Along Gang warbles the opening song) and patchy plot. According to the Peckinpah biographer David Weddle, the director gave Columbia a 161-minute rough cut, but the studio whittled the film down to about two hours. This extended version adds just 12 minutes to the original running time (and a vastly improved new score), additions that help make a case for the film as the work of an emerging auteur. Among the restorations is a shocking image of a bloodied Apache scout suspended in a tree with outstretched arms, a posture of unmistakable martyrdom that is pure Peckinpah.</p>
        <p>There are other moments of such brutal and honest beauty in the film. But where ''Major Dundee'' looks most like a Peckinpah production, almost like a dress rehearsal for the director's next feature, ''The Wild Bunch,'' is during a leisurely sequence in a Mexican village. Having tracked the Apaches across the border, the Americans decamp in a town occupied by the French. After dispensing with the French tout de suite, Dundee and company party hard in quintessential Peckinpah fashion, with lots of booze and authentic regional flavor: as women roll out tortillas and dogs hunt for scraps, a band blares brassy melancholic notes. Among the comely local talent are a young siren, played by Begoña Palacios, whom Peckinpah married, and a frisky widow, played by a miscast Senta Berger, whose finest work involves heavy breathing in tight clothing.</p>
        <p>It's amid the dust and desperate festivities that ''Major Dundee'' wanders beautifully off point, and the lack of narrative focus matters not a whit. During production, Mr. Heston wrote in his journal, ''We still haven't isolated exactly what this picture's about, maybe because we can't agree, or just don't know.'' During this bacchanal, as Dundee and Tyreen share a bottle and give each other a good looking over, it becomes clear that one of the things this film is about is the moment when a man looks in another man's eyes and sees himself staring right back. With ''Major Dundee,'' Peckinpah created a vision of men driven by their own demons, divided by contradictions and hellbent on self-destruction. When he looked in their eyes, it's an easy guess whose image he saw.</p>
        <p>''Major Dundee'' opens today and runs through April 19 at the Film Forum, 209 West Houston Street, South Village, (212)727-8110. Admission: $10, members $5.</p>
        <p>CRITIC'S CHOICE/FILM</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
