<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Starts of Housing Fall for 4th Month</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="362479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900620T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0D6143FF933A15755C0A966958260" item-length="568" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Starts of Housing Fall for 4th Month</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Housing starts fell in May for the fourth consecutive month, dipping to their lowest level since the last recession, the Government said today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Housing starts fell in May for the fourth consecutive month, dipping to their lowest level since the last recession, the Government said today.</p>
        <p>Housing starts fell in May for the fourth consecutive month, dipping to their lowest level since the last recession, the Government said today.</p>
        <p>Analysts attributed the 1.4 percent fall to high mortgage rates, tight credit, a large inventory of new and existing homes, wet weather and a sluggish economy resulting in slackening consumer confidence.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department said starts of new homes and apartments totaled a seasonally adjusted annual rate of 1.21 million units, the smallest number since 1.17 million units in October 1982, at the end of the last recession.</p>
        <p>David Seiders, chief economist of the National Association of Home Builders, said a survey of its members in early June pointed to continuing weakness.</p>
        <p>Building Permits Down</p>
        <p>Applications for building permits - often a barometer of future housing activity - have also fallen for four straight months, said Martin Regalia, chief economist with the National Council of Savings Institutions.</p>
        <p>Such applications fell 4.6 percent, to 1.06 million, after falling 10.1 percent in April. The May level was the lowest since 1.04 million applications were recorded in September 1982. ''It's not a rosy picture at all for the remainder of the year,'' Mr. Regalia said.</p>
        <p>Mortgage rates, which dropped into the single digits toward the end of last year, rose above 10 percent in January and ranged from 10.33 percent to 10.67 percent in May, according to surveys by the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation. Rates fell to 10.12 percent by last Friday.</p>
        <p>David Berson, chief economist with the Federal National Mortgage Association, said declining rates might help single-family homes. But he added that builder uncertainty over proposed Federal regulations governing handicapped access to apartment buildings would continue to slow the multifamily sector.</p>
        <p>Bailout and Banks Cited</p>
        <p>John A. Tuccillo, chief economist for the National Association of Realtors, said many builders have had trouble getting construction loans because of the constraints of the savings and loan bailout law and tighter lending restrictions by banks.</p>
        <p>Richard Peach, an economist at the Mortgage Bankers Association, said that May was a very wet month over parts of the nation, but he also blamed interest rates and large inventories of new and existing homes for the drop in the housing statistics. ''It's not an environment in which builders wanted to go out on a limb and start a whole slew of new units,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Part of the inventory problems, Mr. Regalia said, was the effect of the slowing economy on consumer confidence. ''Consumers, rather than spending to the limit, are starting to increase savings dramatically,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Construction of single-family homes in May fell 1 percent, to an annual rate of 896,000 units, on top of a 9.1 percent drop in April. It was the lowest number of single-family starts since 862,000 in December 1982.</p>
        <p>Apartment construction slipped 2.5 percent, to an annual rate of 311,000 units, after rising 2.6 percent the previous month.</p>
        <p>The building activity means the pace in the first five months of 1990 was 5.3 percent below that of the corresponding period of 1989.</p>
        <p>Starts slumped 8 percent, to 266,000 units, in the Middle West and fell 3.3 percent, to 337,000 units, in the West.</p>
        <p>Increases were posted in the South, up 3.2 percent to 486,000 units, and the Northeast, up 1.6 percent to 129,000 units.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
