<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Iraq Rejects U.N. Agenda For Lifting Of Sanctions</title>
    <meta content="Y06NATI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1022357"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Crossette, Barbara</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sahaf, Mohammed Said Al- (Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Butler, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Embargoes and Economic Sanctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Biological and Chemical Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Atomic Weapons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980606T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E3D91E3BF935A35755C0A96E958260" item-length="482" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Iraq Rejects U.N. Agenda For Lifting Of Sanctions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Crossette, Barbara</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, June 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Iraq's Foreign Minister, Mohammed Saeed al-Sahaf, rejects the agenda that Richard Butler, United Nations' chief arms inspector for Iraq, has set for discussions with Iraqi officials on lifting its oil embargo; denies Butler's charge that Iraq is still withholding critical material and information on biological, chemical and missile systems (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Iraq's Foreign Minister today dismissed as a ''nonstarter'' the agenda that the United Nations' chief arms inspector for Iraq plans to take to Baghdad next week.</p>
        <p>The arms chief, Richard Butler, chairman of the United Nations Special Commission, is due to meet Iraqi officials to discuss what has been called a ''road map'' of requirements to lead Iraq toward the lifting of an eight-year-old oil embargo. He will ask for documents and materials still unaccounted for by the Iraqis.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Iraq's Foreign Minister today dismissed as a ''nonstarter'' the agenda that the United Nations' chief arms inspector for Iraq plans to take to Baghdad next week.</p>
        <p>The arms chief, Richard Butler, chairman of the United Nations Special Commission, is due to meet Iraqi officials to discuss what has been called a ''road map'' of requirements to lead Iraq toward the lifting of an eight-year-old oil embargo. He will ask for documents and materials still unaccounted for by the Iraqis.</p>
        <p>Iraq's Foreign Minister, Mohammed Saeed al-Sahaf, at a news conference here, angrily rejected Mr. Butler's conclusions presented to the Security Council this week that Iraq was still withholding critical material and information on biological, chemical and missile systems.</p>
        <p>''The people in Unscom are politically motivated,'' Mr. Sahaf said of the Special Commission. He left the impression that Mr. Butler could not look forward to a very warm reception in Baghdad next week.</p>
        <p>Amir al-Saadi, a former general and now an adviser to President Saddam Hussein, said at the news conference that Mr. Butler's road map was ''just an excuse to ask for a new slogan: access to documents.''</p>
        <p>''All documents relevant to disarmament have been presented,'' Mr. Saadi said, confirming the suspicion of some Western officials that there are some areas of information in Iraq touching the political leadership where United Nations inspectors will never be permitted to go.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sahaf reiterated Iraq's claims that it had met all the requirements of the disarmament process and that nothing now stood in the way of lifting sanctions. He also repeated complaints that the embargo, imposed in August 1990 after Iraq's invasion of Kuwait, had produced ''the severest suffering in human history'' among the Iraqi people.</p>
        <p>He dismissed as temporary and insufficient the oil-for-food program, under which Iraq can now sell up to $5 billion in oil every six months to pay for civilian goods. He said conditions were continuing to worsen and more children were dying.</p>
        <p>But in Baghdad on Thursday, a spokesman for the program, Eric Falt, said a recent World Health Organization survey on Iraq had found attendance at health clinics rising across the country, with 50 percent of patients interviewed saying they were getting fully prescribed treatments after suffering medicine shortages.</p>
        <p>''On average, 74 percent of the patients felt there had been an increase in the availability of drugs over the last three months,'' Mr. Falt said. Doctors in Government health centers gave a lower figure, saying they received only about a third of the medicines they needed to treat the 10 most common diseases.</p>
        <p>The oil-for-food administrator in Iraq, Denis Halliday, announced recently that he would be allocating money to improve Iraq's run-down schools. Electricity systems and agriculture are also getting larger shares of equipment and money with an increase in the amount of oil allowed to be sold. The program was expanded early this year by the Security Council.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
