<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>My Manhattan; Once-Famous Faces Watch Over a Park</title>
    <meta content="07MALL$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1037232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Madison Square Park (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mallon, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Seward, William Henry (1801-72)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Farragut, David Glasgow (1801-1870)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Worth, William Jenkins (Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arthur, Chester Alan (1829-1886)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Conkling, Roscoe</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leisure</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parks and Other Recreation Areas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980807T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E7D9123BF934A3575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1210" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>My Manhattan; Once-Famous Faces Watch Over a Park</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS MALLON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mallon, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Madison Square Park, six-acre enclave bounded by Fifth and Madison Avenues and 23rd to 26th Streets, contains statues of historical figures, offering visitors view of New York between mid-19th and early 20th centuries when state and city supplied country with some of its grandest political personalities; has statues of William H Seward, Adm David Farragut, Gen William Jenkins Worth, Chester A Arthur and Roscoe Conkling; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When I come into New York these days, it's usually from Connecticut, by way of Grand Central. The terminal's newly restored ceiling, which played a crucial part in one of my novels, delights the eye, but its sudden absence of grime brings to mind not so much the ceiling's Beaux-Arts infancy as the spanking prosperity of 1998. Once arrived, I'm off to the Madison Avenue building of Conde Nast, whose magazines will soon move to a Disneyfied Times Square; or to the New York Public Library, where even the lions have been wearing hard hats; or down to the Strand bookstore, two blocks south of Union Square, whose continuing glamorization would give an anarchist spasms.</p>
        <p>But every so often I need to go see my paperback publisher in the Flatiron Building, situated where Fifth Avenue meets Broadway. Those last five words sound like a marketer's dream slogan, a one-two punch of wealth and dazzle, but they also define an actual crossroads, the nexus that occurs at 23d Street, these days a relatively humble haven in a city undergoing too much gleaming renovation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When I come into New York these days, it's usually from Connecticut, by way of Grand Central. The terminal's newly restored ceiling, which played a crucial part in one of my novels, delights the eye, but its sudden absence of grime brings to mind not so much the ceiling's Beaux-Arts infancy as the spanking prosperity of 1998. Once arrived, I'm off to the Madison Avenue building of Conde Nast, whose magazines will soon move to a Disneyfied Times Square; or to the New York Public Library, where even the lions have been wearing hard hats; or down to the Strand bookstore, two blocks south of Union Square, whose continuing glamorization would give an anarchist spasms.</p>
        <p>But every so often I need to go see my paperback publisher in the Flatiron Building, situated where Fifth Avenue meets Broadway. Those last five words sound like a marketer's dream slogan, a one-two punch of wealth and dazzle, but they also define an actual crossroads, the nexus that occurs at 23d Street, these days a relatively humble haven in a city undergoing too much gleaming renovation.</p>
        <p>The Flatiron's northern offices look out on Madison Square Park, whose six acres stretch east toward Madison Avenue and north to 26th Street. The men and women who walk here are an unassuming lot, less the cell-phoned swells of the new Bryant Park than nine-to-fivers needing a smoke. The benches still fill up with men killing time and, however slowly, themselves. Despite reseeding, the grass remains patchy, and the officially designated ''Squirrel House'' (a hollow dead tree) is ignored by its intended guests, scavengers with no time for cute.</p>
        <p>But Madison Square Park also offers the visitor a small perpetuation of New York between the mid-19th and early 20th centuries, a long period when the state and the city supplied the country with some of its grandest political personalities. Several of ''my'' men, minor and major characters in the historical fiction I've been writing, are frozen stiff here.</p>
        <p>Seated at the park's southwest entrance is William H. Seward, New York's Governor and Senator before being made Secretary of State by Abraham Lincoln, with whom he nearly died on April 14, 1865. He sits casually, legs crossed, looking away from the state paper that rests on an arm of his chair. This is the Seward who bought Alaska for a song, serenely redeemed for his folly, enjoying an eternal I-told-you-so.</p>
        <p>Just outside the park's western boundary, a triangular traffic island supports the obelisk commemorating Maj. Gen. William Jenkins Worth's triumphant 1847 entry into Mexico City. Like Seward's statue, it's been recently restored, but one has to wonder about its presence in an increasingly Hispanic city, and whether the general may one day have to content himself with Fort Worth, Tex., as his big American monument.</p>
        <p>The most impressive memorial inside the park, in its northeast portion, belongs to Adm. David Farragut, to whom New York City gave $50,000 to buy a home after his Civil War successes. The pedestal to this early Saint-Gaudens masterpiece, a sort of swirling triptych with two curving flanks, seems lighter and more animate than the statue it supports.</p>
        <p>Behind Farragut, looking well attired but rather surprised to be here at all, stands Chester Arthur, who became the country's 21st President upon the assassination of James A. Garfield in 1881. The mutton-chopped and always fashionable Arthur (he had Louis Comfort Tiffany help him redecorate the White House) appears to have just risen from the chair behind him, summoned by history to a task he performed rather better than most imagined he would.</p>
        <p>Anxieties about him had everything to do with the park's remaining statue, that of the ever choleric Senator Roscoe Conkling, who has stood since 1893 as a sort of Cerberus near the southeast entrance. The absolute boss of the New York Republican Party in the 1870's, Conkling quite simply owned the pre-Presidential Arthur, who as the port collector of New York watched over the Custom House, the mightiest patronage engine in the country. Neither man suffered from any of our recent confusion about just what constitutes soliciting campaign contributions on Federal property: kickbacks were  sometimes rendered at an office on Hanover -- dubbed ''Hand-Over'' -- Street.</p>
        <p>A gorgeous brute of a man -- casually cruel, unforgiving, an orator who made his colleagues tremble and the galleries swoon -- Conkling looks absolutely certain of his right to be immortalized in the park. In fact, he is in midspeech, his left hand at his hip, his right one open at his side. He's sure he'll convince you, of whatever it is, before you take another step.</p>
        <p>The living Conkling, with his blond forelock, violet ink, bedazzled mistresses and lapses into statesmanship, is a historical novelist's dream. I've written about two-thirds of the book he marauds through, and when passing Madison Square I sometimes feel a literal version of the satisfaction Virginia Woolf expressed to her diary when things were going well with her novel ''The Waves'': ''I think it possible that I have got my statues against the sky.''</p>
        <p>I still keep an apartment in the city, close to the United Nations, whose abstract outdoor sculpture leaves me either bored or suspicious -- so many noble sentiments springing from such dubious donors. The one modern sculpture in Madison Square Park -- three rectangular oblongs by Antoni Milkowski -- merely perplexes me. This is my limitation, to be sure; but my mind, so drawn to replication, is more akin to that of the 19th-century New Yorker, whose zeal for statuary eventually got out of hand.</p>
        <p>In ''The Park and the People,'' their 1992 history of Central Park, Roy Rosenzweig and Elizabeth Blackmar note how ''in 1873 the park board acted to restrict commemorative sculpture to the Mall and the entrance gates and to require prior review of artistic merit.'' But the review committee of artistic experts had only advisory powers and often could not resist ''the pressure to commemorate immensely popular figures.'' Only when the five boroughs amalgamated themselves at the end of the century into the current City of New York did an Art Commission of experts supersede the park board and stop the proliferation of pedestals.</p>
        <p>It was this modern, swelling city that made Conkling and Arthur obsolete. In fact, all the figures in Madison Square were set up to face south in a city rushing north. The great edifice that has dominated the square in this century, Napoleon LeBrun's Metropolitan Life building (1910), towers over the park's forgotten men, a sort of architectural memento mori, reminding the passer-by that one can insure one's life but not one's name.</p>
        <p>Thomas Mallon's most recent book is the novel ''Dewey Defeats Truman'' (Picador).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Thomas Mallon's most recent book is the novel ''Dewey Defeats Truman'' (Picador).</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
