<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A New Role for Beepers: Keep Families in Touch</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Consumer's World Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="471743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAGING SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLOANE, LEONARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paging Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE7DD1E39F934A3575AC0A967958260" item-length="783" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A New Role for Beepers: Keep Families in Touch</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEONARD SLOANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SLOANE, LEONARD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The next time you hear the insistent tones of a beeper in a restaurant or theater, the wearer may not be a doctor or a plumber on call but an expectant father awaiting word from his wife, a mother needed by her baby sitter or someone who just needs to be in touch with a business or home.</p>
        <p>Mark and Amy Collier of St. Louis, who are expecting a child this month, rented a beeper last week to communicate instantly when they are apart.  Mr. Collier is an account manager for SmithKline Beecham and Mrs. Collier is a teacher.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The next time you hear the insistent tones of a beeper in a restaurant or theater, the wearer may not be a doctor or a plumber on call but an expectant father awaiting word from his wife, a mother needed by her baby sitter or someone who just needs to be in touch with a business or home.</p>
        <p>Mark and Amy Collier of St. Louis, who are expecting a child this month, rented a beeper last week to communicate instantly when they are apart.  Mr. Collier is an account manager for SmithKline Beecham and Mrs. Collier is a teacher.</p>
        <p>"He's always on the road calling on key accounts," Mrs. Collier said.  "Our game plan is that I would call the beeper number wherever I am and he would know it's the time."</p>
        <p>Beepers, or pagers, have long been used by professional and business people to make more use of time away from their phones. But recently they have been making greater inroads among people who want them or personal or family reasons for only a short time.</p>
        <p>"Short-term renting is really very limited right now,' " said Jonathan Tarlin, a senior consultant at Economic Management Consultants International of Washington. "But it has been beginning to penetrate the retail market in the past six months."</p>
        <p>Last month, Metromedia Paging Services, a major provider of paging services that is based in Secaucus, N.J., began testing daily and weekly beeper rentals at 35 supermarkets owned by Schnucks Markets, a Midwestern chain. The units rent for $2 to $3.50 a day or $10 to $17.50 a week, depending on the model. Like a Starter, or Sampler Kit</p>
        <p>"The industry has been focused for the most part on business applications," said Cliff Eason, president of Metromedia Paging. "This is sort of a starter kit and gives people the ability to sample it."</p>
        <p>"We rent them in every store that has a video department," said Craig Schnuck, president of the supermarket chain. "The customer signs a rental agreement and shows identification," he added, citing a process similar to renting a videotape.</p>
        <p>Paging, or radio paging, is a one-way calling system in use more than 40 years. As a form of wireless communication, It transmits signals to a beeper that receives only the signal intended for it.</p>
        <p>More than 600 companies around the country, called carriers, offer one or more of four types of services: tone only, a sound or a vibration; tone and voice, a voice message of up to 10 seconds; numeric or digital, which displays a phone number to call; and alphanumeric, which displays a text message of up to 1,000 characters. 11 Million Rent or Own Them</p>
        <p>About 11 million paging subscribers have bought or rented beepers, according to Telocator, a trade association for the personal communications industry. Its surveys show that more than two-thirds of these devices are used for business.</p>
        <p>"When cellular service was introduced, many industry analysts forecast the demise of paging," said Thomas Stroup, president of Telocator. "Instead of replacing paging, cellular served to raise the market consciousness of the value of mobile communications. Paging is the lowest-cost form of personal communications."</p>
        <p>Now the industry is looking at short-term rentals. Paging Network, another carrier, is offering brightly colored devices -- orange, green or pink -- to attract more customers.  "We are renting many 'baby beepers,' " said Terry Scott, senior vice president of the company, referring to the ones used by expectant parents.  "Hopefully, many of the parents will retain the beepers after the baby is born."</p>
        <p>Other temporary users of beepers include working couples who are waiting for a delivery, but don't want to be stuck at home (they leave their beeper number on the door), adults with elderly parents who may need medical care quickly when alone, and families that want to keep in constant contact with their children. Banned by Some Schools</p>
        <p>A number of students at schools and colleges also rent beepers, but others are forbidden to do so because, in some areas, the use of the devices is associated with traffickers in illegal drugs. "Because pagers are somewhat associated with drug calls, some schools don't allow students to wear the pagers," said Ralph Haller, chief of the private radio bureau of the Federal Communications Commission, which regulates paging and licenses carriers.</p>
        <p>Another difficulty with beepers is that there is no two-way communication. "The problem has always been, 'I've got the message, now I've got to call someone,' " said Barry Marks, vice president and general manager of the Gartner Group, a management consulting concern based in Stamford, Conn., "but as more people away from home want to be contacted, beepers have been growing."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
