<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>City Trees, Revisited</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="372912"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="SCIENCE WATCH"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AIR POLLUTION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TREES AND SHRUBS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUILDING (CONSTRUCTION)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">GEORGIA INSTITUTE OF TECHNOLOGY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Construction and Maintenance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trees and Shrubs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Building (Construction)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Air Pollution</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900731T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDC133DF932A05754C0A966958260" item-length="385" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>City Trees, Revisited</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Replacing trees with buildings and concrete can contribute to an increase in air pollution, a new study says.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Replacing trees with buildings and concrete can contribute to an increase in air pollution, a new study says.</p>
        <p>Replacing trees with buildings and concrete can contribute to an increase in air pollution, a new study says.</p>
        <p>The researchers at the Georgia Institute of Technology said that trees cool down overheated cities and help moderate the production of pollutants that become worse with even slight increases in temperature.</p>
        <p>The study is by the same group that found two years ago that in some cases trees can emit as many hydrocarbons, a major component in the pollutant ozone, as other sources, like cars and factories.</p>
        <p>But the latest report, to be published in The Journal of Geophysical Research, says that chopping down trees in cities may be more than an aesthetic loss.</p>
        <p>The reason is that as cities become more developed and lose their green areas to buildings and concrete - they trap heat.</p>
        <p>Atlanta, for example, can be as much as almost 22 degrees Fahrenheit hotter than outlying areas, and over the 15 years studied, the city's average summertime temperature has increased by almost 4 degrees Fahrenheit. At the same time, Atlanta lost 20 percent of its trees.</p>
        <p>The researchers said that even small jumps in temperature can significantly increase hydrocarbon emissons, both from trees and other sources, primarily the evaporation of gasoline.</p>
        <p>These hydrocarbons mix with nitrogen oxides to form ozone, a key component of smog at ground level. The higher temperatures also speed up the photochemical reactions that form ozone, the study says.</p>
        <p>But trees reduce urban temperatures because they evaporate water through pores in their leaves. Trees also do not absorb heat as does concrete, or stifle air flow as do large buildings.</p>
        <p>''If our computations are correct, a city that has trees is going to be better off than a city without trees,'' said Carlos A. Cardelino, a research scientist who wrote the paper with Dr. William L. Chameides, director of the School of Earth and Atmospheric Sciences at Georgia Tech and an author of the 1988 paper.</p>
        <p>The 20 percent loss of trees in Atlanta, along with an estimated 50 percent reduction in man-made hydrocarbons because of clean air laws, should have produced a sizable decrease in ozone concentrations, the study says. But measurements show that ozone has not been reduced, and the researchers calculate that hydrocarbons emissions have increased.</p>
        <p>SCIENCE WATCH</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
