<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NO U.S. ACTION SEEN ON PRISON CAMPS</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="547632"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MILITARY ACTION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA-HERZEGOVINA (YUGOSLAVIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BINDER, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920804T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6DE173FF937A3575BC0A964958260" item-length="716" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NO U.S. ACTION SEEN ON PRISON CAMPS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID BINDER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BINDER, DAVID</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Aug. 3</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The State Department said today that it had information that Serbian forces had opened detention centers in Bosnia where civilians were tortured and killed. But a spokesman said the United States had no plans to intervene to try to stop such actions.</p>
        <p>In response to questions from reporters, Richard Boucher, the department spokesman, said that "our own reports, information similar to press reports," made it clear that "Serbian forces are maintaining what they call detention centers for Croatians and Muslims," and that "there have been abuses and torture and killings taking place in those areas."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The State Department said today that it had information that Serbian forces had opened detention centers in Bosnia where civilians were tortured and killed. But a spokesman said the United States had no plans to intervene to try to stop such actions.</p>
        <p>In response to questions from reporters, Richard Boucher, the department spokesman, said that "our own reports, information similar to press reports," made it clear that "Serbian forces are maintaining what they call detention centers for Croatians and Muslims," and that "there have been abuses and torture and killings taking place in those areas."</p>
        <p>Mr. Boucher said "we're deeply concerned" about the reports, and reiterated the Bush Administration's "condemnation" of the actions. But he said the United States had no plans for responding beyond offering to assist the International Committee of the Red Cross in seeking to relieve the suffering of civilian victims of the fighting in Bosnia.</p>
        <p>A senior United States official said it remained Administration policy to avoid involvement of the American military in the Yugoslav conflict.</p>
        <p>The Administration rationale at this point, the official said, was that no outside military intervention could succeed in separating the antagonists in the ethnic fighting in Bosnia and Herzegovina and that intervention might even spread the war to regions spared from combat so far, like Kosovo, the homeland of nearly two million Albanians in Serbia, or Macedonia. All Sides 'Doing Bad Things'</p>
        <p>The focus on detention centers gained new prominence on Sunday after Newsday reported the existence of large Serbian-run prison camps at Omarska and Brcko in northern Bosnia.</p>
        <p>While corroborating press reports about torture and killing of civilians confined by Serbian forces, Mr. Boucher also said there were "people on all sides" of the Yugoslav conflict "that were doing bad things" -- including Croats and Muslims.</p>
        <p>"I should also note," the spokesman said, "that we have reports of Bosnians and Croatians also maintaining detention centers, but we do not have similar allegations of mistreatment at those."</p>
        <p>"At the same time," he continued, "we have also pointed the finger very particularly and very specifically at the actions of the Serbian forces and the Government in Belgrade in unleashing many of these attacks."</p>
        <p>"We're opposed to the fighting," Mr. Boucher said in defining United States policy. "We're opposed to the expulsion of people from their homes, and we think it ought to stop and people ought to be able to go home and live in peace." At another point he said: "We have made absolutely clear our condemnation of these camps. It's just horrible."</p>
        <p>Asked what the United States position was on the issue of the detention camps, the spokesman said the Administration policy "included a large variety of activities to support the helping of people who need help," such as flying relief supplies to help feed the besieged population of Sarajevo.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boucher said that the United States offered "wholehearted support" to the efforts of the Red Cross "to gain access to some of these camps" where civilians are being held, but that he was not aware of a specific request for American logistical assistance. No 'Specific Consultations'</p>
        <p>He said of the detention camps: "I'm not aware of any specific round of consultations on these reports. I'm sure that when we discuss this issue with allies, that anything that's important like this would be discussed. But I'm not aware of any specific consultations with some specific goal."</p>
        <p>He recalled that President Bush and heads of other governments of industrialized countries who met last month in Munich had agreed to cooperate in providing more emergency relief supplies for the besieged citizens of Sarajevo and assuring that the supplies got through, if need be with vaguely suggested military means.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, Mr. Boucher said the United States was "making efforts on the political front together with the Europeans" to foster arrangements "to encourage the parties to negotiate the political solution" to the conflicts.</p>
        <p>"That position remains," he said, adding that Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d "has often said that the solution has to come from the parties" engaged in the Yugoslav hostilities.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
