<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hurley Proving He's Focal Point For Blue Devils</title>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="45" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="339300"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="THE FINAL FOUR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DUKE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HURLEY, BOBBY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MORAN, MALCOLM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900331T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DD1139F932A05750C0A966958260" item-length="782" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hurley Proving He's Focal Point For Blue Devils</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MALCOLM MORAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MORAN, MALCOLM</byline>
      <dateline>DENVER, March 30</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The focal point stepped off the floor at McNichols Arena and into the bright lights of examination. Bobby Hurley folded his arms across his blue Duke practice jersey and listened to the questions.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The focal point stepped off the floor at McNichols Arena and into the bright lights of examination. Bobby Hurley folded his arms across his blue Duke practice jersey and listened to the questions.</p>
        <p>The focal point stepped off the floor at McNichols Arena and into the bright lights of examination. Bobby Hurley folded his arms across his blue Duke practice jersey and listened to the questions.</p>
        <p>At the end of his freshman season, Hurley was one day removed from a semifinal game against Arkansas in the Final Four of the national collegiate basketball tournament. He was nearly 24 hours from being part of an event that has been important to him for nearly half a lifetime, since he sat at home in Jersey City with his father, and watched North Carolina and Georgetown in a championship game eight years ago, and listened to a parental commentary that extended beyond the game.</p>
        <p>''He'd say, 'Look at this guy. Look how he plays. He does an excellent job playing the point,' '' Hurley remembered. ''Things like that, he would tell me. Will I ever be able to play like that? I don't know.''</p>
        <p>The Place to Be</p>
        <p>For most of the people who have flown into town, the party had already begun. For the fans who nearly filled the arena, the practices today would have to be enough. Throughout the afternoon, a total of 30,748 came and went through the turnstiles in the 16,667-seat arena that will be the showcase on Saturday for semifinal games between Duke-Arkansas followed by Georgia Tech-Nevada-Las Vegas.</p>
        <p>The arena had been dressed in pastels along the base of the upper level and in banners that hung from the ceiling. The high-pitched voices of young people, some not much younger than Hurley's 18 years, called out to the passing players as basketballs and programs were extended over a railing. ''Over here! Here! Over here!'' The focal point was discussing the business to be conducted when Duke meets Arkansas at 5:43 Eastern standard time (Channel 2 in New York). Now it is his turn to be scrutinized, by the dozens of college coaches in the stands, by those millions of eyes in all those living rooms, and by who-knows-how-many coaches' sons working toward their faraway opportunity.</p>
        <p>Hurley had become a focal point earlier in the afternoon, when Nolan Richardson, the Arkansas coach, spoke about the pressure defense employed by the Razorbacks.</p>
        <p>Will Pressure Backcourt</p>
        <p>''We try to put pressure on the guards, extremely hard,'' Richardson said. ''We want the bench to be used. That's our philosophy. We want to make a coach go to his bench, through fatigue, through fouls, or just being dissatisfied with the way the point guard is playing.''</p>
        <p>The only other time Hurley had been the object of that type of attention at this level was last Saturday in the time leading to the East Regional final against UConn. The sense of responsibility became so overwhelming that breakfast was suddenly left behind.</p>
        <p>Less than a week later, Hurley was speaking with the perspective of someone older and wiser. ''I think I was nervous because I didn't know how I was going to handle that,'' he said. ''I think I put too much pressure on myself. That's one thing I'm going to change for this game.''</p>
        <p>Hurley's deep-set eyes, his demeanor on the floor, and his high percentage of wise decisions during a game make him appear far older than his years.</p>
        <p>His position of point guard demands a sense of control. ''I enjoy being in control,'' Hurley said. ''But last week, when I had the ball with 9 seconds left, and we're down one against Connecticut in overtime, I didn't really feel like being in control then. The whole season was in my hands.''</p>
        <p>Near Disaster</p>
        <p>And then, suddenly, it wasn't. As the final seconds disappeared, and Hurley sensed the need to get the ball to Phil Henderson near the left sideline, he released the pass and immediately saw disaster.</p>
        <p>''I just saw Tate George come out like gangbusters,'' Hurley remembered of the UConn guard. ''Then the ball just dribbled off his hands. That was the ultimate relief. That was the most nervous I've ever been in my life.''</p>
        <p>Hurley had committed 2 turnovers in 43 minutes against a Connecticut defense that had created serious problems for far more experienced players, and yet he had very nearly made the pass that could have ended his freshman season.</p>
        <p>He understands that the party is for someone else. His coach, Mike Krzyzewski, had talked of the importance of his youngest players gaining a sense of playing in the Final Four. Hurley sounded more interested in getting rid of a sore throat and congestion.</p>
        <p>He already understands that for the participants, the good times often don't happen until they appear in the past tense.</p>
        <p>''I'm sure after this is over, a couple of weeks, I'll sit back and say, 'Wow. Look at what we accomplished,' '' Hurley said. ''Or, 'Look at what we could have accomplished.' ''  THE FINAL FOUR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
