<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It Was Ugly, but Broncos Are Now 12-0</title>
    <meta content="30CHAR$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1066232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Denver Broncos</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Diego Chargers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Freeman, Mike</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Denver Broncos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/San Diego Chargers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3D91238F933A05752C1A96E958260" item-length="876" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It Was Ugly, but Broncos Are Now 12-0</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MIKE FREEMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Freeman, Mike</byline>
      <dateline>SAN DIEGO, Nov. 29</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Denver Broncos defeat San Diego Chargers, 31-16; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Even the great teams, every now and then, play a game so bad they want to burn the game film. The Denver Broncos are a great team, but they played in one of the ugliest games of the season against the San Diego Chargers tonight.</p>
        <p>After a first half that included eight turnovers by the teams, the Broncos settled down thanks to the steady influence of their offensive stars: rushes by running back Terrell Davis, as well as quarterback John Elway's passes to Ed McCaffrey, Rod Smith and Shannon Sharpe. Denver's first drive in the third quarter went 95 yards in 8 minutes 20 seconds and ended with Elway making a great 18-yard throw to Sharpe in the end zone. It was the Broncos' best drive of the game, and it gave Denver a commanding 28-10 lead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Even the great teams, every now and then, play a game so bad they want to burn the game film. The Denver Broncos are a great team, but they played in one of the ugliest games of the season against the San Diego Chargers tonight.</p>
        <p>After a first half that included eight turnovers by the teams, the Broncos settled down thanks to the steady influence of their offensive stars: rushes by running back Terrell Davis, as well as quarterback John Elway's passes to Ed McCaffrey, Rod Smith and Shannon Sharpe. Denver's first drive in the third quarter went 95 yards in 8 minutes 20 seconds and ended with Elway making a great 18-yard throw to Sharpe in the end zone. It was the Broncos' best drive of the game, and it gave Denver a commanding 28-10 lead.</p>
        <p>More important, the Broncos' 31-16 victory at Qualcomm Stadium keeps alive the most-watched streak in sports. The Broncos improved to 12-0 with four games remaining. The Super Bowl champions are trying to win not just 16 games, but 19, which would give them another Super Bowl title.</p>
        <p>Denver is only the fourth team in National Football League history to go undefeated in 12 games, joining the 1934 Chicago Bears, the 1972 Miami Dolphins and the 1985 Bears.</p>
        <p>''It feels awfully good, 12-0,'' Denver Coach Mike Shanahan said. ''That's what we were shooting for. Next week against Kansas City, hopefully we'll go 13-0.''</p>
        <p>The Broncos' dreams almost came to an end tonight. Elway threw four touchdown passes, but also three interceptions, and the Denver offense was sluggish and clumsy in the second quarter.</p>
        <p>''It was sloppy at times,'' defensive lineman Harald Hasselbach said. ''We'll look at the film, and probably be critical of what we see, but the bottom line is we won the game.''</p>
        <p>Said Elway: ''We knew coming in, San Diego was a good defensive team. They really came after us in the second quarter.''</p>
        <p>Then came the third quarter, and Bronco receivers were wide open. Davis, who had only 32 yards in the first half, squeaked through tight holes in the second half. While Davis was not a huge factor, he still passed the 1,500-yard mark for the season, making him only the second player in league history to rush for at least 1,500 yards in three consecutive seasons. The Detroit Lions' Barry Sanders did it from 1994-97.</p>
        <p>This game could have been one of the roadblocks in Denver's quest for an undefeated season. First, the Broncos might have lost some incentive because they knew coming in that, hours earlier, Oakland had lost to Washington, which meant Denver had captured the American Football Conference West.</p>
        <p>Second, the Chargers had not allowed a 100-yard game by an opposing rusher all year. Earlier this year, Davis was held to a season-low 69 yards on 20 carries by the San Diego defense. The Broncos still won easily, but that game left a bad taste in the mouth of Davis, who is from the San Diego area and likes to do well against his hometown team.</p>
        <p>The Chargers knew that the only chance they had to beat Denver was to jump on the Broncos early and keep the score close. Denver had outscored its opponents this season by 131-23 in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>And San Diego scored first. When Denver made a rare mistake -- Elway bobbled a snap and the ball was recovered by linebacker Junior Seau at the Broncos' 25 -- the Chargers scored, although they managed only a 27-yard field goal by John Carney. That was a bad omen because a turnover like that should produce more than 3 points. Sure enough, Denver got two quick touchdowns, on 15- and 37-yard passes to McCaffrey, for an early 14-3 lead.</p>
        <p>But San Diego was not ready to capitulate. Finding inspiration in the sometimes good play of the backup quarterback Craig Whelihan, who was starting in place of the benched Ryan Leaf, and the great play of Seau, the Chargers cut the lead to 4 points after a 13-yard touchdown on a draw play by running back Terrell Fletcher.</p>
        <p>The teams then went through a period of sloppy play. Elway was sacked by Seau, and Chargers running back Kenny Bynum fumbled at the Denver 5-yard line. That was followed by an interception of Elway by Charles Dimry, who made an over-the-shoulder catch of a pass intended for McCaffrey. Whelihan was intercepted by cornerback Darrius Johnson. Then Dimry picked off Elway again.</p>
        <p>At this point, the Broncos were playing down to the level of their opponent. That continued when, with less than two minutes to go in the half, Elway was picked off by Greg Jackson for the Denver quarterback's third interception of the game. Then Whelihan was intercepted again, by linebacker John Mobley.</p>
        <p>The Broncos capitalized on the last interception when Rod Smith caught a 13-yard touchdown pass. Denver finally began to pull away, gaining a 21-10 lead at halftime. But it had been ugly.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
