<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Youth Is Served In a Geriatric Battle</title>
    <meta content="NFL1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1066241"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="N.F.L. WEEK 13: YESTERDAY'S GAMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Atlanta Falcons</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">St Louis Rams</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jacksonville Jaguars</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cincinnati Bengals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Miami Dolphins</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Orleans Saints</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Seattle Seahawks</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Tennessee Oilers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Baltimore Ravens</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Indianapolis Colts</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Redskins</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Oakland Raiders</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Atlanta Falcons</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Baltimore Ravens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Cincinnati Bengals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Indianapolis Colts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Jacksonville Jaguars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Miami Dolphins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New Orleans Saints</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Oakland Raiders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Seattle Seahawks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/St. Louis Rams</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/Washington Redskins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981130T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E5DD1338F933A05752C1A96E958260" item-length="1658" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Youth Is Served In a Geriatric Battle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Atlanta Falcons defeat St Louis Rams, 21-10; Jacksonville Jaguars defeat Cincinnati Bengals, 34-17; Miami Dolphins defeat New Orleans Saints, 30-10; Seattle Seahawks defeat Tennessee Oilers, 20-18; Baltimore Ravens defeat Indianapolis Colts, 38-31; Washington Redskins defeat Oakland Raiders, 29-19 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>FALCONS 21, RAMS 10</p>
        <p>Forget the geriatric backups slogging it out, it was Jamal Anderson who put the Atlanta Falcons in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The National Football League's oldest player, 44-year-old Steve DeBerg, had a marginal advantage over the Rams' backup, 36-year-old Steve Bono, in the second half of the Falcons' 21-10 victory yesterday. But Anderson did the heavy work with a career-best 188 yards on 31 carries and a touchdown as the National Football Conference West leaders clinched a playoff berth earlier than ever before.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>FALCONS 21, RAMS 10</p>
        <p>Forget the geriatric backups slogging it out, it was Jamal Anderson who put the Atlanta Falcons in the playoffs.</p>
        <p>The National Football League's oldest player, 44-year-old Steve DeBerg, had a marginal advantage over the Rams' backup, 36-year-old Steve Bono, in the second half of the Falcons' 21-10 victory yesterday. But Anderson did the heavy work with a career-best 188 yards on 31 carries and a touchdown as the National Football Conference West leaders clinched a playoff berth earlier than ever before.</p>
        <p>The Falcons (10-2) qualified for the playoffs after 13 games in 1980.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most impressive aspect of Anderson's big day was that the Rams knew he would be coming right at them and still could not do anything about it. In two games against the Rams, Anderson has run for 360 yards and 4 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>DeBerg came on in the second half after Tony Graziani produced only 3 points in the first half in relief of Chris Chandler, Atlanta's injured starting quarterback. DeBerg threw the go-ahead touchdown pass, a 27-yarder to Terance Mathis in the third quarter, but his chief asset to the Falcons was a mistake-free outing.</p>
        <p>Although he threw for only 75 yards, DeBerg was an improvement over Graziani, who was 8 for 18 for 102 yards and an interception in the first half. Chandler, sidelined with ankle and knee injuries, hopes to be back next week.</p>
        <p>People said winning without Chris was one of those hurdles that we had to cross, Falcons Coach Dan Reeves said. I thought Tony did a decent job, but I just felt like Steve would give us a little of the experience we needed.</p>
        <p>The Rams had quarterback problems, too, with Bono replacing Tony Banks in the second half. Vermeil said he did not know which player would start Thursday's game at Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Banks (10 for 21 for 95 yards) shook off an ankle injury to start his 41st consecutive game, but was booed heavily and left in the third quarter. He said it was the first time he has ever been benched.</p>
        <p>I feel like a failure, Banks said. But it happens to the best of them. We'll see how I bounce back from here.</p>
        <p>JAGUARS 34; BENGALS 17</p>
        <p>A week after the most dreadful performance of his career, Mark Brunell threw a career-best four touchdown passes -- one in each quarter -- for a victory at Cincinnati. Jacksonville improved to 9-3 for the first time in its four-year history and opened a two-game lead in the American Football Conference Central, which the Jaguars have never won. Three of the Jaguars' last four games are at home, where they are 5-0 this season.</p>
        <p>We're on the verge of doing something here, said Keenan McCardell, who had 7 catches for 76 yards and 2 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>Last week the Jaguars blew a chance to open a three-game lead when Brunell threw three interceptions in a loss at Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>By losing to Detroit in overtime on Thanksgiving, the Steelers gave the Jaguars another chance to pull away. They took advantage by forcing four turnovers and getting their first victory in Cincinnati.</p>
        <p>The Bengals changed quarterbacks -- Paul Justin gave way to Neil O'Donnell after a first-half interception -- but wound up derided by the crowd of 55,432, which booed repeatedly and waved anti-Bengal banners. That's probably to be expected, Coach Bruce Coslet said. I don't feel good about it myself. How do you think I feel? How do you think the players feel? Maybe it's not worth it to us, either.</p>
        <p>With that, Coslet cut off his post-game interview.</p>
        <p>SAINTS 10, DOLPHINS 30</p>
        <p>Dan Marino threw three touchdown passes to O. J. McDuffie, becoming the first player in N.F.L. history to reach 400 career touchdown passes, as host Miami stayed in a tie with the Jets in the A.F.C. East by overcoming an early 10-3 lead by New Orleans.</p>
        <p>Marino hit McDuffie with a 22-yard scoring pass late in the second quarter, then reached the milestone by hitting McDuffie with a 4-yard touchdown toss on the first play of the fourth quarter. They hooked up again on a 9-yard touchdown pass with 7:34 left. Marino has 63 three-touchdown games in his 16-year career.</p>
        <p>CARDINALS 24, CHIEFS 34</p>
        <p>When Arizona scored quickly in the fourth quarter to get within a touchdown, host Kansas City feared the worst. Losing six games in a row, you tend to lose your confidence, linebacker Donnie Edwards said. Everybody was thinking, 'Don't let it happen again'</p>
        <p>It didn't, and the longest losing streak in Marty Schottenheimer's 15-year coaching career ended.</p>
        <p>Rich Gannon threw three touchdown passes and the Chiefs took a 31-17 lead with 10:26 left on Derrick Alexander's 15-yard touchdown catch. But the Cardinals answered with an 80-yard drive aided by a pass-interference call and made it 31-24 on Mario Bates's 1-yard plunge. Not until Pete Stoyanovich's 18-yard field goal for a 10-point lead with 1:57 left could the Arrowhead Stadium crowd breathe easily.</p>
        <p>OILERS 18, SEAHAWKS 20</p>
        <p>Jon Kitna, replacing the benched Warren Moon, threw two touchdown passes and drove host Seattle into position for the winning field goal with one second left.</p>
        <p>Todd Peterson kicked a 48-yard field goal after Kitna marched the Seahawks from their 29-yard line to the Oilers' 30 after Al Del Greco's 42-yard field goal put Tennessee ahead by 18-17 with 33 seconds to go.</p>
        <p>REDSKINS 29, RAIDERS 19</p>
        <p>Jeff George's return did little to revive the Raiders' stagnant offense. And, for one of the few times this season, Oakland's defense could not make up for the offense's lack of spark.</p>
        <p>Trent Green threw three scoring passes and Washington forced three turnovers as the Redskins won their first road game of the season and severely hurt Oakland's chances of making the playoffs for the first time since 1993.</p>
        <p>The Redskins, who have won three of five after opening the season with seven straight losses, came into the game with the worst turnover differential in the N.F.L. But they recovered two fumbles and made an interception while losing the ball only once.</p>
        <p>George, who had not played past the first quarter of a game since September because of a groin injury, made the start but was pulled at halftime after throwing for 65 yards with an interception.</p>
        <p>COLTS 31, RAVENS 38</p>
        <p>Baltimore's current National Football League team, the Ravens, beat its predecessor, rallying to beat Indianapolis and delighting the 68,898 fans who waited 14 years to root in person against the team that long ago abandoned the city.</p>
        <p>Back in Baltimore for the first time since Robert Irsay moved the club to Indianapolis in 1984, the Colts made themselves at home in a hostile environment by taking a 17-3 lead in the first quarter. But the Ravens outscored Indianapolis by 17-0 in the fourth quarter.</p>
        <p>After the final gun, Raven quarterback Jim Harbaugh gave the game ball to the former Baltimore Colt quarterback Johnny Unitas, who rooted for the Ravens.</p>
        <p>Harbaugh, who played for Indianapolis from 1994 to 1997, threw for 198 yards and 2 touchdowns.</p>
        <p>Priest Holmes ran for 103 yards, including the go-ahead score on a 36-yard run with 13:07 left.</p>
        <p>Marshall Faulk rushed for a career-high 192 yards, scored twice and eclipsed the 1,000-yard mark (1,037) for the fourth time in five seasons with the Colts.</p>
        <p>BUCCANEERS 31, BEARS 17</p>
        <p>When Trent Dilfer heaved a desperation pass toward the end zone, it was just like an ordinary practice for Tampa Bay, with the players bumping and shoving, their hands clawing at the air. Only this time, the play counted.</p>
        <p>Nobody is serious in practice; we just jump around a lot, Bert Emanuel said. But we know in the back of our minds there will be a time in the game when it will actually come into play.</p>
        <p>Emanuel tipped Dilfer's pass to Brice Hunter, who came in from out of bounds to catch the go-ahead touchdown at halftime as the Buccaneers won at Chicago.</p>
        <p>I caught it as if it was meant for us, Hunter said.</p>
        <p>Dilfer threw for three touchdowns. The rookie Moses Moreno, making his first N.F.L. start as the Bears tried to find some kind of offensive spark, threw for 153 yards and a touchdown.</p>
        <p>Moreno will start for the rest of the season, Coach Dave Wannstedt said, because Erik Kramer will have season-ending surgery on Wednesday on his throwing shoulder, which has not got better despite a month of rest. The problem was initially thought to be a strained rotator cuff and tendinitis, but Kramer said doctors still did not know exactly what was wrong.</p>
        <p>I think they expect to go in there and find some kind of tear, he said. They don't know what they're going to find until they get in there.</p>
        <p>EAGLES 16, PACKERS 24</p>
        <p>Host Green Bay needed career days from running back Darick Holmes and wideout Bill Schroeder to slip past Philadelphia.</p>
        <p>Holmes rushed for a career-best 163 yards on 26 carries and Schroeder caught 5 passes for a career-high 128 yards in his first N.F.L. start in a game that was much closer than anybody could have expected. Green Bay trailed by 13-10 in the third quarter after the third-string quarterback, Koy Detmer, making his first N.F.L. start, guided the Eagles on two long scoring drives that he capped with touchdown tosses of 16 and 4 yards to Jeff Graham.</p>
        <p>N.F.L. WEEK 13: YESTERDAY'S GAMES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
