<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Photography; Tantalizing Variations on the Family Snapshot</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="535559"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PHOTOGRAPHY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAGEN, CHARLES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920612T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DD1030F931A25755C0A964958260" item-length="885" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Photography; Tantalizing Variations on the Family Snapshot</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLES HAGEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HAGEN, CHARLES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From family snapshots to pictures of the bowling team, images of people gathered together form a central genre of photography. "Multiple Exposure: The Group Portrait in Photography," at the Zabriskie Gallery, offers a welcome if somewhat specialized survey of pictures of this sort. Leslie Tonkonow, who organized the exhibition, has chosen to emphasize work by 20th-century art photographers like Walker Evans, Andre Kertesz, Man Ray and William Wegman. Although many of these photographers look to commercial or amateur photographs for aspects of their own style, only a small selection of these vernacular pictures are included in the exhibition, which was shown earlier this year at the Ezra and Cecile Zilkha Galery at Wesleyan University in Middletown, Conn.</p>
        <p>Even so, more than a few pictures in the exhibition are essentially variations on the family snapshot. Lee Friedlander includes himself in the frame, along with his wife and two daughters, in a black-and-white photograph that has a casually cheerful air. Tina Barney, meanwhile, presents a large, intensely colored print of herself and her sons at a family cookout.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From family snapshots to pictures of the bowling team, images of people gathered together form a central genre of photography. "Multiple Exposure: The Group Portrait in Photography," at the Zabriskie Gallery, offers a welcome if somewhat specialized survey of pictures of this sort. Leslie Tonkonow, who organized the exhibition, has chosen to emphasize work by 20th-century art photographers like Walker Evans, Andre Kertesz, Man Ray and William Wegman. Although many of these photographers look to commercial or amateur photographs for aspects of their own style, only a small selection of these vernacular pictures are included in the exhibition, which was shown earlier this year at the Ezra and Cecile Zilkha Galery at Wesleyan University in Middletown, Conn.</p>
        <p>Even so, more than a few pictures in the exhibition are essentially variations on the family snapshot. Lee Friedlander includes himself in the frame, along with his wife and two daughters, in a black-and-white photograph that has a casually cheerful air. Tina Barney, meanwhile, presents a large, intensely colored print of herself and her sons at a family cookout.</p>
        <p>Other works are based on the model of the family portrait. The Italian aristocrats in Patrick Faigenbaum's moody pictures are shown at home, carefully posed and surrounded by heavy polished furniture and ornately framed paintings. But the purpose of these pictures is not to record the specific families; indeed, to accentuate the melodramatic overtones of his pictures, Mr. Faigenbaum sometimes throws his sitters into deep shadow.</p>
        <p>A different kind of family is shown in a picture by Diane Arbus from 1965, of a fat nudist couple and their equally hefty son. In this surprisingly tender and hilarious scene, Arbus captures the family lolling on the ground in a pose that, outrageously, recalls that of Manet's "Dejeuner sur l'Herbe."</p>
        <p>It is just such odd and quirky gems that this exhibition abounds in.  Among several pictures by the great German portraitist August Sander, for example, is a studio shot from 1911 of the photographer's own family, in which the mustached Sander fingers a double-necked lute while his wife shyly holds their beaming baby up to the camera.</p>
        <p>Like all such pictures, whether snapshots or formal portraits, these photographs seem to offer tantalizing glimpses into the inner workings of the families involved. This is one of the chief charms of group portraits: they invite viewers to read the relationships between the sitters from their expressions and poses.</p>
        <p>Another main use for group portraits is to commemorate important events and happy times. A number of photographs here belong to the minor but amusing subgenre of pictures showing artists at play. Among these is a lighthearted snapshot taken by T. Lux Feininger in the 1920's of Josef Albers, Marcel Breuer and other artists dancing on the roof of the Bauhaus. Elsewhere, a small strip of pictures records Andre Breton, Paul Eluard and other Surrealists crowded together in a photo booth.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the group in a group portrait is defined as much by the photographer as the people themselves. The newsboys in Lewis Hine's night shot, their eyes blinking in the harsh light of the camera flash, are presented as representatives of a social type enlisted to support Hine's efforts at reform, rather than members of a clearly defined body.</p>
        <p>In other cases, the group in question is even looser in structure, and may simply be the result of people being in the same place at the same time. An extreme example of this is Weegee's great 1940 photograph of the crowd on the beach at Coney Island, in which every square inch of the picture is filled with people, all of them looking at the camera.</p>
        <p>A counterpart to this wonderfully chaotic scene is provided by a picture from 1940 by E. O. Goldbeck, a commercial photographer from San Antonio. In the first decades of the century, he would organize vast numbers of people, usually soldiers, into such shapes as the American flag, the Statue of Liberty, or military insignia (as in the example here), and then photograph the scene from a nearby tower.</p>
        <p>Because of its emphasis on art photography, the exhibition skips over various popular kinds of group portrait. Missing, for example, are banquet photographs, the pictures taken at formal dinners to record just who was there. Also absent are formal photographs of sports teams. Although it is understandable that pictures of this sort would be left out of a gallery show, including them would have given the exhibition added depth, and further demonstrated just how important this subject is.</p>
        <p>In the end it is the groups themselves, in all their surprising and marvelous diversity, that are the most fascinating aspect of this delightful exhibition. No doubt most of the groups have since broken up, the people in them dead or gone their separate ways. But in the photograph, at least, the groups still exist, certifying that all of these people, for this moment, were together. This is the real magic of the group portrait, and it's one that comes through clearly in the rich selection of work here.</p>
        <p>"Multiple Exposure: The Group Portrait in Photography" remains at the Zabriskie Gallery, 724 Fifth Avenue, at 57th Street, Manhattan,</p>
        <p>through June 27.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
