<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Favorites Grounded As a Pilot Takes Off</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="29" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="721509"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="GOLF"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOLF</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOUR CHAMPIONSHIP (GOLF)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRICE, NICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">NORMAN, GREG</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DORMAN, LARRY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Golf</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Golf</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941029T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5DF113FF93AA15753C1A962958260" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Favorites Grounded As a Pilot Takes Off</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LARRY DORMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DORMAN, LARRY</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO, Oct. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Tour Championship was supposed to be the battle of the titans, the duel of the giants, the week that Nick Price and Greg Norman settled the argument as to the identity of the PGA Tour's 1994 leading money winner and the winner of the Vardon Trophy.</p>
        <p>That's not quite the way things are shaping up here at the Olympic Club. At the halfway point of the richest event in golf, Price, the leading money winner, is mired in 29th place in the 30-man field. Norman, whose stroke average of 68.68 is the lowest in golf, shot 75 -- the highest round of the day -- and is tied for 26th.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Tour Championship was supposed to be the battle of the titans, the duel of the giants, the week that Nick Price and Greg Norman settled the argument as to the identity of the PGA Tour's 1994 leading money winner and the winner of the Vardon Trophy.</p>
        <p>That's not quite the way things are shaping up here at the Olympic Club. At the halfway point of the richest event in golf, Price, the leading money winner, is mired in 29th place in the 30-man field. Norman, whose stroke average of 68.68 is the lowest in golf, shot 75 -- the highest round of the day -- and is tied for 26th.</p>
        <p>On an afternoon so spectacularly clear that the Golden Gate Bridge was visible from the third tee, golf's reigning royalty was humbled and one of its relative commoners was temporarily exalted. Bill Glasson, a tough guy from Fresno, Calif., who shows equal aplomb flying his own plane and firing his irons at tucked pin placements, managed a nearly impossible up and down from beyond the pin at the 18th hole to finish off a round of 68 and take a one-stroke lead over Ernie Els (67), David Frost (69) and Steve Lowery (69).</p>
        <p>"I'm playing pretty solid and putting all right," said Glasson, 34, who is 8 under par. "Actually, I feel pretty good about the rest of the week."</p>
        <p>This is a week the top 30 players on the tour pad their bank accounts. And despite their uncharacteristically poor play for 36 holes, the rich -- Price has won $1,442,927 and Norman has won $1,202,369 -- will still get richer. Last place here pays $48,000. But the race for the $540,000 first-place check will apparently not include the two men who have dominated the game this year.</p>
        <p>"At least they're giving us a chance this week," said Els, who won three times this year, including the United States Open at Oakmont and the World Match Play Championship at Wentworth, England. "They've both had such great years, it's hard to keep up that kind of pace."</p>
        <p>Price is battling his swing, which appears to be even quicker than his normal Mach 2 speed. He hit just 10 greens and eight of 14 fairways in his round of 74. And he is not being bailed out by his putter this week. He took 31 putts on the slick Olympic greens.</p>
        <p>"I've decided that tomorrow I'm going to aim away from the hole with the putter," Price joked, "because today aiming it at the hole didn't work."</p>
        <p>Glasson's putter worked quite well. He kept the lead despite a double bogey at the 15th hole, where he left a shot in the right greenside bunker, saving his round with one brave stroke of the putter. At the 18th hole, his 8-iron approach shot went long and left, absolutely the worst place to be on the green that slopes severely from back to front.</p>
        <p>His first putt drifted some 12 feet past the hole, but he made it coming back. It is of such pars that victories are often fashioned.</p>
        <p>"I like what I'm doing," Glasson said, "and I'm having a good time doing it this week."  GOLF</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
