<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hard Cash Talks Loudly in Land of Grumbles</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392700"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="EVOLUTION IN EUROPE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNION OF SOVIET SOCIALIST REPUBLICS (USSR)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINES, FRANCIS X</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DF133BF93BA25753C1A966958260" item-length="938" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hard Cash Talks Loudly in Land of Grumbles</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCIS X. CLINES, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CLINES, FRANCIS X</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, Oct. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Redoubtable Muscovites bored with the Kremlin's agonizing over economic reform are taking their forbidden dollars out of hiding and openly putting their money on the free market at hard-currency stores long restricted to the city's Western residents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Redoubtable Muscovites bored with the Kremlin's agonizing over economic reform are taking their forbidden dollars out of hiding and openly putting their money on the free market at hard-currency stores long restricted to the city's Western residents.</p>
        <p>Redoubtable Muscovites bored with the Kremlin's agonizing over economic reform are taking their forbidden dollars out of hiding and openly putting their money on the free market at hard-currency stores long restricted to the city's Western residents.</p>
        <p>''The Kremlin may not know it, but this is the market,'' Vyacheslav Shapar said calmly, shepherding the day's crush of mostly Soviet shoppers through the checkout counters at Saadko, one of the city's busiest food supermarkets dealing in hard currency.</p>
        <p>In theory, most of the customers could be charged with a crime, as Soviet citizens with large amounts of dollars, German marks or other hard currencies and no officially acceptable explanation of how they got them.</p>
        <p>In truth, they are now able to act with impunity in their self-interest as the authorities promise to formally legalize this traffic someday.</p>
        <p>The Hard-Currency Privileged</p>
        <p>Soviet customers now account for most of the business these days at the foreigners' main stores, according to workers racing to keep ahead of the new rush of Soviet spenders.</p>
        <p>At Saadko, Soviet shoppers who accounted for 10 percent of business a year ago now make 60 percent of the purchases. The city's other major Western supermarket, Stockmann's, is about to go beyond its credit-card policy and accept hard currency in no-questions-asked dealings to tap the under-the-mattress resources of Muscovites.</p>
        <p>The checkout-counter ring of that reality could be heard at a score of such stores for the hard-currency privileged as Parliament remained mired in conflicting theories of free marketry.</p>
        <p>''We know what is really going on,'' Irute Remikaite said, regretting the dearth of decent clothing in Soviet stores as she bought a $40 blouse at a hard-currency store.</p>
        <p>''There is no future in prospect and I want my children to migrate from this,'' she said as legislators in the Kremlin began poring over the latest compromise version of ''the plan,'' the often delayed, always shifting raft of promises for economic change from President Mikhail S. Gorbachev.</p>
        <p>Dollars: Getting and Spending</p>
        <p>The one note of free enterprise brought to the nation by the latest version of the plan was in the form of a packaged leak of its contents being peddled by Kremlin insiders on Tuesday for $25, no rubles please, to Western news organizations taking it more seriously than the average Muscovite out foraging on the shopping lines.</p>
        <p>''The ruble is worth less and less every day and there is so little to be found in Soviet stores,'' said Irina Averina, deputy manager at one of the state's special hard-currency stores, explaining why Moscow residents are being driven to spending their hard-earned, well-hidden dollars or marks or francs at the richly stocked Western stores.</p>
        <p>''Those able to earn dollars are spending them,'' said Piotr Ivanov, a shopper at Saadko, noting that the general motive is one of relative desperation more than prosperity among the privileged minority of Muscovites who have socked away dollars.</p>
        <p>Apart from Soviet workers with Western-related jobs that offer limited access to dollars, Muscovites can come by their dollars by earning them for particularly valued goods or services in the city's growing black-market commerce. They can also purchase dollars outright on the black market, trading in their fast-fading rubles at 20 or 30 times the Government exchange rate.</p>
        <p>Law Becomes Anachronism</p>
        <p>Even a croupier at one of the city's three Western-hotel casinos said most of her customers were Soviet citizens venturing in from the street. But large Government enterprises also have the wherewithal to venture into the hard-currency world.</p>
        <p>A salesman at a German sales fair here said he sold about $13 million in home power tools to Soviet factories and other large enterprises planning to offer them as compensation to ruble-doubting workers.</p>
        <p>The nation's once strictly enforced law against dollar possession is only one of many anachronisms and hypocrisies to be seen as aspects of the market take hold despite the Kremlin's dithering. Only the most adventurous Muscovites can afford to dabble in hard-currency transactions, but clearly more and more are being emboldened by their neighbors' example to come over into the black market.</p>
        <p>''I am a pensioner and all I have is a few rubles,'' Sergei Kurilkin said, laughing at the idea of obtaining dollars as he approached one of the city's nine pawn shops. Inside, the scene was Dickensian, with long waiting lines and tired clerks handling the pitiful possessions of the city's poorest.</p>
        <p>Significantly, only a few people were pawning goods while scores were at the other windows retrieving possessions pawned earlier.</p>
        <p>A Principle Comes to Life</p>
        <p>''Of course,'' said Luisa Oleinikola, the pawn-shop director. ''People do not need cash now because there is nothing to buy in the stores. So it is better to retain their possessions rather than turn them into rubles.''</p>
        <p>Beyond the hard-currency stores, a new kind of hyperpriced ruble store is to be found in the city, offering scarce shoes, for example, but at many times the prices of the empty state shoe stores. The latest such store is named Principle, in honor of the long-running joke about Communism's Shangri-la for shoppers where ''in principle, you can buy anything you need.''</p>
        <p>''They are buying up everything,'' Mr. Shapar said, watching stony-faced Soviet shoppers hand over their dollars at the Saadko checkout lines. ''Thus you see the market show its strength,'' he said, gathering up shopping carts as fast as they were emptied to keep Muscovites' de facto market rolling.</p>
        <p>EVOLUTION IN EUROPE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
