<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Supporters Vow To Save Compromise On Arts Endowment</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392863"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEED6163FF93BA25753C1A966958260" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Supporters Vow To Save Compromise On Arts Endowment</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARTIN TOLCHIN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A move on Tuesday night by the Senate Appropriations Committee to reinstate restrictions on National Endowment for the Arts grants drew immediate opposition today.</p>
        <p>Congressional supporters of a legislative compromise that would remove many of the restrictions in the current law and leave judgments about obscenity to the courts vowed to fight efforts to scuttle the compromise.</p>
        <p>Under the compromise, the life of the National Endowment for the Arts would be extended for three years. The endowment is prohibited from financing obscene or pornographic works, but the determination of what is obscene or pornographic is a matter for the courts. If an artist who received Federal grants violated obscenity laws, he would be required to return the money and could not receive new grants for three years.  The Committee Steps In</p>
        <p>The compromise was approved by the House of Representatives last week by a 382-42 vote, and a similar bill was approved by the Senate Labor and Human Resources Committee last month by a vote of 15-1. The committee's bill is stalled in the Senate, however, and on Tuesday night the Senate Appropriations Committee took over the issue.</p>
        <p>The committee voted to reinstate the anti-obscenity restrictions and approved only $170 million for the endowment in the fiscal year that began Oct. 1. The appropriation is $5 million less than requested by President Bush and $10 million less than the amount approved on Monday by the House.</p>
        <p>The Appropriations panel, led by Senator Robert C. Byrd Jr., a Democrat of West Virginia, revived a series of restrictions that are in the current law. That law prohibits Federal funds for works that ''may be considered obscene, including but not limited to depictions of homoeroticism, the sexual exploitation of children, or individuals engaged in sex acts and which, when taken as a whole, do not have serious literary, artistic, political or scientific value.''</p>
        <p>The Appropriations bill, which would extend the life of the endowment for only one year, may reach the Senate floor on Thursday. Whatever bill the Senate approves will go to a House-Senate conference, where supporters of the compromise hope to prevail.  'Committee Took a Step Backward'</p>
        <p>''Nobody's throwing in the towel,'' said Representative E. Thomas Coleman, the Missouri Republican who is a co-author of the House compromise. ''The Appropriations Committee took a step backward in trying to resolve this issue.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Coleman accused the senators of political cowardice, and said the committee's action was motivated by fear of voter retaliation if the senators supported the compromise. ''We in the House have faced this issue, and every one of us is up for re-election,'' Mr. Coleman said. ''In the Senate, only one-third of the seats are up.'' Representative Sidney Yates, an Illinois Democrat and the chairman of the appropriations subcommittee on the interior, said: ''I don't think that the action by the Senate Appropriations Committee is the end of the drama. It's still being played out.''  Pell Says He's Hopeful</p>
        <p>In the Senate, Claiborne Pell, Rhode Island Democrat and chairman of the Labor and Human Resources Subcommittee on Education, Arts and the Humanities, and coauthor of the Senate compromise, also said the battle was far from over. ''The motto of my state is 'Hope,' '' Mr. Pell said.  The compromise fell afoul of the mathematics of the closing days of a Congressional session in an election year, when a single senator's passionate convictions have undue weight because of the shortness of time. At such times, a senator may filibuster and otherwise block passage of an entire bill rather than yield on what he considers a matter of principle.</p>
        <p>In this case, the Senate Appropriations Committee appeared anxious to placate Senator Jesse Helms, a Republican of North Carolina and a leading critic of the arts endowment, rather than risk Mr. Helms's tying up the bill on the Senate floor. Mr. Helms, in a tough re-election campaign, has focused on the arts endowment and its support of controversial works by the photographers Robert Mapplethorpe and Andres Serrano, in his effort to win votes.  'A Compromise Is Necessary'</p>
        <p>''They did it to avoid a big fight on the floor,'' said Senator Pete Domenici, a New Mexico Republican and a member of the Appropriations Committee. ''Frankly, I don't think it's that big a problem.''</p>
        <p>Senator Jake Garn, a Utah Republican, said that once the bill went to conference, ''I think a compromise is necessary.''</p>
        <p>The issue of Federal support of the arts is one of the most contentious in Congress. Senator Wyche Fowler, a Georgia Democrat and a member of the Appropriations Committee, said: ''The battle will never be over as long as we have critics of any government funding of the arts, and as long as we have artists using public funds producing works repugnant to a sizable portion of American families.''</p>
        <p>Supporters of the compromise have accused conservative opponents of stirring public emotions by inaccurately portraying the endowment as having paid mostly for distasteful works of no redeeming artistic value.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
