<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ads Aimed At Children Restricted</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="392696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ADVERTISING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHILDREN AND YOUTH</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION PROGRAMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">GAMAREKIAN, BARBARA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901018T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DB123BF93BA25753C1A966958260" item-length="681" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ads Aimed At Children Restricted</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA GAMAREKIAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GAMAREKIAN, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush decided today to let a bill that limits television commercials on children's programming become law without his signature. He withheld his official seal of approval because of First Amendment concerns.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Bush decided today to let a bill that limits television commercials on children's programming become law without his signature. He withheld his official seal of approval because of First Amendment concerns.</p>
        <p>President Bush decided today to let a bill that limits television commercials on children's programming become law without his signature. He withheld his official seal of approval because of First Amendment concerns.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush said that he supported the goal of diminishing the commercialization of programming for children, but that doing so was not the responsibility of Government.</p>
        <p>''In an effort to improve children's television, this legislation imposes content-based restrictions on programming,'' he said. ''The First Amendment, however, does not contemplate that Government will dictate the quality or quantity of what Americans should hear. Rather, it leaves this to be decided by free media responding to the free choices of individual consumers.''</p>
        <p>'It Is Now the Law'</p>
        <p>The bill, which was approved by voice vote in both the Senate and House, was sent to the White House earlier this month. President Bush had 10 days - until today - to either veto or sign the legislation or to let the measure simply pass into law without his signature.</p>
        <p>''It is now the law,'' said a jubilant Peggy Charren who as president of Action for Children's Television has been lobbying since 1970 for improved programming for children.</p>
        <p>The bill effectively becomes law Thursday and broadcasters must begin complying with its provisions within 180 days.</p>
        <p>''The lack of his signature is not a problem for me, but I think it is a missed opportunity for President Bush,'' Ms. Charren said. ''The bill has the support of an incredible coalition of teachers, parents, educators, health professionals and mainstream religious groups. Even the industry that will be regulated by this bill supports it. There was no constituency for a veto.''</p>
        <p>'A Good Compromise'</p>
        <p>The National Association of Broadcasters welcomed today's Presidential decision, calling the bill ''a good compromise.''</p>
        <p>Edward O. Fritts, the organization's president, said, ''The legislation addresses Congressional concerns about overcommercialization in children's TV in cable programs but avoids unnecessary and unconstitutional programming standards.''</p>
        <p>The measure is a break with the deregulation philosophy of the Reagan era. Congress passed a similar bill two years ago, but President Reagan vetoed it.</p>
        <p>The bill imposes a limit of 10 1/2 minutes of television commercials an hour for children's programming on weekends and 12 minutes an hour on weekdays. It also directs the Federal Communications Commission to determine the extent to which each station serves the educational needs of children as a condition of license renewal. The current law vaguely defines a broadcaster's responsibility to serve the public interest.</p>
        <p>The bill also requires the F.C.C. to examine the role of those children's programs that are referred to in the legislation as ''program-length commercials.'' This is a reference to those programs, generally cartoon shows, that have characters that are also popular toys, like the Teen-Age Mutant Ninja Turtles. Such programs have helped increase sales for toy manufacturers and, lawmakers say, pushed much educational programming aside.</p>
        <p>There are currently no Federal regulations limiting advertising on television. Some stations show as much as 11 to 12 minutes of commercials an hour during children's programming on weekends and up to 14 minutes on weekdays. Regular prime-time programming has on average less than 8 minutes of commercials an hour.</p>
        <p>'A Narrow Natural Resource'</p>
        <p>Edward J. Markey, Democrat of Massachusetts and chief sponsor of the House bill, said the President's concerns about the unconstitutionality of the measure were misplaced.</p>
        <p>''The case law in the area of television is quite extensive and clear in differentiating televison from other media,'' Mr. Markey said. ''The spectrum has historically been viewed as a narrow natural resource that requires it be treated differently.''</p>
        <p>But Bruce Fein, a constitutional and communications lawyer who was general counsel at the F.C.C. during the Reagan Administration, called the President's concerns justified.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
