<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thousands of Immigrants Gain In a Ruling on Deportations</title>
    <meta content="Y20IMM$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1018484"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Immigration and Naturalization Service</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Stout, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Frauds and Swindling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980520T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E7DD1539F933A15756C0A96E958260" item-length="484" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thousands of Immigrants Gain In a Ruling on Deportations</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID STOUT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Stout, David</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>US Appeals Court in San Francisco, in decision affecting thousands of immigrants nationwide, rules some forms used by immigration authorities are so hard to understand that they deprive accused of right to hearing before deportation; ruling applies to people who face deportation because of allegedly using false documents (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a decision that affects several thousand immigrants across the country, a Federal appeals court has ruled that some forms used by the immigration authorities are so hard to understand that they deprive the accused of their right to a hearing before deportation.</p>
        <p>The ruling, handed down on Monday by a unanimous three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit, in San Francisco, applies to people who face deportation because they have been accused of using false documents. Typically, such document fraud involves work-authorization papers, lawyers for immigrants say.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a decision that affects several thousand immigrants across the country, a Federal appeals court has ruled that some forms used by the immigration authorities are so hard to understand that they deprive the accused of their right to a hearing before deportation.</p>
        <p>The ruling, handed down on Monday by a unanimous three-judge panel of the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit, in San Francisco, applies to people who face deportation because they have been accused of using false documents. Typically, such document fraud involves work-authorization papers, lawyers for immigrants say.</p>
        <p>If it stands, the Ninth Circuit ruling will apply nationwide, because the court upheld a lower court finding that the suit is a class action.</p>
        <p>Russell Bergeron, a spokesman for the Immigration and Naturalization Service, said tonight that the agency was reviewing the decision and that it would have no immediate comment on a possible appeal.</p>
        <p>The Ninth Circuit ruling, which upheld an October 1996 decision by Judge John C. Coughenour of the Western District of Washington, ordered the immigration agency to clarify its documents and grant hearings to people who might have been deprived of them because they were confused.</p>
        <p>Linton Joaquin, a lawyer for the National Immigration Law Center in Los Angeles, said the ruling applied to some people who had already been deported, although as a practical matter they may be hard to find and in any case may be unable to afford to return to the United States.</p>
        <p>The suit was brought by Mr. Joaquin's organization, the American Civil Liberties Union and individual plaintiffs in 1994, several years after Congress had passed legislation to curb the use of fraudulent documents by immigrants.</p>
        <p>A noncitizen accused of document fraud can be deported in many instances if he does not request an immigration hearing. But Judge Coughenour found, and the Ninth Circuit agreed, that the forms and procedures used to notify a noncitizen in such trouble were not just confusing but ''affirmatively misleading'' -- causing the immigrant to think that the all-important immigration hearing will be scheduled automatically, for instance, when in fact he must ask for one.</p>
        <p>''Indeed, the district court observed that the forms are so obscure and confusing with respect to this point that even some of the I.N.S. agents who administer them are unable to explain adequately,'' said the Ninth Circuit's decision, written by Judge Stephen Reinhardt and joined by Judges Alfred T. Goodwin and Samuel P. King.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
