<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Accident Suspected in Black Sea Crash</title>
    <meta content="06PLAN$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/10/06/international/europe/06PLAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1331244"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ukraine</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Black Sea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Tel Aviv (Israel)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Siberian Airlines</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tavernise, Sabrina</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wines, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Ukraine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel/Tel Aviv</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Missiles and Missile Defense Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Russia</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011006T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE2D9153CF935A35753C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Accident Suspected in Black Sea Crash</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Accident Suspected in Black Sea Crash</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SABRINA TAVERNISE with MICHAEL WINES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tavernise, Sabrina; Wines, Michael</byline>
      <dateline>SOCHI, Russia, Oct. 5</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pentagon strongly believes that long-range antiaircraft missile fired during Ukrainian training exercise struck Siberian Airlines jet before it exploded and crashed into Black Sea; salvage vessels ferry wreckage to Russian port of Sochi; photos; map; US experts say intercepted telemetry data shows single missile 'wildly off course' before explosion, almost certainly SA-5 that can hit targets up to 155 miles away; Ukrainian officials back away from denials, while Russians demand US back up assertion; videotape of crash site taken by rescue worker appears to show metallic tip of long cylinder floating amid debris; regular weekly charter flight from Tel Aviv had been subjected to standard rigorous security checks (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As Black Sea salvage ships ferried the shattered wreckage of a Siberian Airlines jet to Russia's shore, Pentagon officials said they strongly believed that a long-range antiaircraft missile fired during a major Ukrainian training exercise had struck the jet before it exploded and crashed Thursday.</p>
        <p>One Pentagon official said intercepted telemetry data on the path of the missile showed a single missile had gone ''wildly off course'' before the plane exploded.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pentagon officials said they believed that an anti-aircraft missile fired during a Ukrainian training exercise had struck a Russian plane before it exploded and crashed Thursday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As Black Sea salvage ships ferried the shattered wreckage of a Siberian Airlines jet to Russia's shore, Pentagon officials said they strongly believed that a long-range antiaircraft missile fired during a major Ukrainian training exercise had struck the jet before it exploded and crashed Thursday.</p>
        <p>One Pentagon official said intercepted telemetry data on the path of the missile showed a single missile had gone ''wildly off course'' before the plane exploded.</p>
        <p>American military experts said analysis of data showed that the missile, which was fired from the Crimean peninsula in the Ukraine, was almost certainly an SA-5, a 35-foot, single-stage tube that can hit large targets as far away as 155 miles. Military officials in Washington said the missile was at the very end of its range when it struck the airliner.</p>
        <p>Ukrainian officials, who initially denied suggestions that a military missile had accidentally shot down the plane, were gingerly backing off their contention late today. The Ukrainian prime minister said the Pentagon explanation ''had a right to exist.'' He said that his government was not certain about the cause of the crash. Russian officials, meanwhile, demanded that the United states provide its evidence to back up what one Russian official called ''its so-called version,''</p>
        <p>The White House today abandoned its own neutrality and offered a backhanded confirmation of the Pentagon experts' version. ''At this time we still haven't seen anything to indicate that it was terrorism,'' said President Bush's spokesman, Ari Fleischer.</p>
        <p>That statement was bolstered, at least circumstantially, by a videotape of the crash site taken from one of the first rescue workers to arrive on the scene. The tape, taken from a helicopter, appeared to show the metallic tip of a long cylinder, roughly the size and length of an SA-5, bobbing amid the aircraft debris in the Black Sea.</p>
        <p>It was not possible to determine from the videotape, which was shot from at least 150 feet above the water, to say with precision what the object was. Nor was it clear whether any of the six salvage ships trawling the area had picked the object up.</p>
        <p>Further evidence came in the form of the jet's wrecked cockpit, which was recovered today and found riddled with several round, bullet-like holes. The antiaircraft missiles being fired in the Ukrainian exercises destroy their targets by hurling thousands of small steel balls as they approach, a worker at the Russian factory that manufactures one of the missiles said in an interview today.</p>
        <p>Publicly, at least, Russian and Ukrainian officials were not accepting the Pentagon version. Russia's defense minister, Sergei Ivanov, dismissed what he called the ''so-called version'' that the plane was shot down accidentally, and said he had demanded proof from Washington.</p>
        <p>''I sent an urgent inquiry to the American side, to the Pentagon, in which we asked to documentarily confirm or refute this,'' he said. ''First of all, documented data.''</p>
        <p>At the Pentagon today, a defense official said that the United States might well give Russia some evidence of what had apparently happened, but that a formal request for information had not yet arrived.</p>
        <p>The dispute seemed unlikely to rise to the level of a diplomatic incident, especially given the new closeness between the United States and Russia in the campaign against terrorism.</p>
        <p>But is likely to embarrass both the Ukrainians and the Russians, who had been advising Kiev in the largest military exercise in the 10 years since Ukraine became independent, a two-week schedule of antiterrorism and antiaircraft assaults staged at a sprawling training ground on the Crimean peninsula.</p>
        <p>Only this afternoon, after a day of furious denials by senior Ukrainian military and government officials, did President Leonid Kuchma's  prime minister, Anatoly Kinakh, allow that the missile theory ''has a right to exist,'' the Interfax-Ukraine news service reported.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kinakh also was quoted as saying that the government had drawn no conclusions about the cause of the crash. That seemingly was at odds with the military's insistence earlier in the day that a review of missile-launch data had categorically ruled out any fault on the military's part.</p>
        <p>Ukrainian officials said earlier today that they had exhaustively analyzed launch data from 23 missile firings around the time of the crash and had concluded that there was no chance that they had accidentally downed the jet.</p>
        <p>The Siberian Airlines jet, a Tupolev Tu-154 carrying 66 passengers and 12 crew, vanished from radar screens early yesterday afternoon about 90 miles off the Russian coast of the Black Sea. An Armenian aircraft pilot reported seeing the plane explode above him, at 30,000 feet, and plunge seaward.</p>
        <p>Fifty-one of the passengers on the  flight were Jewish émigrés, returning to Siberia on vacation during the Jewish holiday Sukkot. The number of passengers was initially reported as 64, but Siberian Airlines officials corrected that figure to reflect the presence of two newborn babies on the plane.</p>
        <p>The jet, a regular weekly charter from Tel Aviv to Novosibirsk, had been subjected before takeoff to the rigorous security measures that are standard at Tel Aviv's Ben Gurion Airport.</p>
        <p>Still, the very nature of the disaster -- a sudden midair explosion over water; a largely Jewish manifest; continuing Palestinian and Israeli conflict and an international terrorism crisis -- sparked instant speculation that terrorists had struck either to provoke more tension between Israel and Palestinians, or to warn Russia to stay out of the coming campaign against Afghanistan's Taliban.</p>
        <p>Those theories have been all but ruled out, American officials said, in the face of overwhelming intelligence evidence that the disaster was a military accident.</p>
        <p>At the time of the crash, Ukraine's military was one week into a two-week training exercise at Cape Opuk, in eastern Crimea on the Black Sea coast. After completing joint antiterrorism exercises with Russian forces, Ukraine's land, sea and air forces were firing missiles at airborne drones drifting some 12 to 25 miles off the coast, over the Black Sea.</p>
        <p>The chief spokesman for the Ukrainian Navy, Nikolai Savchenko, said on Thursday that SA-12 and SA-5 missiles, the NATO designations for Russian missiles used both to down aircraft and intercept incoming rockets, had been fired that day.</p>
        <p>The radar-guided missiles -- similar to the Patriot used by the United States during the Persian Gulf war -- are among the most advanced in the Russian antiaircraft arsenal.</p>
        <p>Ukrainian officials confirmed that a zone of exclusion had been established around the exercise site, and they said the Siberian jet had verified that it was outside the zone before venturing further along its flight path.</p>
        <p>American military officials said today they had no clear idea what had gone wrong on Thursday. But they said it appeared that an SA-5 missile had simply missed its drone and continued flying, locking its radar onto the next large radar target it detected, the Siberian airliner.</p>
        <p>Ukrainian and Russian officials said that the missiles used on Thursday were equipped with devices designed to self-destruct the missiles should they miss their initial targets.</p>
        <p>But at St. Petersburg's Severny Zavod factory, where SA-12 missiles are manufactured, an official who refused to be named said in an interview today that the missiles' radar  can shift to a new target if its radar signal is strong enough.</p>
        <p>Because the missiles are designed to spray a target with shrapnel instead of ramming it and exploding, he said, it is not unusual for the body of a missile to survive its mission.</p>
        <p>''It's quite possible to find a piece or pieces of a missile after the hit. Fuel tanks, instrumentation, that sort of thing can be found,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In an interview today, a Sochi rescue worker who was among the first on the scene -- a long and narrow stream of floating debris -- said his crew was mystified by a long metal object floating vertically in the water, which he displayed on videotape.</p>
        <p>''This remained the biggest mystery for us,'' said Nikolai Kargin, the deputy head of the rescue services in Sochi. ''It was a cylinder floating like a tree trunk, a long floating object that extended about 10 meters under the water. It had a shiny top. At first we thought it was a buoy, but what buoy would be here.''</p>
        <p>An SA-5 is 10.7 meters, or about 36 feet long, according to a Russian weapons directory.</p>
        <p>Russian television later showed debris from the aircraft being unloaded in Sochi which were perforated with what appeared to be several bullet-sized holes.</p>
        <p>Whether they were consistent with the steel shrapnel hurled by an approaching missile was not known. At a news conference here, the chairman of the Kremlin security council. Vladimir Rushailo, said it would be premature to speculate on what caused them.</p>
        <p>As the weather worsened tonight with the wind picking up, officials held out little hope of finding the black boxes recording the aircraft's cockpit conversation and flight data.</p>
        <p>The boxes sank 6,600 feet into the sea, a depth that will make salvage efforts difficult if not impossible. Russia today asked Washington and Israel for help in locating and recovering the recorders.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
