<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="438099"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910418T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DC1539F93BA25757C0A967958260" item-length="563" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Markets</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average closed above 3,000 for the first time, as investors carried the bull market past another milestone. Floyd Norris: Market Place.  [ Page D1. ]  Other major share indexes also set records for the second consecutive day.  [ D10. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Markets</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average closed above 3,000 for the first time, as investors carried the bull market past another milestone. Floyd Norris: Market Place.  [ Page D1. ]  Other major share indexes also set records for the second consecutive day.  [ D10. ]</p>
        <p>Corporate bond prices soared as investors sought higher yields than those available from Treasury issues.  [ D16. ]</p>
        <p>Prices for copper, silver, platinum and palladium rose strongly on the futures markets.  [ D17. ]  The dollar closed higher.  [ D17. ] The Economy</p>
        <p>The Supreme Court ruled that savings and loans can create paper losses for income tax purposes by swapping low-value mortgages.  [ D1. ]  The Court also ruled that international airline passengers cannot recover damages for mental anguish.  [ B12. ]</p>
        <p>President Bush signed legislation early this morning to end the national railroad strike.  [ B8. ]</p>
        <p>The Financial Accounting Standards Board is embroiled in an unusual skirmish over an appointment.  [ D6. ] Companies</p>
        <p>Strong drug sales at Bristol-Myers Squibb and Warner-Lambert led to record growth in profits in the first quarter.  [ D1. ]  Bristol-Myers asked doctors to refrain for now from using a breast implant linked to cancer in animals.  [ B13. ]</p>
        <p>Robert Maxwell will sell up to 49 percent of the Mirror Group to the public. The Daily News may be included later.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Rich's, a landmark in downtown Atlanta, will close the huge store on July 13 after five years of losses.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>A bankruptcy court decision that would have let CNBC, buy its arch rival, Financial News Network was overturned.  [ D19. ]</p>
        <p>General Dynamics reported that operating earnings fell 9 percent, with sharply lower sales of military aircraft.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Coca-Cola reported a 13.2 percent earnings increase in the first quarter, to a record $320.9 million.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>The parent company of American Airlines lost $195.6 million in the first quarter.  [ D8. ]</p>
        <p>Philip Morris's profit rose 21.5 percent for the first quarter. American Brands' profit rose 10.9 percent for the period.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>Harcourt Brace bondholders rejected an increased bid by General Cinema and the two companies broke off merger talks.  [ D19. ]</p>
        <p>The owners of Kermit the Frog accused Disney of "outright theft" of characters like Kermit and Miss Piggy.  [ D19. ]</p>
        <p>Michelin will cut at least 16,000 jobs from its worldwide work force by the end of next year.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>A.T.&amp; T. had a modest gain in net income, while GTE reported a sharp decline in earnings.  [ D5. ]</p>
        <p>NCNB reported a decline of 8.4 percent in first-quarter profit because of problems with bad loans.  [ D21. ] International</p>
        <p>The chairman of the Export-Import Bank said Reagan and Bush had not exerted pressure on export guarantees for Iraq.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Mexico assured California smog authorities that American companies would notbe able to escape pollution controls.  [ A20. ]</p>
        <p>A Bush Administration interagency policy group recommended retaliation against Tokyo over public works construction.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Egypt may not get the level of aid it was promised from the rich Arab gulf states.  [ D6. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>The E.P.A. is expected to expand protection for some lenders. Stephen Labaton: Business and the Law.  [ D2. ]</p>
        <p>A company has applied the technology of video conferences to focus groups. Kim Foltz: Advertising.  [ D19. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
