<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No More 'Probable': Hampton Is a Certainty</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="649571"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK GIANTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEXTON, JOE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HAMPTON, RODNEY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/New York Giants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDB1731F930A25752C1A965958260" item-length="844" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No More 'Probable': Hampton Is a Certainty</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SEXTON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SEXTON, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>EAST RUTHERFORD, N.J., Nov. 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rodney Hampton's burden for the first third of the season was great. He shouldered dozens of rushes a game, led the No. 1 ground game in the National Football League and lifted the Giants to an unbeaten record.</p>
        <p>The burden of late has amounted to carrying himself from trainer's room to surgeon's table to empty Sunday afternoons on the sidelines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rodney Hampton's burden for the first third of the season was great. He shouldered dozens of rushes a game, led the No. 1 ground game in the National Football League and lifted the Giants to an unbeaten record.</p>
        <p>The burden of late has amounted to carrying himself from trainer's room to surgeon's table to empty Sunday afternoons on the sidelines.</p>
        <p>Now, with the season perhaps about to slip away from the Giants, Hampton is again being handed the football and being asked to run as far as he can. Answers Will Probably Come Quickly</p>
        <p>"Games with the Redskins tend to be run-it-up, pound-it-out games," said Hampton, referring to Sunday's contest at Giants Stadium. "I suppose it will be again."</p>
        <p>Questions about Hampton and the Giants will most likely be answered quickly and with violence. Hampton, who has missed the last five games with a troubled knee and ankle, will start. He could last a series or he could decide as important a game as the 5-3 Giants have played this season.</p>
        <p>"It's a big test to see where I stand," said Hampton.</p>
        <p>Hampton, who made the Pro Bowl in 1992 and then broke the bank with his three-year, $6.9 million contract in the off season, offered the statement with no sense of double meaning. He was talking about his health. The backdrop to the words was stark.  Lewis Tillman, Hampton's replacement, has been thoroughly effective.  A Big-Play Performer</p>
        <p>After all, four of the first six entries in the Giants Big Plays in 1993 list Tillman as the performer.</p>
        <p>"A plus situation," Hampton said of Tillman's contributions and continuing presence.</p>
        <p>The Giants, and perhaps Hampton, have little room for any more minuses. It seems Coach Dan Reeves does not care for reputation or popularity when it comes to handing the football to people who could win games for him.</p>
        <p>"I haven't got into that bunker mentality yet, but I'm close," Reeves said after overseeing practice this morning. "We've got to use everybody." Dancing Over the Redskins</p>
        <p>Hampton admits he doesn't have all of himself to offer. "I'm not 100 percent," said Hampton. "But I can do some things. I'm ready to rock and roll."</p>
        <p>More than one club has danced all over the 2-6 Redskins this season. The Giants racked up 415 total yards as Tillman waltzed for 104 in a 41-7 mauling on Oct. 10. The Eagles busted out for 440 yards. Even the Indianapolis Colts, in becoming the first club to lose to Washington in more than a month, rolled up 405 last Sunday.</p>
        <p>"There are certain things we are going to do," Reeves said of his game plan involving Hampton and Tillman. "If Rodney shows he can do more, he may be given it to do."</p>
        <p>There was nothing Hampton wasn't willing or able to do at the start of the season. He opened the season with 76 yards against the Bears and then burst for 134 yards in Game 2 against the Buccaneers. He shook loose for another 134 the following week against the Rams, the first time he had put together consecutive games beyond 100 yards. The chance to become the first back in the history of the franchise to rush for 1,000 or more yards in three straight seasons looked like a lock. A Hit Still Lingers</p>
        <p>The fall from the top of the N.F.L.'s statistical charts -- Hampton led the league in rushes and was second only to Barry Sanders in yardage -- was set in motion, and then Hampton ran into Bruce Smith in a game against the Bills on Oct. 3. More than a month later, the unpleasantness of that hit is too discouraging for Hampton to recall.</p>
        <p>"I don't want to ever think about it," Hampton said.</p>
        <p>After arthroscopic surgery to fix the knee, an ankle sabotaged subsequent starts. He roamed a full assortment of injury designations, from doubtful to probable to deactivated.  Hampton was in uniform and within an hour of playing against the Cowboys last Sunday when a decision was reached not to endanger the ankle on the artificial turf.</p>
        <p>"I thought I could have played," Hampton said. "But I don't think I'd have been effective."</p>
        <p>Hampton, effective enough in practice today despite a huge wrap on his ankle that looked like a homemade cast, will not be ordered anywhere but into the game and then into the line on Sunday. What happens amid all the force that collides thereafter could begin to dictate the fate of the Giants' season.  EXTRA POINTS</p>
        <p>Cornerback MARK COLLINS, who suffered what appeared to be a major back injury Sunday, will play without fear or doubt. "I'm not stupid," said Collins. "If it was an injury that could become worse by playing, I wouldn't do it. But it's time to suck it up and do what has to be done." . . . Linebacker CARLTON BAILEY argued Friday that the overall records of the Giants and Redskins were no more important than the recent records. "We've lost two straight, and so you can't take any team lightly. The Jets we were told were supposed to be a cakewalk. The Redskins play with a lot of emotion, a lot of heart, a lot of tradition." . . . DAN REEVES said LAWRENCE TAYLOR had declared himself more fit than he had felt all season. He will start Sunday.</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
