<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Coleman and Hinson Finally Join Nets' Camp</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="396732"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY NETS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">COLEMAN, DERRICK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HINSON, ROY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CURRY, JACK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New Jersey Nets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DB1138F933A05753C1A966958260" item-length="704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Coleman and Hinson Finally Join Nets' Camp</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JACK CURRY, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CURRY, JACK</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON, N.J., Oct. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The first drill at the Nets' training camp here today was simple enough. The players had to shuffle from one baseline to halfcourt of Jadwin Gym in a defensive stance. Most of them had done it dozens of times; they knew when to shuffle and when to turn.</p>
        <p>Not Derrick Coleman. He shuffled to the left when he should have been shuffling to the right, and he stopped shuffling about halfway through the drill. It was a minor transgression, and certainly not one that is going to hamper Coleman's rookie season, but it was noticeable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The first drill at the Nets' training camp here today was simple enough. The players had to shuffle from one baseline to halfcourt of Jadwin Gym in a defensive stance. Most of them had done it dozens of times; they knew when to shuffle and when to turn.</p>
        <p>Not Derrick Coleman. He shuffled to the left when he should have been shuffling to the right, and he stopped shuffling about halfway through the drill. It was a minor transgression, and certainly not one that is going to hamper Coleman's rookie season, but it was noticeable.</p>
        <p>Coleman missed the first three weeks of training camp before finally signing a five-year, $15 million contract Sunday, and he was rusty and winded during his first National Basketball Association practice. Coach Bill Fitch said Coleman would not start in the Nets' season opener against Indiana on Friday, and would see only spot duty because he was too far behind his teammates.</p>
        <p>"If I blow my stack, it's because he's not as good as he is supposed to be," Fitch said. "I have to have patience with him because there is nothing I can do about it." Competitive Session</p>
        <p>Other events unfolded today to make the practice one of the most competitive and intriguing of the season. Roy Hinson, the forgotten power forward who is recovering from serious knee surgery, also made his first appearance at training camp and looked smooth. And Sam Bowie looked like a 7-foot-1-inch couch potato as he slouched in a chair and did not practice for the fourth day in a row.</p>
        <p>Bowie missed the Nets' last three preseason games with a sore Achilles' tendon in his left leg and Fitch said the starting center was doubtful for the first game of the season.</p>
        <p>"He may not make the opening call," said Fitch, as he delivered a bombshell in a mild manner. "That's something to think about."</p>
        <p>The news took Bowie by surprise. Because he has a history of leg injuries, Bowie said, the Nets were being "super cautious" with him. He disagreed with the coach and said he anticipated playing on Friday.</p>
        <p>"I was anxious to play and participate today, but the medical staff told me not to," Bowie said. "I don't foresee any problem playing on Friday. The coach is entitled to say that because I haven't practiced in three or four days. I'm ready to play and I want them to play me, not to use me sparingly." 'Running Freely'</p>
        <p>Hinson, who said he felt shunned when the Nets did not invite him to training camp until today, impressed Fitch. Sporting a black-and-red brace on his right knee, Hinson raced up and down the court without pain and had a few memorable dunks. He said he wants to be back by December.</p>
        <p>"The fact that he is running freely is a positive," Fitch said. "He's out here so we can get some answers about him."</p>
        <p>"I feel I'll be ready," said Hinson. "Whether or not I'll be out there is a different story. That's someone else's decision. I want to play basketball, maybe even more than some of these rookies."</p>
        <p>One of those rookies is Coleman, who happens to play the same position as Hinson. Bowie said Coleman looked "lost" at practice because he did not know all of the plays. Coleman may be carrying some extra weight on his 6-10 frame. He is listed in the Nets' preseason guide at 235 pounds, but Bowie said the rookie weighed in at 250 on Sunday night.</p>
        <p>Jack Haley, who is the starting power forward until the $15 million man is ready, jostled with Coleman for every spare inch of position underneath the basket today. When he was not offering Coleman a steady diet of elbows, Haley tugged on the rookie's jersey and directed him to specific spots on the floor.</p>
        <p>"I just think we are all competitors and we were out there being competitive," Coleman said. "It's definitely something I expected. I wasn't nervous at all. This is something I like to do." Three Are Released</p>
        <p>The Nets cut the guard Doug Lee, the forward Dan Godfread and the center Danny O'Sullivan Monday and they have 14 players remaining on their roster. Hinson is not included on the roster because he will start the season on injured reserve. Two more players must be cut and they should come from among the swingman Pete Myers, the forwards Derrick Gervin and Anthony Mason and the guard Kurk Lee.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
