<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kyoto Journal; Dreaming City of Temples Awakes to Bulldozers</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="396739"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GEOGRAPHIC PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NYTRAVEL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDDHISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAND USE POLICIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">KYOTO (JAPAN)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">STERNGOLD, JAMES</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ASANO, ZENYO</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan/Kyoto</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buddhism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Land Use Policies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D7173BF933A05753C1A966958260" item-length="1001" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kyoto Journal; Dreaming City of Temples Awakes to Bulldozers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES STERNGOLD, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STERNGOLD, JAMES</byline>
      <dateline>KYOTO, Japan</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Zenyu Asano led the way up the cramped stairway of the five-tiered Yasaka Pagoda. The affable Zen Buddhist priest was discussing the unusual carvings on its altar, but when he reached the ledge beneath the structure's wing-like roof and took in the view of the city that is Japan's cultural soul, he turned to a more consuming matter: real estate development.</p>
        <p>His face bright beneath the stubbled dome of his shaven head, Mr. Asano pointed out a vacant sliver of land just below. Only by mobilizing neighborhood opposition, he said, was he able to halt a plan to put up a tall luxury apartment building there, a threat to the pagoda's five-century-long vigil as a spiritual beacon visible from much of the city.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Zenyu Asano led the way up the cramped stairway of the five-tiered Yasaka Pagoda. The affable Zen Buddhist priest was discussing the unusual carvings on its altar, but when he reached the ledge beneath the structure's wing-like roof and took in the view of the city that is Japan's cultural soul, he turned to a more consuming matter: real estate development.</p>
        <p>His face bright beneath the stubbled dome of his shaven head, Mr. Asano pointed out a vacant sliver of land just below. Only by mobilizing neighborhood opposition, he said, was he able to halt a plan to put up a tall luxury apartment building there, a threat to the pagoda's five-century-long vigil as a spiritual beacon visible from much of the city.</p>
        <p>"This kind of development is the worst threat we have faced, and it is happening all over," Mr. Asano said as he showed how the old tiled roofs and quaint stone-paved lanes of the city, spared by American bombers in World War II, were now succumbing to steel cranes and apartment blocks. "People come to Kyoto for peace of mind, not a concrete jungle."</p>
        <p>Japan's soaring property prices have become a major political issue by driving a wedge between the haves and have-nots. But some now worry more about the damage the new development is doing to the country's cherished cultural fabric as it alters the countryside and skylines. Two Worlds Clash</p>
        <p>Nowhere is that conflict felt more acutely than in Kyoto, the imperial capital for a thousand years and home to more than 1,600 temples and some of the most exquisite gardens in Japan, if not the world.</p>
        <p>The emotional debate over development here highlights a growing clash in many aspects of contemporary Japanese life between the classless, tradition-bound nation that many Japanese still imagine their country to be, and the real one being shaped by vast new wealth, banks, golf courses, developers and bulldozers.</p>
        <p>Kyoto's surging land prices and quickening pace of development are largely a spillover from Tokyo, where values began rocketing upward a decade ago, in large measure a reaction to Government policies holding interest rates and property taxes down as a spur to industry.</p>
        <p>Hungry for cheaper areas to build, the developers began shifting their interest first to the suburbs of Tokyo, then Osaka, Nagoya and Kyoto, which lies about 300 miles west of the capital. Commercial land prices here have shot up 360 percent in the last four years, while residential land prices have jumped 280 percent as developers snapped up parcels for their projects.</p>
        <p>"When a few tall buildings go up, it blocks the sunshine and changes the character of a neighborhood, so other people decide to leave, bringing in more developers," said Shinya Katagata, a professor of city planning at Kyoto University. "It's sort of a chain reaction."</p>
        <p>Uzo Nishiyama, a famous architecture historian, conceded that some Japanese regard the city's new skyline positively as an emblem of prosperity. But he said this was an illusion, since the proliferation of taller buildings was spoiling the charm that is often part of the sales pitch developers use. 40 Million Visitors</p>
        <p>He and others described this as one reason behind a slow decline in Kyoto's population. It has lost 13,000 residents in the last five years, leaving its population at 1.466 million. About 60 percent of the city's income comes from the nearly 40 million visitors each year, most of them Japanese.</p>
        <p>Senichi Oyama, general manager of the city's urban planning department, said the city had tried, through a complex zoning system introduced two years ago, to balance the need for more development to strengthen and diversify the economy with the desire to perserve Kyoto's unique character.</p>
        <p>Opponents complained that the new development was helping drive Kyoto residents away, and Mr. Oyama partly agreed. He conceded that crowding and the deterioration of the traditional qualities of life were forcing many to move to the suburbs or farther. Much of the new development is being done by out-of-town companies, and often the buyers are speculators who leave apartments vacant.</p>
        <p>During a stroll through several neighborhoods, Mayumi Okada, an anti-development campaigner, stopped at a famous old pickle shop to show how the system had left such traditional wooden structures surrounded by concrete.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the zoning guaranteed unobstructed views for taller structures built on the edge of the restricted districts. The new buildings often blocked street-level vistas of pagodas or mountains, a particular problem since the views of distant mountains are often integral elements of the designs of some of the temple gardens. Temple Buys Land</p>
        <p>Even the mountains have become part of the dispute, with citizens' groups having fought to block a golf course development on historic Daimonji mountain. Mount Hiei, considered a holy site, is already home to a synthetic ski slope and is topped with a big circular restaurant called the Panorama.</p>
        <p>In one of the most widely publicized cases, the Kiyomizu Temple, perched on a wooded hillside, was forced to acquire an adjacent piece of property for one billion yen, or about $8 million, to halt construction of a big new structure.</p>
        <p>"I am not completely opposed to development," Shinko Onishi, the temple's secretary general, said as he stood before a spectacular backdrop of Kyoto at the temple's famous west gate. "I ride the Shinkansen all the time, so I enjoy the benefits of modern developments. But it's not necessary for every city to look like Tokyo."</p>
        <p>City officials find themselves searching for a shrinking middle ground between past and future, history and economics.</p>
        <p>"It's wrong to consider Kyoto as a frozen museum," said Mr. Oyama of the urban planning department. "It is not just a place for people to come and look at. Kyoto is a historical city with a special tradition, but on the other hand it is a big city that must prosper and grow."</p>
        <p>"We cannot," he added, "permit either side to lose."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
