<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>About New York;Life's Act II, Wherein Angelo Sings</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="852344"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THEATER</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW SCHOOL FOR SOCIAL RESEARCH</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ACTORS STUDIO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GONZALEZ, DAVID</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRUGLIO, ANGELO</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">ABOUT NEW YORK (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9905E2DB1039F931A15756C0A960958260" item-length="864" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>About New York;Life's Act II, Wherein Angelo Sings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID GONZALEZ</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GONZALEZ, DAVID</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANGELO TRUGLIO daydreamed of being an actor when he was growing up in Canarsie. But the closest he came to the stage as an adult was at a grammar school auditorium in Patchogue, L.I., where he presided as principal.</p>
        <p>Determined in his 50's to prove that American lives do have second acts, he quit his day job last year, moved to New York City and enrolled in a master's degree acting program offered by the New School and the Actors Studio. As a student of the Method, he is prone to introspection as he mulls over a character's passions and desires in search of motivation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANGELO TRUGLIO daydreamed of being an actor when he was growing up in Canarsie. But the closest he came to the stage as an adult was at a grammar school auditorium in Patchogue, L.I., where he presided as principal.</p>
        <p>Determined in his 50's to prove that American lives do have second acts, he quit his day job last year, moved to New York City and enrolled in a master's degree acting program offered by the New School and the Actors Studio. As a student of the Method, he is prone to introspection as he mulls over a character's passions and desires in search of motivation.</p>
        <p>His wife, Joan, a psychotherapist, wonders about his motivation, too.</p>
        <p>"I'm interested in poetry, education and drama, and she asks me why couldn't  I get interested in the stock market," said Mr. Truglio, whose salt-and-pepper beard lends him the tweedy and familiar air of a whats's-his-name character actor. "My wife to this day says to me, 'Are you crazy?' "</p>
        <p>Let's hope it's not her professional opinion.</p>
        <p>So what muse led him to a second career that has left aspiring actors half his age with nothing to show but a string of restaurant gigs and a pocketful of  tips?</p>
        <p>"You take an Italian kid from Brooklyn and make a leap like this and I say to myself, 'Angelo, is this you?' " he said. "Coming from an Italian Catholic background, to consider the art world would have been tantamount to driving my mother crazy. But I feel there is something inside me that I need to share."</p>
        <p>THE directors of the master's program at the New School evidently agreed and  admitted him into a school that is tougher to get into than Harvard College. Already in its second year, the program received 2,000 applications for next year's class of 80 students.</p>
        <p>The system first developed by Konstantin Stanislavsky 99 years ago was honed  into the Method at the Actors Studio, which is located in an impressive, if not  mysterious, building in Hell's Kitchen. It is a place of legend and rumor, whose history has intersected with the likes of Marlon Brando, Marilyn Monroe and Al Pacino, all among the studio's 800 life members.</p>
        <p>The New School program is the first time in the Actors Studio's 49 years that it has offered a formal, academic curriculum.</p>
        <p>"The Studio never opened its doors and showed its wares," said James Lipton,  the school's dean. "It was a place where Studio members would go to be brave and be among like-minded colleagues."</p>
        <p>MEMBERS of the Actors Studio teach the three-year course of instruction, which includes classes in acting technique, voice and theater history, before the students branch off to specialize in acting, directing or writing. They are allowed to drop in on the Actors Studio and watch professionals rehearse, as well as take part in the banter during "Inside the Actors Studio," a program on  the Bravo cable network that features interviews with members like Martin Landau.</p>
        <p>Mr. Truglio learned about the school while watching the show, though to be honest, he was only faintly aware of the Studio's illustrious past.</p>
        <p>"It's not a fly-by-night organization, this school or the Actors Studio," Mr. Truglio said. "I had no experience in acting at all, but there was a showman's flair in me. I always liked teaching more than being an administrator. I liked being with the kids, in order to be on stage."</p>
        <p>But before he could take to the stage, he had to unlearn some old teacher's habits. Voice lessons helped him learn the difference between shouting and projecting one's lines from the stage. He learned to relax his stride and loosen his shoulders (turns out there's an art to that, too). His acting classes have taught him to marshal his senses in the service of his craft, learning to become aware of the feel and sound of a situation, as well as discovering how to chart  an actor's emotional landscape.</p>
        <p>"You have to go back and use feelings, needs, desires and experiences in your background to use in your work," he said. "You walk around with a knot in your stomach. You have to work it through. It's not like reading a chapter in a book  and talking about it."</p>
        <p>The chapters come from his life. Perhaps he can tap into an older actor's feelings of fear that there might not be too many roles waiting for him. Or how  about what it feels like to have spent most of your life doing everything that was expected of you but not what you expected of yourself?</p>
        <p>"A lot of changes have to be made," he said. "I want to sing my song. Before  I die, I want to sing my song."</p>
        <p>Angelo, it's you.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
