<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.O.P. Bill Would Extend Pensions in Small Business</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="852447"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PENSIONS AND RETIREMENT PLANS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SMALL BUSINESS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW ANDLEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSTON, DAVID CAY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Small Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pensions and Retirement Plans</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retirement</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DA1039F931A15756C0A960958260" item-length="841" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.O.P. Bill Would Extend Pensions in Small Business</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID CAY JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSTON, DAVID CAY</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>House Republicans plan to pass legislation on Wednesday that would make it easier for small businesses to offer retirement savings plans for their 36 million workers. And in a break from decades of pension policy, the bill would let owners reap tax benefits for themselves even if their workers do not participate.</p>
        <p>The retirement provisions are part of a $7.5 billion bill filled with changes sought by owners of small businesses to simplify tax, pension and other rules that bedevil companies with fewer than 100 workers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>House Republicans plan to pass legislation on Wednesday that would make it easier for small businesses to offer retirement savings plans for their 36 million workers. And in a break from decades of pension policy, the bill would let owners reap tax benefits for themselves even if their workers do not participate.</p>
        <p>The retirement provisions are part of a $7.5 billion bill filled with changes sought by owners of small businesses to simplify tax, pension and other rules that bedevil companies with fewer than 100 workers.</p>
        <p>For example, over seven years the bill would increase to $25,000 from $17,500 the value of equipment purchases that can be deducted immediately, instead of being depreciated over several years. The bill would also phase out tax breaks for companies that build factories in Puerto Rico and reinvest the profits on the island, using the increased revenues to offset the small business tax breaks.</p>
        <p>These provisions will provide political cover for Republicans who oppose another aspect of the bill, increasing the minimum wage by 90 cents an hour over two years, to $5.15. Polls have shown that raising the minimum wage is widely popular despite concerns expressed by small-business owners and many economists  that it would cost jobs.</p>
        <p>Republicans, citing a rising public concern about retirement income and the safety of nest eggs, sought to focus attention today on changes to pension law.</p>
        <p>Representative Bill Archer, the Texas Republican who is chairman of the House Ways and Means Committee, said the proposals would help workers in small business by "making it easier to get a secure pension and by providing increased security for existing retirement accounts." And he said all 120 million working  Americans stood to benefit from one or more of the two dozen pension changes in  the bill.</p>
        <p>Labor Secretary Robert B. Reich called the bill "a watered down version of what President Clinton has already proposed." And he noted that it did not require accountants or other professionals who find indications that retirement  savings are being embezzled to report their suspicions to the Government.</p>
        <p>But the centerpiece of the bill is what the Republicans call a Simple pension plan for small businesses, which is short for "savings incentive match plan for  employees."</p>
        <p>Companies with fewer than 100 workers at any time during a year could create  a sort of mini-401(k) plan in which workers could save up to $6,000, compared with $9,500 under existing 401(k) plans.</p>
        <p>Existing 401(k)'s require expensive and complex tests comparing the contributions of highly paid and low-wage workers to insure that tax benefits do not flow only to the highly paid. In Simple plans, these tests would not be necessary if the employer either deposited 2 percent of each employee's pay into the employee's account or matched dollar-for-dollar the first 3 percent that employees saved. Employers who choose the matching option could reduce the match in two of every five years if they fell on hard times.</p>
        <p>Under the bill, the owner of a small business could save $6,000 on tax-deferred basis and match the savings with another $6,000, even if none of his or her employees participated in the Simple plan.</p>
        <p>A critic of existing pension laws, Karen Ferguson, co-author of "The Pension  Book," called the bill "a radical departure from decades of pension policy requiring that lower-paid workers get benefits as a condition of owners and managers' getting tax breaks."</p>
        <p>"This is shortsighted, crazy and foodhardy," she said.</p>
        <p>Republican staff members said they were confident that millions of workers, even those earning modest wages, would leap at the chance to save money on a tax-advantaged basis for retirement, especially when their money would be matched by their employers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Reich noted that the President's proposal would require small- business owners to contribute at least 1 percent of their workers' wages to a retirement  savings plan before their own contributions could be tax-deferred.</p>
        <p>Another provision of the bill would allow the one in six workers who are employed by nonprofit organizations to have 401(k) accounts. Currently, workers  at nonprofit organizations are limited to less generous 403(b) plans.</p>
        <p>The bill would also protect the assets of state and local government pension  plans from creditors, putting them on the same footing as business and nonprofit pension plans. This provision was added in response to the bankruptcy filing by  Orange County, Calif., which focused attention on the disparate treatment of government and business plans.</p>
        <p>The bill would also protect truck drivers, carpenters and others who participate in pension plans paid for by groups of employers by making retirement benefits mandatory after five years, the same as the law requires of  plans provided by a single employer.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
