<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>POWER IS FLEETING, BAKER REFLECTS</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="322711"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKER, JAMES A 3D (SEC)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D71631F931A35751C0A966958260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>POWER IS FLEETING, BAKER REFLECTS</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Feb. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In an unusual public reflection on religious faith, Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d said today that after nine years at the center of power in Washington, he has discovered that ''power doesn't really bring the fulfillment that many think it does.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In an unusual public reflection on religious faith, Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d said today that after nine years at the center of power in Washington, he has discovered that ''power doesn't really bring the fulfillment that many think it does.''</p>
        <p>In an unusual public reflection on religious faith, Secretary of State James A. Baker 3d said today that after nine years at the center of power in Washington, he has discovered that ''power doesn't really bring the fulfillment that many think it does.''</p>
        <p>Long considered one of the most enthusiastic and adroit power brokers in Washington, Mr. Baker told 3,000 Government officials (including President Bush), members of Congress and foreign diplomats at the annual National Prayer Breakfast: ''Inner security and true, real fulfillment comes by faith. It doesn't come by wielding power in a town where power is king.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker, who was White House chief of staff and Treasury Secretary throughout the Reagan Administration, rarely reveals any emotion in public, let alone what he described as deep inner feelings. His aides said his speech was meant not to proselytize but to describe the importance of friendship and spiritual faith in his own life.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, his words and the passion with which he spoke them seemed to surprise some at the gathering. As Mr. Baker put it, ''For me, to discuss a personal journey of faith is a new experience.''</p>
        <p>Power 'Can Be Addictive'</p>
        <p>As campaign manager for both Ronald Reagan and Mr. Bush, Mr. Baker has earned a reputation as a highly efficient political operator who never hesitated to take the gloves off. Both campaigns were noted for their success in bringing fundamentalist and evangelical Christians into the Republican column, but Mr. Baker was not regarded as close to either group. His wife, Susan, has been widely involved in religious activities with the wives of other high officials.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker began by observing: ''Power, of course, can be intoxicating. It can be addictive, and few doubt that power tends to corrupt and absolute power corrupts absolutely. Over these last nine years, I have had opportunities to participate in the exercise of more power than I ever would have imagined. I have felt the weight of responsibility that that brings, and I have to admit to you as well that I have felt the temptations that are attendant to it.''</p>
        <p>He said he once thought a successful professional never admitted to hurt or problems. But that changed several years ago, he went on, when he came up against a ''personal problem.'' Mr. Baker did not describe the problem, but said his wife helped him pray and see that ''I really needed to stop trying to play God and turn the matter over to Him.''</p>
        <p>Mrs. Baker has been reported to have had an active interest in religion and the Bible since the days when her first marriage was falling apart.</p>
        <p>''Without this kind of partnership,'' the Secretary said, ''I'm convinced I would never have resolved the problem.''</p>
        <p>When Mr. Baker was facing his problem, a group of devout Christians in the Reagan Administration regularly prayed for him and his wife, according to one member of the group.</p>
        <p>Some evangelical Christians in the audience at the Washington Hilton said they took Mr. Baker's speech as something of a confession of faith, because of his openness about his personal life and feelings. The audience gave him a standing ovation after he finished his address, and several were moved to tears.</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker, an Episcopalian who has long attended church regularly, said he gains strength from prayer and from meetings ''for fellowship'' every Wednesday with a small group of ''very normal guys who just happen to hold positions of power and influence in Washington.'' He said the group, whose members he has always declined to identify, is made of men from both political parties and several different religious traditions.</p>
        <p>The Secretary of State emphasized the importance of friendship and spoke emotionally of how Mr. Bush and his wife, Barbara, helped him get through the painful period before and after the death of his first wife, Mary, of cancer in 1969.</p>
        <p>He also described his sense of the fleeting nature of power, which he said was driven home to him one day when he was riding to his job as chief of staff in his sleek black limousine. Near the White House he noticed a man walking down the street alone.</p>
        <p>''He was someone many of you would have recognized - a chief of staff in a previous Administration,'' said Mr. Baker. ''There he was, alone - no reporters, no security, no adoring public, no trappings of power - just one solitary man alone with his thoughts. That mental picture continually serves to remind me of the impermanence of power and place. That man had it all, but only for a time. That memory puts my own life in perspective.''</p>
        <p>The Secretary said he ''found early on that having a position of power really doesn't bring the fulfillment that many people think it does.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
