<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Corrections Town and Gown Clash Over Zoning</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Page 4, Column" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="322681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ZONING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">PRINCETON (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">PRINCETON UNIVERSITY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LYALL, SARAH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey/Princeton</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Zoning</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDC113EF931A35751C0A966958260" item-length="641140" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Corrections Town and Gown Clash Over Zoning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LYALL, SARAH</byline>
      <dateline>PRINCETON, N.J.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: An article on Feb. 2 about a zoning conflict between Princeton, N.J., and Princeton University referred incorrectly to the university's objections to the borough's zoning procedures. The university does not oppose submitting its plans to a public hearing and a vote by the Regional Planning Board of Princeton.  LEAD: The people of Murray Place are fond of their neighbor Princeton University, with its fine buildings and its feeling of quiet intellectual excitement.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: An article on Feb. 2 about a zoning conflict between Princeton, N.J., and Princeton University referred incorrectly to the university's objections to the borough's zoning procedures. The university does not oppose submitting its plans to a public hearing and a vote by the Regional Planning Board of Princeton.  LEAD: The people of Murray Place are fond of their neighbor Princeton University, with its fine buildings and its feeling of quiet intellectual excitement.</p>
        <p>An article on Feb. 2 about a zoning conflict between Princeton, N.J., and Princeton University referred incorrectly to the university's objections to the borough's zoning procedures. The university does not oppose submitting its plans to a public hearing and a vote by the Regional Planning Board of Princeton. It does object to consulting with the board before submitting plans.</p>
        <p>The people of Murray Place are fond of their neighbor Princeton University, with its fine buildings and its feeling of quiet intellectual excitement.</p>
        <p>But on their street, which borders the engineering quadrangle, they fear that if the university's expansion is not checked, their neighborhood will turn into a huge center of brick and steel laboratories spewing fumes and surrounded by endlessly crawling traffic.</p>
        <p>The neighbors' concerns about the university, which gives this borough its center and, in many ways, its soul, is being expressed on a larger scale as planners consider a proposal to impose stricter zoning on the quadrangle area, which also abuts the commercial area along Nassau Street, and on two other schools in the borough.</p>
        <p>The zoning proposal comes as the university plans for a major expansion in and around its engineering quadrangle. University officials say the new zoning could threaten not only Princeton's science program but also its long-term future as a research institution. For residents, it has forced a rethinking of the historic relationship between the borough and the university.</p>
        <p>Clogged Streets</p>
        <p>''The town is beginning to meet the limits of growth,'' said the president of the Princeton Borough Council, Marvin R. Reed. ''We're realizing that we can't just ignore the university and assume it will always automatically do the right thing.''</p>
        <p>Around Murray Place, residents saytheir quiet streets are clogged with the cars of graduate students. At night, their houses rattle when trucks drop off liquid nitrogen at the engineering building.</p>
        <p>Residents and planners say the borough desperately needs to place limits on itself if it is to remain a small-town oasis in the midst of a sprawling commercial corridor.</p>
        <p>Princeton's vice president for public affairs, Robert K. Durkee, said: ''We think it is entirely appropriate to impose some restrictions over what can be done over time. But we have a very strong track record in creating an attractive campus, and we don't see how it helps to involve the community in the planning process other than in ways they've been involved before.''</p>
        <p>'Conditional Use'</p>
        <p>The rezoning, proposed for an area of the campus where most buldings are about 50 feet high, would restrict new buildings or additions to a height of 36 feet, require them to be set back at least 50 feet from the street and subject plans to a procedure known as site-plan review, which includes a public hearing and a vote by the Regional Planning Board of Princeton.</p>
        <p>The proposal would also change the designation of many kinds of buildings - including laboratories, dormitories and classrooms - from a ''permitted use'' to the more restrictive ''conditional use.'' The university says that would make it much harder to gain acceptance for its projects.</p>
        <p>The plan, which will eventually be voted on by the Borough Council, would also apply to the Westminster Choir College and the Princeton Theological Seminary. Neither has major plans to expand, and neither is a presence on the scale of the university.</p>
        <p>Planners say that Princeton University's educational buildings are now subject to minimal height and setback requirements and thus little oversight.</p>
        <p>''If you're a homeowner, and you want to build something, the town gets to come in and comment,'' said Margen Penick, chairman of the Planning Board. ''But the university has essentially had no review.''</p>
        <p>Limits on Expansion</p>
        <p>University officials say the current proposal would halt their plans to build a new materials-science center and a Jewish studies building and to add to the engineering building. They say the delay could seriously harm some of the university's science programs.</p>
        <p>But residents near the eastern campus suggest that their neighborhood is not the best place to have a science center. ''The university may want to be known as a pre-eminent engineering school, but there isn't that much room in the area to accommodate that kind of growth,'' said Candace Preston, who lives on Murray Place.</p>
        <p>But the university said its science buildings must grow. The electrical engineering department, for instance, is badly overcrowded, Mr. Durkee said. Laboratory space is critical, he said, and the school fears that faculty members would seek better opportunities, with bigger labs, elsewhere.</p>
        <p>In the fledgling field of materials science, which seeks to understand the structure and properties of substances on a molecular level, the situation is more immediate. Officials said they fear that stricter zoning could delay plans to build a new materials science center next to the engineering building.</p>
        <p>'A Permanent Setback'</p>
        <p>''The university has been planning this center for two or three years and has committed significant resources to it,'' said Peter Eisenberger, a professor of physics who joined Princeton last fall as director of the new Materials Institute. ''This might be a permanent setback in terms of Princeton's getting into this important frontier.''</p>
        <p>The university is already upset about the failure last fall of its plan to build a 4-story, 400-car garage at the south end of the quadrangle.</p>
        <p>The university spent half a million dollars on the garage plan, convinced that it had the borough's blessing, but the neighborhood balked at the idea of such a large structure. Meanwhile, the Planning Board had drafted a new master plan, warning of gridlock around the quadrangle; residents feared the garage would draw more traffic while not easing the existing problems.</p>
        <p>The garage was voted down by the Planning Board, and the university sued. The suit is still pending, but the experience has left many residents resentful and put the university on the defensive.</p>
        <p>'Answer Is Strongly No'</p>
        <p>University officials say their proposed expansion in the quadrangle, along with the long-term goal of moving some parking lots away from the east side, will enhance the area's appearance. And they think the borough should trust their motives.</p>
        <p>''We think the addition of green space and buildings will result in a much more attractive part of campus,'' Mr. Durkee said. ''To accomplish that, do we need more active participation on the part of the Planning Board? Our answer is strongly no.'' The buildings on the older western part of campus, where most of the undergraduate classrooms and dormitories are, are considered beautiful: old, intricate and idiosyncratic. But some planners say that some of Princeton's newer laboratory buildings, utilitarian brick structures on the east side, are not so attractive.</p>
        <p>''A lot of it is ugly,'' Mrs. Penick said. ''It's not that we don't trust them, but perhaps they don't realize how ugly it is. This is a town that does not look like Disneyland. We try to protect historic things, and to allow modern buildings as long as they fit in.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
