<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mason's 22 Match 22 By Ewing; Starks Hurt</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="743748"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HEALTH, PERSONAL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK KNICKERBOCKERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MIAMI HEAT</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">NOBLES, CHARLIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">STARKS, JOHN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Miami Heat</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DA1E39F934A25751C0A963958260" item-length="826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mason's 22 Match 22 By Ewing; Starks Hurt</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHARLIE NOBLES,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">NOBLES, CHARLIE</byline>
      <dateline>MIAMI, Feb. 16</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a night in which the Knicks produced their best point run of the season and held an opponent under 90 points for the 18th time this season, Pat Riley still had a lot about which to fret.</p>
        <p>Mainly, the Knicks' coach was concerned about a recurring left shoulder injury to guard John Starks, who went out midway in the fourth quarter of tonight's 96-87 victory over Miami, grimacing and holding his shoulder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a night in which the Knicks produced their best point run of the season and held an opponent under 90 points for the 18th time this season, Pat Riley still had a lot about which to fret.</p>
        <p>Mainly, the Knicks' coach was concerned about a recurring left shoulder injury to guard John Starks, who went out midway in the fourth quarter of tonight's 96-87 victory over Miami, grimacing and holding his shoulder.</p>
        <p>Starks, who was only 2 of 10 in field-goal shooting, had reached in guarding Glen Rice and immediately grabbed the shoulder when Rice collided with him.</p>
        <p>Officially, he has a subluxation, a partly dislocated shoulder. Starks, who underwent X-rays, said he had injured the shoulder worse than in games against Utah and Houston.</p>
        <p>"It felt like a lot of ligaments got torn in there," he said somberly. "I hope I'm wrong. We'll know more tomorrow."</p>
        <p>If Starks is unable to play in a rematch with the Heat Friday night at Madison Square Garden, Hubert Davis figures to get more playing time.</p>
        <p>"I'm not even thinking about that," said Davis, who hit a key 3-pointer near the third quarter's end tonight en route to 10 points for the game. "I'll just have to go out there and see what happens."</p>
        <p>New York got strong performances from Patrick Ewing and Anthony Mason, who had 22 points each, along with Derek Harper, 20.</p>
        <p>"We just have trouble conjuring up the energy we need to start games," Riley said. "Right now we're stuck in mud. We were lethargic at the beginning."</p>
        <p>Things changed when Mason, who also had a team-high 14 rebounds, entered midway through the first quarter. Even though New York wound up on the short end of a 28-22 first-quarter score, Mason's influence was apparent.</p>
        <p>"He brings an awful lot of intensity to the game," Riley said of his No. 1 reserve. "Seems like tonight he had as much intensity as the other four guys combined."</p>
        <p>With Ewing getting two fouls in the game's first 3:51, it was left to Harper to keep the Knicks in the game early. He scored 11 points in the quarter and nearly  had more -- his 40-footer hit off the front rim at the buzzer.</p>
        <p>Still, Miami led by 28-22, largely on the strength of Billy Owens's 9 points and Rice's 7. A point was taken away from Miami after the end of the quarter, when Owens's long jumper with 2.7 seconds left was deemed worth 2 points, not 3.</p>
        <p>Herb Williams, Ewing's replacement, celebrated his 37th birthday today, but definitely not on the court. He wound up with 1 point, and particularly struggled in the opening quarter, missing three shots and looking tentative.</p>
        <p>Ewing re-entered the game to start the second quarter and New York promptly produced its hottest streak of the season. Within a span of 3:29, the Knicks had the lead again, at 32-30, and they weren't through. Before their season-high 17-point run was over, they had stretched their margin to 44-30.</p>
        <p>"Defense was the key," Riley said. "And quickness. They had some misses and a few of our guys got hot."</p>
        <p>Ewing was the obvious catalyst, scoring 13 points, including his team's first 3, and getting 7 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Mason also had a distinguished quarter. His twisting moves around the basket produced 6 points, and he added 3 rebounds, along with a 60-foot pass that led to an easy Ewing layup.</p>
        <p>Harper finished off the 28-11 quarter with a jump shot just four-tenths of a second before halftime, putting the Knicks on top, 50-39.</p>
        <p>New York's longest streak of unanswered points before tonight was 14, against New Jersey Dec. 27 and against Milwaukee Jan. 13.</p>
        <p>Curiously two of Miami's three 3 biggest offensive weapons, Owens and Kevin Willis, each sat out at least half of the second quarter as the Heat went scoreless for 4:55.</p>
        <p>But Coach Alvin Gentry, who replaced Kevin Loughery just two days ago, has acknowledged that he intends to do some experimenting.</p>
        <p>In the third quarter, Miami drew within 3 points of the Knicks once and within 4 on two occasions, the last time at 68-64, when Rice, who had 33 points, was deadly with a 3. Riley called a timeout and Miami Arena rocked with excitement.</p>
        <p>But the little-used Davis then quieted the home-towners with a straight-away 3-pointer at the 38-second mark.</p>
        <p>That allowed New York to enter the final quarter ahead, 71-64. The Knicks' lead never got below 6 points thereafter, but the game turned rough.</p>
        <p>Anthony Bonner was ejected with 7:11 left because of a flagrant foul on Miami's Matt Geiger as the 7-footer drove for a layup. His legs cut out from under him, Geiger hit the floor with a loud thud.</p>
        <p>Several minutes earlier, Geiger and Mason had a heated exchange, after Mason knocked him down on a drive.</p>
        <p>With 3:43 left, Ewing was whistled for a double technical foul along with Willis for their bumping and threatening talk. And inside the final minute, Rice and Harper drew double technicals for their uncomplimentary rejoinders.</p>
        <p>In the end, though, the Knicks got what they wanted and now they are looking at five home games in a row.  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
