<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Angels' Owner Wants Matthews to Talk</title>
    <meta content="09chass" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/09/sports/baseball/09chass.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1831691"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ON BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Los Angeles Angels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steroids</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Los Angeles Angels</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Matthews, Gary Jr</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070309T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01EFD61231F93AA35750C0A9619C8B63" item-length="937" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Angels' Owner Wants Matthews to Talk</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Angels’ Owner Wants Matthews to Talk</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MURRAY CHASS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chass, Murray</byline>
      <dateline>FORT MYERS, Fla.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When Arte Moreno, the Angels' owner, decided to commit $50 million to Gary Matthews Jr. over the next five years, he thought Matthews would enhance the pleasure he would derive from his team. However, the first few weeks of Matthews's tenure with the Angels have produced pain instead.</p>
        <p>Moreno hasn't branded Matthews, his new center fielder, guilty of illegally obtaining performance-enhancing substances online from pharmacies in Alabama or Florida. A district attorney in Albany is leading the investigation into the pharmacies, and published reports have named Matthews as one of the athletes to receive such substances. Moreno, though, said Matthews was guilty of failing to address Angels fans and members of the news media in a timely and a meaningful manner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Arte Moreno, the Angels’ owner, said that Gary Matthews Jr. should have addressed allegations he obtained performance-enhancing substances in a timely manner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When Arte Moreno, the Angels' owner, decided to commit $50 million to Gary Matthews Jr. over the next five years, he thought Matthews would enhance the pleasure he would derive from his team. However, the first few weeks of Matthews's tenure with the Angels have produced pain instead.</p>
        <p>Moreno hasn't branded Matthews, his new center fielder, guilty of illegally obtaining performance-enhancing substances online from pharmacies in Alabama or Florida. A district attorney in Albany is leading the investigation into the pharmacies, and published reports have named Matthews as one of the athletes to receive such substances. Moreno, though, said Matthews was guilty of failing to address Angels fans and members of the news media in a timely and a meaningful manner.</p>
        <p>''I'm not a happy guy,'' Moreno said yesterday in a lengthy telephone conversation.</p>
        <p>Commissioner Bud Selig isn't happy about the latest legal onslaught, either, but he had far less to say than Moreno. ''I need to know more facts,'' Selig said. ''I really don't have any comment.''</p>
        <p>In his discussion of the Matthews case, Moreno said it was premature to talk about Matthews's contract. ''We have not addressed that,'' he said. ''I've talked to the commissioner. I have to pass the ball to Bud and his people on that. I'm not in position now to say I'm sorry I signed him and I'm ready to invoke anything. My frustration is on the communications side.''</p>
        <p>News of the investigation and the alleged involvement of some athletes surfaced last week. At the time, Matthews said that he would have more to say when he received ''more information from my people.''</p>
        <p>Moreno said that he wanted more from Matthews by last Saturday and didn't get it. The owner, who was in advertising but not public relations, had what seemed a good suggestion.</p>
        <p>''Address the press and say: 'Yes, my name has been linked to this story. I'm sorry this has become a distraction and we're going to try to clear it up as quickly as possible,' '' Moreno said. ''I'm not asking him to admit to anything illegal. His response was, 'I'm talking to my people and we'll get back to you.' ''</p>
        <p>Worse, Moreno said, Matthews hired Robert Shapiro, a noted criminal lawyer in Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>''When he hired Shapiro, this doesn't send a very good signal,'' Moreno said. ''When 8 or 10 days go by and the only response is from a criminal attorney, what signals does that send to your fans?''</p>
        <p>Shapiro did not return a call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>Moreno mentioned Jason Giambi as an example Matthews could have followed. Giambi testified before the grand jury in the Bay Area Laboratory Co-operative investigation in San Francisco. His testimony, in which he acknowledged having used steroids, wound up in print in December 2004. Giambi addressed the issue at a news conference before spring training in 2005, but he didn't say that he had used steroids.</p>
        <p>''He really didn't say a lot,'' Moreno said. ''But I watched what happened with him. He looked choked up. He was emotional about letting some people down and he addressed it.''</p>
        <p>At the time Moreno referred to, the Yankees were exploring the possibility of voiding Giambi's contract, a move the players union would certainly have challenged. The Yankees abandoned the idea.</p>
        <p>There is a difference between Giambi's case and Matthews's. Giambi had been suspected of steroids use when he signed with the Yankees as a free agent -- his agent even asked the Yankees to remove all mention of steroids from the contract. Matthews had never been suspected of using illegal substances.</p>
        <p>Human growth hormone was added to baseball's list of banned substances in 2005, but it was already on the federal list of substances that were banned except through a prescription.</p>
        <p>People who have obtained drugs or other substances online, which Matthews reportedly did, have done so largely without prescriptions. According to an article in the Journal of the American Medical Association in October 2005, doctors in the antiaging industry estimated that 100,000 individuals obtained HGH without a prescription in 2002.</p>
        <p>Shapiro said Saturday that Matthews broke no laws or baseball rules, creating the suggestion that if Matthews used HGH, he did so before 2005.</p>
        <p>If the Angels wanted to void his contract, they could argue that they had no idea that he was a user and now that they know when he used HGH, it's highly likely that his use helped him become the player he was in 2006 and prompted them to give him the $50 million contract.</p>
        <p>There's a legal term for that sort of situation -- fraud in the inducement. If the Angels tried to take any action, the union would file a grievance and let an arbitrator decide the matter. Donald Fehr, the union chief, was traveling yesterday and was not available for comment.</p>
        <p>If Selig were to discipline Matthews or any other players whose names have surfaced, the union would challenge those acts, too. It would argue, among other things, that the players had not violated baseball rules. Major League Baseball could argue that the disclosure of substance use or abuse could affect its business if the commissioner did not penalize the players.</p>
        <p>Robert DuPuy, baseball's chief operating officer, wouldn't discuss specific players but said, ''The participation of any of our players in anything that's illegal or the involvement with illegal substances at any time whether they're covered by a specific baseball policy is of concern to us and will be looked into.''</p>
        <p>Moreno will wait and watch with interest for developments from the commissioner's office. First, though, he wants to hear from Matthews.</p>
        <p>ON BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
