<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of the Times; Honesty and Culpability: A Bribe Is a Bribe</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="619278"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOXING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIBERY</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANDERSON, DAVE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MERCER, RAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FERGUSON, JESSE</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">SPORTS OF THE TIMES (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Dave Anderson</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Boxing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bribery</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930704T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEFDA113AF937A35754C0A965958260" item-length="785" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of the Times; Honesty and Culpability: A Bribe Is a Bribe</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVE ANDERSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANDERSON, DAVE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SUPPOSE, just suppose, that Jesse Ferguson had splashed into the tank after Ray Mercer offered him $100,000 to lose.</p>
        <p>If Ferguson suddenly had flopped around like a hooked trout in the late rounds of their Feb. 6 heavyweight bout, if whispers of a fix had surfaced, if the Manhattan District Attorney's office had investigated, if a grand jury had listened to Mercer's words on the HBO videotape, wouldn't Ferguson have been indicted for having fixed a fight?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SUPPOSE, just suppose, that Jesse Ferguson had splashed into the tank after Ray Mercer offered him $100,000 to lose.</p>
        <p>If Ferguson suddenly had flopped around like a hooked trout in the late rounds of their Feb. 6 heavyweight bout, if whispers of a fix had surfaced, if the Manhattan District Attorney's office had investigated, if a grand jury had listened to Mercer's words on the HBO videotape, wouldn't Ferguson have been indicted for having fixed a fight?</p>
        <p>As the world knows, Ferguson spurned Mercer's offer and earned a unanimous decision at Madison Square Garden.</p>
        <p>But in boxing's latest sordid scenario, Jesse Ferguson's honesty does not absolve Ray Mercer's culpability.</p>
        <p>Boxing apologists are trying to minimize Mercer's videotaped offer as trash talk. But trash talk in boxing is Muhammad Ali telling George Foreman, "Is that the best you got?" What Mercer was saying is cash talk. What Mercer was offering Ferguson is a bribe. That's against the law. That's why Mercer has been indicted for a Class D felony that could put him in jail for seven years.</p>
        <p>"What comes across on the tapes," said Dan Castleman, the chief of investigations for District Attorney Robert M. Morgenthau's office, "is a desperate guy who knows he's in a desperate situation taking desperate means to find a solution."</p>
        <p>Mercer, with 15 knockouts in a 20-1 record, had been promised $1.5 million for a heavyweight title bout with Riddick Bowe that hinged on his getting by Ferguson, a journeyman with an 18-9 record. As the bout with Ferguson developed, Mercer realized he had not trained properly. He knew he was going to lose. He knew his only chance was a bribe.</p>
        <p>Not once or twice, but "repeatedly," to use Morgenthau's word, Mercer offered Ferguson $100,000 to take a dive.</p>
        <p>According to someone who has heard the audio portion of the videotape, Ferguson apparently questioned Mercer's sincerity, wondering if he did accept $100,000, how and when he would be paid. Mercer, invoking his mother's honor, assured him of payment the next day.</p>
        <p>Ferguson decided to keep punching for a unanimous 10-round decision that canceled Mercer's $1.5 million title shot.</p>
        <p>Ferguson told his corner about Mercer's offer, but did not report it to the New York State Athletic Commission or any other governing body. Randy Gordon, the commission chairman, pursued it after the bout's referee, Wayne Kelly, reported hearing rumors of Mercer's offer from an unidentified boxing trainer not connected to either fighter.</p>
        <p>As it turned out, Ferguson was chosen as Bowe's next challenger. In their May 22 bout in Washington, the 36-year-old Philadelphia heavyweight collected $500,000 for lasting 17 seconds into the second round. His integrity, or at least his skepticism about how and when Mercer would pay the $100,000, had been rewarded five fold.</p>
        <p>As for Mercer, maybe he didn't realize the consequences of his conversation. Maybe he believed that since Ferguson was an "opponent," meaning a boxer who supposedly had little or no chance to win, he could talk him into losing. But that's no excuse. And legally, that's no defense.</p>
        <p>In boxing, the image of fixed fights has usually involved a conspiracy of gangster types, corrupt managers and pliant pugilists. One of boxing's most celebrated fixes occurred in 1947 when Jake LaMotta lost, standing up, to Billy Fox at the Garden, a fix that was analyzed for posterity at the Kefauver Committee hearings on boxing in 1960.</p>
        <p>"Would you describe in your own words," Jack Bonomi, the committee counsel, asked, "how you faked the knockout?"</p>
        <p>"I just stood helpless," LaMotta answered, "and he was pounding away, and the referee stopped the fight."</p>
        <p>When Joey LaMotta, who acted as his brother's manager, was questioned about a $100,000 bribe from Frankie Carbo, Frank (Blinky) Palermo and Bill Daly for the Fox fight and various other matters, he took the Fifth Amendment a total of 53 times.</p>
        <p>Through the years, a fix has been merely part of the not-so-sweet science's seamy history. So what if Ray Mercer offered Jesse Ferguson $100,000 to fall down, what else is new?</p>
        <p>Judging by Mercer's lawyers, their defense will include the irrelevance of Mercer's past as a nine-year Army veteran who earned an Olympic boxing gold medal in Seoul in 1988.</p>
        <p>But if a baseball slugger was indicted for offering an opposing pitcher $10,000 to serve up a gopher ball late in the season because one more homer would help him collect a $150,000 incentive clause, the sports world would howl. Especially if there were a videotape that included that slugger's words in offering the bribe.</p>
        <p>Just because it's boxing and just because Jesse Ferguson didn't take the money doesn't take Ray Mercer off the hook.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
