<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All Eyes Follow Her In Flea Markets</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Home Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="770360"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANTIQUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">SLESIN, SUZANNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RUSH, ELAINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antiques</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950622T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4D91039F931A15755C0A963958260" item-length="990" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All Eyes Follow Her In Flea Markets</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SUZANNE SLESIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SLESIN, SUZANNE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SHE'S the striking woman whom most people who have shopped at the flea markets in New England for nearly a decade know on sight: tall, imposing, wearing colorful tentlike chenille outfits with coordinated turbanlike hats, day-glo feather-covered totes and extravagant makeup.</p>
        <p>She is Elaine Rush, an antiques dealer, and there is nothing understated about her.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SHE'S the striking woman whom most people who have shopped at the flea markets in New England for nearly a decade know on sight: tall, imposing, wearing colorful tentlike chenille outfits with coordinated turbanlike hats, day-glo feather-covered totes and extravagant makeup.</p>
        <p>She is Elaine Rush, an antiques dealer, and there is nothing understated about her.</p>
        <p>As Ms. Rush makes the rounds from dawn to dusk at the huge outdoor flea markets in New York, Massachusetts, Connecticut, Pennsylvania, she is usually pursued by photographers from the local newspapers while some people pause in their foraging to stare at her.</p>
        <p>None of this is new or surprising to her.</p>
        <p>"For the most part I get a good reaction," she said. "And over the years I've met a lot of wonderful people that I may never have met if they didn't approach me to find out either what I'm selling or what the act's about. The truth is, it's only me." She says she is tired of the attention given to what "is simply the way I am."</p>
        <p>But Ms. Rush's eye and quirky taste for all the things that now come under the umbrella of antiques and collectibles have also drawn attention to her every move.</p>
        <p>"I'm in the business of finding neat things and loving them," said Ms. Rush, who is always one of the first on the flea market field. "You can't expect to go to markets in the afternoon and find things, so I go everywhere and anywhere at 4 A.M." No wonder one of her mottoes is "Keep moving and don't stand still."</p>
        <p>That could apply both to her antiques shopping and her homes. Ms. Rush seems to be always buying old houses, renovating them, filling them with antiques and often selling them as is. In the last couple of years, she has transported her personal collection of tramp art, shell art, wooden Indian clubs (she has hundreds), carved or stuffed toy animals (dogs and moose are favorites), black collectibles and other arcane folk and out-of-the ordinary objects that have caught her eye from Manhattan to New Preston, Conn., then Sharon, Conn., and recently to South Egremont, Mass., in the Berkshires.</p>
        <p>Some things don't fit in when Ms. Rush gets them home. Sometimes these oversize pieces spend time on the porch or she resells them -- mostly to other dealers who have come to know her as a dependable source for fashionable and desirable finds. These days, Ms. Rush has a particularly fertile and welcome outlet for her shopping sprees: her Church Street Trading Company, which has two locations. One is in New Milford, Conn., the other in Great Barrington, Mass.</p>
        <p>The shops, which sell clothing and furniture, are styled after old-fashioned general stores and are run by her husband, Robert Rush, with whom she shares this business and who says, according to his wife, that he never wants to move. But he does anyway. Ms. Rush said: "He always feels the next house will never be as nice. But he's wrong.</p>
        <p>"He is the most incredibly supportive friend, but I like to have a certain independence to be able to run off and go buying on the road whenever I want. In this type of business, you have to be ready at all times to take off, whenever and wherever."</p>
        <p>By all accounts, Ms. Rush has been adventuresome since she was a young girl in Montreal. Her father, Benjamin Fraid, a Russian immigrant, met her mother, Fay, when they were working in a men's store in Montreal. A few years later, her mother opened a small women's clothing store.</p>
        <p>"She was the first woman in Canada to have a department store, and one wild chick," Ms. Rush said. "I'm down-scaled in comparison." Ms. Rush started working at Fraid's when she was 13. What she liked was traveling to New York and Europe as a buyer. "Montreal was great," she said, "but there was no freedom. You felt so stifled."</p>
        <p>In 1970, she moved to New York. "I just thought it was the most exciting place and wanted to meet everyone who was from another place," she said. She left behind her family's "fabulous house with all the desperately stylish and expensive stuff from the late 40's, 50's and 60's," she added.</p>
        <p>A first job as a buyer at Bloomingdale's lasted three weeks. "That's when I decided I should be self-employed," she said. Traveling back and forth to Canada through the Adirondacks and the Berkshires, Ms. Rush started buying. "I like things that talk to your soul," she said, "like tramp and Adirondack stuff." She was one of the first to appreciate the rustic, quirky pieces, buying the things she saw and liked, by instinct, especially the items that had not yet become mainstream. "Back then, I didn't know hot from cool," she added. "But you know when you meet it."</p>
        <p>She soon became obsessed. "I was chasing the stuff everywhere," she said. "I had never been exposed to old things before. You never saw two of them alike. That's how I got me into folk art. Talk about an addictive personality."</p>
        <p>"I was always the odd bird," Ms. Rush continued. But she also seemed to have a practical side. In the late 1980's when, Ms. Rush said, "the recession hit" and her dry-cleaning bills were "over the top," she discovered chenille fabric and started buying every chenille bedspread she could find. Today, chenille forms the basis of her wardrobe. She had the chenille bedspreads made into the versatile coat dresses for which she is known. She has more than 200 outfits, in winter and summer weights.</p>
        <p>"I used to pay $15, $20, maybe $25 for the good ones," she said. "Now, they're upward of $250." She calls them her "recession clothes." "They go in the washing machine, and if they're creased you just put them in the dryer and you have the fluffiest, most gorgeous outfit you've ever seen."</p>
        <p>But they don't last forever. "They're made from old fabrics, and after going through the dryer 350 times, they sort of wear out and get frayed," she said. "Replenishing my supply is getting harder and harder, almost impossible, like finding good tramp art, unless you win the lottery."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
