<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pakistan Tries To Split Army From Mullahs</title>
    <meta content="09STAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/11/09/international/asia/09STAN.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1341336"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: POLITICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington (DC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Afghanistan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Onishi, Norimitsu</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Musharraf, Pervez (Gen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Afghanistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hijacking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Public Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airlines and Airplanes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Taliban</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Musharraf, Pervez</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20011109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7D81638F93AA35752C1A9679C8B63" item-length="1409" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pakistan Tries To Split Army From Mullahs</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pakistan Tries to Split Army From Mullahs</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NORIMITSU ONISHI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Onishi, Norimitsu</byline>
      <dateline>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan, Nov. 8</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses Pakistan's crackdown on Islamic religious parties, including arrests of several party leaders, since siding with United States after Sept 11 terrorist attacks; Pres Pervez Musharraf describes religious groups as representative of small minority of extremists; tensions between groups and military persist and Musharraf's support may erode if war in Afghanistan continues for extended period (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was called the mullah-military nexus, Pakistan's alliance of Muslim clerics and soldiers born out of the war that began next door, in Afghanistan, in 1979.</p>
        <p>Over two decades, this alliance proved mutually beneficial. The army grew increasingly Islamized, producing officers sympathetic to the religious parties and their causes, like supporting the Taliban.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seeking to undercut militant mullahs, Pakistan has arrested religious leaders and sidelined officers with ties to religious parties.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was called the mullah-military nexus, Pakistan's alliance of Muslim clerics and soldiers born out of the war that began next door, in Afghanistan, in 1979.</p>
        <p>Over two decades, this alliance proved mutually beneficial. The army grew increasingly Islamized, producing officers sympathetic to the religious parties and their causes, like supporting the Taliban.</p>
        <p>The army also backed the parties' militant wings, like the Movement of the Mujahedeen, allowing Pakistan to wage a proxy war in Kashmir, the issue behind two wars between Pakistan and India.</p>
        <p>But today, in yet another sign of how Afghanistan has once again changed Pakistan's internal politics, the military government arrested Maulana Fazlur Rehman, a leader of a major Islamic party, the Society of Islamic Clerics.</p>
        <p>Several days before, the government arrested Qazi Hussain Ahmed, the head of the country's most important religious party,  the Islamic Party. He had called on the army to overthrow President Pervez Musharraf for backing the American bombing of Aghanistan.</p>
        <p>''It is the weakest government we have had in our history,'' Syed Munawar Hasan, the secretary general of the Islamic Party, said in a telephone interview from Lahore. ''They don't have any roots in the masses or in the parties. The only support they have is from America. They are frightened people, and frightened people do silly things.''</p>
        <p>Since siding with the United States after the attacks on Sept. 11, the military government has cracked down on religious parties, whose activities it had tolerated and, in some cases, encouraged. Meanwhile, it has taken only tentative steps in talking with the two mainstream parties, which have atrophied under military repression and whose leaders, Nawaz Sharif and Benazir Bhutto, both accused of massive corruption, remain in exile abroad.</p>
        <p>As the West's indispensable ally, President Musharraf can expect only warm greetings during his current six-day foreign tour. The warmest of all could be in the United States, where until recently Mr. Musharraf, a general who seized power in a coup in 1999, had been a pariah.</p>
        <p>But his departure Wednesday from his own country could only be described as hasty. The national mobile phone system was switched off briefly as his plane left here a few hours earlier than announced -- security measures, it appeared, for the head of a government that many describe as increasingly, and dangerously, isolated.</p>
        <p>During a stop in Paris today, Mr. Musharraf described the religious groups as ''a very small minority of religious extremists.''</p>
        <p>In an earlier speech, he said: ''Some elements are trying to take unfair advantage of the situation and promote their personal agenda and advance the interests of their parties. They are poised to create dissensions and damage the country.''</p>
        <p>The words were a departure for the head of a military that has long had an important relationship with the mullahs. In the early 1980's, inspired by the religious overtones of the anti-Soviet war in Afghanistan and a need to legitimize his power, seized in a coup, Gen. Mohammed Zia ul Haq allied himself with this country's religious leaders. Islam was emphasized in everyday life, including in the military, until the general -- and several other senior officers, and the American ambassador -- died in a still unexplained plane crash over southern Pakistan in 1988.</p>
        <p>But in recent weeks, in addition to arresting several religious leaders, the government has banned political groups from staging rallies and mosques from using loudspeakers to transmit political messages. General Musharraf, who is considered a moderate, has retired or sidelined officers who resisted the alliance or who were too closely tied with the religious parties.</p>
        <p>Among them were Lieut. Gen. Aziz Khan, a so-called jihadi general who is said to have been one of the leaders in the military operation in Kargil, Kashmir, which caused a major confrontation with India in 1999, a year after the two countries first tested nuclear arms.</p>
        <p>Despite the reshuffle, it is unclear whether Mr. Musharraf would have the full support of the military if America's war against Afghanistan goes on indefinitely.</p>
        <p>''I think he's trying to play down the tensions, to say everything is hunky-dory,'' said Hamid Gul, a retired lieutenant general who is very close to the religious groups and supports the Taliban. ''It's too much tightrope walking.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gul, who was also the chief of the powerful military intelligence agency, the Inter-Services Intelligence, in the late 1980's, said he did not know whether the army and intelligence agency would support Mr. Musharraf if he ordered them to eliminate the armed groups allied with the religious parties.</p>
        <p>''It will be seen only when there is a face to face,'' he said. ''It will be a critical and dangerous situation.</p>
        <p>''The past record of the army is that whenever there has been a conflict between it and the country's ruler, the ruler has fallen. It would be the first conflict when the president of the country is also the head of the army. I don't know how the army will respond to that situation.''</p>
        <p>The religious parties have never won significantly at the polls, remaining stuck in the single digits. But their influence lies in their ability to deploy thousands of supporters onto the streets, and the potential power of the armed groups allied to them can be measured in the millions of weapons that have washed into Pakistan from Afghanistan -- and from outsiders supporting various causes in Afghanistan -- over the decades.</p>
        <p>Although support for the religious parties often comes from Pakistan's millions and millions of impoverished, individuals inside and outside the country, as well as the military, are believed to have financed them.</p>
        <p>''As far as creating a problem for the government, they have the potential,'' Fazal ur Rahman, a senior researcher at the Institute of Strategic Studies, said of the religious parties.</p>
        <p>General Musharraf's crackdown has therefore likely deepened the isolation of the military government. It lacks a base in the political mainstream, and has now allied itself with the United States, a move that many Pakistanis look at warily. Polls have shown support for that alliance has diminished steadily in the last two months.</p>
        <p>Aziz Khan, the spokesman for the Foreign Ministry, said Mr. Musharraf has consulted widely with all segments of society, from religious to political leaders to intellectuals.</p>
        <p>''The government has to look at the popular support it has,'' he said. ''What is more important is whether the broad masses of the country are angry with the government or are they in favor with the government?''</p>
        <p>''I don't think there is any truth in the statement that it has become isolated,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The military took power in 1999 amid popular discontent over a decade of corrupt and ineffective civilian rule by first Ms. Bhutto and then Mr. Sharif. The military government banned political rallies and earlier this year, arrested hundreds of members of both those politicians' parties before a planned event.</p>
        <p>The Pakistan Muslim League, the country's founding party, split in two after its leader, Mr. Sharif, went into exile in Saudi Arabia after the 1999 coup. One faction is said to be close to the government; Javed Hashmi, the leader of the faction loyal to Mr. Sharif, was arrested recently for criticizing the government.</p>
        <p>Ms. Bhutto, the leader of the Pakistan People's Party, went into exile to Dubai after she and her husband were found guilty of corruption in 1999. This week, she said she had asked the government to guarantee her safe return, saying she could not get a fair trial here. But the government has said that she will have to face trial.</p>
        <p>The party's leaders, analysts here say, are now hoping to return to the political stage after the military government reduces the power of the religious groups. At the same time, Mr. Musharraf may want to keep the leaders out and try to inherit their political base.</p>
        <p>The mainstream political parties ''are his natural allies because they have been meaning to do exactly the kind of thing Musharraf has done'' by curtailing the religious groups, said Rifaat Hussain, the chairman of defense and strategic studies at Quaid-i-Azam University here. ''But out of political consideration, they never found the political courage to do so. Now that Musharraf has done it, it is in his larger interest to carry these people with him.''</p>
        <p>But so far, Mr. Musharraf, who had promised general elections by next October, has not made any serious attempts to win them over.</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: POLITICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
