<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Despite Security, Tradition of Trading Passes Is Thriving</title>
    <meta content="28PASS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="P" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/28/politics/campaign/28passes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1599987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="VIEWS, VENUES AND THE AVENUES: CREDENTIALS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Conventions, National (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Boston (Mass)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lee, Jennifer 8</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Homeland Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Democratic National Convention</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts/Boston</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Massachusetts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Identification Devices</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Conventions and Conferences</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Security and Warning Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040728T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E6DD133DF93BA15754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Despite Security, Tradition of Trading Passes Is Thriving</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Even With Security, Passes Are Still Traded</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER 8. LEE and DAVID JOHNSTON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Johnston, David; Lee, Jennifer 8</byline>
      <dateline>BOSTON, July 27</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Quest for political status at Democratic convention is colliding with its elaborate security measures; convention's credential system, which uses access passes color-coded by degree of exclusivity, is intended to allow only authorized individuals to make it past metal detectors; but controls are being threatened by tradition of trading credentials, even coveted backstage passes for VIP areas; trafficking in credentials and invitations to exclusive events and parties is flourishing among K Street lobbyists, donors, party officials and Boston residents with little formal connection to convention; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The quest for political status at the Democratic convention is colliding with its elaborate security measures.</p>
        <p>The convention's credential system -- access passes color-coded by degree of exclusivity -- was intended to allow only authorized individuals to make it past the metal detectors, Secret Service agents and an eight-foot-high fence encircling the FleetCenter. But the controls are being threatened by the tradition of trading credentials, even coveted backstage passes for V.I.P. areas.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The trafficking in credentials and invitations to exclusive events and parties is flourishing among K Street lobbyists, donors, party officials and Boston residents.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The quest for political status at the Democratic convention is colliding with its elaborate security measures.</p>
        <p>The convention's credential system -- access passes color-coded by degree of exclusivity -- was intended to allow only authorized individuals to make it past the metal detectors, Secret Service agents and an eight-foot-high fence encircling the FleetCenter. But the controls are being threatened by the tradition of trading credentials, even coveted backstage passes for V.I.P. areas.</p>
        <p>The trafficking in credentials and invitations to exclusive events and parties is flourishing among K Street lobbyists, donors, party officials and Boston residents with little formal connection to the convention. People are even trying to buy and sell them on a Web site, craigslist.org.</p>
        <p>The concern in the post-Sept. 11 era is that a legitimate pass may end up in ill-intentioned hands. The authorities say they have the situation under control. Ann Roman, a Secret Service spokeswoman, said that to gain access to highly secure areas, visitors must have not only a credential but also a second pass, issued by the Secret Service, that includes the holder's name and photograph.</p>
        <p>''It's a layered system,'' Ms. Roman said. ''To get into certain secure areas you need a second pass. So far it's worked fine.''</p>
        <p>Still, some security officials acknowledge that the second pass is not always checked. And the system has not stopped the brisk trade in the color-coded credentials.</p>
        <p>The credentials are distributed by the thousands each day to delegations, media organizations and vendors. Each cardboard pass is numbered and protected against counterfeiting by a hologram emblazoned over an image of a Boston landmark. But although the convention controls distribution, what happens to the passes afterward is largely uncontrolled.</p>
        <p>In most cases, the bartering involves attendees who simply want to upgrade their access to get closer to Democratic stars and Hollywood celebrities.</p>
        <p>''You beg, borrow, and steal -- well, not a lot of stealing going on, but there is begging and borrowing,'' said Ocean MacAdams, vice president for news for MTV, who was trying to secure Thursday floor passes for P. Diddy's entourage. Mr. MacAdams admitted that he had offered two concert tickets in exchange for floor passes but was turned down.</p>
        <p>The barter reaches the highest levels of Democratic officialdom. Gov. Bill Richardson of New Mexico, chairman of the convention, wanted tickets to the ultra-exclusive, star-studded fund-raiser the Creative Coalition was holding at the Louis Boston clothing store on Wednesday night. He offered two red floor passes to Maria Fei, vice president of Louis Boston, to push her offer of tickets to four from two.</p>
        <p>''In the end, did he get the number of tickets he wanted?'' Ms. Fei asked. ''Of course he did. He's a good friend.'' And she now has a floor pass for Thursday night, when Senator John Kerry is scheduled to give his acceptance speech.</p>
        <p>At the fringes, there are also outsiders who want to become insiders.</p>
        <p>Michael Bocchini, deputy director of the National Democratic Ethnic Leadership Council, and friends were waiting outside the metal gates trying to secure a convention pass for a friend. They succeeded when another friend who had extra credentials came along.</p>
        <p>''What I can offer people is to get on a guest list in exchange that they hook me up with an extra credential or a trade-up,'' Mr. Bocchini said.</p>
        <p>The color coding has its own hierarchy. Perimeter passes are yellow, passes to the FleetCenter interior are purple, passes to the hall are green, passes to get onto the convention floor are red, passes to the backstage are light blue and passes to the stage area are dark blue.</p>
        <p>The dark blue pass is such a badge of status that three women wanted their picture taken with Jason McElvaney, a 34-year-old Texan of modest political stature, when they saw one hanging around his neck.</p>
        <p>''It was 'Oh, my God, how did you get that?' and 'We will remember you,''' said Mr. McElvaney, who has family connections on the credentialing committee.</p>
        <p>Mr. McElvaney was able to obtain invitations to a party in exchange for a backstage pass for one of the hosts, who then had her picture taken with former President Bill Clinton.</p>
        <p>The market for trading opened well before the convention.</p>
        <p>''You put feelers out to all your contacts and information trickles out slowly,'' said Michael Hacker, a Democratic lobbyist who carried a list of cellphone numbers of potential trading partners. ''Come convention time, you know who your real friends are.''</p>
        <p>VIEWS, VENUES AND THE AVENUES: CREDENTIALS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
