<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Transforming the Decade: 10 Critical Technologies</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="412417"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RESEARCH</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLLACK, ANDREW</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Science and Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910101T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5DB103FF932A35752C0A967958260" item-length="547" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Transforming the Decade: 10 Critical Technologies</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW POLLACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLLACK, ANDREW</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Trains that float above their tracks for a smooth, fast ride. Enormously powerful computers that will understand speech and help design new drugs. Motors the size of a dust speck, battery-powered cars, genetically engineered supercrops.</p>
        <p>The coming decade promises great progress on these and other technologies that have the potential to bolster the nation's economic well-being and help humanity. It also promises to be a decade of conflict as different industries argue for Government help in developing particular technologies.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Trains that float above their tracks for a smooth, fast ride. Enormously powerful computers that will understand speech and help design new drugs. Motors the size of a dust speck, battery-powered cars, genetically engineered supercrops.</p>
        <p>The coming decade promises great progress on these and other technologies that have the potential to bolster the nation's economic well-being and help humanity. It also promises to be a decade of conflict as different industries argue for Government help in developing particular technologies.</p>
        <p>In this report, science and technology reporters from The New York Times, after consultation with experts in universities, Government and industry, have chosen 10 technologies that are expected to be among the most important in the next decade.</p>
        <p>Such lists of critical technologies have recently become quite popular. The Defense Department and Commerce Department have each made lists, and the White House Office of Science and Technology Policy is completing one. The Computer Systems Policy Project and the Aerospace Industries Association of America, two trade groups, have made lists for their respective industries. Other lists have been made in Japan and Europe.</p>
        <p>The lists are similar to one another and to The Times's choices. Semiconductors, biotechnology and advanced computing place on virtually all the lists. "The striking fact is the common ground out there from country to country and agency to agency," said Daniel F. Burton Jr., executive vice president of the Council on Competitiveness, a group of industry, academic and labor union officials that is planning to release its own list early this year.</p>
        <p>The Bush Administration says the Government should not be picking winners and losers. But some scientists and industry executives say such choices are inevitably, if implicitly, made whenever money is spent in one area and not another. And with pressures tightening on the Federal and industrial research and development budgets, such choices are likely to become even more necessary.</p>
        <p>In the past, critical technologies were mainly those deemed necessary for national defense. But with the cold war subsiding, many executives and policy makers say the time has come to make industrial competitiveness the basis for the list.</p>
        <p>Still others say that neither national security nor competitiveness is the appropriate standard. They say critical technologies are those that satisfy human needs, like pollution control and affordable housing, rather than technologies that help American companies sell more television sets.</p>
        <p>"There's a real need for a compelling philosophy for investing in science and technology that motivates people without resorting to these base motives of helping ourselves and beggaring our neighbors," said Gary Chapman, executive director of Computer Professionals for Social Responsibility, a nonprofit group.</p>
        <p>In compiling the list below, all the criteria were considered. The technologies are not ranked in order of importance. Unavoidably, some deserving technologies, including robotics and opto-electronics, were omitted.  Some technologies on the list will undoubtedly turn out to be duds while technologies that cannot even be envisioned now will end up recasting the world.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
