<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mars Is Getting Close, and Maybe So Are Those Little Green Men</title>
    <meta content="24MARS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/08/24/weekinreview/24MARS.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1514320"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Space and Cosmos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Space</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Astronomy and Astrophysics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Astronomy and Astrophysics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Space</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030824T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E0DA1439F937A1575BC0A9659C8B63" item-length="487" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mars Is Getting Close, and Maybe So Are Those Little Green Men</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mars Is Getting Close, and Maybe So Are Those Little Green Men</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANYONE looking at the night sky the last few weeks has seen it coming, Mars looming larger and redder on the way to one of its close encounters with Earth. It happens every two years or so. But this time, on early Wednesday morning, Mars and Earth will be closer together than at any time in almost 60,000 years.</p>
        <p>Near as Mars will be this week, 34,646,418 miles away, observers are hardly likely to see as much as their imaginations once could see.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Near as Mars will be this week, observers are hardly likely to see as much as their imaginations once could see.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANYONE looking at the night sky the last few weeks has seen it coming, Mars looming larger and redder on the way to one of its close encounters with Earth. It happens every two years or so. But this time, on early Wednesday morning, Mars and Earth will be closer together than at any time in almost 60,000 years.</p>
        <p>Near as Mars will be this week, 34,646,418 miles away, observers are hardly likely to see as much as their imaginations once could see.</p>
        <p>The planet's red glow used to remind people of blood and life and war. Mars was assumed to be inhabited, perhaps by intelligent beings like the little green men of lore. It was a neighboring world that enthralled and intimidated people.</p>
        <p>When some astronomers in the late 19th century thought they could make out canals stretching across the planet's deserts, these were presumed to be a great civilization's desperate attempt at survival in a harsh climate. It seemed to follow that adversity drove Martians to interplanetary belligerence, a theme science fiction feasted on, notably in H. G. Wells's ''The War of the Worlds.'' A realistic radio adaptation of the Wells story about a Martian invasion of Earth panicked many listeners on the night before Halloween in 1938.</p>
        <p>Human attitudes were shaped by curiosity as much as dread. Beginning in 1911, Edgar Rice Burroughs wrote 11 romantic books about an American adventurer's travels to spired and domed cities of Mars, where he woos and wins a beautiful princess. Is it any wonder that people began listening for radio messages from Mars?</p>
        <p>Marconi, the wireless inventor, announced in 1921 that he had received mysterious signals in code that he suspected came from Mars. So the next year and again in 1924, at close approaches of Mars, the United States government requested all radio stations to observe complete silence for a certain period while operators listened for Martian signals. Navy transmitters in the Pacific remained silent for three days, while a codebreaker stood by to translate any messages from Mars -- all in vain.</p>
        <p>THE failure discouraged a French astronomer and enthusiastic supporter of Martian life, who told a reporter, ''Perhaps the Martians tried before, in the epoch of the iguanodon and dinosaur, and got tired.''</p>
        <p>Although the Martians never were, their world still beckons. Robotic spacecraft have flown close by, around and onto the cold, dry surface of Mars. Three spacecraft are en route for landings in December and January.</p>
        <p>The attraction is still Martian life, if there is or ever was life there in some modest form.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
