<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inflatable Angst</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Styles of The Times" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="688696"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEW MODELS, DESIGN AND PRODUCTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUNCH, EDVARD (1863-1944)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">New Models, Design and Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940522T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9801E7D71738F931A15756C0A962958260" item-length="604" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inflatable Angst</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Judith Newman</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHAT IT IS: A 50-inch inflatable doll called the Scream. There is also a 12-inch version called Scream Junior. WHAT INSPIRED IT: "The Scream," the late-19th-century masterpiece by the Norwegian artist Edvard Munch. The 36-by-29-inch waxed crayon and tempera canvas of a ghoulish waif shrieking against the backdrop of a blood-red sky has become a symbol of modern angst in a century devastated by war, social upheaval, disease, famine and the ascendance of Barney.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHAT IT IS: A 50-inch inflatable doll called the Scream. There is also a 12-inch version called Scream Junior. WHAT INSPIRED IT: "The Scream," the late-19th-century masterpiece by the Norwegian artist Edvard Munch. The 36-by-29-inch waxed crayon and tempera canvas of a ghoulish waif shrieking against the backdrop of a blood-red sky has become a symbol of modern angst in a century devastated by war, social upheaval, disease, famine and the ascendance of Barney.</p>
        <p>WHY: "Everybody can identify with the frustration, the tension, the sense of being overwhelmed that is part of modern existence," said Robert Fishbone, whose company, On the Wall Productions, in St. Louis, makes the inflatables. "That's what the Scream is about. Besides, it looks cool." WHERE IT LOOKS COOL: College dormitories (they're popular graduation gifts) and offices -- especially in California. One was recently spotted on the passenger seat of a New York City taxi. Dave Leavy, special assistant to the White House press secretary, Dee Dee Myers, keeps a Scream Junior perched on his desk. Jodie Foster, a woman with more than her share of unwholesome admirers, received a Scream anonymously, Mr. Fishbone said. WHERE IT'S HYPER-COOL: Japan. About 50,000 of them have been sold there so far this year (compared with 25,000 in the United States). "It's kind of a tough time in Japan economically, and the Scream embodies the national angst," Mr. Fishbone said. "I guess it's hard for a lot of Japanese businessmen to cut loose." GONE WITH THE WIND: Recently, a distraught New York City secretary called On the Wall Productions, demanding the company ship her an inflatable Scream immediately. It seems the woman had wanted to air out the office while her boss was away on business -- and the boss's Scream was sucked out the window. WHY ACQUIRE A SCREAM? About half the people who buy an inflatable Scream don't realize it was inspired by a famous painting, Mr. Fishbone said. But sales of the inflatable figure soared in the United States after the original painting was stolen from the National Art Museum in Oslo on Feb. 12. The break-in took all of 50 seconds and was recorded on a video camera; the thieves left behind a postcard that said, "Thanks for the poor security."</p>
        <p>Anti-abortion activists in Norway, who had adopted "The Scream" as a symbol of their movement, said they would arrange the safe return of the painting if Norway's state television broadcast "The Silent Scream," a propagandist film depicting an abortion. But on May 9 the painting was recovered in a hotel in Asgardstrand, Norway, and three international art thieves were arrested after trying to sell it for $410,000 to undercover police officers. THE PRIMAL PRICE: The Scream retails for about $28 (Scream Junior, $11) at gift stores and novelty shops. Had the thieves made their deal, they could have bought 14,643 Screams. CELEBRITY LOOK-ALIKES: Macaulay Culkin, Kate Moss. RECENT MEDIA APPEARANCES: On "Murphy Brown" and "Bob." And in The New Yorker, side by side with Elvis in a piece by Bobbie Ann Mason titled "All Shook Up." SCREAM AS MEDIA PUNDIT? When he was with CBS, the correspondent Robert Krulwich talked about the possibility of world recession while surrounded by a troika of inflatable Screams. WIPE THAT SMILE OFF YOUR FACE: On the Wall Productions also sells a companion figure for Scream Junior called Little Happy Guy, a 12-inch yellow smiley-face figure with outstretched arms and legs. "He doesn't sell nearly as well as Scream Junior," Mr. Fishbone said. Welcome to the 90's.  THING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
