<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cone Wins His 18th And Courts History</title>
    <meta content="18YANK$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1040003"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Yankees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Kansas City Royals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE0D9173DF93BA2575BC0A96E958260" item-length="1012" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cone Wins His 18th And Courts History</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BUSTER OLNEY</byline>
      <dateline>KANSAS CITY, Mo., Aug. 17</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Cone is closer to his 50th birthday than to his high school graduation, and lines that did not exist 10 years ago cut across his face and neck when it is hot and he is straining to get outs.</p>
        <p>But at age 35, David Cone is having perhaps the best season of his career. After he and the Yankees beat the Kansas City Royals tonight, 7-1, he is just two victories shy of 20, leaving Cone on the verge of setting a major league record.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Cone is closer to his 50th birthday than to his high school graduation, and lines that did not exist 10 years ago cut across his face and neck when it is hot and he is straining to get outs.</p>
        <p>But at age 35, David Cone is having perhaps the best season of his career. After he and the Yankees beat the Kansas City Royals tonight, 7-1, he is just two victories shy of 20, leaving Cone on the verge of setting a major league record.</p>
        <p>Nine seasons have passed since Cone last won 20 games, when he was 20-3 for the Mets in 1988. If he wins 20 this year, the nine-year span would be the longest between 20-victory seasons, according to STATS Inc. Jim Kaat, a Yankee broadcaster, holds the record of seven years. Kaat was 25-13 for the Minnesota Twins in 1966 and did not win 20 again until he went 21-13 for the Chicago White Sox in 1974. Breaking the record, Cone said, ''would mean a lot, considering what I've been through the last couple of years.''</p>
        <p>Bernie Williams, Tim Raines and Tino Martinez each hit home runs to support Cone, Martinez breaking open the game against the Royals' Jose Rosado (6-9) with a three-run homer in the fifth inning. The Yankees are 91-30, on track to win 121 games, and they lead the American League East by 20 games over Boston.</p>
        <p>Cone has lived a nomadic baseball existence since 1988, pitching for the Mets in their decline before leaving for Kansas City, then on to Toronto and then the Yankees. Two years were shortened by labor strife, and Cone became familiar with aneurysms and arthroscopic shoulder surgery as he struggled through the 1996 and 1997 seasons. He took the mound tonight exactly one year after pain in his shoulder forced him to walk off a mound for the first time in his life.</p>
        <p>But his baseball career survived the journey, and here he is with 18 victories, more than any other major league pitcher, and 4 losses. He is a solid candidate for the American League Cy Young award, his earned run average at 3.37, and he ranks among the league's top 10 in strikeouts and opponents' batting average. ''I'm healthy again,'' he said. ''I've had some perseverance.''</p>
        <p>His grit seems to be tested in each game. The last time he pitched, Cone coped with a large hole on the mound dug by the other pitcher. Tonight, Cone's biggest problem was sweat. Pitching in the hot and humid conditions of his hometown, Cone's uniform and arms and hands were wet by the time he took the mound, sweat glistening off his face and below his Adam's apple.</p>
        <p>He struggled to grip his curveball, slider and split-fingered fastball, and threw a whopping 62 pitches in the first three innings and walked four. In the midst of a Kansas City rally in the third -- the Royals had loaded the bases -- Cone essentially decided to challenge the Royals with his fastball. Here it is; try to hit it. ''It's a lot easier to try and pitch that way,'' he said. ''It's encouraging I had a little pop on my fastball in August.''</p>
        <p>A pop-up and a flyout, and Cone was out of the third. He needed just 46 pitches to get through his final four innings; he allowed five hits in seven innings, striking out four.</p>
        <p>Mel Stottlemyre was the pitching coach for the Mets in 1988, and he is Cone's pitching coach now.</p>
        <p>''He's had the type of season where you win 20 games,'' Stottlemyre said, explaining how, early in the season, the Yankees scored a lot of runs for Cone when he was not pitching well, enabling him to win. ''Things always have to break right for someone to put up those big numbers and win 20 games, no matter who it is.</p>
        <p>''Right now, he's in a good groove, and with the number of starts he has left, he should get it.''</p>
        <p>If the Yankees continue to average more than seven runs a game for Cone, he will get it, and tonight they scored seven exactly.</p>
        <p>The Yankees were vulnerable to left-handed pitching for most of June and into July, when Williams was out with a knee injury. But Williams has come back and Derek Jeter has matured as a hitter, and now the switch-hitting Chili Davis -- who returned to the lineup tonight -- can be the designated hitter against left-handers. Now the Yankees are quite potent against left-handers. Through Saturday's games, in fact, the Yankees' lineup included the league's top four batting averages against lefties: Jorge Posada (.370), Jeter (.368), Scott Brosius (.363) and Williams (.359).</p>
        <p>Those numbers improved against the left-handed Rosado tonight. Leading off the second, Williams -- who closed Sunday's victory at Yankee Stadium with an upper-deck home run -- crushed a fastball an estimated 421 feet to center field, onto the knoll beyond the fence.</p>
        <p>Joe Girardi singled in the fifth and Jeter walked, bringing Davis to the plate with two outs. Rosado had struck out Davis with fastballs in his first two at-bats -- Davis, like most older players, sometimes cannot catch up to a high fastball -- and Rosado started Davis with a high fastball in the fifth, missing high.</p>
        <p>Rosado then made the mistake of throwing the ball low; Davis ripped a single to left-center, Girardi scoring the Yankees' second run. Williams followed that with a run-scoring single, before Martinez hit his three-run homer.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>DAVID CONE needs only 37 innings before a contractual clause, activated when reaches 200 innings, will give him the option of staying with the Yankees for 1999.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
