<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In New Blow to Peace in Ulster, I.R.A. Quits Arms Talks</title>
    <meta content="16ULST" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1176918"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Northern Ireland</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Great Britain</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Irish Republican Army</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoge, Warren</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain/Northern Ireland</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EED81231F935A25751C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1228" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In New Blow to Peace in Ulster, I.R.A. Quits Arms Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WARREN HOGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoge, Warren</byline>
      <dateline>LONDON, Feb. 15</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Irish Republican Army retaliates for Britain's shutdown of power-sharing Northern Ireland government by ending its contact with disarmament mediators and withdrawing newly offered proposals to abandon its weapons; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Irish Republican Army retaliated tonight for Britain's shutdown of the power-sharing Northern Ireland government by ending its contact with disarmament mediators and withdrawing newly offered proposals to abandon its weapons.</p>
        <p>It was a dismaying development for supporters of the peace plan who had been holding meetings throughout the weekend hoping that the new I.R.A. arms initiative would be a basis for restoring the home rule government that was suspended on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Irish Republican Army retaliated tonight for Britain's shutdown of the power-sharing Northern Ireland government by ending its contact with disarmament mediators and withdrawing newly offered proposals to abandon its weapons.</p>
        <p>It was a dismaying development for supporters of the peace plan who had been holding meetings throughout the weekend hoping that the new I.R.A. arms initiative would be a basis for restoring the home rule government that was suspended on Friday.</p>
        <p>But though the I.R.A.'s move constituted a grave setback for the already battered peace accord, it did not appear to signal any return to violence by the I.R.A. Sir Ronnie Flanagan, chief of the Royal Ulster Constabulary, said security forces had no intelligence to indicate that the clandestine army ''intends to re-engage in acts of violence contrary to their stated cessation.''</p>
        <p>The British and Irish prime ministers, Tony Blair and Bertie Ahern, planned an emergency meeting at 10 Downing Street on Wednesday to try to decide how to move forward. They hope to put to rest differences that have arisen between the two governments, both sponsors of the peace talks, over how to deal with the I.R.A.</p>
        <p>John Hume, the Nobel Prize-winning head of the moderate Catholic Social Democratic and Labor Party,  who inspired the current peace effort, sought to put tonight's development into perspective, saying, ''It is not a death knell for the process, but a stumbling block.''</p>
        <p>The I.R.A. announced its decision in a statement defending its resistance to dismantling its arms stockpile. It contended that the real responsibility for the breakdown in the peace plan lay with Britain and the pro-British Ulster Unionist Party, who, it said, have ''no desire to deal with the issue of arms except on their terms.''</p>
        <p>Britain justified its suspension of the two-month-old government on Friday by citing the I.R.A.'s failure to move on weapons even after members of Sinn Fein, its political wing, had been admitted to their ministerial posts in the new administration.</p>
        <p>The I.R.A. maintains that its cease-fire, now in its third year, is proof enough that it is cooperating and argues that as an undefeated army it has no obligation to surrender weapons.</p>
        <p>''Those who seek a military victory in this way need to understand that this cannot and will not happen,'' the statement said. ''Those who have made the political process conditional on the decommissioning of silenced I.R.A. guns are responsible for the current crisis in the peace process.'' Decommissioning is the word used for disarmament in Ulster politics.</p>
        <p>The latest setback in the struggle to bring stability to Ulster stemmed from a bewildering flurry of events on Friday evening when the Northern Ireland secretary, Peter Mandelson, announced that the new Belfast administration was being suspended and that London was reimposing direct rule.</p>
        <p>Minutes before Mr. Mandelson spoke, Gerry Adams, president of Sinn Fein, the political wing of the I.R.A., made a surprise announcement of his own. He said a long-awaited ''major breakthrough'' in the central dispute over guerrilla disarmament had occurred, and he urged Britain to hold off the suspension order.</p>
        <p>Then Gen. John de Chastelain of Canada, head of the independent panel charged with supervising the disarmament of paramilitary groups, confirmed the news in a hurried report, saying the I.R.A. had earlier that day made moves to put their  arms and explosives ''beyond use.''  He portrayed this as ''valuable progress.''</p>
        <p>The hasty new report replaced a far gloomier one by the general on Jan. 31 that said the I.R.A. had shown no willingness to discuss disarmament. The report two weeks ago had dashed widespread expectations that the I.R.A. was going to make a move,  and resulted in feverish but unavailing diplomacy involving London, Dublin, Belfast and Washington aimed at persuading the I.R.A. to start disarming.</p>
        <p>At stake was the continuation of the two-month-old Northern Ireland government created by the peace settlement under a formula that balanced power among republicans and unionists. Republicans, most of whom are Catholic, want to see Ulster more closely linked with the Irish Republic while unionists, who are largely Protestants, want to reinforce the province's British identification.</p>
        <p>After the general's first report that there was no apparent movement from the I.R.A., Britain rushed a suspension law through Parliament with the announced goal of acting by last Friday. The deadline was important because the Ulster Unionist leader, David Trimble, whom Britain considers essential to keeping the unruly Protestant party committed to the peace settlement, faced being ousted that night as head of the Northern Ireland Assembly.</p>
        <p>He had to give his party members a postdated letter of resignation in November in exchange for their agreeing to enter government with Sinn Fein in the absence of any disarmament. The letter, a form of collateral, promised that he would step down if there had been no I.R.A. moves on weapons by Feb. 12.</p>
        <p>The I.R.A., in November, announced that it had established contact with General de Chastelain's commission, a development that set up the anticipation of news of a matching move by the I.R.A in the general's January report. It is that contact that has come to an end, at least temporarily, tonight.</p>
        <p>Pressure mounted on Sinn Fein during the two-week period to produce a cooperative response from the I.R.A., and party leaders complained that they were being unfairly scapegoated for the looming failure. In the past, it has been the unionists who have been pictured as the obstructionists, and Sinn Fein has mounted a furious campaign in recent days to deflect any responsibility for the new breakdown from itself onto the unionists and the British.</p>
        <p>Mr. Adams emerged from a talk with Mr. Mandelson today in Belfast that he described as a ''bad meeting,'' and he was due in London on Wednesday. He said he had ''stretched'' his constituency to the limit. ''As far as we are concerned, we have moved beyond our obligations. We have been morally and politically bound to do all of that, and this Sinn Fein leadership has now no further room to move.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Trimble said he thought that republicans had ''squandered'' the best opportunity to date to settle the vexing problem of arms with their ''precipitate withdrawal'' from disarmament talks. The April 1998 peace agreement, intended to end the sectarian violence that has cost more than 3,600 lives in three decades, specifies May 22 as the date for total disarmament. General de Chastelain's first report said he saw no evidence that the I.R.A. could disarm by then, but his second one on Friday night said he now did.</p>
        <p>Sinn Fein has assailed Mr. Mandelson for disregarding the general's conclusion. Mr. Mandelson says he received the report too late to put off his order and he said he also thought its language too vague a commitment to have forestalled Mr. Trimble's forced resignation. He said the job in the days to come would be to seek ''clarification'' of the I.R.A. proposals, but that was before tonight's withdrawal of the secret proposals themselves.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
