<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Chaplinesque Character, Tripped Up by a Delusion</title>
    <meta content="12DOCT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/12/theater/reviews/12DOCT.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1596156"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL REVIEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Lincoln Center Festival</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genzlinger, Neil</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gabriadze, Rezo</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Baryshnikov, Mikhail</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Devries, Jon</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Doctor and the Patient, The (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Lincoln Center Festival</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Gabriadze, Rezo</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Baryshnikov, Mikhail</person>
        <object.title class="online_producer">Forbidden Christmas, or the Doctor and the Patient (Play)</object.title>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040712T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406E2DC113BF931A25754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="760" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Chaplinesque Character, Tripped Up by a Delusion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Chaplinesque Character, Tripped Up by a Delusion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neil Genzlinger reviews play The Doctor and the Patient, written and directed by Rezo Gabriadze, part of Lincoln Center Festival; Mikhail Baryshnikov star and Jon DeVries star; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Ostensibly, Mikhail Baryshnikov is trying to turn himself into a car in ''Forbidden Christmas, or the Doctor and the Patient,'' a play by Rezo Gabriadze that opened over the weekend at the Lincoln Center Festival. What he is really trying to become, though, is Charlie Chaplin. He doesn't quite make it, but this lightweight fable has diverting moments nonetheless, and it adds another respectable line to Mr. Baryshnikov's amazing résumé.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gabriadze, the internationally known director and puppeteer, says in a program note that he based the story on a real person from his childhood in the republic of Georgia who believed he was a car. Mr. Baryshnikov plays that man, Chito, and the conceit gives him a chance to show off his flexibility and his skill as a mime. When he becomes the car, he vibrates and zips around the stage like the real thing. How authentic looking is this car? Dogs chase it. It may be gimmicky, but it's a pleasure to watch anyway.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>This play about sanity and insanity starring Mikhail Baryshnikov cannot quite escape its gimmickry to achieve true poignancy, though it comes close.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Ostensibly, Mikhail Baryshnikov is trying to turn himself into a car in ''Forbidden Christmas, or the Doctor and the Patient,'' a play by Rezo Gabriadze that opened over the weekend at the Lincoln Center Festival. What he is really trying to become, though, is Charlie Chaplin. He doesn't quite make it, but this lightweight fable has diverting moments nonetheless, and it adds another respectable line to Mr. Baryshnikov's amazing résumé.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gabriadze, the internationally known director and puppeteer, says in a program note that he based the story on a real person from his childhood in the republic of Georgia who believed he was a car. Mr. Baryshnikov plays that man, Chito, and the conceit gives him a chance to show off his flexibility and his skill as a mime. When he becomes the car, he vibrates and zips around the stage like the real thing. How authentic looking is this car? Dogs chase it. It may be gimmicky, but it's a pleasure to watch anyway.</p>
        <p>The story is set in motion by a lovely opening scene in which Chito, a sailor, is returning from the sea, eagerly signaling from the ship by semaphore flag to the woman he has left waiting for him. But we soon come to understand that she has not waited for him at all; she has married someone else. Mr. Gabriadze builds in a perfect time delay here; Chito is a few moments behind the audience in figuring out that he has been abandoned, and in those moments the sense of heartbreak fills the theater.</p>
        <p>That, though, is as close as Mr. Gabriadze gets to the pathos Chaplin's Tramp achieved routinely. Not that he doesn't try; his staging consciously duplicates the creaky feel of a silent movie. The music sounds as if it could have come out of a pre-talkie movie house, and the first words are not spoken for 20 minutes. An explanatory sign is even pulled across the stage as the play begins, reminiscent of the lettered opening sequences of so many silent films.</p>
        <p>Being jilted sends Chito over the edge. First he tries to drown himself, only to be rescued by an angel, and then he finds the window crank from a car on the beach, sending him into his delusion. It lasts years, and his mother seeks the help of a doctor (Jon DeVries). One night, Christmas Eve, Chito tells the doctor that a sick girl needs his help, and they set off in search of her.</p>
        <p>But the doctor has demons of his own, and in the end the play is as much about his struggle as it is about Chito's. Some modest points are made about the fine line between sane and crazy, and about who is better off, the doctor in his real world or Chito in his fantasy.</p>
        <p>The play, which runs tomorrow through Saturday at the John Jay Theater, cannot quite escape the cuteness of Mr. Baryshnikov's car to achieve true poignancy, though it comes close. It has pacing problems, slowing to a near stop a couple of times, and for several stretches Mr. Gabriadze seems more interested in sound effects than story. And it's hard to ignore that the play is undercut by being performed out of season. It is no accident that the story takes place on Christmas Eve, a time of illusion and delusion and hope. The kind of sweet story told here is best sold to an audience that enters the theater already in that magical frame of mind.</p>
        <p>THE DOCTOR AND THE PATIENT</p>
        <p>Written and directed by Rezo Gabriadze; sets, sound collage and costumes by Mr. Gabriadze; lights by Jennifer Tipton; sound by David Meschter; script translation by Ryan McKittrick and Julia Smeliansky; choreographer, Luis Perez; assistant director, Dmitry Troyanovsky; executive producers, Baryshnikov Dance Foundation and David Eden Productions Ltd. John Jay College Theater, 899 10th Avenue, Manhattan.</p>
        <p>WITH: Luis Perez (Ermonia and various roles); Mikhail Baryshnikov (Chito); Pilar Witherspoon (Tsisana and various roles); Yvonne Woods (Mother, Nunu and various roles) and Jon DeVries (The Doctor).</p>
        <p>LINCOLN CENTER FESTIVAL REVIEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
