<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Balancing Success in Schools and a Lie on the Record</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="21" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532321"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDUCATION AND SCHOOLS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PERJURY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SCHOOL ADMINISTRATION AND COMMUNITY ROLE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">UBINAS, WILLIAM E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEBER, BRUCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Perjury</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">School Administration and Community Role</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D81E39F933A05756C0A964958260" item-length="1543" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Balancing Success in Schools and a Lie on the Record</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRUCE WEBER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WEBER, BRUCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>One recent afternoon, William E. Ubinas, the beleaguered superintendent of Manhattan's School District 1, gave a whirlwind tour of his fiefdom, which comprises 18 schools and some 9,500 students on the Lower East Side.</p>
        <p>During the course of a couple of hours, he stopped in four schools and a dozen different classrooms, striding the halls with the loping, loose-limbed gait of an ex-basketball athlete, taking the stairs two and three at a time, picking up litter and working up a serious sweat as he greeted everyone in sight, teachers, parents and students, many of them by name. He was fed bread baked by some 5-year-olds and serenaded by a clarinet-heavy band of 10- and 11-year-olds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>One recent afternoon, William E. Ubinas, the beleaguered superintendent of Manhattan's School District 1, gave a whirlwind tour of his fiefdom, which comprises 18 schools and some 9,500 students on the Lower East Side.</p>
        <p>During the course of a couple of hours, he stopped in four schools and a dozen different classrooms, striding the halls with the loping, loose-limbed gait of an ex-basketball athlete, taking the stairs two and three at a time, picking up litter and working up a serious sweat as he greeted everyone in sight, teachers, parents and students, many of them by name. He was fed bread baked by some 5-year-olds and serenaded by a clarinet-heavy band of 10- and 11-year-olds.</p>
        <p>"This is the good part of the job," he said. "This is what you do it for."</p>
        <p>But his mood was stifled a bit when he stopped in a fourth-grade classroom at Public School 188 on East Houston Street. A boy sitting in the front row looked up from the book he was reading and asked: "Aren't you the guy in the newspaper? They want to take your job away, right?" A Final Ruling Awaits</p>
        <p>Everyone in the neighborhood, it seems, knows Mr. Ubinas (pronounced oo-BEAN-yas) and knows about his problems. Last year, Mr. Ubinas was suspended for two weeks by the district school board because he failed to disclose a 1974 drug conviction on his certification application. He was reinstated by the board after vigorous protest from district parents.</p>
        <p>Then the state began its own investigation and three weeks ago a state Education Department panel recommended that his administrator's certification be revoked. Mr. Ubinas has appealed the three-member panel's decision -- which was not unanimous -- and is now awaiting a final ruling by the State Education Commissioner, Thomas Sobol. If Mr. Sobol goes along with the panel's recommendation, Schools Chancellor Joseph A. Fernandez would be compelled to remove Mr. Ubinas.</p>
        <p>No one contests that Mr. Ubinas, as an 18-year-old college student at Auburn University in Alabama, was convicted of possession of marijuana and sale of cocaine and sentenced to 10 years probation. Nor does anyone dispute that he never said anything about it to the district school board or that on his certification form he answered "no" to the question: Have you ever been convicted of a felony?</p>
        <p>On the other hand, Mr. Ubinas, at 36 the city's youngest district superintendent, seems to have large-scale support among district parents and many teachers, who praise his energy and devotion. Even some of Mr. Ubinas's harshest critics concede that in the two years he has been at his post, he has wrought necessary changes in a school district -- the city's smallest -- that had been plagued by stagnation and a steady egress of students. Advances in the District</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Ubinas arrived in July 1990 from Boston, where he had been an elementary school principal for six years, 14 of the district's 18 schools have signed up for the Chancellor's pet project, school-based management, and the district has implemented a number of new programs, including three alternative early childhood schools.</p>
        <p>The groundwork has been laid for the district's first high school, scheduled to open in September, and Mr. Ubinas has been widely credited for opening the door to businesses that want to collaborate with district schools. Two weeks ago, for example, I.B.M., which supports several programs in the district, designated Public School 142 as "The Technology School" and donated more than $750,000 worth of equipment.</p>
        <p>"Let me put it this way," said John Johnson, a parent interviewed at a noisy rally in support of Mr. Ubinas after the state panel's recommendation. "If you were drowning and I offered a hand to save you, I'm sure you wouldn't care what my past was."</p>
        <p>The issue, said a spokeswoman for Mr. Sobol, Patricia Keegan, is: "Does Mr. Ubinas's perjury on an application form constitute a violation of good moral character?" And thus the question of Mr. Ubinas's character is being debated on the Lower East Side with a vehemence that is extraordinary even by the normally volatile standards of school board politics. Racial Factors Cited</p>
        <p>Not surprisingly, given the character of school politics in the city, the dispute over Mr. Ubinas is given a racial cast by some. He is a native of San Juan, P. R., in a district where 73 percent of the student body is Hispanic. Mr. Ubinas says he thinks the charges against him are racially motivated. His opponents say that even though many in the community have their doubts about the superintendent, he is being protected by them as one of their own.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ubinas's detractors also say that the application form omission, what Mr. Ubinas now refers to as a "lack of judgment," is evidence of a pattern of untrustworthiness. They note that Mr. Ubinas did not confess to the conviction on his application for licenses in Massachusetts either.</p>
        <p>They also note that he involved his former Deputy Superintendent, Anthony Cavanna, in a conflict of interest by having Dr. Cavanna sign a guaranty for a lease on Mr. Ubinas's apartment. The critics also say that Mr. Ubinas has mood swings, forgets promises and bullies subordinates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ubinas and his supporters contend, however, that this is simply his temperament -- aggressive, often overheated -- and that it is how he gets done what he has gotten done.</p>
        <p>"What am I about?" said Mr. Ubinas, who is paid $102,000 a year. "Alternative schools, developmental programs, an integrated curriculum, business patrons, parents as partners, school-based management."</p>
        <p>He said he erred politically by introducing too many programs too quickly. "My point is I don't have a generation to wait," he said. "I don't think it's Bill Ubinas they're after. It's what I stand for. I'm a symbol of change." Board Members Are Split</p>
        <p>Either to his credit or to his detriment, he has not modified his behavior, almost to the extent of courting suspicion.</p>
        <p>"Tony Alvarado is one of my heroes," Mr. Ubinas said, referring to the current superintendent of Manhattan's District 2, also flamboyant and also Puerto Rican, who in 1984 resigned as the city's schools chancellor under shadow of fiscal improprieties. "They say he's arrogant. Well, I'm a little arrogant, too."</p>
        <p>Interviews with some of those who worked with Mr. Ubinas in Boston, at the Blackstone School, a public elementary school, indicate that menacing argumentativeness in pursuit of a progressive agenda was his method there as well. Though no one would speak for attribution, more than one person said that Mr. Ubinas responded to criticism with overbearing anger and that, as one school official put it, "his mood swings went off the charts either way."</p>
        <p>On the Lower East Side, the nine-member community school board is angrily split. Six are unqualified supporters of Mr. Ubinas, two are intractable opponents, and one, D. Perry Brandsten, has maintained a conscience-stricken ambivalence.</p>
        <p>"I'm supporting him somewhat equivocally," Mr. Brandsten said. "He's a good superintendent and we're very likely to do worse with whoever would come next. But every time I feel I'm getting to trust him, something happens that makes me feel I can't." 'What Do They Win?'</p>
        <p>The "character" debate begins with whether Mr. Ubinas knowingly lied about his criminal record. He has offered a dual explanation, which he reiterated in an interview, first that he thought the criminal record had been sealed and second that it had happened so long ago he had simply put it behind him.</p>
        <p>Edward F. Stancik, the special commissioner of investigations for the New York City school district, for one, thinks Mr. Ubinas fabricated the closed-record defense.</p>
        <p>"When we first interviewed him, he never made that defense," Mr. Stancik said. In March 1991, a few months after Mr. Ubinas's 1974 arrest was reported by the F.B.I. to the Board of Education, through a standard fingerprint check, Mr. Ubinas, who served four of the 10 years of his probationary sentence, applied to close his record.</p>
        <p>Also within weeks of the F.B.I. report, Mr. Ubinas interviewed for the headmaster's job at the Baldwin School in his hometown of San Juan.  He was offered the job in a letter dated Jan. 18, 1991. In an interview, Mr. Ubinas said he did not take the job because he decided "I'm not going to run."</p>
        <p>By far the most serious, and most persistent, allegation against Mr. Ubinas is that he still uses cocaine or was using it at the time he came to New York. The drug rumors are widely discussed in the school district and were one of the focuses of the city school district's investigation. Mr. Stancik said there is no evidence of drug use. Mr. Ubinas categorically and vociferously denies any drug use since his conviction.</p>
        <p>Mr. Ubinas calls the charges against him "character assassinations," motivated by board members who initially supported him but, he said, then discovered they could not push him around. After a year of battling, now on the brink of the state commissioner's decision about his future, he conceded that "sometimes it's tough to get up in the morning."</p>
        <p>"If I lose my certificate," he said, angrily, but with a hint of desperation and despair, "what do they win? What do they win?"</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
