<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>To Help Itself, Utility Aids Riot Area</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="33" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="532349"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DEMONSTRATIONS AND RIOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTRIC LIGHT AND POWER</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">LOS ANGELES (CALIF)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA EDISON CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California/Los Angeles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Demonstrations and Riots</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Light</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Electric Light and Power</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Energy and Power</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920530T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DC163AF933A05756C0A964958260" item-length="1402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>To Help Itself, Utility Aids Riot Area</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD W. STEVENSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">STEVENSON, RICHARD W</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, May 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the Southern California Edison Company, the response to last month's riots did not end when it finally got the power back on.</p>
        <p>The utility, whose profits from selling electricity are directly dependent on the economic health of the Los Angeles area, saw that the unrest would be another blow to the long-term prospects of the region. The area was already being hurt by a severe recession and by a flight of companies and jobs to other states.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the Southern California Edison Company, the response to last month's riots did not end when it finally got the power back on.</p>
        <p>The utility, whose profits from selling electricity are directly dependent on the economic health of the Los Angeles area, saw that the unrest would be another blow to the long-term prospects of the region. The area was already being hurt by a severe recession and by a flight of companies and jobs to other states.</p>
        <p>The riots also made clear to corporate leaders the severity of the city's social problems, giving Edison a troubling glimpse of what the future holds if nothing is done to give inner-city residents more economic hope.</p>
        <p>So within two weeks of the rioting, the utility put together what is so far the biggest corporate financial commitment to improving conditions in some of the area's most blighted neighborhoods. The plan is to contribute $35 million worth of cash, buildings, labor and services over the next five years to create job training centers, support educational and charitable programs, and help businesses devastated by looting and arson.</p>
        <p>"We as a company will be successful only if the region is vibrant, and the region will be vibrant and healthy only if companies like ours assume some responsibility for leadership," said John E. Bryson, the chairman of Edison and its parent company, SCEcorp.</p>
        <p>Southern California Edison's response is an example of what government officials and economic development experts call enlightened corporate self-interest. If they are to succeed in building a stronger economic foundation for the poor neighborhoods of Los Angeles and other cities, those officials said, they will need to persuade many more companies to adopt that kind of attitude -- and then do more.</p>
        <p>Government officials have long looked to corporations to play a greater role in shoring up schools, providing jobs and job training and financing charities and community development efforts. But perhaps never before have corporations been so directly challenged by government officials and community leaders to make a lasting difference as they have in the wake of the Los Angeles riots.</p>
        <p>And although they express their thanks for programs like Edison's, government and community leaders ultimately want the business community to do more than make charitable contributions. They want companies to open factories, distribution centers and other operations in poor neighborhoods as a means of creating jobs for local residents and a strong framework for further economic growth. Opportunity for Profit</p>
        <p>In return, they acknowledge that government must work harder to give companies greater opportunity to make a profit from their investments in the inner city. No matter how civic-minded, they said, no company will stay long in any area if it is losing money.</p>
        <p>"Corporate America has to come together on a sustained, long-term basis to create opportunities that are money-making for them and that create jobs as well as real ownership possibilities for disadvantaged people," said Mark Fabiani, a Deputy Mayor of Los Angeles. "Anything short of that means failure."</p>
        <p>Mr. Fabiani said a number of large companies had already offered to open new factories or other operations in the area to create jobs. But none have made public announcements, and Mr. Fabiani declined to identify them. He said that the companies, local governments and the privately financed Rebuild L.A. effort headed by Peter V. Ueberroth, the former baseball commissioner, first wanted to study issues such as community support, tax breaks and low-interest loans that would give the companies a better chance of being successful in the long run.</p>
        <p>"Our goal has to be to convince corporations that these investments are in their best interests, that they are essential to their interests," Mr. Fabiani said. "They have to know that the investments will be profitable and ultimately advantageous to their shareholders."</p>
        <p>But Mr. Fabiani and others said it was unclear how many companies would be willing to make substantial investments in new operations in South-Central Los Angeles and other poor communities, especially once the publicity surrounding the unrest faded away along with the urgency of dealing with the underlying problems. 'Project for Marathoners'</p>
        <p>For every company that can identify a reason to make large-scale investments in improving the inner city, there clearly are many more that see little direct benefit to themselves in taking on the problems of security, insurance and an inexperienced work force by establishing some kind of permanent presence in a blighted area like South-Central Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>"This is a long-haul game, a project for marathoners," said Jon P. Goodman, the director of the Entrepreneur Program at the University of Southern California, who has worked extensively in aiding businesses in the inner city. "What I am really waiting to see is whether, after the crisis, after the pressure of the recent events abates, they are still there, still rolling these projects out."</p>
        <p>There are limits, in fact, to what even socially active companies like Edison are willing and able to take on, especially when it comes to actually creating new jobs in the areas that most need them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bryson said Edison would try to step up hiring efforts to some extent in poor communities. Yet Edison, which like many large corporations has been reducing its work force, decided it could not prudently make a commitment to hiring any substantial number of people in coming years from the neighborhoods affected by the rioting, he said.</p>
        <p>Edison is instead concentrating much of its effort on job training programs. As part of its $35 million plan, it is allocating $6.5 million to developing such programs in Compton and Long Beach, two of the communities hardest hit by the rioting. In Compton, the company is donating an unused building it owns and will pay for it to be renovated and then finance the center's operations. The company expects the center to provide job training for hundreds of people each year. Forgiving Utility Bills</p>
        <p>The company plans to contribute $7.5 million in cash, equipment and technical expertise to various charities, economic development efforts and community organizations, and increase by $500,000 the $2.25 million it had previously planned to spend on a program to help "at risk" students in local schools. To help owners of homes and businesses destroyed in the rioting, the company will forgive bills owed to it by those owners and will provide low-interest loans toward the purchase of energy-efficient equipment as they rebuild.</p>
        <p>Edison will also make a multimillion-dollar donation to Rebuild L.A. And the company said it was still seeking suggestions from community leaders on how to spend an as-yet unallocated portion of the $35 million.</p>
        <p>"As an electric utility, we have a network of wires, but also a network of people in all of the affected communities," said Robert H. Bridenbecker, Edison's vice president for customer service. "We're talking to leaders in each community to see what's needed."</p>
        <p>For the most part, he said, the answers have centered on help in creating jobs and in improving education. But the company has also tried to address narrower and more immediate needs by soliciting employee suggestions.</p>
        <p>Ed Robinson, an energy services representative in Compton, suggested after talking to many customers that Edison provide some employees to help small-business owners fill out the complex forms needed to apply for assistance from the Small Business Administration. He is also pushing for the company to help involve gang members, unwed mothers and other disenfranchised residents in deciding how to address the community's problems. Key Is Involvement</p>
        <p>Economic development specialists say the key to any company's sustained efforts at community improvement is the involvement of employees. Edison executives concede that some employees oppose the spending of $35 million to address inner-city problems, especially at a time when the company is cutting employment. But over all, they said, employee support and involvement have been strong.</p>
        <p>"I was around after the Watts riots in '65, and I saw a lot of Band-Aid solutions," said Bill Thomas, an area manager in Compton. "I see some of the things we are doing now as having positive long-term effects."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
