<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Winning Ways With Winter Squash</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="642232"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931017T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDB133DF934A25753C1A965958260" item-length="830" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Winning Ways With Winter Squash</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE farm stands and markets are now overflowing with brightly colored winter squashes. Summer squashes, mostly thin-skinned yellow ones or types of zucchini in green or gold, are more delicate than the sturdy, thick-skinned winter varieties.</p>
        <p>Fall's crop ranges in color from nearly white to yellow, orange, green and even, in the case of some Hubbard varieties, battleship gray and blue. They come striped and solid. Some are round, some elongated and some are deeply ridged. There are squashes with smooth skins and others that are warty. They may be perfectly symmetrical or lopsided.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE farm stands and markets are now overflowing with brightly colored winter squashes. Summer squashes, mostly thin-skinned yellow ones or types of zucchini in green or gold, are more delicate than the sturdy, thick-skinned winter varieties.</p>
        <p>Fall's crop ranges in color from nearly white to yellow, orange, green and even, in the case of some Hubbard varieties, battleship gray and blue. They come striped and solid. Some are round, some elongated and some are deeply ridged. There are squashes with smooth skins and others that are warty. They may be perfectly symmetrical or lopsided.</p>
        <p>Most winter squashes have sweet, yellow to deep orange flesh, relatively big seeds and thick skins. They can be baked or boiled until tender, then pureed to serve as a side dish, to make into a souffle or soup or to use for filling pasta. The puree is also suitable for breads and muffins. Pumpkin belongs to this family.</p>
        <p>Cubes of peeled, seeded squash from meaty kinds like butternut can be seasoned and baked without par-cooking.</p>
        <p>Smaller squashes, including a number of new types like delicata and kabachi, can be par-baked, then stuffed and baked again before serving. Golden nugget, a tiny orange variety, which looks like a miniature pumpkin, is also good for this. Once an oddity, spaghetti squash is now widely available. It has a smooth, oval shape and is pale yellow in color; its mild-tasting cooked flesh comes out in strings, hence its name.</p>
        <p>Winter squashes keep well. And while they are often served sweetened, almost any seasoning suits them. Try giving them a whiff of Italy with garlic and olive oil or spice them Mexican style. And if you have a large squash or pumpkin on your hands, you can cook the whole thing, use what you need, then puree and freeze the rest for future recipes. Squash Soup With Fennel Total time: 1 1/2 hours  1 large bulb fennel  2 tablespoons unsalted butter  1/2 cup chopped onion  1 teaspoon fennel seeds, pulverized  4 1/2 cups Hubbard or butternut squash, in 2-inch cubes  4 1/2 cups vegetable stock or water  1 1/2 cups milk  Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Trim stems from fennel bulb. Chop and reserve a tablespoon and a half of the leaves. Discard the rest of the stems. Chop the fennel bulb.</p>
        <p>2. Heat the butter in a heavy saucepan. Add the chopped fennel bulb and the onion. Cover and place over medium-low heat for about 15 minutes, until the vegetables are tender. Check and stir them from time to time to see that they do not brown.</p>
        <p>3. Stir in the fennel seeds and the squash. Add the stock, cover and simmer until the squash is tender, about 40 minutes. Allow the mixture to cool about 15 minutes, then puree it in one or two batches in a food processor.</p>
        <p>4. Return puree to saucepan and add milk. Reheat. Season to taste with salt and pepper. Serve garnished with reserved chopped fennel tops.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings. Baked Spaghetti Squash Total time: 1 hour  1 spaghetti squash  1/4 cup extra-virgin olive oil  4 cloves garlic, minced  6 ripe plum tomatoes, chopped  3 tablespoons minced fresh basil leaves  Salt and freshly ground black pepper to taste  1/2 cup freshly grated Parmesan cheese  1/4 cup bread crumbs.</p>
        <p>1. Place the squash in a large pot with water to cover, bring to a boil and cook until the squash is tender, about 40 minutes.</p>
        <p>2. While the squash is cooking, heat a tablespoon of the oil in a large skillet, add the garlic and saute until the garlic is golden. Add the tomatoes, heat through, then remove from the heat and set aside.</p>
        <p>3. When the squash is tender, cut it in half and scoop out the seeds. Using a large metal spoon, scoop out the flesh -- it will come out in spaghetti-like strands -- and transfer it to the skillet with the garlic. Mix with the tomato and garlic mixture and add the basil and the remaining olive oil. Season to taste with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>4. Just before serving, preheat a broiler. Reheat the squash and transfer it to a shallow baking dish. Sprinkle the top with the Parmesan cheese and bread crumbs.</p>
        <p>5. Place baking dish under broiler, at least four inches from source of heat; brown top lightly, then serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 to 6 servings. Mexican Squash Total time: 50 minutes  4 cups butternut, acorn or Hubbard squash, in 1-inch cubes  1 teaspoon ground cumin  1/2 teaspoon ground cinnamon  1/4 teaspoon cayenne pepper, or to taste  Salt to taste  1 cup fresh or frozen corn kernels  4 tablespoons olive oil  3/4 cup finely chopped fresh coriander leaves  Juice of 1 lime.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 400 degrees.</p>
        <p>2. Toss the squash in a bowl with the cumin, cinnamon, cayenne pepper and salt. Mix in the corn kernels. Add the oil and coriander and mix again.</p>
        <p>3. Transfer mixture to shallow baking dish and place in oven. Bake about 25 minutes, until squash is tender.</p>
        <p>4. Sprinkle with lime juice and serve.</p>
        <p>Yield: 3 to 4 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
