<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Conversations/Stanley Crouch; A Jazz Critic Stretches His Solos, Not Caring Who Winces in Pain</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="631682"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MACARTHUR, JOHN D AND CATHERINE T, FOUNDATION</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">RICHARDSON, LYNDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CROUCH, STANLEY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE1D7133FF93AA1575BC0A965958260" item-length="1201" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Conversations/Stanley Crouch; A Jazz Critic Stretches His Solos, Not Caring Who Winces in Pain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNDA RICHARDSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">RICHARDSON, LYNDA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE words tumble out urgently, often poetically, from a man whose spiritual tattoo is jazz. He sees himself as the voice of the people rather than as the provocateur that some think he is.</p>
        <p>"I've been applauded by black bus drivers, subway drivers, mechanics, various people who have come up to me and said, 'I'm sure glad somebody is saying it.' That's enough for me. I don't care what some trickle-down Negro Marxist says. That means nothing to me. And I don't care what some confused group of what a friend calls 'lumpen bourgeoisie middle-class black folks who want to be street' say."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE words tumble out urgently, often poetically, from a man whose spiritual tattoo is jazz. He sees himself as the voice of the people rather than as the provocateur that some think he is.</p>
        <p>"I've been applauded by black bus drivers, subway drivers, mechanics, various people who have come up to me and said, 'I'm sure glad somebody is saying it.' That's enough for me. I don't care what some trickle-down Negro Marxist says. That means nothing to me. And I don't care what some confused group of what a friend calls 'lumpen bourgeoisie middle-class black folks who want to be street' say."</p>
        <p>For more than 20 years, Stanley Crouch, who is best known for his extensive writings on jazz, has been spinning out prose on subjects as varied as race, politics, literature and culture. His judgments are more than a bit contrarian, and often harsh.</p>
        <p>His targets have included Louis Farrakhan, Malcolm X and Stokely Carmichael. He's called Spike Lee a "nappy headed Napoleon" and Toni Morrison a "literary conjure woman."</p>
        <p>He derides a host of contemporary black women writers, including Ms. Morrison, Alice Walker and Ntozake Shange, saying they have manipulated the guilt of whites, and have taken over "the role played by the black maids in so many old films: when poor little white missy is at a loss, she is given guidance by an Aunt Jemima look-alike."</p>
        <p>He argues that all people, regardless of color or gender, have to be held to the same standards. He favors affirmative action "until they figure out something better to do," but gives scant attention to complaints that he ignores institutionalized white racism.</p>
        <p>"They don't need me to say that over and over," he said. "They can get that from James Baldwin."</p>
        <p>While his critics dismiss him as a conservative, even some of them have a grudging respect for his knowledge of music and black culture. And his admirers, like Ralph Ellison, author of " Invisible Man," say he cannot be easily categorized. "He makes the most of his Americanness," Mr. Ellison said. "He's irreverent. He questions the views of both liberals and conservatives, and that's what critics should do."</p>
        <p>Mr. Crouch suffers the scorn with a shrug of his heavy shoulders. "I usually write something I think is true, and if in the process it's provocative, it's too bad." A MacArthur Grant</p>
        <p>But the 47-year-old essayist, one of this year's recipients of a $296,000 MacArthur Foundation "genius" grant, said he is wearied by the arguments being bandied about by "intellectual court jesters in academia."</p>
        <p>"A lot of the discussions on race are extraordinarily inaccurate," he said. "Usually, it's simple-minded and overly influenced by the ideas of determinism -- if you're poor, you're going to act a certain way."</p>
        <p>He grew up poor in Los Angeles, the son of a drug-addicted criminal and a domestic worker. He was able to break out of that cycle largely because, he said, his public school teachers took no excuses.</p>
        <p>"These people were on a mission. They had a perfect philosophy: you WILL learn this. If you came in there and said, 'I'm from a dysfunctional family and a single parent household,' they would say, 'Boy, I'm going to ask you again. What is 8 times 8?'</p>
        <p>"When I was coming up, there were no excuses except your house burned down and there was a murder in the family. Eight times eight was going to be 64 whether your family was dysfunctional or not. It's something you needed to know!"</p>
        <p>He came to politics slowly, through art. As a child, he had posters of Dizzy Gillespie "hanging everywhere," formed a jazz club in high school and was an actor and director with the Watts Repertory Theatre. In the wake of the Watts riots of 1965, he was caught up in the black nationalist movement. But he "became a traitor" to it later because he was bored with its militant strategies.</p>
        <p>The movement, he wrote, "helped send not only black America but this nation itself into an intellectual tailspin on the subjects of race, of culture, of heritage. Where there was not outright foolishness, there was a mongering of the maudlin and a base opportunism."</p>
        <p>He found himself lured to writers like Mr. Ellison, Albert Murray and others whose works had an all-inclusive vision of America rather than one of cultural separatism.</p>
        <p>Many of the essays in his first book, "Notes of a Hanging Judge" (Oxford University Press, 1990), originally ran in The Village Voice, where he was a staff writer.</p>
        <p>He was dismissed several years ago after punching out another Voice writer, Harry Allen, in an argument over, among other things, rap music.</p>
        <p>Their relations have mended, but Mr. Crouch is now a freelance curmudgeon and high-brow, as always, when it comes to music. He still dismisses rap, saying: "It's either an infantile self-celebration or anarchic glamorization of criminal behavior. I don't see what's good about it."</p>
        <p>His interests are as eclectic as his treatises. He is a founder of Jazz at Lincoln Center and is working with the trumpeter Wynton Marsalis on a television mini-series about jazz. He is writing a biography of Charlie Parker and has written 500 pages of a novel, "First Snow in Kokomo," a first-person narrative which uses the "destruction of the civil rights movement by black power as a metaphor for the international problem of tribalism." His third book of essays, "Affirmation and Attack," is to be published in 1995.  'On My Stuff'</p>
        <p>"When I'm on my stuff, I'm ready for anybody out there who writes," said Mr. Crouch, who hopes the recognition from the MacArthur Foundation will let him develop even more virtuosity. "I have a wild side to my personality. I'm not always the Cub Scout leader that I'd like most adults to be, sometimes in ways that are surprising to myself. I can get lower than a snake in wagon tracks. I can do things that are kind of strange. I think a lot of life is about seeking forms of redemption."</p>
        <p>The money, he said, will make it easier to raise his 15-year-old daughter, who recently moved into the Greenwich Village apartment he shares with his fiance, a sculptor. He plans to enroll her in Horace Mann, an expensive private school in the Bronx.</p>
        <p>Of public schools, he said "If they had teachers like the ones who taught me when I was going to school, I'd put her in one right now."</p>
        <p>Public schools, he said, have become "spiritual fly-traps" and America's decaying inner cities are overdue for an "incredible clean-up." Too much time is squandered, he said, casting young black males who commit crimes as victims themselves.</p>
        <p>"Those people who do these things represent less than one percent of the community of black youth. They don't define anything other than criminality. The victims are the people on the receiving end of the criminal action, not them."</p>
        <p>On the ground level, he said, black people do not care much about the theories on race mouthed by academics.</p>
        <p>"They match the crime with the criminal. There are certain things you have to have. You cannot have a civilization and have anarchy. You can't have criminals feel safe. You can't have babies having babies. You can't have substandard public schools. To me, that's not way out. What's way out is to have these lawless murderous areas in cities."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
