<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Horse Racing Notebook; Java Gold Retired As Comeback Fails</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19880830T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="174276"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HORSE RACING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">THOROUGHBRED RACING</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CRIST, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Horse Racing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880826T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5D71139F935A1575BC0A96E948260" item-length="888" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Horse Racing Notebook; Java Gold Retired As Comeback Fails</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN CRIST, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CRIST, STEVEN</byline>
      <dateline>SARATOGA SPRINGS, N.Y., Aug. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''It would take a miracle for Java Gold to make it back to the races,'' Paul Mellon said last week, and today owner of Rokeby Stable announced he had stopped waiting for one. The broken foot that cost Java Gold the Horse of the Year title last season has ended his racing career, and he is being retired to stud.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''It would take a miracle for Java Gold to make it back to the races,'' Paul Mellon said last week, and today owner of Rokeby Stable announced he had stopped waiting for one. The broken foot that cost Java Gold the Horse of the Year title last season has ended his racing career, and he is being retired to stud.</p>
        <p>''It would take a miracle for Java Gold to make it back to the races,'' Paul Mellon said last week, and today owner of Rokeby Stable announced he had stopped waiting for one. The broken foot that cost Java Gold the Horse of the Year title last season has ended his racing career, and he is being retired to stud.</p>
        <p>Java Gold, the 4-year-old son of Key to the Mint and Javamine, was New York's most popular colt last year, when he bloomed in the late summer. Knocked out of the spring classics by a virus, Java Gold returned in July and scored consecutive Grade I victories in the Whitney Handicap, the Travers Stakes and the Marlboro Cup. He then fractured the wing of the coffin bone in his right front foot during the running of the Jockey Club Gold Cup, where he continued on bravely to finish second in what turned out to be his final career start.</p>
        <p>He tantalized his trainer, Mack Miller, by coming within days of a complete recovery this summer. The bone appeared healed, but the colt was having nerve trouble in the foot. Twice this summer, he strung together several promising workouts, but went lame again when things looked their brightest.</p>
        <p>''He was the best and most exciting horse I ever trained,'' Miller said today.</p>
        <p>Java Gold won 9 of 15 career starts and earned $1,908,832. Rivalry Continues</p>
        <p>Alysheba and Bet Twice, who carved up last year's Triple Crown but then finished far behind Java Gold in the Travers, resume their rivalry Saturday in the $500,000 Iselin Handicap at Monmouth Park.</p>
        <p>Alysheba, making his first Eastern appearance since the Travers, carries 124 pounds as he attempts to rebound from two straight defeats. Bet Twice, who carries 123, has lost his last three. Gulch (122), Slew City Slew (116), Bolshoi Boy (115), Back Bay Banquet (114) and Make a Decision (107) complete the field of seven.</p>
        <p>The medication merry-go-round takes another turn in the Iselin when Alysheba, who won last year's Kentucky Derby and Preakness with the help of Lasix, races without it for the first time this year. Bet Twice, who finished second in those two races and won the Belmont Stakes without medication, has now added Lasix to his equipment. Slew City Slew, Bolshoi Boy and Back Bay Banquet will also run with Lasix.</p>
        <p>This will be the eighth meeting between the two colts. Alysheba finished in front of Bet Twice the first three times they met, but Bet Twice has come out on top the last four times.</p>
        <p>Alysheba may take on Forty Niner and Brian's Time in the Woodward at Belmont Sept. 17 if he runs well without Lasix Saturday, but plans for Bet Twice are uncertain because of his newly medicated status.</p>
        <p>The Iselin, at a mile and an eighth with a $500,000 purse, will be televised by ESPN on a one-hour broadcast beginning at 5 P.M. Post time is scheduled for 5:30 P.M. Stars to Miss Hopeful</p>
        <p>The Hopeful Stakes at Saratoga Saturday, the year's first Grade I race for 2-year-olds, drew a field of seven yesterday. Missing are the two quickest 2-year-olds to have raced in New York this season: Houston, the Seattle Slew colt who is nursing sore shins, and Easy Goer, the son of Alydar who is being pointed for longer races while a stablemate, Fast Play, tries the Hopeful.</p>
        <p>Trapp Mountain, the son of Cox's Ridge who won the Saratoga Special on Aug. 5 to stay undefeated in two starts, is a shade the best and the one to beat Saturday. Trapp Mountain showed versatility by winning his debut from far back, and the Special after battling for the lead. The quality of the Special was confirmed when Bio, the runner-up, won the Sapling at Monmouth in his next start.</p>
        <p>Trapp Mountain's six opponents in the six-and-a-half-furlong Hopeful are Mercedes Won and Leading Prospect, first and second in that order in the Sanford here Aug. 17; Fast Play, a son of Seattle Slew and half brother to Seeking the Gold, who won his debut by 10 lengths in the slop Aug. 15; Harperstown, a Devil's Bag colt who won by six lengths on a sloppy track here Aug. 6, and the Leroy Jolley-trained entry of Commendably and Even Faster, both unimpressive winners of five-furlong races here this month. Family Affair</p>
        <p>The featured Seneca Handicap at Saratoga today became a family affair when Fuller's Folly held off El Senor to win by a neck at 32-1. Fuller's Folly was bred by, owned by and named for Peter Fuller of Boston, and was ridden by his daughter, Abigail.</p>
        <p>Fuller's Folly is a 5-year-old gelding by Affirmed and the Pia Star mare Eastman Star. He got his name when Fuller tried to sell him as a yearling, with a reserve price of $100,000. Through a mix-up at the sale, the colt was sold for $50,000, and Fuller had to spend $55,000 to buy him back.</p>
        <p>''When we got him home, we decided this was indeed Fuller's Folly,'' Fuller recalled recently. Today, Fuller's Folly paid $66.60 for $2 to win. Graustark Dead at 19</p>
        <p>Graustark, the Darby Dan Farm stallion who sired 48 stakes winners, including Proud Truth, died last Sunday at the age of 19. . . . The Hopeful card here Saturday will also feature the Saratoga Breeders' Cup, a Grade III race for the first time this year. Steinlen, Wanderkin and Real Courage head a field of 10 going a mile and a sixteenth on the grass. . . . Scarlet Ibis and Valid Case head a field of eight New York-bred 2-year-olds in the featured Empire Stakes Friday.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 30, 1988, Tuesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>He was 25.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 30, 1988, Tuesday, Late City Final Edition</p>
        <p>He was 25.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
