<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Williamsburg Bridge Is Shut For 2 Weeks as Cracks Are Found</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="135661"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BRIDGES AND TUNNELS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ROADS AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ACCIDENTS AND SAFETY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUBWAYS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DELAYS (TRANSPORTATION)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRANSIT SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MANHATTAN (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BROOKLYN (NYC)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">WILLIAMSBURG BRIDGE</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LYALL, SARAH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Subways</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Delays (Transportation)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bridges and Tunnels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Roads and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transportation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880413T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE1D8113BF930A25757C0A96E948260" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Williamsburg Bridge Is Shut For 2 Weeks as Cracks Are Found</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SARAH LYALL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LYALL, SARAH</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: The crumbling Williamsburg Bridge, which 240,000 commuters depend on for passage between Brooklyn and Manhattan each day, was closed to all traffic last night and will not open for at least two weeks.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: The crumbling Williamsburg Bridge, which 240,000 commuters depend on for passage between Brooklyn and Manhattan each day, was closed to all traffic last night and will not open for at least two weeks.</p>
        <p>The crumbling Williamsburg Bridge, which 240,000 commuters depend on for passage between Brooklyn and Manhattan each day, was closed to all traffic last night and will not open for at least two weeks.</p>
        <p>The 85-year-old structure, the oldest steel bridge in New York City, has become the most striking example of the long neglect of the city's bridges. Last May, a six-foot section of a beam on the bridge's deck plunged into the East River, leaving a gaping hole in one of its outer roadways and illustrating the urgency of the problem.</p>
        <p>The New York City Transportation Commissioner, Ross Sandler, said last night that engineers studying the bridge for the last several weeks found further corrosion yesterday, and at 9:30 P.M. decided ''it would be most prudent to shut the bridge until they have completed their inspection.''</p>
        <p>All motor vehicles have been banned and service on the M and J subway lines over the bridge has been suspended. People may still walk or ride bicycles across the bridge, he said.</p>
        <p>The department's chief engineer, Samuel I. Schwartz, said there was a 5 percent chance there would have been ''a failure at a given section'' of the bridge had it remained in use.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sandler said he believed it was the first time a major New York bridge has been completely closed for repairs.</p>
        <p>The closing is expected to cause major traffic snarls between Manhattan and Brooklyn, where traffic has already been clogged because of construction work on roadways and repairs being made on the other bridges between Manhattan and Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>Two lanes each in the Manhattan Bridge and the Queensboro Bridge are closed; the Brooklyn Bridge is fully open.</p>
        <p>Mr. Sandler advised people to use carpools and to take public transportation. ''Don't drive alone,'' he said.  With the M and J lines out of commission, The Transit Authority is advising commuters to take the L, A and C lines, which go through tunnels between the two boroughs.</p>
        <p>Service on the L line is being nearly doubled, and additional cars are being added to C trains to handle the larger crowds, said a Transit Authority spokesman, Termaine Garden.</p>
        <p>Officials said that inspections on the bridge were about 40 percent complete, and that they would try to correct the problems as they found them.</p>
        <p>''The most optimistic scenario, and an unlikely one, is that we find no further problems and we make concurrent repairs,'' Mr. Schwartz said. ''Should we find additional problems, the bridge will be closed even longer.''</p>
        <p>But he said all of the problems on the bridge were ''manageable and correctible.''</p>
        <p>The decision to close the bridge, which Mr. Schwartz described as ''torturous,'' was made after teams of inspectors found cracks and perforations along a 20-foot floor beam on one of the inner roadways at the Manhattan end of the bridge. Previously, they had discovered cracks in beams on the outer roadways and under the subway tracks, and corrosion in the cables.</p>
        <p>''We realized there are cracks on beams in every roadway'' on the bridge, Mr. Schwartz said. The discovery made the risk of an accident ''unacceptably high,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Under Federal law, bridges must be inspected every two years. The Williamsburg Bridge was last inspected by state contractors in 1985 and 1986, and was approved as safe. The inspection results were being reviewed, Mr. Sandler said.</p>
        <p>Officials have been closing the bridge in bits and pieces for the last several weeks. Four of the eight roadways were closed, at different times, when inspectors uncovered increasing examples of decay. When corrosion was discovered in the floor beams under the train tracks on Monday, subway service was suspended. More Damage Found</p>
        <p>The closing comes amid concern that all the major bridges in the city are ailing, with the Williamsburg Bridge as the most egregious example.</p>
        <p>It is in such poor condition that city officials are now trying to decide whether to repair it, which would cost well over $250 million, or to replace it alogether, at an even greater cost.</p>
        <p>The Williamsburg Bridge is generally regarded as a case study on how not to maintain a bridge. It has a number of problems: decayed steel towers, deteriorated beams, rusted and worn walkways and roadways and four large cables woven from 7,696 steel wires that have been corroding steadily. Bridge Reconstruction</p>
        <p>The Williamsburg Bridge Technical Advisory Committee, a city and state advisory group formed last summer, is due to report its decision to Mayor Koch and Governor Cuomo by July 1.</p>
        <p>The Williamsburg Bridge is among 2,098 large and small bridges in New York City. The city is in the midst of a repair program that seeks to restore about 400 bridges that are rated in poor or fair condition. About 100 are to be replaced.</p>
        <p>Thirty-two city bridges are now partly closed for safety reasons, Mr. Sandler said.</p>
        <p>Among those being refurbished are the three other major East River crossings: the Manhattan, Queensboro and Brooklyn Bridges.</p>
        <p>Last month, city and state officials closed a viaduct of the Van Wyck Expressway in Flushing, Queens, when inspectors discovered that three of five steel stringers were corroded and the roadbed was in danger of collapsing. The closing affected for several days a one-third mile stretch of the road between Northern Boulevard and the Whitestone Expressway. More Problems</p>
        <p>The bars anchoring the cables of the Manhattan Bridge are deteriorating, and the steel stringers on the Queensboro Bridge are corroded, as are the steel columns of the Queens Boulevard Bridge.</p>
        <p>In addition, the concrete deck and supporting floor beams have deteriorated on the Washington Bridge, which crosses the Harlem River and connects the Bronx and upper Manhattan. And cracks mar the grating of the Madison Avenue Bridge, which also connects the Bronx and Manhattan.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
