<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bush's Roles on World Stage: Triumphs, but Troubles, Too</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Bush Record -- Second article of a series." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="538816"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1992 CAMPAIGN"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920626T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2D91630F935A15755C0A964958260" item-length="2610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bush's Roles on World Stage: Triumphs, but Troubles, Too</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS L. FRIEDMAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FRIEDMAN, THOMAS L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Conventional wisdom holds that there are two George Bushes: the skilled architect of foreign policy and the neglectful caretaker of domestic affairs. Even some people on the Bush team have come to cultivate this image, since it allows them to explain away the President's shortcomings at home by saying he was too busy saving the world abroad.</p>
        <p>But in fact George Bush has also shown at least two personalities in his conduct of the nation's foreign policy. He has often really been the consummate seasoned statesman, but at other times he has seemed distracted and ineffective in a world undergoing dizzying change.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Conventional wisdom holds that there are two George Bushes: the skilled architect of foreign policy and the neglectful caretaker of domestic affairs. Even some people on the Bush team have come to cultivate this image, since it allows them to explain away the President's shortcomings at home by saying he was too busy saving the world abroad.</p>
        <p>But in fact George Bush has also shown at least two personalities in his conduct of the nation's foreign policy. He has often really been the consummate seasoned statesman, but at other times he has seemed distracted and ineffective in a world undergoing dizzying change.</p>
        <p>There was the George Bush who, working the telephones and personal contacts with other heads of state, skillfully managed the Western alliance's response to the cataclysmic revolutions in Eastern Europe and the Soviet Union, helping to insure that one of this century's great upheavals went off relatively peacefully. 'We Should Get Credit'</p>
        <p>There was the George Bush who was the galvanizing force in building an international coalition to roll back the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait and strip Baghdad of its weapons of mass destruction.</p>
        <p>And there was the George Bush who encouraged his Secretary of State, James A. Baker 3d, to bring together the first full-scale peace talks between Israel and all its Arab neighbors. More recently, it was the George Bush who with Mr. Baker negotiated sweeping nuclear arms cuts with the Russians that were highly advantageous to Washington.</p>
        <p>"I think we'd get blamed if things went wrong," Mr. Bush said in an interview, assessing his record; therefore, "we should get credit if they've gone right, and they've gone right. I think handling the changes inside what used to be the Soviet Union has been good, and I am very pleased that ancient enemies are talking to each other in the Middle East. And, of course, Desert Storm was a significant and major accomplishment, because it said to aggressor nations: you can't just go take over a friendly country next door."</p>
        <p>But there has been another George Bush as well -- the one who built up Saddam Hussein of Iraq before the Persian Gulf war in the mistaken hope that money and favors would modify his behavior. The George Bush whose disastrous trip to Japan early this year only underscored the degree to which his Administration had ignored a fraying relationship with Tokyo. There was the George Bush who virtually had to be shamed into giving aid to Russia by former President Richard M. Nixon. The George Bush who after the end of the cold war seemed to lose his moorings and began seesawing between engagement and disengagement in such messy post-cold-war problems as Haiti and Yugoslavia.</p>
        <p>And finally there was the George Bush who, as Vice President and President, holds at least some responsibility for the ballooning Federal deficit, which has deprived his Administration of precisely the dollar resources it now needs to help consolidate the democratic revolutions the United States helped spawn from Managua to Prague.</p>
        <p>"When future historians look back on the Bush foreign policy they will find a lot to like about it," said Michael R. Beschloss, who has written several histories of American foreign policy. "But they will also find it largely reactive. The new world order was a creation not of George Bush but of Mikhail Gorbachev and Boris Yeltsin. They were the event-makers. Bush reacted constructively and creatively to their initiatives and concessions." Policy of 'Status Quo Plus'</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush was most comfortable when he was acting within the boundaries of his traditional cold-war framework. His performance was much less consistent and commanding when the Soviet Union came apart, the cold war ended and he was "called upon to fashion a new template for American foreign policy," Mr. Beschloss said.</p>
        <p>If the Bush team came into office with a philosophy, the Administration's first foreign policy review described it best. It was dubbed "status quo plus" -- preserve the cold-war balance of power where necessary while promoting incremental change in relations with Moscow where openings presented themselves.</p>
        <p>While it did not openly disdain human rights, the Bush team's refusal to use trade sanctions to modify China's human rights behavior and its lack of concern for democracy in Kuwait after the gulf war underscored that the issue was never its first principle. But the real problem was that soon after Mr. Bush's watch began, the status quo simply collapsed. When it did, the Bush team's instinctive prudence and alliance-management skills seemed to serve the nation well, at least at first. Indeed, when asked what he is most proud of, Brent Scowcroft, Mr. Bush's national security adviser, said it was the liberation of Eastern Europe, the unification of Germany and the dissolution of the Soviet empire "without a shot being fired" across the old East-West divide. 'We Were Instrumental'</p>
        <p>"Now, I am not saying we necessarily did this all by ourselves," he said, "but we were instrumental in the way it happened. I think if you asked people 10 years ago if the Soviet Union was going to collapse, would it be this way, I think most people would say no. It is probably going to take place in the context of a grand confrontation."</p>
        <p>But prudence is an instinct not a vision. It has its limits, and those limits became clear later in the Bush Administration when the President was called upon not to be just reactive. The times required a proactive, creative leader.</p>
        <p>If his public statements are any measure, Mr. Bush was not prepared for this new, unexpected role. Indeed, for a President so preoccupied with foreign policy, it seems odd that he has not given even one memorable foreign policy speech. For Mr. Bush, the theories, the speeches, "the vision thing," as he put it, always came later -- if at all.</p>
        <p>Even the hallmark phrase the White House began using midway through the term to sum up Mr. Bush's approach to the changing world came into being by happenstance, not through any real planning.</p>
        <p>In late August 1990, Mr. Scowcroft was sitting around the Nonantum resort in Kennebunkport, Me., talking with White House press aides about how to explain the need to confront the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait. "Tell them we can't just let Iraq get away with this -- there is a new world order developing," an aide recalled Mr. Scowcroft remarking</p>
        <p>"New world order" -- the White House press team liked the sound of that. It was catchy. It was fresh. It had potential. Later, two members of the White House press team were in their office at another hotel, the Shawmut, when Pam Olson, a White House correspondent for CNN, came in.</p>
        <p>"We told her it's 'a new world order,' " one of the officials recalled. "She liked it, and 30 minutes later it was on CNN. So the 'new world order' was born at the Shawmut Hotel. It was really just an accident. The philosophy came later."</p>
        <p>Unification of Germany  Bush Aids Process Behind the Scenes</p>
        <p>By most accounts, Mr. Bush reacted slowly but effectively to the problems that awaited him when he took office. This was Phase I of his foreign policy.</p>
        <p>Behind the scenes he helped refashion the world from one in which the United States confronted the Soviets from Germany to Nicaragua to one in which Moscow and Washington could solve problems together in both those countries and in others, too. His aides and allies say Mr. Bush's work to bring about the peaceful unification of Germany is one of the least known but most important acts of his Presidency.</p>
        <p>"Behind the scenes Bush stage-managed the outcome," said Peter Rodman, a former member of the Bush National Security Council. "He stiffened Chancellor Kohl's spine on the question of staying in NATO, when there were great pressures on him to leave. He stroked Mitterand to get the French to re-endorse the NATO alliance and also agreed to adapt NATO, to make it less threatening and address Gorbachev's fears. You really could have had an explosion and an unraveling, and you had just the opposite." Helped by Soviet Decisions</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's attention to all the parties was undeniably helpful. But Germany would not have reunified smoothly if the Germans had not been willing to buy the Soviets out of Berlin, and had Mr. Gorbachev not been ready to take the billions of dollars that Bonn gave him to resettle his troops and shore up his economy. And at the same time, it was while Mr. Bush was focused on Germany that his Administration went on autopilot in the Middle East and slipped into its policy of continuing to build up Iraq against Iran, even when the Iraqi leader's threatening behavior clearly argued for a new approach.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's instinctive pragmatism also played well in Latin America, where the President dropped the Reagan Administration's confrontational approach and chose instead to compromise. Again, he was helped by the Soviet retreat and withdrawal of aid from its clients.</p>
        <p>"After a decade of civil war, the Bush approach offered space for all of the actors to negotiate terms that permited peaceful political change," said Robert A. Pastor, an adviser on Latin America to President Jimmy Carter. Little Focus on Latin America</p>
        <p>But the same political pragmatism that enabled Mr. Bush to disengage from Ronald Reagan's politically contentious contra policy in Nicaragua also prompted his Administration to focus on the issue only as long as it took to defuse an explosive political problem.</p>
        <p>Since its first year and a half, the Administration has devoted little attention to Latin America. Just when aid and attention are needed to consolidate some of the infant democracies America helped create, the Bush policy for the hemisphere seems to have lost energy and focus.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush certainly acted decisively in December 1989 when he ordered the invasion of Panama and seizure of Gen. Manuel Antonio Noriega. But the tear gas Mr. Bush inhaled when he returned to Panama early this month was just one more demonstration that the consolidation of democracy is much more difficult than its forceful installation. The Gulf Crisis  Paving the Way For Peace Talks</p>
        <p>The largest challenge President Bush has faced was the Iraqi invasion of Kuwait. Even his foes now credit him with deft handling of the crisis after the invasion; he built a coalition unlike any before in modern history. This was Phase II of his foreign policy.</p>
        <p>Out of the war, Mr. Bush and Mr. Baker are also given much credit for engineering an opening for Arab-Israeli peace talks.</p>
        <p>The Middle East was one area of the world where the Bush team actually worked to overturn a status quo -- in this case the stubborn deadlock over the West Bank.</p>
        <p>So far, though, this effort has not produced any concrete results -- largely because it has been based entirely on external pressures and not on any fundamental change of view by Israel, the Palestinians or the Arab states. But the stunning victory of the Labor Party in Israel this week suggests that Israel may now undergo precisely that sort of internal change. If that leads to a breakthrough in the peace talks, that will be attributable, at least in part, to the environment created by the Administration's Madrid peace conference. An Election Setback  Politics Intrude On Foreign Policy</p>
        <p>Phase III of the Bush foreign policy began on November 5, 1991 -- the day the Republicans lost the Senate race in Pennsylvania to a Democratic upstart, Harris Wofford.</p>
        <p>The White House drew a hard lesson from that shock; Mr. Bush's success in foreign policy had been turned into a political liability because of the perception that it had come at the expense of domestic policy. On that election day last November, Mr. Bush postponed his long-planned visit to Japan. Then three weeks later, realizing this had been a mistake, he rescheduled the visit, but turned it into an automobile sales mission that was as embarrassing as it was unproductive.</p>
        <p>In some ways, Mr. Bush has been lurching back and forth ever since -- and not just because of political concerns. The concurrent problem was that, as the Soviet Union disintegrated, so too did the broad framework for the Bush foreign policy. Soviet Compass Is Lost</p>
        <p>The Soviet Union had been the main problem, around which Mr. Bush's reactive foreign policy was organized and, later, the main partner for many of its diplomatic endeavors. Once it disappeared, the defining core of the policy was lost, and the Administration began having trouble sorting out what exactly was the national interest, where should the United States intervene and with whom this country should work. As one Administration official put it: "There was nothing big to react to anymore."</p>
        <p>To make matters worse, foreign policy issues increasingly grew to be intrastate quandaries -- ethnic and national disputes, or environmental problems -- instead of interstate questions. Rather than dealing with the implications of Iraq's invading Kuwait, the kind of problem the President clearly understood, he found himself called upon to confront Serbia's threat to Bosnia or turmoil in Haiti -- situations about which he seemed to know little and care even less.</p>
        <p>Even critics of the President acknowledge that he should not have been expected to provide magic answers for these new and beguiling problems. But the Administration seemed to find all these new quandaries disorienting. This seems to account for the oscillations in the Administration's dealings with the crises in Haiti and Yugoslavia; first he ignored them, then there was a sudden burst of activity, and then inactivity again.</p>
        <p>Traditional foreign policy problems could be dealt with by mobilizing troops or negotiating arms control agreements. But the conflicts in Yugoslavia and Haiti, the destruction of rain forests or the democratization of the former Soviet Union all required not just creative solutions but money -- money for United Nations peacekeeping operations, money to help Russia make the transition from a Communist to a market economy, money that is no longer available.</p>
        <p>This is so in part because Mr. Bush grew to be a victim of the Reagan Administration he had helped to lead. The deficit ballooned during the Reagan years. And Reagan Administration officials even boasted in memoirs that this was deliberate. They said they hoped that under the burden of a record deficit, there would be intense pressure to starve liberal social programs. Hampered by the Deficit</p>
        <p>But years later, that came back to haunt the Bush Administration and tie its hands in the one area where it wanted and needed money. As the historian Ronald Steel put it: "The huge deficit made it impossible for the Administration to fund an activist foreign policy. When all of these opportunities to develop free markets and democracies were out there in Eastern Europe and Russia, we could not afford to nurture them."</p>
        <p>The end result, argued Stanley Hoffmann, a Harvard University European affairs expert, is that American foreign policy today seems reduced to two conflicting statements: We are the only superpower left, and we are broke so we can't do anything.</p>
        <p>"During the first few years," Mr. Hoffmann said, "I think the Bush people thought they saw the future almost the way it looked in 1945 -- we would be clearly the No. 1 superpower, but the Soviet Union would follow our lead. The two great powers and a few lesser ones would do things together. That is not going to happen. Now we have to shut up or put up, and since we don't want to put up, we may have to shut up."</p>
        <p>--------------------</p>
        <p>NEXT: The policy toward Iraq.</p>
        <p>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
