<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Josephine Baker Unfit for the Mail? (It Wasn't Even a French Postcard)</title>
    <meta content="09about" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/05/09/nyregion/09about.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1846161"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="ABOUT NEW YORK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/About New York/About New York - Dwyer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Censorship</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Postal Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <person class="online_producer">Baker, Josephine</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Dwyer, Jim</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070509T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E5DA1731F93AA35756C0A9619C8B63" item-length="734" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Josephine Baker Unfit for the Mail? (It Wasn't Even a French Postcard)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Josephine Baker Unfit for the Mail? (It Wasn’t Even a French Postcard)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JIM DWYER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dwyer, Jim</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On the endless march toward liberty and justice for all, a new cause has joined the parade: postcards featuring the breasts -- clad, unclad, and pretty much clad -- of Josephine Baker, famous long ago and dead these many years.</p>
        <p>Still, however, haunting the United States Postal Service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Postal Service balked at a mass mailing of risqué postcards depicting the great beauty of the Jazz Age covered, sort of, by feathers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On the endless march toward liberty and justice for all, a new cause has joined the parade: postcards featuring the breasts -- clad, unclad, and pretty much clad -- of Josephine Baker, famous long ago and dead these many years.</p>
        <p>Still, however, haunting the United States Postal Service.</p>
        <p>''Every year, I send exquisite, exquisite, postcards of Maman,'' says Jean-Claude Baker, who became the ward of Ms. Baker when he was living on his own as a young boy in Paris after World War II. The postcards -- exquisite, in case you didn't hear -- are sent to promote Mr. Baker's restaurant on West 42nd Street, named for Ms. Baker, and which he has run unburdened by excess modesty for 21 years.</p>
        <p>Striking images of Ms. Baker are not hard to come by: a great beauty of the Jazz Age, she held Paris in her thrall as a singer and dancer and later served the French Resistance.</p>
        <p>Still, this year, Mr. Baker -- whom Ms. Baker called the ''13th of my 12 adopted children'' -- decided to use a watercolor by Henry Fournier that depicted Ms. Baker dressed in feathers here and there, but essentially naked above the waist.</p>
        <p>Before printing up postcards for 15,000 good friends, Mr. Baker strolled to the post office down the street from his restaurant to make sure that there would be no problem mailing them.</p>
        <p>''It's a big open post office, with an open counter; I know the man and showed it to him,'' Mr. Baker said.</p>
        <p>As Mr. Baker recalled the encounter, the postal clerk issued a stern verdict. ''He said, 'That's pornographic advertising.' ''</p>
        <p>Asked about the circumstances, a spokeswoman for the postal service sighed.</p>
        <p>''It was the clerk's interpretation of the domestic mail manual,'' said the spokeswoman, Pat McGovern. ''A thick book with thousands of different aspects of the regulations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker, 64, reports that many other people were in the post office at the time, including some younger women who overheard the exchange of views about the image of his Maman.</p>
        <p>''So I look like an old pornographer,'' he said. ''Everyone looking at me, laughing.''</p>
        <p>He promptly notified the press of this humiliation, after going to the big post office on 33rd Street, where the card was rejected a second time. ''I was given the regulations to confirm that I could not use the post office for such a decadent illustration,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The post office has a long and not terribly successful history as a guardian of shifting notions of morality and decency. In Mr. Baker, it faced an adversary with a long and very successful history of self-promotion. He plotted his next move.</p>
        <p>''I had the brilliant, funny idea to put 'censored' across Josephine's breasts,'' he said. Even better than being brilliant or funny, the censorship banner somehow flunked the decency tests, too. The image probably would not draw a second glance, if not for the ''censored'' banner across the unoffending parts.</p>
        <p>''At my post office, they told me that it was still no good -- a little tiny bit of the bottom of the breast could still be seen,'' Mr. Baker reported. He made yet another postcard with an even larger banner to cover the relevant rib cage, and mailed it by the thousands. He posted the original image on the Web site of his restaurant, chezjosephine.com.</p>
        <p>Asked about the dispute yesterday, Ms. McGovern of the postal service cleared her throat.</p>
        <p>''Regulation 9.1.1, it goes on and on,'' Ms. McGovern said. ''When I was first looking into this, a clerk from another area heard me, and said, no, not 9.1.1, and she's giving me another section, 12.5.4.''</p>
        <p>Civil liberties lawyers, postal lawyers, and other great minds began to study the codes. In the end, all parties agreed: Under part 601-12.11, ''Unauthorized Decisions by Postmasters,'' the breasts could show.</p>
        <p>''We did apologize,'' Ms. McGovern said. ''It was really a misunderstanding.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Baker, who took Ms. Baker's surname when he accompanied her on a United States tour in 1973, plans to have a triumphant public mailing next Tuesday of the original, uncensored postcards.</p>
        <p>Told that the rates increase Monday -- each postcard will cost an additional two cents -- he scoffed, magnanimously.</p>
        <p>''But I don't care,'' Mr. Baker said. ''I'm a good American taxpayer, I don't want to save two or three cents. The press conference is set for Tuesday. Le Figaro, Le Monde and Agence France-Presse -- they're all coming.''</p>
        <p>ABOUT NEW YORK E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: dwyer@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
