<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Books of The Times; Humanizing Douglass With Warts and Virtues</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Word and Image Page" name="feature_page"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="425382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MITGANG, HERBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCFEELY, WILLIAM S</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">FREDERICK DOUGLASS (BOOK)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEEDE1139F930A15751C0A967958260" item-length="745" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Books of The Times; Humanizing Douglass With Warts and Virtues</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HERBERT MITGANG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MITGANG, HERBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frederick Douglass By William S. McFeely Illustrated. 465 pages. W. W. Norton. $24.95.</p>
        <p>William S. McFeely's biography of Frederick Douglass succeeds in humanizing one of the most influential blacks of the 19th century by revealing his shortcomings as well as his achievements. After all that has been written about Douglass, including some myth-making by Douglass himself in three autobiographies, Mr. McFeely's "Frederick Douglass" has a freshness of fact and boldness of interpretation that is admirable.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frederick Douglass By William S. McFeely Illustrated. 465 pages. W. W. Norton. $24.95.</p>
        <p>William S. McFeely's biography of Frederick Douglass succeeds in humanizing one of the most influential blacks of the 19th century by revealing his shortcomings as well as his achievements. After all that has been written about Douglass, including some myth-making by Douglass himself in three autobiographies, Mr. McFeely's "Frederick Douglass" has a freshness of fact and boldness of interpretation that is admirable.</p>
        <p>More than their predecessors, modern American biographers tend to probe the personal lives of their subjects by deeper research into their backgrounds, often retracing their footsteps and bringing new information to the surface. This is what Mr. McFeely does so well here as he tracks Douglass all over the country and abroad. The author, a professor of history at the University of Georgia, followed a similar course in his notable biography of Ulysses S. Grant. While offering a good deal of psychological speculation about Douglass, his interpretations seem rooted in solid evidence.</p>
        <p>This new biography is more than generous to the man and his legend. Here is how Mr. McFeely handles one of the most controversial aspects of Douglass's life:</p>
        <p>"It has been said that he ran away from being black. The opposite is true. Every time he walked up to a lectern to speak, he was seen: by his very presence he not only announced that he was black but also instructed all who looked at him that they were not to see that fact pejoratively. As Whitman did, Douglass sang of himself, and he did so just by standing on the platform. His simple appearance was a proud assertion that neither color nor previous condition of servitude was relevant to his aspirations, either for himself or for others."</p>
        <p>Slavery, color, racism and the struggle for equal rights all come together in the Douglass story, which he told and changed himself in three divergent autobiographies. Using generous excerpts, Mr. McFeely draws upon Douglass's "Narrative of the Life of Frederick Douglass" (1845), a declaration of freedom by a runaway slave that became a powerful antislavery tract. As a mature writer in "My Bondage and My Freedom" (1855), Douglass gave his reflections on slavery a few years before the Civil War. "Life and Times of Frederick Douglass" (1881, revised 1892), while including his slavery days, reveals that Douglass relished his honors and smarted when they were denied.</p>
        <p>Mr. McFeely fleshes out these lives with additional details about Douglass's origins in Maryland, the son of an illiterate mother and unknown white father; his escape from bondage, self-education with the help of his owner's wife, who broke the law by teaching him to read; how he turned himself into one of the greatest 19th-century orators; his recognition as a role model by the leading white Abolitionists, yet his independence from them; his years as an influential newspaper editor in Rochester, where he urged blacks to become politically active; his vision in realizing the need for blacks to serve in the Union ranks to strengthen their argument for equality; his second marriage to a white woman and close relationships with several other white women; his advocacy of women's rights but his break with Susan B. Anthony, the feminist leader, who felt that blacks were in competition with women to gain the right to vote; his disappointments in private and government jobs.</p>
        <p>One of the great virtues of Mr. McFeely's biography is that he relates Douglass's life and concerns to continuing 20th-century attitudes and problems faced by blacks in the United States. Mr. McFeely writes:</p>
        <p>"His light skin and aristocratic mien have long suggested the same distancing from color of which much of the upper-class black community in America is accused. What has been missed has been Douglass's struggle to bridge that distance with his intellect, with an unswerving commitment to human dignity and equality. More than some of us with a different sense of society would have preferred, he sought to draw his people over to his side of the span instead of crossing back and engaging them in their own world."</p>
        <p>Mr. McFeely's "Frederick Douglass" should now join Benjamin Quarles's outstanding 1948 biography, also titled "Frederick Douglass," as a fundamental source on the life and times of the former slave who turned himself into a heroic symbol of freedom.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
