<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sticking to Deadline, Gooden Breaks Off Talks</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="43" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="425460"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONTRACTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FREE AGENTS (SPORTS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SEXTON, JOE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOODEN, DWIGHT</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Free Agents (Sports)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910223T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CEFD9153CF930A15751C0A967958260" item-length="950" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sticking to Deadline, Gooden Breaks Off Talks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE SEXTON, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SEXTON, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>PORT ST. LUCIE, Fla., Feb. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Determined to become the highest-paid player in baseball and making good on his threat regarding a deadline for negotiations, Dwight Gooden today broke off talks with the Mets on a contract extension. Gooden, who insisted he would file for free agency at the end of the coming season, made clear that the failure to work out a deal left open the very real possibility that this would be his last year with the Mets.</p>
        <p>"The next time I talk to the Mets, I'll be talking to everybody," Gooden, fresh from the opening workout of spring training, said this afternoon at a hastily arranged news conference here. "We'll see what everybody feels about Dwight Gooden."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Determined to become the highest-paid player in baseball and making good on his threat regarding a deadline for negotiations, Dwight Gooden today broke off talks with the Mets on a contract extension. Gooden, who insisted he would file for free agency at the end of the coming season, made clear that the failure to work out a deal left open the very real possibility that this would be his last year with the Mets.</p>
        <p>"The next time I talk to the Mets, I'll be talking to everybody," Gooden, fresh from the opening workout of spring training, said this afternoon at a hastily arranged news conference here. "We'll see what everybody feels about Dwight Gooden."</p>
        <p>In today's last-ditch negotiations, Gooden, a 26-year-old right-hander with a Cy Young Award to his credit, a breathtaking career record of 119-46 and an undeniably special place in the hearts and minds of the organization and its loyalists, agreed to accept an extension for three years instead of the four he had sought. But he would not budge from his demand for an average annual salary of $5.4 million. 'A Difficult Situation'</p>
        <p>"We both recognize it's a difficult situation, one that proved to be a situation we couldn't work out," said Al Harazin, the executive vice president of the Mets and the man who conducted the negotiations with Gooden's agent, James Neader, including an hourlong phone conversation this morning. "I was anxious to compromise."</p>
        <p>But the Mets, whose last official offer to Gooden this week was for three years and $13 million, were obviously resolved not to accept Roger Clemens's four-year, $21.5 million contract extension with the Boston Red Sox as a valid market standard. The team has repeatedly termed that pact "an aberration," and maintained that Gooden's insistence on a comparable package was unacceptable because such a deal would endanger both the Mets' salary structure and future financial health.</p>
        <p>"If we step up and make the Clemens standard the standard of the Mets, it impacts on the entire organization," Harazin said. "Everything flows from that."</p>
        <p>Harazin said today's decision was one made by the "entire organization." General Manager Frank Cashen, who consulted with Harazin this morning about the negotiations, did not make himself available to answer questions. Neader Won't Listen</p>
        <p>Neader said that he, on behalf of Gooden, would not listen to any further word from the Mets until November. He said it was his evaluation that the Mets had staked out a position and were not genuinely interested in considering moving off it.</p>
        <p>"Al had his chance, a great chance to get the deal done," said Neader, who added that a multimillion-dollar insurance policy against injury had been taken out for Gooden. "We believed their sticking point was the length of the extension, and so we agreed to accept three years. But we then asked for them to give us our 5.4. He, though, didn't give us any indication of coming anywhere close. Anywhere."</p>
        <p>Visibly upset by today's developments, Harazin said he continued to hold out hope that an agreement could be achieved, and he said the organization "would not stand on ceremony" and thus not hesitate to make subsequent offers during the season despite Gooden's pointed assertion that talks had been terminated. Not Optimistic</p>
        <p>When pressed, though, Harazin conceded that the organization was not optimistic about its ability to prevent Gooden from eventually leaving the Mets, a departure that would, after Darryl Strawberry's exit as a free agent last November, represent the second seismic shock to the organization and its competitive stature in the span of 12 months.</p>
        <p>In addition, Harazin admitted that the club could be reasonably faulted for not having worked toward a deal with Gooden last fall in advance of the Clemens contract. Gooden, who will make $2.25 million for the 1991 season, notified the Mets last October that a deadline for a deal was in place.</p>
        <p>"Tactically, you could well fault us," Harazin said of the failure to sign Gooden quickly. "I don't really have an answer as to why we didn't." Gooden said Thursday that if the Mets' latest offer had been made last fall, he would have probably agreed to it.</p>
        <p>The rest of the Mets, meanwhile, could only guess at the ramifications of the standoff and cross their fingers that it wouldn't produce the kind of perpetual distraction that attended Strawberry's situation last season. The front office, of course, is left to hope that in his efforts to enhance his value Gooden will turn in one of his finest seasons. Cone's View</p>
        <p>"Is what they've done a grave mistake?" David Cone, a colleague of Gooden on the pitching staff who recently signed a $2.35 million contract for 1991, asked aloud of the Mets. "It quite possibly could be. I think it's a little premature to say.</p>
        <p>"The Mets are tough. They don't like the pressure, they don't like deadlines. Maybe they have some private, inside information about future revenues or something. Maybe there is some formula to which they are adhering. But I believe what you'll see is Dwight stick to his word."</p>
        <p>Gooden, who has never threatened to hold out over the extension, reported promptly this morning for the first supervised workout for pitchers and catchers. He completed the drills and then conducted a basically cool and composed news conference with reporters in an office adjacent to the locker room.</p>
        <p>"I'm maybe a little disappointed," Gooden said, declining to characterize himself as angry or spiteful. "You see what the market it paying. I can't ask why they aren't going to pay it. The bottom line is they don't want to do it. They never gave me a reason. They don't owe me one."  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
