<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times; Jackson's Teammates Saw Only a Captain</title>
    <meta content="30BERK$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2000/12/30/sports/30BERK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1259006"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Yale University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berkow, Ira</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jackson, Levi</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Sports of the Times (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/Ira Berkow</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Deaths (Obituaries)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20001230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E0DF143BF933A05751C1A9669C8B63" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times; Jackson's Teammates Saw Only a Captain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By IRA BERKOW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berkow, Ira</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ira Berkow Sports of The Times profiles Levi Jackson, who in 1949 became first black to be voted captain of Yale football team; Jackson died earlier this month; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE vote was held in secret, in a room in Ray Tompkins House beside the Yale gym in New Haven in late November 1948. It was to determine the captain for the 1949 Eli football team. A school sports ethic held that no one was to discuss whose name he was going to write on the paper ballot.</p>
        <p>As one of the guards on the team, Lenny Fasano -- now Dr. Fasano, an internist in New Haven -- recalls, the vote was 49 to 1 for a fullback and punter named Levi Jackson.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE vote was held in secret, in a room in Ray Tompkins House beside the Yale gym in New Haven in late November 1948. It was to determine the captain for the 1949 Eli football team. A school sports ethic held that no one was to discuss whose name he was going to write on the paper ballot.</p>
        <p>As one of the guards on the team, Lenny Fasano -- now Dr. Fasano, an internist in New Haven -- recalls, the vote was 49 to 1 for a fullback and punter named Levi Jackson.</p>
        <p>''Levi was so adored and beloved by the rest of us, and he was such a good player, that I couldn't believe anyone voted for someone else,'' Fasano said. ''After the vote was announced, and we followed the traditional drinking a glass of Champagne to our new captain and then throwing the glasses against the wall, I said to Levi, 'I've got to find out who voted for the other guy.' He said: 'I did, Lenny. I wouldn't vote for myself.' ''</p>
        <p>The election made national news, for Levi Jackson was black, the first of his race to be chosen for the prestigious honor in the history of Yale football. Editorials praised the so-called ''broad-mindedness'' of the electors as being ''wonderful.'' Two, however, saw it a bit differently.</p>
        <p>''What the hell's so wonderful about it? This is America, isn't it?'' asked Bill Corum, sports columnist for The New York Journal-American. And Red Smith replied to the rhetorical questions in his column the following day in The New York Herald Tribune: ''A small echo answers, 'Hooray!' Look, what the Yale kids did wasn't anything wonderful. . . . It's what decent people expect of decent people.'' He added: ''When you say the Yale football players have struck a blow for tolerance, then you are condescending to Levi Jackson. . . . Do you tolerate right guys?''</p>
        <p>Of course, Corum and Smith knew the significance of such acceptance of a black, 19 months after Jackie Robinson broke the color barrier in major league baseball. And what they were saying in their bitter irony was: Why should something like this have taken so long, at Yale and elsewhere in America? Where were the masses of decent people? Why should there even be a need for ''racial progress,'' which Jackson's election supposedly symbolized?</p>
        <p>Jackson, who set 13 modern Yale football records, died earlier this month at age 74. He graduated from Yale with majors in sociology, psychology and economics, had served in the Army, became an executive with Ford, rising to become one of its top executives before retiring in 1983 as a vice president. He was active in community affairs in Detroit, his adopted hometown -- he was reared in Branford, Conn. -- and was appointed to the National Selective Service Appeal Board, which settled disputes over eligibility for the military draft.</p>
        <p>''Levi and I talked often about the black athlete in America,'' said  Fasano, who went to grade school, high school, college and served in the Army with Jackson, a lifelong friend. ''He wasn't happy with black athletes leaving college early, or even going straight to the pros.''</p>
        <p>Fasano said Jackson believed black athletes ''had to take advantage of an education, otherwise you won't be able to rise.''</p>
        <p>''With no education, you go from being a star in sports back to the ghetto.''</p>
        <p>Jackson lived what he believed. ''I remember even in high school that Levi would stay up to 1 or 2 in the morning, studying,'' Fasano recalled. Jackson, whose father was a steward in the Yale dining halls, was the youngest of six children and the only one to get a college education -- helped by the G.I. Bill of Rights, after he served in the Army during World War II.</p>
        <p>''It upset him when some black athletes acted inappropriately,'' Fasano said, ''but he said he comprehended where some of that came from. Having been so discriminated against by whites, these athletes had so much hatred in them that it blinded their judgment. Levi said, 'They have to learn that they will not be able to compete in this world with that attitude.' ''</p>
        <p>Denyse Jackson, one of Jackson's two daughters, recalled that her father ''never said a mean thing about anyone.''</p>
        <p>''He always tried to understand,'' she said. ''And he always wanted to be known first, not for football, but for having got his education.''</p>
        <p>About that vote for the Yale captaincy, Fasano recalled: ''You know, it didn't dawn on us that we were voting for someone of a different color. And when he was carrying the ball, we would have killed ourselves for him. We didn't tolerate Levi Jackson, we loved him.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
