<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>May Spending Unchanged; Income Shows a Small Rise</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="32" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="363101"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INCOME</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CONSUMER BEHAVIOR</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMERCE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Income</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7D8103DF930A15755C0A966958260" item-length="603" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>May Spending Unchanged; Income Shows a Small Rise</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, June 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Personal spending was flat in May, the Government said today in a report pointing to growing caution among consumers who have been a major source of strength for the economy during seven years of growth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Personal spending was flat in May, the Government said today in a report pointing to growing caution among consumers who have been a major source of strength for the economy during seven years of growth.</p>
        <p>Personal spending was flat in May, the Government said today in a report pointing to growing caution among consumers who have been a major source of strength for the economy during seven years of growth.</p>
        <p>''The consumer clearly has pulled back in a dramatic fashion,'' said Stephen S. Roach, senior economist at Morgan Stanley &amp; Company in New York.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department also said personal income rose by only three-tenths of 1 percent in May for a second straight month, to a seasonally adjusted annual rate of $4.7 trillion.</p>
        <p>Rate of $3.66 Trillion</p>
        <p>The department said consumer spending remained unchanged at a seasonally adjusted annual rate of $3.66 trillion after seven straight months of gains, including five-tenths of 1 percent in April and three-tenths in March. But even the April and March rises were weaker than first thought. They were revised downward from the six-tenths of 1 percent and five-tenths increases reported last month.</p>
        <p>Consumer spending is considered a barometer of economic health since it accounts for about two-thirds of the nation's economic activity.</p>
        <p>Analysts have cited a poor job market and weak wage increases for the flagging consumer confidence.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the income gains of only three-tenths of 1 percent in both April and May followed three consecutive monthly rises of eight-tenths and were the lowest since a two-tenths increase last September.</p>
        <p>No Match for Inflation</p>
        <p>The income gains have not even matched the inflation rate, said Sandra Shaber, an economist at the Futures Group, a Washington management consulting firm.</p>
        <p>Today's report was the latest indicating a slowdown in consumer spending, which has been a driving force for much of the current economic expansion that is now in its eighth year.</p>
        <p>The Commerce Department reported last week that retail sales fell in May, their third consecutive monthly decline. It was the first time retail sales fell for three straight months since the summer of 1981, during the last recession. Retail sales represent about half of overall consumer spending. And the department on Thursday revised downward its previous estimate of consumer spending in the first quarter.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Mr. Roach of Morgan Stanley said the slow pace of consumer spending was not likely to tip the economy into a recession because ''there are other things out there still giving the economy a boost.'' He cited a second report today showing that orders for durable goods - ''big ticket'' items expected to last at least three years - jumped by 3.9 percent in May.</p>
        <p>Savings Figure Improved</p>
        <p>The difference between incomes and spending in May helped improve the savings rate of Americans. The rate - savings as a percent of disposable income - rose to 6.2 percent following a 6 percent rate in April and a 6.3 percent rate in March. March's was the highest in five years.</p>
        <p>A higher savings rate means less dependence on foreign capital as more funds are available domestically for business investment.</p>
        <p>The report said the income of Americans after taxes increased by two-tenths of 1 percent, the same rate as in April. The key component of the income category - wages and salaries - rose by $10.3 billion after a $16.4 billion gain in April.</p>
        <p>On the spending side, purchases of durable goods fell by $12.6 billion after an $8.5 billion gain in April. Durable goods purchases had fallen the previous two months.</p>
        <p>Purchases of nondurable goods were down $500 million in May, their third consecutive decline. Spending on services slowed to $13.1 billion after a $14.7 billion gain in April and a $19.6 billion rise in March.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
