<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="18FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1003067"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980318T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F02EED61039F93BA25750C0A96E958260" item-length="1294" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Netanyahu Cancels Dinner With British Diplomat  Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel canceled a dinner with Robin Cook, left, the British Foreign Secretary, accusing him of violating an agreement by meeting with Palestinians near the planned site of a disputed Jewish settlement.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-12</p>
        <p>Netanyahu Cancels Dinner With British Diplomat  Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel canceled a dinner with Robin Cook, left, the British Foreign Secretary, accusing him of violating an agreement by meeting with Palestinians near the planned site of a disputed Jewish settlement.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>Panel Approves I.M.F. Funding  A Senate panel approved $18 billion in financing for the I.M.F., but only if the fund formally voted to make major changes in how it lent money to nations in distress. Treasury Secretary Robert E. Rubin, as well as several Republicans, expressed strong opposition to the changes.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Court Notion Gains Steam  The final planning session for the first permanent International Criminal Court began at the United Nations with legal experts saying the United States was drawing closer to other nations on the roles of the Security Council and governments in deciding cases to be heard.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Clinton Pushes Irish Talks  All the parties to the Northern Ireland peace negotiations came to the Oval Office to hear President Clinton admonish them not to squander a chance for peace.</p>
        <p>A10</p>
        <p>Senate Opens NATO Debate  The Senate unexpectedly opened debate on the expansion of NATO when the Republican leader, Senator Trent Lott, altered the Senate schedule and called for opening statements on a resolution to add Poland, Hungary and the Czech Republic.</p>
        <p>A12</p>
        <p>Deposed Prince Is Convicted  Cambodia tried its deposed co-Prime Minister, Prince Norodom Ranariddh, in absentia and convicted him of threatening national security by plotting with the Khmer Rouge guerrillas to overthrow the Government. The Prince, now in Bangkok, Thailand, is expected to be pardoned, making him eligible to run in upcoming elections.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>Bishops' Apology to Philippines  The Catholic Bishops Conference of the Philippines apologized in a pastoral letter for clergy who sided with Spanish rulers and opposed the Philippine revolution 100 years ago, in a statement to be distributed to churches in the nation.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>Rain Forest Burns in Brazil  Forest fires that have been moving across northern Brazil were burning the rain forest, despite efforts to check the flames. The fires, worsened by a drought linked to the El Nino weather phenomenon, have burned an area the size of Lebanon in the northern savannah highlands in the past two months.</p>
        <p>(Reuters)</p>
        <p>Suharto Pledges Salary to Poor  President Suharto of Indonesia and his new Cabinet pledged to hand over one year's salary to a fund for the poor in an effort to counter charges of high-level corruption. The promises came as thousands of students demonstrated to demand democratic reform and vent frustration over economic turmoil.</p>
        <p>(AP)</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A14-19</p>
        <p>The Senate Is Offered A Republican Budget Plan  The chairman of the Senate Budget Committee proposed a Republican fiscal blueprint that rejected nearly all of President Clinton's calls for increased domestic spending, but provided smaller tax cuts than sought by many Republicans.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Revealing a Secret Past  Mississippi unsealed more than 124,000 pages of secret files from a state agency that used spy tactics, intimidation, false imprisonment, jury tampering and other illegal methods to thwart the activities of civil rights workers decades ago.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Illinois Primary Results  Voters in the Illinois Republican primary selected a conservative man, State Senator Peter Fitzgerald, over a centrist woman to run against Senator Carol Moseley-Braun.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Campaign Limits and Speech  A Federal Appeals Court heard arguments on whether limits on the money that political candidates can spend in campaigns violate constitutional protections of free speech.</p>
        <p>A14</p>
        <p>Accuser Seeking Book Deal  The former White House aide Kathleen E. Willey has been pursuing a $100,000 book deal in recent months, but her lawyer and a prospective publisher differ on how closely those negotiations were linked to her decision to go public with her accusations against President Clinton.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Ellen W. McCathran, the keeper of detailed accounts of President Clinton's activities and visitors for historical purposes, appeared before the Federal grand jury investigating the President's relationship with Monica S. Lewinsky.</p>
        <p>A18</p>
        <p>Expanding Medicare  President Clinton went to Capitol Hill and, at a rally with Democratic members of Congress, pushed his proposal to open Medicare to millions of people 55 to 64 years old.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>Vitamin E and Prostate Cancer  Vitamin E pills reduced the risk of prostate cancer by a third and the disease's death rate by 41 percent in a study of thousands of smokers. The study, in Finland, also showed that a form of vitamin A had no effect on reducing cancer.</p>
        <p>A19</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-8</p>
        <p>City and State Populations Show a Small Net Growth  More than a million people moved out of New York City in the 1990's, but immigrants and children born to them have more than replaced those who left, according to Federal census figures. The city's population in 1997 was 7,342,636. Although New York State and New Jersey showed some gains, states in the Northeast and Midwest generally continued to lose ground to the South and West.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>Kennedy Collector Yields a Bit  Robert White, a collector whose auction of John F. Kennedy memorabilia has invoked the wrath of Kennedy's children, agreed to turn over 21 items of historical importance to the National Archives. But other items at the core of the dispute remain headed for the block today.</p>
        <p>B2</p>
        <p>Sex Shop Law Is Delayed  A Federal appeals court temporarily barred the Giuliani administration from enforcing a law restricting X-rated businesses.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>Vote on Easier Uniform Rule  The Board of Education is scheduled to vote today on a school uniform policy considerably less stringent than the one originally proposed.</p>
        <p>B4</p>
        <p>Charges in School Death  A construction company and one of its supervisors were charged with manslaughter and other crimes in the death of a 16-year-old girl who was fatally injured in January by a brick that fell off a Brooklyn elementary school under repair. At another school in Brooklyn, a worker and two students were hurt when a brick parapet under renovation collapsed.</p>
        <p>B3</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>D20</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>B9</p>
        <p>DINING</p>
        <p>F1-8</p>
        <p>LIVING ARTS</p>
        <p>E1-10</p>
        <p>Whitney's Director Moving On  David Ross, director of the Whitney Museum of American Art, will become director of the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.</p>
        <p>E1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>D1-19</p>
        <p>S.&amp; L. Giants to Merge  Washington Mutual and Ahmanson, the nation's two largest savings and loan companies and once intense rivals in the takeover game, agreed to merge in a $9.9 billion stock swap that would create a West Coast behemoth capable of competing with the new giants of consumer banking.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Chase Manhattan Layoffs  Chase Manhattan, the nation's largest bank, said it would lay off 2,250 employees, about 3 percent of its work force, as it consolidated administrative and business functions.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>C1-8</p>
        <p>Turner vs. Murdoch  Ted Turner, the owner of the Atlanta Braves, is expected to make a rare appearance at a baseball owners meeting tomorrow to try to block the $311 million sale of the Los Angeles Dodgers to Rupert Murdoch, a rival in the media business.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A20-21</p>
        <p>Editorials: Editorials: The Vatican's Holocaust report; Mr. Giuliani and the ''L'' word; like watching Al Gore; topics.</p>
        <p>Columns: Maureen Dowd, Frank Rich.</p>
        <p>Crossword</p>
        <p>E8</p>
        <p>Weather</p>
        <p>C8</p>
        <p>Public Lives</p>
        <p>B2</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
