<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NATO Urged to Keep Force In Bosnia After Pullout Date</title>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Front Page" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="838235"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CIVIL WAR AND GUERRILLA WARFARE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITEDSTATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SOCIAL CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">YUGOSLAVIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA AND HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GREAT BRITAIN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service"></location>
        <location class="indexing_service">FRANCE</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">BOSNIA&amp; HERZEGOVINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">NORTH ATLANTIC TREATY ORGANIZATION (NATO)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United Kingdom</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Serbia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Montenegro</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Great Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Bosnia and Herzegovina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Britain</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/France</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Social Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Civil War and Guerrilla Warfare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Immigration and Refugees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">War and Revolution</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960321T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9501E3D71739F932A15750C0A960958260" item-length="1345" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NATO Urged to Keep Force In Bosnia After Pullout Date</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CRAIG R. WHITNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WHITNEY, CRAIG R</byline>
      <dateline>TUZLA, Bosnia and Herzegovina, March 20</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As warnings mount that the fragile Bosnian peace could collapse without the presence of NATO peacekeepers, international civilian and military authorities here have begun to press for keeping at least a reduced NATO force in Bosnia beyond the currently scheduled departure at the end of this year.</p>
        <p>While the Clinton Administration continues to insist that all 20,000 American troops will be out of Bosnia only nine months from now, key officials here say the delicate tasks of resettling refugees and rebuilding the country are likely  to fail without the security of outside peacekeepers. The NATO-led international force, known as IFOR, totals about 60,000 troops.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As warnings mount that the fragile Bosnian peace could collapse without the presence of NATO peacekeepers, international civilian and military authorities here have begun to press for keeping at least a reduced NATO force in Bosnia beyond the currently scheduled departure at the end of this year.</p>
        <p>While the Clinton Administration continues to insist that all 20,000 American troops will be out of Bosnia only nine months from now, key officials here say the delicate tasks of resettling refugees and rebuilding the country are likely  to fail without the security of outside peacekeepers. The NATO-led international force, known as IFOR, totals about 60,000 troops.</p>
        <p>At American insistence -- and consistent with pledges President Clinton made to Congress when he sought support for the peacekeeping mission here -- the NATO forces are to leave at the end of the year. Both Britain and France have said that if the Americans go, the Europeans will pull out, too.</p>
        <p>But many international officials in Bosnia say a total withdrawal could be disastrous. "We need something after IFOR, though not a 60,000-man force," said  Carl Bildt, the international representative in charge of coordinating civilian  efforts to put the peace agreement into effect.</p>
        <p>"Refugee return is a two-year plan," Mr. Bildt said. "Reconstruction will take much longer than one year. Almost everything depends on a feeling of overall security for which some kind of military presence will be required."</p>
        <p>The Pentagon itself, in an intelligence assessment drawn up last month, warned that without major new aid for economic and political rebuilding, Bosnia  was likely to fragment and fall back into conflict after NATO forces pull out at year's end.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bildt has already asked officials of the alliance in Brussels to begin thinking about what NATO could do after its one-year mandate here runs out. Secretary of State Warren Christopher and other allied foreign ministers will probably have to make a preliminary decision about what comes next when they meet in Berlin in June.</p>
        <p>Some European officials have hinted that they might keep troops in Bosnia after the end of the year if the United States would keep troops nearby, providing logistical support.  If so, that would give President Clinton a political break since he could withdraw Americans from the danger zone.</p>
        <p>In an interview today, Maj. Gen. William L. Nash, the commander of the American sector for NATO forces in Bosnia, stressed the unwavering American determination to withdraw on schedule.</p>
        <p>"The burden for peace in Bosnia and Herzegovina is on the shoulders of those  folks that live here," he said. "If they don't want peace, there ain't gonna be  peace. If they want peace, one year is more than enough to get them started.</p>
        <p>"The military part has gone pretty well. As people gain confidence, some sort of elections take place, and the international police force does its work, by next December things can be in a reassuring posture that will make withddrawal not the concern that it is now."</p>
        <p>"Should there be a follow-on force?" General Nash asked. "I don't know."</p>
        <p>Allied commanders here say the hardest part of the military implementation of the accords is almost over, with the forces of the warring parties disengaged from the old battle lines and many troops demobilizing.</p>
        <p>If by mid-April, as called for under the peace plan, the sides have withdrawn their artillery, tank, and other heavy weapons forces to base areas designated by the NATO commander in Bosnia, Adm. Leighton W. Smith Jr., the allies can start thinking about when to begin withdrawal of the heaviest elements of their  own forces.</p>
        <p>"Everything has to stay until the Bosnian elections, which have to be held by the middle or the end of September," a high-ranking French official said in Paris. "After that, everybody leaves if the Americans do."</p>
        <p>But according to Mr. Bildt and French commanders on the scene here, the threat that international force will be used has been the key to making the warring parties observe the agreements they all assented to in Dayton, Ohio, last November.</p>
        <p>"There is some thought that we should wait until the Bosnian elections at the end of the summer before beginning the withdrawal, and some thought that we could begin before then," said Maj. Gen. Robert Rideau, the French commander of  the NATO multinational division deploying 14,000 troops around Sarajevo.</p>
        <p>"Nothing has been decided yet," he said, "but yes, it does seem that some force should remain in the future. Perhaps the Americans will be prepared to leave some troops at their staging area in Hungary." The United States now has more than 4,000 troops in Hungary supporting the Bosnian operation.</p>
        <p>The implication of these and other statements by European officials is that if some Americans stayed, at least in the neighborhood if not in Bosnia itself, then some European forces would stay as well. Several thousand troops from Russia, Ukraine, Malaysia, Morocco, the Czech Republic, Poland, Morocco, and 10 other non-NATO countries are also participating with troops from 15 allied countries.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bildt, like just about everybody else in Sarajevo, shakes his head when asked whether a residual peacekeeping force could come under United Nations command, like the ineffectual protection force that NATO replaced in December.</p>
        <p>But a smaller, less heavily armed force than the one NATO deployed to be ready to impose peace on the belligerents is essential, in his view, to keep the peace in the future.</p>
        <p>Other international officials agree.  Sadako Ogata, the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, said recently that she could not imagine how to get two million refugees safely back to their homes, or resettled in other areas, over the next two years without the security provided by an effective international force.</p>
        <p>Lieut. Gen. Sir Michael Walker, a Briton who is Admiral Smith's principal deputy here, said that NATO military authorities had long assumed a need for a continuing force.  "We made the assumption there probably would have to be a follow-on force, but that wasn't acceptable language at the time," he said at his headquarters here.</p>
        <p>"I think the argument will go on for some time," he said. "NATO is trying to  allow its member states to discuss the issues at the national level before trying to make a decision."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bildt is particularly concerned about the need to remove millions of mines scattered around the country, and to resolve a dispute about boundaries in the critical Brcko area, the part of northern Bosnia that links the eastern and  western Serb-controlled areas. The Dayton accords called on the parties to name  arbitrators by June 14 and put their decision into effect by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>"In Brcko all the issues that originated the conflict come together again," he said. "The area was 52 percent Muslim before the war, but Serb ethnic cleansing was brutal, and President Alija Izetbegovic is insisting that his boundary has to extend through Serb territory right to the Sava River. It's nowhere near being sorted out."</p>
        <p>In addition, he and other officials point out, there is concern about the road that under the accords is to be built in a corridor through Bosnian Serb territory to the Muslim enclave of Gorazde in eastern Bosnia. The road is unlikely to be planned, let alone built, by the time the peacekeepers are now scheduled to leave, these officials said.</p>
        <p>"I've told the alliance in Brussels that the issue has to be confronted within the near future," he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
