<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Those Schools. That Dreadful Uncle. Those Hats.</title>
    <meta content="29GENZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/29/arts/television/29GENZ.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1363216"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Genzlinger, Neil</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Life and Adventures of Nicholas Nickleby, The (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Public Broadcasting Service (PBS)</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E4D9123AF93AA15752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="536" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Those Schools. That Dreadful Uncle. Those Hats.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Those Schools. That Dreadful Uncle. Those Hats.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Neil Genzlinger reviews two-part television presentation of The Life and Adventures of Nicholas Nickleby, on Bravo; photo of James D'Arcy (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's getting to the point where it's almost impossible to make a bad television adaptation of a Dickens novel. Or to make one that looks substantially different from all the others. The two-part ''Life and Adventures of Nicholas Nickleby'' that turns up tonight and tomorrow night demonstrates these dueling truisms perfectly.</p>
        <p>Dickens seems to be enjoying a new popularity among the made-for-television crowd, and viewers who stumble upon ''Nickleby'' tonight may be excused if they think they've tuned in ''Masterpiece Theater's'' ''Oliver Twist'' or ''David Copperfield.'' There's a look to these shows and these stories: everything's brown, nobody smiles, the characters seem unable to chew with their mouths closed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dickens seems to be enjoying a new popularity among the made-for-television crowd.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's getting to the point where it's almost impossible to make a bad television adaptation of a Dickens novel. Or to make one that looks substantially different from all the others. The two-part ''Life and Adventures of Nicholas Nickleby'' that turns up tonight and tomorrow night demonstrates these dueling truisms perfectly.</p>
        <p>Dickens seems to be enjoying a new popularity among the made-for-television crowd, and viewers who stumble upon ''Nickleby'' tonight may be excused if they think they've tuned in ''Masterpiece Theater's'' ''Oliver Twist'' or ''David Copperfield.'' There's a look to these shows and these stories: everything's brown, nobody smiles, the characters seem unable to chew with their mouths closed.</p>
        <p>''Nickleby,'' though, is not on PBS, but on Bravo. Fans of ''Masterpiece Theater'' needn't fear, however; they will feel perfectly comfortable with this incarnation, directed by Stephen Whittaker and adapted by Martyn Edward Hesford. That's the thing about Dickens: he doesn't allow much room for innovation. A frisky director might set ''Romeo and Juliet'' in the bobby-socks decades, but Dickens's stories demand their 19th-century settings, with the manners, class divisions, oppressiveness and wardrobe of the time.</p>
        <p>James D'Arcy stars here as Nicholas, the young man who, after his father dies, must figure out how to make his way in the world so that he can free his mother (Diana Kent) and beautiful sister (Sophia Myles) from dependence on nasty Uncle Ralph (Charles Dance).</p>
        <p>Nicholas gets a job at a boarding school where horrific things are done to boys, especially to Smike (nicely played by Lee Ingleby), who becomes Nicholas's lifelong friend. The two of them flee the school and join an acting troupe, while back home Kate works at a dressmaker's and fends off unwanted advances from crude men.</p>
        <p>The novel is often called a tragicomedy, largely on the basis of Dickens's colorful descriptions of his outlandish characters, but the comedy doesn't get a chance to emerge much in this rendition because the dark passages are very dark. At the school, Mr. Squeers, the headmaster, is played by Gregor Fisher with maximum fierceness, minimum buffoonishness, and when the camera pans the students, it calls to mind images from Hitler's death camps.</p>
        <p>As for the distillation of the unwieldy novel, the first of the two parts does the best job of keeping things coherent. Part 2 gets a bit hard to track as it tries desperately to condense its way to the story's conclusion.</p>
        <p>THE LIFE AND ADVENTURES OF NICHOLAS NICKLEBY</p>
        <p>Bravo, tonight and tomorrow night at 8</p>
        <p>Written by Martyn Edward Hesford, based on the novel by Charles Dickens; directed by Stephen Whittaker; director of photography, Sean Bobbitt; production designer, James Merifield; producer, Nicolas Brown; executive producers, George Faber, Suzan Harrison and Charles Pattinson; line producer, Nick Goding.</p>
        <p>WITH: Charles Dance (Ralph Nickleby), James D'Arcy (Nicholas Nickleby), Sophia Myles (Kate Nickleby), Diana Kent (Mrs. Nickleby), Simeon Andrews (Ned Cheeryble), Lee Ingleby (Smike), Gregor Fisher (Mr. Squeers), Pam Ferris (Mrs. Squeers), Debbie Chazen (Fanny Squeers) and George Innes (Newman Noggs).</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
