<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Missing American Journalist Wasn't Spy, Friends Say</title>
    <meta content="357243SGM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/01/29/national/29PEAR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1363202"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="A NATION CHALLENGED: PORTRAITS OF GRIEF: THE VICTIMS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pakistan-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pakistan-International Relations-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pakistan</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Central Intelligence Agency</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Wall Street Journal</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckholm, Erik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pearl, Daniel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barringer, Felicity</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eckholm, Erik</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pearl, Daniel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Pakistan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Foreign Service</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Customs (Tariff)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Pakistan</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Stanford University</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Powell, Colin L</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6D8173BF93AA15752C0A9649C8B63" item-length="1146" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Missing American Journalist Wasn't Spy, Friends Say</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Missing American Journalist Wasn't Spy, Friends Say</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FELICITY BARRINGER with ERIK ECKHOLM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barringer, Felicity; Eckholm, Erik</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article profiles missing Wall Street Journal reporter Daniel Pearl, apparently abducted in Pakistan; friends and colleagues are anxious not only about his disapperance, but by accusations that he worked for CIA; say he was not spy; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Danny Pearl never seemed stressed. From the mid-1980's, when he was a laid-back radio host on the overnight shift at Stanford University's campus station, to the mid-1990's, when he was writing lighthearted articles for The Wall Street Journal about federal agencies that had no reason for being, Daniel Pearl, the Journal reporter apparently kidnapped in Pakistan last week, has seemed impervious to pressure.</p>
        <p>Craig Sherman, a friend who has known Mr. Pearl since both were 11 years old, said yesterday that Mr. Pearl was ''perfect academically, everybody's friend and no matter how stressed out he was, he seemed perfectly relaxed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Friends of Daniel Pearl, the Wall Street Journal reporter apparently kidnapped in Pakistan last week, are fustrated by the accusation that he was a United States spy.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Danny Pearl never seemed stressed. From the mid-1980's, when he was a laid-back radio host on the overnight shift at Stanford University's campus station, to the mid-1990's, when he was writing lighthearted articles for The Wall Street Journal about federal agencies that had no reason for being, Daniel Pearl, the Journal reporter apparently kidnapped in Pakistan last week, has seemed impervious to pressure.</p>
        <p>Craig Sherman, a friend who has known Mr. Pearl since both were 11 years old, said yesterday that Mr. Pearl was ''perfect academically, everybody's friend and no matter how stressed out he was, he seemed perfectly relaxed.</p>
        <p>''Danny's that way right now, knowing him,'' added Mr. Sherman, a managing partner at Venture Law Services in Kirkland, Wash. ''He's relaxed, and the rest of us are stressing out.''</p>
        <p>The anxiety for Mr. Pearl's friends and colleagues is caused not only by his disappearance but by the accusation that he had worked for the Central Intelligence Agency.</p>
        <p>A previously unknown group sent an e-mail message to news organizations late Saturday claiming, in an attachment in Urdu, to have ''arrested C.I.A. officer Daniel Pearl.'' Friends and colleagues said the accusation was absurd. The C.I.A. and Dow Jones &amp; Company, which owns The Journal, each issued denials of any such connection.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pearl disappeared on Wednesday in Karachi, where he was doing research on the Richard C. Reid, the shoe-bomb suspect.</p>
        <p>Late Saturday, eastern time, an e-mail message from a group calling itself ''The National Movement for the Restoration of Pakistani Sovereignty'' was sent to two Pakistani news organizations, The Washington Post, The New York Times and The Los Angeles Times.</p>
        <p>The Post's Southeast Asia bureau chief, Rajiv Chandrasekaran, was among the first to open the message, which he said he nearly mistook for junk mail.</p>
        <p>After he opened the four pictures of Mr. Pearl in captivity, one showing a gun to his head, Mr. Chandrasekaran telephoned a friend at The Journal.</p>
        <p>There was no indication yesterday that investigators in Pakistan or the United States had made any progress, though Mr. Pearl's case was the focus of high-level attention. Secretary of State Colin L. Powell spoke yesterday about the case with Pakistan's president, Gen. Pervez Musharraf, said Richard Boucher, the State Department spokesman.</p>
        <p>Mr. Boucher added: ''We want to reiterate our view that he should be released immediately and unconditionally. He is a respected journalist, and he has no connection with the United States government.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Boucher confirmed that F.B.I. agents had been sent to the United States Embassy in Pakistan to help local authorities in their investigation.</p>
        <p>Police investigators in Karachi said they suspected that Mr. Pearl had been kidnapped by an Islamic jihad organization called Harakat ul-Mujahedeen, or Movement of Holy Warriors, which has been tied to previous kidnappings of foreigners and had dozens of members killed by an American bombing in Afghanistan last fall.</p>
        <p>Yet officials in Karachi were puzzled by the tone of the message that the apparent abductors sent to news groups. The statement made no reference to God or common Islamic militant goals, like the removal of American forces from Saudi Arabia. It called for legal protections for 177 Pakistanis detained in the United States, the repatriation of Pakistanis now held in Cuba and the completion of a sale of fighter jets to Pakistan that Congress blocked in 1990.</p>
        <p>The authorities are trying to retrace Mr. Pearl's calls and meetings in recent weeks, when he made several trips to Pakistan to check the movements of Mr. Reid, who had studied at Islamic centers in Pakistan.</p>
        <p>Such reporting was not the kind of fare that had filled Mr. Pearl's career. He was born in Princeton, N.J., moved to California and first showed an interest in journalism at a high school in suburban Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>Alan Epstein, who was Mr. Pearl's physical education teacher in high school, said yesterday that Mr. Pearl had asked him for an introduction to a relative who edited a local college newspaper.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pearl was not always so direct. He decided on his top college choices -- Oberlin College, Reed College and Stanford -- by systemically eliminating every other university, Mr. Sherman said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pearl chose Stanford, where -- when he was not entertaining night owls with his programming of bluegrass, rock, jazz and classical music -- he was editing Stanford Commentary, a quarterly journal he co-funded. The publication featured dueling articles by ideological opponents.</p>
        <p>After graduating with a degree in communications, Mr. Pearl joined The North Adams Transcript, a newspaper in western Massachusetts with a circulation of about 8,100. There, Mr. Pearl, then 24, wrote a series of articles on the personalities and business mistakes behind the financial collapse of a local hotel.</p>
        <p>The series caught the eye of Lewis Cuyler, then the business editor of The Berkshire Eagle, who said that he guided Mr. Pearl onto his own staff. There, Mr. Pearl wrote a series of articles on land use that won a national award.</p>
        <p>At The Wall Street Journal, which he joined in 1990, Mr. Pearl made his reputation doing ''A-heads'' -- the quirky feature articles that are a staple of the newspaper's front page.</p>
        <p>''He sort of had a very offbeat sensibility, and that works very well at The Wall Street Journal,'' said Alan Murray, The Journal's Washington bureau chief.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pearl moved from Washington to the London bureau, and met his wife, Mariane, on a weekend trip to Paris.</p>
        <p>Daniel Gill, a lawyer and childhood friend, said Mr. Pearl and Mariane were married at a Cuban-themed wedding at a Normandy chateau. She is pregnant with their first child.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pearl became the South Asia bureau chief for The Journal about two years ago.</p>
        <p>Jill Abramson, who was Mr. Murray's deputy and is now The New York Times Washington bureau chief, said yesterday that Mr. Pearl was known in the bureau not just for the humorous edge to his articles but for his command of the violin and the electric bluegrass fiddle, which he played many evenings at small bars in Washington's Adams-Morgan neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''The idea they think he's a spy for the government is absurd,'' Ms. Abramson said. ''Of all the reporters who worked in the Washington bureau, he had the most jaundiced view of government. Official Washington offended him.''</p>
        <p>One 1994 feature article Mr. Pearl wrote on the Interstate Commerce Commission began: ''It is a place Franz Kafka would have loved. The tariffs have little meaning. The I.C.C. no longer has the power to regulate the shipping rates listed in the filings. So companies that have products trucked don't protest the rates. In fact, few people can decipher them.''</p>
        <p>A NATION CHALLENGED: PORTRAITS OF GRIEF: THE VICTIMS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
