<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>USA Today Top Executive Named to Run News Service</title>
    <meta content="Y29APE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1476196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Associated Press</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Usa Today</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bayot, Jennifer</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Curley, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boccardi, Louis D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Newspapers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030329T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE1DF1739F93AA15750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="382" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>USA Today Top Executive Named to Run News Service</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER BAYOT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bayot, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Thomas Curley, president and publisher of USA Today, will become president and chief executive of Associated Press; news service's governing board says appointment supports mission of Associated Press to broaden its reach to other media and to services like placement of advertising; Curley will succeed Louis D Boccardi (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Thomas Curley, the president and publisher of USA Today, will become the president and chief executive of The Associated Press, the news service's governing board said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The appointment supports the mission of The Associated Press to broaden its reach to other media and to services like placement of advertising, the board said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Thomas Curley, the president and publisher of USA Today, will become the president and chief executive of The Associated Press, the news service's governing board said yesterday.</p>
        <p>The appointment supports the mission of The Associated Press to broaden its reach to other media and to services like placement of advertising, the board said.</p>
        <p>''Tom can extend our effort in both the news and the other efforts The A.P. is in -- international video, services to newspapers, etc.,'' said Burl Osborne, the chairman of the board.</p>
        <p>Mr. Curley's appointment came with high praise for his work at USA Today, which was once mocked as a ''McPaper'' for its short articles and flashy format.</p>
        <p>''He is one of the people who was instrumental in turning it into the very serious and seriously regarded operation that it is today,'' Mr. Osborne said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Curley, 54, will succeed Louis D. Boccardi, 65, who announced in January that he would retire this summer after 18 years as top executive. The Gannett Company, the owner of USA Today and publisher of 100 daily newspapers in the United States, said it would announce a successor to Mr. Curley shortly.</p>
        <p>Mr. Curley has been president and publisher of USA Today, which has the largest circulation among the nation's daily newspapers, since 1991. He was on the news staff of the 1979 project that gave rise to the newspaper and eventually worked in every one of its departments. He is also a senior vice president of Gannett.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press last year had revenue of $562 million and serves nearly all of the country's daily newspapers, more than 5,000 of its radio and television outlets, as well as thousands more news channels internationally.</p>
        <p>Under Mr. Boccardi's tenure, it has expanded to offer a multimedia Internet operation and the Associated Press Television News, an international service based in London.</p>
        <p>Mr. Curley, who met with some Associated Press employees yesterday, said: ''I asked for their wisdom and patience as I come up to speed. I hope to convince the people at The A.P. that I am a fit.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
