<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Civilian Says Submarine Took Precautions</title>
    <meta content="Y17HAW$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/02/17/national/17HAWA.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010220T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1271413"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Greeneville (Submarine)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ehime Maru (Ship)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Japan</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hall, John M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Drew, Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waddle, Scott (Comdr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Submarines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ships and Shipping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010217T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E3D91030F934A25751C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1275" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Civilian Says Submarine Took Precautions</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER DREW</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Drew, Christopher</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>John M Hall, Texas oilman who was aboard submarine Greeneville when it struck Japanese trawler, says officers made six sweeps with periscope at two slightly different depths but saw no other ships less than 10 minutes before it surfaced and caused trawler to sink; says submarine's captain, Lt Comdr Scott Waddle, did more to check areas for other ships than has been known; statements leave submarine experts even more baffled how crew could have failed to detect trawler so close by (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Texas oilman who was aboard the submarine Greeneville said yesterday that its officers made six sweeps with the periscope at two slightly different depths but saw no other ships less than 10 minutes before it surfaced and slammed into a Japanese fishing trawler.</p>
        <p>The businessman, John M. Hall, was one of two civilians who handled some of the submarine's controls at the start of the surfacing drill that caused the accident on Feb. 9. The Greeneville shot to the surface, crashing into and sinking the Ehime Maru, a 190-foot Japanese fishing trawler. Nine people on the trawler, including four Japanese students, are missing and presumed dead.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A Texas oilman who was aboard the submarine Greeneville said yesterday that its officers made six sweeps with the periscope at two slightly different depths but saw no other ships less than 10 minutes before it surfaced and slammed into a Japanese fishing trawler.</p>
        <p>The businessman, John M. Hall, was one of two civilians who handled some of the submarine's controls at the start of the surfacing drill that caused the accident on Feb. 9. The Greeneville shot to the surface, crashing into and sinking the Ehime Maru, a 190-foot Japanese fishing trawler. Nine people on the trawler, including four Japanese students, are missing and presumed dead.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall's comments, made during a telephone interview, show that the Greeneville's captain, Lt. Cmdr. Scott Waddle, did more to check the area for other ships than had been known. But as Navy and other safety investigators search for what went wrong, submarine experts said the comments left them even more baffled how the crew could have failed to detect a trawler so close by.</p>
        <p>As soon as the periscope was raised, Mr. Hall said, a submarine officer made two 360-degree rotations and indicated that the area was clear. Commander Waddle then rotated the scope twice before giving orders to raise the submarine, and thus the height of the periscope, by two feet, Mr. Hall said. He said the commander looked through the twirling scope two more times.</p>
        <p>Retired submarine officers say that a scope provides greater visibility -- and the ability to see greater distances -- the higher it is raised.</p>
        <p>The height of the periscope is key because the Navy has said the seas were choppy, with swells as tall as six feet. Mr. Hall said he did not know how far the scope rose above the sea.</p>
        <p>Retired submarine officers say that in training exercises, a periscope would normally be raised about four to six feet above the seas. But some say that in choppy conditions and when visibility was difficult, it would be more prudent to extend the scope as high as 20 to 30 feet above the seas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall said that he and some of the 15 other civilians watched a black-and-white monitor that displayed the periscope's view. Asked what he saw during the six searches, he responded: ''Nothing but gray.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall, who first discussed the accident on NBC's ''Today'' show on Thursday, said that 10 minutes later, when the submarine shuddered with the force of the collision, Commander Waddle was so surprised that he asked, ''What the hell was that?''</p>
        <p>In yesterday's interview, Mr. Hall also provided more details about how the civilians had arranged the submarine ride and about the haunting confusion following the accident.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall said that as the trawler's passengers spilled into the sea in life rafts, the submarine officers did not know at first if they were Japanese or Chinese and asked if any civilian spoke either language and could help the crews communicate.</p>
        <p>Later, he said, an officer announced over the submarine's intercom that all 35 people on the trawler had been saved, promoting cheers among the civilians, who had been sent to wait in the torpedo room.</p>
        <p>About 10 minutes later, Mr. Hall said, the officer took back that assessment, saying that ''we have only 26 accounted for.'' Then, Mr. Hall said, some women in his group ''began crying, and the despair set in.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall also said he disagreed with criticism in Japan that the submarine crew did not do enough to try to save the trawler's passengers. He said a diver was prepared to exit a hatch toward the rear of the submarine, but that the sea swells made it too dangerous to open the hatch.</p>
        <p>At that point, the submarine's crew did not realize anyone from the trawler was missing, Mr. Hall said. The Greeneville officers, he said, also feared that if the hatch was opened, so much water could flood in that it would harm the submarine.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall, 52, has said he was the civilian who pulled a switch that set off the emergency surfacing operation. He said a crew member put his hands over Mr. Hall's to make sure the switch was engaged.</p>
        <p>Navy officials have said that a second civilian, also under close supervision, held a wheel that helped guide the submarine's ascent.</p>
        <p>In Tokyo, Japan's defense minister, Toshitsugu Saito, said it was ''outrageous'' that civilians were at the controls of the submarine.</p>
        <p>Japan's foreign minister, Yohei Kono, called Secretary of State Colin L. Powell to demand more information about what the civilians were doing at the time of the incident. And Defense Secretary Donald H. Rumsfeld met yesterday at the Pentagon with a Japanese envoy to discuss Japan's concerns about the accident.</p>
        <p>Navy officials have insisted that the civilians did nothing to contribute to the accident. The Navy has long taken civilians, as well as government officials and journalists, on such outings to build support. But Navy officials said yesterday they would no longer conduct emergency surfacing drills with civilians on board or let them sit at controls.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall said he did not see any sign that the visitors distracted the officers from their jobs. He said the sub had been at sea for more than six hours before the accident, and most civilians had already taken turns operating the levers that control the submarine's depth and direction.</p>
        <p>When he passed through the sonar room earlier in the day, he said, the operators were tracking five vessels. But Mr. Hall said he did not know if they ever detected the trawler.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall, an energy-industry consultant, served as a Marine in Vietnam. He said he had lobbied for nearly a year to get a ride on a submarine, which, he said, he viewed as the ''opportunity of a lifetime.''</p>
        <p>He said he met retired Admiral Richard C. Macke, who suggested the civilians for the Greeneville cruise, last spring while they were both involved in a golf tournament to raise money for restoration work on the U.S.S. Missouri, the World War II battleship on which the Japanese surrendered in 1945.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall was then the chief executive of Fossil Bay Resources Ltd., an oil and gas company in Texas that paid $7,500 to the U.S.S. Missouri Memorial Association in Honolulu to be a sponsor of the golf tournament.</p>
        <p>Earlier this week, Admiral Thomas Fargo, the commander of the Pacific Fleet, told several congressmen that most civilians on the Greeneville were donors to the Missouri restoration fund. But Mr. Hall said that was incorrect. He said he believed only one couple on board, Michael and Susan Nolan of Honolulu, had given money to the memorial.</p>
        <p>He said the others were ''just a social group that we put together.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Hall's wife, Leigh Ann, was on board, as was another former Fossil Bay executive, Todd Thoman and his wife, Deanda. Mr. Hall would not identify any others in the group.</p>
        <p>He said that none of the civilians were politically active or had any business ties to Admiral Macke.</p>
        <p>''When a hell of an opportunity like this comes up to go on a submarine, you get a group together,'' he said. ''It's just that simple.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  February 20, 2001, Tuesday  Articles on Feb. 12 and last Tuesday, Friday and Saturday, and in some copies on Sunday, about the Navy submarine collision that sank a Japanese training ship misstated the rank of Scott D. Waddle, the officer in charge of the submarine. He is a commander, not a lieutenant commander.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: February 20, 2001, Tuesday</p>
        <p>Articles on Feb. 12 and last Tuesday, Friday and Saturday, and in some copies on Sunday, about the Navy submarine collision that sank a Japanese training ship misstated the rank of Scott D. Waddle, the officer in charge of the submarine. He is a commander, not a lieutenant commander.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
