<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BEHIND THE WHEEL/2007 Chevrolet Silverado and GMC Sierra; Blue-Collar Work Ethic, White-Glove Manners</title>
    <meta content="25AUTO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Automobiles" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/25/automobiles/autoreviews/25AUTO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1828795"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="Behind the Wheel | 2007 Chevrolet Silverado and GMC Sierra"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Utility Vehicles and Other Light Trucks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Chevrolet Division of General Motors Corp</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C03E2DF103EF936A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1763" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BEHIND THE WHEEL/2007 Chevrolet Silverado and GMC Sierra; Blue-Collar Work Ethic, White-Glove Manners</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Blue-Collar Ethic, White-Glove Polish</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER JENSEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jensen, Christopher</byline>
      <dateline>BETHLEHEM, N.H.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WORK -- that is the role of a pickup truck in a rural area. Pickups haul stuff. They plow snow. They are tools, not macho-mechanical ego-support systems.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, there aren't too many people whose goal is to be uncomfortable while doing any kind of work, including driving a full-size pickup.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The 2007 Chevrolet Silverado and the similar GMC Sierra Silverado are all-new trucks that combine a traditional work ethic with a surprising amount of finesse.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WORK -- that is the role of a pickup truck in a rural area. Pickups haul stuff. They plow snow. They are tools, not macho-mechanical ego-support systems.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, there aren't too many people whose goal is to be uncomfortable while doing any kind of work, including driving a full-size pickup.</p>
        <p>''We worked very diligently in terms of refinement,'' said Jully Burau, the assistant chief engineer for General Motors' full-size pickups, including the 2007 Chevrolet Silverado and the similar GMC Sierra.</p>
        <p>It is irksome that diligence doesn't always guarantee success. But it did with the Silverado and Sierra, all-new trucks that combine a traditional work ethic with a surprising amount of finesse.</p>
        <p>That's a good thing for General Motors, since Toyota has just come out with its own all-new (and bigger than ever) full-size truck, the 2007 Tundra. [Page 4.]</p>
        <p>G.M. cannot afford to have the Silverado fail. Last year, it sold 636,000 of the trucks, making the Silverado the second-best-selling vehicle in the United States. First was the Ford F-Series pickups. (G.M.C. sold another 210,000 Sierras.)</p>
        <p>Pickups are also money machines. An automaker easily makes $4,000 to $5,000 in net profit on a full-size pickup, said David E. Cole, chairman of the Center for Automotive Research, a consulting and research firm in Ann Arbor, Mich.</p>
        <p>As with most full-size pickups, there are so many variants of the Silverado/Sierra that the indecisive may never be able to settle on one. The offerings start with a regular cab, which comes with only a front seat that carries two adults comfortably. The extended cab offers a back seat, but one so small that adult legs may not be extended.</p>
        <p>Finally, there is the crew cab with a truly usable back seat where two adults may ride with dignity.</p>
        <p>The cargo beds are available in lengths of 5-foot-8 (short bed), 6-foot-6 (standard bed) and 8 feet (long bed).</p>
        <p>There are five suspensions ranging from ''smooth ride'' and ''off road'' to one designed for maximum towing prowess.</p>
        <p>There is a choice of four engines: a 195-horsepower 4.3-liter V-6, a 295-horsepower 4.8-liter V-8, a 315-horsepower 5.3-liter V-8 and a 367-horsepower 6-liter V-8.</p>
        <p>Base prices for these light-duty Silverados start at $18,760 and run to $38,990 including the destination charge. Options can push the price above $45,000.</p>
        <p>My test model was an extended-cab LT2 with four-wheel drive and the standard bed. It had a 5.3-liter V-8 and a starting price of $31,690. The options, totaling $3,029, included leather upholstery and the Z71 off-road suspension package, bringing the price to $35,619. Beneath an updated and smoothed-out look is a new, stronger frame and redesigned suspension -- the changes included replacing the old torsion-bar front suspension with a new coil-over shock design.</p>
        <p>Befitting the work-truck role, the rear suspension is still a solid-axle design, but it is well behaved and not inclined to skitter even while cornering on a rumpled surface.</p>
        <p>The advantage of the more robust body and frame became clear on Route 16 along the lovely Androscoggin River. Hit a rough surface and the Silverado feels solid, unlike a 2007 Ford F-150 driven about the same time that easily got the shakes.</p>
        <p>Unfortunately that feeling of solidity carries over to the Z71 suspension. Its stiff ride is mildly unpleasant on a bad road and jiggly at other times.</p>
        <p>The steering is vastly improved, giving the driver a far better sense of what the vehicle is doing. Consequently, the Silverado felt remarkably responsive for a 5,300-pound vehicle as it followed Route 26, climbing and turning to slip through the crack in the mountains called the Dixville Notch. In comparison, the F-150 felt ill at ease and a bit clumsy.</p>
        <p>The feel of the brake pedal is quite good; antilock brakes are standard on all models.</p>
        <p>Should the Silverado start to slide, help is available from electronic stability control, which G.M. calls StabiliTrak. Unfortunately that life-saving help is available only to those with extra cash.</p>
        <p>While StabiliTrak is standard on the crew cab, it is a $425 option on the extended cab -- and only if you buy the more expensive LT rather than the base model, the WT (for ''Work Truck''). Getting an LT increases the price over the entry-level model by almost $3,000; the fancy LTZ is another $5,500 or so.</p>
        <p>Nor can you get StabiliTrak on Silverados with the regular cab.</p>
        <p>One worry about any vehicle with a high center of gravity, like a pickup, is rolling over. In rollover-resistance tests conducted by the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, the tested Silverado (which had StabiliTrak) did well, earning four out of five stars.</p>
        <p>Powertrain snobs may sneer at G.M.'s quaint four-speed automatic transmission, given that the new Tundra is available with either a five-speed or six-speed automatic.</p>
        <p>But the four-speed and the 5.3 engine are splendid companions. There is neither a wait for acceleration nor a racket when power is delivered. Downshifts come quickly and upshifts go smoothly, so there is no sense of second-class gearbox status.</p>
        <p>The 5.3-liter engine has a cylinder-shutdown system that G.M. calls ''active fuel management.'' When all cylinders aren't needed, the engine switches from a V-8 to a V-4 to save gas. At a steady speed on a flat surface, four cylinders may suffice, but if you nudge the gas pedal the truck is running on all cylinders again.</p>
        <p>On a 200-mile Interstate trip through the hills of Vermont I set the cruise at 65 miles an hour, watched an instrument on the dash tell me how many cylinders were being used, and managed 18 m.p.g.</p>
        <p>The model I was driving was rated at 16 miles a gallon in town and 20 on the highway by the Environmental Protection Agency. That is a tiny bit better than the E.P.A. estimate for the 4.3-liter V-6 or the 4.8-liter V-8.</p>
        <p>The test truck's engine also had a flexible fuel feature, which means it can use E85, a blend of 15 percent gasoline and 85 percent ethanol. But E85 is hard to find outside the Midwest and using it with an engine that can also burn gasoline means a huge drop in fuel economy. Burning E85 drops the city rating to 12 m.p.g., from 16 m.p.g., the E.P.A. says, and the highway rating to 15, from 20.</p>
        <p>Working on the assumption that gas costs $2.24 a gallon and E85 is $2.11, the E.P.A. figures that over 15,000 miles the reduced fuel economy would cost you $434 more than burning 100 percent gasoline.</p>
        <p>Work trucks have to be able to work, obviously, and G.M. says that almost every Silverado variant can now carry a bigger payload. A payload is the combined weight of people and cargo. The increase is typically 100 to 200 pounds depending on the model, the automaker says.</p>
        <p>The model I tested had a payload capacity of 1,735 pounds, an increase of about 350 pounds. Its cargo bed can carry 60.7 cubic feet of whatever, an increase of almost 4 cubic feet.</p>
        <p>With the 6-liter V-8, the maximum towing capacity has increased to 10,500 pounds from 10,200.</p>
        <p>The interior has received a serious upgrade along with everything else. It includes comfy front seats and enough soundproofing to make the cabin wonderfully hushed even at highway speeds. There are plenty of trays and bins for orderly motoring.</p>
        <p>The only complaint about the controls is that the heating and air-conditioning switches are so low and small that they can be hard for squinting baby boomers to read. This suggests a new profit center: a dealer-installed magnifying glass with suction cups that could be fixed to the dash or the driver's forehead.</p>
        <p>One safety disappointment is that inflatable air curtains, which cover the side windows andare designed to provide head protection in a side-impact crash, are not available on the base (''Work Truck'') models. Buyers must make a big leap to at least an LT, at which point the safety device is a $395 option.</p>
        <p>Safety researchers say such protection can significantly reduce the chance of serious head injuries. It is unfortunate G.M. has restricted its availability.</p>
        <p>The Silverado has yet to be crashed in side-impact tests, but it got a top score -- five stars -- in front tests by the safety agency.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s cars have taken a lot of criticism over the years, but with the new Silverado and Sierra the company has proved that it still has the expertise to build a first-rate full-size pickup. The only disappointment is that lifesaving equipment is not available to budget-minded buyers.</p>
        <p>INSIDE TRACK: Whistle while you work.</p>
        <p>A Big Fist and Some Trash Talk</p>
        <p>WITH the arrival of the 2007 Tundra this month, Toyota has made its most serious move yet into the full-size pickup market, which it calls ''the single largest opportunity for Toyota's future growth'' in the United States.</p>
        <p>The truck's maximum-macho styling also makes it clear that Toyota is not pulling its visual punches with the bigger-than-ever model. One subtle hint that Toyota is taking off the gloves: it describes the design theme as ''the power of the fist.''</p>
        <p>Toyota introduced its first large pickup, the T-100, in 1993 when American-Japanese trade tensions were high. Small by American full-size-truck standards, the T-100 wasn't a serious competitor.</p>
        <p>Toyota regrouped in 1999 with its first Tundra, then in 2003 added the hefty Double Cab, which posed a more direct challenge to Chevy, Dodge and Ford.</p>
        <p>The latest Tundra gets right in the face of Detroit's big trucks in size and abilities. It comes in three cab styles and three bed lengths.</p>
        <p>The transmissions are five- and six-speed automatics. Engine choices are a 236-horsepower 4-liter V-6; a 271-horsepower 4.7-liter V-8; and a 5.7-liter V-8 rated at 381 horsepower and 401 pound-feet of torque.</p>
        <p>But unlike the new Chevrolet Silverado's 5.3-liter V-8, the Toyota engines cannot shut down four cylinders to save fuel. That gives the Silverados better fuel economy, according to government estimates.</p>
        <p>Tundras start at $22,935 for a regular cab with two-wheel drive. The most expensive Tundra has a base price of $42,495. One big advantage over the Silverado: electronic stability control and inflatable side air curtains are standard on all models.</p>
        <p>Toyota is in a position to more than double Tundra sales. A new San Antonio plant can build 200,000 a year, and an Indiana factory is expected to produce about 100,000.</p>
        <p>A decade ago nobody imagined Toyota would have the nerve to build a full-size truck in Texas, the star-spangled heartland of American pickups. But who would have guessed that a Camry would compete in Nascar's Nextel Cup?</p>
        <p>CHRISTOPHER JENSEN</p>
        <p>Behind the Wheel | 2007 Chevrolet Silverado and GMC Sierra</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
