<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Discovering Divine Sites for Condos</title>
    <meta content="25post" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Real Estate" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/02/25/realestate/25post.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1828787"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="POSTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Convents</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gospel Temple Church of America (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hughes, C J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City/Manhattan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Condominiums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3DF103EF936A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="609" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Discovering Divine Sites for Condos</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Discovering Divine Sites for Condos</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By C. J. HUGHES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hughes, C J</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Number of former houses of worship in Manhattan are being converted to non-religious uses; among projects is Rhapsody, 22-apartment condominium building at 127th Street in Harlem in former home of Gospel Temple Church of America; at 233 East 17th Street, former convent will offer 13 luxury condominiums priced from $1.58 million to $4.95 million; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ANYONE entertaining hopes of someday living in a converted church should not necessarily be heartened by the recent decision by the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of New York to shutter or merge 21 parishes.</p>
        <p>''It's our hope and intention to use those for other forms of ministry,'' said Joseph Zwilling, a spokesman for the archdiocese, explaining that nursing homes and schools were the most likely uses for the space.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A number of former houses of worship in Manhattan will soon offer new options in post-ecclesiastical living.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ANYONE entertaining hopes of someday living in a converted church should not necessarily be heartened by the recent decision by the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of New York to shutter or merge 21 parishes.</p>
        <p>''It's our hope and intention to use those for other forms of ministry,'' said Joseph Zwilling, a spokesman for the archdiocese, explaining that nursing homes and schools were the most likely uses for the space.</p>
        <p>Yet there are other former houses of worship in Manhattan, and a number of them will soon offer new options in post-ecclesiastical living.</p>
        <p>Rhapsody on Fifth Avenue is the name of a new condominium at 127th Street in Harlem that has commandeered the limestone-and-brick former home of the Gospel Temple Church of America, which held services inside for 50 years.</p>
        <p>In November, when construction is scheduled for completion, Rhapsody will have 22 apartments, from 520-square-foot studios to 2,000-square-foot three-bedrooms. Prices will range from $420,000 to $1.5 million. Since the sales office opened two months ago, four condos have sold, said Arthur Fefferman, president of AFC Realty Capital, the project's developer.</p>
        <p>Unlike the Mount Moriah Baptist Church next door, the 1917 Gospel Temple building did not have an ecclesiastical look, Mr. Fefferman said. Although its facade is generously decorated with Beaux-Arts garlands and shields, he explained, its understatedness made it easier to convert and to sell.</p>
        <p>A similarly neutral facade attracted the Vesta Development Group to a former convent, cater-corner to Stuyvesant Square, at 233 East 17th Street.</p>
        <p>A 19th-century red-brick edifice, the former convent does have at least one feature associated with religious architecture: arched Gothic windows. Its 13 condos, priced from $1.58 million to $4.95 million, will be ready by April, said Tamir Shemesh, an executive vice president at Prudential Douglas Elliman who is handling the sales, adding that 70 percent had been sold.</p>
        <p>Although one four-story unit, still on the market, contains a chapel with 24-foot painted wood ceilings, none of the others bear any trace of their previous functions, Mr. Shemesh said, explaining that ''most buyers don't want it to look too much like a church.''</p>
        <p>Two exceptions are Jonathan and Melinda Gould, who are designing a new home for themselves inside Christ Lutheran Church, at 355 East 19th Street between First and Second Avenues.</p>
        <p>A new luxury condo tower, which the Goulds will also develop, will stretch above the church and contain six units, all three-bedrooms. They will come up for sale in late fall, according to Mr. Shemesh, who is also the broker for this project, with a move-in date for spring 2008.</p>
        <p>Ecclesiastical flourishes will also be an attraction at a luxury condo to be called the Novare, now under construction in a marble edifice that used to be a Methodist church at 135 West Fourth Street, near Washington Square Park. Flank Architecture, the developer, plans to use the building's dazzling stained-glass windows in six of the eight apartments, which range in price from $2.2 million to $5.6 million.</p>
        <p>So far, three units have found buyers, said Brian Babst, a senior associate of the Corcoran Group.</p>
        <p>Next door to the Novare is the Parsonage, a four-unit luxury condo that DJH Development is building inside the 7,000-square-foot red-brick building where the church's pastors used to live.</p>
        <p>The units range in size from 1,000 to 3,100 square feet, and each will have a wood-burning fireplace original to the building. Sales start in the next few weeks; prices will begin at $1.6 million and top out at $3.6 million, Mr. Babst said.</p>
        <p>''There were three Methodist churches in this ZIP code,'' he said, explaining how the two properties became available. ''Closing one made sense.''</p>
        <p>POSTING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
