<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Snooping on Your Tech-Savvy Teenagers</title>
    <meta content="25RparentingCN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2007" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1828719"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2007"/>
      <series series.name="PARENTING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Winerip, Michael</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20070225T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C02E0DA133EF936A15751C0A9619C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Snooping on Your Tech-Savvy Teenagers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL WINERIP</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Winerip, Michael</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Michael Winerip Parenting column explores issue of whether or not parents should monitor their teens' use of Internet; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I AM a technological idiot. I pay my bills in envelopes, write my columns and books on a 16-year-old desktop computer and use a laptop to meet my very limited online needs: e-mail; research; occasional MapQuesting; Googling myself.</p>
        <p>My kids, on the other hand, come home from school and make a beeline for the computers. They put the TV on mainly for background noise. Once in a while they'll glance from the computer screen to see what's happening on this week's episode of MTV's ''Date My Mom,'' but it is the computer that rivets them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I AM a technological idiot. I pay my bills in envelopes, write my columns and books on a 16-year-old desktop computer and use a laptop to meet my very limited online needs: e-mail; research; occasional MapQuesting; Googling myself.</p>
        <p>My kids, on the other hand, come home from school and make a beeline for the computers. They put the TV on mainly for background noise. Once in a while they'll glance from the computer screen to see what's happening on this week's episode of MTV's ''Date My Mom,'' but it is the computer that rivets them.</p>
        <p>We don't give them cellphones, and still, our phone rarely rings -- they're busy instant messaging their thousand closest friends. They listen to music, check the surfing sites for wave height and weather, get the West Coast basketball scores, play games and visit YouTube, MySpace and Fantasy Sports, along with numerous other sites I don't know.</p>
        <p>Should I know?</p>
        <p>I don't want to.</p>
        <p>As a parent, it's hard to know how much you need to know.</p>
        <p>I know how much time they spend on the computer, and we battle over that.</p>
        <p>But I don't know how they spend that time.</p>
        <p>As a journalist, I get bombarded with e-mail messages from tech companies extolling software that will protect children from online predators. And while I'm definitely 100 percent against predators, on or offline, my instinct is that this is not a technology issue. Still, I am not totally trustworthy on this front -- the technological idiot inside warps me -- so I talked with someone who gets paid by parents to outsmart their children's computers.</p>
        <p>Jim Mulvaney is a private investigator whose Manhattan-based company, Tactical Intelligence Services, does everything from corporate security to divorce sleuthing to snooping on kids' computer use.</p>
        <p>While a child is at school, he installs software that records all incoming and outgoing images and messages, forwarding copies either to his own or the parents' e-mail address. He says half these cases concern 17- to 19-year-old boys who have already been caught drinking or using drugs, and whose parents want to monitor them.</p>
        <p>The other half, he says, involve young teenage girls. He describes a businessman from Garden City, on Long Island, who discovered his 13-year-old posting on MySpace. The girl wasn't in trouble, he says -- she was an honors student and athlete -- but the father was unsettled to find she had a secret cyberlife. After a month of spying, Mr. Mulvaney concluded, ''There wasn't a problem, just normal girl stuff'' -- which cost the father $1,000 to know.</p>
        <p>Was her privacy violated? ''She's 13, she doesn't have privacy rights when it comes to her parents,'' says Mr. Mulvaney. ''She's living in their house, using the computer they paid for, eating their food, and they're responsible for her.''</p>
        <p>In the case of a 13-year-old girl in Dix Hills, N.Y., Mr. Mulvaney says, he intercepted a message about drinking a concoction (in her words) ''of like jim beam, jack, vodka and God knows what else haha then puked everywhere not a good time haha.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulvaney says the parents didn't confront the girl but took this as a wake-up call to give her more attention. ''They changed family schedules to make sure a parent was home with her more, planned more family outings, spent more time showing her she was loved,'' he says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mulvaney's 16-year-old son, Jack, has played ball with my sons, and I asked the father if he had installed the software to snoop on Jack's computer. ''No,'' he said. ''This product is actually something I have mixed feelings about. Parents should consider it, but you don't want to invent problems. I think it's best to be minimally invasive as long as you're feeling you're on top of things.''</p>
        <p>He told me that Jack had a few drinking incidents last summer and once was with two girls who were stopped by the police for smoking pot, though Jack maintained he was not. For his work, Mr. Mulvaney uses a special swab that picks up traces of drugs, and that night he swabbed Jack. ''I swabbed his forehead, his Palm Pilot, his iPod, his cellphone. Nothing.''</p>
        <p>But with three incidents in a few weeks' time, the father was concerned. The computer expert's solution? Very low-tech. He changed his son's curfew from midnight to 10, monitored Jack's choice of friends, and, most important, he says, spent more time with him. They went to lunch, movies, took a weeklong family trip, went together to buy new tape for Jack's hockey sticks.</p>
        <p>Asked about this, Jack says he noticed. ''We were doing stuff so I could stop being out too much and doing nothing,'' he says. Did it work? His father says yes. Jack says: ''It worked a little. I think most teenagers will get in trouble. I started being smarter. If I was going to do something bad, I'd do it someplace safe where no one could see me.''</p>
        <p>My approach is closer to Carolyn Cuttler's. She's a friend, a mom and a high school guidance counselor in Long Beach, N.Y. Ms. Cuttler insists that her three sons -- no matter how late they get in -- come kiss her goodnight. That's her alcohol test.</p>
        <p>I get up close and sniff my boys. They know why. And if they've gone to bed, and I'm concerned, I'll stick my head in the room to see if it smells of alcohol.</p>
        <p>Our solution to computer issues is also low-tech. The computers are not in bedrooms, they're in the family room, our most public space.</p>
        <p>And much harder -- and more important, I think -- my wife and I have devised a work life (hers in the early years, mine now) so there's a parent around from the time they get home until they go to bed.</p>
        <p>As I write this, yet another cautionary e-mail message has arrived citing a new study, in the journal Pediatrics, which found that 42 percent of 10- to 17-year-olds had seen online pornography in the previous year. The study, which recommends getting a state-of-the-art Internet filter, was forwarded to me by a company selling state-of-the-art Internet filters.</p>
        <p>While it is true there was no online when I was a kid, there were magazines full of naked women that we looked at in Jack Walker's basement, and Playboy magazines that we found in plain envelopes in my dad's den.</p>
        <p>Part of the greatness of those magazines was that our parents didn't know. Now, I'm not endorsing online pornography, and if I walked by the computer and saw it, I'd make my kids get rid of it this second. Still, those magazines a generation ago did the same thing for us that 16-year-old Jack Mulvaney describes today -- made us feel a little dangerous in a safe place.</p>
        <p>PARENTING E-mail: parenting@nytimes.com</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">E-mail: parenting@nytimes.com</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
