<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mirror, Mirror on the Wall</title>
    <meta content="09MIRROR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1534175"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parnes, Francine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Dorothy</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ray, Emily</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weinberger, Kathryn</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Sova, Michel</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031109T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DB1030F93AA35752C1A9659C8B63" item-length="2233" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mirror, Mirror on the Wall</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FRANCINE PARNES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Parnes, Francine</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on cosmetic make-overs describes work of makeup artists Dorothy White, Emily Ray, Kathryn Weinberger and Michel Sova; photos (Special Issue: Westchester at Its Best) (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF ever there has been someone who knows how to recreate her image through the decades, it is Madonna.</p>
        <p>''She tortures me with her style,'' Isaac Mizrahi, the fashion designer, once said during her early incarnations. ''No one has to tell her, 'Madonna, it's really time to change your look.'''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF ever there has been someone who knows how to recreate her image through the decades, it is Madonna.</p>
        <p>''She tortures me with her style,'' Isaac Mizrahi, the fashion designer, once said during her early incarnations. ''No one has to tell her, 'Madonna, it's really time to change your look.'''</p>
        <p>Since the 1980's, Madonna has changed her look about as often as some people change their mind. But only recently have makeovers dominated the popular culture, thanks to television programs like ''Extreme Makeover'' and ''Queer Eye for the Straight Guy.''</p>
        <p>Still, you don't have to be on the air to reinvent yourself. You can try out a new you by changing your hairstyle or hair color, applying colored contact lenses or slipping into a wig or padded bra.</p>
        <p>One of the quickest tickets to a transformation is available at a local department store cosmetics counter or hair salon. Makeup makeovers allow for a commitment-free transition, as easily removed as applying cold cream.</p>
        <p>If you're ready to hear your friends remark that you somehow look better but they don't know quite why, it might be time to try a makeover. Here are four cosmetic artists whose love of makeup became a full-time job.</p>
        <p>Look, Mom. No Bare Faces.</p>
        <p>Dorothy White, a makeup artist for Clinique, never doubted her calling, even though her mother prohibited her from wearing makeup before she was 18.</p>
        <p>''As a young girl, I always admired women who wore makeup, because I wanted to wear it so badly,'' said Ms. White, who works at the Clinique counter for Macy's at Garden State Plaza in Paramus, N.J.</p>
        <p>Ms. White took her cue from her glamorous Aunt Gertrude.</p>
        <p>''She would wear it every day, whether she was going to the supermarket or running outside, or to church,'' Ms. White said. ''As teenagers, we would sit there and watch her put it on, and I'd say to myself: 'Oh, my goodness. I can't wait to wear makeup.'''</p>
        <p>Indeed, she didn't wait. The piles of mascara, eye shadow and foundation were all the enticement that Ms. White needed to break her mother's embargo.</p>
        <p>''You know when your mom says you can't wear it, it makes you want to do it more?'' said Ms. White, who succumbed to the lure of lipstick at 13. ''My aunt would wear red lipstick and had full lips. I always admired her lips. ''I would question her, 'Why do you wear makeup every day?' She would always say, 'It enhances my beauty.'''</p>
        <p>Though Ms. White made an early foray into cosmetics, she said: ''A lot of women really don't know how to apply makeup. This is a teaching process for them.''</p>
        <p>That is why she does a Clinique makeover on only half of the customer's face and then lets her subject practice on the other side.</p>
        <p>After attending a cosmetology school, Ms. White gained expertise in makeup for African-American women. Her top tip: ''Because black skin comes in so many shades, you have to match it with the shade of foundation as perfectly as possible,'' she said. ''If you don't match the tone, the risk is a customer walking away from the counter with an embarrassing demarcation under the jawbone that doesn't look natural.''</p>
        <p>Embarrassment is bad enough, but sometimes a faulty application of makeup can inspire downright terror. Ms. White recalled her own horror story from age 16.</p>
        <p>''I always admired Diana Ross with the long lashes and dark eyeliner,'' she said, explaining why she went out and bought fake lashes for the first time. ''I got to the left eye and apparently had too much glue on the lash. I proceeded to press down the lash and glued my eye together. I panicked. I was yelling, 'Help me' and the funny thing was, tears were only going out of the one eye.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''I didn't realize all you had to do was wait for the glue to dry and peel it off. I never will forget that story. Now I can put lashes on with my eyes closed.''</p>
        <p>Clinique counter at Macy's, Garden State Plaza, Routes 4 and 17 Paramus, N.J. Phone at counter: (201)291-3251. Clinique does not charge for makeovers, which are done if staff members are available.</p>
        <p>In the Right Light</p>
        <p>One makeup tip that works for just about everyone is to use the right lighting, said Emily Ray, who travels nationally for Avon, primarily in the Northeast, in Connecticut and New York, doing makeovers and teaching makeovers to Avon beauty representatives.</p>
        <p>Ms. Ray learned that lesson one time when she scheduled a makeover with a woman who wanted to remake her look for a new job at a conservative company.</p>
        <p>''I was thinking it would be a quick color updating,'' Ms. Ray said.</p>
        <p>Instead, a redheaded, green-eyed woman met her at the door with bright green eye shadow, vibrant peach blush and iridescent pink lipstick.</p>
        <p>''I knew right then and there this was going to be an overhaul,'' she said.</p>
        <p>After Ms. Ray recalibrated her colors, ''a radiant but businesslike woman was standing before me,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Pleased with the makeover, the client said she just wanted to observe it in her bathroom mirror, though the lighting there was darker.</p>
        <p>''Several minutes passed and she still hadn't come out,'' Ms. Ray said. ''Imagine my surprise when she walked out with the green eye shadow and pink lipstick back on. I just about fell over.''</p>
        <p>When the client explained that she was accustomed to more color, Ms. Ray asked if she ever checked her makeup in natural light.</p>
        <p>''Not surprisingly, the answer was no,'' she said. ''She had this funky 40-watt bulb, with a plastic cover over it. She wasn't getting true light.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Ray added: ''For another hour we worked together reviewing magazines and looking in the mirror a lot and worked out a look. She has since installed a skylight in her bathroom.''</p>
        <p>Not that looking unique is bad. ''I love it when I get to do makeovers for fashion shows or people -- yes, I've done men -- who are very fashion-forward, or have careers where they can truly flaunt their individuality,'' Ms. Ray said. ''It really brings out the 'artist' in 'makeup artist.'''</p>
        <p>But she is just as creative when she gives skin care and makeup consultations to chemotherapy patients who have lost their hair.</p>
        <p>''When you look good on the outside, it really does affect how you feel,'' said Ms. Ray, who started as an Avon representative in her neighborhood, in part because the job allowed her to bring along her baby daughter in a stroller.</p>
        <p>After one makeup lesson in which she taught patients how to create eyebrows with makeup and how to adjust their skin tone from the side effects of chemotherapy, ''they could look in the mirror and not see a cancer patient but see a woman,'' Ms. Ray said.</p>
        <p>''I realized right then that my career as a beauty consultant was more than just applying makeup to a woman and teaching her about beauty products.''</p>
        <p>Emily Ray, makeup artist; (860)912-9373; www.youravon.com/emilyray; emilyray@avon.net. A one-hour makeover at a customer's home is free, and there is no obligation to buy makeup products, though the average sales are $65.</p>
        <p>Here Come the Brides</p>
        <p>At the Richard Scott Salon and Day Spa in Mount Kisco, N.Y., which opened last March, Kathryn Weinberger loves working with brides because ''it is the most exciting time of any woman's life,'' she said.</p>
        <p>''To be a part of making that the most memorable and beautiful experience is truly rewarding.''</p>
        <p>Sure, but sometimes excitement can be nerve-racking, and Ms. Weinberger should know. At the salon she owns with Ellen Mancuso, the KathrynEllen Make-up Studio, bridal makeup is a large portion of her work.</p>
        <p>One time a bride scorched her head when her sister attempted to style her hair with a curling iron, Ms. Weinberger said. ''I am talking a huge welt on her forehead,'' she said. ''Needless to say, the bride was hysterical.''</p>
        <p>The solution? ''Thank God I happened to have Dermablend,'' she said, referring to the concealing cream commonly used for disguising scars and birthmarks.</p>
        <p>Another time, ''I had a bride who had 'Daddy' tattooed across her back,'' Ms. Weinberger said. ''I had to cover it.'' The bride wore a backless dress.</p>
        <p>''Who gets 'Daddy' written across their back?'' Ms. Weinberger wondered. ''Was it a former boyfriend?''</p>
        <p>Did she ever find out? ''In those kinds of scenarios, you don't even ask,'' Ms. Weinberger said. ''You're paying good money; sure, I'll cover whatever you want.''</p>
        <p>What about putting makeup on the flower girl? ''I might give her lip gloss and some blush,'' Ms. Weinberger said. ''There are no rules in makeup,'' she added, but ''generally, women under 20 do not need foundation.''</p>
        <p>Still, she said, ''I have done makeup on 9-year-olds where the mother says, 'Do eyeliner and whatever she wants,' like she's a 20-year-old. If she wants a full face of makeup, if she wants to pay me to do that, I'm going to have to do that.''</p>
        <p>There is the money question again. What if budgets were not an issue and Ms. Weinberger had the resources available to make over artists on television shows?</p>
        <p>''I would love to videotape all my makeovers,'' she said. She would give the tape to the client ''so they can see the transformation and can also have something to watch when they want to replicate it.''</p>
        <p>The easiest makeup tip for brides: no exchanging smooches with anyone before the wedding. It will only smudge your makeup. ''They have to do air kisses,'' Ms. Weinberger said.</p>
        <p>KathrynEllen Make-up Studio at Richard Scott Salon and Day Spa, 15-17 South Moger Avenue, Mount Kisco, N.Y. Salon: (914)242-1700, www.richardscottsalon.com. Fee: $25 to $100, depending on the type of makeup application.</p>
        <p>Open Minds, Hidden Shadows</p>
        <p>Michel Sova's earliest makeup memory is watching her mother whenever she got ready to go out with her father.</p>
        <p>''She was always beautiful without makeup, so when she did her makeup it was even more amazing,'' Ms. Sova said. ''I somehow wanted to become a part of that process, because it seemed like such a happy, beautiful thing to me. So I started putting baby powder on the eyelids of this platinum-blond doll my sister and I had. I somehow knew that putting that frosty white stuff on her eyelids would make her look even more angelic, and it really did.''</p>
        <p>She added, ''As a child that felt pretty powerful, to know I had an idea like that and it worked beautifully the very first time.''</p>
        <p>Frosty white stuff may add charm, but pragmatism dictates that it is important to first hide under-eye circles with concealer. Of all the faces she has beautified in the last 14 years, ''99.5 percent need some level of cover under their eyes,'' Ms. Nova said. ''And yet it seems to be the most ignored makeup step I've seen. Women will put lipstick on or eye shadow before they address the dark circles under their eyes. It makes a person look tired at best and sickly at worst, and it makes the actual eye look smaller.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sova said the most fun makeup work is with teenagers, typically for proms and bat mitzvahs.</p>
        <p>''Makeup is usually still new to them, so they are very open and don't put the same limitations on makeup possibilities as women who have been wearing makeup for years,'' she said. ''Women who have already worn makeup regularly for much of their lives may have had a bad makeup experience with a previous artist or tried themselves to wear colors or certain products and worn them incorrectly.''</p>
        <p>Once that has happened, ''it is very difficult for them to trust someone else's ideas of what will look beautiful on them,'' she said.</p>
        <p>If Ms. Sova could try anything, she would transform a client into a famous personality like Marilyn Monroe or Sophia Loren, or create looks from different decades, from the 1920's to the present day.</p>
        <p>''I love the transformation process of making people look totally different,'' she said. ''It would be interesting to see which time period suits them best.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Sova works at Maximus Spa/Salons, 1504 Old Country Road, the Source Mall, Westbury, N.Y. 11590. Salon: (516)222-8880, www.maximusspasalon.com. Fee: Maximus makeovers are $45 to $70, but the fee can be waived with the purchase of products. Michel Sova: www.makeupartistny.com or makeupartist@att.net.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
