<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What Do Blue Jays Like to Eat? Ask a Virtual Moth</title>
    <meta content="13MOTH" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1053687"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Virtual Reality (Computers)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Virtual Reality (Computers)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Birds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9804E2DB163AF930A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="949" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What Do Blue Jays Like to Eat? Ask a Virtual Moth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CAROL KAESUK YOON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Yoon, Carol Kaesuk</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Scientists are training birds to aim at virtual insects, computer-generated fakes at heart of growoing field of ecology; increasing number of such bloodless creatures are being shaped, colored and directed on computer screens as researchers find new ways to explore wide array of questions about why real animals act the way they do; virtual menagerie already in use by biologists includes spiders, flies, chickens and fish, variously posed as prey, predators or alluring mates; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The scene has been played out again and again over the millennia: a hungry bird spies a bug and pounces, driving its beak into its hearty insect meal. Now, in a twist on this ancient story, scientists are training birds to aim at virtual insects, computer-generated fakes at the heart of a growing field of ecology.</p>
        <p>An increasing number of such bloodless creatures are being shaped, colored and directed on the computer screen as researchers find new ways to explore a wide array of questions about why real animals act the way they do. The virtual menagerie already in use by biologists includes spiders, flies, chickens and fish, variously posed as prey, predators or alluring mates.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The scene has been played out again and again over the millennia: a hungry bird spies a bug and pounces, driving its beak into its hearty insect meal. Now, in a twist on this ancient story, scientists are training birds to aim at virtual insects, computer-generated fakes at the heart of a growing field of ecology.</p>
        <p>An increasing number of such bloodless creatures are being shaped, colored and directed on the computer screen as researchers find new ways to explore a wide array of questions about why real animals act the way they do. The virtual menagerie already in use by biologists includes spiders, flies, chickens and fish, variously posed as prey, predators or alluring mates.</p>
        <p>''What we have here is a virtual ecology,'' said Dr. Alan B. Bond, who along with Dr. Alan C. Kamil, a fellow behavioral ecologist at the University of Nebraska, carried out a study reported in the current issue of the journal Nature. ''The blending of the living animal and the computer model allows us to ask questions that were inaccessible.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Bond and Dr. Kamil were interested in the longstanding question of why members of a single species may have very different color patterns. One popular hypothesis was that the variation results when predators focus on hunting down the most common type until it becomes rare and then switch to hunt whatever has become the common type in its place. By doing so, they would prevent any one color type from being hunted into oblivion.</p>
        <p>But the hypothesis has been difficult to test. Field studies involved things like leaving out banquets of differently colored worms fashioned of pastry and coming back to see what the birds had taken. But while researchers saw that the common type was favored, they were unable to show that birds actively switched their favorite from one type to another as frequencies of different types changed.</p>
        <p>On the computer, however, researchers created a virtual population of differently patterned black-and-white winged moths, based on the wing pattern of actual underwing moths. The computer then drew sample moths from the virtual population and offered them to the birds. Pecked moths were considered killed and were removed from the population.</p>
        <p>Researchers saw that the birds tended to attack the common types and pass on the uncommon types, just as predicted, as different types waxed and waned in frequency.</p>
        <p>It took researchers two months to train each blue jay to recognize on-screen moths as food items, but once they did, researchers say the birds went at the images with such vigor that they had to place a protective shield over the screen to keep the jays from shattering the monitors.</p>
        <p>Although the blue jays were slow to catch on, some animals respond instantly to a computer-generated meal.</p>
        <p>When shown a computer-generated insect, toads ''will look at it, hop over to it and actually put their tongue on the screen trying to get it,'' said Dr. David Clark, an animal behaviorist at Alma College in Michigan who is also doing virtual experimentation. A praying mantis, he said, will stalk a virtual fly and lunge its legs at it.</p>
        <p>Dr. Clark has also worked with spiders and finds that females do their come-hither leg tapping at the sight of virtual males performing just the right courtship behaviors. He said he had been able to tease apart the important elements of courtship by creating male spiders of varying color patterns (something he said would have killed real animals if done with paint) and programming them to perform combinations of behaviors that no actual spider would ever do.</p>
        <p>But not all animals take to computers so readily.</p>
        <p>''I tried showing snakes mice walking around on a little screen,'' Dr. Clark said. ''I didn't have much luck.'' Lizards were similarly unimpressed.</p>
        <p>Part of the problem, researchers said, is that computer monitors are specifically built to reproduce the world for the human eye.</p>
        <p>Bird color vision, for example, ''is so very different and so much better than ours,'' said Dr. John A. Endler, an evolutionary biologist at James Cook University in Australia, that using color images may always be an impossibility with them. (Researchers on the new study used black and white patterned moths.)</p>
        <p>Exploring the technology and discovering what animals find convincing is all part of this new field, just as it was years ago when biologists first began playing taped recordings of frog, bird and insect songs -- now a tried and trusted experimental technique -- to see if animals would respond.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bond and Dr. Kamil are also using birds known as Clark's nutcrackers to study the three-dimensional problem of spatial memory -- that is, how a bird remembers where it stored all its bits of food -- a seemingly perfect experimental problem to solve using virtual reality. But even if the birds are ready, the researchers may not be.</p>
        <p>After spending two months training blue jays to peck a computer screen, Dr. Bond realizes it would take a tremendous amount of work to train Clark's nutcrackers to react naturally to a computer-generated three-dimensional space.</p>
        <p>''I just wouldn't want to think of what you'd have to do to get reliable virtual reality with a nutcracker,'' Dr. Bond said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
