<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Bold Assault on El Nino's Mysteries</title>
    <meta content="13GOOD$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19981017T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1053710"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TELEVISION REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">El Nino (Pacific Ocean Phenomenon)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Goodman, Walter</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Nova (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Television/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Weather</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981013T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E2D9163AF930A25753C1A96E958260" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Bold Assault on El Nino's Mysteries</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WALTER GOODMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Goodman, Walter</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Walter Goodman reviews Nova production Chasing El Nino, on PBS; photo (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>''Nova'' ventures tonight on the track of El Nino, the mysterious phenomenon that every few years rages out of the Pacific Ocean to wreak havoc around the world. Its impact in 1997 and 1998 is fresh in memory.</p>
        <p>What happens when El Nino strikes is lamentably clear; the puzzle of why has sent a team of scientists, the focus of tonight's program,  patrolling the Pacific with a long line of data-collecting stations.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>''Nova'' ventures tonight on the track of El Nino, the mysterious phenomenon that every few years rages out of the Pacific Ocean to wreak havoc around the world. Its impact in 1997 and 1998 is fresh in memory.</p>
        <p>What happens when El Nino strikes is lamentably clear; the puzzle of why has sent a team of scientists, the focus of tonight's program,  patrolling the Pacific with a long line of data-collecting stations.</p>
        <p>What the scientists know already is that El Nino disrupts normal weather patterns: trade winds may reverse direction, sending the warm water that normally moves toward Australia and Indonesia back toward the South American coast, with infamous consequences. In the 1982-83 El Nino, areas of Peru, which was hit first, received 30 times the normal rainfall; the flooding cost that unfortunate country some $1 billion in damages and 600 deaths. Worldwide damage came to $13 billion and 2,000 deaths.</p>
        <p>Put in place in 1994, the El Nino detection system, perhaps the largest scientific instrument ever built, is kept afloat by buoys. Constantly monitoring the Pacific's winds and waves, its 70 stations can come up with hints of suspicious changes and may deliver an El Nino forecast, as they did in 1997. But what was predicted to be a minor event, as one forecaster concedes and television viewers may recall, turned out to be a ''whopper.''</p>
        <p>The result, dramatically recorded, was destruction from Africa to California, where meteorologists can be seen flying smack into the storms to measure their impact. It makes for quite a show, and the only sure prediction about El Nino is that it will come again.</p>
        <p>NOVA  Chasing El Nino  PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 8)</p>
        <p>Written, produced and directed by Carol L. Fleisher; Alex A. Adams and Mark S. Hoover, co-producers.</p>
        <p>'Frontline'  'Plague War'  PBS, tonight  (Channel 13, New York, at 9)</p>
        <p>Relying on defectors from what is alleged to have been an all-out effort by the Soviet Union to develop biological weapons during the cold war and possibly after, ''Frontline'' delivers a dire report on suspicions of the existence of stockpiles of smallpox, plague and anthrax viruses. All are said to be readily convertible to offensive biological warfare, with lethal potential. Two pounds of powdered anthrax efficiently deployed, one researcher notes, would be enough to kill hundreds of thousands of New Yorkers.</p>
        <p>''Plague War'' raises doubts about the enforcement of international agreements banning biological weapons. Intelligence experts warn that some former Soviet colonels and generals may still be working at developing them, either for Russia or for terrorist-prone clients. Coming immediately after ''Nova,'' this hour is enough to make El Nino seem benign.</p>
        <p>TELEVISION REVIEW  Correction:  October 17, 1998, Saturday  A television review on Tuesday about ''Plague War,'' a ''Frontline'' documentary shown Tuesday night on PBS stations, referred incorrectly to two of three diseases mentioned as possible biological weapons. Plague and anthrax are caused by bacteria; only smallpox is a virus.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 17, 1998, Saturday</p>
        <p>A television review on Tuesday about ''Plague War,'' a ''Frontline'' documentary shown Tuesday night on PBS stations, referred incorrectly to two of three diseases mentioned as possible biological weapons. Plague and anthrax are caused by bacteria; only smallpox is a virus.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
