<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Thomas Keeps Searching For Ways to Stir Knicks</title>
    <meta content="13knicks" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/13/sports/basketball/13knicks.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1804542"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Knicks</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Thomas, Isiah</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061113T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE0D9163EF930A25752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="654" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Thomas Keeps Searching For Ways to Stir Knicks</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Thomas Keeps Searching for Ways to Stir Knicks</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HOWARD BECK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Beck, Howard</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bruce Bowen and his extended right foot faded into the Knicks' rearview mirror late Saturday night, and Isiah Thomas set about finding new ways to prod his team to compete.</p>
        <p>The Knicks landed in New York early yesterday morning, having lost their mental battle with Bowen and the San Antonio Spurs, and having lost two of three games on their trip. They are 2-5 in Thomas's first two weeks as the coach, and he is reaching for ways to keep spirits afloat in a tough opening month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the Knicks returned home, Isiah Thomas turned his frustration back toward the New York fan base, which has made Madison Square Garden inhospitable only to the home team.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bruce Bowen and his extended right foot faded into the Knicks' rearview mirror late Saturday night, and Isiah Thomas set about finding new ways to prod his team to compete.</p>
        <p>The Knicks landed in New York early yesterday morning, having lost their mental battle with Bowen and the San Antonio Spurs, and having lost two of three games on their trip. They are 2-5 in Thomas's first two weeks as the coach, and he is reaching for ways to keep spirits afloat in a tough opening month.</p>
        <p>On Saturday, that meant orally attacking and threatening Bowen over his defensive tactics. It temporarily sparked the Knicks, who nevertheless lost to the Spurs for the second time in six days. An N.B.A. spokesman said the league did not plan to review Thomas's actions.</p>
        <p>As the Knicks returned home, Thomas turned his frustration back toward the New York fan base, which has made Madison Square Garden inhospitable only to the home team. The Cleveland Cavaliers arrive tonight, and it is possible that LeBron James will be greeted with far more enthusiasm than the Knicks.</p>
        <p>''We got to start winning at home,'' Thomas said. ''And we got to get to the point where we make our arena uncomfortable. It disappoints me that players feel that they can come into New York and that's the place to put on a show and play your best. We got to change that mind-set across the league.''</p>
        <p>He added: ''Save your best performances for other arenas. We don't necessarily want them in ours.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks have lost both of their home games, to Indiana and San Antonio, and they have been booed throughout. Much of the discontent has been directed at Stephon Marbury, a Brooklyn native who struggled in the first few games of the season.</p>
        <p>Thomas is so concerned with the psyche of his team that he has directed his public critiques at everyone and everything else -- fickle fans, opposing players, referees, the schedule makers.</p>
        <p>The Knicks have the same record through seven games as they did under Larry Brown last season. Yet if not for Jamal Crawford's game-saving 3-pointer in Denver and a triple-overtime victory in Memphis, the Knicks would be 0-7. After the Knicks lost Saturday in San Antonio, Thomas continued to accentuate the positive, saying, ''Hey, won one out of three.''</p>
        <p>In the Knicks' locker room, the mood was not quite as chipper.</p>
        <p>''One and two on a three-game road trip, it's not good,'' Malik Rose said. ''That's how I look at it.''</p>
        <p>Told that Thomas expressed modest satisfaction, Rose said: ''He gets paid to make that decision, so I guess that's the one we'll go with as a team. I would have much rather -- and I'm sure he would, too -- rather have saw us go 3-0. I'm just tired of losing the same way.''</p>
        <p>The Knicks have faced double-digit deficits in every first half this season. Despite a number of impressive late rallies, they rarely have enough to push their way to victory.</p>
        <p>There is no letup in the schedule. Over the next three weeks, the Knicks have home games against Cleveland, Washington, Boston, Houston and Chicago, and road games against Miami, Minnesota, Boston, Chicago, Cleveland and Detroit.</p>
        <p>If they are to survive November, the Knicks may need to adopt some of the edginess that Thomas showed Saturday in San Antonio.</p>
        <p>''Eventually, we'll get there,'' Thomas said. ''My job is to set the tone, and I will set the tone.''</p>
        <p>Quentin Richardson, who has been the Knicks' best player at both ends of the court, said he appreciated Thomas's extreme tactics Saturday, but he noted that they should not be necessary.</p>
        <p>''Our coach is fighting, we obviously have to fight,'' Richardson said. ''But we have to find a way to just get that started sooner. We shouldn't have to have him come out and trigger something. We should be doing that anyway, playing hard.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
