<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Political Theater: Some Bash, Some Bellow, and Some May Even Last</title>
    <meta content="20pol" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/10/20/theater/20pol.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1798481"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Culture Project</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Synapse Productions</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061020T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504EED81F30F933A15753C1A9609C8B63" item-length="1542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Political Theater: Some Bash, Some Bellow, and Some May Even Last</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Political Theater: Some Bash, Some Bellow, and Some May Even Last</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL GENZLINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Genzlinger, Neil</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Uptown at the Triad, President Bush spends time as a chimp, because ''jungle'' rhymes with ''bungle.'' At the Red Room in the East Village, he vehemently denies being a chimp, but he's eating a banana when he does it. At the Actors' Playhouse in Greenwich Village, although there is a monkey in the cast, the president himself doesn't do anything chimplike. He does, however, do a softshoe with Jesus.</p>
        <p>Yes, with an election imminent, political theater is everywhere in New York. Some of it is broad and partisan, as the above scenes from, respectively, ''Bush Is Bad,'' ''Dumbya's Rapture'' and ''Bush Wars'' testify. Some of it is more subtle, aiming at issues rather than personalities. Some of it even aspires to be work you could stand to watch years from now, when the current administration and its troubles are in the history books.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>With an election imminent, political theater is everywhere in New York.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Uptown at the Triad, President Bush spends time as a chimp, because ''jungle'' rhymes with ''bungle.'' At the Red Room in the East Village, he vehemently denies being a chimp, but he's eating a banana when he does it. At the Actors' Playhouse in Greenwich Village, although there is a monkey in the cast, the president himself doesn't do anything chimplike. He does, however, do a softshoe with Jesus.</p>
        <p>Yes, with an election imminent, political theater is everywhere in New York. Some of it is broad and partisan, as the above scenes from, respectively, ''Bush Is Bad,'' ''Dumbya's Rapture'' and ''Bush Wars'' testify. Some of it is more subtle, aiming at issues rather than personalities. Some of it even aspires to be work you could stand to watch years from now, when the current administration and its troubles are in the history books.</p>
        <p>The words ''political'' and ''theater'' have, of course, been joined from the beginning of the art form: so many kings, so many tragedies. And every new display of presidential foibles inspires its own theatrical ripple. In 1972 ''An Evening With Richard Nixon and ...'' turned up at the Shubert (by Gore Vidal no less) and the next year saw ''Watergate Classics'' at Yale Rep. In 1982 Reaganomics took a hit in ''The Bottom Line'' at the Labor Theater and five years ago at the 78th Street Theater Lab two actresses were reading excerpts from actual conversations between Monica Lewinsky and Linda Tripp.</p>
        <p>This month, besides that assortment of Bush-bashing shows, two festivals (each running through Sunday) are taking on issues national and international. The Culture Project is in Week 6 of the Impact Festival, an ambitious collection of works ranging from the slapdash to the starry, like Eve Ensler's didactic drama ''The Treatment'' with Dylan McDermott. Synapse Productions, meanwhile, has the Ignite Festival, an even more eclectic grab bag of short pieces with some impressive contributors (like Kathleen Chalfant and Caryl Churchill) offered under the slogan ''small works, big ideas.''</p>
        <p>Watch enough of this stuff and you realize how easily politics -- or at least theater about it -- can be pigeonholed into one of these categories:</p>
        <p>CHEERLEADER PRACTICE -- These shows aspire only to rope in those who are already converted and lead them in comfortably laughing or booing at familiar targets. A tipoff that you're at such a show is that the audience is often whooping before the first performer appears.</p>
        <p>Typical of this group are the musical revues ''Bush Is Bad,'' which ends with the cast holding up signs promoting impeachment Web sites, and ''Bush Wars,'' which sells countdown key chains in the lobby that tabulate the days until the end of the president's term. The chief weapon of each is the rhyming couplet: homo/Cuomo, disparage/marriage, angry mob/heckuva job and a million more.</p>
        <p>Such shows are probably the easiest type of political theater to create, replacing the hard work of art with mere button-pushing. But they're difficult to keep fresh, since Jay Leno et al. mine the same material nightly. ''Bush Is Bad,'' whose current incarnation (the show was first seen in 2005) is subtitled ''Impeachment Special,'' is at least making an effort: there was a Mark Foley joke, albeit a lame one, in the production seen on Oct. 7, a week after that Congressional scandal broke. ''Bush Wars,'' on the other hand, which had an initial run last March at the Rattlestick Theater, still has a tasteless Terri Schiavo song in it, more than a year and a half after she died.</p>
        <p>As for the effect of such shows, Clive Barnes summed it up nicely in these pages when reviewing that Gore Vidal show back in 1972: ''There is no real drama, no real excitement. There is only a crowd of radical liberals, including, of course, myself, watching another crowd of radical liberals giving what Mr. Nixon once called the shaft to a president who is not a radical liberal. It is fun while it lasts but no more exciting than seeing candy taken from little kids.'' It is also a bit desperate. All that laughter is really just impotent rage redirected.</p>
        <p>DENTAL SURGERY -- These plays have a point they want to make, and they're going to drill it into you whether you like it or not. For instance, Eric Diamond and his Rough Theater, with ''Dumbya's Rapture,'' want you to know that they think the president and his aides are venal incompetents. The problem is that they're so intent on putting that across with their crass caricatures of Mr. Bush and others that they forget to have fun or insight; the result is a humorless satire, if that's possible.</p>
        <p>The danger of uninvolving screeds and sermons is why the format chosen by the Ignite Festival works nicely. Each of the seven programs it has been offering consists of four to six works; if any one of those begins to feel like a lecture, at least it doesn't last long. And there's a good chance it will be alongside a gem, like ''The Doorman's Double Duty,'' a sweet one-act by Robert Lyons that is obliquely about surveillance and suspicion, or ''A Modest Adjustment'' by Daniel Rebellato, a tongue-in-cheek play about how to solve Africa's financial problems.</p>
        <p>THE BAIT-AND-SWITCH -- Some shows are well disguised: you walk into what you think is neutral territory and a political play breaks out. ''The Cartells,'' a staged soap opera by Douglas Carter Beane on four consecutive Monday nights at Comix, seems as if it has nothing on its mind but silliness, though you soon realize there's a subversive political thread running through the nonsensical plot, having to do with big oil. (Ah, the title!) If you happen to have just read the business section before seeing Irish Repertory's ''Hairy Ape,'' you'll have a hard time shaking the feeling that O'Neill's 1922 classic is actually an attack on the growing gap between rich and poor.</p>
        <p>Similarly, what may seem political can turn out not to be. One Broadway marquee, the Brooks Atkinson's, has on it the title of perhaps the greatest anthem for political change ever written, but those expecting the Twyla Tharp/Bob Dylan musical ''The Times They Are a-Changin' '' to sound like a call to battle might be surprised. The song is there, of course -- it opens the show -- but, at least at a recent preview performance, its most political verse, the one that begins, ''Come senators, congressmen, please heed the call,'' had been shorn. (The staging of another highly charged song, however, ''Masters of War,'' is blunt and angry; it couldn't sound more topical.)</p>
        <p>THE KEEPER -- Once in a while you'll stumble on a piece of political theater that, like the bear's porridge, is not too hot, not too cold; not too dated, not too timebound. The proof is at the Lucille Lortel Theater, where a revival of ''Nixon's Nixon'' by Russell Lees shows that that play, a dialogue between Henry Kissinger and Richard Nixon, is holding up just fine.</p>
        <p>It's tempting to attribute that to the men being portrayed: larger-than-life political figures, love 'em or hate 'em; somehow no one today seems in the same class. But is the corollary that political theater can last only if it's built on the shoulders of big characters like Nixon, that theater pegged to some timely issue is doomed to date quickly? Allan Buchman, artistic director of the Culture Project, doesn't think so.</p>
        <p>''I wish we were worried about whether these things have a shelf life,'' he said; instead, he said, he fears that issues like torture and government surveillance will come around again and again.</p>
        <p>As for creating works that last and that don't feel didactic, the playwright Ariel Dorfman, whose stage version of Kerry Kennedy's book ''Speak Truth to Power'' is up next for Culture Project, said the key, counterintuitively, is not to try to tell audiences what to think.</p>
        <p>''There are two species of this sort of theater,'' Mr. Dorfman said. ''One is where you know the answer and want to give people the answer and want them to act in a certain way. And then there is another where you don't know the answer yourself and are kind of searching for it.''</p>
        <p>''I'm not against trying to mobilize people,'' he added, ''but I'm more interested in mobilizing their doubts and intelligence and uncertainty.''</p>
        <p>Protests, Staged  Here is information about the political shows mentioned.</p>
        <p>'BUSH IS BAD,' Triad Theater, 158 West 72nd Street, Manhattan, (212) 279-4200. Open-ended run.  'BUSH WARS,' Actors' Playhouse, 100 Seventh Avenue South, at Fourth Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 239-6200. Open-ended run.  'THE CARTELLS,' Comix, 353 West 14th Street, West Village, (212) 524-2500. Through Nov. 6.  'DUMBYA'S RAPTURE,' The Red Room, 85 East Fourth Street, East Village, (212) 636-9264. Through Nov. 4.  'THE HAIRY APE,' Irish Repertory Theater, 132 West 22nd Street, Chelsea, (212) 727-2737. Through Nov. 19.  'NIXON'S NIXON,' Lucille Lortel Theater, 121 Christopher Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 279-4200. Through Oct. 28.  'IGNITE FESTIVAL '06' (''The Doorman's Double Duty,'' and ''A Modest Adjustment''), at the Ohio Theater, 66 Wooster Street, SoHo, (212) 352-3101. Through Sunday.  'IMPACT FESTIVAL' (''The Treatment''), Culture Project, 45 Bleecker Street, Greenwich Village, (212) 307-4100. Through Sunday.</p>
        <p>THEATER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
