<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>COMPANY NEWS;</title>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="35" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="746567"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <series series.name="COMPANY NEWS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS AND DIVESTITURES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">US SHOE CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">LUXOTTICA GROUP SPA</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ADELSON, ANDREA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950304T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE5D81538F937A35750C0A963958260" item-length="494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>COMPANY NEWS;</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREA ADELSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ADELSON, ANDREA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Italian eyewear maker, Luxottica Group S.p.A., yesterday made an unsolicited offer of $24 a share, or $1.12 billion, for the U.S. Shoe Group, the parent of Lenscrafters, the nation's largest retail optical chain.</p>
        <p>Shares of U.S. Shoe surged $5.375 yesterday, to $24.125, a new 52-week high, in heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Italian eyewear maker, Luxottica Group S.p.A., yesterday made an unsolicited offer of $24 a share, or $1.12 billion, for the U.S. Shoe Group, the parent of Lenscrafters, the nation's largest retail optical chain.</p>
        <p>Shares of U.S. Shoe surged $5.375 yesterday, to $24.125, a new 52-week high, in heavy trading on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>Because the shares closed slightly above the price of the offer, industry analysts and shareholders said Luxottica would probably have to sweeten its bid for U.S. Shoe, possibly to as high as $28 a share. But they doubted another bidder was likely to emerge for the company, which has been under pressure from dissident shareholders for several years to improve its performance.</p>
        <p>"They would have surfaced long before," said Barry Bryant, an analyst for Ladenberg, Thalmann &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>In its offer, Luxottica of Agordo, Italy, the world's largest manufacturer of eyeglasses, said it would keep only the Lenscrafter division of U.S. Shoe and would sell its footwear and apparel division.</p>
        <p>Lenscrafters, U.S. Shoe's best-performing division with more than 600 stores, had revenue of $630 million in 1993, according to 20/20 Magazine, a trade publication.</p>
        <p>A takeover would give Luxottica a larger pipeline for its products, which would support a larger advertising effort.</p>
        <p>Luxottica makes glasses ranging in cost from $40 to $250, some of them under license with well-known designers. The company distributes its own products in 12 countries and has joint ventures in 4 other nations. About 39 percent of its $504 million in sales last year came from the United States.</p>
        <p>Optical chains now capture 38 percent of the $13.8 billion domestic eyewear market, a significant shift in five years, said Susi Belli, a Luxottica spokeswoman.</p>
        <p>In a statement, U.S. Shoe, based in Cincinnati, urged shareholders to defer tendering their shares to Luxottica until hearing the company's own recommendations, which the company promised by March 16.</p>
        <p>"They know it's a tempting offer," said Margot Murtaugh, an analyst with Snyder Capital Management in San Francisco, a money management company that owns U.S. Shoe shares. "They have to be able to demonstrate to us that they have something better."</p>
        <p>Luxottica would have trouble winning control of U.S. Shoe's board because its 11 members were elected to serve staggered terms, and only 4 are up for re-election. To successfully seek a special meeting of U.S. Shoe shareholders to unseat the board, Luxottica would need to obtain a simple majority of the 46 million shares outstanding.</p>
        <p>Restive shareholders were disappointed last month, when U.S. Shoe rejected a $525 million offer for its footwear division from the Nine West Group. Last April, a plan to break the specialty retailer into three companies was defeated after U.S. Shoe management successfully convinced institutional holders that it could revive its troubled Casual Corner clothing stores.</p>
        <p>COMPANY NEWS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
