<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Prices for Platinum Plunge To Near a Five-Year Low</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="418865"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="FUTURES/OPTIONS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FUTURES TRADING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PLATINUM</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Chemistry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Metals and Minerals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE2DC1330F93AA15752C0A967958260" item-length="474" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Prices for Platinum Plunge To Near a Five-Year Low</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Platinum futures prices approached five-year lows yesterday as industrial and investment demand for the metal lagged.</p>
        <p>Platinum futures settled $8.40 to $9 lower on the New York Mercantile Exchange, with the contract for delivery in January at $379.30 an ounce, the lowest spot platinum price on the exchange since Feb. 14, 1986. The more actively traded April contract finished at $383.50.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Platinum futures prices approached five-year lows yesterday as industrial and investment demand for the metal lagged.</p>
        <p>Platinum futures settled $8.40 to $9 lower on the New York Mercantile Exchange, with the contract for delivery in January at $379.30 an ounce, the lowest spot platinum price on the exchange since Feb. 14, 1986. The more actively traded April contract finished at $383.50.</p>
        <p>Gold futures settled $1 to $1.60 higher on New York's Commodity Exchange, with gold for January delivery up $1, to $376.70 an ounce and the active February contract at $377.10 an ounce. Silver was 2.3 cents to 2.5 cents higher, with March at $3.842 an ounce.</p>
        <p>Platinum soon could be trading at a discount to gold for the first time since 1985 unless the market's fundamentals change, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Bernard Savaiko, senior metals analyst with Paine Webber Inc., said recession worries had strangled platinum demand by investors and industrial users, which include car and jewelry manufacturers.</p>
        <p>The price of silver, which also has a large industrial component, has also fallen sharply lately, though gold has remained relatively firm.</p>
        <p>One factor that could give platinum a lift is the tension in the Soviet Union, the world's second-largest platinum producer.</p>
        <p>"If law and order break down, we could see a supply disruption over there," Mr. Savaiko said. "It is a possibility that should not be overlooked."</p>
        <p>World sugar futures fell sharply to new life-of-contract lows in a late selloff on New York's Coffee, Sugar and Cocoa Exchange.</p>
        <p>It was sugar's sharpest one-day drop since the Persian Gulf war began, halting most sugar exports to the Middle East.</p>
        <p>Harry Schwartz, a analyst with Cargill Investor Services Inc., said that because most of the selling occurred in the last five minutes, traders would be watching today's early action to determine whether "this is significant or just a bear raid."</p>
        <p>Sugar settled 0.16 cent to 0.2 cent lower, with March at 8.76 cents a pound.</p>
        <p>Livestock and meat futures rose on the Chicago Mercantile Exchange in line with stronger cash cattle markets.</p>
        <p>But gains in cattle were limited by selling prompted by Friday's quarterly Agriculture Department cattle-on-feed report. The report showed the largest on-feed inventories since 1979 in the 13 largest cattle states.</p>
        <p>Live cattle futures settled 0.05 cent to 0.4 cent higher, with February at 78.10 cents a pound; feeder cattle were 0.17 cent to 0.4 cent higher, with January at 90.50 cents a pound; live hogs were 0.1 cent to 0.77 cent higher, with February at 54.27 cents a pound; frozen pork bellies were 0.35 cent to 1.22 cents higher, with February at 69.47 cents a pound.</p>
        <p>Stronger domestic feed-grain demand lifted corn futures prices on the Chicago Board of Trade and helped push most other grain and soybean futures higher as well.</p>
        <p>FUTURES/OPTIONS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
