<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>An Edge for Incumbents: Loopholes That Pay Off</title>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="The Trouble With Politics/Running vs. Governing &#10;&lt;br&gt;&#10;Third of four articles." name="series_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="336196"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SURVEYS AND SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">SENATE (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BERKE, RICHARD L</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAUGHLIN, GREG (REPR)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">SERIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Surveys and Series</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900320T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DC1239F933A15750C0A966958260" item-length="1826" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>An Edge for Incumbents: Loopholes That Pay Off</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. BERKE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BERKE, RICHARD L</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, March 19</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: In his first term in office, Representative Greg Laughlin, Democrat of Texas, has learned how business is done on Capitol Hill. Lobbyists calling on the Congressman often stroll past the desk of a senior aide and drop off campaign contributions of as much as $10,000.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: In his first term in office, Representative Greg Laughlin, Democrat of Texas, has learned how business is done on Capitol Hill. Lobbyists calling on the Congressman often stroll past the desk of a senior aide and drop off campaign contributions of as much as $10,000.</p>
        <p>In his first term in office, Representative Greg Laughlin, Democrat of Texas, has learned how business is done on Capitol Hill. Lobbyists calling on the Congressman often stroll past the desk of a senior aide and drop off campaign contributions of as much as $10,000.</p>
        <p>Sometimes the top drawer of the desk holds as many as 20 checks, according to Tim Richardson, who resigned as Mr. Laughlin's administrative assistant this month.</p>
        <p>''There was no quid pro quo,'' Mr. Richardson said, because Federal laws prohibit lawmakers themselves from discussing or soliciting money in their offices, and Mr. Laughlin followed the law to the letter.</p>
        <p>Even as Mr. Richardson insists on the innocence of the transactions, he goes on to acknowledge the facts of Congressional life: ''It's safe to say the member knows exactly how much is given,'' said Mr. Richardson, who is leaving politics to try his luck in the oil business. ''A politician who does not know who is contributing to him is a politician who will probably not be around very long.''</p>
        <p>While the law prohibits members of Congress from talking about money in their offices in the capital, it was carefully worded to allow staff members to receive payments on the premises. The loophole is an apt symbol of the reality of modern politics: The pursuit of money is a central part of officeholders' lives, and the rules are written to make it almost impossible for politicians to avoid either the appearance or the reality of conflict of interest.</p>
        <p>In Washington today, raising money takes nearly as much time as legislative work. After days in hearing rooms or on the floor of Congress, lawmakers make the rounds of fund-raising receptions or spend evenings ''dialing for dollars,'' as many members call their telephone appeals. The average senator who was elected in 1988 spent $3.7 million in his or her campaign, a 22 percent rise from only two years before. The winning candidates for House seats spent, on the average, $393,000, an increase of more than 10 percent over 1986.</p>
        <p>''Who can afford to run?'' asked James M. Ruvolo, chairman of the Ohio Democratic Party. ''The person who's concerned about the environment can run. But he can't win. Donald Trump can run any time he wants to. But the average person who may be a teacher or a lawyer - they can't do it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Ruvolo speaks for many who think money has become the most potent winnowing force in determining who runs for office. Even incumbents with relatively safe seats feel compelled to scramble, often tailoring their views on issues to attract or keep donors.</p>
        <p>''The fact is,'' says Lloyd Meeds, a seven-term Democratic Representative from Washington who is now a lobbyist as well as a lawyer, ''when you take $10,000 from somebody, it's pretty damn difficult to look across the table from them and vote against something that is important to them.''</p>
        <p>The Hunt</p>
        <p>Perpetual Drive For New Funds</p>
        <p>Mr. Meeds emphasizes the role that fear and the drive for political survival play in trapping members on the hamster wheel of getting and spending.</p>
        <p>''Every one of them lives with the nightmare that some jillionaire is going to come out of the woods,'' he said of his former colleagues, ''and spend $5 million on his own campaign and roll him.''</p>
        <p>So members of Congress have written campaign laws and built war chests that practically assure the body's low turnover rate. In the House, 98 percent of those who seek re-election win. The success rate is lower in the Senate, but 85 percent of incumbents who ran were re-elected in 1988. The laws that ostensibly regulate spending have, in fact, become potent de facto regulations fencing newcomers out of politics.</p>
        <p>On Capitol Hill, the swirl of fund-raising breakfasts, lunches and dinners dictates the pace of life. ''I often stopped in four or five in a typical evening,'' said Jim Wright, the former Speaker of the House, who resigned last year because of disclosures about his finances.</p>
        <p>And often, Mr. Wright recalled, members would ask him to put off votes, confessing ''that they had to be present at a fund-raiser because it had been planned for some time.'' ''They plead with you to try to rearrange the schedule to accommodate them,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Indeed, in Congressional offices, the top-ranking administrative assistants are now often hired as much for their fund-raising prowess as for their legislative insight. ''You end up having a second life that's just as important to a member's survival as his voting record,'' said Mr. Richardson, who also worked for Senator Lloyd Bentsen, the Texas Democrat who is one of Congress's most accomplished money raisers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Meeds, who retired from Congress rather than face what he expected to be a tough and expensive re-election campaign and is now ethics committee chairman of the American League of Lobbyists, disputes the pro forma denials voiced by most members of Congress when asked whether they are influenced by the people who give them money.</p>
        <p>''I felt that I might be obligated or ingracious, one or the other,'' he said, no matter how he voted on issue of major concern to a contributor. ''There isn't any middle ground. That really scared me.''</p>
        <p>The Strategy</p>
        <p>Skirting a Law With Few Teeth</p>
        <p>The Federal Election Commission's lack of aggressiveness has spurred campaigns to test assorted fund-raising techniques that push the limits of the law, said Senator Mitch McConnell, Republican of Kentucky, a recent convert to the advocacy of some regulation of spending.</p>
        <p>''You have kind of a Rube Goldberg approach to politics under which there is massive cheating,'' Mr. McConnell said.</p>
        <p>Indeed, politicians seem endlessly inventive. In 1988 the fad was accepting contributions with credit cards or electronic bank drafts. This year 900 numbers that facilitate giving by long-distance telephone are gaining popularity, though the F.E.C. has issued mixed opinions on their legality. The practice was pioneered by Senator Phil Gramm of Texas, a Republican who some say is thinking about a Presidential bid and who is currently the Senate's leading fund-raiser. His campaign offered two 900 numbers for telephone billing: callers to one were billed $25, the second number was for $50 donations.</p>
        <p>The circumvention of campaign laws has become a fixed feature of Presidential contests.</p>
        <p>In their general election campaigns, George Bush and Michael S. Dukakis were supposed to spend only the lump sums given them by the Federal Government, $46 million each. The major parties raised as much as $60 million more for both nominees, in money funneled through state parties and often used to finance voter drives and other efforts not subject to Federal regulation.</p>
        <p>The election commission, instead of being feared as a potential critic of such practices, is not even regarded in high campaign circles as a threat. ''Any good election lawyer can show you how to get around virtually all of the campaign finance laws,'' said Carol C. Darr, who was chief legal counsel for the Democratic Presidential campaign of Governor Dukakis of Massachusetts.</p>
        <p>Increasingly, the national parties are relying on this unregulated money, known as soft money and not subject to Federal reporting requirements, to supplement Congressional campaigns. In fact, Ronald H. Brown, the chairman of the Democratic National Committee, has altered the party's fund-raising releases to publicize his success in raising this money.</p>
        <p>The impotence of the election commission can be linked to the same incumbent-protection impulse evident in the rules for collecting money in Capitol Hill offices.</p>
        <p>The F.E.C., a product of the post-Watergate reformist mood, was established by Congress in 1974 to monitor compliance with new national campaign laws. But incumbents, not wanting to get themselves thrown out of office, gave the panel limited resources and little enforcement authority, and it built in partisan deadlock by having three members from each party. Their bipartisan agreements to apply weak sanctions and condone practices designed to skirt legal restrictions are even more striking than their partisan deadlocks.</p>
        <p>The commission is led this year by a former officer of the American Medical Association's political action committee, Lee Ann Elliott, a Republican. Money cannot influence the outcome of campaigns, she argues. ''The candidate,'' she said, ''is not going to win unless he can use that money to convince his constituency that he is the best person for the job.''</p>
        <p>Others see this view as hopelessly naive. Senator Robert C. Byrd, Democrat of West Virginia, declared in introducing a campaign finance bill last year that got mired in a partisan stalemate: ''The Congressional campaign system has become toxic with money. We chafe over the burden of having to take our time to go, tin cup in hand, begging to PAC's for the money to run for public office. Yet we have it in our power to stop the madness.''</p>
        <p>The Trap</p>
        <p>Every Cure Begets a Disease</p>
        <p>The Byrd view is more widely held than Mrs. Elliott's among politicians, lobbyists and big donors, who agree that money is overwhelming the public's trust in the political process. They also agree on the inadequacies of the Federal Election Commission.</p>
        <p>But they cannot agree on how to change the system.</p>
        <p>One problem is partisanship. Republicans championed political action committees as a conduit for business contributions, to counter labor union contributions to Democrats. Democrats railed against them. Now the sides are reversed, because PAC's give more to the Democrats, who control Congress, than to the Republicans.</p>
        <p>In the meantime, the costs of campaigns has spiraled upward.</p>
        <p>The Watergate reforms brought changes like public financing for Presidential campaigns and limits on the amount an individual can give to a Congressional campaigns.</p>
        <p>But every cure has become a new disease.</p>
        <p>Political action committees, created to substitute for the large sums contributed by fat cat donors, are now viewed as tools of special interests. A $1,000 limit on the amount a Congressional candidate can raise from an individual in any one election is forcing candidates to spend more time soliciting money and encouraging donors to funnel large unregulated sums to state party committees.</p>
        <p>A bipartisan consensus seems to be building for voluntary spending limits, as proposed in a bill passed this month by the Senate Rules Committee. But final passage is another matter. Despite their calls for reform, a lack of will among politicians seems to be a central problem.</p>
        <p>Edmund G. Brown Jr., once a reformer, is now a cynic about the possibility of driving money out of campaigns in the mother lode of political fat cats, California.</p>
        <p>''The only answer is a dictatorship,'' said Mr. Brown, the former two-term Governor of California, who is now chairman of the state's Democratic Party. ''That's the only way to control the money.''</p>
        <p>Next: Seeking solutions.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
