<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>For Frenchman and Armstrong, Magic in the Alps</title>
    <meta content="Y13TOUR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/07/13/sports/sportsspecial/13TOUR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1504239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abt, Samuel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Virenque, Richard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Tour de France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030713T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06E7D71F3DF930A25754C0A9659C8B63" item-length="852" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>For Frenchman and Armstrong, Magic in the Alps</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Armstrong Confident After 2 Leaders Fall Back</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAMUEL ABT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Abt, Samuel</byline>
      <dateline>MORZINE, France, July 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Richard Virenque wins seventh stage of Tour de France, and takes overall lead; map; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Something magical happened to Richard Virenque in the Tour de France today, and something only a little less magical happened to Lance Armstrong. Both had many reasons to celebrate the abracadabra.</p>
        <p>Virenque, the reformed bad boy of French cycling, joined a small attack early in the seventh stage, hoping to pick up some points toward his sixth King of the Mountains title. Instead, he wound up with that climbers' jersey, a stage victory and the yellow jersey of the race's overall leader.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lance Armstrong remained in second place over all in the Tour de France and saw two of his leading opponents vaporize during the first of three days in the Alps.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Something magical happened to Richard Virenque in the Tour de France today, and something only a little less magical happened to Lance Armstrong. Both had many reasons to celebrate the abracadabra.</p>
        <p>Virenque, the reformed bad boy of French cycling, joined a small attack early in the seventh stage, hoping to pick up some points toward his sixth King of the Mountains title. Instead, he wound up with that climbers' jersey, a stage victory and the yellow jersey of the race's overall leader.</p>
        <p>Although he collected no clothing, Armstrong did almost as well. He remained in second place over all and saw two of his leading opponents vaporize during the first of three days in the Alps. They were Gilberto Simoni, an Italian with Saeco, and Santiago Botero, a Colombian with Telekom. Each lost more than 10 minutes today.</p>
        <p>''I'm very happy with the situation,'' said Armstrong, the leader of the United States Postal Service team, who is seeking his fifth consecutive victory in the Tour. The race still has two weeks to go.</p>
        <p>''It's good not to have the yellow jersey,'' he added, meaning that his team will not have to work hard to defend it against attackers.</p>
        <p>Armstrong, a Texan, owes a good part of his happiness to the impulsive Virenque, who explained afterward: ''You know how I am. I saw an attack and just had to join it.'' Then something magical happened.</p>
        <p>Virenque, who rides for the Quick Step team from Belgium, acknowledged that he was not certain how long he could keep the yellow jersey.</p>
        <p>''It will be an honor to wear it tomorrow on Alpe d'Huez, but I don't know how well I'll recover from my efforts today and I could lose it there,'' he said. ''Or maybe not.''</p>
        <p>Over the long haul, he continued, his chances are dim. ''I'll probably lose five minutes in the first long time trial,'' he said. It is scheduled Friday, just before the entry into the Pyrenees.</p>
        <p>For now, however, he is leading the Tour for the first time in 11 years, when he made his debut and took the jersey in a long breakaway. He lost it the next day.</p>
        <p>Since then, he has finished second in the Tour in 1997 and third in 1996, won the white jersey with red polka dots on five final podiums, been heavily involved in the Festina drug scandal of 1998 and served a nine-month suspension in 2001 after he finally admitted using illegal performance-enhancing drugs.</p>
        <p>His fans have remained faithful, especially after his comeback victory on Mont Ventoux in the last Tour. The fans, mainly teenage girls, festooned the 230.5 kilometer (143.2-mile) course with ''Allez Virenque'' signs and personal tributes like ''Suzanne With Virenque.''</p>
        <p>He finished the stage from Lyon to the mountain resort of Morzine in 6 hours 6 minutes 3 seconds -- an average speed of 37.7 kilometers an hour over five climbs.</p>
        <p>Rolf Aldag, a German with Telekom, who was part of the original five-man breakaway, held on for second, 2:29 back. Armstrong was 15th, 4:06 behind, in a group of chasers.</p>
        <p>Besides Simoni and Botero, a big loser on the day was Victor Hugo Peña, an Armstrong teammate, who started the day in the yellow jersey and lost it by finishing 148th in the 187-man field, 24:56 behind.</p>
        <p>Virenque replaced Peña as the leader, 2:37 ahead of Armstrong and 2:48 ahead of Aldag, a journeyman. More real threats to Armstrong's quest are Joseba Beloki, a Spaniard with ONCE, in sixth place, 3:09 behind Virenque, and Jan Ullrich, a German with Bianchi, in ninth place, 3:15 behind.</p>
        <p>Other than Virenque's victory, the news that shook the Tour was the withdrawal early in the stage of Alessandro Petacchi, an Italian with Fassa Bortolo who won four sprint finishes this week.</p>
        <p>Word had circulated for days that Petacchi felt his job was done and that he had no intention of struggling in the mountains for a chance at another sprint victory days away. Better to spend the rest of July on a beach in Italy, he believed.</p>
        <p>That supposed lack of dedication to suffering was exactly the reason Tour organizers cited when, for the fourth year, they refused to invite the team led by Mario Cipollini, the world champion and king of the sprinters before Petacchi began laying claim to the title with six victories in the Giro d'Italia last month and the four in the Tour.</p>
        <p>Petacchi was not racing against Cipollini when he racked up the victories in France and half of those in the Giro, where Cipollini had to quit after a crash. It would have been a treat to watch them go against each other in the Tour, no matter how short the time.</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
