<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Using Surprise Strategy, Kevorkian's Lawyers Seek Acquittal</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="682140"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUICIDES AND SUICIDE ATTEMPTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TRIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAW AND LEGISLATION</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MICHIGAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">DETROIT (MICH)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ROYAL OAK (MICH)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">KEVORKIAN, JACK (DR)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HYDE, THOMAS W JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Michigan/Detroit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suicides and Suicide Attempts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940422T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE0DA1331F931A15757C0A962958260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Using Surprise Strategy, Kevorkian's Lawyers Seek Acquittal</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, April 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Lawyers for Dr. Jack Kevorkian said today that they would ask a judge to acquit him of charges of violating Michigan's ban on assisted suicide on the ground that the patient died in a county other than the one specified in the charges.</p>
        <p>The disclosure of the surprise defense strategy came on the opening day of testimony in Michigan's first assisted-suicide trial. Before today, the case seemed likely to be a straightforward test of whether a jury would be willing to convict Dr. Kevorkian under Michigan's suicide law, which three other county judges have ruled unconstitutional since it took effect in February 1993.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Lawyers for Dr. Jack Kevorkian said today that they would ask a judge to acquit him of charges of violating Michigan's ban on assisted suicide on the ground that the patient died in a county other than the one specified in the charges.</p>
        <p>The disclosure of the surprise defense strategy came on the opening day of testimony in Michigan's first assisted-suicide trial. Before today, the case seemed likely to be a straightforward test of whether a jury would be willing to convict Dr. Kevorkian under Michigan's suicide law, which three other county judges have ruled unconstitutional since it took effect in February 1993.</p>
        <p>But in addressing the jury today, Geoffrey Fieger, the doctor's chief defense lawyer, said that the patient Dr. Kevorkian is accused of helping actually died at the doctor's suburban home and not in a Detroit park 25 miles away, where the authorities said it had occurred.</p>
        <p>The lawyer later told reporters that after the prosecution completes its case he would ask Judge Thomas E. Jackson to order a verdict of acquittal on the ground that "you have to bring the case where the body was." Skepticism Is Expressed</p>
        <p>Legal experts, including the Chief Judge of Recorders Court, expressed skepticism about the legal merits of Mr. Fieger's argument. "I don't think that will fly legally," the chief judge, Dalton Roberson, said in an interview. He added that he thought the case would go forward as planned. "I am surprised they are muddying the issue," he said.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kevorkian, a 65-year-old retired pathologist, has admitted assisting the suicide of Thomas W. Hyde Jr., 30, who was suffering from amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, or Lou Gehrig's disease, and was nearly paralyzed. The doctor said he had placed a mask over the man's face and given him a string to pull to release a flow of carbon monoxide gas into his lungs.</p>
        <p>Today in court, Dr. Kevorkian spent most of the time studying a book on the Japanese language. Occasionally he looked up and listened to the proceedings.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hyde was the 17th of 20 people whom Dr. Kevorkian has helped commit suicide since June 4, 1990. He was also charged with violating Michigan's law forbidding assisted suicide in the last three cases, but those charges were dismissed by judges who ruled the law unconstitutional. The Michigan Court of Appeals is now considering the challenges to the law.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hyde's body was discovered in Dr. Kevorkian's van on Belle Isle, a Detroit city park, early that morning. But today, Mr. Fieger said Dr. Kevorkian had actually driven Mr. Hyde from his home in the Detroit suburb of Novi to Dr. Kevorkian's apartment in Royal Oak, where the suicide took place in a parking space behind the building.</p>
        <p>After the man was dead, Mr. Fieger said, Dr. Kevorkian drove to Belle Isle to surrender to the police.  Addressing a jury that is mostly black and mostly female, Mr. Fieger said: "Thomas Hyde did not die in the city of Detroit and the county of Wayne on Belle Isle. His suicide took place in Royal Oak, Michigan, at Dr. Kevorkian's home, and they never even bothered to check."</p>
        <p>Mr. Fieger said he would argue that the legal doctrine of double jeopardy would prevent Oakland County prosecutors from trying Dr. Kevorkian on the same charge. He contended that once the jury was sworn in and the charges dismissed, it would be double jeopardy to try Dr. Kevorkian again.</p>
        <p>But Timothy Kenny, the Wayne County assistant prosecutor, said he did not believe that Mr. Hyde died in Royal Oak. Testifying in his behalf was a Detroit police officer, Anita Banks, who said she saw Dr. Kevorkian's van parked on Belle Isle about 8 A.M., about an hour and a half before the police stopped the doctor, who was driving on the island, and learned of the suicide.</p>
        <p>In his opening remarks, Mr. Kenny told the jurors that whatever sympathy they might have for Mr. Hyde or for Dr. Kevorkian, Michigan still has a law against assisting in a suicide, and "if a person does in fact commit suicide, and a person such as Jack Kevorkian provides the means, that is a violation of that law."</p>
        <p>Dr. Kevorkian's defense team has been forbidden from telling the jurors that the law, which makes assisting in a suicide a felony punishable by up to four years in prison, has been declared unconstitutional by other judges.</p>
        <p>Besides his claim that the suicide occurred elsewhere, Mr. Fieger told jurors that they should find his client not guilty because "it is not against the law in the state of Michigan to assist in a suicide if your intention is to relieve suffering." A clause in the law forbidding assisted suicide says a doctor cannot be prosecuted for measures he takes to relieve suffering, even if in doing so he hastens death.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
