<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Children's Books</title>
    <meta content="10SHULMN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1686031"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Columns/Children's Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E6DB103AF933A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Children's Books</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Polly Shulman</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>CONRAD'S FATE</p>
        <p>A Chrestomanci Book.</p>
        <p>By Diana Wynne Jones.</p>
        <p>375 pp. Greenwillow Books. $16.99.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>CONRAD'S FATE</p>
        <p>A Chrestomanci Book.</p>
        <p>By Diana Wynne Jones.</p>
        <p>375 pp. Greenwillow Books. $16.99.</p>
        <p>With the madness for juvenile wizards at an all-time peak, why have so few Americans heard of Diana Wynne Jones? Now 70, she has been writing magically inventive fiction for children since before J. K. Rowling learned to read, and even has her name on a new movie -- ''Howl's Moving Castle,'' a fantastical yet faithful anime version of her 1986 novel by the Japanese director Hayao Miyazaki.</p>
        <p>Jones studied with C. S. Lewis and J. R. R. Tolkien at Oxford in the 1950's, and has published more than 30 books. Her award-winning young adult novels, which are better known in her native Britain than here, are as hilarious and playful as they are terrifying and psychologically true -- every bit as good as Rowling's, if not even better. Certainly, wherever Rowling goes, chances are Jones went there first. Some of her novels, like ''Witch Week'' (1982), are school stories with magicians as students. Many feature a sprawling gothic mansion with dangerous, enchanted grounds and powerful animals -- cats, dragons, griffins -- as smart and sympathetic as the humans. But mention her to the average Harry Potter fan and you'll get a blank stare.</p>
        <p>Maybe what's holding her back in the United States is her very inventiveness. Unlike Rowling, she's never formulaic. The Harry Potter books are rooted in satisfying repetition: the trip to school, the Quidditch match, the shopping expeditions, the cozy Christmas bash. But Jones comes up with something new every time, weaving the most unlikely threads into ingeniously patterned tangles that nevertheless miraculously hold together. In her novel ''Dogsbody'' (1975), the noble denizen of the Dog Star, Sirius, is set up by treacherous fellow celestials and banished to lowly Earth in the body of -- what else? -- a puppy, where he's rescued by a lonely girl (and eventually has a chance to rescue her in turn). In ''Dark Lord of Derkholm'' (1998), a good-natured magician with a large family of children -- some human, some griffin -- is stuck with the thankless job of playing the supreme evil being to tourists from a nonmagical world like ours. The visitors have read enough Tolkienesque fantasies to insist on fighting in a war between good and evil during their holidays.</p>
        <p>Jones's new book, ''Conrad's Fate,'' is the fifth in the Chronicles of Chrestomanci, named for an enchanter with the thankless job of keeping all the magic workers in the Related Worlds in line. (There are lots of thankless jobs in Jones novels.) In the scheme of the Chrestomanci books, our world is only one of many similar ones -- each world containing versions of the same events, landscapes and people, but with a few important differences, such as whether magic works or not. In ours, as you may have noticed, it doesn't, but that's unusual; in most of the Related Worlds, magic rules.</p>
        <p>''Conrad's Fate'' is a stand-alone novel linked to the other four books in the series by a common setup and sensibility and by a few important characters. When Conrad, the narrator, turns 12, his wicked Uncle Alfred sends him to nearby Stallery Mansion to train as a servant. Conrad would rather go to school, but his uncle persuades him that his fate lies in the mansion -- unless Conrad finds and kills his destined victim, he'll die himself. On the way to the mansion, Conrad meets Christopher Chant, another apprentice, and a key figure in the previous books in this series; here a tall and overconfident 15-year-old, he is the destined enchanter, the future Chrestomanci.</p>
        <p>Evil uncles abound in Jones's books. Christopher spends most of ''The Lives of Christopher Chant'' (1988) grappling with his own: a charismatic bounder who tricks him into using his powers to traffic in cruel, illegal magic ingredients, like mermaid tails. Jones also has a penchant for weak fathers, neglectful mothers, sisters who steal their brothers' magic and their very lives, and innocents who learn almost too late whom to trust and how to stand up for themselves and the people they love. She understands families, with their loyalties and betrayals, better than anyone writing in her genre. Her awful relatives are nuanced people who choose to act badly, rather than over-the-top cartoons like the Dursleys in the Harry Potter books or the evil aunts in Roald Dahl's ''James and the Giant Peach.''</p>
        <p>Given Jones's sense of humor and her interest in free will, faithful readers might expect ''Conrad's Fate'' to be about just the opposite of what its title suggests: Conrad's decisions. Like so many of her heroes, Conrad must learn to trust his friends, recognize his enemies and take charge of his life. Uncompromisingly intelligent beyond the wildest dreams of more famous fantasists, Diana Wynne Jones deserves a much bigger audience. Surely there's a world out there where she gets her due.</p>
        <p>Polly Shulman's novel for young adults, ''Enthusiasm,'' will be published next year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Polly Shulman's novel for young adults, ''Enthusiasm,'' will be published next year.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
