<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Go to the Mattresses (No, It's Not a Mob War)</title>
    <meta content="10njARCADE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/10/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/10njARCADE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1686294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="New Jersey"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer and Video Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050710T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903E6DD1F31F933A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Go to the Mattresses (No, It's Not a Mob War)</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Go to the Mattresses (No, It's Not a Mob War)</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVEN ZEITCHIK</byline>
      <dateline>BUTLER</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT least once a month, James Callari, 36, grabs some cans of Red Bull, packs up his computer and tells his girlfriend he is going out to play some video games. Don't bother waiting up, he'll say -- he won't be back for two or three days.</p>
        <p>Mr. Callari's destination is a LAN party, an intense, almost ritualistic convocation of gamers that has been springing up -- almost invisibly -- in pockets all over New Jersey.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For days on end, men are quietly gathering for intense, almost ritualistic electronic gaming benders.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT least once a month, James Callari, 36, grabs some cans of Red Bull, packs up his computer and tells his girlfriend he is going out to play some video games. Don't bother waiting up, he'll say -- he won't be back for two or three days.</p>
        <p>Mr. Callari's destination is a LAN party, an intense, almost ritualistic convocation of gamers that has been springing up -- almost invisibly -- in pockets all over New Jersey.</p>
        <p>In hotel conference rooms, firehouses, paramedic call centers -- anywhere that offers enough cheap real estate (and electric power) -- men are quietly gathering for gaming benders that by turns resemble an epic paintball match, a scene from the movie ''Fight Club,'' a high-tech game of ''Dungeons and Dragons'' and an Iron John meeting.</p>
        <p>Video arcades usually allow only one or two people to play a game at one time -- bad news for modern gamers, who like to play in groups.</p>
        <p>But through high-powered temporary servers, local area networks, or LANs, enable computers in a concentrated area to communicate. For Mr. Callari and his cohorts, LANs are the ticket to video-game orgies, sessions of intense play and bonding that can last days. Seventy-two hours is not unheard of. Computer equipment is obligatory. Air mattresses are optional.</p>
        <p>''Once you get that sense of camaraderie, you never want to leave,'' said Mr. Callari, who lives in Summit.</p>
        <p>Long past midnight on a recent Saturday, a dozen boys and men between the ages of 10 and 40 sat squinting in front of terminals. They were at a volunteer firehouse they had rented in Butler, on a quiet street next to a cemetery. Behind a room filled with hoses, award plaques and a gleaming fire truck sat the paraphernalia of the LAN life -- rows of snazzy C.P.U.'s, oversize monitors and mounds of snaking wires. A U.F.O. landing would not have seemed much stranger.</p>
        <p>The party's organizer was the boyishly gregarious John Pezzino. Outside the LAN matrix, Mr. Pezzino lives in Butler and works a desk job at U.P.S. In it, he is known as Murdock, and he calls the shots. ''UT?'' he says, the abbreviation for the game Unreal Tournament. Then, in reference to which mode they would play, ''Capture the Flag? Let's jump on.''</p>
        <p>With that, teammates erupt with warnings; opponents intimidate with (usually) good-natured digs; neighbors whisper conspiratorially. On the screen, perfect digital representations of masked men toting weaponry leap from rooftops and run across deserts. Gamers mechanically swig designer caffeine drinks with names like Bawls, their eyes sweating with the possibility of a virtual escape, their mouths motoring off instructions.</p>
        <p>If the office IT guys ever threw a rave, it would probably look something like this.</p>
        <p>''Warlord, where are you? Get out of there.''</p>
        <p>''I'm almost out of health.''</p>
        <p>''Dad, did you like the way I killed you?''</p>
        <p>''My health's, like, really gone.''</p>
        <p>''Spray and prey, spray and prey. Beautiful.''</p>
        <p>''Well, I'm dead.''</p>
        <p>Of course, LAN parties are not limited to New Jersey. California is a hotbed, and the Dallas mega-LAN Quakecon draws thousands. But the Garden State is fast becoming its Northeast capital. One of the country's biggest LANs, the GXL -- a three-day, 500-person bacchanal -- takes place at a rescue squad in Millville. And then there are the smaller gatherings nearly every week, run by at least five separate groups.</p>
        <p>''Jersey has things other places don't -- a lot of space and a lot of gamers,'' says a LAN-er who goes by the tag Kobalt and runs Weekend Wars, a South Jersey LAN. (In his non-LAN life, Kobalt is Mike Kowarski, who describes his career as ''on the law-enforcement side of things.'')</p>
        <p>Many of the games LAN-ers play are first-person shooters. To those of us for whom Frogger still represents the cutting edge, this can be a tricky concept. It basically means that no gamer can see the whole game at once, instead viewing it strictly from the perspective of their own character.</p>
        <p>Paradoxically, this enhances the thrill; you're never quite able to trust your eyes. It also increases the team factor. A nearby gamer either has your back -- or is waiting to put a bullet in it.</p>
        <p>Games also last a lot longer than they used to. The abundant number of virtual layouts, or maps, leads to complicated expeditions.</p>
        <p>But if the goals of particular games vary, what doesn't change is the stakes: Team pride and individual skills, measured by rankings of things like ''kills'' and ''health,'' which the computer periodically spits out.</p>
        <p>As a result, LAN-ers hone their craft with the diligence of a trained actor; for all the yelling, a LAN party can sometimes seem more like a play rehearsal, complete with furrowed brows and shared advice.</p>
        <p>As with many subcultures, language can be an unresolved thicket (''You got to get kills, and then you can kill'').</p>
        <p>As the night wears on, though, more recognizable forms of conversation flower. Men ogle one another's computer equipment. Some segue from Quake and Doom to life and love.</p>
        <p>In one corner of the room on Saturday, Mr. Callari is ruminating on the vagaries of relationships.</p>
        <p>''Inviting a woman to a LAN party is like inviting your wife to meet your mistress,'' he says to a group of five who have gathered around his chair. ''It's not that you can't do it, but why would you?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Callari, who goes by the tag Tora Bora Kid, is an unofficial leader in the LAN hierarchy. An electrician with an absurdist streak, he dresses in what you might call Haute Matrix -- black dress shirt embossed with a black flower, black dress slacks and black aviator sunglasses (at midnight).</p>
        <p>When asked if LAN parties ever ruined any of his relationships, he replies, ''Yes,'' with a slight hint of pride.</p>
        <p>Given how much LAN can feel like a religion, it is no surprise that each party plays off the same creation myth. It goes something like this:</p>
        <p>One or two friends sit home, playing games online. But they're tired of being separated from teammates. So they invite some people to bring over their computers. Before long, the gathering becomes too big. (Mr. Pezzino's moment of revelation came when he had to take apart his bed to accommodate gamers at his Waldwick apartment.) So they seek out a new place. Word-of-mouth grows. A LAN party is born.</p>
        <p>What is striking about LAN parties is how much they counter the notion of the video game as an isolating force. Across New Jersey's suburbs and towns, it is not lone figures in dark basements, but groups of 10 or 20 sharing an uncanny, if square, kinship.</p>
        <p>''Anyone can play a game online,'' Mr. Kowarski says. ''But it's not the same as being able to yell at them across the room.''</p>
        <p>While not technically a secret -- most parties welcome new members -- the gatherings thrive underground. Locations are revealed only shortly before each event. Word spreads via the scene or through cryptic postings on sites with gangsta-geek names like s2i.org, for shoot2ill.</p>
        <p>Turf wars are common to LAN scenes, and New Jersey is especially tangled. The s2i guys don't like the GXL guys. NJLanParty has been ripped off by NewJerseyLan, according to Weekend Wars. (NewJerseyLan has since gone silent.) LAN cafes -- cyber cafes that provide LAN gaming -- are to be scoffed at, though Mr. Kowarski allows they are not all bad because ''they could be a gateway drug'' for LAN parties.</p>
        <p>And many LAN-ers hate Counterstrikers, the fiends who exclusively play a popular older shooter called Counterstrike.</p>
        <p>''They cheat,'' Mr. Callari says. ''And they're so competitive.''</p>
        <p>LAN parties have come a long way since their basement days. Sensing an obsessive audience, sponsors like Red Bull and the graphics firm Nvidia have begun to get involved. Some parties are also now infiltrated by ''traders'' -- people who want to exploit the speedy network to share movie and music files. Prizes and betting can run to the hundreds of dollars.</p>
        <p>Yet the scene retains a purity; it's more skater park than X Games. Few organizers make a profit, and gamers pay just a small fee to cover costs.</p>
        <p>''Most of us just want to play,'' says Gregg McCarthy of Old Bridge, who runs the site NJGamers.</p>
        <p>LAN parties also look to initiate new members, and many fathers will bring sons. At the Butler LAN, Mr. Callari explained to Ryan Price, a 10-year-old up way past his bedtime, how gaming used to be.</p>
        <p>''We didn't have hard drives,'' he said. ''We had to put everything on a floppy disk.''</p>
        <p>The boy nodded, but the befuddled look on his face said, ''What's a floppy disk?''</p>
        <p>And like most subcultures, the underground does not always translate above ground. Those who rent out the space to LAN-ers have, perhaps understandably, reservations upon seeing dozens of sleep-deprived souls showing up with large suitcases of equipment as though at a high-tech vampire convention. (Perhaps as a result, many LAN parties now donate profits to local causes.) Not to mention all the spouses shaking their head as the males prepare for what seem like a very odd hunting trip.</p>
        <p>Somewhere around 1 a.m. in Butler, as people mill about between games, Mr. Pezzino tells how the fire captain who had rented him the hall hassled him when he saw the equipment they were dragging in.</p>
        <p>''I just want to go somewhere where we're appreciated, you know?'' Mr. Pezzino says. A few others nod, and Lou, a LAN-er with slick blond hair and a pile of software guides, says, ''Well, that's not going to happen,'' in a you-should-know-better tone.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pezzino pauses as he uploads a version of the next game. Then, looking contemplative, he says, ''Yeah, I guess that's true.''</p>
        <p>New Jersey</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
