<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Out of Jail, Into Temptation: A Day in a Life</title>
    <meta content="28RIKE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/28/nyregion/28RIKE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1371438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rikers Island Prison Complex (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Feuer, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nando (Convicted Drug Dealer)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Probation and Parole</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cocaine and Crack Cocaine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Bronx (NY)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E3DD1231F93BA15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="2530" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Out of Jail, Into Temptation: A Day in a Life</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Out of Jail, Into Temptation: A Day in a Life</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALAN FEUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Feuer, Alan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Convicted drug dealer 'Nando' returns home after 8-month stay in Rikers Island for selling crack, to confront world of traps and troubles that sent him to prison to begin with; article describes Nando's first day home, as he returns to Morrisania section of Bronx where his girlfriend and old pals are, as is his past as addict and dealer; he finds his best friend has been arrested; he makes frustrating trip to welfare office, then visits his mother in Brooklyn hospital room where she lays, catatonic; all day he is offered opportunities to get high again, and to work for his old crack boss; he ends day discouraged; more than 20,000 inmates like Nando are released from Rikers Island each yuear after serving terms of year or less; like Nando, they are free to find jobs, or buy drugs, without authorities watching; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Nando came home from jail to a small apartment in the Bronx that stank like a backed-up toilet.</p>
        <p>He had been gone eight months, behind bars for selling crack, and as he came through the door from Rikers Island, he wrinkled his nose at the smell. His spider plant was dead. Its blackened leaves crumpled under his touch. His telephone was dead. He blew in the receiver, but the line was out.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>"Nando," a 20-year-old Bronx man, just released from prison, is now facing the same rough choices he did before he was convicted.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Nando came home from jail to a small apartment in the Bronx that stank like a backed-up toilet.</p>
        <p>He had been gone eight months, behind bars for selling crack, and as he came through the door from Rikers Island, he wrinkled his nose at the smell. His spider plant was dead. Its blackened leaves crumpled under his touch. His telephone was dead. He blew in the receiver, but the line was out.</p>
        <p>The bathroom faucet spewed brown water. A bag of chips in the kitchen was covered in dust.</p>
        <p>''It's like a garbage dump,'' he said. ''I've got a lot of work to do.''</p>
        <p>The work would not be easy. What lay ahead for Nando, a 20-year-old man who agreed to spend his first day out of jail with a reporter and photographer as long as his last name did not appear in print, would prove to be a veil of dark temptation, a toxic mix of the traps and troubles that sent him off to prison to begin with.</p>
        <p>Each year, more than 20,000 inmates are released from the C-76 jail on Rikers Island, which houses those serving terms of a year or less. Unlike state prisoners, these city convicts have no probation or parole officers to report to once they are released. They are free to find jobs, or buy drugs, without the authorities watching.</p>
        <p>Nando was released at 5 a.m. on Feb. 4. By 7 a.m., he had learned that his best friend had just been arrested on a crack charge. By 9 a.m., he was languishing in a welfare office. By 10, he had been offered a joint. By 10:15, he had been offered his old job back, selling crack and marijuana.</p>
        <p>By the end of the day, he had watched an old friend try to hide her drug habit from her curious toddler son. He had stood at the hospital bed of his catatonic mother. He had sorted through the mail that had piled up for months. The electric company was threatening to shut his power off.</p>
        <p>He chose to return to his fifth-floor walk-up in the Morrisania section of the Bronx. His girlfriend and his old pals were still in the neighborhood; so was his past as an addict and a dealer. Though home seemed the natural place to go, it was also where his problems had started. Nando knew that in advance. He knew it the moment he stepped off the Rikers Island bus in northern Queens at 5:16 a.m.</p>
        <p>It was still dark and the other men ran for the subway. Nando sniffed the air and smiled. ''It's good to be out,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Nando, short for Fernando, is a skinny man with scruff on his chin and Chinese characters tattooed along his neck. He started peddling drugs at 14, started using them at 15. He was jailed last June for selling 200 grams of crack to an undercover officer.</p>
        <p>The city releases Rikers Island inmates on a squalid street corner in Queens Plaza every day between 3 and 5:30 a.m. Each one carries a $3 MetroCard provided by the prison and his jailhouse chattel in a paper bag. Nando got off the bus with a Hermann Hesse novel in his bag and an ambitious to-do list in his head: Reconnect with family. Stay off drugs. Enroll in college. Find a job.</p>
        <p>His first stop was his father's apartment in Co-op City. He arrived about 6. His younger brother, David, hugged him in the kitchen, still wearing his pajamas. His father, Fernando Sr., handed him a winter coat, a videotape of the Super Bowl and a couple of $20 bills.</p>
        <p>''I never expected any kid of mine to wind up where he wound up,'' the father said. ''I ain't never going back, not even on a visit. Don't know about him, but I ain't never going back.''</p>
        <p>It was a brief reunion. Nando's father was due at the factory where he works and his brother was due at school. His father gave Nando keys to the apartment. Nando mused that he might just buy a dog.</p>
        <p>It was a terrible idea, his father said. ''No dogs,'' he ordered. ''Right now, you can't afford to feed yourself.''</p>
        <p>East Tremont Avenue cuts through the Bronx like a swollen femoral artery. It is a wide urban boulevard of barber shops and Spanish greasy spoons. But to Nando, it might as well have been the only road in a tiny town.</p>
        <p>He knew everyone. The woman walking by was the manager of a grocery store, he said. The crumpled  man on the corner was a crackhead. An unmarked Chevrolet rolled by and, out of instinct, Nando ducked; it was a prowling team of undercover cops.</p>
        <p>''I don't want to be here, but there's nowhere else to go,'' he muttered as the car drove by. ''Lots of us end up right back in the same damn place. It makes me want to blow up the 'hood.''</p>
        <p>Bad News About a Friend</p>
        <p>He turned down Boston Road until he came to a dim apartment house on Crotona Park East. Nando put his hands to his mouth and hooted like an owl. ''Hey yo, Chuckie!'' he yelled. ''Hey yo, where's Chuck?''</p>
        <p>A woman appeared in a fourth-floor window and shouted for him to come inside. The lobby smelled like feces. Its ceiling light was smashed. The walls looked like a notebook, covered in graffiti. The scrawl praised murder and masturbation.</p>
        <p>The woman in the window was Nando's former girlfriend, Jackie, who quickly gave him the news: Chuckie -- her brother and Nando's friend -- had been arrested the day before.</p>
        <p>Nando was crushed. He had just left Rikers Island, and now Chuckie might be headed there himself.</p>
        <p>Five minutes later, Nando left. ''The ghetto of all ghettos,'' he said as he walked toward home.</p>
        <p>At his old apartment, the stench got up to meet him. It smelled like a stadium men's room on a hot summer's day. Dirty dishes were piled in the sink; a box of Cheerios stood open on the table. He turned on the television, and the screen looked like a finger-painting. The picture tube was blown.</p>
        <p>It was starting to dawn on him, he said: he was out of jail, responsible for himself, alone. He popped a compact disc in the player and sat down on his rocking chair. ''I used to sit here for hours getting high,'' he said, rocking slowly, staring at his hands. ''I can feel the whole thing pulling at me. What am I going to do?''</p>
        <p>On the walk home from Jackie's, he had called his girlfriend, Mery, and set a date for 9 a.m. He needed to clean himself, but first he had to clean the shower. A thick layer of scum had settled in the tub.</p>
        <p>He went to the bathroom with a toilet brush. There, on the sink, were his mother's false teeth.</p>
        <p>A Reminder of His Mother</p>
        <p>Six months ago, a guard woke him to say, ''Your mother's had a heart attack. She's in the hospital in Brooklyn.'' The jail allowed him a visit. He went and stared at his mother. All she could do was twitch her head.</p>
        <p>Nando ignored the teeth. He cleaned the tub and showered. Then he looked for clothes in the bedroom his mother had used before she had fallen ill. The bed was stripped of sheets and gave the impression of a vacant lot. Nando ignored that, too.</p>
        <p>Three hours earlier, after getting off the prison bus, Nando had laughed at a movie billboard with the slogan, ''Behind every good man, there is a woman kicking his butt.'' At 9 a.m., Mery was waiting for him on the corner of Suburban Place and Boston Road. Her smile lit up the sidewalk two full blocks away.</p>
        <p>They hugged. They kissed. She touched his hair, grown long on Rikers Island. They kissed again and didn't care who watched.</p>
        <p>Mery is going to college while living in a homeless shelter. She is Nando's one good thing, and Nando freely admits it. Still, he sometimes finds her loving attention hard to take.</p>
        <p>They walked down Boston Road to the subway station so Mery could head to school. She scooted up the stairs, then turned around. ''Yo, behave!'' was all she said.</p>
        <p>At the welfare office across the street, Nando filled out forms for Medicaid. It was 9:15, and the room was already packed. Telephones rang. Babies cried. Nando put his name on the list. He was 21st in line.</p>
        <p>The form asked, ''Do you have any of these problems?'' Nando checked the boxes next to ''Urgent Personal or Family Problems'' and ''No Food.''</p>
        <p>Thirty minutes later a clerk informed him that he had come to the wrong place. The office he needed was on 138th Street, 40 blocks away.</p>
        <p>He was mad at the clerk. He was mad at himself. He stormed outside to a pay phone and punched in a number. ''Yeah,'' he said. ''What up? I'm on the block. I'm home.''</p>
        <p>Minutes later, a bony man in a baggy sweatshirt came walking down the block. His name was Rob, and he was a member of Nando's former drug crew. On Boston Road, the two old friends bumped chests. Rob made fun of Nando's hair.</p>
        <p>''What you up to, son?'' Nando asked.</p>
        <p>Rob did not waste time. ''I'm smoking a blunt with you.''</p>
        <p>Everywhere, Temptation</p>
        <p>Suddenly, a choice: Go to the welfare office or get high with Rob. The choice got harder when Rob's cellphone began to ring. The call was for Nando. It was his old crack boss, asking if he wanted to go back to work.</p>
        <p>According to city officials, 80 percent of Rikers Island's inmates test positive for drug use, and drugs are why most end up on the island to begin with. In the past, Nando had taken drugs and sold drugs. Now, within 60 seconds, he'd had offers to do both again.</p>
        <p>''No, I'm straight,'' he told the boss, ''but I'll let you know.'' Then he turned down Rob's joint. But as he stood there talking, his old crack customers walked by. They waved and nodded. It was as if he'd never left.</p>
        <p>With Rob in tow, Nando went back to Jackie's place. He wanted someplace quiet to use the phone. He wanted the address of his mother's hospital in Brooklyn. It had been six months; he wanted to see her face.</p>
        <p>When Jackie opened the door, the marijuana smoke enveloped him like a blanket. He called information for the hospital's address, trying to ignore the smell. Jackie ran through the rooms, opening windows, spraying a can of air freshener. Her little boy, Aaron, came down the hallway. Aaron is 3. Jackie is 18.</p>
        <p>Nando headed for the door and as he went out, Rob came in. He had bought a cheap cigar and stuffed it full of dope.</p>
        <p>Nando unloaded on him on the street.</p>
        <p>''Keep doing that and you'll wind up on Rikers Island,'' he said. Rob brushed him off. Nando let out a cold laugh at his buddy. ''You best make sure you don't wind up in jail,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The trip to the hospital took an hour. As Nando approached his mother's room, an orderly stopped him in the hall.</p>
        <p>''Who are you?'' she asked. She was baffled by the answer. ''Her son?'' the woman said. ''Why don't you ever visit? Where have you been the last six months?''</p>
        <p>His mother's limbs were frozen, her eyes so empty of emotion they looked like dirty glass. Her face twitched uncontrollably, and Nando stood there, wordless. The orderly told him if he pinched her fingers she would feel it. But other than that, she would not respond.</p>
        <p>Nando stared at his mother for 30 minutes, trying to fight back tears. On the nightstand was the fake red rose he had bought on the way to see her.</p>
        <p>''A day in my life,'' he said on the street again, his voice gone soft. ''Anyone want it?'' It was 2:15 p.m.</p>
        <p>A Reminder in the Mail</p>
        <p>Back at home, he planned his week. Hit the job center. Hit the right welfare office.</p>
        <p>Then he went downstairs to get his mail.</p>
        <p>On Rikers, he had taken a writing class, and his last assignment was to write a letter to himself as a happy 70-year-old man. He was to describe that happy life, writing from the future, to himself as he was now, at 20. He had to describe the choices he had made.</p>
        <p>The letter was in his mailbox.</p>
        <p>Dear Nando,</p>
        <p>I remember those days we spent on Rikers Island. Pretty rough, huhh! Well, as for me, I made the best of it. I chose to change a couple of things about myself in order to get where I'm at now. Let's just say I'm at a place where it's always sunny and hot and when it rains, it really rains. I got a few kids now and a beautiful wife with a handful of grandchildren. What I chose to do was leave all the drugs and negative things alone. It was really rough at first, but I never gave up. I always knew I could do more.</p>
        <p>Sincerely,</p>
        <p>Nando</p>
        <p>He sat on the rocking chair and read the letter, twice. Then he lay down on his mother's bed.</p>
        <p>It was 4 p.m. and he wasn't sleepy. Tomorrow was only eight hours away.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
