<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Costs of Consolidation</title>
    <meta content="28JONE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="27" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/28/opinion/28JONE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1371382"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Alex S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Regulation and Deregulation of Industry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Decisions and Verdicts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Federal Communications Commission</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9400EED91531F93BA15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="810" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Costs of Consolidation</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Costs of Consolidation</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Alex S. Jones</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Alex S</byline>
      <dateline>CAMBRIDGE, Mass.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alex S Jones Op-Ed article expresses misgivings over recent appeals court decision relaxing limits on television and cable-system ownership of media outlets; says rules limiting media ownership are rapidly disappearing, and that if they are allowed to vanish, nation's news landscape will change dramatically and not for better (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rules limiting media ownership are rapidly disappearing. If they are allowed to vanish, the nation's news landscape will change dramatically -- and not for the better.</p>
        <p>Last week's appeals court decision relaxing the limits on television and cable-system ownership is only the first step. This could well be the beginning of a trend in which local newspapers and radio stations are merged with local television stations, consolidating the gathering and distribution of news in most American cities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>If the rules limiting media ownership are allowed to vanish, the nation's news landscape will change dramatically  and not for the better.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rules limiting media ownership are rapidly disappearing. If they are allowed to vanish, the nation's news landscape will change dramatically -- and not for the better.</p>
        <p>Last week's appeals court decision relaxing the limits on television and cable-system ownership is only the first step. This could well be the beginning of a trend in which local newspapers and radio stations are merged with local television stations, consolidating the gathering and distribution of news in most American cities.</p>
        <p>The ruling ordered the Federal Communications Commission to reconsider its limits on the number of TV stations any one network can own, and it struck down the F.C.C.'s rule prohibiting cable companies from owning TV stations in markets where they operate. Given the terse language of the opinion, and a 1996 law that requires the F.C.C. to review its rules every two years and ''repeal or modify any regulation it deems not to be in the public interest,'' it's likely there will be further reductions, or even the elimination, of limits on ownership. In 1999 the F.C.C. gave networks permission to own two stations in the same city, and not surprisingly the result has been a wave of acquisitions.</p>
        <p>The next, and more important, shoe to drop will be the F.C.C.'s expected relaxation or elimination of the rules preventing a single company from owning both a town's newspaper and a TV station -- or, now, two TV stations. These rules against what is called cross-ownership have been on the books for more than 25 years, but Michael Powell, the chairman of the F.C.C., has sent strong signals that he feels they are anachronisms.</p>
        <p>In the vast majority of cities and towns in the United States, there is now only one major newspaper. Most newspapers and TV stations are already owned by major chains -- but not in combination in the same town.</p>
        <p>Deregulation would almost certainly set in motion a frenzy of acquisitions of media properties by companies like Gannett and the Tribune Company, which own both newspapers and TV stations. By trading a significant media stake in two towns for a bigger -- and more profitable -- position in one town, these companies stand to become even more powerful. Similarly, networks can be expected to want to own the newspaper in places where they already operate TV stations.</p>
        <p>One response to this phenomenon might well be, So what? Even with such concentration, Americans still have many sources for news. The Internet, with its limitless supply of news and information, is available everywhere in America. Most cable systems offer scores of channels and programming formats. Many cities have alternative newspapers.</p>
        <p>With local and regional news, however, all this diversity hardly matters. The Internet, for instance, gives people greater access than ever before to national and international news. But in almost every town in America, the daily paper dominates local news and competes with only a handful of local television and radio stations. Some say local TV news reporting will improve under newspaper management, but that is merely a hope. Besides, it's just as likely that the TV station will take over the newspaper as vice versa.</p>
        <p>These possible F.C.C. rule changes will almost certainly create a concentration of media power far beyond what now exists in most places. Such a local media leviathan may have the best of intentions and have no wish to stifle disparate voices. But consolidation could well foreclose the possibility of any competition that would improve news coverage.</p>
        <p>A vision of this future can be glimpsed in about 25 cities, including Atlanta and Dallas, where the local newspaper also owns a local TV station, an arrangement that predated the cross-ownership ban and was allowed to survive.</p>
        <p>In Tampa, a major newspaper chain owns a local TV station and they have merged newsrooms in a closely watched experiment. Both the newspaper and TV station are directed from a single news desk, which suggests the kind of consolidation of news judgment that may come with such mergers. Viewers and readers may grow accustomed to this kind of arrangement. But if given the choice, would business and community leaders choose it?</p>
        <p>T oo much media concentration in any town is inherently unhealthy, like relying on a single dominant industry or investing heavily in only one stock. Excessive dependence on a single source of news can put at risk the free exchange of ideas essential to democracy.</p>
        <p>The First Amendment is meant to assure robust debate, and the limitations on local cross-ownership were written with that objective in mind. On the local level, rolling back those rules will inevitably make that debate more one-sided.</p>
        <p>Alex S. Jones is director of the Joan Shorenstein Center on the Press, Politics and Public Policy at Harvard's Kennedy School of Government.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Alex S. Jones is director of the Joan Shorenstein Center on the Press, Politics and Public Policy at Harvard's Kennedy School of Government.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
