<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Achilles' Heel Found in Legs Of the T. Rex</title>
    <meta content="Y28DINO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="22" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/28/science/28DINO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1371397"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Tyrannosaurus Rex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Nature (Journal)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cornell University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Stanford University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wilford, John Noble</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hutchinson, John R (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Garcia, Mariano (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science/Environment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dinosaurs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Paleontology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Endangered and Extinct Species</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020228T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E7D71531F93BA15751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Achilles' Heel Found in Legs Of the T. Rex</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Achilles' Heel Found in Legs of the T. Rex</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOHN NOBLE WILFORD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wilford, John Noble</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Paleontologists Drs John R Hutchinson (Stanford Univ) and Mariano Garcia (Cornell Univ) report in journal Nature that Tyrannosaurus Rex, biggest and fiercest predator in age of reptiles, was not superior in all respects; say contrary to popular belief it was biomechanically disadvantaged; say it lacked enough muscle in hind legs to produce forces required for animal of its huge size to break into sprint, let alone achieve 45-miles-per-hour speeds some paleontologists once assumed; diagram (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Every school child knows that Tyrannosaurus rex was the biggest, fiercest predator in the Age of Reptiles. No plant-eating Triceratops or duckbill dinosaur was safe when a hungry T. rex came around with sharp teeth ready to tear flesh.</p>
        <p>But scientists have now found that this fearsome animal was not superior in all respects. It was biomechanically disadvantaged. Contrary to what had been thought, T. rex was slow of foot. It lacked enough muscle in its legs to produce the forces required for an animal of its huge size to break into a sprint, let alone achieve the 45 mile-per-hour speeds some paleontologists once assumed.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Scientists have discovered that the Tyrannosaurus Rex had mechanical disadvantages that were previously unknown.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Every school child knows that Tyrannosaurus rex was the biggest, fiercest predator in the Age of Reptiles. No plant-eating Triceratops or duckbill dinosaur was safe when a hungry T. rex came around with sharp teeth ready to tear flesh.</p>
        <p>But scientists have now found that this fearsome animal was not superior in all respects. It was biomechanically disadvantaged. Contrary to what had been thought, T. rex was slow of foot. It lacked enough muscle in its legs to produce the forces required for an animal of its huge size to break into a sprint, let alone achieve the 45 mile-per-hour speeds some paleontologists once assumed.</p>
        <p>The surprising discovery, being reported in today's issue of the journal Nature, was made by Dr. John R. Hutchinson of Stanford and Dr. Mariano Garcia of Cornell. The two men, specialists in biomechanics, conducted their research while at the University of California.</p>
        <p>The amount of muscle needed for running, they found, increases at a faster rate than an animal's body mass. They determined that an adult T. rex would have needed more than 80 percent of its mass in its leg muscles to run fast, an implausibly high figure.</p>
        <p>The findings were supported by research with alligators and chickens, distant relatives of extinct reptiles. A chicken, for example, runs well with only 17 percent of its mass in leg muscles. But if it were the size of a 13,000-pound tyrannosaur, it would need 99 percent of its body mass in each leg to get up any speed.</p>
        <p>''Therefore, it is doubtful that Tyrannosaurus and other huge dinosaurs were capable runners or could reach high speeds,'' the two researchers said.</p>
        <p>In an interview, Dr. Hutchinson said T. rex was probably capable of running at brief bursts of speeds of at least 10 m.p.h., the average for people and elephants. But depending on widely different assumptions introduced to the models, the big animals could not run at all, or, at an unlikely best, might have achieved very brief bursts of speeds comparable to an Olympic sprinter, 23 m.p.h. By any estimate, a T. rex would have been left hopelessly in the dust of a 65-m.p.h. cheetah.</p>
        <p>Even though not built for speed, some scientists said, tyrannosaurs managed on their two long legs to be efficient hunters of large prey and a terror on the landscape in the twilight of the dinosaurs, more than 65 million years ago.</p>
        <p>Dr. Kevin Padian, a paleontologist at the University of California, praised the research, with its computerized analysis of anatomy and biomechanics, as ''setting a standard for how this kind of work will have to be done in the future.''</p>
        <p>Even the makers of the movie ''Jurassic Park'' seem to have suspected that there was something wrong with images of the fleet tyrannosaur. Analyzing the film of a tyrannosaur chasing people in a vehicle, scientists noted that the animated beast always had one foot on the ground and the cadence of the footfalls was too slow to be moving at more than 40 m.p.h., as the audience was asked to believe.</p>
        <p>The moviemakers acknowledged that they had had to resort to some camera trickery, Dr. Hutchinson and Dr. Garcia said.</p>
        <p>''Why didn't the filmmakers just have the Tyrannosaurus moving 40-plus miles per hour?'' they asked. ''Those basic biomechanical principles of size and locomotion just wouldn't allow it to 'look right' to our eyes. The scene would strain credulity, and our research shows why.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
