<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Toys 'R' Us Plans Charge For Global Reorganization</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827154"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHUTDOWNS (INSTITUTIONAL)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOYS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANYREPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LABOR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LAYOFFS AND JOB REDUCTIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">TOYS 'R' US INC</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">BABIES 'R' US INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">GILPIN, KENNETH N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDSTEIN, MICHAEL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shutdowns (Institutional)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0DB1739F931A35751C0A960958260" item-length="645" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Toys 'R' Us Plans Charge For Global Reorganization</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KENNETH N. GILPIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GILPIN, KENNETH N</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a move intended to shore up sagging profitability, Toys "R" Us Inc. announced yesterday that it was reorganizing its worldwide operations, a plan that included closing 25 stores and paring the array of merchandise it offers to consumers.</p>
        <p>To cover the reorganization costs, the company said it would take a one-time  after-tax charge of $270 million in the fiscal fourth quarter of 1996.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a move intended to shore up sagging profitability, Toys "R" Us Inc. announced yesterday that it was reorganizing its worldwide operations, a plan that included closing 25 stores and paring the array of merchandise it offers to consumers.</p>
        <p>To cover the reorganization costs, the company said it would take a one-time  after-tax charge of $270 million in the fiscal fourth quarter of 1996.</p>
        <p>Michael Goldstein, chief executive of Toys "R" Us, the world's largest toy specialty retailing chain, said that operating profits before the charge were expected to be about $590 million for the fourth quarter, compared with $665 million in the comparable period last year, and about $740 million for the full  fiscal year, which ends tomorrow. In its 1995 fiscal year, Toys "R" Us, which is based in Paramus, N.J., had operating profits of $912 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein added that the changes announced yesterday were expected to increase operating earnings this year by at least $50 million, and by even more  in 1997 and beyond.</p>
        <p>Investors cheered the changes. So did Wall Street analysts, who added that many were long overdue. After the announcement, Toys "R" Us shares climbed $1.50, to $23.50 yesterday, on the New York Stock Exchange.</p>
        <p>"This will be the first year in which the company has taken meaningful initiatives within the context of a changing competitive environment," said Donald Trott, a retailing analyst at Dean Witter Inc. "But it won't be before 1997 or 1998 that these embellishments will proliferate throughout the system."</p>
        <p>Like most retailers, Toys "R" Us has been feeling intense pressure from discounting giants like Wal-Mart Stores and the Kmart Corporation, as well as specialty chains like Noodle Kiboodle, a unit of Greenman Brothers Inc. Tepid consumer spending and the lack of a hot toy have not helped.</p>
        <p>"You have to avoid overstating just how off-track the company is," said David Poneman, an analyst at Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company.</p>
        <p>"In an environment where everybody made less money from toys last year, Toys  "R" Us is looking at about a 10 percent drop in fourth-quarter operating income," Mr. Poneman said. "That sort of drop is well in line with the decline that Wal-Mart has talked about in its toy business. From earlier in the year, they have turned the business."</p>
        <p>The company said it would cut the number of items it carries to 11,000 from 15,000 to focus on its best-selling goods, update its merchandise and increase the pace of inventory turnover.</p>
        <p>"In this environment, where price is important, the streamlining will allow us to be more efficient and have less clutter in our stores," Mr. Goldstein said in a telephone interview. "That will make it easier for consumers to shop, and easier for us to gain market share."</p>
        <p>The company said stores to be closed included three Toys "R" Us stores and 12 Kids "R" Us outlets in the United States. It also plans to franchise or close 10 stores in Europe. In addition, the company plans to consolidate three distribution centers and seven administrative facilities in the United States and Europe.</p>
        <p>Mr. Goldstein said the store closings would result in "minimal" layoffs in the United States, because the company plans to open 55 new stores, including 10 in its new Babies "R" Us division.</p>
        <p>"On a net basis we feel we are going to be hiring many more people this year," he said.</p>
        <p>Toys "R" Us has more than 50,000 employees. The company operates 653 toy stores in the United States, 337 international toy stores and 213 Kids "R" Us children's clothing stores.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
