<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. Auto Makers Fear Strength Of Dollar Gives Edge to Japan</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827173"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AUTOMOBILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INTERNATIONAL TRADE AND WORLD MARKET</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRICES (FARES, FEES AND RATES)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SALES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CURRENCY</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">GENERAL MOTORS CORP</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FORD MOTOR CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CHRYSLER CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prices (Fares, Fees and Rates)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DEEDB1739F931A35751C0A960958260" item-length="1105" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. Auto Makers Fear Strength Of Dollar Gives Edge to Japan</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>DETROIT, Feb. 1</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With rebates spreading and profits threatened, the nation's car makers are now complaining about the strength of the dollar.</p>
        <p>When the dollar was falling and the Japanese yen was rising, Japan's auto makers were raising prices regularly and handing the Big Three auto makers the best import-fighter ever: a price advantage. But now Japanese auto makers are skipping some price increases thanks to a round of significant cost-cutting, and the price difference between Japanese and American cars and trucks is shrinking.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With rebates spreading and profits threatened, the nation's car makers are now complaining about the strength of the dollar.</p>
        <p>When the dollar was falling and the Japanese yen was rising, Japan's auto makers were raising prices regularly and handing the Big Three auto makers the best import-fighter ever: a price advantage. But now Japanese auto makers are skipping some price increases thanks to a round of significant cost-cutting, and the price difference between Japanese and American cars and trucks is shrinking.</p>
        <p>What is more, Japanese auto makers, who have learned to live with a high yen-weak dollar, are anticipating a potential profit windfall as the dollar strengthens. Now, analysts say the Japanese are on the verge of raising the industry's standard for competitiveness.</p>
        <p>By reducing costs, analysts believe, most Japanese car makers can compete profitably at an exchange rate of 100 yen to the dollar and either expand their  market shares or reap large profits at today's exchange rate of nearly 107 yen to the dollar, from about 80 yen last April.</p>
        <p>"At 80 yen per dollar, those shipments from Japan were losing billions of dollars -- at 107, they are wildly profitable again," said Jay N. Woodworth, an  auto industry analyst in Summit, N.J. "The U.S. Big Three do not realize that, and I think that they do not appreciate the dramatic cost cutting the Japanese have done."</p>
        <p>Indeed, despite some the most aggressive cost-cutting in the industry's history, Detroit may find it still has significant work to do just to hang on to its share of the auto market.</p>
        <p>The chief executives of the General Motors Corporation, the Ford Motor Company and the Chrysler Corporation agreed here today to warn the Clinton Administration about the cost of its strong-dollar policies. The car companies will not ask the Administration to intervene to drive the dollar down, said Andrew H. Card Jr., the president of the American Automobile Manufacturers Association. "I think that's premature," he said. "We're going to express our concern and ask them to be sensitive to the impact it has on our domestic manufacturers."</p>
        <p>Mr. Card would not rule out the possibility of seeking intervention, particularly if the dollar reaches 110 yen. "I personally think it should be at  100," he said. "If you just look at the numbers, from 80 to 107, that's billions of dollars" in sales.</p>
        <p>Wall Street analysts are only now assessing what the dollar's rise and the yen's fall might mean for the American automobile industry. The combination of a rising dollar and falling Japanese costs represents "sort of a double-edged sword that they're dealing with here, or potentially being whacked with," said Joseph S. Phillippi, an analyst at Lehman Brothers.</p>
        <p>Detroit is "wholly vulnerable" to a higher dollar, said Maryann Keller, an analyst at Furman Selz. It forces "us to look again at the basic competitiveness and cost structure" of Detroit, she said.</p>
        <p>The dollar's 34 percent rebound to 107 yen has not only allowed the Japanese  companies to return to robust profitability but also makes it harder for Detroit to keep raising prices, hold its market share, and continue reporting strong earnings.</p>
        <p>The Mazda Motor Corporation has already refrained from any price increases in November, December and January for the first time in at least five years. The Nissan Motor Company is also planning little or no price increases for now.</p>
        <p>"If the dollar had not appreciated like it has, we probably would have seen a continuation of the 2 to 3 percent a year price increases," said Robert J. Thomas, the president and chief executive of the Nissan Motor Corporation USA.</p>
        <p>Heavy price discounts by Japanese manufacturers, made possible in part by the stronger dollar, pushed up the Japanese share of the United States market by 1.6 percentage points in December from a year earlier. And Japanese car makers announced further sales gains today.</p>
        <p>Until recently, Detroit auto executives have said little publicly about the dollar's rise. But Chrysler officials say that the company's chairman and chief  executive, Robert Eaton, did tell senior managers at a meeting last September that Toyota's costs to make the Previa mini-van in Japan, when converted from yen into dollars, were $4,870 greater than Chrysler's costs for the Plymouth Grand Voyager mini-van at an exchange rate of 80 yen to the dollar. But Chrysler faces a $2,650 disadvantage if a dollar is worth 110 yen, Mr. Eaton warned.</p>
        <p>Auto executives have been more vocal about their concerns this week. David McCammon, Ford's vice president for finance, said recently that foreign exchange losses hit $500 million last year, reflecting the diminished value in dollars of overseas profits earned in foreign currencies.</p>
        <p>But Mr. McCammon said the bigger cost of a higher dollar lay in the greater difficulty it poses for American companies as Japanese vehicles become cheaper here. "Mostly we think of it as hurting us in a competitive sense," he said.</p>
        <p>American auto makers have a tradition of complaining about an overvalued dollar and may find that their latest worries will be ignored in Washington. And the effects of a rising dollar may not be as noteworthy this time around. Nearly 40 percent of the cars and trucks sold by Japanese companies in the United States last year were made in North America, so much of the manufacturing costs  are in dollars, not yen.</p>
        <p>American auto executives took pains in interviews to say that they were not complaining about the outcome from currency market trading but that they were concerned that the dollar's current level was partly the result of American and  Japanese Government rehetoric and market interventions.</p>
        <p>"I don't know if it's so much to complain to the Administration as to make the Administration aware of the effects a stronger dollar has on the auto industry," said Martin B. Zimmerman, Ford's executive director for government relations and corporate economics.</p>
        <p>Even if the Administration wanted to brake the dollar's rise, there is no guarantee that the usual combination of rhetoric from top officials and currency market intervention would have much effect. A senior Treasury official said tonight that while the Administration cared about the auto industry, it still believed that "a strong dollar is in our overall national interest."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
