<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>RESULTS PLUS</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827206"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">BOSTON COLLEGE</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E4DA1739F931A35751C0A960958260" item-length="676" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>RESULTS PLUS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>COLLEGE BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>Providence Staves Off Boston College</p>
        <p>Providence was hot from outside; Boston College couldn't miss from the line.  It doesn't take a math major to figure out who is going to win a trade of 1-pointers for 3-pointers.</p>
        <p>Derrick Brown and Michael Brown combined for 43 points and eight of the Friars' 14 3-pointers last night as Providence held off No. 21 Boston College, 76-75, in Newton, Mass.</p>
        <p>Providence (11-7 over all, 4-6 in the Big East) went 9 of 10 from 3-point range in the second half to beat the Eagles (12-5, 5-4) for the fourth consecutive time, the seventh in eight games. It was the Friars' first victory over a ranked team in four attempts this season. (AP)</p>
        <p>SYRACUSE 72, MIAMI 51: Otis Hill and John Wallace pounded Miami inside for a  combined 36 points and No. 18 Syracuse harassed the Hurricanes into 30 percent shooting. It was the second straight blowout loss for Miami (10-8, 4-6 Big East), which lost by 28 to Villanova on Saturday. Syracuse (15-6, 6-5) avenged a 75-66 loss to Miami earlier this year. (AP)</p>
        <p>MEMPHIS 83, DePAUL 82: In Rosemont, Ill., Mingo Johnson scored 6 points in overtime as No. 11 Memphis (16-3, 7-1 Conference USA) withstood DePaul's second-half surge, sending the Blue Demons (7-12, 0-8) to their school-record ninth straight loss. (AP)</p>
        <p>MARYLAND 80, VIRGINIA 72: In Charlottesville, Va., Keith Booth scored 11 of his career-high 27 points during a 17-2 run when Maryland (10-7, 3-4 Atlantic Coast Conference) took command, handing Virginia (7-10, 2-6) its fifth straight  loss. (AP)</p>
        <p>UTAH 77, TEXAS-EL PASO 62: In Salt Lake City, Brandon Jessie and Keith Van Horn scored 17 points each to lead No. 7 Utah (17-3, 9-1 Western Athletic Conference) to a victory over Texas-El Paso (10-9, 2-8). (AP)</p>
        <p>WASHINGTON 80, ARIZONA 79: Jason Hartman made a free throw with 1.1 seconds left in overtime, lifting Washington (13-4, 6-2 Pac-10) to its first victory in  Tucson in 12 years over No. 14 Arizona (15-4, 5-3). (AP)</p>
        <p>TENNIS</p>
        <p>Seles Gains Despite Ailing Shoulder</p>
        <p>Top-seeded Monica Seles, in obvious distress because of an aching shoulder, defeated Irina Spirlea of Romania, 6-4, 6-2, yesterday and led the way into the  quarterfinals of the Toray Pan Pacific Open in Tokyo. Eighth-seeded Lindsay Davenport also advanced by beating another American, Lisa Raymond, 6-1, 6-3.</p>
        <p>Seles, a left-hander, several times rubbed her left shoulder with her right hand during breaks in the 65-minute match.</p>
        <p>Seles won her fourth Australian Open women's singles title last Saturday. In  today's quarterfinals, she takes on seventh-seeded Iva Majoli of Croatia, who eliminated Brenda Schultz-McCarthy of the Netherlands, 7-6 (8-6), 7-5. (AP)</p>
        <p>N.H.L.</p>
        <p>Flyers Edge Canadiens in Overtime</p>
        <p>Eric Desjardins scored from the right circle with 29.8 seconds remaining in overtime last night as the Philadelphia Flyers beat Montreal, 3-2. Shjon Podein  scrambled for the puck behind the Canadiens' net and spotted Desjardins coming down from the point. Desjardins ripped a shot that got by goaltender Pat Jablonski for his fifth goal of the season. The loss snapped Montreal's four-game winning streak. (AP)</p>
        <p>BRUINS 2, PANTHERS 2: Jody Hull knocked a rebound past Bill Ranford at 11:15  of the third period and John Vanbiesbrouck stopped four Boston shots in overtime as the Bruins and Florida played to a tie. (AP)</p>
        <p>CAPITALS 4, SENATORS 2: Dale Hunter scored the game-winner midway through the third period as Washington overcame a two-goal deficit to beat host Ottawa. (AP)</p>
        <p>BLUES 2, CANUCKS 2: Alexander Mogilny had one apparent goal waved off in the  final minute of regulation, then scored with 7.9 seconds to go to give Vancouver a tie in St. Louis. (AP)</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
