<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sports of The Times;This League Is Chock Full Of Griffeys</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827177"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">VECSEY, GEORGE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Columns/George Vecsey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E7DA1739F931A35751C0A960958260" item-length="824" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sports of The Times;This League Is Chock Full Of Griffeys</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GEORGE VECSEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VECSEY, GEORGE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LAST Sunday, the National Basketball Association gave all but two teams the day off, so the players could join the rest of the nation in hunkering down with the snacks and the drinks and the betting slips and the blaring commercials and  the yammering commentators and the lugs in helmets.</p>
        <p>Basketball can afford to be magnanimous, to darken its arenas for one Sunday  night. This is basketball's time now, almost until the Fourth of July.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LAST Sunday, the National Basketball Association gave all but two teams the day off, so the players could join the rest of the nation in hunkering down with the snacks and the drinks and the betting slips and the blaring commercials and  the yammering commentators and the lugs in helmets.</p>
        <p>Basketball can afford to be magnanimous, to darken its arenas for one Sunday  night. This is basketball's time now, almost until the Fourth of July.</p>
        <p>If it isn't Michael, it's Magic. And sometimes it's both of them, like tonight, on television.</p>
        <p>This league sends out superstars the way pizza chains send out delivery vans, careening around corners, tires squealing, bright lights flashing, the whiff of  pungent sauce in the air. If it isn't Sir Charles, it's Reggie. If it isn't Riley, it's Hakeem.</p>
        <p>The seven-league boots of Shaquille O'Neal came thundering into town last night, with Madison Square Garden still quivering from Michael Jordan and the Bulls stomping on the Knicks a week ago. "We didn't figure we were going to get  whupped," Patrick Ewing said, after standing in the way of destiny.</p>
        <p>This time the Knicks stopped the visiting superstars, 110-102, in a game of hard-earned shots and rugged defense. The Magic have won all 22 games at home but lost 13 of 22 road games.</p>
        <p>There was an easy way to tell that Shaq and Penny and Horace and Dennis and Nick were not amused: Showers. Long showers. Privacy. Lots of privacy.</p>
        <p>"We had an opportunity to win," said Dennis Scott, when he was the first to emerge from the sanctuary of the back room. "We cut it to 5 points, and we didn't get closer. At home, if we cut it to 5, we feel we can win."</p>
        <p>The Magic is supposed to become the super team one of these years, but Don Nelson switches the defense around, and Anthony Mason leans his bulky frame into O'Neal, who gets in foul trouble and finishes with only 18 points and 11 rebounds.</p>
        <p>Being a superstar does not guarantee dominance in this league. Even in this expansion era -- Vancouver and Toronto are in, can Barcelona and Tokyo be far behind? -- almost every team in this league has a player you just might pay to watch.</p>
        <p>The Garden was sold out last night for the 152d consecutive time. And the N.B.A. keeps beaming dynamic stars out on the air waves, night after night after night.</p>
        <p>Just look at the two legitimate human dramas in the last 12 months: Michael Jordan coming back from baseball fantasy camp and Magic Johnson coming back four years after learning he is H.I.V.-positive.</p>
        <p>What a wonderful quest for this proud star (I never said "hero") to try to excel once again, while there is still time. This is the reason people love sports, to watch people try to overcome barriers of gravity and time and space and weight and age and other people's elbows, to say nothing of a fatal virus.</p>
        <p>Basketball has taken over. I realized that while waiting two weeks for the Super Bowl to be over. I remembered how I used to get through the last two weeks of January -- by dreaming of Chavez Ravine. During this very week, the wire services would run a photograph of Steve Garvey stretching or Dusty Baker running laps at informal workouts. Winter was halfway over; spring training was  coming up; we would survive.</p>
        <p>Basketball? It was raffish and goofy and artistic, but would the league survive? During one championship round between the Celtics and the Lakers, I was thrilled to drive up the hill to watch two young pitchers headed for the Baseball Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>Fernando Valenzuela against Doc Gooden meant more to me than Magic Johnson and Larry Bird. Whatever happened to Fernando and Doc? Whatever happened to baseball stars?</p>
        <p>The most captivating baseball player I have seen in recent years is Ken Griffey Jr., who just signed a four-year, $34 million extension that will keep him (and the Mariners) in Seattle until the millennium.</p>
        <p>Griffey lights up even gloomy domes with his smile, his power, his speed and  his alertness. His signing appears to have made an entire football team extraneous. The Seahawks were talking yesterday about moving from the stodgy Kingdome to the outdated Rose Bowl in Pasadena, Calif., but Seattle will survive.</p>
        <p>In the N.B.A., the stars show up in bunches. The Orlando Magic sent four or five Griffeys into the Garden last night. And the Knicks won. No wonder the N.B.A. can rest on Super Bowl Sunday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
