<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Judge's Reasoning in Drug Case Was Sound</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="827210"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DRUG ABUSE AND TRAFFIC</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAER, HAROLD JR (JUDGE)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENTHAL, A M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Letter</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Letters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C00E4DA1739F931A35751C0A960958260" item-length="444" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Judge's Reasoning in Drug Case Was Sound</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re "Contempt in Court" (column, Jan. 30): A. M. Rosenthal, in his assault on  Judge Harold Baer Jr. for suppressing evidence in a Federal narcotics case, reserves his harshest criticism for the judge's observation that residents of Washington Heights in upper Manhattan tend to regard police as "corrupt, abusive and violent" and that under the circumstances "had the men not run when the cops began to stare at them it would have been unusual."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>To the Editor:</p>
        <p>Re "Contempt in Court" (column, Jan. 30): A. M. Rosenthal, in his assault on  Judge Harold Baer Jr. for suppressing evidence in a Federal narcotics case, reserves his harshest criticism for the judge's observation that residents of Washington Heights in upper Manhattan tend to regard police as "corrupt, abusive and violent" and that under the circumstances "had the men not run when the cops began to stare at them it would have been unusual."</p>
        <p>I am a white lawyer who visited Washington Heights last year when I represented someone accused in a homicide case. My experiences provide overwhelming evidence to support Judge Baer's observations.</p>
        <p>Since I was looking to find and talk to young men, contemporaries of my client, I often agreed to meet on streetcorners or in front of buildings, where  I hoped they would feel they could speak freely. Invariably, when I arrived, my  potential witnesses were not where they promised to be.</p>
        <p>When I would catch up with them, I would be told that they had dispersed at police direction.</p>
        <p>Naturally, I was initially incredulous. After all, witnesses from most neighborhoods find excuses to avoid involvement with the justice system, and I had heard plenty of excuses over the years.</p>
        <p>Finally, on one bright sunny Saturday morning in the middle of the trial, my  incredulity was put to rest. Accompanied by my co-counsel, a man of Cuban ancestry, I met with my client's three dark-skinned Dominican brothers on the sidewalk in front of their apartment building.</p>
        <p>Sitting on a fire hydrant, surrounded by the four standing men, I was perhaps hidden from view. A police patrol car pulled up alongside and, without inquiry,  the driver ordered us to leave the area. We ignored his unauthorized order.</p>
        <p>I explained to the men that we had every right to stand and converse on the street. They looked skeptical, but I was a lawyer and they didn't want to show disrespect by disagreeing. The officer next opened his car door, nightstick gripped tightly in his fist. Before he could take more persuasive action, he apparently noticed my suit and retreated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Rosenthal endorses the suggestion that Judge Baer should be "sentenced to live a year in Washington Heights, to see if he would run away when he saw police." Perhaps it is Mr. Rosenthal who would benefit most by a year's residency on Amsterdam Avenue.</p>
        <p>PETER J. NEUFELD New York, Jan. 31, 1996</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
