<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S., Pushing Its Route For Pipeline, Aids Turkey</title>
    <meta content="Y22CAS$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1055964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Offshore Exploration and Installations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Turkey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Caspian Sea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Azerbaijan</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Baku (Azerbaijan)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Ceyhan (Turkey)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Georgia (Georgian Republic)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Mediterranean Sea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Black Sea</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Supsa (Georgia)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kinzer, Stephen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eizenstat, Stuart E (Under Sec)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Azerbaijan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Georgia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Turkey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Azerbaijan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Georgia (Georgian Republic)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Aid</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Oil (Petroleum) and Gasoline</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reserves (Natural Resources)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pipelines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE1DA133DF931A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="787" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S., Pushing Its Route For Pipeline, Aids Turkey</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEPHEN KINZER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kinzer, Stephen</byline>
      <dateline>ISTANBUL, Turkey, Oct. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Clinton Administration, increasing pressure on oil companies to build pipeline for Caspian Sea oil that suits American interests, says it will give Turkey $823,000 to help plan its part of line; favors route from Baku, Azerbaijan, across Turkey to Mediterranean port of Ceyhan, holding it would help stabilize region; oil companies believe pipeline across route would be too costly to build soon; favor shorter route, to Supsa, Georgia, on Black Sea; Under State Sec Stuart E Eizenstat, one of several top Administration officials traveling to push for route, ends three days of meetings with Turkish officials (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Clinton Administration, increasing the pressure on oil companies to build a pipeline for Caspian Sea oil that suits American interests, said today that it would give Turkey $823,000 to help plan its part of the line.</p>
        <p>As oil company executives appear close to making a recommendation on a pipeline route, the United States is making a major push for a plan that would send oil across Turkey to the Mediterranean port of Ceyhan. Administration officials say a pipeline along this route would help stabilize the region and serve long-term United States interests.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Clinton Administration, increasing the pressure on oil companies to build a pipeline for Caspian Sea oil that suits American interests, said today that it would give Turkey $823,000 to help plan its part of the line.</p>
        <p>As oil company executives appear close to making a recommendation on a pipeline route, the United States is making a major push for a plan that would send oil across Turkey to the Mediterranean port of Ceyhan. Administration officials say a pipeline along this route would help stabilize the region and serve long-term United States interests.</p>
        <p>''Over all, Baku-Ceyhan offers the best option from environmental, economic and strategic standpoints,'' said Under Secretary of State Stuart E. Eizenstat. ''No one should underestimate our determination to make Baku-Ceyhan a reality.''</p>
        <p>Oil companies favor the American-backed pipeline route but believe that its projected cost of $2.8 billion makes it too costly to build anytime soon. Indeed, some executives believe that the project could cost $4 billion or more. Mr. Eizenstat's announcements were apparently part of a last-minute campaign to make it more economical.</p>
        <p>''The idea is to give Turkey financial help to lay the groundwork for this project,'' said an official in Ankara who was briefed on this week's meetings. ''It's to help Turkey prepare a financial package, figure out how to line up financing and firm up details of the route.''</p>
        <p>Executives of oil companies active in the Caspian region said today that they still favor a shorter pipeline route running from Baku, the capital of oil-rich Azerbaijan, to the Georgian port of Supsa on the Black Sea.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eizenstat concluded three days of meetings with Turkish officials today. He said that the Trade and Development Agency, which supports American business projects abroad, would provide the money to Turkey.</p>
        <p>He is one of several top Administration officials who are traveling to push for the Baku-Ceyhan route. Jan Kalicki, a senior Commerce Department envoy, was in Azerbaijan last weekend. President Clinton's special envoy to the Caspian region, Richard Morningstar, and the head of the Trade and Development Agency are due in Istanbul next week.</p>
        <p>The discovery of large amounts of oil and gas under and around the Caspian has attracted dozens of energy companies to what may be the century's last big bonanza. Because the new nations in the region are unstable and wedged into a strategic region between Russia and Iran, they have also become an arena for big-power competition. The decision on where to build an oil export pipeline could have profound geopolitical as well as economic effects.</p>
        <p>Oil companies active in the Caspian, among them Exxon, Pennzoil and BP Amoco, are expected to announce soon which pipeline route they favor. Officially they are making only a recommendation to the Government of Azerbaijan. Since they will pay for the pipeline, however, their recommendation is likely to be decisive.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the oil consortium, Pamela Mounter, said executives hoped to recommend a pipeline route next week. ''Our contract calls for us to make a draft recommendation to the Azerbaijani Government,'' Ms. Mounter said in a telephone interview from Baku. ''The deadline is the end of this month, and we hope to meet that deadline.''</p>
        <p>Asked if the recommendation would be made public, she replied, ''Yes, to the right people.''</p>
        <p>An executive close to the consortium, however, said intense international interest would probably force the companies to make their recommendation fully public.</p>
        <p>''The recommendation is being made to Socar,'' the executive said, referring to Azerbaijan's state-owned oil company. ''They've asked for a delay of a week or two because they're still working on next year's budget and some other matters that have to be discussed at the meeting. It's a legitimate delay, nothing horribly nefarious.''</p>
        <p>Published reports suggesting that the companies will not recommend immediate construction of a pipeline across Turkey have set off waves of protest and denial in several countries.</p>
        <p>''Baku-Ceyhan will definitely be constructed,'' President Suleyman Demirel of Turkey assured anxious Turks. ''It is the safest route and has the backing of the United States.''</p>
        <p>The date originally set for the companies' announcement, Oct. 29, is also the 75th anniversary of the founding of the Turkish Republic.  The Presidents of Azerbaijan and Georgia will be in Turkey for the celebrations, and they are expected to join President Demirel in a statement committing themselves to the Baku-Ceyhan route. Since their Governments will not be putting up the money for the pipeline, however, the statement will be largely symbolic.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
