<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Outlook for Political Dynamics: More of the Same</title>
    <meta content="22CONG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1056001"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mitchell, Alison</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981022T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407E7DF103DF931A15753C1A96E958260" item-length="1124" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Outlook for Political Dynamics: More of the Same</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALISON MITCHELL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mitchell, Alison</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Oct. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Alison Mitchell analysis finds no sign that political stalemate between Pres Clinton and Republican Congress will end in year ahead; says Republicans and Democrats alike are grappling for an agenda for the new millennium and are being fractured by the quest (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>As the 105th Congress cast its final legislative vote today, it stood identified less with any signature bill than with the paralysis of American politics near century's end.</p>
        <p>For it was a year in which much of the partisan energies went into blocking initiatives, not passing them.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>As the 105th Congress cast its final legislative vote today, it stood identified less with any signature bill than with the paralysis of American politics near century's end.</p>
        <p>For it was a year in which much of the partisan energies went into blocking initiatives, not passing them.</p>
        <p>The Republicans stymied the Democrats' drive for regulation of health maintenance organizations, overhaul of campaign finance laws, and anti-tobacco legislation. And President Clinton took such a strong stand against tax cuts in the first year of a new government surplus that even Senate Republicans refused to embrace the tax-cutting fervor of their more ideological brethren in the House.</p>
        <p>In part this represents the trade-offs of a government divided between a Democratic President and a Republican-controlled Congress. But in many ways the stalemate runs far deeper.</p>
        <p>With the cold war gone, and the surplus changing the deficit politics that had defined the two parties for decades, Republicans and Democrats alike have been left with grappling for an agenda for the new millennium. And it is a quest that fractures both parties.</p>
        <p>''There are all these books and articles that have been written about the end of things,'' said Bill Curry, a former domestic policy adviser to President Clinton, ''the end of history, the end of ideology, the end of the business cycle. We're not at the end of ideology but we are at the end of the ideology of these two parties.''</p>
        <p>From the other side of the spectrum, in remarkably similar tones, Representative David M. McIntosh of Indiana, one of the conservative Republican firebrands of the House, said, ''The leaders who took us into the majority, you get the sense they're coming up with stale ideas and are not focused on bringing the next agenda forward.''</p>
        <p>Both parties have been thrown off course not just by the changing times but also by the nation's antipathy to sweeping change in a period of prosperity. Mr. Clinton tried, and failed, to carry out a major overhaul of the nation's system of health care coverage early in his first term, only to see the voters turn over control of Congress to the Republicans.</p>
        <p>Then Speaker Newt Gingrich and his fervent conservatives took their turn and tried to use a Government shutdown in 1995 to make Mr. Clinton accede to the Republican call for sweeping tax cuts and a scaling back of the Great Society programs. But a year later, their standard bearer was unable to capture the Presidency and Mr. Gingrich's House majority fell to 11 seats, one of the most precarious for either party this century.</p>
        <p>''It's a time at which big ideas failed,'' said Andrew Kohut, director of the Pew Research Center for the People and the Press. ''Given those failures and given the fact that this is a time of relative tranquillity, it's hard to get people going on big ideas.''</p>
        <p>The response of the two parties has been a fallback to look-alike agendas and a politics of small gestures that gives neither a broad mandate.</p>
        <p>''The ideal political place to be at the end of this millennium is to have Republican policy and Democratic language,'' said Frank Luntz, a Republican pollster. ''That is the perfect place for the American people.''</p>
        <p>So in 1996 Mr. Clinton embraced the Republican idea of a balanced budget and then added grace notes on education and health care and the environment.</p>
        <p>Going into this election, the Republicans have put forward no new Contract With America but instead are mostly running on the welfare overhaul and a balanced budget pact with a tax cut, which were the achievements of 1996 and 1997. Learning from Mr. Clinton's strategy of co-opting Republican issues, they agreed in the final spending bill of this session to $1.1 billion for new teachers in hopes of neutralizing the traditional Democratic advantage on the education issue.</p>
        <p>Beyond that, sending his majority home to campaign with a final balloon-festooned rally, Mr. Gingrich also took credit for stopping Federal financing of needle-exchange programs for drug addicts. And in almost nostalgic tones, he said Congress had included some money for Ronald Reagan's cold-war-era dream of a Star Wars missile defense system.</p>
        <p>But the final hours of the session put in sharp relief the fractures in the Republican Party that had haunted Congress all year, causing the House and Senate to fail to pass a budget for the first time since 1974 and costing Republicans the large $700 billion tax cut that House leaders proposed in early summer.</p>
        <p>Conservatives took turns denouncing the Republican leadership in the final hours of the session while Mr. Gingrich fired back at his critics on the right, calling them a ''perfectionist caucus'' who lacked maturity. And today, he said the Republican Congress had failed to pass a major election-year tax cut ''because the Senate blinked.''</p>
        <p>Of the issues looming for the next Congress, chief among them is insuring the solvency of the Social Security system for the baby boom generation. Mr. Gingrich and other House Republicans are vowing to push earlier and harder for a large tax cut. Mr. Gingrich said today that ''you can be much bolder'' in the year after an election.</p>
        <p>The Democrats want to try again to regulate health maintenance organizations and overhaul campaign finance laws. And the economic turmoil in Asia and Russia could yet cause serious tremors in the American economy.</p>
        <p>But there is little sign that the political stalemate will change. Most strategists are predicting that the November election will only reinforce the status quo and produce no large shift in the balance of power.</p>
        <p>''People are more or less both content with national conditions and disgusted with national politics,'' Mr. Kohut said. ''So there ain't much going on.''</p>
        <p>The struggle over whether to impeach Mr. Clinton is likely to distract him and consume much of the energy in Congress. It will also tie the President closely to the liberal Democrats who have been his strongest defenders, keeping him from being free to side with the Republican majority.</p>
        <p>Adding to the likely polarization, Republicans may have to find other ways to placate conservative activists if they do not ultimately have the votes to remove Mr. Clinton from office.</p>
        <p>In both parties the true battle for a new agenda is likely to come in the next Presidential race.</p>
        <p>''The big serious political agendas are Presidential agendas,'' said William Kristol, the editor of The Weekly Standard, a conservative journal. ''Clinton's not going to have one in 1999 and the Republican Congress isn't either. The interesting action will be in both parties in 2000.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
