<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="713699"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9406EFDF143AF930A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="606" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>Northrop Grumman will cut its work force by more than 18 percent, or 8,650 jobs, by the end of 1995, as the newly combined company seeks to adapt to a fast-consolidating arms industry. The job cut will be another hard blow to the economies of California and Long Island.  [ Page D1. ]  Few employees of Grumman, which was Long Island's biggest employer for more than five decades, were surprised by the announcement of job cuts.  [ D11. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Companies</p>
        <p>Northrop Grumman will cut its work force by more than 18 percent, or 8,650 jobs, by the end of 1995, as the newly combined company seeks to adapt to a fast-consolidating arms industry. The job cut will be another hard blow to the economies of California and Long Island.  [ Page D1. ]  Few employees of Grumman, which was Long Island's biggest employer for more than five decades, were surprised by the announcement of job cuts.  [ D11. ]</p>
        <p>Walt Disney has been rocked by turmoil since its chairman, Michael D. Eisner, essentially dismissed Jeffrey Katzenberg, the head of Disney's movie studio. Production delays and breakdowns in projects and marketing have plagued the studio since the departure of Mr. Katzenberg. And the public enmity between the two former allies has embarrassed the company.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Disney won its first two local approvals for a plan to build a giant theme park in Virginia celebrating American history.  [ A28. ]</p>
        <p>Paul B. Kazarian accused Borden of treating him unfairly in his takeover overtures. Mr. Kazarian seemed to be laying the groundwork for a suit but said litigation was not his ultimate aim.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Canadian Pacific offered to buy the eastern rail freight operations of its rival, Canadian National Railways, for $1 billion.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>La Quinta Inns plans to open 22 hotels in Mexico, joining other U.S. chains trying to fill out the middle of the Mexican market.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>American Airlines said it would contract out the work of 550 agents at 30 airports in an effort to cut costs.  [ D3. ]</p>
        <p>Compuserve will invest in a spinoff of Novell that provides Internet publishing services to commercial customers.  [ D3. ] General Motors agreed to sell the assets of National Car Rental to an investment group for an undisclosed sum.  [ D3. ] International</p>
        <p>The Clinton Administration sought to increase pressure on Japan as the President warned Japan's Foreign Minister that the United States was prepared to impose trade sanctions if agreements on opening Japanese markets were not reached by Sept. 30.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Japan's Cabinet approved a plan to cut income taxes. Japan had long pledged to cut taxes to stimulate its economy.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>Computer and telecommunications companies are still looking for the on ramp to the information highway. At an annual conference of senior high-tech executives this week, there was little agreement on when and exactly how the technologies of the computer, telephone and television will converge.  [ D1. ] Markets</p>
        <p>Some technology stocks tumbled, dragged down by the closing of a brokerage house, D. Blech, which had been the underwriter for most of the companies. In the broader market, traders sold off stocks in advance of the Federal Reserve's policy-making meeting on Tuesday. The Dow industrials fell 14.47 points.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Treasury prices rose. Investors were heartened after Alan Greenspan, the Fed chief, said economic growth was slowing.  [ D11. ]</p>
        <p>Frozen orange juice futures surged on worries over a drought in Brazil. Crude oil and lumber prices also gained.  [ D14. ]</p>
        <p>The dollar was little changed as dealers kept a cautious watch on trade talks between the United States and Japan.  [ D14. ] Today's Columns</p>
        <p>Just what is Paul B. Kazarian offering Borden? His proposal has more management bromides and a lot fewer numbers than a typical takeover offer. Floyd Norris: Market Place.  [ D4. ]</p>
        <p>Lois/USA plans to go public. Lois, never a quiet voice on Madison Avenue, is one of the few agencies in recent years that have sought to be heard on Wall Street. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D15. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
