<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Now Playing: Disney in Turmoil</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="713695"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REFORM AND REORGANIZATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUSPENSIONS, DISMISSALS AND RESIGNATIONS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DISNEY, WALT, CO</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">EISNER, MICHAEL D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">KATZENBERG, JEFFREY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WEINRAUB, BERNARD</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Reform and Reorganization</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suspensions, Dismissals and Resignations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940923T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D02E3DF143AF930A1575AC0A962958260" item-length="1662" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Now Playing: Disney in Turmoil</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD WEINRAUB with GERALDINE FABRIKANT,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRIKANT, GERALDINE; WEINRAUB, BERNARD</byline>
      <dateline>HOLLYWOOD, Sept. 22</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a decade, Michael D. Eisner and Jeffrey Katzenberg transformed the slumbering Walt Disney Company into an $8.5 billion entertainment giant whose success has seemed magical. Investors surged to the company, and its stock price multiplied. Its top executives were lavishly rewarded. Mr. Eisner, the chairman, earned more than $203 million last year.</p>
        <p>And this year Disney is enjoying the most profitable film ever, "The Lion King"; the top-rated television show, "Home Improvement," and the most successful musical on Broadway, "Beauty and the Beast."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a decade, Michael D. Eisner and Jeffrey Katzenberg transformed the slumbering Walt Disney Company into an $8.5 billion entertainment giant whose success has seemed magical. Investors surged to the company, and its stock price multiplied. Its top executives were lavishly rewarded. Mr. Eisner, the chairman, earned more than $203 million last year.</p>
        <p>And this year Disney is enjoying the most profitable film ever, "The Lion King"; the top-rated television show, "Home Improvement," and the most successful musical on Broadway, "Beauty and the Beast."</p>
        <p>But three weeks ago Mr. Eisner shocked the entertainment industry by denying Mr. Katzenberg's request for a promotion to the No. 2 position at the company and essentially dismissing Mr. Katzenberg, his longtime colleague and ally.</p>
        <p>Now Disney is suffering the consequences.</p>
        <p>Without Mr. Katzenberg, the studio division that was the most profitable in Hollywood and the star performer at Disney in recent years has been nearly paralyzed, according to Disney studio executives and Hollywood producers and agents. And the company has been embarrassed as Mr. Eisner and Mr. Katzenberg have lashed out at each other.</p>
        <p>Entertainment executives in Hollywood and New York are watching Disney as if passing a car wreck, shocked that such a dazzling team could come to such an end.</p>
        <p>Since Mr. Katzenberg's departure, an animated movie in production, "Hunchback of Notre Dame," has been delayed, according to Disney executives. The theater division that Mr. Katzenberg also ran, which is responsible for "Beauty and the Beast," is leaderless. And there is uncertainty about the timing of the show's openings and the shape of future theatrical projects like "Aida" (with music by Elton John).</p>
        <p>Mr. Katzenberg's efforts to sign a superstar, Janet Jackson or Whitney Houston, to record songs for Disney's next animated film, "Pocahontas," due next summer, have been halted. Several Katzenberg projects have been discarded and Disney executives have been told that the company plans to halve the number of films it makes each year.</p>
        <p>One of Disney's newest and most profitable divisions, interactive games, which was also run by Mr. Katzenberg, is now rudderless as the holiday season approaches.</p>
        <p>And the producers of several coming Disney films said the marketing side of the company seemed crippled. Mr. Katzenberg was especially good at using Disney characters in profitable merchandising ventures.</p>
        <p>"It's an incredibly distressed organization," said one top producer with a Disney film set for release. "When someone as powerful as Jeffrey leaves, insecurity in the ranks takes a tremendous toll."</p>
        <p>Even Disney's interest in acquiring the NBC television network from General Electric -- Mr. Eisner is in New York for talks with network officials and others -- has been shadowed by the departure.</p>
        <p>"Losing Katzenberg was like losing an important piece of manpower," said Emanuel Gerard of the investment firm Gerard Klauer Mattison. "If you go out and buy a network at a time when you are restructuring management, it puts a lot of pressure on management."</p>
        <p>Then there was the remarkable animus between two men who were once allies. The anger is so intense that Mr. Katzenberg has been told that he will not be welcome next month at the London premiere of "The Lion King," at which Mr. John, the composer of the score, wanted to have a party for him.</p>
        <p>Animators at the studio who sought to hold a farewell party for Mr. Katzenberg were barred from doing so by Mr. Eisner. Moreover, Mr. Katzenberg has been told to leave his office at the studio as quickly as possible.</p>
        <p>Perhaps most cutting for Mr. Katzenberg, Mr. Eisner has sought to diminish the impact of his role in animation and even taken some credit for the new film "Quiz Show," approved by Mr. Katzenberg.</p>
        <p>(Mr. Eisner has said that he saw a PBS special on the quiz show scandals, and told Mr. Katzenberg to get a movie script on the subject. Actually, Robert Redford, the director, and Barry Levinson and his former partner, Mark Johnson, were largely responsible for the idea for the film.)</p>
        <p>The level of genuine rage now between Mr. Eisner and Mr. Katzenberg hardly diminishes their extraordinary success. Taking over the moribund company with Frank G. Wells in 1984, the men built an empire embracing theme parks, stores, hotels, publishing, sports and, notably, films and television. Except for "Jurassic Park," which was made by Universal Pictures, the highest- grossing films in history are from Disney -- "The Lion King," "Aladdin" and "Beauty and the Beast."</p>
        <p>Revenues climbed to $8.5 billion last year, from $1.45 billion in 1984.  Shares of Disney closed at $40.25 today, down 50 cents on the day, but up from $3 in 1983. (The company's main problem in recent years has been theme parks, notably Euro Disney, near Paris.)</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner oversaw the growth of the whole company, from its theme parks to its stores to its films. Mr. Katzenberg ran the movie side of the company, including animation; was responsible for Disney's Broadway musicals; dominated Disney's successful television production with hits like "Home Improvement," and, perhaps most important, had the sheer force of personality to energize Disney's merchandising worldwide of products spawned by animated films. "The Lion King," for example, is expected to earn $1 billion worldwide, partly because of its merchandising and video success.</p>
        <p>Certainly Mr. Katzenberg's record was flawed. He oversaw dozens of movies in the last two years that were duds. There have been exceptions like "The Joy Luck Club" and "Quiz Show." But other films like "Hocus Pocus" and "Life with Mikey" embarrassed Mr. Eisner.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Mr. Eisner has made it plain that he saw Mr. Katzenberg's efforts to rise within the company as too aggressive. Mr. Eisner believed that the studio chief had made a mistake in not only taking over animation from Roy E. Disney, the vice chairman of the company and nephew of Walt Disney, but brushing him aside. (Mr. Katzenberg's allies say Roy Disney spent long periods on golfing trips in Ireland and was barely visible at the studio.)</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Eisner's dissatisfaction with Mr. Katzenberg's aggressive style is among the roots of their rift. Others include Mr. Eisner's unhappiness with the studio's nonanimated films and the sense that his protege was crowding him.</p>
        <p>Mr. Katzenberg's responsibilities have been divided by Mr. Eisner, who appointed Joe Roth, former chairman of 20th Century Fox, to run the nonanimated movie business. Mr. Roth's mandate is to reduce the number of films to 20 or 25, from 40.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner also promoted Richard Frank, former president of the Walt Disney Studios, to the newly created job of head of television and telecommunications. As for the pivotal job of head of animation, Mr. Eisner has chosen to take charge himself.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner's move involving animation was highly unusual, given his responsibilities as chairman and the fact that he is recovering from heart surgery in July. Except for some weight loss, Mr. Eisner, who is 52, seems vigorous and healthy. But several Disney officials said Mr. Eisner could hardly replicate Mr. Katzenberg's schedule of spending two or three hours a day, five days a week, on animation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner has denied that the departure of Mr. Katzenberg, who is 43, came about because Mr. Eisner viewed Mr. Katzenberg as a threat. Instead, Mr. Eisner has told friends, the growth of the company during the last 10 years required him to decentralize the organization. He began planning to overhaul Disney's structure about two years ago, he has said, and Mr. Katzenberg's days were numbered since then.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner has said that he is taking his model, in part, from William Paley, who successfully ran CBS for 30 years "and kept reinventing it." That means new people, old people taking new jobs, moving people almost in the Japanese style, he has told associates.</p>
        <p>Yet top-level studio executives at Disney said that dividing Mr. Katzenberg's responsibilities had proved far more difficult than Mr. Eisner had expected, and there was great confusion at the studio.</p>
        <p>Privately, the animus between Mr. Eisner and Mr. Katzenberg seems boundless. Both men declined to comment publicly. But Mr. Eisner angrily told a staff meeting last Monday that he was sick of hearing about Mr. Katzenberg.</p>
        <p>"I don't want to hear any more about who is happy and who is unhappy and who is staying and who is leaving," Mr. Eisner told his staff. He added that Mr. Katzenberg would probably run a studio or high-technology entertainment company or "run his deli -- I don't know what he's going to run." The reference was to Dive, the restaurant in Century City, Calif., that Mr. Katzenberg owns with Steven Spielberg.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner has also said that he failed to promote Mr. Katzenberg -- and essentially ousted him -- because the quality of nonanimated films produced by the studio in recent years had been embarrassing.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner also told associates that it was incomprehensible that he could promote Mr. Katzenberg to the No. 2 job at the company -- replacing Mr. Wells, the president and chief operating officer, who died in a helicopter accident in April.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner has gone so far as to say on various occasions that Mr. Katzenberg's lack of a college education and his ownership of the restaurant worked against his promotion to the Wells job. (Mr. Eisner graduated from Denison University in Granville, Ohio, in 1964.)</p>
        <p>Of Mr. Katzenberg's departure, Mr. Frank, who now heads the television and telecommunications divisions, said the feelings at the company were mixed. "There's a little bit of an adrenalin rush for people," he said. "The feeling is, 'Let's go out and do it ourselves now; let's prove what we can do.' "</p>
        <p>But Mr. Frank said he missed Mr. Katzenberg. "There's been a wrenching away," he said. "Frank Wells died. Now Jeffrey's gone. The family's been broken up."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
