<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How He Kept 'Em in Stitches</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="34" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="727791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="COMEDY VIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HUMOR AND WIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BLACKS (IN US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WATKINS, MEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRYOR, RICHARD</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Comedy and Humor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Blacks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9807E2DB1F31F934A15752C1A962958260" item-length="1507" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How He Kept 'Em in Stitches</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mel Watkins;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WATKINS, MEL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT THE HEIGHT OF Richard Pryor's fame in the late 1970's, he was the undisputed king of stand-up comedy. Considered a genius by many, he was recognized for his brilliance even by those who were offended by the content and candor of much of his material. But his near death by fire, his several heart attacks and the gradually disabling effects of multiple sclerosis have almost ended his career as an active comic performer.</p>
        <p>In his absence since the early 80's, some outstanding black comedians have emerged. Eddie Murphy, Whoopi Goldberg and, more recently, Martin Lawrence top the list of those who dominate the field. Others, like Damon and Keenen Ivory Wayans, Sinbad, Marcia Warfield, George Wallace, Robin Harris and the up-and-coming Dave Chappelle and Paul Mooney, have also carved out respectable niches as comedians. And, of course, the legendary and indefatigable Bill Cosby remains a formidable comic presence, largely through his popular television series "The Cosby Show," which is now in syndication.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT THE HEIGHT OF Richard Pryor's fame in the late 1970's, he was the undisputed king of stand-up comedy. Considered a genius by many, he was recognized for his brilliance even by those who were offended by the content and candor of much of his material. But his near death by fire, his several heart attacks and the gradually disabling effects of multiple sclerosis have almost ended his career as an active comic performer.</p>
        <p>In his absence since the early 80's, some outstanding black comedians have emerged. Eddie Murphy, Whoopi Goldberg and, more recently, Martin Lawrence top the list of those who dominate the field. Others, like Damon and Keenen Ivory Wayans, Sinbad, Marcia Warfield, George Wallace, Robin Harris and the up-and-coming Dave Chappelle and Paul Mooney, have also carved out respectable niches as comedians. And, of course, the legendary and indefatigable Bill Cosby remains a formidable comic presence, largely through his popular television series "The Cosby Show," which is now in syndication.</p>
        <p>Mr. Murphy and Ms. Goldberg, however, have successfully moved into acting careers, making stand-up comedy an occasional dalliance for them. With the recent debut of "The Cosby Mysteries," even Mr. Cosby has stepped back from comedy. And while Sinbad, Ms. Warfield, Mr. Wayans, Mr. Wallace and Mr. Chappelle are fine comedians, none as yet have reached the level of accomplishment and box-office appeal that would rank them with the comic elite.</p>
        <p>Even in decline as his 54th birthday approaches, Richard Pryor continues to cast a vast, perhaps inescapable, shadow over black humor and, indeed, the entire comic landscape. Echoes of his voice can be heard in the routines of nearly every black comedian working today; most readily affirm his preeminence. "Pryor started it all," Mr. Wayans, for instance, says. "He made the blueprint for the progressive thinking of black comedians, unlocking the irreverent style."</p>
        <p>The re-release of three of Mr. Pryor's earliest albums this month by Loose Cannon Records not only makes this vintage humor available again but also reasserts the innovative nature of his work and its lasting importance. One of the reissued works, "Craps (After Hours)," which was originally recorded live at the Redd Foxx Club in Hollywood in 1971, marked a decisive turn in Mr. Pryor's humor and is among the best examples of his recorded work. The other works being released are "Who Me? I'm Not Him," from 1977, and "Black Ben and the Blacksmith," from 1978.</p>
        <p>"Craps" was recorded four years after Mr. Pryor stormed off the stage at the Aladdin Hotel in Las Vegas, Nev., shouting: "What am I doing here? I'm not going to do it anymore!" For many, that explosive outburst was just another example of Mr. Pryor's antic behavior and brash, unpredictable nature. In fact, it was the desperate expression of a long-simmering frustration that despite his success had plagued him for some time.</p>
        <p>He had moved up from small black clubs and honky-tonks in the Midwest to Greenwich Village clubs like Cafe Wha? In 1964, a year after arriving in New York, he made his first national television appearance on Rudy Vallee's "On Broadway Tonight," doing the kind of nonoffensive humor that freely copied the styles of more successful comics, particularly Bill Cosby.</p>
        <p>"I made a lot of money being Bill Cosby," he later recalled. "But I was hiding my personality. I just wanted to be in show business so bad I didn't care how. It started bothering me later because I was being successful at it. I was being a robot comic . . . repeating the same lines, getting the same laughs for the same jokes. The repetition was killing me."</p>
        <p>After the Aladdin Hotel incident, Mr. Pryor began radically changing the focus of his comedy and, by 1970, he had gone underground to reassess his life and his comic approach. For a year or so he sequestered himself in Berkeley, Calif., where he befriended a coterie of young black writers and intellectuals that included Ishmael Reed, Cecil Brown, Al Young, David Henderson and Claude Brown. He began reading the speeches of Malcolm X, whom he came to regard as "someone who thinks like I do." He also began meticulously observing the behavior and speech of ghetto types like those he had grown up with in his home town, Peoria, Ill. After haunting the hip bars and clubs in the Bay Area, he would return to his apartment to tape his impressions of the people he had seen and to work on his new material.</p>
        <p>When he returned to Los Angeles, his comedy had changed radically. "Richard took on a whole new persona -- his own," Mr. Cosby recalled upon seeing his new act.  "Richard killed the Bill Cosby in his act, made most people hate it. Then he worked on them, doing pure Pryor, and it was the most astonishing metamorphosis I have ever seen. He was magnificent."</p>
        <p>"Craps" was the first album on which Mr. Pryor completely abandoned the whitewashed, generally nonracial material on which his early success was based and fully embraced the hard-edged satire and more profane ghetto voices and observations for which he would eventually become known.</p>
        <p>Despite its early cult following, sales were dismal. But, notwithstanding the resistance and stunned silence he encountered from club owners and most integrated audiences when he first presented comic routines steeped in the language and attitudes of the winos, prostitutes and pimps that he unveiled on "Craps," Mr. Pryor persisted. At the same time, he worked behind the scene as a writer for the Redd Foxx and Flip Wilson television shows. He was also an award-winning co-writer on Lily Tomlin's 1973 television specials and on the 1974 movie "Blazing Saddles."</p>
        <p>When "That Nigger's Crazy" was released in 1974, the number of Mr. Pryor's followers had increased substantially. The album went gold and won the Grammy Award for the best comedy recording of the year. Subsequent albums expanded his popularity, as did minor roles in "Uptown Saturday Night" (1974) and "The Bingo Long Traveling All-Stars" (1976) and his co-starring role in "Silver Streak" (1976). And although "The Richard Pryor Show" (1977) on television lasted less than two months, it is also now considered a classic series that was simply before its time.</p>
        <p>By the time the filmed concert performance "Richard Pryor Live in Concert" was released in 1979, Mr. Pryor was one of Hollywood's most sought after movie stars and was also considered the nation's most creative funny man. The playwright Neil Simon called him "the most brilliant comic in America" and asserted, "There is no one funnier or more perceptive."</p>
        <p>During the course of a decade, Mr. Pryor had moved from being an outcast holed up in a small West Coast college town to gaining near unanimous acclaim as one of the most imaginative comedians to appear on an American stage. Small wonder, then, that nearly every comedian who followed him has been influenced by him and compared with him, mostly invidiously.</p>
        <p>His status, however, is well deserved and is not likely to be diminished in the near future. Although Mr. Pryor may have been surpassed as a pure storyteller by such accomplished humorists as Will Rogers and Mr. Cosby and, by his own admission, never excelled at telling straight-out jokes, he was gifted to excess in practically every other element of comic technique.</p>
        <p>As a mime, Mr. Pryor ranked with Charlie Chaplin and the black Ziegfeld Follies star Bert Williams. He was also a consummate actor and used that ability to enliven the people he portrayed in his character-based humor and to disarm his audience. He didn't simply tell stories; he brought them to life. He drew on both satiric and frivolous aspects of comedy to project a comic presence that combined the social criticism of Dick Gregory and the exuberant playfulness of Flip Wilson.</p>
        <p>HIS EVOCATION AND USE of the blunt cadences of street language allowed him to venture into areas that in the hands of lesser comedians would have and, as much stage humor in the 90's demonstrates, often did become merely obscene. More than any other comedian before or since, he revealed nearly the entire range of what might be called black humor, from its folksy rural origins to its raunchier urban expression.</p>
        <p>Finally, however, Richard Pryor's comedy transcended most traditional notions of performance comedy. As the writer and comedian Steve Allen has observed, "Pryor is much closer to literature than to traditional nightclub or concert comedy." In this he was revolutionary.</p>
        <p>In fact, even more than most black novelists who wrote before the 1970's, he engaged aspects of black life that had been carefully concealed from the mainstream for centuries. He was also the first black stand-up comedian to introduce white characters into his comic routines and to candidly speak to integrated audiences in a manner that honestly reflected how blacks spoke and joked among themselves.</p>
        <p>The reissue of even a few of Mr. Pryor's early comic albums is a cause for celebration. One is tempted to ask why it took this long.  COMEDY VIEW Mel Watkins is the author of "On the Real Side," a history of black humor from slavery to Richard Pryor.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Mel Watkins is the author of "On the Real Side," a history of black humor from slavery to Richard Pryor.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
