<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>New &amp; Noteworthy Paperbacks</title>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="727755"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PAPERBACK BOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOK TRADE</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAEBER, LAUREL</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books/Book Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Book Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19941127T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E4DA1231F934A15752C1A962958260" item-length="920" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>New &amp; Noteworthy Paperbacks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Laurel Graeber</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GRAEBER, LAUREL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SLEEPING BEAUTIES By Susanna Moore. Vintage Contemporaries, $11. This novel, set in Hawaii, traces the difficult maturation of a young girl, Clio, whose struggles to define herself as a woman are complicated by the odd behavior of her mother, her stepmother and her eccentric aunt Emma. The book "expands a body of work that is eloquent and disturbing," Abby Frucht said here last year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SLEEPING BEAUTIES By Susanna Moore. Vintage Contemporaries, $11. This novel, set in Hawaii, traces the difficult maturation of a young girl, Clio, whose struggles to define herself as a woman are complicated by the odd behavior of her mother, her stepmother and her eccentric aunt Emma. The book "expands a body of work that is eloquent and disturbing," Abby Frucht said here last year.</p>
        <p>PRESIDENT KENNEDY: Profile of Power By Richard Reeves. Touchstone/Simon &amp; Schuster, $15. The portrait of J.F.K. offered here is less that of a young knight riding into Camelot than of a naive and secretly ill politician suddenly forced to confront a host of crises, from Castro's and the Soviet Union's machinations to the repression of blacks' civil rights in the South. Last year our reviewer, Douglas Brinkley, called the book "a beautifully written, judicious and disinterested appraisal." The early political career of one of the President's younger brothers is revealed in THE ENEMY WITHIN: The McClellan Committee's Crusade Against Jimmy Hoffa and Corrupt Labor Unions, by Robert F. Kennedy (Da Capo, $14.95). Now restored to print, this personal account describes the workings of both the Senate Select Committee on Improper Activities in the Labor or Management Field -- to which Robert Kennedy was chief counsel from 1957 to 1959 -- and the unions it investigated. "It is an exciting, valuable and honest book," J. A. Loftus said here in 1960.  HOTEL PASTIS: A Novel of Provence By Peter Mayle. Vintage, $12. A bored, frustrated and recently divorced advertising executive leaves gloomy London for the pleasures -- and, as it turns out, perils -- of life in a rural village in southern France. Last year our reviewer, Eric Kraft, found this tale of bucolic innkeeping "delightful, amusing and appealing." A love affair with the French language is at the heart of FRENCH LESSONS: A Memoir, by Alice Kaplan (University of Chicago, $9.95), which describes how this American author helped gain control of her adolescent emotional life by acquiring mastery of a foreign tongue. The book demonstrates an "insistent probing into the complex connection between language and self," Angeline Goreau said here last year. There is a homage to French wine in PULIGNY-MONTRACHET: Journal of a Village in Burgundy, by Simon Loftus (Owl/ Holt, $14.95), a British merchant's story of the vineyards of a small town and the people who have made its chief product famous. Last year our reviewer, Alida Becker, enjoyed the "quirks of human character" it reveals. Another Londoner leaves for the Continent in A WALK ACROSS FRANCE, by Miles Morland (Fawcett Columbine, $10). Originally published as "Miles Away," this memoir recounts the trek the author and his wife made through the foothills of the Pyrenees -- from sea to sea -- in 1989. Readers "may be amused by this journey," Francine Prose said here last year.  MORE THAN ALLIES By Sandra Scofield. Plume/Penguin, $9.95. The conflicting claims of marital love and personal independence are explored in this novel, which focuses on two Oregon mothers who can't decide whether to follow their husbands to Texas. Last year our reviewer, Wendy Martin, said the author "refuses to trivialize or sentimentalize domesticity."  EVELYN WAUGH: The Later Years, 1939-1966 By Martin Stannard. Norton, $15.95. This is the second volume in the biography of an author who eschewed the modern world, favoring an old-fashioned aristocratic style and the strictness of the Roman Catholic Church before Vatican II. "Minute attention to detail, perseverance, diligence Mr. Stannard certainly has," Penelope Fitzgerald said here in 1992.  BODY &amp; SOUL By Frank Conroy. Island/Dell, $5.99. Claude Rawlings endures poverty and bleakness growing up in the Manhattan of the 1950's and 60's, but finds solace in a rising career as a pianist and composer. Last year our reviewer, David Plante, found this novel "a legitimate and moving piece of Americana."  AN EVIL CRADLING By Brian Keenan. Penguin, $10.95. In 1986 the author, a teacher, was kidnapped by Islamic fundamentalists in Beirut. This memoir describes how he drew upon his love of poetry, his observant powers and his stubborn Irish character to survive four and a half years as a hostage. It is "beautifully and movingly written," Eugene Kennedy said here last year.  THE LATE MAN By James Preston Girard. Onyx, $5.99. Preoccupations with their own failed marriages lead a police detective and a reporter to become obsessed with finding a serial killer who strangles women. Last year our reviewer, Marilyn Stasio, said the author has created a "mesmerizing novel" that elevates "a sordid crime story into a powerful existential drama."  JOE THE ENGINEER By Chuck Wachtel. Penguin, $10.95. Working-class Queens is the setting for this author's first novel, which focuses on the difficult marriage of a meter reader who has given up his early ambitions and a waitress who refuses to renounce hers. It offers a "fresh, realistic" look at "comparatively unfamiliar social territory," Julian Moynahan said here in 1983.  MRS. DE WINTER By Susan Hill. Avon, $6.50. For readers who want to go to Manderley yet again, this sequel to Daphne du Maurier's "Rebecca" re-creates the original's Cornish scene and characters without delivering the same suspense, our reviewer, Rachel Billington, said last year. But Ms. Hill has given her novel "a psychologically appropriate and dramatic end," she added. LAUREL GRAEBER</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
