<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Convergence of Views in Israel</title>
    <meta content="29WED1" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="905188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Middle East</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Hebron (West Bank)</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970129T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E0D61E3AF93AA15752C0A961958260" item-length="539" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Convergence of Views in Israel</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial contends that something new and important has emerged in Israel in recent weeks--makings of consensus on peacemaking with Palestinians; maintains that one clear sign came in decisive parliamentary vote supporting Hebron agreement; holds that another is set of guidelines for final peace settlement jointly endorsed by number of leaders of Labor and Likud parties (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Something new and important has emerged in Israel in recent weeks -- the makings of a consensus on peacemaking with the Palestinians. One clear sign came in the decisive 87-to-17 parliamentary vote supporting the Hebron agreement two weeks ago. Another is the set of guidelines for a final peace settlement jointly endorsed by a number of leaders of both the Labor and Likud parties.</p>
        <p>Less than a year ago, Israeli society was sharply divided. A Labor-led Government was ready to push ahead toward a final territorial settlement that would have conceded most of the occupied Gaza Strip and West Bank, outside Jerusalem, to the Palestinians. The Likud-led opposition was opposed to the initial round of Israeli troop withdrawals and remained determined to keep most of the West Bank under permanent Israeli control.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Something new and important has emerged in Israel in recent weeks -- the makings of a consensus on peacemaking with the Palestinians. One clear sign came in the decisive 87-to-17 parliamentary vote supporting the Hebron agreement two weeks ago. Another is the set of guidelines for a final peace settlement jointly endorsed by a number of leaders of both the Labor and Likud parties.</p>
        <p>Less than a year ago, Israeli society was sharply divided. A Labor-led Government was ready to push ahead toward a final territorial settlement that would have conceded most of the occupied Gaza Strip and West Bank, outside Jerusalem, to the Palestinians. The Likud-led opposition was opposed to the initial round of Israeli troop withdrawals and remained determined to keep most of the West Bank under permanent Israeli control.</p>
        <p>But seven months in power has shown the Likud mainstream, including Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, that a strong majority of Israelis believe in trading Palestinian-inhabited territory for a secure peace. Much of Labor, meanwhile, including some of the party's most prominent doves, now understands that without securing a consensus for peace there can be little prospect for successful negotiations on the critical issues that remain. These include the future of Jerusalem, Jewish settlements, security arrangements and the possibility of Palestinian statehood.</p>
        <p>The joint peace guidelines announced on Sunday are based on three central principles. Palestinians should be able to establish their own self-governing ''political entity.'' Israel should retain the right and ability to defend itself, including special security provisions in the Jordan Valley. Finally, no Jewish settlements should be forcibly uprooted, although some outlying communities may be surrounded by Palestinian-ruled territory.</p>
        <p>The leaders also agreed that Jerusalem must remain united under Israeli sovereignty, but that a Palestinian administrative capital might be established in the suburbs and special status provided for the city's Muslim and Christian holy places. Participants failed to reach a consensus on other key details, for example, whether the Palestinian ''political entity'' should be called a state.</p>
        <p>For the Likud participants, the guidelines represent the first explicit acceptance of eventual territorial partition. For those on the Labor side, the biggest step involves recognizing the permanence of settlements. There was no Palestinian participation in drafting the guidelines. But some of the provisions on Jerusalem reflect ideas informally worked out between Israeli and Palestinian negotiators when the Labor Government was in power.</p>
        <p>The negotiating guidelines are not binding on either Labor or Likud. But the proposals, and the process that produced them, make it more likely that Israel can be united as it addresses the emotional issues deferred to the final round of peace talks. Setbacks to Mideast peacekeeping can come at any moment. But so can surprising advances. Few have been as important as the growing convergence of Labor's and Likud's positions on peace.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
