<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At Crusade, Spirit Meets Science in the Altar Call</title>
    <meta content="25CRUS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/06/25/nyregion/25crusade.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1682841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Queens (NYC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Graham, Billy</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050625T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B01E3D7163AF936A15755C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1143" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At Crusade, Spirit Meets Science in the Altar Call</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">At Crusade, Spirit Meets Science in the Altar Call</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDY NEWMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is, to many minds, the cornerstone of the Christian religious experience. For millions of people, it is a defining moment in their lives.</p>
        <p>It is the altar call, the moment at the end of an evangelical Protestant church service -- or a revival, or a stadium-size rally -- when the minister urges audience members to step forward, make a public decision to accept Jesus Christ as their savior and be born anew.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Billy Graham, who at 86 may be conducting his final crusade, is almost certainly the champion of the altar call.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It is, to many minds, the cornerstone of the Christian religious experience. For millions of people, it is a defining moment in their lives.</p>
        <p>It is the altar call, the moment at the end of an evangelical Protestant church service -- or a revival, or a stadium-size rally -- when the minister urges audience members to step forward, make a public decision to accept Jesus Christ as their savior and be born anew.</p>
        <p>The act of answering the altar call is understood to be spontaneous, personal and deeply felt.</p>
        <p>But the structure of the event, like that of so many religious rituals and ceremonies, is also carefully choreographed and intensely overseen. And perhaps nowhere more so than at a Billy Graham Crusade like the one that began last night at Flushing Meadows-Corona Park in Queens.</p>
        <p>Indeed, when Mr. Graham issues his call and the candidates, known in the Graham organization's parlance as inquirers, begin moving down the aisles, their decision to stand up and start walking is just the beginning.</p>
        <p>The inquirer is met at the foot of the stage by a trained volunteer counselor, chosen on the spot from a pool of thousands to match the inquirer's sex and approximate age. The counselor offers a warm welcome, a copy of the Gospel of John and a quick tutorial in how to receive Christ. (Step 1: Confess your sins. Step 2: Surrender your life to God's control. Step 3: Ask for his strength daily to stay on God's pathway.)</p>
        <p>The inquirer also fills out a ''commitment card,'' and the counselor takes down name, address and phone number. Within minutes, this information is relayed to the crusade's on-site data-processing team, armed with computers and phone books. Within hours, a pastor from one of the hundreds of local churches participating in the crusade is sent the inquirer's contact information and urged to follow up immediately. Within two days, the counselor calls the inquirer to follow-up. A successful crusade, said Art Bailey, the New York campaign's director, requires lightning action.</p>
        <p>''We feel that the nearer that person is to their decision, the better,'' he said. ''As that decision cools, there's more likelihood of something interfering.''</p>
        <p>Over 58 years and 416 crusades -- the 417th started last night -- Mr. Graham and his associates have honed altar-call management to a science, with every interaction intended to maximize the new sheep's likelihood and desire to stay in the flock.</p>
        <p>''It's like a tent revival,'' Mr. Bailey said, ''but this is a little more pointed, it's a great deal more organized, the involvement is a little more stipulated, and the fruit is greater.''</p>
        <p>A lot greater. According to the Graham organization, 3,198,522 people have come forward and pledged their lives to Jesus at Billy Graham crusades. That's about equal to the entire population of Oregon. Or Armenia. Or Yokohama, Japan. While no reliable statistics are kept on this sort of thing, Mr. Graham, who at 86 may be conducting his final crusade, is almost certainly the champion of the altar call.</p>
        <p>Nor does the Graham organization's involvement stop after the crusade leaves town. A Graham volunteer calls the inquirer three weeks later to check up. If the local church has not contacted the inquirer within eight weeks, the Graham organization sends out what it diplomatically calls a Blessed Assurance Letter.</p>
        <p>''It tells them, 'If we don't hear from you by Thursday at noon, we're going to send this person to another church,''' said Gary Cobb, the Graham organization's vice president for training.</p>
        <p>Some people have compared this process to closing a sales deal. Mr. Bailey, understandably, prefers a different analogy.</p>
        <p>''It's the same as a child,'' he said. ''As soon as a child is born, it is put immediately into its mother's arms. It needs care to survive from the first moment. A spiritual baby needs the same care.''</p>
        <p>What the inquirer does in the months and years to follow has not been well studied. In 1979, a sociology professor at Vanderbilt University contacted 189 people who had made commitments at a Graham crusade in Seattle three years earlier. Eighty-three percent of them said that the experience had had a positive or very positive effect on their lives, while 15 percent said it had had no effect and 3 percent noted a negative or very negative effect.</p>
        <p>But the survey was paid for by the Graham organization itself, and the professor, Glenn Firebaugh, now at Pennsylvania State University, said that he recalled that the letters to the inquirers were sent out on a Graham letterhead.</p>
        <p>According to an authorized biography of Mr. Graham, ''A Prophet With Honor,'' by William Martin, an internal study conducted after the 1957 Madison Square Garden crusade found that a high proportion of inquirers were already members of a church or at least a denomination.</p>
        <p>But the Billy Graham Evangelical Association does not discriminate against experienced Christians. Those already firm in their faith become better, more active Christians by coming forward, Graham officials said. Any reason to come forward is a good one, said Elizabeth Rodriguez, a counselor.</p>
        <p>''We need to find out, are they coming to accept the Lord, or to look for assurance, or do they feel something in their heart and they want to know more?'' she said just before last night's service began.</p>
        <p>Like most of the counselors, Ms. Rodriguez, 45, a prekindergarten teacher at a Christian school and a resident of the Bronx, had never worked a Graham crusade before. But she said she was ready.</p>
        <p>She had completed the four-session training in Christian Life and Witness. She had signed a pledge ''not to advocate a particular doctrine beyond Jesus Christ as Lord and Savior or proselytize for my particular denomination or church.'' She had her gum and her Kleenex.</p>
        <p>''They have made it so simple for us,'' she said. ''Everyone's on the same page.''</p>
        <p>Besides, Ms. Rodriguez said, though the responsibility placed upon her was great, it is not as if she were being asked to work miracles. Answering the altar call may take only a moment, she said, but finding peace through Christ is the work of a lifetime.</p>
        <p>''A lot of people are looking for instant magic,'' she said. ''We have to tell them they have to wait.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
