<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Public &amp; Private; Wounded in Battle</title>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="508153"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">QUINDLEN, ANNA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Op-Ed/Contributors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920216T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE6D71130F935A25751C0A964958260" item-length="730" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Public &amp; Private; Wounded in Battle</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA QUINDLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">QUINDLEN, ANNA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When he looks back on the Presidential campaign of 1992, which he may understandably be disinclined to do, Bill Clinton could well be amazed at how much he did for America while getting less than nothing in return.</p>
        <p>Because of Governor Clinton we have had a national debate about the effect of private life on public matters, about the relationship between marriage vows and integrity. We have plumbed our antipathy toward the press and the press's antipathy toward itself. And we have wondered who decides someone is a front-runner, and whether that is second cousin to the kiss of death.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When he looks back on the Presidential campaign of 1992, which he may understandably be disinclined to do, Bill Clinton could well be amazed at how much he did for America while getting less than nothing in return.</p>
        <p>Because of Governor Clinton we have had a national debate about the effect of private life on public matters, about the relationship between marriage vows and integrity. We have plumbed our antipathy toward the press and the press's antipathy toward itself. And we have wondered who decides someone is a front-runner, and whether that is second cousin to the kiss of death.</p>
        <p>We have questioned the question of electability, and what it says about us if we can acknowledge that some candidates are good on the issues but somehow not quite right because they cannot punch up the applause buttons in a speech or grin convincingly.</p>
        <p>America is a nation having a massive identity crisis. Without the Soviet Union to play yin to our yang -- oh, how strange it is to see those Olympic athletes called the Unified Team, as though there simply had not been time to think up a real name -- we have resorted to bickering with the Japanese to delineate who we are not. Who we are, what we care about and what we're made of are more troubling questions, and we are working some of them out on Bill Clinton's back.</p>
        <p>Last week we read the letter the Governor wrote when he was 23 to the officer overseeing R.O.T.C. at the University of Arkansas, a colonel from whom Mr. Clinton had secured a draft deferment by promising to join both the law school and the corps, although he did neither. He was attempting to sit out a war "I opposed and despised with a depth of feeling I had reserved solely for racism in America before Vietnam."</p>
        <p>It is an intelligent and eloquent letter, and it has made admirers of some who were not so sure of Mr. Clinton before. I would have been proud to have raised a child capable of writing it. It describes my own belief: that the war was a senseless waste. I still recall the day when, as a summer copy clerk at a small daily newspaper, I haunted the AP wire machine, watching as my boyfriend's birthday turned up number 365 in the draft lottery. Relief was sweet and tangy as a lemon drop.</p>
        <p>But this is a country populated partly by people who were proud to see their sons go and by sons now grown who are proud to have served.  They remember the boys with student deferments, the boys in the National Guard, the boys who signed up for R.O.T.C. in the hopes of doing what Mr. Clinton describes in his letter as "saving me from the draft."And they do not necessarily remember them fondly, particularly if the names of their children and friends are inscribed on that great dark wall in Washington.</p>
        <p>Some may find the timing of Mr. Clinton's agonizings convenient; he came clean to the colonel about his feelings just two days after he was assigned a lottery number certain to keep him from being called. And the R.O.T.C. deferment, which he eventually gave up, covered the period when he was most likely to be drafted, although the Governor rejects any notion that he knew that at the time.</p>
        <p>In his letter Mr. Clinton writes, with calculation rare in one so young and ambitions unthinkable to many coming of age in the 60's, that he wants "to maintain my political viability." Even then he was a pragmatist. We accept that our Presidents should be pragmatic. But in campaigns, we do not like to be reminded of it. We look for principles, perhaps even perfection.</p>
        <p>No one will ever again accuse Bill Clinton of being perfect, although it seems like the only thing he hasn't been accused of. Instead it's turned out he's like us. He's like so many who hated the war, who didn't want to serve, who looked around to find ways to avoid it. He's like so many who've had trouble in their marriages and a roving eye. He's like so many who've grabbed for the gold ring and fallen off the carousel horse.</p>
        <p>Except that he's done all those things in public and perhaps in the process watched the dreams he was dreaming even all those years ago be destroyed. He says that we've got to get back to the issues. Instead we are plumbing our ethos, perhaps the one issue most worth exploring. And we are doing it, in part, on Bill Clinton's back. Maybe it is only now, 23 years later, that Bill Clinton will be wounded in the service of his country.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
