<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pearson Receives U.S. Approval To Buy Simon &amp; Schuster Unit</title>
    <meta content="Y24PEAR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1064659"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Simon &amp; Schuster Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Pearson Plc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hicks Muse Tate &amp; Furst Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Justice Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Carvajal, Doreen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Antitrust Actions and Laws</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404E6D61E30F937A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="451" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pearson Receives U.S. Approval To Buy Simon &amp; Schuster Unit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DOREEN CARVAJAL</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Carvajal, Doreen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pearson PLC says it has received Justice Department approval of its $4.6 billion purchase of education unit of Simon &amp; Schuster, but it is moving forward without major investor, Hicks, Muse, Tate &amp; Furst, which backed out of its part of $600 million deal (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Pearson P.L.C., the British media conglomerate, announced yesterday that it had received Federal approval of its $4.6 billion purchase of the education unit of Simon &amp; Schuster, but it is moving forward without a major investor, Hicks, Muse, Tate &amp; Furst, which backed out of its part of the deal to buy the reference and business publishing divisions for $860 million in cash.</p>
        <p>Each company gave a slightly different version of why it was not able to conclude the agreement. Pearson said that Hicks, Muse, the buyout firm based in Dallas, had sought to renegotiate the ''price, financing and timing agreed in the contract.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Pearson P.L.C., the British media conglomerate, announced yesterday that it had received Federal approval of its $4.6 billion purchase of the education unit of Simon &amp; Schuster, but it is moving forward without a major investor, Hicks, Muse, Tate &amp; Furst, which backed out of its part of the deal to buy the reference and business publishing divisions for $860 million in cash.</p>
        <p>Each company gave a slightly different version of why it was not able to conclude the agreement. Pearson said that Hicks, Muse, the buyout firm based in Dallas, had sought to renegotiate the ''price, financing and timing agreed in the contract.''</p>
        <p>However, Hicks, Muse issued a one-page statement from London saying, ''Our ability to finance the transaction has never been at issue.''  The company then added that the critical point was that their own due-diligence research indicated that the reference and professional divisions had achieved results ''that were not in line with what had previously been projected.''</p>
        <p>Shona Prendergast, a spokeswoman for Hicks, Muse, declined to be more specific about the company's concerns about results, but she stressed that ''the figures didn't match up.'' After several weeks of trying to renegotiate the price, she said, Hicks, Muse decided to withdraw.</p>
        <p>A Pearson executive, who spoke on the condition of anonymity, insisted that the negotiations did, in fact, involve ''how much they paid, how they paid and when they paid.''</p>
        <p>Hicks, Muse had planned to buy the divisions that included Macmillan's computer, general and library reference programs. Pearson will now merge the computer publishing business into its technology publishing group. The library reference and business publishing operations will join the education unit, although a person involved in the deal said that other companies had expressed interest in buying them.</p>
        <p>The antitrust review of the deal by the Department of Justice had lingered for several months longer than Pearson executives had originally expected, with the company undergoing a more intensive analysis known as a second-level review.</p>
        <p>To gain Federal approval, Pearson has to sell its elementary science program along with 55 titles that gave the division too much concentration in the market. Pearson intends to sell off various titles involving engineering, biological science, economics and teacher education. Together the elementary program and the titles produced more than $35 million in annual revenue.</p>
        <p>The sale of Simon &amp; Schuster's education division is expected to be finished by Friday. After the announcement, Pearson's chief executive, Marjorie Scardino, said, ''The immediate task is to make the most of these great businesses so that we can create the value and deliver the earnings we have promised.''</p>
        <p>Simon &amp; Schuster is a subsidiary of Viacom Inc.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
