<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Union's Problems Don't Taint the Mayor</title>
    <meta content="24MAYO$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1064781"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">District Council 37</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Barry, Dan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Employees</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981124T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505E1D81F30F937A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="970" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Union's Problems Don't Taint the Mayor</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAN BARRY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Barry, Dan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>News analysis contends that criminal and internal investigations into widespread corruption in District Council 37, city's largest municipal union, will have no impact on Mayor Rudolph Giuliani despite his perception of being friend to organized labor (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>There was that campaign television commercial in 1997 that depicted a prominent member of District Council 37 embracing the candidate, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. There was the endorsement of Mr. Giuliani's re-election that same year by the council's top official. Above all, there was the council's ratification of a city contract with a two-year pay freeze in 1996 that turned out to be a mayoral coup.</p>
        <p>For several years now, Mr. Giuliani has enjoyed the perception that he had forged close ties to the leadership of District Council 37, the city's largest municipal union with 120,000 members. That impression served him on several levels, including its counterintuitive nature: a Republican Mayor being lauded as a friend of labor by the officials of a traditionally Democratic union.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>There was that campaign television commercial in 1997 that depicted a prominent member of District Council 37 embracing the candidate, Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani. There was the endorsement of Mr. Giuliani's re-election that same year by the council's top official. Above all, there was the council's ratification of a city contract with a two-year pay freeze in 1996 that turned out to be a mayoral coup.</p>
        <p>For several years now, Mr. Giuliani has enjoyed the perception that he had forged close ties to the leadership of District Council 37, the city's largest municipal union with 120,000 members. That impression served him on several levels, including its counterintuitive nature: a Republican Mayor being lauded as a friend of labor by the officials of a traditionally Democratic union.</p>
        <p>But now District Council 37 is reeling from criminal and internal investigations into widespread corruption. The latest blow came yesterday, when two top officials resigned amid allegations that ballot fraud had tainted the contract vote in 1996. A natural question then arises: What does all this union turbulence mean for Mr. Giuliani?</p>
        <p>At first blush it might appear that the corruption allegations could taint a public official who earned his reputation as a corruption-fighting Federal prosecutor. In truth, it probably will have no impact at all, say his aides and labor analysts, with the outside chance that it might resurface if he seeks higher office.</p>
        <p>The five-year contract stands and probably will not be reopened, they say. When does it expire, at the end of 2000, this term-limited Mayor will either already be gone -- depending on his political aspirations -- or approaching his last months in office. Finally, as Deputy Mayor Randy Levine says, it is not the Mayor's problem.</p>
        <p>''Anything having to do with vote tampering and election fraud is outrageous, despicable and has to be condemned,'' Mr. Levine said. ''But this has nothing to do with Rudy Giuliani. This is an internal union matter. It is unfortunate that this union doesn't seem to have adequate controls, but the Mayor's role is irrelevant.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levine went on to complain that the media have not also asked questions about the district council's cordial relationship with several other politicians, from State Comptroller H. Carl McCall to the city's Public Advocate, Mark Green. But he conceded that neither Mr. McCall nor Mr. Green negotiated contracts with the union, nor did the union offical who embraced the Mayor in the commercial, Charles Hughes, then the president of the local representing 22,000 school cafeteria aides and crossing guards, appear in any of their campaign commercials.</p>
        <p>In fact, the Mayor's continuing and somewhat complicated relationship with the union has played a significant role in how he managed New York City in the last half of the 1990's.</p>
        <p>When in February 1996, after a contentious battle, the union approved a five-year contract with the city with no raises the first two years and a combined 13 percent pay increase for the final three years, it was widely seen as a watershed moment in the Giuliani administration.</p>
        <p>The contract allowed the Mayor to hold down spending at a time of fiscal crisis and to keep the peace with the union that represents more than half the city's workers. It permitted him to continue reducing the size of city government, because no job security had been promised to union members working as aides in municipal hospitals. And it established a pattern in municipal contracts that was soon followed by other unions.</p>
        <p>The contract had its critics. Many within the union leveled accusations of ballot fraud, accurately, it turned out. Good-government groups complained that the back-loaded structure of the contract, with a 6 percent pay increase in the last year, would cause fiscal havoc in the future. Overall, though, it provided Mr. Giuliani with the aura, attractive to Republicans, that he had tamed the big bad union.</p>
        <p>''It made him look very good to a sizable group of voters because he could say: 'I kept the unions in tow.  The voters now run the city,' '' said Stanley Aronowitz, a sociologist at the Graduate Center of the City University of New York. ''I think it was an important force in his whole presentation of himself as a parsimonious, effective mayor.''</p>
        <p>There was a flip side to the presentation, Mr. Aronowitz said, one harbored by the rank and file, ''that D.C. 37's leadership slept with the Mayor.''</p>
        <p>What happened in 1997 only reinforced that impression. Mr. Hill endorsed Mr. Giuliani's re-election, a decision that angered many other union officials. And Mr. Hughes appeared in the Mayor's campaign commercial.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Levine said that the Mayor's relationship with District Council 37 has been much more complicated and contentious. He has earned the ire of James Butler, the president of the local representing some workers at municipal hospitals, for proceeding with plans to shut down the hospitals, and he is routinely criticized by Charles S. Ensley, the president of the 14,000-member social workers' local, for trying to thwart collective bargaining.</p>
        <p>''Charles Hughes does commercials for the Mayor, Charles Ensley savages the Mayor,'' Mr. Levine said. ''Stanley Hill said something nice about the Mayor, Jim Butler goes after the Mayor.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Levine said that Mr. Giuliani is fair but tough; so tough, in fact, that so far no municipal union has sought to negotiate new contracts.</p>
        <p>''It's a little early,'' Mr. Levine  said. ''But what they tell me is that it may be easier negotiating with the next mayor, whoever that may be.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
