<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Pataki Coasts to a 3rd Term; McCall Is a Distant Second</title>
    <meta content="06YORK$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Front Page; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/11/06/nyregion/metrocampaigns/06YORK.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1438316"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE 2002 ELECTIONS: THE GOVERNOR"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comptrollers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Connecticut</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Liberal Party (NYS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Independence Party (NYS)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Senate (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccall, H Carl (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Golisano, B Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, James C Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Spitzer, Eliot L (Atty Gen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Alan G (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Irizarry, Dora</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faso, John J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lautenberg, Frank</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rowland, John G (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rockefeller, Nelson Aldrich (1908-79)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dewey, Thomas E (1902-71)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Front Page</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Governors (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attorneys General</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Results</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">McCall, H Carl</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Golisano, B Thomas</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE3DF113EF935A35752C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Pataki Coasts to a 3rd Term; McCall Is a Distant Second</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Pataki Coasts to a 3rd Term in New York</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMES C. McKINLEY Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, James C Jr</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Gov George E Pataki, pragmatic Republican, is elected to third term in New York with solid majority over H Carl McCall; photos; Atty Gen Eliot Spitzer obliterates Dora Irizarry, firmly establishing himself as rising Democratic star and potential gubernatorial candidate; Comptroller Alan G Hevesi squeaks by Republican John J Faso; Frank R Lautenberg is elected once again to Senate from New Jersey; Conn Gov John G Rowland wins easily; Pataki is only third Republican, with Thomas E Dewey and Nelson A Rockefeller, to win more than two terms in New York; McCall, who failed to raise enough money, did not hold onto Democratic base and made key campaign errors, comes close to record loss for Democrat; Pataki gets 50 percent of vote to 33 percent for McCall and 14 percent for Independence Party nominee Tom Golisano, with 98 percent of districts reporting; county-by-county tally; maps; Liberal Party fails to get 50,000 votes needed to automatically remain on ballot (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki, a pragmatic Republican who ran a campaign intended to appeal as much to liberals as to conservatives, was elected to a third term yesterday with a solid majority, ending the quest of the Democratic challenger, H. Carl McCall, to become the state's first black governor.</p>
        <p>In other New York races, Attorney General Eliot Spitzer obliterated his Republican opponent, Dora Irizarry, to win a second term, firmly establishing himself as one of the brightest young stars in the state Democratic Party and a possible candidate for governor.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki was elected to a third term with a solid majority, ending the quest of the Democratic challenger, H. Carl McCall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gov. George E. Pataki, a pragmatic Republican who ran a campaign intended to appeal as much to liberals as to conservatives, was elected to a third term yesterday with a solid majority, ending the quest of the Democratic challenger, H. Carl McCall, to become the state's first black governor.</p>
        <p>In other New York races, Attorney General Eliot Spitzer obliterated his Republican opponent, Dora Irizarry, to win a second term, firmly establishing himself as one of the brightest young stars in the state Democratic Party and a possible candidate for governor.</p>
        <p>The closest statewide race in New York was for comptroller. Alan G. Hevesi, the Democratic nominee and a former city comptroller, squeaked by John J. Faso, the former Republican leader in the State Assembly, winning with 50 percent of the vote to Mr. Faso's 47 percent.</p>
        <p>In New Jersey, Frank R. Lautenberg, a Democrat, was elected to the Senate by a comfortable margin, and in Connecticut, the Republican governor, John G. Rowland, was returned to office easily. [Pages B1 and B16.]</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki declared victory at 11:15 p.m. and profusely thanked all 18 million New Yorkers for their confidence in his policies.</p>
        <p>''There are no stronger, better people than New Yorkers,'' Mr. Pataki said, as supporters cheered. ''And when we are united, when we stand together, we can accomplish miracles. And it's been my goal as governor not to be the governor of some, but to be the governor of all.''</p>
        <p>His victory makes him only the third Republican to win more than two terms in New York, putting him in a class with Thomas E. Dewey and Nelson A. Rockefeller.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall went down in defeat after running a campaign that failed to raise enough money to mount a viable challenge to Mr. Pataki and could not hold onto the traditional Democratic base. Mr. McCall also made several pivotal mistakes in the final weeks of campaigning that kept him from cutting Mr. Pataki's lead, political strategists said.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. McCall wanted to make history as the first black governor, he came dangerously close last night to making history in another way, as the Democratic candidate who received the smallest percentage of total votes in modern history for a statewide race. That record was held by Peter F. Vallone, who got 33 percent of the vote four years ago in the governor's race. The only major party candidate to do worse in modern times was Pierre Rinfret, the Republican candidate in 1990, who got 21 percent of the vote.</p>
        <p>With 98 percent of election districts reporting, Mr. Pataki had 50 percent of the vote, Mr. McCall 33 percent and Tom Golisano, the Independence Party candidate, 14 percent, with minor party candidates picking up another 3 percent. The Liberal Party failed to get the 50,000 votes it needed to automatically remain on the ballot for future elections.</p>
        <p>The race was the most expensive in the state's history, with the major candidates expending more than $131 million.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall, 67, conceding defeat last night, said that while he wished the governor well, the schools and flagging economy still needed attention. ''If we could just put the same effort and the same level of passion and energy and funding into governing as we put into campaigning,'' he said, ''things would be a lot better.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Golisano, 60, a Rochester billionaire who has run three times for governor, spent more than $65 million of his own fortune and came in third. He said before the polls closed that he felt he had won a moral victory by attacking what he considers inertia, waste and fraud in state government.</p>
        <p>He conceded shortly after 11 p.m., but did not congratulate the governor in his speech. ''If we achieved anything,'' he said, ''it's for the next several years, the two-party system in this state has got to keep their eye out on us, because we're going to be watching them.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki, who is 57, coasted to a third victory by taking credit for cutting income taxes, winnowing the welfare rolls and reducing crime. He talked up several liberal programs that expanded under his watch, among them health insurance for poor children and their parents.</p>
        <p>Yet the governor did not offer an agenda for his next term as governor, an office with an annual salary of $179,000. Nor did he present concrete plans for confronting the deep financial crisis the state faces next year, including a yawning $5 billion budget gap. He stressed his experience instead, saying he had handled a similar crisis in 1995 and could be trusted to do so again.</p>
        <p>It remained unclear whether Mr. Pataki had achieved the kind of crushing victory that could transform him into a contender for national office. He won with 54 percent of the votes in 1998 against Mr. Vallone, but he faced a much more formidable campaign this year by Mr. Golisano.</p>
        <p>The election was a defining moment in the career of an adaptable politician who has evolved over his first two terms. He first ran in 1995 as a conservative who promised to slash income taxes, revamp welfare and restore the death penalty. But he has taken on more and more liberal causes over the years, championing tight gun-control laws, an equal-rights bill for homosexuals and expansion of Medicaid benefits to cover indigent children, to name a few.</p>
        <p>He won this year in part because of his aggressive pursuit of traditionally Democratic voters, especially Latinos and union members. At the Hilton New York Hotel in Midtown last night, several hundred happy Republican campaign workers and Pataki supporters stood around the ballroom, eagerly awaiting the governor's anticipated victory speech. Some danced to loud rock music or shrieked with pleasure as the returns rolled in. ''The bottom line is people know him, they like him, they trust him,'' Michael McKeon, the governor's chief spokesman, said.</p>
        <p>The mood was more subdued at Mr. McCall's headquarters in a union hall downtown, where prominent Democrats were taking some solace in the thought that their candidate had run a good campaign with the resources he had.</p>
        <p>''I think it's very important to recognize that no campaign is perfect, no winning campaign is perfect,'' said former Mayor David N. Dinkins, a longtime friend of Mr. McCall. ''We should not be so quick to condemn this campaign.''</p>
        <p>Yet other McCall supporters also talked of betrayal by the National Democratic Party for not pumping more money into the New York race, and were already second-guessing campaign strategies, even as they praised their candidate.</p>
        <p>The race failed to inspire many voters, as turnout across the state was light to moderate. In New York City, some Democrats expressed disappointment with Mr. McCall's candidacy even as they voted for him.</p>
        <p>Lacking a big campaign treasury, Mr. McCall had turned to his Democratic allies for help and support, especially Representative Charles B. Rangel of Harlem, who has been Mr. McCall's mentor for decades.</p>
        <p>Bill Clinton and his wife, Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton, both campaigned hard for Mr. McCall in the closing days. Senator Charles E. Schumer endorsed Mr. McCall early on and appeared in an advertisement, warmly recommending him to voters. So did Mr. Clinton.</p>
        <p>In a sense, Mr. McCall ran an old-fashioned partisan campaign, laboring to persuade moderate Democrats who support Mr. Pataki to come back home.</p>
        <p>But the governor presented himself as a nonpartisan liberal, despite having run as a tax-slashing conservative in 1994. He rarely mentioned his party on the hustings, but repeated a mantra about unity and wanting to be ''the governor of all the people.'' He attracted a significant number of prominent Democratic supporters to his camp.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki also benefited from history. The governor's popularity soared after Sept. 11, as New Yorkers, and Americans across the country, rallied around their leaders. What had seemed a winnable race for the Democrats became much tougher overnight, strategists said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Pataki seldom spoke of his high profile role after the attacks, but other Republicans praised his leadership frequently at campaign rallies, and he often appeared in front of a giant American flag.</p>
        <p>Toward the end of the campaign, Mr. Pataki adopted a frontrunner's strategy, issuing no position papers and refusing to debate unless the full slate of candidates for governor were included.</p>
        <p>Mr. McCall, meanwhile, tried to run on two main themes: that the governor had failed to improve the state's schools and had not had any success lifting the upstate economy from the doldrums.</p>
        <p>Last night, Mrs. Clinton praised Mr. McCall, saying he had set a wonderful example. ''This is a man,'' she said, ''that you should tell your children and grandchildren about.''</p>
        <p>THE 2002 ELECTIONS: THE GOVERNOR</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
