<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MOVIE GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="31MOVI$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1531411"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DB1730F932A05753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="4401" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MOVIE GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A selective listing by Times critics of new or noteworthy movies playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film. Ratings and running times are in parentheses.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>''BEYOND BORDERS,'' starring Angelina Jolie and Clive Owen. Directed by Martin Campbell (R, 127 minutes). Sitting through the romantic action-melodrama ''Beyond Borders,'' which follows a glamorous movie star couple as they tend to the needy in trouble spots like Ethiopia, Cambodia and Chechnya, is like watching someone trying to dry his hands with sandpaper. No amount of misguided effort is going to help. Ms. Jolie plays a shallow young woman, Sarah Jordan, who's shaken out of her insular existence by the dashing Dr. Nick Callahan (Mr. Owen). ''Borders'' wants to dramatize the chasm between Sarah and Nick, whose impatient compassion endangers as many refugees as it saves. That metaphorical land mass is supposed to be her middle-class naïveté and his brooding, no-nonsense altruism. But they're much closer than they think -- a pair of noble idiots. Inspired by his example, she raises money and follows him with medical supplies and food to Ethiopia. He repays her kindness with blithe cruelty. This is a movie so oblivious that Mr. Campbell, an accomplished action filmmaker, forgot that in the 1940's, ''Casablanca'' had the good sense to have Rick note that the troubles of ordinary people don't amount to a hill of beans (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A selective listing by Times critics of new or noteworthy movies playing this weekend in New York City. * denotes a highly recommended film. Ratings and running times are in parentheses.</p>
        <p>Now Playing</p>
        <p>''BEYOND BORDERS,'' starring Angelina Jolie and Clive Owen. Directed by Martin Campbell (R, 127 minutes). Sitting through the romantic action-melodrama ''Beyond Borders,'' which follows a glamorous movie star couple as they tend to the needy in trouble spots like Ethiopia, Cambodia and Chechnya, is like watching someone trying to dry his hands with sandpaper. No amount of misguided effort is going to help. Ms. Jolie plays a shallow young woman, Sarah Jordan, who's shaken out of her insular existence by the dashing Dr. Nick Callahan (Mr. Owen). ''Borders'' wants to dramatize the chasm between Sarah and Nick, whose impatient compassion endangers as many refugees as it saves. That metaphorical land mass is supposed to be her middle-class naïveté and his brooding, no-nonsense altruism. But they're much closer than they think -- a pair of noble idiots. Inspired by his example, she raises money and follows him with medical supplies and food to Ethiopia. He repays her kindness with blithe cruelty. This is a movie so oblivious that Mr. Campbell, an accomplished action filmmaker, forgot that in the 1940's, ''Casablanca'' had the good sense to have Rick note that the troubles of ordinary people don't amount to a hill of beans (Elvis Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''BROTHER BEAR,'' with the voices of Joaquin Phoenix, Jeremy Suarez, Rick Moranis and D. B. Sweeney. Directed by Aaron Blaise and Robert Walker (G, 85 minutes). The fine line separating good-hearted family movies from inspirational films that drum in moral values is breached in ''Brother Bear,'' a plush, Disney animated film that would like to think of itself as ''The Lion King Plus.'' Set in the Pacific Northwest at the end of the Ice Age, it traffics in the same sort of cosmic mumbo-jumbo as its forerunner. Cobbling together ancient cross-cultural myths of initiation and humans who turn into animals, it tells the story of Kenai (Mr. Phoenix), a hot-headed Native American boy on the verge of manhood who is transformed into a bear so he can learn compassion for all creatures great and small. The self-serious movie is beautiful to look at but light on humor. The soundtrack features six songs by Phil Collins (Stephen Holden).</p>
        <p>* ''BUS 174,'' directed by José Padilha (not rated, 122 minutes; in Portuguese, with English subtitles). This Brazilian documentary is so wrenching and absorbing that you can easily lose sight of the sophistication of its techniques. Using a combination of video taken for Brazilian television and ex post facto talking-head interviews, the filmmakers have made a deceptively straightforward documentary that has the force of tragedy and the depth of first-rate investigative journalism. Their work explores a bus hijacking that took place in Rio de Janeiro in 2000, and paints a heartbreaking, shocking portrait of the perpetrator, a child of the slums who had survived a notorious police massacre of homeless children in 1992, and a society riven by poverty and violence (A. O. Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''ELEPHANT,'' starring Alex Frost, Eric Deulen, Alicia Miles and John Robinson. Directed by Gus Van Sant (R, 81 minutes). This unusual and remarkable film has a premise so simple that, in the abstract, it borders on the banal: plotless and stubbornly resistant to conventional narrative structure, the movie has its camera follow students around the halls and grounds of a high school in Portland, Ore., for a day until violence erupts. ''Elephant'' is the director's take on the murders that took place at Columbine High School. The title comes from the British director Alan Clarke's 1989 short film of the same name, a tough and dense look at the violence in northern Ireland. Mr. Clarke's short outraged or absorbed viewers in the way Mr. Van Sant's movie, which won the Palme d'Or at Cannes, is likely to do. (Mr. Clarke's title referred to the aphorism about the elephant in the living room -- a problem that people refuse to face for so long that they are no longer even able to see it.) ''Elephant'' will confound audiences looking for solutions or villains, because it doesn't supply them. Mr. Van Sant gives ''Elephant'' a spartan yet elusive life by shifting the film's focus from one group of students to another. And by the end of the movie, we realize where much of the power and clarity of the film come from. By making the camera an observer, we get a perspective that often comes out of horror movies, a choice that whips the ordinary with the terrifying -- an unforgettable mix (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''IN THE CUT,'' starring Meg Ryan and Mark Ruffalo. Directed by Jane Campion (R, 118 minutes). Ms. Campion (''The Piano,'' ''Holy Smoke,'' ''The Portrait of a Lady'') is an inveterate navigator in the murkier zones of female sexuality, and this film, adapted from Susanna Moore's novel, plots a hazardous nexus of dread, danger and desire. The camera, as it surveys the grimy streets and cramped apartments of Lower Manhattan, trembles as if it were running a fever, and Dion Beebe's cinematography is jumpy and bleary-eyed. Ms. Ryan, who has darkened her hair and suppressed all of her characteristic perkiness, plays Frannie, a writing teacher whose feverish love affair with a homicide detective (Mr. Ruffalo) involves her in the search for a serial killer. The movie's association of female sexuality with mortal risk is potentially interesting, but the cooked-up, conventional serial-killer plot smothers its suggestive nuances and makes the psychology of the two main characters, which might have been provocatively mysterious, seem as deliberately smudged as the film's visual style (Scott).</p>
        <p>''KILL BILL: VOL. 1,'' starring Uma Thurman, David Carradine and Lucy Liu. Written and directed by Quentin Tarantino (R, 95 minutes). Mr. Tarantino's fourth movie, his first in six years, is astonishingly violent, intermittently fascinating and sometimes tedious. This may be the picture's most serious flaw, since it comes from a man whose worship of action movies from all over the world (but especially Asia) is evident in every frame. Also evident is his obsession with Ms. Thurman: by far the most emotionally charged relationship in the movie is the one between the director and his star, who functions as his muse, idol, alter ego and fetish object. Her character, the Bride, is a former assassin whose former lover (that would be Bill) tried to kill her on her wedding day. In this film, the first installment in a two-part revenge epic, the Bride wakes up from a four-year coma and goes after the hired swords and guns who attacked her. Most of the exposition has been left for Vol. 2; this one is an anthology of increasingly violent sequences, some sickening, some rather thrilling, that culminates in a Tokyo nightclub blood bath during which Ms. Liu, playing a petite yakuza boss, shows off her Japanese, and also (quite literally) her brains (Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''MYSTIC RIVER,'' starring Sean Penn, Tim Robbins, Kevin Bacon, Laurence Fishburne, Marcia Gay Harden and Laura Linney. Directed by Clint Eastwood (R, 137 minutes). Mr. Eastwood's film, scrupulously faithful to the letter and spirit of Dennis Lehane's novel, has the gritty efficiency of superior crime fiction and the somber weight of tragedy. Set in working-class Irish Catholic Boston, this film revisits the themes of violence, honor and guilt that have haunted many of Mr. Eastwood's movies; it is among the most humane of his films, but also the most rigorously pessimistic. Mr. Robbins, Mr. Bacon and Mr. Penn play Dave, Sean and Jimmy, boyhood friends who must revisit the traumas of their youth when Jimmy's daughter is murdered. Sean and his partner (Mr. Fishburne) must investigate the killing, which it appears Dave may have committed. The performances are first rate. Ms. Harden, as Dave's wife, Celeste, and Ms. Linney, as her cousin Annabeth, who is married to Jimmy, expand the film's emotional compass, allowing us to see how grief ripples through families and communities. Mr. Penn's volcanic, furiously disciplined performance is surely one of the best pieces of screen acting you'll see this year; it may even be one of the finest ever (Scott).</p>
        <p>* ''PIECES OF APRIL,'' starring Katie Holmes, Patricia Clarkson, Derek Luke, Alison Pill, John Gallagher Jr. and Oliver Platt. Written and directed by Peter Hedges (PG-13, 81 minutes). Mr. Hedges's intelligent and touching farce makes an important contribution to a small and insignificant subgenre: Thanksgiving Day failure. It does so by raising the bar. ''April'' focuses intently on the neuroses that Thanksgiving Day creates even for the inoffensively punky April Burns (Ms. Holmes), who seeks a rapprochement with her family by preparing a holiday meal that looks like a serving suggestion photo. She now lives in downtown Manhattan with her boyfriend (Mr. Luke). And this is an occasion her suburban family needs to cling to as well. Her dad, Jim (Mr. Platt), and siblings, Timmy (Mr. Gallagher) and Beth (Ms. Pill), are already worn to a frazzle trying to keep their spirits up around April's ill mother, Joy (Ms. Clarkson). They're traveling into the city to dine at April's, in what could be the last holiday they share as a group. When her oven stops working on Thanksgiving morning, April finds the strength to stave off an extravagant meltdown and find a solution. Her willful, spoiled naïveté is a great joke that the director doesn't overplay. Yet it's her surliness, as well as her intransigence -- she's determined to make Thanksgiving work -- that keeps the laughs coming (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''RUNAWAY JURY,'' starring John Cusack, Gene Hackman and Dustin Hoffman. Directed by Gary Fleder (PG-13, 123 minutes). Mr. Hackman and Mr. Hoffman have never shared the screen before, as they do in this latest film adaptation of a paranoid John Grisham courtroom potboiler. Yet something about the picture feels familiar. Mr. Hackman has played this grubby-souled, hand-tailored heart of modern corruption before, and in a previous Grisham adaptation, ''The Firm.'' This time, he's a slick jury consultant named Rankin Fitch who employs ruthless tactics to empanel a jury that will best service his client. And like ''The Firm,'' the schematic crassness of the narrative provides an actor the opportunity to deliver some fine work. Mr. Cusack gives one of his wiliest performances in some time, and one of his most adult, as the aging slacker who is drafted into jury duty. Apparently, the writers realize there's not much to be done with the boilerplate narrative, which involves the machinations of the jury that Fitch is laboring to bend to his own will. (Mr. Hoffman is the endearing plaintiff attorney.) You may end up wishing that the actors had found a less needlessly showoffy picture to practice their craft (Mitchell).</p>
        <p>''SCARY MOVIE 3,'' starring Anna Faris, Leslie Nielsen, Camryn Manheim, Simon Rex, Queen Latifah, Regina Hall and Charlie Sheen. Directed by David Zucker (PG-13, 90 minutes). The third installment of the comedy franchise whose jokes derive largely from references to recent hit films has been given a shot of adrenaline by Mr. Zucker, who pioneered the genre with ''Airplane,'' and who has taken over the creative reins from the Wayans Brothers. Most of the spoofing is at the expense of movies like ''Signs,'' ''The Ring'' and the first two ''Matrix'' movies. The funniest sequence in a comedy that revels in knockabout farce and has the attention span of a hyperactive child is a strenuous group effort to revive a corpse, first through some alarmingly aggressive artificial respiration, then through slapping and slamming the body until it breaks apart. Think of ''Scary Movie 3'' as an accelerated junk-culture vaudeville with a Mad magazine sensibility (Holden).</p>
        <p>* ''SCHOOL OF ROCK,'' starring Jack Black, Joan Cusack and Mike White. Directed by Richard Linklater (PG-13, 110 minutes). Mr. Black gives a roaring, star-making performance as Dewey Finn, an out-of-work heavy-metal rocker who impersonates a substitute teacher and turns a class of nerdy fifth graders into a rock band. Mr. Black's incandescent comic energy should establish him as the screen's most popular rock-fueled wild man since John Belushi. Under the nose of the prim school principal (Ms. Cusack), Dewey, who knows nothing of academics, preaches the gospel of rock 'n' roll and secretly converts the class from loving Christine Aguilera and the musical ''Annie'' to cheering Led Zeppelin and AC/DC. This family-friendly movie, which has a big, rousing ''Rocky''-style finale and isn't believable for a second, is a hilarious cotton-candy fantasy with a beat. It knows just where to draw the line to avoid becoming too cute, too esoteric or too risqué (Holden).</p>
        <p>*''SYLVIA,'' starring Gwyneth Paltrow and Daniel Craig. Directed by Christine Jeffs (R, 110 minutes). Since her suicide in 1963 at 30, Sylvia Plath's life, her work and her marriage to Ted Hughes have been the subject of endless argument, and Plath herself has become a quasi-allegorical figure -- a feminist martyr and an icon of poetic misery. Ms. Jeffs's film is relatively even-handed in its treatment of Hughes (Mr. Craig), and turns its subject from a case study in literary pathology into the heroine of a modern literary opera. The film, shot in dark, oversaturated colors by John Toon, is itself oversaturated with feeling. Rather than try to explain Plath's death, or probe the roots of her poetry, Ms. Jeffs and Ms. Paltrow burrow deep into her personality, leaving its essential, unsettling mysteries intact. Ms. Paltrow is a vivid, passionate presence throughout the film -- she is rarely off the screen -- and she charts the jagged course of Plath's abbreviated adulthood with ardor and intelligence. The movie turns biography into melodrama, but it does so out of a fierce, fascinated loyalty to Plath, who after all did much the same thing in her best poems (Scott).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
