<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>James's Debut Leaves Critics Gushing</title>
    <meta content="31LEBR$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/31/sports/basketball/31LEBR.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1531621"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sacramento Kings</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broussard, Chris</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">James, Lebron</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Sacramento Kings</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cleveland Cavaliers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">James, LeBron</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031031T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E5D61530F932A05753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="1213" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>James's Debut Leaves Critics Gushing</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Floodgates of Praise Burst Open for James</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRIS BROUSSARD</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Broussard, Chris</byline>
      <dateline>PHOENIX, Oct. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cleveland Cavaliers point guard LeBron James impresses team, NBA, critics, fans and media in debut against Sacramento Kings by scoring 25 points, handing out 9 assists, grabbing 6 rebounds and making 4 steals; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>If anyone was going to bring millions in the basketball world back to reality, back from premature visions of an 18-year-old playing like an N.B.A. superstar, it would be Larry Bird.</p>
        <p>After all, Bird, the Indiana Pacers' president, was a longtime rival and buddy of Magic Johnson's, a nemesis to Isiah Thomas and one of the few players to foil the postseason plans of Michael Jordan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>LeBron Jamess debut on Wednesday was by far the best N.B.A. debut of any of the current high school-to-pros stars.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>If anyone was going to bring millions in the basketball world back to reality, back from premature visions of an 18-year-old playing like an N.B.A. superstar, it would be Larry Bird.</p>
        <p>After all, Bird, the Indiana Pacers' president, was a longtime rival and buddy of Magic Johnson's, a nemesis to Isiah Thomas and one of the few players to foil the postseason plans of Michael Jordan.</p>
        <p>So Bird would certainly put LeBron James's dazzling debut in perspective by reminding us all of the wisdom of the wait-and-see approach, right?</p>
        <p>Wrong.</p>
        <p>After watching James record 25 points, 9 assists, 6 rebounds and 4 steals in Cleveland's 106-92 loss to Sacramento on Wednesday night, Bird was as smitten with James as everyone else. He has anointed the Cleveland Cavaliers rookie as the truth. Not the truth in a year or so, but right now.</p>
        <p>''He's going to be one of the top players in the league by the time the season's over,'' Bird said yesterday in a telephone conversation. ''These other players in the league, these veterans, can say all they want about him not being ready, but this kid is for real.</p>
        <p>''I've never seen anybody like this. He passes as well as anybody I've seen, and with his quickness, his size and his strength -- I hate to put a label on a guy, but if we're not talking about him being in the Hall of Fame within the next five years, something went wrong. He's the best talent I've seen come out in years.''</p>
        <p>James did nothing to change Bird's mind in the Cavaliers' 95-86 loss to the Suns here Thursday night, recording 21 points, 12 rebounds and 8 assists in what looked like an almost effortless performance. If there can be any criticism of James after two games, it might be that he has not asserted himself enough offensively. He is so controlled and nonchalant that it seems he can be more dominating if he wants to be.</p>
        <p>A check around the league revealed that Bird's sentiments were closer to the rule than the exception.</p>
        <p>''People that do this for a living knew,'' said John Nash, the general manager of the Portland Trail Blazers. ''I don't think it sent shock waves throughout the league. I think what we saw against Sacramento will be a consistent performance for him.''</p>
        <p>James's performance was by far the best N.B.A. debut of any of the current high-school-to-the-pros stars, including Kevin Garnett, Kobe Bryant and Tracy McGrady. The previous record for points scored in a debut by such a player was 10, shared by Jonathan Bender of Indiana in 1999 and Amare Stoudemire of Phoenix last season.</p>
        <p>James's 25 surpassed the totals of Garnett (8), Bryant (0), McGrady (0), Jermaine O'Neal (2), Kwame Brown (2), Eddy Curry (2) and Tyson Chandler (1) combined.</p>
        <p>Nash believes James will not struggle through an adjustment period like some of his predecessors because at 6-8 and 240 pounds, he already has an N.B.A. body.</p>
        <p>''Unlike other youngsters that come into the league that might need an opportunity to develop physically, he's already way ahead of his peers in terms of his physical maturity,'' Nash said. ''He was a man among boys last year, and now he's a man among men. So he's not going to suffer as a result of not being as big as the other guys in the N.B.A. Physically, he's a force.''</p>
        <p>James was a force in the world of marketing before he hit his first jumper against the Kings. With endorsements from Nike, Sprite and Upper Deck surpassing $100 million, there was a lot riding on James's shoulders Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Naturally, Nike, which signed him to a seven-year, $100 million contract, liked what it saw. James wore his Air Zoom Generation sneakers, which will be in stores on Dec. 20.</p>
        <p>''We think we have the athlete in LeBron that people want to emulate,'' said Rodney Knox, Nike's public relations director for basketball and football.</p>
        <p>Rod Thorn, the president and general manager of the Nets, said he was most impressed by James's ability to excel under such pressure at Arco Arena, one of the most raucous gyms in the league, against one of the league's elite teams.</p>
        <p>''How about the court presence that he has?'' Thorn said in a telephone interview. ''Isn't that amazing that he can go out and play as under control and play as well as he played with the hype of that game? It's a special kind of player that would not succumb to that and try to do crazy things to try to live up to the hype.''</p>
        <p>James grabbed his first rebound and made an alley-oop pass (a dunk by Ricky Davis) within the first two minutes. By the end of the first quarter, he had 12 points, 3 assists, 3 steals and an awe-inspiring dunk.</p>
        <p>''Now I can see what all the media is so ecstatic about,'' Sacramento's Bobby Jackson said after the game. ''He's a terrific talent.''</p>
        <p>James also displayed Magic Johnson-like unselfishness by forgoing a breakaway dunk to pass back to a trailing Davis, who finished with a two-handed reverse slam.</p>
        <p>When asked why he passed back to Davis, James said: ''That's just me. I'm a team player. He's the scorer. I'm the point guard. That's what point guards do.''</p>
        <p>Joe Dumars, the Pistons' president, said, ''LeBron plays to win and not just for stats.''</p>
        <p>Cleveland Coach Paul Silas admitted that he did not expect such a start from James. ''I knew he was capable of it,'' Silas said. ''I just didn't think it was going to happen. This is a great start for him.''</p>
        <p>James had come under fire after shooting below 40 percent in the preseason, and rather than gloat after shooting 12 of 20 against the Kings, he joked about his skeptics.</p>
        <p>''Coach Silas told me not to start until the regular season,'' James said with a smile. ''I like criticism. It makes me stronger. All those who said I couldn't shoot, thank you. Ya'll helped me a lot.''</p>
        <p>His debut on ESPN generated a 2.8 rating (or 2.49 million cable households), higher than the rating for all but one of the network's N.B.A. games last season (the first game in which Yao Ming played against Shaquille O'Neal).</p>
        <p>Dennis Johnson, Bird's former Celtics teammate and now a scout for Portland, was more cautious about predicting that James would be a dominant force all season.</p>
        <p>''We have to keep it all in perspective and perspective says the kid is 18 years old and he's going to stumble,'' Johnson said. ''When he gets to 30 games, he's going to get tired and that's where you may see a little downfall. But with his size and ability, he may catch on again real quick. I hope he does. I hope he's everything everyone writes him to be.''</p>
        <p>While nothing is promised, 25 points and an endorsement from Bird is a good start.</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
