<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Capturing the wild wild West -- as well as the not-so-wild rest of the country.</title>
    <meta content="Y23ADCO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026752"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Dallas</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cropper, Carol Marie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Copeland, Top</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CEEDD123CF930A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="793" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Capturing the wild wild West -- as well as the not-so-wild rest of the country.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Marie Cropper</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Cropper, Carol Marie</byline>
      <dateline>DALLAS</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on increased number of television advertising spots that are being filmed in Texas; Tom Copeland, director of Texas Film Commission, says about $80 million a year is spent across the state making TV spots; recent study by University of Dallas's Graduate School of Management estimates that 678 commercials were shot in 1997 in Dallas and Houston alone (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN executives of a Kentucky restaurant chain wanted desert scenery and armadillos for a commercial, they knew where to go.</p>
        <p>Trouble was, said Lynn Birdwell, co-founder of Rio Bravo Pictures, the Houston production company that filmed the spot for the chain, Texas Roadhouse of Louisville, Texas doesn't have any trained armadillos. State law forbids selling the critters or keeping them for sale except for limited purposes. So two had to be flown in from Oklahoma.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN executives of a Kentucky restaurant chain wanted desert scenery and armadillos for a commercial, they knew where to go.</p>
        <p>Trouble was, said Lynn Birdwell, co-founder of Rio Bravo Pictures, the Houston production company that filmed the spot for the chain, Texas Roadhouse of Louisville, Texas doesn't have any trained armadillos. State law forbids selling the critters or keeping them for sale except for limited purposes. So two had to be flown in from Oklahoma.</p>
        <p>Despite the sometimes arduous task of appearing Texan enough to suit outsiders, the Lone Star State's commercial production companies report a growing business. The industry was jump-started in the 1980's by the television series ''Dallas,'' as locals gained experience on the set and some out-of-state professionals chose to remain in Texas, said Jeff Klein, executive director of the Texas Association of Film/Tape Professionals, a nonprofit group.</p>
        <p>The state now ranks third -- or perhaps fourth -- in the amount of money spent there to make TV commercials, he said. California is first, with New York a distant second. Illinois, primarily Chicago, would be the most likely rival of Texas for No.  3, according to Mr. Klein.</p>
        <p>A recent study by the University of Dallas's Graduate School of Management estimated that 678 commercials were shot in 1997 in Dallas and Houston alone.</p>
        <p>While Houston and, especially, Dallas are the focal points of the industry, production companies have also sprouted in Amarillo, Austin, Corpus Christi and El Paso, Mr. Klein said.</p>
        <p>According to Tom Copeland, director of the Texas Film Commission, about $80 million a year is spent across the state making TV spots.</p>
        <p>Texas is an obvious choice for beer commercials, given the populace's drinking preferences. But commercials are produced here for other reasons as well.</p>
        <p>''There are so many varied looks in Texas,'' Mr. Copeland said, from coastline and mountains to deserts and piney woods. Also, he said, ''the weather is probably going to be good,'' with lots of sunshine.</p>
        <p>Then there is the mystique of the Old West, Mr. Copeland added, despite the imported armadillos.</p>
        <p>Tammie Edwards, co-founder of the Dallas production company Bednarz Film, gave another reason. ''It's easy to shoot here'' compared with cities like New York and Los Angeles, she said, because of less ''red tape'' in obtaining permits and other such details.</p>
        <p>Wages and other costs are lower, Ms. Edwards said. ''They're looking at $200-a-day for a hotel in New York, whereas in Dallas, it's $75 to $100,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Costs can also be kept down, Mr. Klein said, because the state has no income tax and does not levy a sales tax on film or equipment rental.</p>
        <p>On top of all that, said Adolfo Aguilar Jr., president of one of the nation's top Hispanic ad agencies, there is a growing market for commercials aimed at Spanish-speaking consumers, who have a large presence in Texas.</p>
        <p>Mr. Aguilar said that his San Antonio agency, Bromley, Aguilar &amp; Associates, part of the D'arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles unit of MacManus Group, often uses local production companies to make their Spanish-language spots.</p>
        <p>While production crews can, of course, be imported to film in Texas, there are now enough talented locals to do the work, those in the state's industry say.</p>
        <p>''It's usually easier to find someone who's already in Texas rather than bringing in the whole show,'' said Rodrigo Rodriguez, the other co-founder of Rio Bravo.</p>
        <p>Indeed, Texas production companies now compete nationally and film spots elsewhere. Of the 26 spots Bednarz Film made last year, Ms. Edwards said, 10 were set outside Texas. And Bednarz staff members went to New York this year to shoot an American Airlines ad featuring the city's bridges, part of a campaign created for the New York market.</p>
        <p>Texas companies have produced commercials for Sports Illustrated and McDonald's, Mr. Klein said. A recent Sprint commercial was also a Texas creation.</p>
        <p>Texas companies sticking close to home are also doing well. Pony Pictures of Lubbock, which produces mostly regional commercials, saw its revenues double last year, said Dwight Harper, its owner.</p>
        <p>While some advertisers like the Texas look, Mr. Harper added, others come to the state because it can look like somewhere else. He recalled, for example, going to the mountains of West Texas recently to shoot a commercial for a Mexican restaurant whose owners ''wanted it to look like interior Mexico.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
