<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Viagra's Other Side Effect: Upsets in Many a Marriage</title>
    <meta content="23VIAG" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026738"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Impotence</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Viagra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinhauer, Jennifer</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)/Viagra (Drug)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Impotence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sex</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Men</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marriages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drugs (Pharmaceuticals)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DE123CF930A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1821" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Viagra's Other Side Effect: Upsets in Many a Marriage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER STEINHAUER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Steinhauer, Jennifer</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Experts on sexuality and therapists are finding that Viagra and other impotence aids may actually throw into chaos relationships that have fallen into their own routine, sexual dysfunction and all; they say most common problem is that men hope to treat their impotence as simple mechanical issue, while women tend to want to address emotions related to impotence; in other cases, a man and a woman are forced to confront their divergent views about what it means to have sex and how often they want to have it--issues that impotence had rendered moot; many couples are finding that a solution to what they thought was a medical problem may uncover myriad other issues in relationship; drawings (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ON the surface, the couple from Queens seemed like perfect candidates for Viagra.</p>
        <p>The woman, 53, has been married to her husband, 59, for 30 years. A few years ago, he started to have trouble achieving an erection. He was unhappy about it, but learned to see some good in it. ''My eye doesn't wander anymore,'' he said, ''because I can't do anything about it.'' Though the woman said she ''could not imagine staying in a relationship without sex,'' she, too, became reconciled once they learned to have other kinds of intimacy and other forms of sex.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ON the surface, the couple from Queens seemed like perfect candidates for Viagra.</p>
        <p>The woman, 53, has been married to her husband, 59, for 30 years. A few years ago, he started to have trouble achieving an erection. He was unhappy about it, but learned to see some good in it. ''My eye doesn't wander anymore,'' he said, ''because I can't do anything about it.'' Though the woman said she ''could not imagine staying in a relationship without sex,'' she, too, became reconciled once they learned to have other kinds of intimacy and other forms of sex.</p>
        <p>Viagra, the popular new drug for impotence, would appear to be their ticket back to a more conventional sex life. But like many couples contemplating Viagra, the two are starkly divided about whether to try it: While he is looking for a medical panacea for a physical problem that often comes with age, she has long wondered whether the problem might be better addressed on a therapist's couch than in a doctor's office.</p>
        <p>A few months ago, Viagra was being promoted by everyone from urologists to  drug company analysts as the new miracle drug destined to help solve millions of Americans' sexual problems. The drug flew off pharmacy shelves.</p>
        <p>But experts on sexuality and therapists are finding that Viagra and other impotence aids may actually throw into chaos relationships that have fallen into their own routine, sexual dysfunction and all.</p>
        <p>The most common problem they say, is that men hope to treat their impotence as a simple mechanical issue, while women tend to want to address the emotions related to impotence. In other cases, a man and woman are forced to confront their divergent views about what it means to have sex and how often they want to have it -- issues that impotence had rendered moot.</p>
        <p>The result is that many couples are finding that a solution to what they thought was a medical problem may uncover myriad  other issues in the relationship.</p>
        <p>''We are in a very high-tech society, and people are used to having things done very quickly,'' said Eileen Palace, director of the Center for Sexual Health at Tulane University Hospital in New Orleans. ''We saw in the 1960's how the pill could control biology. Later, we saw how to control infertility. People want a simple, easy, fast solution. And many physicians assume that just because there is a physical problem means there is no psychological cause.''</p>
        <p>Urologists interviewed for this article said they had been writing Viagra prescriptions by the dozens, many for patients who had never before said they were impotent.  Some had not even confided in their partners. Instead, they simply avoided sex.</p>
        <p>''The guy sees himself having trouble, and he, out of embarrassment and lack of communicativity, he says 'I am going to sleep in the other room,' '' said Dr. Walter Bortz, a geriatrics specialist at the Palo Alto Medical Foundation, in California. ''The wife thinks he has a girlfriend. And it becomes a gulf that enters a well-cemented relationship, because egos get in the way.''</p>
        <p>When the possibility of sex resurfaces, a couple is often at a loss. They never talked much about their problems before, and now they have no idea how to approach the change. In the meantime, all the issues that  contributed to the impotence or resulted from it have been long swept under the rug.</p>
        <p>''When someone hears about Viagra, they are expecting to get better on their sexual problems,'' said E. Douglas Whitehead, the director of the Association for Male Sexual Dysfunction in New York. ''But there are many issues that affect desire: life stresses, the stock market, other issues. But most of the time, people don't talk about those problems. They are the secret of the bedroom. They think Viagra will address them.''</p>
        <p>The woman from Queens who, like her husband, agreed to be interviewed if they were not identified, said she had given up trying to persuade her husband to address the emotional aspects of their sexual problems in therapy.</p>
        <p>''His doctor suggested he go into therapy because he couldn't find any medical reason for his borderline erections,'' she said. ''I thought therapy was a great opportunity, but he didn't want to do it. I was frustrated. I am a believer that therapy is the most noninvasive, and look at all the added benefits it would bring to your life.''</p>
        <p>Therapy is where many couples dealing with impotence belong, even if they use Viagra, many doctors say. The couple may never have discussed the inevitable resentment and pain that resulted from their damaged sex lives, feelings that will not disappear with medication. Once Viagra allows a couple to have sex again, their relationship can change. There might be divergent views on how often they should have sex, and how they should plan for it.</p>
        <p>For example, Viagra, which must be taken an hour before intercourse, and other drugs for impotence, leave little room for spontaneous romantic encounters. What is more, a couple used to not having sex may be out of practice in the language and gestures of sexual intimacy.</p>
        <p>Dr. Palace recalled a man with diabetes, which often contributes to impotence, who was using injected drugs commonly used to help impotent men achieve erections.</p>
        <p>''He came in in tears, because his wife's romantic gesture was to lay the syringe on the pillow,'' she said.  ''You have to be able to talk about the role of the treatment in the relationship. And I've learned to trust penises, because they are good indicators of what is going on in a relationship.''</p>
        <p>Steven and Katherine, who spoke on the condition that their last name  not be used, found that their marriage was in trouble after Steven began using penile injections. Testicular cancer left him impotent in 1990, and he and Katherine were married shortly after.</p>
        <p>''When we would go to the urologist,'' Katherine said, ''they would come up with this or that and address really only my husband and his physical problems.'' This or that turned out to be injections that produced erections but terrible sex. The injections themselves were disturbing enough, she said, but the underlying problem was her unacknowledged feelings about having married a man who was impotent. Ultimately, she said, she worked through the problem in sex therapy at Tulane. ''Part of what therapy did was help me face the grief that I had never faced being married to a man who was impotent.''</p>
        <p>Steven agreed that he had not thought through the emotional issues related to their sexual problems. ''I thought my primary problem was plumbing,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''One thing that amazed me when we finally opened the lines of communication was that my sexual performance was not satisfactory for her. I thought things were fine. But because she loved me anyway, she made a conscious decision to forgo a good sexual life to have a good marriage.''</p>
        <p>In the end, they have decided to forgo Viagra and explore other avenues of sexual intimacy.</p>
        <p>Many therapists and urologists say that most men are loath to discuss their sexual problems with anyone, especially a therapist. Those men see the pill as an easy way out.</p>
        <p>Pepper Schwartz, a professor of sociology at the University of Washington in Seattle and author of several books about American sexual habits, cited two things about Viagra that appeal to men: ''They don't have to talk about impotence and they have a high assurance of potential good in using it.''</p>
        <p>''The issues that have been shrugged off are the psychological and social aspects of it,'' Dr. Schwartz said. ''And I do believe that any drug that alters the core way a couple relates to each other requires discussions of expectations and pressures.''</p>
        <p>But most men seem reluctant to talk even to their partners, let alone an outsider, about their sexual problems. A 74-year-old man from Long Island who has had erectile dysfunction since his 20's, particularly in relationships that lasted for a while,  could never quite talk to his wife of 25 years about the problem. ''I would tend to kind of brush the problem under the rug,'' he said. ''It isn't an easy topic to deal with. It goes to the heart of your masculinity.''</p>
        <p>After a divorce, he became involved with a much younger woman. ''Let's be candid,'' he said. ''Obviously, that is a stimulating situation for a male.'' But his problem recurred. ''I do think that had we had a more active sex life, perhaps my marriage could have been saved,'' he said.  ''And I am quite certain that in the 20-year live-in relationship that followed, had the sexual part been better, that would have gone on.''</p>
        <p>He is convinced that Viagra is the answer to his lifelong sexual problem and that no amount of therapy would help. ''When you're dealing  with circulatory problem, all the talking in the world doesn't make any difference,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The woman from Queens went into therapy alone and kept her emotional journey to herself. ''Therapy was helpful to me,'' she said. ''I felt like it made me understand that this was just one more thing to deal with, not the end of the world.''</p>
        <p>Yet in a review of dozens of E-mail sites, including an impotence support group site and Viagra chat rooms, almost all the postings were limited to questions about where to obtain the drug, its possible side effects or concerns that seem almost akin to choosing a new dry cleaner: ''Since the 100-mg strength and the 50-mg cost about the same,'' read an E-mail message from Carl, ''it seems that getting 100's and splitting them would be beneficial financially.''</p>
        <p>Or the messages brag about the new sexual prowess afforded to Viagra users: ''Took 100 mgs last night and had great five hours of fun,'' wrote someone identified as Bump. ''Did have a bit of a headache, but went away with some ibuprofen after about an hour. Of course being up till 3 A.M. didn't help . . . grin.'' A few  women voiced concern that sex offenders would have a new weapon.</p>
        <p>But next to none of the E-mail  messages seem concerned about the emotions surrounding sexual problems and the effects they had on relationships. Dr. David L. Casey, a  urologist in Denton, Tex., spends a lot of time answering questions about Viagra in Internet chat rooms as a public service.</p>
        <p>But when asked about emotional complications that using Viagra may introduce to a couple's relationship, he replied: ''I really have no comment on such a question. I try to stick with answering technical questions, and really have little time for the sociologic discussions.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
