<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: Don't Cry Over Diving Loonies; Canadian Dollar Plummets to a Collective Ho-Hum</title>
    <meta content="Y23LOO$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1026783"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Canada</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Depalma, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/Canada</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Currency</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980623T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E5DA123CF930A15755C0A96E958260" item-length="1736" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS: Don't Cry Over Diving Loonies; Canadian Dollar Plummets to a Collective Ho-Hum</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY DePALMA</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Depalma, Anthony</byline>
      <dateline>REGINA, Saskatchewan, June 18</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Canada's currency has fallen more than currencies of other industrialized nations; but country is not panicking because its economy is otherwise relatively healthy; Canada's dollar, popularly known as the 'loonie,' is worth around 68 American cents, just above the record low; while exporters may laud currency's depreciation, plenty of Canadians are feeling some pain; importers have watched their profit margins shrink drastically; among clear winners of weaker Canadian dollar are American tourists; charts; graphs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It has become a regular, almost routine, occurrence: another day, another record low for the Canadian dollar.</p>
        <p>The recurring declines that have sent Canada's currency to one low after another since the beginning of this year might have caused a panic in many countries, especially in these jittery economic times when fluctuations in the Japanese yen or the Thai baht send shivers throughout the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It has become a regular, almost routine, occurrence: another day, another record low for the Canadian dollar.</p>
        <p>The recurring declines that have sent Canada's currency to one low after another since the beginning of this year might have caused a panic in many countries, especially in these jittery economic times when fluctuations in the Japanese yen or the Thai baht send shivers throughout the world.</p>
        <p>But this is calm, collected, Canada. Its currency is worth around 68 American cents today, just above the record low. Yet, despite the best attempts of chauvinist columnists and all-news radio stations to stir things up every time the Canadian dollar weakens, Canadians are acting as though pretty much nothing has happened.</p>
        <p>Indeed, not only have most Canadians blandly tolerated the latest, relatively modest, decline of their dollar -- popularly known as the ''loonie'' because the dollar coin bears the image of a common loon on one side -- some are even cheering the currency's steady fall.</p>
        <p>''Every time I see the loonie fall I think 'Yes! All Right!','' said Jack Degelman, a manufacturer and exporter of farm equipment in Regina, Saskatchewan. ''Having a lousy dollar definitely helps us out.''</p>
        <p>A lousy Canadian dollar makes products like the rock pickers produced by Degelman Industries Ltd. cheaper for buyers with American dollars, and Mr. Degelman's sales have been on the rise. Since more than 80 percent of Canadian exports go to the United States, the lopsided exchange rate helps lift the entire manufacturing and export sector.</p>
        <p>That has given Ottawa one big reason not to do much to keep the loonie from sinking. Besides, the overall Canadian economy continues to be strong, with low inflation, attractive growth and the first balanced budget in decades.</p>
        <p>But while exporters may laud the currency's depreciation -- and record numbers of American tourists discover how much further their dollars can go north of the border -- plenty of Canadians are feeling some pain.</p>
        <p>Even with slight improvements that have, at least for now, pushed the loonie back up over 68 cents, importers have watched their profit margins shrink drastically. Canadians who usually flock to Florida and other warm spots in the United States are cutting their trips short or flying directly to Mexico, where the Canadian dollar continues to hold its own against the peso. The Toronto Blue Jays, with their $50 million payroll in American dollars, buy greenbacks months in advance as a safeguard against further currency shocks.</p>
        <p>Despite the depreciation, prices have not yet increased substantially for all the imported food, clothing and other items that Canadians buy every day. But business is warning consumers to be prepared.</p>
        <p>''Canada is a big importing nation,'' said Robert J. Armstrong, president of the Canadian Importers Association, an industry group. ''Apparel, footware, appliances, electronic goods, food stuffs -- we're all going to have to pay a higher price this winter.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Armstrong said the federal Government had not acted to arrest the dollar's slide because it was focusing almost entirely on the export part of the economy without taking into account how badly the rest of Canada was hurting.</p>
        <p>''We can't cope with a dollar this low,'' he said. ''It's not good for the country.''</p>
        <p>But his pleas are falling on mostly deaf ears. Government economists preach pragmatism and patience. Canada's official policy is to let the market set the value of the loonie against the United States dollar and other currencies. While the rate is supposed to float freely, the Bank of Canada -- the country's central bank -- can influence currency exchange rates by raising or lowering interest rates, which now stand at 4.41 percent for three-month Treasury bills (compared with 5.18 percent for United States T-bills).</p>
        <p>Fundamentally, a weaker Canadian dollar reflects the declining competitiveness of Canadian industry and an oversupply of the natural resources that Canada produces in abundance. Officials argue that allowing the loonie to weaken is the least damaging way to deal with the situation and contend that trying to artificially support it with higher rates would be much worse, hammering investment and consumer spending on big-ticket items.</p>
        <p>Occasionally, the central bank has intervened in the open market to buy back Canadian dollars. But it does so rarely, and then only to stabilize the currency on a particularly volatile day, not to rebuild its value.</p>
        <p>The Bank of Canada enjoys a high degree of independence but it is more under the influence of the elected Government than is the Federal Reserve in the United States. Canada's Minister of Finance appoints directors, who in turn select a bank governor. In the case of disputes over policy, by law it is the Government, through the finance minister, and not the Bank of Canada, that has final say.</p>
        <p>The last time one Canadian dollar was worth one American dollar was in late 1976. Since then, the loonie has continuously lost ground, though it had generally stabilized from early 1994 to last summer, when the decline resumed. But the decline has been gradual, minimizing the impact. And even this year, while the exchange rate has bounced through several record lows, the cumulative depreciation so far is under 3 percent, far less than the huge declines of several Asian currencies in the last year.</p>
        <p>Economists here generally attribute the currency's latest dips to outside factors, particularly the Asian economic situation itself, which has dampened demand for the natural resources and other commodities that Canada produces. ''Canada's resources sector is besieged by plummeting prices,'' said Jeff Rubin, chief economist at CIBC Wood Gundy in Toronto. Over all, the Canadian dollar, like other currencies, has been hurt in part because the tremors in the Asian market have investors seeking out the strongest currency, which is currently the American dollar.</p>
        <p>The economists also credit other factors, including the Bank of Canada's reluctance to raise interest rates to levels equivalent to those offered in the United States, and, to a lesser degree, lingering worries over a possible fall election in the restless province of Quebec.</p>
        <p>None of this seems to overly concern federal officials. Prime Minister Jean Chretien has been predicting since January that the Canadian dollar's slide will not last. Speaking before New York investors in March, he blamed currency speculators ''in red suspenders'' for causing fluctuations in the exchange rate.</p>
        <p>But some economists think the problems are more serious. ''We might as well take the loonie and rename it the ugly duckling because it only looks good against Asian currencies,'' said David A. Rosenberg, senior economist for Nesbitt Burns Inc., a Toronto firm. He believes that for the situation to be reversed, the Bank of Canada must raise interest rates, even if doing so hurts exports.</p>
        <p>''Some people may feel we can devalue our way to prosperity,'' Mr. Rosenberg said, ''but the ever-weakening Canadian dollar is nothing more than a tax hike on all Canadians.''</p>
        <p>Most economists do not think the loonie's slide has ended. Some expect to see the Canadian dollar drop to as low as 65 cents to the dollar. That further complicates things for Canadian companies that are already struggling to cope with the worsening exchange rate.</p>
        <p>Take the Toronto Blue Jays. About 80 percent of the baseball team's income is in Canadian dollars, but 80 percent of its expenditures are in American dollars. That includes travel, lodging and the club's roughly $50 million payroll.</p>
        <p>To protect itself from depreciation of the dollar, the team tries to forecast its cash requirement and then relies on currency experts at banks and investment houses to lock in its position by buying American dollars in advance, said Susan Quigley, vice president of finance and administration for the Blue Jays.</p>
        <p>For most Canadians though, adjusting to the weakened dollar has simply meant tightening their belts.</p>
        <p>''We used to go down to the States at least two or three times a year, but the dollar is so low we can't afford to do that any more,'' said David Crocker, a swimming pool store owner from Brantford, Ontario. He and his wife, Judy, were spending the day at a casino on the Canadian side of Niagara Falls, where a Canadian dollar buys four slot machine tokens, but an American dollar brings almost six.</p>
        <p>After a day at the casino, the Crockers usually cross the border to Buffalo or Niagara Falls, N.Y., to have dinner. This time, they said, the limping loonie forced them to stay in Canada.</p>
        <p>''We just can't afford it,'' Mr. Crocker said.</p>
        <p>The ups and mostly downs of the exchange rate have been a nightmare for Janet Ellen Lee, who lives in Niagara Falls, Ontario. In September, she and her husband will have two daughters attending universities in the United States.</p>
        <p>''We had cashed in some of our investments,'' Mrs. Lee said, ''and I remember waking up in the middle of the night wondering if it would be enough when we converted the money into American dollars.''</p>
        <p>The clear winners in all this include Americans, like Darla M. Brown of Ellenton, Fla., who find more money in their purses as soon as they cross the border into Canada.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Brown, visiting Casino Niagara, in Niagara Falls, had settled comfortably in front of the $1 slots. She had given herself a $100-a-day limit, but with the exchange rate, her $100 bought her 145 tokens.</p>
        <p>Which may or may not have been a fortunate thing.</p>
        <p>''If you're just playing and planning on losing anyway,'' she said, ''you've just got that much more to lose.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
