<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Culture Zone; Sorority Sisters</title>
    <meta content="22CULTURT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1063948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0DE5DE1F31F931A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1086" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Culture Zone; Sorority Sisters</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Deborah Solomon</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I'm glad I never met Julia Margaret Cameron. She seems to have been the sort of woman who craved the company of powerful men but had little use for women. She spoke of her male friends as if they were gods; her art was her ticket into their kingdom. Cameron, one of the leading portrait photographers of 19th-century England, captured the illustrious figures of her time -- Darwin, Longfellow and Tennyson among them. And which women did she photograph? Mainly the maids who dusted her curtains and served her tea.</p>
        <p>Curiously, however, Cameron is now being celebrated as an avatar of sisterhood, the Gloria Steinem of Victorian photography. I refer you to ''Julia Margaret Cameron's Women,'' the title of a traveling exhibition and accompanying jumbo-size book. Sorry, Darwin, and sorry, Longfellow: you guys didn't make the cut. The show (it's now at the Art Institute of Chicago and opens at the Museum of Modern Art on Jan. 28) confines itself to Cameron's photographs of pale British women, granting them a pantheon of their own.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I'm glad I never met Julia Margaret Cameron. She seems to have been the sort of woman who craved the company of powerful men but had little use for women. She spoke of her male friends as if they were gods; her art was her ticket into their kingdom. Cameron, one of the leading portrait photographers of 19th-century England, captured the illustrious figures of her time -- Darwin, Longfellow and Tennyson among them. And which women did she photograph? Mainly the maids who dusted her curtains and served her tea.</p>
        <p>Curiously, however, Cameron is now being celebrated as an avatar of sisterhood, the Gloria Steinem of Victorian photography. I refer you to ''Julia Margaret Cameron's Women,'' the title of a traveling exhibition and accompanying jumbo-size book. Sorry, Darwin, and sorry, Longfellow: you guys didn't make the cut. The show (it's now at the Art Institute of Chicago and opens at the Museum of Modern Art on Jan. 28) confines itself to Cameron's photographs of pale British women, granting them a pantheon of their own.</p>
        <p>When, exactly, did the history of art become a sorority? The Cameron show is just the latest in an unsettling flurry of girls-only exhibitions; in the museum world, nothing's more chichi than she-she shows. I'm not talking about shows of work by female artists, but rather shows devoted to the theme of womanhood -- shows, in other words, in which every single work of art depicts a woman who might be either ancient or modern, dressed or undressed, heroic or just a chain-smoking wreck. ''Picasso and the Weeping Women,'' for instance, at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, rounded up paintings of Picasso's endless lovers and redefined the founder of Cubism as someone who liked to see girls cry. It wasn't clear whether you were supposed to admire the art or just bond with the women in it.</p>
        <p>Mothers, too, are getting new respect on the museum circuit. Consider ''Farewell to the Wet Nurse,'' a show of 18th-century French pictures now at the Clark Art Institute in Williamstown, Mass. Usually when we think of ancien regime painting, we think of the rococo fantasies of Boucher or Fragonard. Yet this is an exhibition devoted instead to the lactating set -- images of breast-feeding mothers!</p>
        <p>Womanhood, of course, is one of the grand themes of art, but that doesn't mean it's an interesting topic for an exhibition. When you go to a museum, you want to have an esthetic experience, to escape your own head and enter someone else's imagination. Such leaps aren't possible when art is treated as an illustration of the female condition -- a dreary, overly literal approach that strips works of art of all nuance and complexity. On the other hand, it isn't hard to explain the vogue for such shows. What began a few years ago as an earnest exercise in feminist scholarship has turned out to be a marketing smash hit. Men like to look at women. And women like to look at women, too. As Hollywood has always known, the female body is box-office gold.</p>
        <p>Besides, how else can you celebrate womanhood at a moment when there aren't any more female artists left to discover? The neglected female daubers of the past by now have become pop icons. Georgia O'Keeffe, America's favorite desert prophet, got her own museum in Santa Fe last year. Frida Kahlo -- she of the single eyebrow and multiple wounds -- has had her agonies reproduced on calendars and coffee mugs. Even Artemisia Gentileschi, a capable, B-minus, Baroque painter whose work almost no one has actually seen, was vaulted into stardom last spring with the release of the soft-core Miramax movie ''Artemisia.''</p>
        <p>Which brings us back to Julia Margaret Cameron, the latest candidate for art sainthood. The current show of her photographs is the first I know of that comes with a double feminist twist, featuring images of women by a female artist. Surely it represents the next generation of museum shows: by women, of women, for women. As applied to Cameron, the concept smacks of the absurd. A spirited woman who took up photography in middle age, she believed that genius was a male trait; in her photographs she favored blurry, out-of-focus effects that made her male sitters look sensual and spontaneous while hinting at the trembling excitement she felt in their presence.</p>
        <p>To be sure, Cameron took some wonderful pictures of at least one woman: her niece Julia Jackson, the mother of Virginia Woolf, capturing her as a soulful beauty gazing out from thick shadows. Yet the other women in Cameron's photographs remain mostly unidentified; in fact, they're just props. Cameron liked to have her maids dress up in costumes and pose as mythological or biblocal characters; they appear in her pictures as anonymous lasses who swoon in gardens and do other melodramatic things involving flowers. If this sounds like standard Victorian fluff, it is. Without the stimulus of a famous male face, Cameron was lost.</p>
        <p>Yet now her images of women have been gathered into their own gushy show. The photographs were taken in the 1860's, but they seem close in spirit to the 1960's; all that long hair, all those searching gazes and flowing dresses, remind me of a Judy Collins album cover. Maybe the show is supposed to bring female baby boomers back to their flower-child roots, to evoke the days when we ourselves had frizzy hair and spent our afternoons swaying to folk music in our girlfriends' bedrooms.</p>
        <p>As gratifying as that memory may be, it doesn't have a whole lot to do with the wonder years of early photography or the pioneering role that Cameron played in elevating the medium into an art form. But then that's the point. The Cameron show wasn't conceived to highlight her best work or to clarify her achievements as an artist, but to warmly welcome a new sister into the sorority of art -- Sigma Delta Picassoette. And the truth is that we, too, have been tapped for that sorority. We once went to museums to muse on masterpieces. Now we go to muse on female muses. It's enough to fill me with a Cameron-like craving for bearded faces: Please, bring back the guys.</p>
        <p>Deborah Solomon, an art critic and biographer, is a regular contributor to the magazine.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Deborah Solomon, an art critic and biographer, is a regular contributor to the magazine.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
