<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From/Pleasantville; Young Voices Ring Out: Next Stop, Maybe, Fame</title>
    <meta content="22VIEW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1064020"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Pleasantville (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dreamcoat Singers (Music Group)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ames, Lynne</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9407EED81630F931A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1192" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From/Pleasantville; Young Voices Ring Out: Next Stop, Maybe, Fame</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Ames, Lynne</byline>
      <dateline>PLEASANTVILLE</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Dreamcoat Singers, nonprofit group of professionally-trained young singers in Pleasantville, NY; pre-teens and teenage members comment; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAYBE it is a coincidence, but the youngsters in the Dreamcoat Singers all seem unusually nice. The nonprofit, professionally trained group was rehearsing in a rented hall here on a recent Saturday and not one of the 34 members was even slightly snobbish, sour or snidely hip, the way preteen-agers and teen-agers can sometimes be around strangers. In fact, they were eager to talk about their singing, their budding social consciences and their performance season.</p>
        <p>Nikki Yarnell, an articulate 14-year-old from Rye, mused aloud about the concepts of talent, ambition and gratitude for one's natural gifts. Blessed with a strong, sweet soprano voice, she said she particularly likes those concerts that the group gives to benefit the needy. The Dreamcoat Singers have raised money for the Children's Cancer Research Center of New York Medical College in Valhalla, the Lord's Pantry, a food program based in White Plains for people with AIDS and the Red Cross. They also perform at nursing homes and hospitals throughout the county.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAYBE it is a coincidence, but the youngsters in the Dreamcoat Singers all seem unusually nice. The nonprofit, professionally trained group was rehearsing in a rented hall here on a recent Saturday and not one of the 34 members was even slightly snobbish, sour or snidely hip, the way preteen-agers and teen-agers can sometimes be around strangers. In fact, they were eager to talk about their singing, their budding social consciences and their performance season.</p>
        <p>Nikki Yarnell, an articulate 14-year-old from Rye, mused aloud about the concepts of talent, ambition and gratitude for one's natural gifts. Blessed with a strong, sweet soprano voice, she said she particularly likes those concerts that the group gives to benefit the needy. The Dreamcoat Singers have raised money for the Children's Cancer Research Center of New York Medical College in Valhalla, the Lord's Pantry, a food program based in White Plains for people with AIDS and the Red Cross. They also perform at nursing homes and hospitals throughout the county.</p>
        <p>''Everyone has his or her own definition of comfortable -- you can be materially well off but emotionally unhappy,'' Nikki said. ''But if you go by the definition that someone who is comfortable is someone whose life is supplied with enough food, with substantial housing and with relatively good health, then all of us here in this group are comfortable. We have a lot to be grateful for at Thanksgiving and all year. I feel that we are lucky to have a talent -- singing -- that can help people, whether by raising money or simply by making them a little happier when they listen to us.''</p>
        <p>On Dec. 21 at 7 P.M. the choir will perform at the Westchester Broadway Dinner Theater in Elmsford, with some of the proceeds going back to the group and some to Camp Viva, a camp in Pawling for children who have AIDS or whose family members have it. Entitled ''Holiday From the Heart,'' the program will feature Christmas and Hanukkah songs and dances. Tickets are $25, $20 for students and $40 for box seats. The number to call for information or to book the group is 835-6750.</p>
        <p>Joey Pirone, 16, from Thornwood who wears his baseball caps backward, has an earring and sings in a rock band, is looking forward to this concert. He is keenly aware of the way life can turn someone from fortunate to unfortunate in a frighteningly short time. ''Look at Christopher Reeve,'' he said of the actor, now paraplegic after a horse-riding accident. ''Things can go wrong in an instant. One second can change everything. If my singing can make someone who has had something bad happen to them feel better, that's great.''</p>
        <p>The group also benefits the singers. Boys and girls 10 through 17 from Westchester and Putnam Counties, they audition each year and generally have high levels of talent and theatrical ambition, said Gerry Micera, music director of the group and a music teacher in the Pleasantville school system, and George Puello, artistic director. Ann Hopwood of Harrison, president of the group's board of directors and mother of Heather, 15, an alto, added: ''They have an opportunity to work at a high level with other young people with similar interests. They rehearse and practice every Saturday for six hours and and then they do more hours during the week.''</p>
        <p>The work, however, is perceived as fun by the participants who share common goals with other performers. ''When I've had a rough day at school, I feel so happy when I know I'm coming here in the afternoon,'' Nikki said.</p>
        <p>The choir takes its name from the Andrew Lloyd Webber-Tim Rice musical ''Joseph and the Amazing Technicolor Dreamcoat.'' When the show had a revival on Broadway in 1993, open auditions were held for a choir of young people. Most choirs that tried out were already established at schools, but two Yonkers women, Abbe Harkavy and Carol Arrucci, decided to put together a choir made up of the best singers from Westchester and Putnam schools. The Carolabbe Choir, as it was then known, landed the Broadway job. When the show closed a year and a half later, those involved in the choir decided to keep it going as an independent nonprofit group and changed its name to the Dreamcoat Singers. (Two of the original members are still singing with them.)</p>
        <p>The choir began performing for nonprofit organizations and at corporate parties and special events. It also started an affiliation with the Westchester Broadway Theater: Mr. Puello, who is the artistic director there, said he considers the Dreamcoat Singers ''an amazing pool of talented children from which to draw'' and uses its members whenever a show at the theater calls for singing teen-agers and preteen-agers. Members also perform at other local venues, including Yorktown Stage, where, next month they will be doing a version of ''A Christmas Carol,'' written by Mr. Puello. (The show runs Fridays at 8 P.M., Saturdays at 8 P.M. and Sundays at 2 P.M., from Dec. 4 through 20. Tickets are $18 and $22. The number to call for reservations is 962-0606.)</p>
        <p>For members of the group, the choir is a chance to gain professional experience and socialize with fellow aspiring performers. Candice Calabro, 15, an alto from Thornwood, said, ''It's not just music -- we're a bunch of people who really like and understand each other.'' Kaitlyn Delaney, 14, a soprano from Rye, added: ''In regular school, kids gossip all the time; here, because we're all in different schools, there's no gossip; it's just enjoyable.'' Lindsey Budnar, 15, a soprano from Carmel, said, ''It's more fun than regular school.''</p>
        <p>Parents are also happy with what the choir has done for their children. Dr. Gary Yarnell, a veterinarian, and Laurie Yarnell, a public relations consultant, said it gives their daughter Nikki, a freshman at Rye Country Day School, a chance to relax and work on her career simultaneously. ''It's a respite from some of the pressures of school, but it's also a way for her to get incredible performing experience,'' Mrs. Yarnell said. ''And it's interesting -- the choir members are really good kids, really serious about their music, but they're not nerds. They're active, well-rounded kids who happen to be very dedicated.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Yarnell said: ''It's great for these young people to find an outlet for their talents and dreams. At Thanksgiving especially, it's nice to think of these kids, who are blessed with the natural gift of great voices, using that gift to help others.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
