<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In Catskills, Resort's Death Darkens the View</title>
    <meta content="22CONC$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1064294"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Catskills (NYS Area)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Sullivan County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Concord Resort Hotel</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders Union</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Chen, David W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parker, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/Catskills</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bankruptcies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hotels and Motels</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E3DE1130F931A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="2049" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In Catskills, Resort's Death Darkens the View</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID W. CHEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Chen, David W</byline>
      <dateline>MONTICELLO, N.Y., Nov. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Over 400 people lost their jobs when legendary Concord Resort Hotel in Catskills closed on Nov 3; Robert Parker, whose family has owned hotel since 1937, made tearful announcement; hotel is tentatively scheduled to be auctioned on Dec 2 at Federal Bankruptcy Court in White Plains; Concord workers criticize Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders Union Local 76 for refusing to allow them to draw early from their $6.8 million pension fund; they have placed heavy demands on Sullivan County economy that was already pinched; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It wasn't supposed to end this way. Not this personally. Not this jarringly.</p>
        <p>Everyone knew that the legendary Concord Resort Hotel in the Catskills was past its prime, unable to bring the tourists back to what was once the crown jewel of the resort area. Everyone knew that the hotel was in financial distress and desperate to attract buyers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It wasn't supposed to end this way. Not this personally. Not this jarringly.</p>
        <p>Everyone knew that the legendary Concord Resort Hotel in the Catskills was past its prime, unable to bring the tourists back to what was once the crown jewel of the resort area. Everyone knew that the hotel was in financial distress and desperate to attract buyers.</p>
        <p>Still, when the Concord closed on Nov. 3 after 61 years under the same family, the shutdown hurt more than anyone could have imagined. More than 400 people lost their jobs, including many who had scraped by as full-time workers for 40 years at this hotel in Sullivan County. About 60 employees who had been living in the hotel suddenly became homeless and found their next meal at a soup kitchen. And everyone, it seemed, began flooding local employment and welfare offices, looking for guidance and help.</p>
        <p>''When you've got to change your priorities from 'What do we do for our vacation?' to 'What are we going to do for dinner or pay the rent?' it changes your priorities a lot,'' said Wesley Katz, 41, a former security guard at the Concord who was eating lunch at Tom's Program Soup Kitchen, the only soup kitchen in Monticello. ''I'm a diabetic, too, so I have to make sure I have some medical coverage.''</p>
        <p>The failure of the Concord was marked with various elegiac testimonials to the end of what had been a beloved institution, but those impressive words have done little or nothing for the people who sweated to make the Concord run so smoothly. Those people -- the waitresses, the busboys, the porters -- are suffering mightily.</p>
        <p>The county has relatively few residents -- about 70,000 -- and its support services are small enough to be easily strapped. Although the county has had low unemployment, the 400 who lost their jobs at the Concord, when added to the 500 other jobs lost in the county this year, have placed heavy demands on an economy that was already pinched.</p>
        <p>For some time, it had not been easy to find a job -- not in Kiamesha Lake, the community where the Concord is located, not in Monticello, the county seat and a village of 6,800, nor in the other nearby communities in the mountain region.</p>
        <p>''I'm afraid that these people who have hung in there with the hotel for so long are going to put a strain on the local economy,'' said Mayor Gary Sommers of Monticello. ''I don't know what this is going to do to the crime level, the homeless level, the welfare level. We're very apprehensive, because the ripple effect is unbelievable.''</p>
        <p>The former Concord workers say that almost all have applied for unemployment benefits, and that some have applied for welfare and Medicaid. Karen Burns, executive director of the Sullivan County Federation for the Homeless, a nonprofit agency that operates Tom's Program Soup Kitchen, said it has been feeding twice as many people as normal since the Concord closed. The United Way has worked with county and state agencies to set up an emergency site to help steer people to jobs and retraining programs.</p>
        <p>A Wal-Mart that is to open next year will help some, said Jonathan Drapkin, the County Manager, but since winter is approaching, others believe that the worst is yet to come.</p>
        <p>''I don't think we've seen the crunch of what's going to happen,'' said Linda Cellini, chief professional officer for the United Way of Sullivan County. ''We don't have enough to meet the needs of our county normally, so this extra burden on the emergency food and shelter needs is just going to make things worse.''</p>
        <p>Anyone who has never been to the Catskills may well wonder: Why didn't the Concord workers get out earlier? After all, there were plenty of warning signs: the hotel's bankruptcy, its pursuit of financial suitors, its loss of guests to entertainment sites as far away as Atlantic City and beyond.</p>
        <p>But talking about changing jobs is usually easier than doing it, especially after you have worked at a good-paying job at the same place for so long. More than half the employees had put in more than the 10 years required to qualify for a union pension. And in years past, some of the workers said, they could get by in the Catskills on the $10,000 to $30,000 a year they took in at the Concord.</p>
        <p>And yet, there was something else about the Concord that made it more than just a place to draw a paycheck. Some employees had come from New York City, 90 miles away, and had found rural life soothing. Others had checkered pasts before coming to the Concord, and found a second chance here. Still others enjoyed the camaraderie with the longtime guests who returned often over the years. They came to know many of them by their first names.</p>
        <p>''We had a lot of good times, and everyone was like family,'' said Marilyn Gill, 56, a Queens native who worked as a waitress at the Concord for 26 years. ''We really wanted to believe that there would be a last-minute miracle. We were in denial.''</p>
        <p>The hope had been that the hotel, about $20 million in debt, might make it through the holiday season and that an interested investor would snap it up and keep it going. But on Nov. 3, Robert Parker, whose family has owned the hotel since 1937, made his tearful announcement that the hotel would be unable to continue.</p>
        <p>All the workers lost their jobs and benefits with only a few days' notice, and those who were living in the hotel, or the adjacent dilapidated bungalows, also had to pack their belongings and look for shelter.</p>
        <p>It was an abrupt end for an institution that had courted performers like Jackie Mason and Buddy Hackett, appealed to people seeking a refuge from New York and become a popular place for people to be married or celebrate a bar mitzvah.</p>
        <p>Now, only a skeletal staff of about 30 people remains, mainly security and maintenance workers. The hotel is tentatively scheduled to be auctioned on Dec. 2 at Federal Bankruptcy Court in White Plains. And while there has been much talk about potential bidders who might renovate the 1,710-acre resort, no one professes to know what will happen.</p>
        <p>''It's very hard for me to talk about,'' Mr. Parker said in a telephone interview, his voice cracking. ''It's a tremendous effect, psychologically and everything else. When you let go employees you've known for 30 years, what do you tell them?''</p>
        <p>For union employees, the shock has been aggravated by the actions of their union, Local 76 of the Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders Union. The workers said the local had refused to allow them to draw early from their $6.8 million pension fund. The local also says they cannot draw their pensions until they are 65, although the contract provides for retirement at 60. The workers said officials at the local maintained that the hotel's closure had nullified the contract.</p>
        <p>The changes would mean that Ms. Gill would have to wait another nine  years to receive her $550 a month and that Jorge Pelosi, 33, who has worked at the Concord as a busboy for 16 years, would have to wait until he is 65 to receive a pension of perhaps $250 a month.</p>
        <p>Union officials did not return calls requesting comment.</p>
        <p>Today, more than 150 union employees attended a rally of union members, organized by Ms. Gill, Pat Kislowski and Joe Blum to challenge the union local leadership. ''Just give us something now, because we don't know if there will be any money left in the future,'' said Ms. Gill, at the rally at Apollo Plaza, a strip mall in Monticello. ''Otherwise, we're all going to be wards of the county.''</p>
        <p>How much workers can get from the union remains to be seen, since they cannot afford a lawyer, and they have had little help so far from the State Department of Labor. But if anything, the rally was more for commiseration than confrontation.</p>
        <p>Ramon Martinez, who turned 60 today, had worked as a chef at the Concord since 1958. He had hoped to retire soon; more immediately, he had been planning to visit his ailing 89-year-old mother in Puerto Rico this winter. But not anymore. ''It's been a shock, just a shock,'' said a sullen Mr. Martinez, who has applied for jobs at three hotels in the area.  ''I'm scared.''</p>
        <p>Linda DaCosta, 50, is worried, too. She had worked as a waitress at the Concord since 1988, but she and the union disagree on how much time she put in; she says 10 years, the union says 9. She has had to cut back on some things, like taking her grandson to a store to buy a toy, like going out to a restaurant or a movie once in a while.</p>
        <p>''I can't afford that extra $5 or $10,'' she said. ''People ask me, 'What's the difference?' and I joke around with them, sort of. I say to them, 'It's the difference between cat food and tuna fish.' ''</p>
        <p>Those hardest hit may be the workers who lived at the Concord.</p>
        <p>When Ernest Parker (bartender, 12 years) and Robert Matthews (cook, 2 years) left, they found nothing but a dingy room at the Heritage Motel for $140 a week. Both have had no luck finding work; both have vouchers from the county for a one-way bus ticket to New York.</p>
        <p>Charles Bowman, 38, a Brooklyn native who had worked in the hotel's dining room for three years, is trying a different tack: he is staying in the bungalows illegally, without a phone and barely enough heat. An asthmatic who has no car, Mr. Bowman has to walk about an hour each way to the employment office to look at the latest jobs. So far, nothing.</p>
        <p>Frank Wilson, 52, is also a Brooklyn native -- Bedford-Stuyvesant. Until two years ago, he had never left home. Then, when he heard there was work in the Catskills, he took the next bus and got a job, with room and board, as a porter at the Concord. When the hotel closed, he had no car and no family nearby and moved in with a friend.</p>
        <p>''This is my first time in a soup kitchen, but I do what the Romans do,'' Mr. Wilson said softly, as he ate a piece of kielbasa. ''I didn't feel I'd end up like this.''</p>
        <p>Disappearing In the Catskills</p>
        <p>The closing of the Concord Resort Hotel leaves only a handful of the famous Catskills resorts.</p>
        <p>Earlier this year, the acknowledged queen of the hotels, Grossinger's, closed after steadily declining for years, said John Conway, the Sullivan County historian. So, too, did the Pines, which was in South Fallsburg and, like many of the hotels, became prominent in the 1930's.</p>
        <p>Other names from the past have been closed for much longer. The Flagler closed in the early 1970's, and is now the Crystal Run School for developmentally disabled children. Four hotels -- the Brickman, the Windsor, the Gilberts and the Nemerson -- have also been closed since the early 1970's and are now part of a collection of private religious centers operated by the followers of an Indian guru, Mr. Conway said.</p>
        <p>The Stevensville closed in the early 1980's, Mr. Conway said. But its new owners plan to reopen it in early 1999 as the Swan Lake Golf and Tennis Resort Center, said Jonathan Drapkin, the Sullivan County Manager. It will join Kutsher's -- whose patriarch, Milton Kutsher, died last week [Obituary, page 55] -- and the Raleigh as the only vestiges of the region's storied past.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
