<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Bach to 'Butterfly,' A Very Full Day</title>
    <meta content="22MUSI$18" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1064081"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00EFD81430F931A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="799" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Bach to 'Butterfly,' A Very Full Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TODAY may be the busiest concert day of the year. ''Beauty and the Beast,'' the classic tale retold with classical music and puppets as well, is an entertainment suitable for children at 1, 3 and 5 P.M. this afternoon at Jorgensen Auditorium in Storrs.</p>
        <p>At 3 o'clock, at the Rich Forum in Stamford, a recital will be given by the violinist Hilary Hahn, who plays Bach's Solo Partita No. 1, then sonatas by Beethoven and Brahms with the pianist Andrius Zlabys.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TODAY may be the busiest concert day of the year. ''Beauty and the Beast,'' the classic tale retold with classical music and puppets as well, is an entertainment suitable for children at 1, 3 and 5 P.M. this afternoon at Jorgensen Auditorium in Storrs.</p>
        <p>At 3 o'clock, at the Rich Forum in Stamford, a recital will be given by the violinist Hilary Hahn, who plays Bach's Solo Partita No. 1, then sonatas by Beethoven and Brahms with the pianist Andrius Zlabys.</p>
        <p>Also at 3 are the following: works for violin and harp at the Hartford Seminary by Anhared Stowe and Susan Knapp; chamber music for flute, guitar and cello performed by the Vinci-Brown-Alton Trio at the Keeler Tavern Museum in Ridgefield, and at Naugatuck Valley College, actors from the Yale School of Drama and the Waterbury Symphony in Mendelssohn's incidental music to ''A Midsummer Night's Dream.''</p>
        <p>In Stamford at 4 o'clock today, one can enjoy works by Bach, Widor and more in a free organ recital by Curtis Pierce at St. John's Episcopal Church, or Connecticut Grand Opera and Orchestra's production of Puccini's ''Madama Butterfly'' at the Palace Theater. Period instruments will be used at St. Stephen's Church in Ridgefield when the Connecticut Early Music Festival Ensemble performs a program called ''The Glory of Dresden,'' and in United Church on the Green in New Haven, a period instrument orchestra will be on hand to help the soloists and choir perform Haydn's ''Lord Nelson'' Mass and one of Handel's Chandos Anthems, under the direction of Mark Brombaugh. In yet another 4 o'clock concert today, at the Central Middle School, the Greenwich Symphony under David Gilbert showcases works by Mozart, Barber and Berlioz as well as Sibelius's Violin Concerto with Brian Lewis as guest soloist.</p>
        <p>One can also opt for jazz today at 4 P.M. with the Bill Charlap Quartet (the guitarist Bucky Pizzarelli, the bassist Jay Leonhart and Warren Vache on trumpet) at the Pequot Library in Southport, or at 5:30 with the Saundra Silliman Quartet at the Rich Forum in Stamford.</p>
        <p>Winding up the day is a classical performance at 7:30 in Ives Hall, Western Connecticut State University, when the Danbury Concert Chorus under Leslie Eckstein performs Mozart's Te Deum, Brahms's ''Alto Rhapsody'' (with the mezzo-soprano Amy Champagne as soloist) and Benjamin Britten's ''Ceremony of Carols.'' (The chorus, by the way, begins rehearsals for its Dec. 20 ''Messiah'' performance on Tuesday, and welcomes more singers for the occasion. The number to call for more information is (203) 748-1617.</p>
        <p>Once Thanksgiving comes, of course, the Yuletide rush begins in earnest, the first arrivals including ''A Christmas Carol'' and ''The Nutcracker.'' The Nebraska Theater Caravan production of the Dickens classic includes more than 40 actors, singers, dancers and musicians. There are 2 and 7 P.M. Saturday shows at the Shubert in New Haven as well as a matinee at 2 next Sunday. The box office number is (203) 562-5666.</p>
        <p>Hartford Ballet is setting the Tchaikovsky dance favorite in the foothills of the Sierra Nevadas, and bringing such legendary folks as Black Bart and Mark Twain to the party scene. It is ''The American Nutcracker,'' with more than 125 local children joining their professional elders for seven performances at the Bushnell: opening night is Thanksgiving Day at 7:30, with Friday and Saturday curtains at 2:30 and 7 P.M. and matinees next Sunday at 1 and 5 (860-987-590).</p>
        <p>Connecticut has a new arts organization, called Greater Waterbury Classic Concerts. ''Our mission,'' says the nonprofits group's marketing director, Marsha Stein, ''is to bring to the area a high quality chamber music series, as well as to further the educational and performance opportunities of Greater Waterbury's talented young musicians.''</p>
        <p>Teikyo Post University is the venue for next Sunday afternoon's Waterbury presentation, as the Ars Classica Trio -- the violinists Routa Kroumovitch and Alvaro Gomez and the pianist Michael Rickman -- convene at 3 o'clock to perform duos and trios by Mozart, Martinu, Wieniawski, Shostakovich and Moszkowski. The number to call for more information about the new society is (203) 754-5590.</p>
        <p>Four artists, all of whom have appeared in past seasons at one or more of the Wilton Candelight Concerts, have now formed a chamber group, and so it is that the violinist Ida Kavafian, the violist Steve Tenenbaum, the cellist Peter Wiley (all of whom are Fairfield County residents) and the pianist Anne Marie McDermott will be making their ensemble debut in Wilton as Opus 1. Their 4 P.M. program in the Congregational Church next Sunday lists the Kodaly Duo for Violin and Cello as well as Piano Quartets by Mozart and Brahms (203-762-3401).</p>
        <p>MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
