<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sharing the World of Kipling on Stage</title>
    <meta content="22GOOD$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Theater; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1064047"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Goodspeed Opera House</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Willis, Karen Meister</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Miller, Julie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0DEFDB1730F931A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sharing the World of Kipling on Stage</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JULIE MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Miller, Julie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on work of Karen Meister Willis, first director of educational outreach at Goodspeed Opera House, in providing Korn Elementary School in Durham, Conn, with visiting artists, teachers' workshops and performances aimed at fostering appreciation of musical theater; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN an age of computers and video games, students at Korn Elementary School in Durham are reading stories written by Rudyard Kipling.</p>
        <p>The third and fourth graders are also learning firsthand about American musical theater through a study  of ''Just So,'' a new musical inspired by Kipling's ''Just So Stories.'' The stories, published in 1902, include the  tales of ''How the Whale Got His Throat,'' ''How the Camel Got His Hump'' and ''How the Rhinoceros Got His Skin.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN an age of computers and video games, students at Korn Elementary School in Durham are reading stories written by Rudyard Kipling.</p>
        <p>The third and fourth graders are also learning firsthand about American musical theater through a study  of ''Just So,'' a new musical inspired by Kipling's ''Just So Stories.'' The stories, published in 1902, include the  tales of ''How the Whale Got His Throat,'' ''How the Camel Got His Hump'' and ''How the Rhinoceros Got His Skin.''</p>
        <p>The musical opened this month at the Goodspeed Opera House's second stage, Goodspeed-at-Chester/The Norma Terris Theater.</p>
        <p>Goodspeed is providing Korn School with visiting artists, a teachers' workshop and a performance intended to help foster an appreciation of musical theater. Over the last six years, the school has been restoring its programs in the arts, which were lost due to budget cuts, said the principal, Robert Wolfe.</p>
        <p>After receiving requests for educational assistance from many schools in the state, Goodspeed hired Karen Meister Willis last summer to be its first director of educational outreach.</p>
        <p>''Towns throughout Connecticut have cut their music and arts programs to the point where school administrators and teachers are looking to the private sector to fill the void,'' said Jennifer Wislocki, director of marketing and public relations at Goodspeed.</p>
        <p>Ms. Willis, a teacher certified in music and theater, created a series of education programs for schools that allows them to choose the program most closely meets their needs. Goodspeed's partnership with Korn School is a pilot project that Ms. Willis expects to eventually offer to other schools, she said.</p>
        <p>The cost to the school for a performance of ''Just So,'' visiting artists and a workshop for teachers is  $6,710, Ms. Wislocki said. The school's parent-teacher organization has agreed to pay for a portion of the project. Other financial support may be obtained from grants and businesses in the community, Mr. Wolfe said.</p>
        <p>An educator's guide, prepared by Ms. Willis, provides learning activities that highlight the geography, zoology and history in ''Just So Stories.'' Workshops, led by teachers, actors, artists, designers and technicians, demonstrate specific techniques to use in the classroom. Artists from ''Just So,'' including the writers, musical director, choreographer and orchestrator, are visiting the school this month to explain to students how a musical is produced. The choreographer will teach fourth graders dance routines from the musical.</p>
        <p>''They'll get as close as anyone can get. They'll experience what goes on backstage in the minds of the actors, musicians and technicians,'' said Michael Price, executive director of Goodspeed Opera House.</p>
        <p>The students are also learning about Kipling's life and times. Kipling, a short story writer, poet and novelist, was born in 1865 in Bombay, India, where his father was the principal of a school of art.</p>
        <p>Since many of his parents' friends and relatives were writers and artists, Kipling became familiar with books and art at an early age. The Indian servants who cared for him taught him the Hindi language and local folklore, which is reflected in ''Just So Stories.''</p>
        <p>In 1883, at the age of 18, Kipling began work in India as a journalist. His feature articles became popular, and some of his poems were published. During this time, he traveled through India and to South Africa, New Zealand, Australia and America. After seven years of news writing, he returned to England, where his stories were widely admired.</p>
        <p>He married an American, Caroline Balestier, and the couple lived in Vermont from 1892 to 1894. But Kipling was unable to adjust to life in America, and he and his family returned to England again. The family settled in the countryside, where the author spent the rest of his life and wrote ''Captains Courageous,'' ''The Jungle Book'' and ''Kim,'' three of his best-known works. In 1907, when he was 42, Kipling won the Nobel prize for literature.</p>
        <p>''Just So,'' written by Anthony Drewe and George Stiles, is one of  100 new musicals, including ''Annie,'' ''Man of La Mancha'' and ''Shenandoah,'' produced by Goodspeed. The opera house, dedicated to the advancement of musical theater, produces three musicals a season on its stage in East Haddam and new musicals at Goodspeed-at-Chester/The Norma Terris Theater. Goodspeed-at-Chester gives artists an opportunity to develop their material through actual production.</p>
        <p>The musical ''Just So'' begins with an empty stage. A voice heard in the darkness is the Eldest Magician, who begins to create his world, filling it with the inventions of his daydreams. The magician creates animals to share his world. One animal that intrigues him is the Elephant's Child, who is on a journey to discover the new world and his place in it. The musical is about that journey.</p>
        <p>''What a resource this is in our back yard,'' said Mr. Wolfe. ''Here's a play based on a great children's book. It's presented at the opera house, a historical landmark. Very few children have been in such a place.'' The secret to capturing the students' interest in the Kipling stories has to do with getting them actively involved, said Ms. Willis, who recalled her experience as director of performing arts at a high school in Florida. ''I started out with some real tough characters,'' she said. ''These kids didn't get any positive reinforcement.''</p>
        <p>At the end of the first semester, Ms. Willis and her students presented a small play for the school. By the end of the first year, they had put together a production so good they invited the town to see it.</p>
        <p>''I didn't care whether or not they were able to read or had math skills,'' said Ms. Willis. ''I gave them a job to do, and they had pride in it. Then they started paying attention to math and geography.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Willis recalled that some of her students were unable to speak English until they started picking up words in a script.</p>
        <p>''They learned English because they were motivated. It's a matter of figuring out what will motivate them,'' she said. ''In many cases, it's the arts.''</p>
        <p>Teachers at Korn School are using ''Just So Stories'' to teach reading and writing. After attending ''Just So,'' students will write their own musicals. They will also be invited to weekly breakfast and book discussion sessions using the Kipling stories.</p>
        <p>''I'll make breakfast for everyone,'' Mr. Wolfe said. ''One of the greatest challenges is creating lifelong learners and readers. Being able to see a live performance and interacting with the people who wrote the show makes a connection between reading and real life.''</p>
        <p>Students gathered in Korn School's gymnasium one day to learn a song from ''Just So.'' They watched Ms. Willis intently as she demonstrated the rhythm of the music by clapping her hands. Then, heads bobbed and small shoulders shifted back and forth to the beat of the recorded music.</p>
        <p>Noreen Oslander, a third-grade teacher who was sitting nearby, discussed her students' reactions to writing of the early 20th century. ''Some of the language in the stories is different from what they're used to,'' she observed. ''We took time to talk about the period in which the stories were written. When they understand that, they can appreciate the language, and they're familiar with vocabulary not ordinarily used in stories today.''</p>
        <p>As the children sang along with Ms. Willis, Nancy Faccadio, a special education teacher, said two of her students were enjoying the music. ''Although they may not understand the stories, I saw them moving to the beat,'' she explained.</p>
        <p>Max Coviello, a student who introduced himself as a shy type, said he told his mother about ''Just So Stories'' and even made up his own tales. ''I haven't published them yet,'' he added.</p>
        <p>Another student, Mary Randazzo, said the stories are a lot better than television. She especially likes the explanation of how the leopard -- ''the 'sclusivest sandiest-yellowest-brownest of them all, a grayish-yellowish catty-shaped kind of beast'' -- got his spots. ''I like the language,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The children said they were glad not to be living in Kipling's time, when there were no video games or fast food. Even so, the author had a good imagination and was very creative. ''He's cool,'' they all added.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
