<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>How the Other Half Gives</title>
    <meta content="20GIVE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1071270"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="PERSONAL BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fabrikant, Geraldine</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">White, Shelby</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gates, Bill (William H)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Turner, Ted</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Welch, John F Jr</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Eisner, Michael D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Weill, Sanford I</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Isenberg, Eugene M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pfeiffer, Eckhard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mark, Reuben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Broad, Eli</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Heimbold, Charles A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Case, Stephen M</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bossidy, Lawrence A</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, Summerfield K Jr</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Philanthropy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E3DB1F3DF933A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="4307" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>How the Other Half Gives</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GERALDINE FABRIKANT and SHELBY WHITE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fabrikant, Geraldine; White, Shelby</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>While some best-paid corporate executives, such as William H Gates and Ted Turner, advertise their donations, others, such as John F Welch of General Electric, say their giving is no one else's business; with huge sums that many chief executives earn, they are increasingly seen as standard-setters in philanthrophy; survey of charitable giving of 12 of best-paid executives of nation's 500 biggest companies focuses on Michael D Eisner of Walt Disney Co, Sanford I Weill of Citigroup, Eugene I Isenberg of Nabors Industries, Eckhard Pfeiffer of Compaq Computer, Reuben Mark of Colgate-Palmolive, Eli Broad of SunAmerica, Charles A Heimbold Jr of Bristol-Myers Squibb, Stephen M Case of America Online, Lawrence A Bossidy of Allied-Signal, and Summerfield K Johnston Jr of Coca-Cola Enterprises; photos; biographical sketches and chart on corporate compensation (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHEN it comes to receiving, many of America's chief executives have clearly been reaping fortunes. When it comes to giving, however, the picture is a lot murkier.</p>
        <p>After all, charity, though tax-subsidized, is a personal matter. Some of the best-paid corporate titans advertise their donations -- witness the recent $100 million gift from William H. Gates of Microsoft for childhood vaccinations or Ted Turner's $1 billion pledge to the United Nations. But others, like John F. Welch Jr. of General Electric, say their giving is nobody else's business and disclose only what the tax laws demand. (Public records show only that Mr. Welch's charitable foundation gave away $134,186 last year.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHEN it comes to receiving, many of America's chief executives have clearly been reaping fortunes. When it comes to giving, however, the picture is a lot murkier.</p>
        <p>After all, charity, though tax-subsidized, is a personal matter. Some of the best-paid corporate titans advertise their donations -- witness the recent $100 million gift from William H. Gates of Microsoft for childhood vaccinations or Ted Turner's $1 billion pledge to the United Nations. But others, like John F. Welch Jr. of General Electric, say their giving is nobody else's business and disclose only what the tax laws demand. (Public records show only that Mr. Welch's charitable foundation gave away $134,186 last year.)</p>
        <p>Yet with the huge sums that many chief executives are making in this era of bull markets and stock options, they are increasingly being seen as standard-setters in philanthropy. ''It's important to give money away,'' Mr. Turner said, ''because the needs are so great and such great wealth is being accumulated.''</p>
        <p>So Money and Business set out to survey the charitable giving of a sampling of the best-paid chief executives at the nation's 500 biggest companies. For this article, ''pay'' was defined broadly, to include all the earnings an executive could have given away last year if he so chose: salary, bonus, other cash compensation and gains from the exercise of stock options -- plus gains from options he elected not to exercise. (The pay data were calculated by Graef Crystal, a compensation expert in San Diego.)</p>
        <p>By that definition, the pay packages of the 12 executives in the sampling ranged from $471.4 million for Michael D. Eisner, chairman of the Walt Disney Company, to $110.4 million for Louis V. Gerstner Jr., chairman of I.B.M. And beyond their pay, of course, some of these executives have other fortunes -- from smart investing or earlier jobs. Four of the 12 are on the latest Forbes magazine list of the 400 richest Americans.</p>
        <p>Information on the executives' giving is harder to come by than the numbers on their pay. Money and Business reviewed the public records of the business leaders' personal foundations, talked to people familiar with their giving, interviewed company officials and, when they would come to the phone, spoke with the executives themselves. Those who were unwilling to answer questions may be donating more than is publicly disclosed, but it is impossible to know.</p>
        <p>The available evidence shows that extremely rich executives can be extremely generous. Eli Broad, chairman of SunAmerica, the insurer in Los Angeles, gave away $11.6 million last year. Sanford I. Weill, chairman of Citigroup, pledged $100 million, over an undisclosed number of years, to the medical school at Cornell University, his alma mater.</p>
        <p>Still, the biggest earners are not necessarily the biggest givers. Charles A. Heimbold Jr., chairman of Bristol Myers-Squibb, had a total pay package of $146.14 million and wrote checks last year for $5 million to a range of charities. The pay package of Eugene M. Isenberg, chairman of Nabors Industries, a Houston oil drilling company, was one-third higher, totaling $209.6 million, and he gave away $2.5 million -- half as much as Mr. Heimbold, and about five times as much, Mr. Isenberg said, as he gives in an average year.</p>
        <p>''To know people's income, sex or age won't give you much insight into their charitable giving or enable you to predict it,'' said Ann Kaplan, editor of Giving USA, an annual report on philanthropy.</p>
        <p>The youngest corporate chief on the list is just discovering charity.</p>
        <p>''It's only in the past two years that I felt I had the wherewithal to give away money,'' said Stephen M. Case, 40, the chairman of America Online, whose personal foundation over that time has grown from $1 million in assets to more than $50 million.</p>
        <p>Of course, personal giving is not the only option for corporate executives. Many can, and do, exercise control over their companies' donations -- a source of status not available to the average giver. Such donations can leave executives in high demand as board members and community leaders.</p>
        <p>Not all chief executives are involved in their companies' foundations. And some, including Mr. Isenberg, do not believe in corporate philanthropy. In other cases, corporate giving mirrors the chief executive's interests; that is the case for I.B.M. and Mr. Gerstner, a company spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Whatever the size of their giving, the wealthiest executives are often quite ordinary when it comes to choosing recipients. Like many other people, they direct much of what they give to religious, educational and health care causes. And their friends and colleagues often get them involved.</p>
        <p>According to Bishop Edward M. Egan, the head of the Roman Catholic Diocese of Bridgeport, Conn., it was Mr. Welch who prompted Mr. Gerstner and Lawrence J. Bossidy, chairman of the Allied Signal Corporation, to become active in the Inner City Foundation, which supports educational and charitable programs, primarily for Catholic institutions but also for other religious and charitable groups.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gerstner was chairman of a recent dinner that raised $1.2 million for the foundation. He also gave $1 million to Faith in the Future, a program run by Bishop Egan that supports Catholic schools.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Welch and Mr. Bossidy also donate money to the Sankaty Head Foundation, which provides college scholarships for caddies at the Sankaty Head Golf Club on Nantucket.</p>
        <p>''Jack and Larry always get the best caddies,'' one longtime member joked.</p>
        <p>Knowing How Much They Have to Give</p>
        <p>The articles on these two pages, by Geraldine Fabrikant and Shelby White, describe the charitable giving of 12 of the highest-paid executives in a sampling of the nation's 500 biggest companies, ranked by market capitalization.</p>
        <p>The data on pay were collected by Graef Crystal, an executive compensation expert, from corporate proxy statements filed for the companies' 1997 fiscal year. Following are explanations for terms in the accompanying charts:</p>
        <p>CASH COMPENSATION: Includes salary, bonus and other cash in an executive's pay package.  GAINS FROM OPTIONS EXERCISED: The difference between the preset, or ''strike'' price of the executive's stock options and the stock price on the date the options were exercised.  ADDITIONAL EXERCISABLE OPTIONS: The gain that the executive would have realized on exercisable options accumulated over time, but not exercised, had he exercised them on the last day of the 1997 fiscal year.  TOTAL COMPENSATION: The sum of the three categories above, representing the earned income that an executive could have given away, if he so chose.  NET WORTH: Estimates from Forbes magazine for those executives in its latest listing of the 400 richest Americans. The executives' rankings on the list were provided by Forbes.</p>
        <p>Michael D. Eisner, 56  company -- The Walt Disney Company  title -- Chairman and chief executive  cash compensation -- $10.7 million  Gains from options exercised -- $460.8 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $0  Total compensation -- $471.5 million  ranking, Forbes 400 286  Net worth $710 million</p>
        <p>THOUGH he has been the honorary chairman of a number of fund-raising benefits in the last several years, Michael D. Eisner, who has been on the Forbes list of the wealthiest Americans since 1993, has not been known for megagifts to charity.</p>
        <p>That is likely to change.</p>
        <p>Last year, Mr. Eisner reaped a stock-option windfall. He had 21.9 million options that were worth $460.8 million at the end of Disney's fiscal year in September 1997. When he cashed them in late that year, they were worth $550 million.</p>
        <p>During 1997, Mr. Eisner also put Disney shares worth about $116 million into his personal foundation. For Mr. Eisner, as for any donor in his situation, the donation had two tax advantages: It reduced his taxable income, perhaps by the full $116 million, and he did not have to pay capital gains taxes on the donated shares.</p>
        <p>For the charitable world, the donation created an important new benefactor. Like all foundations, his must give away about 5 percent of its net asset value annually -- millions of dollars, in this case.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner has said his foundation would help needy children and children with learning disabilities. No details of its giving are yet known, but there are clues to the Eisner family's interests.</p>
        <p>For nearly a decade, Mr. Eisner's wife, Jane, has been on the board of the American Foundation for AIDS Research. ''They have always taken the position that what they give is anonymous,'' said Jerome Radwin, executive vice president of the organization. Mr. Eisner also has contributed more than $1 million to Georgetown University, his son's alma mater. The school's president, the Rev. Leo J. O'Donovan, is on Disney's board.</p>
        <p>Mr. Eisner is president of Disney's foundation, but its giving does not reflect a personal point of view. A company spokesman said: ''It gives in communities where we are physically located. We want to be good neighbors.''</p>
        <p>Sanford I. Weill, 65  company -- Citigroup  title -- Chairman and co-chief executive  cash compensation -- $7.2 million  Gains from options exercised -- $220.2 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $0  Total compensation -- $227.3 million  ranking, Forbes 400 299  Net worth -- $675 million</p>
        <p>SANFORD I. WEILL thinks about charity in the same way he thinks about mergers: big.</p>
        <p>This year, big meant $100 million to Cornell University, which renamed its medical school the Joan and Sanford I. Weill Medical College and Graduate School of Medical Sciences.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Weill has been extremely coy about revealing the number of years over which he is giving his money away, making the real value of his gift hard to figure.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weill has been chairman of the board of overseers of the medical school since 1996 -- and last year was an opportune year for giving. Mr. Weill exercised stock options for a gain of $220 million. Giving away $100 million or some portion of that figure in the same year could have helped him reduce his taxable income.</p>
        <p>On April 30, the day he announced his gift to the medical school, shares of Travelers, where he was then chairman, were selling at $61.1875. ''When the market is up, you feel good about giving,'' Mr. Weill said. Five months later, the price had plummeted to $31.75. On Friday, stock in Citigroup, the company formed from the merger of Citicorp and Travelers, closed at $49.875.</p>
        <p>Mr. Weill has long been aware of the value of the corporate purse.</p>
        <p>In the 1970's, he helped found the National Academy Foundation, based in New York, a group that trains high school students for jobs in the financial industry. American Express, where Mr. Weill was then an executive, assisted with $100,000 to start the program. In 1996, when Mr. Weill was chief executive of Travelers Group, its foundation gave the program $1.2 million.</p>
        <p>The Travelers foundation also gave to the Cornell medical school and to Carnegie Hall, where the recital hall is named for Mr. Weill because of a gift he made in 1983 and where he is chairman of the board. Last year, Carnegie Hall was the site of the Travelers annual meeting.</p>
        <p>Eugene M. Isenberg, 70</p>
        <p>company -- Nabors Industries  title -- Chairman and chief executive  cash compensation -- $1.7 million  Gains from options exercised -- $83.0 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $125.0 million  Total compensation -- $209.7 million</p>
        <p>EUGENE M. ISENBERG doesn't believe that his company should have a corporate foundation. ''Basically, I think it is the shareholders' money,'' Mr. Isenberg said. ''It's not for the executives to make the decision. They should give the money to the shareholders and let them make it.''</p>
        <p>What did Mr. Isenberg himself donate last year? A total of $2.5 million, he said, well above his usual giving of about $500,000 annually.</p>
        <p>Mr. Isenberg's prime cause is education, and the major beneficiary has been his alma mater, the University of Massachusetts. Last year, he pledged $6 million over five years, giving $2 million of that sum in 1997. Separately, he gives $90,000 annually for scholarships at the university in mathematics, engineering, computer science and business.</p>
        <p>''It was time to give something back to education,'' Mr. Isenberg said. ''I could afford to do it, and I did it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Isenberg lives in Palm Beach, Fla., where he makes some donations to the Palm Beach Opera and to a home for abused children. He is sponsoring a fellowship in stroke prevention at the Intercoastal Health Foundation in West Palm Beach.</p>
        <p>The Isenberg family also supports New York's Parkside School for children with learning challenges. This year, Mr. Isenberg pledged to give $750,000 if the school could raise an additional $500,000. ''The headmistress is my daughter's best friend,'' Mr. Isenberg said. ''They came to me 10 years ago. I helped them do a business plan.''</p>
        <p>Eckhard Pfeiffer, 57</p>
        <p>company -- Compaq Computer  title -- President and chief executive  cash compensation -- $4.5 million  Gains from options exercised -- $0  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $188.0 million  Total compensation -- $192.5 million</p>
        <p>ECKHARD PFEIFFER has been in Houston for just eight years, but he is already a familiar figure at charitable events, where gossip columns record his attendance at A-list functions, escorting the socialite Caroline Farb.</p>
        <p>It is not surprising that as one of Houston's most prominent businessmen, he would be invited to join his adopted city's most prominent boards, including those of the Houston Symphony, the Greater Houston Partnership and the M. D. Anderson Cancer Center. He is also on the board of Southern Methodist University in Dallas.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Pfeiffer, who was born in Germany and spent most of his working life in Europe, does not appear to have embraced big-ticket American philanthropy. Mr. Pfeiffer has not established a personal foundation, so there is no public record of his giving, and he declined to comment on his donations. Symphony officials confirmed that he gives to that organization in the range of $7,500 to $10,000 a year, and Compaq says he is a member of the Alexis de Toqueville Society of the United Way, which requires a minimum gift of $10,000.</p>
        <p>Compaq's corporate giving is being reassessed as the company absorbs recent acquisitions: the Digital Equipment Corporation and Tandem Computer. It gave away $4.2 million last year, primarily to education, health, social services and arts programs, mainly in Houston.</p>
        <p>Reuben Mark, 59</p>
        <p>company --  Colgate-Palmolive  title -- Chairman and chief executive  cash compensation -- $3.8 million  Gains from options exercised -- $18.2 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $148.6 million  Total compensation -- $170.6 million</p>
        <p>REUBEN MARK is a company man, having worked for Colgate-Palmolive since he graduated from the Harvard Business School in 1963. He became chief executive in 1984 and has grown wealthy along the way.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mark declined to comment on his giving. But his philanthropic interests seem to focus on education.</p>
        <p>Both Mr. Mark and his wife, Arlene, served a few years ago as trustees of the I Have a Dream program. In that organization, founded by Eugene Lang, a New York industrialist, benefactors adopt classes of primary school students, work with them through junior high and high school and then help them get into college. The project generally involves a financial commitment of $500,000 to $1 million over seven years for each benefactor, and a large commitment of personal time.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mark formerly was a trustee of Bank Street College of Education in New York and is a director of New Visions for Public Schools, which uses private funds to establish small new schools in the city. Colgate-Palmolive is a corporate contributor to the program.</p>
        <p>Eli Broad, 65</p>
        <p>company -- SunAmerica  title -- Chairman and chief executive  cash compensation -- $3.4 million  Gains from options exercised -- $6.2 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $140.2 million  Total compensation -- $149.8 million  ranking, Forbes 400 55  Net worth -- $2.7 billion</p>
        <p>ELI BROAD does not shirk the philanthropic limelight; he is eager to talk about both his views on philanthropy and the size of his gifts.</p>
        <p>''In Los Angeles we don't have a tradition of philanthropy,'' Mr. Broad said in a telephone interview. ''I don't mind being out front, and hopefully others will follow.''</p>
        <p>The single largest beneficiaries of Mr. Broad's giving last year were Pitzer College in Claremont, Calif., at $1.6 million; Michigan State University, $1 million, and the new Disney Hall concert facility in Los Angeles, also $1 million.</p>
        <p>''I also give to United Jewish Appeal,'' Mr. Broad said. ''But I am more interested in the community. Some people fault me for it. They say how can you give to Michigan State and not to some Jewish hospital? But I tell them that you have to do your own thing. I am more a citizen of the city than I am of the Jewish community.''</p>
        <p>His giving is clearly structured with taxes in mind. Last year, he said, his adjusted gross income was $38 million, between pay from SunAmerica and investment income. Mr. Broad said he gave away $11.6 million, or 30 percent of his adjusted gross income -- the maximum a donor can deduct. Mr. Broad, an art collector, put $8 million of that sum into two family foundations: one that provides grants for art students and one that buys art and lends it to museums for exhibits. The two foundations gave away $5.5 million.</p>
        <p>SunAmerica's corporate foundation, he said, gives primarily to charities in the Los Angeles area, like the United Way, and makes grants to local artists.</p>
        <p>Charles A. Heimbold Jr., 65</p>
        <p>company -- Bristol-Myers Squibb  title -- Chairman and chief executive  cash compensation -- $3.8 million  Gains from options exercised -- $25.3 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $117.5 million  Total compensation -- $146.6 million</p>
        <p>WHEN a fire badly damaged Central Synagogue in Manhattan last September, Charles A. Heimbold Jr. quickly wrote a personal check for $25,000 to help with restoration. Though Mr. Heimbold is Roman Catholic, a spokesman for Bristol-Myers Squibb explained that he ''wanted to be a good neighbor.''</p>
        <p>He declined to be interviewed about his giving, but a surprisingly eclectic collection of charities benefited from the $5 million Mr. Heimbold donated last year, primarily through his personal foundation.</p>
        <p>The largest gift was $2 million to the University of Pennsylvania Law School, where Mr. Heimbold worked on the Law Review in 1960. Others were $1 million to Villanova University, where he received his bachelor's degree; $500,000 to Phoenix House, a drug treatment network, and $100,000 to the American Museum of Natural History.</p>
        <p>Mr. Heimbold's wife, Monica, a social worker, is a trustee of the American Scandinavian Foundation, and the Heimbolds have given $500,000 toward the group's Child Center. They also gave $250,000 to a library in Maine.</p>
        <p>The Bristol-Myers foundation gave about $28 million last year to organizations aimed at furthering science, education and child care. But a spokesman said Mr. Heimbold was careful that the foundation's giving not mirror his own.</p>
        <p>John F. Welch Jr., 63</p>
        <p>company -- General Electric  title -- Chairman and chief executive  cash compensation -- $8.0 million  Gains from options exercised -- $31.8 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $98.8 million  Total compensation -- $138.6 million</p>
        <p>JUDGING from the gifts made last year by the personal charitable foundation of John F. Welch Jr., his philanthropic passions are education, religion and the United Way.</p>
        <p>The largest single gift from the $6.2 million foundation was $25,000 to the Sankaty Head Foundation, which provides college scholarships for young people who caddie at the Sankaty Head Golf Club on Nantucket.</p>
        <p>In all, the foundation gave away $134,156 last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Welch also makes gifts other than those reported through records of the foundation, but he does not like to talk about them, a G.E. spokeswoman said. ''He does believe in charitable giving, but he feels it is a private matter and he is not going to discuss it,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The Welch foundation gave $19,381 to the Inner City Foundation in Bridgeport, Conn. ''Jack Welch has been the guiding light behind it for seven years, and his wife, Jane, is on the board,'' said Bishop Edward M. Egan, president of the Inner City Foundation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Welch's foundation also gave $15,000 to the Tri-State United Way; $7,500 to his alma mater, the University of Massachusetts, and $5,000 to the Bridgeport Hospital Foundation.</p>
        <p>G.E.'s corporate foundation gave away about $40 million last year, primarily to educational institutions.</p>
        <p>Summerfield K. Johnston Jr., 65</p>
        <p>company -- Coca-Cola Enterprises  title -- Chairman  cash compensation -- $2.4 million  Gains from options exercised -- $0  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $130.0 million  Total compensation -- $132.4 million  ranking, Forbes 400 281  Net worth -- $730 million</p>
        <p>HE is chairman of an Atlanta company, but Summerfield K. Johnston Jr. has his heart and heritage in Chattanooga, Tenn., where his family's century-old bottling business was based before it was bought by Coca-Cola Enterprises in 1991.</p>
        <p>Though he was chief executive of the Atlanta company for seven years before easing into his current job last April, he ''is a real mystery'' on the Atlanta charity scene, according to an executive active in giving there who requested anonymity.</p>
        <p>Mr. Johnston does serve on the board of the Morehouse School of Medicine in Atlanta and has made contributions to the school and to Spelman College, also in Atlanta.</p>
        <p>In Chattanooga, he is on the board of the University of Chattanooga Foundation and has given grants for research on the blighted American chestnut tree and to endow professorships.</p>
        <p>Last year, his foundation also gave $50,000 to the Baylor School, a Chattanooga preparatory school that he, his father and his son all attended.</p>
        <p>In all, the foundation, which had assets of $23 million in 1997, gave away $1 million last year. Other beneficiaries included a community foundation in Sheridan, Wyo., near where he has a home; and his alma mater, Vanderbilt University.</p>
        <p>Stephen M. Case, 40</p>
        <p>company -- America Online  title -- Chairman and chief executive  cash compensation -- $0.3 million  Gains from options exercised -- $26.6 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options $92.6 million  Total compensation -- $119.5 million</p>
        <p>SOME people want to change the world; Stephen M. Case wants to connect it to the Internet. A founder of America Online, he now hopes to use some of the same techniques in philanthropy that he uses in business.</p>
        <p>One of them is entrepreneurship. In 1996, Mr. Case and his wife, Jean, started the Computer Learning Center to put computers in low-income housing projects in Virginia.</p>
        <p>''Otherwise,'' Mr. Case said, ''kids go home from school and don't have access to computers.''</p>
        <p>He hopes to enlist others to start similar centers elsewhere. ''This is the same way venture capitalists help create new companies,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Computers, of course, have made it possible for Mr. Case to become a philanthropist. Six years ago, all of America Online was worth $70 million. Last year, his total pay, including unexercised options, was more than $119 million.</p>
        <p>Also in 1997, Mr. Case established a personal foundation with a donation of America Online stock worth $981,250. His subsequent contributions -- and the run-up in Internet stocks -- have increased its assets to $50 million, according to the company.</p>
        <p>America Online started a corporate foundation last year, as well, dedicated to helping the Internet have a positive impact on society. The foundation gave away $400,000 in its first year.</p>
        <p>Lawrence A. Bossidy, 63</p>
        <p>company -- Allied Signal  title -- Chairman and chief executive  cash compensation -- $5.2 million  Gains from options exercised -- $23.1 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $82.6 million  Total compensation -- $110.9 million</p>
        <p>IT'S likely that few chief executives have such large private organizations to support as Lawrence A. Bossidy, the father of 9 and the grandfather of 20.</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Bossidy gives money to a number of institutions in which he is personally involved, including religious and alumni groups.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bossidy worked at General Electric for 34 years, and, to an extent, his giving mirrors that of his former boss, John F. Welch Jr.</p>
        <p>The largest gift last year from Mr. Bossidy's personal foundation, which has $3.7 million in assets, was $50,914 to Faith in the Future, a Bridgeport, Conn., group that is headed by Bishop Edward M. Egan and helps Catholic schools.</p>
        <p>The Sankaty Head Foundation, which gives scholarships for caddies at a Nantucket golf club and is a favorite charity of Mr. Welch, received $10,000 of the $206,962 that Mr. Bossidy's foundation gave away. Mr. Bossidy also gave $40,000 to St. Mary's Roman Catholic Church in Ridgefield, Conn., near his home, and $19,950 to the Tri-State United Way.</p>
        <p>A Colgate University alumnus, Mr. Bossidy has been a steady contributor to the school; last year, his foundation gave it $24,590.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bossidy declined to be interviewed; Bishop Egan said he was very generous, and another associate added that he sometimes preferred to be quiet about his giving.</p>
        <p>Louis V. Gerstner Jr.</p>
        <p>company -- I.B.M.  title -- Chairman and chief executive  cash compensation -- $8.1 million  Gains from options exercised -- $6.7 million  ADDITIONAL exercisable options -- $95.6 million  Total compensation -- $110.4 million</p>
        <p>LOUIS V. GERSTNER JR. has long been a champion of education. And while much of his philanthropy was financed until recently from the corporate coffers of I.B.M., he has begun to make big gifts of his own as his personal wealth has soared. This year, he has given away $2 million, partly through his personal foundation, according to an I.B.M. executive.</p>
        <p>Among the gifts were $1 million to Bishop Edward M. Egan's Faith in the Future campaign for Catholic schools, for which he has established a distinguished scholars program; $500,000 to the Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons, and $300,000 to Chaminade High School, the Catholic school he attended in Mineola, N.Y.</p>
        <p>In 1997, Mr. Gerstner gave his foundation $1.1 million and it made gifts totaling $118,000, including $34,460 to Faith in the Future; $15,000 to the United Way of Greenwich, Conn., and smaller amounts to various community, educational and religious organizations.</p>
        <p>I.B.M's corporate giving ''mirrors Mr. Gerstner's own commitments,'' according to Stanley Litow, a company vice president. I.B.M. makes grants to schools and state education departments to foster the use of technology in the classroom. It donated $26.6 million cash and $70.2 million in computers last year, about two-thirds to educational projects.</p>
        <p>PERSONAL BUSINESS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
