<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Will Bird's House Fly As a City Landmark?</title>
    <meta content="20JAZZ" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1071219"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: LOWER EAST SIDE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Landmarks Preservation Commission (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Moynihan, Colin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Parker, Charlie (1920-55)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Historic Buildings and Sites</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E6D81E3DF933A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="630" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Will Bird's House Fly As a City Landmark?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By COLIN MOYNIHAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Moynihan, Colin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Landmarks Preservation Commission considers petition to designate as a landmark the house on Lower East Side where the alto saxophonist Charlie Parker lived in early 1950's; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Growing up in South Carolina, where she listened to the music of Miles Davis, Ella Fitzgerald and Sarah Vaughn, Judy Rhodes never imagined that she'd live in a house once occupied by Charlie Parker, the alto saxophonist who was a creator of bebop jazz. Nor, she said, did she ever think she'd lead an effort to have the house she has lived in since 1979, declared a landmark.</p>
        <p>Though the four-story brownstone at 151 Avenue B, near Tenth Street, was put on the National Register of Historic Places in 1994, after Ms. Rhodes hired a preservationist to help make the case, she has been trying for eight years to have the city declare it a landmark.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Growing up in South Carolina, where she listened to the music of Miles Davis, Ella Fitzgerald and Sarah Vaughn, Judy Rhodes never imagined that she'd live in a house once occupied by Charlie Parker, the alto saxophonist who was a creator of bebop jazz. Nor, she said, did she ever think she'd lead an effort to have the house she has lived in since 1979, declared a landmark.</p>
        <p>Though the four-story brownstone at 151 Avenue B, near Tenth Street, was put on the National Register of Historic Places in 1994, after Ms. Rhodes hired a preservationist to help make the case, she has been trying for eight years to have the city declare it a landmark.</p>
        <p>In 1990, a Landmarks Preservation Commission official said that ''the building is of some historical and architectural interest.'' But  commission staff members decided not to recommend landmarking at that time.</p>
        <p>But now the commission is considering the proposal. Last week, at a commission hearing, preservationists and members of community groups spoke in favor of landmark status for the house. (No one spoke against the plan.) Parker, his wife, Chan Richardson, and three children lived in its basement apartment from around the middle of 1950 until fall 1954. He died on March 12, 1955 at the age of 34.</p>
        <p>Some speakers praised the unusual Gothic Revival entry to the building. Others focused on the importance of Parker, whose nickname was Bird, as a cultural figure. Phil Schaap, a jazz historian, disk jockey and archivist-curator at WKCR-FM, the radio station affiliated with Columbia University, used a boom box to play a recorded message of support from the drummer Max Roach, who played with Parker.</p>
        <p>A spokeswoman for the commission, Katy McNabb, said it had received a petition with 150 signatures urging landmark designation, as well as a letter accompanied by a feather that said: ''Bird lives and flies forever. Please preserve his cage.'' The commission is expected to make a decision early next year, Ms. McNabb said.</p>
        <p>''Things that have made it this far usually have a pretty good chance,'' she said. In 1992, the city named part of Avenue B, between 7th and 10th Streets, Charlie Parker Place.</p>
        <p>These days, Ms. Rhodes, who has booked shows at jazz clubs like the Village Vanguard and Sweet Basil's,  shares the basement apartment with a dog named Thelonious, after the jazz pianist Thelonious Monk.</p>
        <p>''The first time I was in this house, I went into a closet in the back where legend had it Bird used to practice,'' she said, ''though the truth is he never did practice. When I shut the door, it almost felt like he was in there with me, and that's when I knew I really wanted to have the house.''</p>
        <p>She added: ''This neighborhood has changed a lot, and it's going to keep changing. That's why it's important to preserve parts of the past.''</p>
        <p>COLIN MOYNIHAN</p>
        <p>LINEUP  Ornithology</p>
        <p>When Charlie Parker made his home at 151 Avenue B from 1950 to 1954, he was also making music. Here are some of his recording and performing dates from around that time:</p>
        <p>FALL 1950 -- Tours Europe</p>
        <p>MARCH 1951 -- Records ''My Little Suede Shoes,'' which becomes a hit</p>
        <p>JANUARY 1952 -- Records ''Autumn in New York'' with 40-piece orchestra</p>
        <p>FEB. 24, 1952 -- Legendary TV appearance with Dizzy Gillespie</p>
        <p>SEPT. 26, 1952 -- Appearance at Rockland Palace with Paul Robeson</p>
        <p>JAN. 30, 1953 -- Records ''Round Midnight'' with Miles Davis</p>
        <p>MAY 15, 1953 -- Massey Hall concert in concert with Max Roach, Bud Powell, Dizzy Gillespie and Charles Mingus. (Recorded for an album titled ''The Greatest Jazz Concert Ever''</p>
        <p>FALL/WINTER 1953-54 -- Tours West Coast with Chet Baker and Stan Kenton</p>
        <p>(Source: Phil Schaap, jazz historian)</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: LOWER EAST SIDE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
