<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Card-Carrying Angst of the Dysfunctional Shopper</title>
    <meta content="20ROZH$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Week in Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; Week in Review" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19981227T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1071289"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krueger, David W (Dr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rozhon, Tracie</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Week in Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Mental Health and Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Consumer Behavior</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mental Health and Disorders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D00E0DE163CF933A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="846" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Card-Carrying Angst of the Dysfunctional Shopper</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TRACIE ROZHON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Rozhon, Tracie</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Psychologists discuss shopping disorders that afflict people who spend more than they should, for inaapropriate reasons; photo of hand-to-hand combat over Furby toys; Dr David W Krueger offers self-help quiz and hints on spotting danger, as when shopper begins to feel that favorite salesclerk is his or her only friend (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AS holiday shoppers clogged the thoroughfares last week, clutching glossy bags emblazoned with status names, one 59-year-old lawyer confided her innermost feeling: guilt.</p>
        <p>''I had a great year,'' said the woman, who worried that if she gave her name, her clients would think they had paid her too much. ''In past years, I always went to Toys ''R'' Us and bought my grandson some cheap thing. This year, I'm heading to F.A.O. Schwarz and buying him one of those expensive motorized Legos. I don't care how much it costs. And my daughter-in-law. She asked for a Polartec robe. Well, I'm getting her cashmere! Then I'm going to Tiffany's and buy my son Limoges.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AS holiday shoppers clogged the thoroughfares last week, clutching glossy bags emblazoned with status names, one 59-year-old lawyer confided her innermost feeling: guilt.</p>
        <p>''I had a great year,'' said the woman, who worried that if she gave her name, her clients would think they had paid her too much. ''In past years, I always went to Toys ''R'' Us and bought my grandson some cheap thing. This year, I'm heading to F.A.O. Schwarz and buying him one of those expensive motorized Legos. I don't care how much it costs. And my daughter-in-law. She asked for a Polartec robe. Well, I'm getting her cashmere! Then I'm going to Tiffany's and buy my son Limoges.''</p>
        <p>How does she sound to you? Normal? Stressed? Over the edge? It all depends on who's sizing up the situation. Psychiatrists who specialize in ''shopping disorders'' might say she's at risk.</p>
        <p>A shopping disorder? That's when people spend more than they should, for reasons they shouldn't. They are not the regular stripe of holiday shoppers caught up in the wretched excesses of the season. These problem consumers are engaged in compulsive shopping, competitive shopping and revenge shopping (spending a loved one's money to exact punishment, which may be seen as an indication of caring).</p>
        <p>Doctors say these feelings, which reflect deeper psychological disturbances, may intensify around Christmas, when people are inundated with subtle and not-so-subtle messages to spend.</p>
        <p>''The holidays are particularly difficult for some patients because these ritualistic events resonate with memories of festive and happy times,'' explained Dr. David W. Krueger, a Houston psychiatrist who wrote a book called ''Emotional Business: The Meanings of Work, Money and Success'' (Slawson Communications, 1992), which focuses on the way people handle money.</p>
        <p>Some people shop to compensate for feelings of intense loneliness, Dr. Krueger said. ''Shopping becomes a proxy,'' he said, but the the thrill doesn't last that long. ''It's like treating appendicitis with morphine. It doesn't resolve the conflict.''</p>
        <p>Dr. David Belgray, the director of the Jewish Association for Counseling and Psychotherapy in New York City, says patients seek him out when ''they're to the point where they're in pain -- and the charge cards are up to their limits.''</p>
        <p>''Some people want to get the most, give the most, get the biggest present, give the biggest present,'' said Dr. Gail Saltz, a clinical instructor in psychiatry at New York Hospital-Cornell Medical Center in Manhattan. ''It's natural to want to say: 'I love you. You love me. Here's something special I picked out for you.'</p>
        <p>''It's when you get carried away,'' she said. ''Then a lot of resentment can build up. You've spent too much. And in your mind, the people you gave the holiday presents to didn't pay you back emotionally.''</p>
        <p>So how does anyone know if a loved one is a compulsive holiday shopper, heading straight for a new year full of anger, resentment and remorse?</p>
        <p>Dr. Krueger gives his patients a self-help quiz:</p>
        <p>* ''Do you go shopping to escape feeling bored, empty, angry or scared?''</p>
        <p>* ''Do you use shopping or spending in a way that creates conflicts for you, or between you and others?''</p>
        <p>* ''Do you buy things with your credit cards that you wouldn't buy if you had the cash?''</p>
        <p>* ''When you shop or make a purchase, does your mood change -- do you feel euphoric or anxious?''</p>
        <p>(If the answer is yes to any of the questions, he writes, patients could be using shopping as a way to regulate their self-esteem. Not good.)</p>
        <p>Another hint from Dr. Krueger: If a shopper starts to feel that her favorite salesclerk is her only friend, she might also be in real trouble. Another psychiatrist, Dr. Mark Sehl, the director of the Psychology Information Center in New York City, said a danger signal was ''somebody bragging about how much they've spent and then asking aloud: 'Why did I buy that?' ''</p>
        <p>Out of control? Sometimes it may not be your fault.</p>
        <p>''The mother comes in to complain about her grown son, who's been running her credit cards up to the limit,'' Dr. Belgray said. ''It's our job to separate who's the adult. Why does the adult child have use of the parents credit cards?''</p>
        <p>FOR those who simply want to curb their spending, Dr. Sehl recommends that they pay attention to their mood when buying for themselves or others. ''Check the impulse. Write it down on a piece of paper after you either buy or don't buy. If you're not in therapy, it could be therapeutic.''</p>
        <p>Then again, if you bought a gift for all the wrong reasons, there is another solution. You can always return it.</p>
        <p>What about the lawyer who felt so bad about years of being cheap?</p>
        <p>''She's trying to atone,'' said Dr. Sehl, who said he would need to see if her spending patterns repeated. ''If she only does it one year, she actually can atone. But if she keeps depriving, atoning, depriving, atoning, then she probably has a problem.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  December 27, 1998, Sunday  An article last Sunday about compulsive shoppers misstated the profession and affiliation of Dr. Mark Sehl, who recommended some remedies. He is a psychoanalyst, not a psychiatrist, and is the executive director of the Psychotherapy Information Center, not the Psychology Information Center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: December 27, 1998, Sunday</p>
        <p>An article last Sunday about compulsive shoppers misstated the profession and affiliation of Dr. Mark Sehl, who recommended some remedies. He is a psychoanalyst, not a psychiatrist, and is the executive director of the Psychotherapy Information Center, not the Psychology Information Center.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
