<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Put on Your High-Heeled Oxfords: It's Swing Time Again</title>
    <meta content="20SWIN$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1071162"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="POP MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">California</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Demasters, Karen</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E03E7DE113DF933A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="1207" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Put on Your High-Heeled Oxfords: It's Swing Time Again</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KAREN DeMASTERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Demasters, Karen</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Revival of interest in swing music and dancing in New Jersey and elsewhere discussed; swing comeback, which began in late 1980's in California, has swept nation in last few months; NJ musicians, dance teachers and club owners comment; photo (M)s</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SWING music and dancing seem to be everywhere these days, including all over New Jersey. But this swing is new. It may lean on the horn-heavy sound born of the post-Prohibition era, but it rocks in a way the prewar generation never would have imagined.</p>
        <p>This is not music for listening; it's dance music, perhaps even more so than in the old days. And if you don't know how to dance, somebody probably is giving lessons in a bar or hall near you.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SWING music and dancing seem to be everywhere these days, including all over New Jersey. But this swing is new. It may lean on the horn-heavy sound born of the post-Prohibition era, but it rocks in a way the prewar generation never would have imagined.</p>
        <p>This is not music for listening; it's dance music, perhaps even more so than in the old days. And if you don't know how to dance, somebody probably is giving lessons in a bar or hall near you.</p>
        <p>Swing music is at the center of the aptly titled 1996 independent film ''Swingers,'' and it's being used in television commercials for the Gap to push khaki pants. It revived the dancing career of Frankie Manning, 84, a retired postal worker in New York City who was once considered the best swing dancer in the world as he danced his way through the 1930's in Harlem. It's being played in punk bars and hailed as an alternative to the depressing, antisocial sounds of grunge. It is even being heard in country bars where patrons do jive-oriented line dances to its pounding beat.</p>
        <p>One of the three leading swing bands, Big Bad Voodoo Daddy from Los Angeles, will be in the halftime shows of the Super Bowl and the Orange Bowl next month after playing Atlantic City last summer.</p>
        <p>Scotty Morris, founder and lead singer of Big Bad Voodoo Daddy, and his counterparts in Cherry Poppin' Daddies and the Brian Setzer Orchestra, who labored mostly in obscurity until this year, say artistry and musicianship are the keys to swing. But many of those caught up in the movement would argue that dancing is what counts.</p>
        <p>For decades, dancing has meant rock-and-roll, which has meant bopping on a dance floor essentially by yourself, said Laura Gilford, a Manhattan-based dance instructor who teaches swing at Shout in Plainfield, Reddy's in Long Branch and the Somerset Hills Y.M.C.A., among other places. Ms. Gilford started teaching a variety of dances part time about a year ago. Now she teaches swing full time and still cannot keep up with all the requests for lessons.</p>
        <p>''Couples dancing is a way for a man and woman to communicate,'' she said. ''The man leads and gives strength. It's a way for a woman to express her personality and her attitude in her style and flair to her partner and to the people watching.''</p>
        <p>Swing started coming back in the late 1980's in California but has swept the country in the last few months, in part just because it is so much fun, said Lenny Lelinko of Wall Township, better known as the disc jockey and band promoter Lenny Lounge. Swing ''is 1990's rebellion in a positive way,'' said Mr. Lelinko, 41, a self-described ex-punker who is starting a swing club called the Leopard Lounge at Club Bene in Sayreville. ''The energy is appealing, plus it is more romantic and more social'' than other recent musical phenomena, he said.</p>
        <p>At the Hunka Bunka Ballroom in Sayreville, which features all types of music for the 20-something crowd, a special party featuring the Cherry Poppin' Daddies recently packed the ballroom. The club wants to try swing with dance lessons on a regular basis, said Joey Pignatelli, its promotions director. On the Trenton waterfront, Katmandu has offered swing lessons on Sundays for most of this year.</p>
        <p>Resorts Casino Hotel in Atlantic City  booked the Brian Setzer Orchestra more than two years ago. Mr. Setzer, a Long Island native who fronted the now-defunct Stray Cats in the 1980's, has since played his version of rockabilly swing at the Trump Marina Resort and Casino several times.</p>
        <p>''The first time, it was a struggle in terms of attendance,'' said Steve Gietka, executive director of entertainment and public relations at the Trump Marina. ''But after that first time, we have sold out every show. Then we booked Big Bad Voodoo Daddy last March, and it caught us by surprise. We put them in the small theater with 500 seats, and we had one of the longest lines waiting to get in that we have ever seen.''</p>
        <p>The casino now plans a regular Sunday night swing session with dance lessons. The concertgoers are easy to spot on the casino floor, Mr. Gietka said, because they dress the part in zoot suits, flip fedoras and wide ties for the men, and circle skirts, saddle oxfords and anklets for the women.</p>
        <p>W E were a rock band, and we looked awful,'' said Steve Perry, lead singer of the Cherry Poppin' Daddies, based in Eugene, Ore. ''Then we got into swing, and we wanted to look good. It seems like people understand us better when we dress up.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Morris of Big Bad Voodoo Daddy agreed. ''It shows respect for the music,'' he said. ''We have the best-looking suits in town.''</p>
        <p>Swing music now comes in two forms: regulation 17-piece big bands that play acoustic and reproduce the sounds of the 1930's, and the new upstart swingers, eight- or nine-piece bands that combine rock-and-roll, jazz, blues, punk, ska and a lot more to write new songs that have the rhythm and energy of the old swing.</p>
        <p>The Brass Tacks, a big band based in Ocean County that plays original arrangements of 1930's tunes by Louis Prima, Duke Ellington and Glenn Miller, has also seen a jump in popularity.</p>
        <p>''It amazes me lately to see the young people outnumber the older people on the dance floor,'' said Paul Clauss, a Brass Tacks founder and its lead trombonist.</p>
        <p>Rock-oriented groups writing their own music still use a lot of horns for a rich, complicated brand of music, but the bands just as often feature an electric guitar out front. The sound appeals to young people who were bored and ready for a change, Mr. Morris said, and playing electric makes the sound as big as the 17-piece orchestras. (Most of these bands have eight or nine members.)</p>
        <p>''This is American roots music,'' he said. ''It goes back to New Orleans jazz, and that's as American as it gets.'' The sound has a lot of followers and is still growing but will eventually fade, Mr. Perry predicts, because this is a disposable society.</p>
        <p>But some fans will stay. ''Once you learn swing dance, you're not going to throw that away,'' he said. The bands that have talent will have staying power, and the music will probably retain its appeal. It is fun with an attitude.</p>
        <p>GREGG CARPENTER BAND  Katmandu  Route 29, Waterfront Park, Trenton  Tonight at 7 P.M.; swing dance lessons from 5 to 6 P.M. Swing and rhythm-and-blues jam, Wednesday at 6 P.M.  (609) 393-7300</p>
        <p>BLUES JUMPERS  Wave Nightclub, Trump Marina, Huron Avenue and Brigantine Boulevard, Atlantic City  Tonight at 8 P.M.; swing dance lessons before show. Free.  (800) 777-8477</p>
        <p>FLIPPED FEDORAS  Leopard Lounge at Club Bene  Route 35, Sayreville  Saturday at 10 P.M.; swing dance lessons, 9 P.M.  (732) 727-3000</p>
        <p>POP MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
