<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Alcohol and Drug Use by Teen-Agers Declines Some, Report Says</title>
    <meta content="20TEEN" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="45" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1071312"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of Michigan</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Johnston, Lloyd D</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Midwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beer</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Marijuana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Research</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Beverages</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Drug Abuse and Traffic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Alcoholic Beverages</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E4DE173CF933A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="619" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Alcohol and Drug Use by Teen-Agers Declines Some, Report Says</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CHRISTOPHER S. WREN</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>University of Michigan annual survey finds use of marijuana and other drugs by teen-agers may be ebbing somewhat, after rising since early 1990's; researcher Lloyd D Johnston is optimistic; 49 percent of 12th graders and 22 percent of 8th graders report trying marijuana, but number of 12th graders smoking marijuana in previous month declined to 22.8 percent, from 23.7 percent; marijuana and beer are substances most abused by teen-agers (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>After rising since the early 1990's,  the use of marijuana and other drugs by teen-agers may be ebbing, however modestly, according to a new survey that is considered the most reliable gauge of substance abuse among secondary school students.</p>
        <p>The annual survey of nearly 50,000 students around the country, titled Monitoring the Future, was conducted at the Institute for Social Research at the University of Michigan and released on Friday. Though the levels of drug and alcohol use remain higher than several years ago, the survey reported, all grades studied  showed a slight but often statistically significant drop in overall drug use in the previous 12 months.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>After rising since the early 1990's,  the use of marijuana and other drugs by teen-agers may be ebbing, however modestly, according to a new survey that is considered the most reliable gauge of substance abuse among secondary school students.</p>
        <p>The annual survey of nearly 50,000 students around the country, titled Monitoring the Future, was conducted at the Institute for Social Research at the University of Michigan and released on Friday. Though the levels of drug and alcohol use remain higher than several years ago, the survey reported, all grades studied  showed a slight but often statistically significant drop in overall drug use in the previous 12 months.</p>
        <p>Last year, the institute's researchers found use of illicit drugs declining only among eighth graders. That trend continued this year, and drug use declined slightly among 10th and 12th graders, as well.</p>
        <p>''I think this is the best news we've had to bring the country in some years,'' the principal researcher, Lloyd D. Johnston, said in a telephone interview. ''Young people seem to be appreciating more fully the dangers of various drugs, including alcohol and cigarettes.''</p>
        <p>The overwhelming majority of adolescent drug use involves marijuana, which remained widespread. This year, 49 percent of 12th graders and 22 percent of 8th graders sampled said they had tried marijuana.</p>
        <p>But the number of 12th graders who smoked marijuana in the previous month declined to 22.8 percent from 23.7 percent, while the number of 8th graders using it dropped to 9.7 percent from 10.2 percent. The decline in regular use was more noticeable among 10th graders: 18.7 percent had smoked marijuana in the previous month, compared with 20.5 percent a year ago.</p>
        <p>''We certainly are not back to levels at the beginning of the 90's and it's too soon to trumpet victory,'' Dr. Johnston said, ''but certainly it's very encouraging news that this upward trend has finally begun to reverse.''</p>
        <p>The use of harder drugs, notably heroin and cocaine, remained statistically small and appeared to level off or decline for most groups surveyed. Among high school seniors, 2 percent acknowledged experimenting with heroin, marginally down from 2.1 percent a year ago. But 9.3 percent said they had tried cocaine at some point, compared with 8.7 percent last year.</p>
        <p>Asked about their use in the previous 30 days, 2.4 percent of the seniors said they had snorted or smoked cocaine, compared with 2.3 percent a year ago. And 0.5 percent said they had used heroin in the previous month, a statistic unchanged from last year.</p>
        <p>Alcohol, primarily beer, remains the substance most frequently abused by teen-agers, though even its use declined. Among eighth graders, 23 percent said they had drunk alcohol in the previous month, compared with 24.5 percent last year. Among 10th graders, monthly alcohol use dropped to 38.8 percent from 40.1 percent.</p>
        <p>But 8.2 percent of eighth graders admitted getting drunk in the previous month, a slight rise from the 8 percent who reported doing so a year ago. Among high school seniors, 32.9 percent said they had been drunk in the previous month, compared with 34.2 percent last year.</p>
        <p>The survey also showed tobacco use down slightly.</p>
        <p>Dr. Johnston and his fellow researchers, Jerald G. Bachman and Patrick M. O'Malley, attributed the  changes in drug-seeking behavior to a reassessment by teen-agers of the risks and to stronger expressions of concern by parents and other adults.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
