<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mad Tidings</title>
    <meta content="20BEAUTYT" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="80" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1071015"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="APPEARANCES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tannen, Mary</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cosmetics and Toiletries</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981220T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0D7143DF933A15751C1A96E958260" item-length="958" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mad Tidings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Mary Tannen</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tannen, Mary</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Humorous comment on overindulgence in cosmetics; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the velvet darkness of the bedroom, it could be any time, any place. She rises and walks with unerring steps to the bathroom, only then switching on a light, but does not confront the mirrors. Instead, she showers, standing out of the spray to gently, and with circular motions, massage on Chanel Multihydroxy Active Body Polisher. The BHA and AHA will delicately exfoliate her skin; the exclusive ingredient, Nutrifirm, will moisturize and firm. After rinsing, she lathers with Shiseido 5S Refreshing, a total wash with the scent of orange extract and lemongrass. She inhales deeply to gather in the aromatherapy benefits.</p>
        <p>When she turns off the shower, she is aware of a faint sound -- like the clanking of chains. She tries to focus on what it could mean, but the effort brings on the beginnings of a headache. Christian Dior Nourishing Body Creme for Dry Skin offers distraction: the way she rubs it into her calves with special attention to the backs of her heels, the way she smooths it onto her arms, lingering over the dry elbow area. She finds a silk kimono hanging on the back of the door and wraps it around her body. The clanking is persistent but no louder. She squints at the jars and tubes before her.</p>
        <p>She chooses Prescriptives Vibrant for her face, to infuse it with vitamins for a healthy glow. From a tube of Lancome Bienfait Yeux, she squeezes out a tiny worm of blue gel, then works it into eyelids still puffy from sleep or excesses of the night before. Contact lenses transform her eyes from indifferent gray to uncommon lavender. They also bring her face into focus. It is not modesty that until now has kept her from examining her reflection. It is myopia.</p>
        <p>She flinches. There is an intruder in the mirror. A scream strangles in her throat as she perceives the ghastly truth: the intruder is her own unrecognizable self.</p>
        <p>Her shaking hand (the nails lacquered a garnet red, Kennebunk-port by OPI) hovers over a collection of bottles and plucks out Romance, a woody floral fragrance by Ralph Lauren. Does she crave its patchouli ''coeur,'' with its reputed benefits of clearing and balancing the mind, sharpening the wits and heightening sensual experience?</p>
        <p>A few spritzes and some deep breathing have a calming effect. Plus the clanking has stopped. Must have been a tow truck outside. She runs her fingers through her luxuriant shoulder-length hair. The shade is Deep Currant from L'Oreal. She applied it herself just a week ago, a fact she does not recall. She is searching for tender spots on her skull, but finds no sign of concussion. It is only amnesia, she thinks. It happens all the time in soap operas. It is temporary, brought on by some hard partying and perhaps too many cosmetic improvements in too short a time. (Her nose, chin and cheekbones all seem to have benefited from the attentions of a plastic surgeon -- likewise the snow-cone breasts, the board-flat stomach.)</p>
        <p>She is relieved that amnesia struck in her own home, not some terrible little bus station in a small, dreary town. At least, she believes it is her home; she seems to know where everything is. She walks through the dark bedroom to the living room and is heartened to see an artificial Christmas tree decorated in silver and crystal and beneath it a scattering of tastefully wrapped gifts. She sinks to her knees and seizes a package, eagerly looking at the tag. It will be from her, or to her, and she will recognize her own name. But the card is blank. Ditto the next package; ditto the third. They are all blank. Apparently, for a stress-free holiday season, she efficiently ordered up a bunch of prewrapped gifts suitable for anyone -- generic gifts for generic friends!</p>
        <p>She staggers to the window, thinking the sight of a familiar street will ground her, but she has settled in a deserted post-industrial neighborhood. Blind eyes of shuttered windows stare back at her through a thin veil of falling snow.</p>
        <p>A tear slides down her cheek. The holidays are a time for family and friends. She is doomed to spend them alone with a stranger -- herself. A fragrance candle, Noel, by Annick Goutal, stands ready on the coffee table. She lights it. Anticipating Proustian recall of a Christmas past, she inhales balsam and burnt sugar, chocolate and hot wax. It smells exactly the way Christmas should, but stirs no emotions in her breast. Maybe her family went to the Caribbean for the holidays.</p>
        <p>This is a nightmare, not reality. She has only to find her way back to bed and sleep it off. As her eyes adjust to the dim light, she sees a form in the bed. Man? Woman? She hopes for a large dog. Another person is a complication she cannot cope with right now. Silently, she lifts a corner of the black-out shade to get some light. It is a man. No body-piercing or tattoos -- she is grateful for that. He is sleeping peacefully, innocently. An Armani tuxedo jacket is neatly hung over the back of a chair.</p>
        <p>He turns and a heavy chain crashes to the floor.</p>
        <p>She gasps. ''Who are you?''</p>
        <p>''Marley,'' he sighs. [To be continued]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the velvet darkness of the bedroom, it could be any time, any place. She rises and walks with unerring steps to the bathroom, only then switching on a light, but does not confront the mirrors. Instead, she showers, standing out of the spray to gently, and with circular motions, massage on Chanel Multihydroxy Active Body Polisher. The BHA and AHA will delicately exfoliate her skin; the exclusive ingredient, Nutrifirm, will moisturize and firm. After rinsing, she lathers with Shiseido 5S Refreshing, a total wash with the scent of orange extract and lemongrass. She inhales deeply to gather in the aromatherapy benefits.</p>
        <p>When she turns off the shower, she is aware of a faint sound -- like the clanking of chains. She tries to focus on what it could mean, but the effort brings on the beginnings of a headache. Christian Dior Nourishing Body Creme for Dry Skin offers distraction: the way she rubs it into her calves with special attention to the backs of her heels, the way she smooths it onto her arms, lingering over the dry elbow area. She finds a silk kimono hanging on the back of the door and wraps it around her body. The clanking is persistent but no louder. She squints at the jars and tubes before her.</p>
        <p>She chooses Prescriptives Vibrant for her face, to infuse it with vitamins for a healthy glow. From a tube of Lancome Bienfait Yeux, she squeezes out a tiny worm of blue gel, then works it into eyelids still puffy from sleep or excesses of the night before. Contact lenses transform her eyes from indifferent gray to uncommon lavender. They also bring her face into focus. It is not modesty that until now has kept her from examining her reflection. It is myopia.</p>
        <p>She flinches. There is an intruder in the mirror. A scream strangles in her throat as she perceives the ghastly truth: the intruder is her own unrecognizable self.</p>
        <p>Her shaking hand (the nails lacquered a garnet red, Kennebunk-port by OPI) hovers over a collection of bottles and plucks out Romance, a woody floral fragrance by Ralph Lauren. Does she crave its patchouli ''coeur,'' with its reputed benefits of clearing and balancing the mind, sharpening the wits and heightening sensual experience?</p>
        <p>A few spritzes and some deep breathing have a calming effect. Plus the clanking has stopped. Must have been a tow truck outside. She runs her fingers through her luxuriant shoulder-length hair. The shade is Deep Currant from L'Oreal. She applied it herself just a week ago, a fact she does not recall. She is searching for tender spots on her skull, but finds no sign of concussion. It is only amnesia, she thinks. It happens all the time in soap operas. It is temporary, brought on by some hard partying and perhaps too many cosmetic improvements in too short a time. (Her nose, chin and cheekbones all seem to have benefited from the attentions of a plastic surgeon -- likewise the snow-cone breasts, the board-flat stomach.)</p>
        <p>She is relieved that amnesia struck in her own home, not some terrible little bus station in a small, dreary town. At least, she believes it is her home; she seems to know where everything is. She walks through the dark bedroom to the living room and is heartened to see an artificial Christmas tree decorated in silver and crystal and beneath it a scattering of tastefully wrapped gifts. She sinks to her knees and seizes a package, eagerly looking at the tag. It will be from her, or to her, and she will recognize her own name. But the card is blank. Ditto the next package; ditto the third. They are all blank. Apparently, for a stress-free holiday season, she efficiently ordered up a bunch of prewrapped gifts suitable for anyone -- generic gifts for generic friends!</p>
        <p>She staggers to the window, thinking the sight of a familiar street will ground her, but she has settled in a deserted post-industrial neighborhood. Blind eyes of shuttered windows stare back at her through a thin veil of falling snow.</p>
        <p>A tear slides down her cheek. The holidays are a time for family and friends. She is doomed to spend them alone with a stranger -- herself. A fragrance candle, Noel, by Annick Goutal, stands ready on the coffee table. She lights it. Anticipating Proustian recall of a Christmas past, she inhales balsam and burnt sugar, chocolate and hot wax. It smells exactly the way Christmas should, but stirs no emotions in her breast. Maybe her family went to the Caribbean for the holidays.</p>
        <p>This is a nightmare, not reality. She has only to find her way back to bed and sleep it off. As her eyes adjust to the dim light, she sees a form in the bed. Man? Woman? She hopes for a large dog. Another person is a complication she cannot cope with right now. Silently, she lifts a corner of the black-out shade to get some light. It is a man. No body-piercing or tattoos -- she is grateful for that. He is sleeping peacefully, innocently. An Armani tuxedo jacket is neatly hung over the back of a chair.</p>
        <p>He turns and a heavy chain crashes to the floor.</p>
        <p>She gasps. ''Who are you?''</p>
        <p>''Marley,'' he sighs. [To be continued]</p>
        <p>APPEARANCES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
