<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ad or Art? A Connecticut Court Must Say If Statute Covers Statue</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="136014"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RETAIL STORES AND TRADE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUITS AND LITIGATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOPPING CENTERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SIGNS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAMDEN (CONN)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">HAMDEN PLAZA (HAMDEN CONN)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">AMERICAN CIVIL LIBERTIES UNION (ACLU)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MADDEN, RICHARD L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./New England</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Shopping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Retail</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Retail Stores and Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Shopping Centers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Signs and Symbols</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19880414T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE6D7133FF937A25757C0A96E948260" item-length="628" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ad or Art? A Connecticut Court Must Say If Statute Covers Statue</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD L. MADDEN, Special to the New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MADDEN, RICHARD L</byline>
      <dateline>BRIDGEPORT, Conn., April 13</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: For an hour today, Connecticut's highest court listened to arguments on whether a 32-foot-tall sculpture was a work of art, or merely a sign.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: For an hour today, Connecticut's highest court listened to arguments on whether a 32-foot-tall sculpture was a work of art, or merely a sign.</p>
        <p>For an hour today, Connecticut's highest court listened to arguments on whether a 32-foot-tall sculpture was a work of art, or merely a sign.</p>
        <p>A sign, said a lawyer for the Town of Hamden, which has twice rejected applications by a shopping center, Hamden Plaza, to put the sculpture at an entrance along a busy stretch of Dixwell Avenue that is locally known as the ''Magic Mile.''</p>
        <p>Art, said lawyers for the plaza's owners, who contend that the sculpture is protected by the First Amendment guarantee of free speech and cannot be barred from private property by a town ordinance that regulates the size of signs.</p>
        <p>The five justices of the Connecticut Supreme Court gave no indication of when they would decide the matter. They did, however, ask for a picture of the sculpture, along with the usual legal briefs.</p>
        <p>The sculpture, composed of brushed-aluminum cylinders that revolve in the wind, is known as ''Landmark'' and is by Harold Lehr, a New York sculptor. It is owned by David W. Bermant, an art collector and shopping-center developer from Harrison, N.Y., who sometimes mixes the two activities.</p>
        <p>Hamden Plaza, a 30-year-old shopping center of which Mr. Bermant is part owner, is known for its ''Ghost Parking Lot,'' a display of 20 old automobiles covered with asphalt.</p>
        <p>Other pieces of abstract art at the shopping center, ranging from neon sign displays to ''Moonbells,'' dot the sidewalk in front of the stores.</p>
        <p>According to the court papers, in 1981 and 1986 the Hamden Planning and Zoning Commission rejected applications by Mr. Bermant and the other owners to put ''Landmark'' at an entrance to the center.</p>
        <p>The commission ruled that the sculpture was a sign that would attract business to the center, and that it would exceed zoning limits that keep signs to 20 feet in height.</p>
        <p>'' 'Landmark' lacks a message, an idea, and any subject matter,'' the town argues in its legal papers, seeking to refute Mr. Bermant's contention that a zoning board cannot restrict free expression because of its message or content.</p>
        <p>''Far from restricting 'Landmark' because of its content, which is non-existent,'' the papers state, ''the commission has suggested that another site might be more appropriate for 'Landmark,' based on public health, safety and welfare considerations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bermant, in a telephone interview, said ''Landmark'' had been displayed in 1984 in front of the Wadsworth Atheneum in Hartford, and that an identical sculpture, known as ''Lighthouse,'' was at the entrance to a shopping center in which he has an interest near Rochester, N.Y.</p>
        <p>''Landmark,'' Mr. Bermant said, cost about $40,000 and was now in storage.</p>
        <p>Lawyers for the shopping center and for the Atheneum and the Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, who filed briefs in support of the owners, contend that Federal and other state courts have held that art is protected by the First Amendment, that the sculpture is an example of abstract or kinetic art, and that it contains no words or messages that would classify it as a sign.</p>
        <p>Harriette K. Dorsen, a New York City lawyer who argued for the owners, told the court that other courts, including the United States Supreme Court, have upheld the constitutional protection of such other art forms as motion pictures and the dance.</p>
        <p>Hugh I. Manke, the town attorney for Hamden, said that ''Landmark,'' with its moving parts, was ''an attention-getting device'' for the shopping center.</p>
        <p>When the justices asked for a picture of what Justice Shea termed ''this object,'' Ms. Dorsen said the only one she had was taken in 1984 when ''Landmark'' had a light on its top. The light has since been removed, she said.</p>
        <p>''No light, we understand,'' said Associate Justice T. Clark Hull, smiling. ''It won't shed any light on this case.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
