<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Women and the Mysteries They Write</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="348833"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AWARDS, DECORATIONS AND HONORS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CRIME AND CRIMINALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAU, ELEANOR</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEILBRUN, CAROLYN G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Crime and Criminals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900430T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFDE1E3FF933A05757C0A966958260" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Women and the Mysteries They Write</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR BLAU</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAU, ELEANOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Some 40 women of mystery -crime fiction writers from around the country - met at St. Bartholomew's Episcopal Church on Park Avenue at 51st Street on Friday night to honor one of their own: Amanda Cross.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Some 40 women of mystery -crime fiction writers from around the country - met at St. Bartholomew's Episcopal Church on Park Avenue at 51st Street on Friday night to honor one of their own: Amanda Cross.</p>
        <p>Some 40 women of mystery -crime fiction writers from around the country - met at St. Bartholomew's Episcopal Church on Park Avenue at 51st Street on Friday night to honor one of their own: Amanda Cross.</p>
        <p>She does not exist, per se. But that was no mystery to the more than 200 fans who came to hear their favorite authors.</p>
        <p>Amanda Cross is an alias for Carolyn G. Heilbrun, the Avalon Foundation Professor in the Humanities at Columbia University. Her cover was blown in the early 1970's, when colleagues thought they recognized the academic setting of one of her stories. Her mysteries include the recently published ''A Trap for Fools'' (E. P. Dutton) and eight earlier books, all featuring a spirited amateur sleuth who is also a literature professor.</p>
        <p>In her other life, Professor Heilbrun has written works, all published by W. W. Norton, which include ''Toward a Recognition of Androgyny,'' ''Reinventing Womanhood'' and ''Writing a Woman's Life,'' a highly praised look at women's biographies.</p>
        <p>Wide Audience, Positive Message</p>
        <p>The two of her won the evening's tribute: a first Writer of Distinction Award from the National Council for Research on Women, a coalition of 60 groups. The award, a clay sculpture, recognizes women who have reached wide audiences with positive characterizations of women's lives.</p>
        <p>Such writing, Professor Heilbrun said in an interview, contrasts with men's detective stories in which ''women are either sex objects or bad mothers or dead.''</p>
        <p>The event, ''An Evening With Women of Mystery,'' was to raise funds for the council. It celebrated an increase in recent years in the number and prominence of mystery-writing women, who are at least as prolific writers as men these days, participants said.</p>
        <p>It ended with a third-floor supper session in which fans mingled with authors, listened to readings, bought books and had them autographed.</p>
        <p>But first, Professor Heilbrun moderated a talk on the altar with the writers Mary Higgins Clark, Marilyn French, Charlotte MacLeod and Sharyn McCrumb and an editor at Charles Scribner's Sons, Susanne Kirk.</p>
        <p>It Started With Eden</p>
        <p>Ms. Clark traced her craft to the Garden of Eden: ''Eve convinced Adam to commit a felony. They had two kids and one killed the other.''</p>
        <p>An audience member asked if anyone had so tired of her protagonist that she was tempted to bump her off. No need, replied Ms. MacLeod, noting that Agatha Christie did not do in Hercule Poirot, but merely created Miss Marple, ''who I think was more to her taste.''</p>
        <p>Can a man write successfully from a woman's point of view? Professor Heilbrun thought not. ''What he can't know is what it is to be a member of an oppressed group,'' she said. ''You can't know unless you live it.''</p>
        <p>When men write as women, Ms. French complained, they always make men the central concern in women's lives. ''It just isn't so,'' she said, except perhaps ''when you're 18.''</p>
        <p>Ms. MacLeod suggested that women were more versatile and devious than men in inventing misdeeds. ''There are nice little domestic things that can be put to horrible uses,'' she noted.</p>
        <p>Wits Sharpened by Oppression</p>
        <p>Ms. McCrumb reasoned that ''women are obsessed with figuring out mysteries because most of us live with men.'' Lacking men's power, they learn to notice subleties like a tone of voice, she said: ''Our wits have been sharpened by that for 20 generations.''</p>
        <p>And Ms. Kirk reported that women's novels had so grown in popularity in recent years that she now found it easier to get manuscripts accepted by Scribner's if they were written by women.</p>
        <p>Where is the mystery novel heading? Ms. MacLeod replied to that with questions of her own: ''Is the maleness or femaleness of a protagonist going to be less important? Can we begin thinking of people as human beings instead of representatives of their sex?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
