<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Weighing Other Hevesi Challengers</title>
    <meta content="06trail" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1802849"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="2006 ELECTION: OFF THE TRAIL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Comptrollers</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York State</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">LaForge, Patrick</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hevesi, Alan G (Comptroller)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Callaghan, J Christopher</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Willebrand, Julia</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cotton, Willie</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cain, John J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20061106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01EFDC113FF935A35752C1A9609C8B63" item-length="647" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Weighing Other Hevesi Challengers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PATRICK LaFORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LaForge, Patrick</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Campaign for New York State comptroller includes candidates other than Democrat Alan G Hevesi and Republican J Christopher Callaghan; other candidates are Julia Willebrand, Willie Cotton and John J Cain; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Frustrated by having to decide between Alan G. Hevesi and J. Christopher Callaghan, below, in the race for New York State comptroller? Well, there are alternatives, since voters can pull the lever for a third-party candidate in this race.</p>
        <p>Julia Willebrand, the Green Party candidate, has been involved with the Greens for about a dozen years. As she tells it, she grew up poor, one of 10 children in Greenpoint, Brooklyn. She has been a waitress, a college professor and a mother. She ran for State Senate on the Upper West Side in 1998 and for mayor of New York in 2001. She did not win.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Frustrated by having to decide between Alan G. Hevesi and J. Christopher Callaghan, below, in the race for New York State comptroller? Well, there are alternatives, since voters can pull the lever for a third-party candidate in this race.</p>
        <p>Julia Willebrand, the Green Party candidate, has been involved with the Greens for about a dozen years. As she tells it, she grew up poor, one of 10 children in Greenpoint, Brooklyn. She has been a waitress, a college professor and a mother. She ran for State Senate on the Upper West Side in 1998 and for mayor of New York in 2001. She did not win.</p>
        <p>If elected, she said in a questionnaire from the League of Women Voters, she would use the position to end handouts to corporations, crack down on Medicaid fraud and create government incentives to promote environmental projects, affordable housing and new jobs. She would also work to promote world peace and end the genocide in Darfur.</p>
        <p>Willie Cotton is running for the Socialist Workers Party. A sewing machine operator in his 20s and a self-described revolutionary, he ran against Representative Charles B. Rangel in 2004. He did not win.</p>
        <p>In response to the questionnaire from the League of Women Voters, he said, ''We need a revolutionary movement that can lead a fight by workers and our allies to take power out of the hands of the ruling billionaire class.''</p>
        <p>John J. Cain is the Libertarian Party candidate. Mr. Cain has a Master of Arts, works in the insurance industry and lives in Congers, Rockland County.</p>
        <p>And here's an intriguing aside about Mr. Cain: When he served on the Clarkstown Planning Board, he was offered a bribe and wore a wire for federal investigators in a case that led to the conviction of the county Democratic Party chairman.</p>
        <p>In his questionnaire, Mr. Cain said he would like to stop prosecuting victimless crimes, put everyone in state government on a 401(k) instead of a pension and get the government out of the health care business.</p>
        <p>Even his supporters can't resist the puns: ''He's Cain and Hevesi's Not Able.''</p>
        <p>Campaign Highlights</p>
        <p>As this is the last Off the Trail column of this campaign season, we asked reporters covering the region's races to nominate some highlights. There are more at The Empire Zone blog, nytimes.com/empirezone, where readers may submit their own.</p>
        <p>Best Score in a Campaign Ad: The Beastie Boys, in Kirsten Gillibrand's ad focusing on Representative John E. Sweeney's attendance at a fraternity party.</p>
        <p>Best Actor in a Campaign Ad: David Strathairn, reprising his role as Edward R. Murrow in a Gillibrand ad.</p>
        <p>Best ''Checkers'' Speech: Alan G. Hevesi, telling voters in a campaign ad, ''I'm a good comptroller who did a dumb thing. If you give me the chance to keep serving you in the job I love, I'll owe you everything, and those politicians nothing.'' Runner-up: Jeanine F. Pirro, about allegations she wanted to secretly tape her husband: ''Nothing happened here that is, or should be, the business of the United States attorney's office.''</p>
        <p>Best Waste of a Good Debate Performance: ''The Rage Backstage,'' Thomas R. Suozzi's decision to focus on an argument he had with Eliot Spitzer beforehand instead of on what proved a pretty good debate.</p>
        <p>Best Tech Support Problem: The crash of Joseph I. Lieberman's Web site on Primary Day, which the senator's staff blamed on hackers. How is that F.B.I. inquiry going?</p>
        <p>Best Campaign Event Heckling: Members of the LaRouche Youth Movement, who interrupted a Lieberman event by serenading the senator with an anti-Joe ditty in perfect harmony.</p>
        <p>Best Campaign Accessory: The Albany Insider All-Star Team cards that Mr. Suozzi handed out featuring party leaders and lobbyists close to Mr. Spitzer. But why no gum?</p>
        <p>Best Gifts to Reporters on Sleepy New York Campaigns: Albert J. Pirro and J. Christopher Callaghan's secret Hevesi tipster (tie).</p>
        <p>2006 ELECTION: OFF THE TRAIL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
