<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>No Markings Evident on Cut Water Mains</title>
    <meta content="03WATE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1066844"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Clifton (NJ)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Water Resources</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Passaic Valley Water Commission</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Water</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Accidents and Safety</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE1D7123BF930A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="639" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>No Markings Evident on Cut Water Mains</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <dateline>CLIFTON, N.J., Dec. 2</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey officials probing shattering of two water mains by work crews, Clifton, fail to find any of markings state requires to alert excavators to presence of buried pipes and cables; United Water Resources and Passaic Valley Water Commission say lines had been marked (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>New Jersey officials investigating the shattering of two water mains by work crews here on Tuesday said today that they had not found any of the markings that the state requires as a way of alerting excavators to the presence of buried pipes and cables.</p>
        <p>Under a law passed four years ago after a devastating gas explosion in Edison, companies that own underground pipes must mark their paths with little flags and spray-painted stripes before construction crews may start work near them. The head of the state's investigation into the ruptures said today that inspectors had been unable find any evidence of markings above the pipelines.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>New Jersey officials investigating the shattering of two water mains by work crews here on Tuesday said today that they had not found any of the markings that the state requires as a way of alerting excavators to the presence of buried pipes and cables.</p>
        <p>Under a law passed four years ago after a devastating gas explosion in Edison, companies that own underground pipes must mark their paths with little flags and spray-painted stripes before construction crews may start work near them. The head of the state's investigation into the ruptures said today that inspectors had been unable find any evidence of markings above the pipelines.</p>
        <p>Officials of the water companies said the lines had been marked and suggested that water gushing from the two broken mains might have washed away the paint and flags.</p>
        <p>The ruptures were the most significant since the state enacted the 1994 law in hopes of getting excavators and utility companies to prevent damage to underground pipes and cables. The shattering of the bigger of the two pipes -- a 72-inch-diameter line from the Boonton Reservoir --  left about 300,000 residents in Jersey City, Hoboken and Lyndhurst with no water or low pressure from early morning until mid-afternoon on Tuesday, forced Jersey City's schools to close and disrupted service in stores and restaurants.</p>
        <p>The other pipe, which was 16 inches in diameter, fed only a high-rise apartment complex near the ruptures, at the intersection of the Garden State Parkway and Route 3.</p>
        <p>''At this point, we're investigating why they weren't marked out,'' said James Giuliano, director of the division of service evaluation for the state's Board of Public Utilities. ''We want to get to the heart of why there appeared to be a failure to mark out, and take whatever appropriate action we can.''</p>
        <p>Rich Henning, a spokesman for United Water Resources, which owns the larger main, said the private company that marks its pipeline routes before excavations applied the required markings about a month ago.</p>
        <p>He expressed disappointment that the state released ''preliminary information before a full investigation has been conducted,'' adding, ''We don't have all the information, and releasing it piecemeal is not conducive to getting a full story.''</p>
        <p>Officials at the Passaic Valley Water Commission, which owns the smaller pipe, said that their work crews marked pipes in the vicinity on Nov. 25 but that they were uncertain that they marked the pipe that was cut. James Duprey, the commission's chief engineer, said the site had been extensively damaged by water from the 72-inch main.</p>
        <p>Work crews from J. Fletcher Creamer &amp; Sons of Hackensack, N.J.,  dug into the pipes while installing conduits and fiber optic cables for the E-Z Pass electronic toll system. The company has a $55 million contract to install the wiring and other E-Z Pass electronic equipment on 400 miles of toll roads in New Jersey and Delaware, including the Parkway, the New Jersey Turnpike, the Atlantic City Expressway and a section of Interstate 95 in Delaware, highway officials said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliano said workers from J. Fletcher Creamer had dug into underground lines, including two gas pipes, at least three times since the 1994 law was enacted. Those incidents did not cause injuries or major damage and the company was fined $5,000, he said. ''They are certainly not one of the top offenders in New Jersey,'' he said.</p>
        <p>In this case, he said, the company had fulfilled its legal requirement to notify a clearinghouse, New Jersey One-Call Systems, about its plan to dig near the pipes. Mr. Giuliano also said the clearinghouse properly relayed the news to United Water Resources and the Passaic Valley Water Commission. Once the water companies get the information, they are responsible for marking the routes of their pipes, he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
