<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sacred and Secular Clash at an Auction</title>
    <meta content="03AUCT$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1066910"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sotheby's</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loke, Margarett</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Auctions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Indians, American</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Culture</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981203T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990DE2DE133BF930A35751C1A96E958260" item-length="865" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sacred and Secular Clash at an Auction</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARGARETT LOKE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Loke, Margarett</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sotheby's or consignors withdraw nineteen objects from auction of American Indian art for legal reasons after protests by several Indian tribes; three other objects that Indians asked to be withdrawn go to buyers who say they will turn them over to tribes; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An auction of American Indian art at Sotheby's in Manhattan turned out to be less of an auction than expected yesterday, after protests by several Indian tribes that argued that their cultural heritage should not be sold into private hands.</p>
        <p>Nineteen of the objects, including six that several tribes had asked to  be removed from the auction block, were withdrawn by the auction house or the consignors for legal reasons.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An auction of American Indian art at Sotheby's in Manhattan turned out to be less of an auction than expected yesterday, after protests by several Indian tribes that argued that their cultural heritage should not be sold into private hands.</p>
        <p>Nineteen of the objects, including six that several tribes had asked to  be removed from the auction block, were withdrawn by the auction house or the consignors for legal reasons.</p>
        <p>In three other cases, objects that Indians had also requested be withdrawn -- a Plains ceremonial club, a Yurok ceremonial dance apron and a 16th- or 17th-century Aleut wooden mask -- went to buyers who said they intended to turn them over to the tribes.</p>
        <p>Behind the scenes, the lines were drawn between those who support the Indians' right to repossess sacred objects and those who believe that objects in private hands should remain so.</p>
        <p>In the former camp is Elizabeth Sackler, who advised the successful bidders for the three disputed items. Ms. Sackler, the daughter of the antiquities collector Arthur M. Sackler, is the founder and president of the American Indian Ritual Object Repatriation Foundation in Manhattan. She created the foundation after another Indian auction at Sotheby's in 1991, where she bought and returned to the tribes three masks, two Hopi and one Navajo, that the Indians consider sacred and had asked to be withdrawn from the sale.</p>
        <p>On the other side was the anthropologist Edmund Carpenter, who said that he was ''saddened'' by the  auction's direction. ''Disgust is too positive,'' he said. ''It's a sad scene.''</p>
        <p>He said he deplored a 1990 Federal statute that provides for the return of many Indian objects to the tribes, but makes no provision for housing or caring for the objects.</p>
        <p>An Eskimo wood mask consigned by Mr. Carpenter's wife, Adelaide de Menil, and sought by the Aleuts was purchased by a California woman, Anne Bleecker Corcos, for $46,000. Ms. Corcos, the head of a nonprofit organization that supports Indian issues, said she planned to return the mask to the Aleuts.</p>
        <p>''It's a personal thing,'' she said. ''I feel it's important for native Americans to receive these things back, especially those of ceremonial and spiritual value.''</p>
        <p>Ann Rockefeller Roberts, president of Fund of the Four Directories, a group that offers grants to Indian causes, bought the Yurok apron for $11,500 ''because this is an object that the Yurok nation has identified as sacred to their spiritual practices and cultural lineage.''</p>
        <p>Lawrence Gutstein, an I.B.M. administrator at the company's headquarters in Armonk, N.Y., paid $7,475 for a Plains ceremonial club that the Fort Peck Assiniboine and Sioux Tribes of Montana had asked be withdrawn from auction. ''My interest,'' he said, ''was to return it to its owners. It's a ritual object that has meaning to its community and serves a binding role.''</p>
        <p>Altogether, more than 600 lots of American Indian art were at auction yesterday, and in most cases, their sale was not in dispute.</p>
        <p>Of the 19 objects that were pulled from the sale at the last minute because of unresolved legal issues, 7 were withdrawn because Sotheby's said further research was needed to ascertain whether tribes claiming the items had been notified.</p>
        <p>In the other cases, items were withdrawn because the auction house had not determined whether  the feathers on them were covered by a 1916 act regulating the sale of feathers from certain migratory birds.</p>
        <p>Among the items was a bentwood hunting hat from the Aleut Indians. Representatives of the tribe had protested the hat's sale.</p>
        <p>Ms. de Menil, the hat's consignor, and Mr. Carpenter had rejected requests to withdraw the hat and the Aleut mask, saying that they feared the objects would not be properly cared for by the tribes.</p>
        <p>''My wife and I,'' Mr. Carpenter said, ''have been vigilant in protecting these objects for future generations.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Gutstein and his wife, Nancy, have set up two scholarships (for a young man and young woman) at each of the 30 American Indian tribal colleges in the country.</p>
        <p>A three-member delegation of Aleuts from the Aleutian/Pribilof Islands Association that had flown in from Alaska for the sale expressed pleasure at the outcome yesterday.</p>
        <p>''We are finally breaking the ice and working toward gathering items,  spiritual, ritual and cultural items,'' said Dimitri Philemonof, who heads the association.</p>
        <p>Speaking of the wood mask to be returned to the Aleuts, Allison A. Young, the cultural heritage director of the association, said, ''There are no words to describe the joy the people in the region will feel when they see the ancestral object.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
