<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Viola's Stats and Leverage Both Slide</title>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="468635"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VIOLA, FRANK</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SMITH, CLAIRE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DE1739F930A1575BC0A967958260" item-length="570" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Viola's Stats and Leverage Both Slide</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CLAIRE SMITH</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SMITH, CLAIRE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>When it comes to salary drives, players can sometimes fall to either side of the spectrum.</p>
        <p>Some drive toward a new contract with the skill and aplomb of an Indy racer; witness the Pirates' Bobby Bonilla, a hit this summer and undoubtedly heading for even more successes this winter. Then there's the flip side, the players who wind up in the ditch, losing their gamble that contract offers made in the spring will improve after a good season. Players like Shawon Dunston of the Cubs, who may find his bargaining chips down now that a season-long slump has landed him on the bench.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>When it comes to salary drives, players can sometimes fall to either side of the spectrum.</p>
        <p>Some drive toward a new contract with the skill and aplomb of an Indy racer; witness the Pirates' Bobby Bonilla, a hit this summer and undoubtedly heading for even more successes this winter. Then there's the flip side, the players who wind up in the ditch, losing their gamble that contract offers made in the spring will improve after a good season. Players like Shawon Dunston of the Cubs, who may find his bargaining chips down now that a season-long slump has landed him on the bench.</p>
        <p>And then there's Frank Viola, the left-hander for the New York Mets, caught somewhere in the middle of the two extremes.</p>
        <p>Viola is on the verge of qualifying for free agency because this past spring he declined a Mets' offer of a three-year, $13 million-plus contract, opting to hold out for a four-year deal either here or elsewhere.</p>
        <p>Now Viola has a 12-10 record with a 3.68 earned run average, numbers that might lead some to believe Viola is having a lot of second thoughts about that road not taken. 'No Regrets at All'</p>
        <p>Not so, the pitcher said last night, one day before he was scheduled to face the Cincinnati Reds.</p>
        <p>"No regrets at all," Viola said. "The reason I asked that we not do anything during the season was because, no matter what kind of year I had, I wanted peace of mind. And I've accomplished that. All I have on my mind is pitching. I believe it's all going to work out, no matter what happens this season."</p>
        <p>Viola does admit to two frustrations, neither of which has to do with the lack of a contract. One, he says, deals with the fate of the team, which has so rapidly fallen from contention in the second half. "Just the way we've played, myself, included, it's nothing like I would have ever expected," Viola said. Second-Half Blues</p>
        <p>Personally, Viola does not let himself off the hook, pointing to his 2-5 record and a self-described "horrendous" e.r.a since the All-Star Game break. "You try to do too much," he said. "I've been in the major leagues 10 years and I still do that. I'm not a strikeout pitcher and still I find myself trying to make that perfect pitch instead of just putting the ball into play and letting the fielders take care of it."</p>
        <p>The second frustration dovetails with Viola's second-half woes and his reputation of a first-half wonder and second-half disappointment. Viola thinks that's unfair.</p>
        <p>"In a nutshell, the wins and losses have something to do with a lot of things, things like run support," he said. "That kind of thing is out of my control.</p>
        <p>"The bottom line is that as long as I feel good and feel that I can cut down on some of the little things, some of the mistakes, I feel like I can go on for quite some time."</p>
        <p>Viola, 31 years old, has often said the primary reason he rejected the Mets' offer was the lack of a fourth year on the contract. The pitcher says that his career record and durability justify such a request. "But, from what they've said, they don't want to give anything more than a three-year contract," Viola said.</p>
        <p>Al Harazin, senior vice president of the Mets, would not say whether the last offer made to Viola was on the table or off. "What we've said and what both sides agreed to at the end of spring training is this: 'Let's drop it and start again in the fall, look at the whole situation again then,' " Harazin said.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
