<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Racing Its Rivals, I.B.M. Risks Tripping Itself Up</title>
    <meta content="16PLAC$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/16/technology/16place.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1665259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET PLACE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">International Business Machines Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lohr, Steve</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Market Place (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Sales and Business Development</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sales</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">International Business Machines Corporation</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E4D7113EF935A25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="755" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Racing Its Rivals, I.B.M. Risks Tripping Itself Up</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Racing Its Rivals, I.B.M. Risks Tripping Itself Up</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STEVE LOHR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lohr, Steve</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Disappointing performance that IBM has reported may be nothing more than momentary stumble, but earnings shortfall also points to risk in company's strategy for its corporate services business--main engine of IBM's growth and its hope for prosperous future; risk is that competition in IBM's traditional technology services will erode company's business faster than it can replace it with more lucrative work; graph (Market Place column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The disappointing performance that I.B.M. reported late Thursday may be nothing more than a momentary stumble. But the earnings shortfall, which dragged down the market, also points to the risk in the company's strategy for its corporate services business -- the main engine of I.B.M.'s growth and its hope for a prosperous future.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. is making an ambitious shift in its services business to move beyond helping corporate customers run their data centers to using information technology to make their business operations more efficient. It means putting I.B.M. researchers and software programmers to work for customers to redesign and automate business tasks like procurement, human resources management, accounting and customer service. Customers often hand these tasks over to I.B.M.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>I.B.M.'s disappointing earnings report points to the risk in the company's strategy for its corporate services business.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The disappointing performance that I.B.M. reported late Thursday may be nothing more than a momentary stumble. But the earnings shortfall, which dragged down the market, also points to the risk in the company's strategy for its corporate services business -- the main engine of I.B.M.'s growth and its hope for a prosperous future.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. is making an ambitious shift in its services business to move beyond helping corporate customers run their data centers to using information technology to make their business operations more efficient. It means putting I.B.M. researchers and software programmers to work for customers to redesign and automate business tasks like procurement, human resources management, accounting and customer service. Customers often hand these tasks over to I.B.M.</p>
        <p>The logic is to move up the economic ladder to more complex and more profitable tiers of the services industry, thus staying ahead of rivals offering less expensive services -- Indian outsourcing companies like Infosys, for example, and Dell, which is expanding rapidly in technology services.</p>
        <p>The risk, however, is that competition in its traditional technology services will erode I.B.M.'s business faster than the company can replace it with more lucrative work.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. blamed its services unit for its poor first quarter, which produced earnings of 85 cents a share, 5 cents below Wall Street's expectations.</p>
        <p>''It does suggest that the transition in services is turning out to be tougher than expected,'' said Steven Milunovich, an analyst for Merrill Lynch &amp; Company, which has a buy recommendation on I.B.M.</p>
        <p>I.B.M.'s services business has shown sluggish growth for a year, removing the lift that comes from currency gains from the weak dollar. And analysts have raised concerns about the falling trend in signings of new services contracts, an indicator of future growth. New contract signings in 2004 were $43.1 billion, down from $55.5 billion the year before.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. countered that there were more smaller, short-term contracts. Those deals, I.B.M. said, would yield more profitable growth than the multibillion-dollar, multiyear contracts they often replaced. Services represent more than half of I.B.M.'s revenues.</p>
        <p>The 16 percent drop in mainframe computer sales for the quarter did not help. While mainframe sales account for less than 5 percent of the company's revenues, they pull in a lot of other business for the company, including services, software, maintenance, finance and storage. A.M. Sacconaghi, an analyst for Sanford C. Bernstein &amp; Company, estimates that all the mainframe-related business represents 25 percent of I.B.M. revenues and 40 percent of its profits.</p>
        <p>I.B.M. executives characterized the fall-off in mainframe sales as cyclical and expected.</p>
        <p>Services revenues inched up 3 percent, excluding currency gains, to $11.7 billion in the quarter, and pretax income fell 5 percent, to $942 million. To be sure, the newer services business -- a category I.B.M. calls business performance transformation services -- grew 40 percent, to $900 million, up from $600 million in the year-earlier quarter.</p>
        <p>But that category accounts for less than 10 percent of I.B.M's total services business. ''It's going to take a year or two before the business transformation services really help,'' said Mr. Milunovich of Merrill Lynch.</p>
        <p>Company executives gave no guidance for the second quarter, but said that analysts' profit estimates for the second half of the year were still ''reasonable.'' Mark Loughridge, chief financial officer of I.B.M., told analysts in the Thursday conference call, ''We're driving to get there a different way, on lower revenue, and more cost and expense savings.''</p>
        <p>I.B.M., analysts say, may well trim its payroll by 5,000 or 10,000 workers in its cost-cutting drive, especially in Europe, where business was particularly weak.</p>
        <p>The company's stock price fell sharply yesterday to $76.70, down $6.94, contributing significantly to the overall decline in the market.</p>
        <p>I.B.M., analysts note, is trying to navigate a strategic shift in its services business at a time when the technology industry is growing slowly and erratically, making its task more difficult. Besides lower-cost rivals like the Indian outsourcing companies, it faces competition from companies like Accenture, which had a strong first quarter. Still, even though the ride may be bumpier than expected, the strategic path I.B.M. has chosen seems to be the right one, most analysts say.</p>
        <p>''The going will be tougher for I.B.M., but my sense is that this is a blip rather than a trend,'' said Bob Djurdjevic, president of Annex Research, a technology services consulting firm.</p>
        <p>MARKET PLACE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
