<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>2 Mobile Phone Makers Report Declines in Profit</title>
    <meta content="16TECH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="16" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/04/16/business/businessspecial3/16tech.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1665227"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Sony Ericsson Mobile Communications</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Samsung Electronics Co</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cellular Telephones</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Telephones and Telecommunications</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Samsung Electronics Co</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050416T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD9113EF935A25757C0A9639C8B63" item-length="418" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>2 Mobile Phone Makers Report Declines in Profit</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">2 Mobile Phone Makers Report Declines in Profit</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ERIC PFANNER and CHOE SANG-HUN; Eric Pfanner reported from London for this article and Choe Sang-Hun from Seoul.</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Samsung Electronics and Sony Ericsson, world's leading mobile phone makers, report huge declines in first-quarter profit; Samsung's net profit dropped 52 percent, to 1.50 trillion won, or $1.47 billion; sales declined 4.2 percent, to 13.81 trillon won, or $13.55 billion; Sony Ericsson's net earnings declined 61 percent, to 32 million euros, or $41.02 million, while sales were 1.29 billion euros, or $1.65 billion, down 4 percent (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two of the world's leading mobile phone makers, Samsung Electronics and Sony Ericsson, reported steep tumbles in profit yesterday, accelerating a slide in technology stocks worldwide.</p>
        <p>Both companies said harsh competition hurt their results. Samsung's first-quarter net profit sank 52 percent, to 1.50 trillion won, or $1.47 billion. Sales fell 4.2 percent, to 13.81 trillion won, or $13.55 billion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Samsung Electronics and Sony Ericsson reported steep tumbles in profit on Friday, accelerating a slide in technology stocks worldwide.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two of the world's leading mobile phone makers, Samsung Electronics and Sony Ericsson, reported steep tumbles in profit yesterday, accelerating a slide in technology stocks worldwide.</p>
        <p>Both companies said harsh competition hurt their results. Samsung's first-quarter net profit sank 52 percent, to 1.50 trillion won, or $1.47 billion. Sales fell 4.2 percent, to 13.81 trillion won, or $13.55 billion.</p>
        <p>At Sony Ericsson, quarterly net earnings plummeted 61 percent, to 32 million euros, or $41.02 million, while sales were 1.29 billion euros, or $1.65 billion, down 4 percent.</p>
        <p>The results sent chills through consumer electronics shares in Asia and Europe as well as on Wall Street, where I.B.M.'s poor results Thursday had already hit the market. Samsung fell 2.09 percent, and the two companies that make up Sony Ericsson also fell. Sony dropped 2.65 percent and Ericsson was down 3.35 percent.</p>
        <p>Motorola and Nokia, which will report next week, dropped 2.12 percent and 1.4 percent respectively. The Nasdaq stock index, which contains many technology companies, fell 38.56 points, or 1.3 percent, to 1,908.15 yesterday.</p>
        <p>The mobile phone industry is struggling to find the new must-have feature to drive sales the way last year's novelty, the camera phone, did. The cameras became an almost universal accessory in new phones, replacing cigarette lighters as the accessory of choice in teenagers' outstretched arms at rock concerts.</p>
        <p>The popularity of the camera phones sent sales of mobile phones up 25 percent, to 670 million units last year, according to Ovum, a technology research company based in London. This year, sales are expected to rise only 8 percent, Ovum said.</p>
        <p>The slowdown was evident at both Sony Ericsson and Samsung. Profits were squeezed by falling prices of phones and, in the case of Samsung, chips and other products, too.</p>
        <p>Martin Garner, director of wireless research at Ovum, said the softness in the mobile phone market might be relatively short-lived. The industry still has high hopes for new technologies.</p>
        <p>In Asia, technology and other major manufacturing stocks had a generally bad week after a smaller-than-expected increase in March retail sales in the United States, signaling possible sluggishness in the top export market for Asian electronics makers.</p>
        <p>Samsung, which has been the most profitable technology company outside the United States, and its competitors have been hit by falling prices of computer chips and liquid-crystal displays and lower profit margins on mobile phones.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
