<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Craps 101 (a Noncredit Class)</title>
    <meta content="22TAFFY" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="New Jersey Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13NJ" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="ATLANTIC CITY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="878640"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="ATLANTIC CITY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Craps (Game)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Slot Machines</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Caesars Atlantic City Hotel-Casino</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kent, Bill</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Slot Machines</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Casinos</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gambling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A06E4DA1E3AF931A1575AC0A960958260" item-length="808" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Craps 101 (a Noncredit Class)</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BILL KENT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kent, Bill</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>*Caesars Atlantic City Hotel-Casino, NJ, is luring gamblers back to craps tables by teaching the game; craps, a popular game in Las Vegas, Nev, in 1950's, has suffered decline in interest in Atlantic City; since 1994, most Atlantic City casinos have reduced number of craps tables to make room for more slot machines; photo (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE dice tumbled and lay still. ''A 9 for the shooter! Shooter makes his point!'' Brian Guiliani called out like a peppy sports announcer.</p>
        <p>''Pass line wins; dealer pays all pass line bets,'' he explained as he doubled the number of gambling chips on the craps table's pass line. ''Now, isn't that a beautiful thing.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE dice tumbled and lay still. ''A 9 for the shooter! Shooter makes his point!'' Brian Guiliani called out like a peppy sports announcer.</p>
        <p>''Pass line wins; dealer pays all pass line bets,'' he explained as he doubled the number of gambling chips on the craps table's pass line. ''Now, isn't that a beautiful thing.''</p>
        <p>''Breaks your heart,'' grumbled a student gambler, whose chips on the don't-pass line rapidly disappeared.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani smiled affably. ''You win some and you lose some.''</p>
        <p>And sometimes you learn. For six people slumped around a craps table at Caesars at 6 P.M., the goal was education, not prosperity. Of varying ages, dress and stages of inebriation, they had assembled for an hour's free instruction in Atlantic City's fastest, most confusing and, in some casinos, least popular game.</p>
        <p>''Everybody says craps is hard to understand, but it's really very simple,'' continued Mr. Giuliani, one of eight Caesars employees who teach the game to beginning gamblers.</p>
        <p>''You've got your meat-and-potatoes bets, like the pass line,'' he said. ''Then you've got your numbers. You can also bet on the number the shooter wants to roll, which is, at the moment, the number 9. Or you can bet on the numbers the shooter doesn't want to roll. Or you can bet on combinations of numbers. Simple, right?''</p>
        <p>Perhaps for some. Others are intimidated by the bewildering array of bets and payouts. A winning $10 bet on 9, for example, will return $10, $14 or $15, depending on when the bet is made during the game and where it is positioned on the table.</p>
        <p>The language can also puzzle beginners. Only in craps can you turn your bets on and off; lay bets, buy bets or lay odds; bet the field, bet the horn, bet the high horn, bet the hardway, bet ''any craps'' (2, 3 and 12) or bet ''the yo'' (11).</p>
        <p>A popular game in Las Vegas in the 1950's, craps has suffered a decline in interest in Atlantic City as the game's players, mostly older,  have been supplanted by baby-boomers who prefer blackjack, roulette and slot machines. Since 1994, most Atlantic City's casinos have reduced the number of craps tables to make room for more slot machines.</p>
        <p>A few casinos, like Caesars and most recently Harrah's, have tried to attract new gamblers to the game by offering classes. Joseph Brunini, the executive who designed the Caesar's instructional craps program, said about 3,000 people had taken the class since last September.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to expose people to the game in a humorous fashion, to get them past the intimidation many of them feel,'' Mr. Brunini said. ''We also wanted to make it as realistic as possible. The way it used to be, if you wanted to learn the game, you could find some dealers who weren't busy, and if they had the time, they could run through the bets for you. But if they got a game going, they had to give their entire attention to the game. And if you wanted to try betting, you had to use your own money, which can be very intimidating.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Brunini specified that his teachers, culled from the casino's dealers and supervisors, would give students ''complete and undivided attention, answering any question, no matter what.'' He also has instructors give each student a stack of  dummy chips so that the simulated game the students play is ''as close as you can get to the real thing.''</p>
        <p>Playing even a simulated game in a casino setting tends to inspire students to put their newly acquired education to use. Because the casino tracks the students' gambling, Mr. Brunini could say that none of his instructional craps graduates had experienced severe losses.</p>
        <p>''We don't tell them what to bet,'' he added. ''We just tell them what the bets are, and that makes the students come out of the courses a little cautious. They've been more apt to play the low-limit tables and stick with the safer bets.''</p>
        <p>Caesars offers craps lessons at noon and 6 P.M. Mondays through Fridays, with lessons in blackjack, roulette and mini-baccarat throughout the day. The lessons last about an hour and are free to anyone over 21.</p>
        <p>Mr. Giuliani said he didn't have an answer to the most frequently asked question. ''When they ask me how to win, the best I can do is say it's like surfing,'' he said. ''If you catch a nice wave, you'll have a nice time.''</p>
        <p>Asked how to catch a nice wave, Mr. Giuliani said he didn't surf.</p>
        <p>ATLANTIC CITY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
