<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Care Is Required With Roof Repairs</title>
    <meta content="WCCLINIC" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="HOME CLINIC" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="878756"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="HOME CLINIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOME REPAIR</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Roofing and Siding</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Home Repairs</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lipinski, Edward R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D04E0DD143DF931A1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1033" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Care Is Required With Roof Repairs</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD R. LIPINSKI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lipinski, Edward R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Edward R Lipinski column offers advice on repairing roof; drawing (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE part of the house that receives the most punishment from the elements is the roof. It is assaulted by rain and snow, baked by the hot sun and buffeted by severe winds. Sooner or later, even the best roof will show signs of wear and tear. Unfortunately, this is also the part of the house that receives the least care because it is relatively inaccessible.</p>
        <p>Still, it is essential to inspect the roof at least once a year for signs of damaged or missing shingles. Climbing onto a high roof can be dangerous, especially if it has a steep pitch. Wait for a calm, dry day for the inspection. Wear rubber-soled shoes; do not attempt to climb on a wet roof. Make sure that you understand, and follow, all ladder safety rules. When moving about on the roof, watch for loose or torn shingles, moss, wet leaves or other debris. If you are unsure of yourself on a high roof, call a professional to complete the job.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE part of the house that receives the most punishment from the elements is the roof. It is assaulted by rain and snow, baked by the hot sun and buffeted by severe winds. Sooner or later, even the best roof will show signs of wear and tear. Unfortunately, this is also the part of the house that receives the least care because it is relatively inaccessible.</p>
        <p>Still, it is essential to inspect the roof at least once a year for signs of damaged or missing shingles. Climbing onto a high roof can be dangerous, especially if it has a steep pitch. Wait for a calm, dry day for the inspection. Wear rubber-soled shoes; do not attempt to climb on a wet roof. Make sure that you understand, and follow, all ladder safety rules. When moving about on the roof, watch for loose or torn shingles, moss, wet leaves or other debris. If you are unsure of yourself on a high roof, call a professional to complete the job.</p>
        <p>Carerfully inspect the roof covering. If you have asphalt singles, they may be cracked or have missing corners. These are not serious problems; they can be repaired with roofing cement (available at home centers).</p>
        <p>To repair a cracked shingle gently raise it and apply cement under the crack. Press the shingle onto the cement layer then smooth more cement over the crack. If you find a shingle with a torn corner, do not attempt to repair it with a new corner piece. Instead, raise the shingle and cover the exposed area with roofing cement. Press down a piece of aluminum flashing (available in rolls in hardware stores and home centers) and nail it in place. Cover the nail heads with more roofing cement.</p>
        <p>Admittedly, repairs with roofing cement are somewhat unsightly; but they are effective in stopping leaks, and few people will see the remedy from below. Perfectionists, however, may prefer to remove the damaged shingle and replace it with a new one.</p>
        <p>Cold weather can make asphalt shingles stiff and brittle. Flexing or bending can break them. If possible, wait for a warm, sunny day when the shingle will be soft and pliable to make roof repairs.</p>
        <p>Some shingles may be curled up away from the roof. Apply a generous dab of roofing cement under the shingle, then press it onto the cement. It may be necessary to weight it down until the cement sets.</p>
        <p>Shingles that are severely torn or missing must be replaced. Before you can position the replacement, you'll have to remove the torn shingle and also the roofing nails that secure it. The nails will be concealed under the good shingles overlapping the damaged one. Gently bend these back and pull the nails with a pry bar. Again, do not attempt to do this on a cold day.</p>
        <p>Another way to remove a damaged shingle is by slipping a hacksaw blade (wrap one end of the blade with tape to protect your hand or use a mini-hacksaw) under it and saw through the hold-down nails. Pull the shingle out and slide a new one in place. Secure it with roofing nails. Finish the job by dabbing roofing cement under the new shingle.</p>
        <p>Not all roofs are protected with asphalt shingles. Some have wood shakes or shingles (wood shingles are smaller and lighter than wood shakes, and they are commonly sawed on one or both sides). Problems with wood shakes and shingles include splits and cracks, buckles and severe rotting.</p>
        <p>Cracks or splits in wood shingles will let water seep through the roof. Fill narrow cracks with roofing cement. Wider ( 1/2 inch or more) cracks should be backed with aluminum flashing. Secure the flashing by driving a nail (3d aluminum, or galvanized nail) on either side of the crack. The bottom of the nail head should be flush with the surface of the shingle, not countersunk into it. Cover the crack and nail heads with roofing cement.</p>
        <p>When a wood shingle absorbs too much moisture, it can swell and buckle away from the roof. In order to flatten the shingle, you'll have to remove some wood from the buckle. Use a wood chisel to make two splits about  1/8- to  1/4-inch apart. Remove the sliver of wood from between the cracks. Press the shingle down and secure it with two nails. Cover the crack and nail heads with roofing cement.</p>
        <p>Replacing a damaged wood shingle requires a bit more skill. First, you'll have to split the old shingle into pieces with a wood chisel. Be careful with the chisel, you don't want to damage the surrounding shingles or you'll have to replace them also. Pull out the split pieces, then use a hacksaw blade to cut the nails that held the damaged shingle. Trim a new shingle to size, then tap it into place. The fit should be loose, with about  1/8 inch of space on either side to allow for moisture expansion.</p>
        <p>Nailing a replacement wood shingle in place is not as simple as nailing an asphalt shingle, because you cannot bend back the overlapping shingle. The easiest way to nail this shingle is by driving a nail through the expansion gaps (one nail in each gap) in the overlapping shingles. Put a dab of roofing cement in the gap to cover the nail heads. Do not overdo the cement here or you'll clog the expansion joint.</p>
        <p>A better way to protect the nail head is with a ''copper bib.'' This is a small piece of flexible copper about four inches square. Bend the copper until it has a slight concave shape, then slip it under the overlapping shingle, concave side up, until it covers the nail head. The slight bend in the metal will create a friction fit that will keep the piece in place.</p>
        <p>HOME CLINIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
