<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LeRoy Neiman Looks In the Mirror</title>
    <meta content="22YORK" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="NEW YORKERS &amp; CO." name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="878835"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="NEW YORKERS &amp; CO."/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="biographical_categories">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="names">LeRoy Neiman</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Columbia University</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewine, Edward</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Neiman, LeRoy</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Gifts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960922T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E01E3DB153DF931A1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1156" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LeRoy Neiman Looks In the Mirror</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By EDWARD LEWINE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewine, Edward</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on artist LeRoy Neiman discusses his career and notes that he has donated $6 million to Columbia University for new printmaking studio; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE man who is arguably America's best-known artist leaned back in his baronial Central Park West duplex and rested his feet, encased in paint-splattered tennis shoes, on the desk in front of him. Lighted from behind by mid-September sun, LeRoy Neiman was trying to sum up a career spent in a brighter spotlight.</p>
        <p>''I've been doing a self-assessment about how this whole thing flew by,'' said Mr. Neiman, in his typical tongue-in-cheek fashion. ''It's got to mean something. I gave my life to it.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE man who is arguably America's best-known artist leaned back in his baronial Central Park West duplex and rested his feet, encased in paint-splattered tennis shoes, on the desk in front of him. Lighted from behind by mid-September sun, LeRoy Neiman was trying to sum up a career spent in a brighter spotlight.</p>
        <p>''I've been doing a self-assessment about how this whole thing flew by,'' said Mr. Neiman, in his typical tongue-in-cheek fashion. ''It's got to mean something. I gave my life to it.''</p>
        <p>And what a life! From the late 1950's to the early 1970's, when television was creating a new class of celebrities, Mr. Neiman was everywhere, inventing himself as a star painter who portrayed the newly minted stars. In his bright, Neo-Impressionist style he depicted a fantasy of Playboy bunnies, sports heroes and luxe locations from Monte Carlo to the Caribbean. One day would find him sketching the Masters golf tournament in Georgia; the next, painting Prince Philip in Britain.</p>
        <p>''It was nonstop partying and everything else,'' said Frank Gifford, who played football for the New York Giants during those years. ''And he was the historian of that time.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Neiman took his shot at fame and big money and hit the bull's-eye. But these days, as time grows short, he wonders more and more: if he had done things differently, could he have also won critical respect? ''Neiman has become what Norman Rockwell was to an earlier generation,'' said Arthur C. Danto, art critic for The Nation and a philosophy professor at Columbia University. ''It would be difficult to find anyone who would defend Rockwell or Neiman.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Neiman has felt much worse from the critical lash.</p>
        <p>''It's reached me now, this evaluation,'' he said. ''I take it seriously because I take my work seriously.''</p>
        <p>He is in his 70's now, his famous brushed-back hair and wide mustache are still brown, and his paintings, prints, drawings and books make a small mint. But lately he has been in what his good friend and employer Hugh Hefner of Playboy magazine calls a more reflective mode. ''The days of my going to everything are over,'' Mr. Neiman said. ''Things don't supply me with the vibes I used to get.''</p>
        <p>What Mr. Neiman has been concentrating on instead is philanthropy. He said that his donations -- of his archives to the Smithsonian Institution and of paintings to a proposed LeRoy Neiman Museum in his hometown, St. Paul -- had given him the opportunity to look back. Now a $6 million gift to underwrite a printmaking studio on the Columbia campus may offer him some inner redemption.</p>
        <p>Mr. Neiman presents himself as someone who just fell into good fortune, but he has worked to get where he is. The signature moment in Mr. Neiman's life was meeting Mr. Hefner in 1950, for Mr. Neiman is the quintessential Playboy artist. The success of both the magazine and the artist is based on repackaging a certain vision of the ''good life'' for an audience that has no access to that life.</p>
        <p>''These things don't happen by accident,'' said Mr. Hefner. ''You have to invent yourself.''</p>
        <p>And both Mr. Hefner and Mr. Neiman understood their audience. They had been born into modest Midwestern households with dreams of something bigger. Mr. Neiman's most important Playboy work was ''Man at His Leisure,'' a series of travel articles, which he wrote and illustrated, that focused on chic events like bullfights in Spain or the Cannes film festival. He invented an artistic vocabulary to celebrate high living and created his own celebrity.</p>
        <p>He came to Manhattan in 1963. It was in the years of Namath, Mantle and Ali that Mr. Neiman became associated with big-time sports.</p>
        <p>By the 1970's sports had propelled him onto television himself when he began painting on camera for ABC. With his Salvador Dali face, he was a natural. But somehow, the success was unsatisfying. Mr. Neiman says he has allowed himself to follow the path of least resistance.</p>
        <p>''The mob knows me, but Jasper Johns couldn't care less,'' he said. ''I have a great respect for elitists. There's got to be something very satisfying about reaching a discerning audience.''</p>
        <p>At other times he remains defiant. ''I can't satisfy the people who don't like my work,'' he says. ''Or give the people who like it any more than I already have.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Neiman is waging this psychic struggle with customary grace and detachment. These days, he is looking forward to the opening of the print center at Columbia in January. He craves contact with the world of ''high'' art. ''It is a way for me to work toward the area of art that I have disregarded incorrectly,'' he said.</p>
        <p>At a time of life when many people limit themselves, Mr. Neiman is reaching out. Not that he has any illusions about how the world works. As autumn moves toward winter, Mr. Neiman knows he'll have to keep going it alone.</p>
        <p>''I'd love to hang out with the critics who don't like what I do,'' he said. ''But there are some things that are out of the question. You can't let it get to you.''</p>
        <p>NEW YORKERS &amp; CO.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
