<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Argentine Leader Sees Gulf Role As Best Way to Reverse Old Image</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="388010"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CREDIT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOREIGN INVESTMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ARMAMENT, DEFENSE AND MILITARY FORCES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARGENTINA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">IRAQ</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">SAUDI ARABIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">KUWAIT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MENEM, CARLOS SAUL (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GOLDEN, TIM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Americas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Kuwait</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Central and South America/Argentina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Saudi Arabia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Foreign Investments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4D81738F932A35753C1A966958260" item-length="781" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Argentine Leader Sees Gulf Role As Best Way to Reverse Old Image</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TIM GOLDEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">GOLDEN, TIM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: President Carlos Saul Menem of Argentina, the only Latin American leader to order forces to join the blockade against Iraq, says he did so in the hope of presenting a new image of his country as a reliable partner.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: President Carlos Saul Menem of Argentina, the only Latin American leader to order forces to join the blockade against Iraq, says he did so in the hope of presenting a new image of his country as a reliable partner.</p>
        <p>President Carlos Saul Menem of Argentina, the only Latin American leader to order forces to join the blockade against Iraq, says he did so in the hope of presenting a new image of his country as a reliable partner.</p>
        <p>''We felt that we could not take the same attitude of other years, which caused us serious damage,'' Mr. Menem said in an interview on Saturday evening, referring to his country's neutrality throughout most of World War II. ''This attitude of Argentina opens enormous possibilities for us in the new international order.''</p>
        <p>First among those opportunities will be the chance to meet privately in New York with President Bush on a day when some 70 other foreign leaders will be jockeying for the American leader's attention.</p>
        <p>After Mr. Menem announced on Sept. 19 that he would send two warships, a cargo plane and as many as 450 troops to the Persian Gulf, United States officials rescheduled a session with President Bush that Mr. Menem was to have shared with several other foreign leaders. The two Presidents and their aides are now to have breakfast together this morning.</p>
        <p>Sees Positive Response</p>
        <p>Despite protests in Buenos Aires against Mr. Menem's decision, including criticism from some lawmakers in his own Peronist party, Mr. Menem said that reaction elsewhere had been quick and positive.</p>
        <p>He pointedly noted the congratulations of Prime Minister Margaret Thatcher of Britain, from whom warm words until recently would have been unimaginable.</p>
        <p>Argentina's last military conflict was its six-week war in 1982 over the Falkland Islands, which it lost to Britain. Immediately after taking office, Mr. Menem sought a rapprochement that led to the restoration in February of full diplomatic relations between the two countries. Argentina still claims sovereignty over the islands.</p>
        <p>''Argentina has been treated in the last few years like a country that was unserious and unreliable,'' President Menem said. ''Argentina is now relocating itself in a world that will make possible its definitive and sustained development.''</p>
        <p>Reassuring Creditors</p>
        <p>Mr. Menem said he did not expect an Argentine presence in the gulf to be rewarded with direct economic aid from abroad. But other Argentine officials said the move was one of many intended to reshape Argentina's international image in a way that would reassure creditor nations and potential foreign investors.</p>
        <p>The Argentine Foreign Minister, Domingo Cavallo, noted that his country acceded last fall to a request by President Bush that it halt cooperation with Iraq and Egypt on the development of the Condor-2 ballistic missile. Mr. Cavallo said the missile program has been phased out over the last year.</p>
        <p>Mr. Cavallo said in an interview that Mr. Menem would use his meeting with President Bush to discuss not only the gulf crisis, but trade issues. Argentina is opposed to subsidies for American grain and is requesting that Washington lift import duties on Argentine steel, leather and fruit juices.</p>
        <p>Since he took office 14 months ago, Mr. Menem has scaled back state control of the economy. But despite policies that have reduced inflation from a rate of more than 200 percent the month he became President, the economy remains unstable. He said his Government was having difficulty attracting buyers for some of the companies it wants to sell.</p>
        <p>Will Fight Isolation</p>
        <p>Mr. Menem said that one Peronist experience he is determined not to repeat was Argentina's economic isolation, particularly in regard to the United States, in the decade after World War II when Juan D. Peron ruled the country.</p>
        <p>As a powerful army colonel and then as Minister of War and Vice President, Mr. Peron was prominent among the nationalist officers who sought to keep Argentina neutral until near the end of World War II. Argentina finally declared war on Germany and Japan in late March of 1945.</p>
        <p>Later the United States helped send the Argentine economy into a tailspin when it rejected a plea to let the recovering nations of Western Europe spend Marshall Plan dollars on imports from Argentina.</p>
        <p>Contrary to reports of some Argentine military opposition to the shipment of troops to the Persian Gulf, Mr. Menem declared, officers are ''lining up to go.'' He said that many of those volunteering were veterans of the war for the Falklands.</p>
        <p>With the prospect of military conflict with its neighbors virtually nonexistent, other Argentine officials say, the country's armed forces should focus their efforts on taking part in international security missions.</p>
        <p>''The old hypotheses of conflict are losing their validity,'' Mr. Cavallo said. ''If the armed forces aren't available for this, what are they for?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
