<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Remaking the North Stars</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="388138"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MINNESOTA NORTH STARS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPOINTE, JOE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE7DF113BF932A35753C1A966958260" item-length="1485" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Remaking the North Stars</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOE LAPOINTE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LAPOINTE, JOE</byline>
      <dateline>BLOOMINGTON, Minn.</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: SHORTLY after he bought 51 percent of the Minnesota North Stars in June, Norman Green grew unhappy with Howard Baldwin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: SHORTLY after he bought 51 percent of the Minnesota North Stars in June, Norman Green grew unhappy with Howard Baldwin.</p>
        <p>SHORTLY after he bought 51 percent of the Minnesota North Stars in June, Norman Green grew unhappy with Howard Baldwin.</p>
        <p>Among other things, he didn't think Baldwin, the team president, was dismissing employees fast enough. So he got rid of Baldwin and eventually eliminated about 70 percent of the staff.</p>
        <p>''We gave out 900 dismissal slips,'' said Green, who runs his business lean and mean.</p>
        <p>Although the staff cuts please him, Green isn't happy about other provisions of the agreement in which the North Stars remained in Minnesota under new ownership while their former owners got an expansion franchise in San Jose, Calif.</p>
        <p>''It's a screwy deal,'' said Green, who intends to change its terms. ''The Board of Governors was so eager to see this team stay here they had to grasp at any good news. I hope these types of deals never happen again.''</p>
        <p>With a new owner in Green, a new general manager in Bob Clarke and a new coach in Bob Gainey, the North Stars management is trying to rebuild a longstanding franchise that has become a source of worry and embarrassment to the National Hockey League.</p>
        <p>The fate of the North Stars, a team that has struggled for success and support despite operating in a hotbed of hockey, could have a significant impact on the image of the sport as a business as it begins a seven-team expansion through the 1990's.</p>
        <p>Green comes from a background of success, a shopping center developer who has owned 18 percent of the thriving Calgary Flames for the last decade.</p>
        <p>Clarke, a Hall of Fame player, comes from the Philadelphia Flyers, where he was dismissed last spring after his team's record declined for the fifth consecutive season.</p>
        <p>Gainey, a former defensive star of the Montreal Canadiens with five Stanley Cup rings to prove it, is a rookie N.H.L. coach who worked last season as a player-coach for a minor league team in France.</p>
        <p>Green calls the revival of the Minnesota franchise ''the ultimate entrepreneur's dream,'' although he considers the terms an entrepreneur's nightmare.</p>
        <p>According to provisions of the franchise agreement that Baldwin had helped negotiate, the former owners, the Gund brothers, will get 30 players from the Minnesota organization in 1991 to start an expansion franchise called the San Jose Sharks.</p>
        <p>Green, who bought into the North Stars after this deal was made, thinks terms are too generous to San Jose, too damaging to Minnesota.</p>
        <p>''We are willing to be fair, but if we must deal from strength, we will,'' Green said of his proposed renegotiation with the Gunds. ''If we feel we are not being treated fairly, we can harm them. The North Stars are not going to be intimidated.''</p>
        <p>The Gund brothers, George and Gordon, will have no public comment, a team spokesman said. ''They're not happy about it,'' Green said. John Ziegler, the N.H.L. president, won't comment, either, a league spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Art Savage, chief executive officer of the Sharks, said, ''We're not interested in re-negotiating the deal.'' But he says the team is willing to listen to whatever Green proposes. In the meantime, in the first of Green's anti-Shark sanctions, San Jose is the only team that won't get free passes for its scouts during games in Minnesota.</p>
        <p>''That's correct,'' said Savage. ''But we can afford to pay to get into the games.''</p>
        <p>And the North Stars need all the ticket buyers they can get. They averaged about 8,000 fans a game last season under the Gunds, who had threatened to move the team to San Jose. Although the Stars have existed for 24 years in one of the most hockey-oriented locations in the United States, the Gunds - who had been involved with two other failed hockey franchises in Oakland and Cleveland - said they couldn't make the hockey business profitable in the Twin Cities.</p>
        <p>Abandoning Minnesota on the eve of expansion, ''would have been terrible,'' said Green.</p>
        <p>How could the N.H.L. entice investors to put up $50 million for expansion franchises in places like California, Texas and Florida, the theory goes, if experienced owners couldn't sell the game in the Land of 10,000 Lakes, where water freezes naturally in the winter and hockey thrives in high schools and colleges?</p>
        <p>''Expansion might have been in serious trouble,'' Green said of the proposed move of the North Stars.</p>
        <p>So the Board of Governors awarded the Gunds an expansion franchise and approved the sale of the North Stars to Baldwin and his partner, Morris Belzberg, last May.</p>
        <p>When Baldwin and Belzberg had trouble raising money to complete the deal in June, they offered controlling interest to Green. The N.H.L. approved the new deal. Baldwin emerged with 24.5 percent of the Minnesota franchise, although he had put up little of his own money to purchase it. Belzberg got the other 24.5 percent.</p>
        <p>Shortly after Baldwin left his presidential office, he sold his share to Green for an unannounced sum. ''Howard made a handsome profit,'' Green said. ''He's entitled to it.''</p>
        <p>That makes Baldwin the first North Stars' owner to profit from the team in several years. The Gunds said they were losing millions every season and Green says he feels ''sorry'' for them.</p>
        <p>''They mismanaged a franchise in a good market in a growing industry,'' Green said. ''The things they did were nonsensible. It was a disaster.''</p>
        <p>Another disaster last year was Clarke's Flyers. Although successful at the gate, they missed the playoffs for the first time in 18 seasons. Some of the critics blamed Clarke's loyalty to veteran players. Green suggests that Clarke didn't get full freedom to operate under Jay Snider, the team president.</p>
        <p>''The choice to leave the Flyers wasn't my own, and you don't forget overnight,'' said Clarke, captain of the team when it won the Stanley Cup twice in the mid-1970's. Was he limited in his role as Flyers' general manager? ''Whatever I say will look like a slap at the Flyers,'' he said. Does he have enough power under Green? ''Yes,'' he said. ''There are no restrictions on me other than the deal with the Gunds.''</p>
        <p>If that deal holds, the Stars have a dilemma. The only players they can protect are those that had 50 N.H.L. games as of last spring. If they bring up a rookie and he blossoms this season, the Sharks can take him.</p>
        <p>''It is an unenviable position,'' Clarke said. ''You still want to put the best possible team on the ice.''</p>
        <p>He took the new job, he said, because ''I wanted to stay in the N.H.L. and I wanted to work.''</p>
        <p>''I don't think I have anything to prove,'' Clarke said, ''but when you get fired like I did, you get scared. Scared that I wouldn't get back in the league. I worked hard and I was loyal and, all of a sudden, I was out in the street. It's not a very friendly place when you are out on the street.'' Green says Clarke has ''quiet intelligence.'' Clarke has viewed the Minnesota franchise as an outsider for two decades.</p>
        <p>''I remember coming here as a player,'' he said. ''At first, it seemed like a great franchise. Building full. Snow on the ground. Hockey country. ''Then, as a manager, I remember so much turmoil all the time here. It had to filter through to the team.''</p>
        <p>Clarke hired Gainey, who had been vice president of the N.H.L. Players Association when Clarke was president.  ''I played against him and I played with him in Canada Cup tournaments and I knew him very well,'' Clarke said. ''He has a lot of knowledge and a lot of confidence. He played on championship teams with championship players. He knows the committment it takes.''</p>
        <p>Gainey, a man of serious visage and deep voice, says, ''I am a player still in my mind.'' He doesn't expect all the players to like him, he said, just as not all Montreal players liked Scotty Bowman when Bowman led Montreal to four consecutive cup championships after the reign of Clarke's Flyers.</p>
        <p>''He was uncompromising on things that were important,'' Gainey said of Bowman. ''I enjoyed my time with Scotty because of all the success. Those things leave a mark on you and I have a few of those marks.''</p>
        <p>He said one of the lures of coming to Minnesota is ''the chance of the upside potential.''</p>
        <p>Green agrees, saying he expects to show profit in a year or two. He says he wants to buy the Met Center and expand it and pulls from his desk an architect's drawing of proposed balconies. He plans to put private luxury boxes near ice level. He will change the color and fabric of every seat. He will put in a television replay board above center ice.</p>
        <p>He strides through the building, a tall, lean man with gray hair and gray suit, bending over to re-arrange the furniture in the private lounge for luxury seat buyers. He stops to buff with his sleeve the brass North Stars' pin on an employee's lapel.</p>
        <p>After the game, Green passes through the locker room, shaking hands and chatting with players. But he says he won't interfere with the affairs of Clarke and Gainey.</p>
        <p>''They'll do the hockey thing,'' Green said. ''I'll do the business thing.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
