<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Founders of Shelter Honored at a Benefit</title>
    <meta content="ABUSE.$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="969777"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Westchester County (NY)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">My Sisters' Place (Women's Shelter)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wetzler, Cynthia Magriel</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Steinem, Gloria</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Violence</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Domestic Violence</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971102T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E2D91031F931A35752C1A961958260" item-length="1073" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Founders of Shelter Honored at a Benefit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CYNTHIA MAGRIEL WETZLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Wetzler, Cynthia Magriel</byline>
      <dateline>TARRYTOWN</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Fund-raising dinner is held in Tarrytown, NY, for My Sisters' Place, refuge for abused women in Westchester; Gloria Steinem gives keynote address; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BEFORE domestic violence was called by that name people used to consider it life, said Gloria Steinem, the feminist writer who helped found Ms. magazine. In a keynote address at a fund-raising dinner here last month for My Sisters' Place, a refuge for abused women in Westchester, Ms. Steinem identified intimate violence as the familiar and acceptable seed of larger arenas of violence in society. ''Violence feels like home,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In 1978 at a time when domestic abuse was considered simply a marital problem, a group of Westchester women opened a shelter in Yonkers, the first residential refuge in Westchester for battered women and their children. That shelter is now My Sister's Place, with offices in White Plains and a staff of 20 women and men. (Before 1978 it was not against state law for a husband to beat or kick his wife or force her to have sexual relations.)</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BEFORE domestic violence was called by that name people used to consider it life, said Gloria Steinem, the feminist writer who helped found Ms. magazine. In a keynote address at a fund-raising dinner here last month for My Sisters' Place, a refuge for abused women in Westchester, Ms. Steinem identified intimate violence as the familiar and acceptable seed of larger arenas of violence in society. ''Violence feels like home,'' she said.</p>
        <p>In 1978 at a time when domestic abuse was considered simply a marital problem, a group of Westchester women opened a shelter in Yonkers, the first residential refuge in Westchester for battered women and their children. That shelter is now My Sister's Place, with offices in White Plains and a staff of 20 women and men. (Before 1978 it was not against state law for a husband to beat or kick his wife or force her to have sexual relations.)</p>
        <p>At the dinner at Abigail Kirsch at Tappan Hill, special tribute was paid to the 17 founders of the shelter as ''true pioneers who identified unmet needs of women in Westchester and mustered the resources and support to do something about them at a time when such was unheard of,'' said Charlotte Watson, executive director of My Sisters' Place. The event also celebrated a second shelter for battered women, opening in Mamaroneck, which will be accessible to the disabled.</p>
        <p>About 400 people attended the dinner, including Assemblywoman Naomi C. Matusow, Democrat from Mount Kisco, and State Senator Suzi R. Oppenheimer, Democrat from Mamaroneck. The event also honored the shelter's benefactors.</p>
        <p>Since 1978 My Sisters' Place has answered more than 15,000 hot line calls, given refuge to more than 1,400 women and 1,900 children in its 15-bed shelter, but has had to turn away more than 5,000 women because of a lack of space.</p>
        <p>My Sisters' Place also provides counseling, 14 community-based support groups, including the first teen-age support group of its kind in the county, a school-based education and prevention program that reached 5,200 teen-agers last year, a program for lesbians who are abused by their partners, a toll-free 24-hour 7-day-a-week hot line at (800) 298-7233, a Life Skills Center -- where battered women can get training in life-management skills -- and a Legal Center.  Another of its programs, Operation Safestop, combines the hot line with cooperation from retail stores to give a victim a confidential place to make the call for help.</p>
        <p>''It's a slow revolution, but a revolution,'' said Clarice Pollock, one of the founders.</p>
        <p>Another founder, Jennifer Lefrieri Ries, said, ''But we still need to battle so badly for women's rights.''</p>
        <p>According to statistics compiled by My Sisters' Place from Federal and state sources, battering is the single major cause of injury to women, more frequent than auto accidents, muggings and rapes combined. Almost four million women in the United States are beaten in their homes each year by their husbands,  former husbands or male lovers, one every nine seconds, according to the shelter's compilation. More than 42 percent of all women killed in the United States are killed by a male partner who had professed love, most often when she left or after she left, according to the figures. The Westchester County District Attorney's office said that battering results in one murder a month in the county.</p>
        <p>In an interview after her speech here, Ms. Steinem observed that eliminating domestic violence requires a shift in attitude and must come from everywhere, including men. ''The impulse on the part of men to sustain our male-dominant society is tremendous,'' she said. ''There's the attitude that if he is not dominating he won't feel like a real man. It's like a drug -- getting a fix of dominance. But one must be taught to dominate.</p>
        <p>''Someone has to say to abusive men: 'You've been lied to. It's not true that men are more aggressive than women. Just go cold turkey and stop.' '' Domestic abuse to women should not be taken less seriously than abuse to men who are prisoners of war, she added.</p>
        <p>In the White Plains office of My Sisters' Place recently, Ms. Watson also said that solutions to problems of domestic violence must come from men as well as women.</p>
        <p>''We need to get men to join in battle,'' she said. ''Domestic violence is not just about hitting. It's about a belief men have inherited, a God-given right to rule. It's about emotional abuse, financial control and minimization.</p>
        <p>''Men have to challenge other men and challenge themselves. This is not about bashing men or about bad men but about bad beliefs. Domestic violence is a societal, political problem, not an illness or defect on the part of either the man or the woman. Power and control over women is a belief like racism or anti-Semitism.''</p>
        <p>Abuse, which damages the spirit and psyche, is much harder to repair than bruises, Thea DuBow, assistant executive director at My Sisters' Place, said in an interview in the shelter's offices. Women of all races and from all social and economic classes seek help, she added. ''Included are wives of doctors, lawyers, business owners, who all represent the affluent Westchester community,'' she said. ''The many different women we see have internalized the messages of the abuser. We help them identify that it's his voice, not hers. We must stop asking, 'Why doesn't she just leave?' and start asking, 'Why is he allowed to terrorize her?' ''</p>
        <p>In her speech, Ms. Steinem proposed one solution when she said, ''I look forward to a time when there is a My Brothers' Place for violent men so that the women and children don't have to leave their homes.''</p>
        <p>Besides the hot line at My Sisters' Place, another number to call for help is 969-5800.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
