<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rates on Treasury Bills Tumble</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="210410"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <series series.name="CREDIT MARKETS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">GOVERNMENT BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RATES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">TREASURY, DEPARTMENT OF THE</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">MAIDENBERG, H J</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881230T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0D9113CF933A05751C1A96E948260" item-length="725" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rates on Treasury Bills Tumble</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By H. J. MAIDENBERG</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MAIDENBERG, H J</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: Treasury bill discount rates plunged yesterday as the traditional year-end demand for the 90- and 180-day bills reached near feverish levels.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: Treasury bill discount rates plunged yesterday as the traditional year-end demand for the 90- and 180-day bills reached near feverish levels.</p>
        <p>Treasury bill discount rates plunged yesterday as the traditional year-end demand for the 90- and 180-day bills reached near feverish levels.</p>
        <p>The 90- and 180-day issues are especially in demand at the end of the year, when many corporate and investment portfolio managers engage in ''window dressing'' to adorn both their quarterly and annual statements with large amounts of cash.</p>
        <p>Prices of the Treasury notes and bonds were narrowly mixed in light trading. While most Government securities dealers will staff their offices all day today, those market participants who have not closed their books for 1988 will be clearing paperwork before the long holiday weekend.</p>
        <p>''We will probably see some last minute window dressing on Friday and little else,'' said one bemused dealer, who added: ''It is also a common practice among fund managers with black ink on their books, to try to impress clients further by showing large cash positions as well at yearend. They do this even though most of their clients are very sophisticated today and see right through the window dressing.''</p>
        <p>But window dressing moves large amounts of Treasury bills off dealers' shelves, even if many of the buyers turn into sellers immediately after New Year's Day, he added.</p>
        <p>Yesterday the buyers caused bill rates to tumble, despite a late recovery. For the day, the discount rate on 90-day Treasury bills were down 10 basis points, at 8.13 percent, with the six-month issue off 11 basis points, to 8.23 percent. The one-year bills dipped a basis point, to 8.40 percent.</p>
        <p>Banks and other financial institutions were also engaged in their often frenetic pursuit of reserves to dress their quarterly and year-end accounts. This caused the Federal funds rate to jump a quarter-point, to 9 3/4 percent, despite another injection of reserves into the banking system by the Federal Reserve. The Federal funds rate is what banks charge each other for temporary loans and is thus considered the basic cost of credit.</p>
        <p>Despite the generally tight credit situation that normally prevails at this time of year, the Treasury found aggressive bidders at its auction of $7.25 billion of 9 1/8 percent four-year notes. The notes were sold at an average yield of 9.22 percent, a bit lower than the market had expected. It was the highest average yield since Oct. 6, 1987, when it was 9.24 percent.</p>
        <p>Still, the Treasury paid far more than it did at the last quarterly auction of this maturity, Sept. 28, when the average yield was 8.76 percent.</p>
        <p>The notes were accorded a good reception, despite the thinness of the market, Donald H. Straszheim, chief economist at Merrill Lynch Capital Markets, pointed out. ''Many investors think note and bond yields in general will be less attractive in 1989,'' he explained. ''So do we.''</p>
        <p>For one, Mr. Straszheim believes the economy will finally slow in the second half of 1989, which would ease fears of inflation.</p>
        <p>''Furthermore, the fixed-income market doesn't see an imminent rise in the Fed's discount rate,'' he continued, ''because recent economic statistics have been contradictory. The Fed acts only when it has clear indicators and when its decisions can command a strong majority vote of its policy makers. We haven't seen either development materializing in the next few months.''</p>
        <p>There was also good demand for the two-year 9 1/8 percent notes that the Treasury auctioned this past Wednesday. The 9 1/8 percent notes of 1990 were offered late in the session at 99 31/32, for a yield of 9.14 percent. The average yield produced by the auction was 9.23 percent.</p>
        <p>At the longer end of the Treasury market, the long notes, the 8 7/8 percent issue of 1998, rose 5/32, to 98 6/32, to yield 9.15 percent, while the bellwether long bond, the 9 percent issue of 2018, rose 1/32, to 100.00, but the yield remained unchanged at 9.00 percent.</p>
        <p>Following are the results of the Treasury's auction of four-year notes:  (000 omitted in dollar figures)</p>
        <p>Average Price</p>
        <p>99.689</p>
        <p>Average Yield</p>
        <p>9.22%</p>
        <p>Low Price</p>
        <p>99.689</p>
        <p>High Yield</p>
        <p>9.22%</p>
        <p>High Price</p>
        <p>99.787</p>
        <p>Low Yield</p>
        <p>9.19%</p>
        <p>Accepted at low price</p>
        <p>62%</p>
        <p>Total applied for</p>
        <p>$23,026,491</p>
        <p>Accepted</p>
        <p>$7,257,529</p>
        <p>N.Y. applied for</p>
        <p>$20,087,311</p>
        <p>N.Y. accepted</p>
        <p>$6,235,460</p>
        <p>Noncompetitive</p>
        <p>$1,042,000</p>
        <p>Interest set at</p>
        <p>9 1/8%</p>
        <p>The four-year notes mature Dec. 31, 1992.</p>
        <p>CREDIT MARKETS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
