<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>LIVING HERE | High-Rise Condominiums; Above the Action</title>
    <meta content="10live" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Escapes" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1738579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Havens</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Columns/Living Here</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE0DD153EF933A25751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="861" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>LIVING HERE | High-Rise Condominiums; Above the Action</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">As told to Bethany Lyttle</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHO -- Edward Turrentine, 60, owner of an interior design firm, shown with his wife, Patty Turrentine, 60, a film locations manager  WHERE -- Las Vegas  WHAT -- 2-bedroom condominium</p>
        <p>Our daughter Gwyneth is always pushing us toward great things. She sells properties in the Las Vegas area and she convinced us to purchase this unit. We purchased the one next door, too, for guests. At the time, we were downsizing since we were entering the empty nest phase. We'd just sold our very large house in Pasadena and purchased a smaller one, and we were interested in spending time in more than one place.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHO -- Edward Turrentine, 60, owner of an interior design firm, shown with his wife, Patty Turrentine, 60, a film locations manager  WHERE -- Las Vegas  WHAT -- 2-bedroom condominium</p>
        <p>Our daughter Gwyneth is always pushing us toward great things. She sells properties in the Las Vegas area and she convinced us to purchase this unit. We purchased the one next door, too, for guests. At the time, we were downsizing since we were entering the empty nest phase. We'd just sold our very large house in Pasadena and purchased a smaller one, and we were interested in spending time in more than one place.</p>
        <p>At first we were skeptical about high-rise living. I had designed apartments, but we'd never lived in one. The tower was just being built and we had to wear hard hats to look around. But I used my design skills to transform the concrete space. We put in coffered ceilings and added columns and stone floors. We moved walls to get rid of the dining room and open up more space.</p>
        <p>The great thing about high-rise living is there's no yard to care for and there's wonderful security. We just come and go as we please. There's a concierge, a gym and pool, and access to the Sterling Club. Charlie Palmer is the chef, and when we have a dinner party, the food can be prepared then delivered directly to our door.</p>
        <p>We love our two wraparound balconies, and we have views of the monorail, the strip and Red Rock mountain. It's beautiful at night. And it's exciting to be right at the center of everything, too. It's like being in New York. You walk out the front door and suddenly you're where everything is happening.</p>
        <p>As told to Bethany Lyttle</p>
        <p>Information on properties was supplied by the listing companies.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- San Diego  WHAT -- 2-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $1,825,000</p>
        <p>This 1,945-square-foot unit is on the 26th floor of the Grande at Santa Fe, a tower in the Columbia District with views of the harbor and cruise ships in port. It has an electric fireplace, floor-to-ceiling windows, cherry wood floors, a den and two bathrooms. The kitchen has a wine cooler and granite countertops. There are two underground parking spaces. The building has concierge service, a pool and spa, wet and dry saunas and a gym. Agent: Raye Scott, Scott-Finn and Associates, Prudential California Realty, 858-229-5424; www.scottfinnhomes.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Fort Pierce, Fla.  WHAT -- 3-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $1,485,000</p>
        <p>This 2,250-square-foot penthouse unit is in the 12-story Atrium II tower on North Hutchingson Island. It has a wraparound balcony, a roof terrace with a hot tub, river and ocean views, granite counters, 10-foot ceilings and two and a half bathrooms. The building has a pool, a sauna, a fitness center and a boardwalk to the ocean. Agent: Lois Sferra, Dale Sorensen Real Estate, 772-231-4712; www.sorensenrealestate.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Chicago  WHAT -- 3-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $989,900</p>
        <p>On the 31st floor of the Fordham, this unit has city views and a limited lake view. It has mahogany floors, a wraparound window, a recessed balcony, granite counters, nine-foot ceilings, crown moldings and three bathrooms. The building has 24-hour doormen, a fitness center, a screening room, a wine cellar, a humidor and a party room. Parking is available. The building is near the restaurants and clubs of the Rush Street area. Agent: Chezi Rafaeli, Coldwell Banker Gold Coast, 312-654-4242; www.coldwellbankeronline.com/chezirafaeli.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Minneapolis, Minn.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $849,000</p>
        <p>This 3,221-square-foot loft-style penthouse is in the new eight-story Rock Island Lofts. It has 20-foot ceilings, an open floor plan, a media room, floor-to-ceiling arched windows, maple floors and cabinets, granite counters, a laundry room, three bathrooms and a private deck. The building has 63 units, a fitness center and a community room. It is a block from the Mississippi River. There is parking in a heated underground garage. Agent: Fran Davis, Coldwell Banker Burnet Minneapolis Lakes, 612-920-5605; www.cbburnet.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Las Vegas  WHAT -- 1-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $1.94 million</p>
        <p>This 2,805-square-foot unit, in one of four towers at Turnberry Place, originally had three bedrooms but has been remodeled with a single master suite instead. It has a five-seat home theater, solid walnut doors, rosewood flooring, beamed ceilings, a fireplace and two bathrooms with heated floors. It is on the 20th floor with views of the Las Vegas Strip. The complex has a fitness center, a nightclub, a restaurant, tennis courts and limousine and concierge services. Agent: Fred Trujillo, Turnberry West Realty, 702-784-4601; www.turnberryplace.com.</p>
        <p>WHERE -- Seattle, Wash.  WHAT -- 2-bedroom condominium  HOW MUCH -- $945,000</p>
        <p>This newly completed 1,239-square-foot corner penthouse is in the 13-story Avenue One Condominiums in the Belltown area. It has floor-to-ceiling windows with views of Mount Rainier, the Olympic Mountains, downtown and Elliott Bay. There are a gas fireplace, two balconies, a roof deck, granite counters, slate and carpeted floors and two bathrooms, one with a soaking tub. The master bedroom overlooks Puget Sound. Two parking spaces are included. Agent: Larry Kramer, John. L. Scott Real Estate, 206-269-2253; www.larrykramer.com.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
