<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>In the Cendant Trial, Ignorance Was an Excuse</title>
    <meta content="10forbes" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/10/business/10forbes.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1738601"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <series series.name="News Analysis"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">News Analysis</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Cendant Corporation</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Forbes, Walter A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE5DC153EF933A25751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="1230" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>In the Cendant Trial, Ignorance Was an Excuse</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In the Cendant Trial, Ignorance Was an Excuse</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLOYD NORRIS</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walter A. Forbes was paid more than $100 million as chairman and chief executive of the CUC Corporation. To hear him tell it, he did not do very much to earn the money.</p>
        <p>Operations of the company, he testified at a trial where he faced charges of masterminding a fraud that cost investors billions, were left to others.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Walter A. Forbes testified that operations of the company were left to others, a defense that worked at his first trial and has worked again</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Walter A. Forbes was paid more than $100 million as chairman and chief executive of the CUC Corporation. To hear him tell it, he did not do very much to earn the money.</p>
        <p>Operations of the company, he testified at a trial where he faced charges of masterminding a fraud that cost investors billions, were left to others.</p>
        <p>He admitted signing quarterly and annual financial statements that turned out to be fraudulent, but said he neither prepared nor read them.</p>
        <p>''We were a public company with thousands of employees, divisions all over the country and all over the world,'' he testified. ''I don't think they would have expected me to be reading 10-Q's.''</p>
        <p>It was a defense that worked at his first trial, when a jury convicted CUC's No. 2 official but was unable to reach a verdict on Mr. Forbes. And it has worked again. Yesterday, the jury in the second trial was dismissed after it, too, was unable to reach a verdict after 27 days of deliberations. [Page C6.]</p>
        <p>The jury foreman, Ken Premo, said afterward that he did not feel the accounting issues in the trial had been too complex and thought that Mr. Forbes was guilty. But, he added, ''I wouldn't say it was clear cut.''</p>
        <p>If he had been convicted, Mr. Forbes would have faced more than 20 years in prison. A spokesman for Christopher J. Christie, the United States attorney for the New Jersey district, said the government had not yet decided whether it would prosecute Mr. Forbes a third time.</p>
        <p>The fraud was discovered after CUC merged with another company, HFS, to form the Cendant Corporation, with holdings that included Avis car rental and Century 21 real estate. When the fraud was discovered in 1998, it was called the largest accounting fraud in American history -- and investors lost $19 billion when Cendant's stock fell in the wake of the disclosure. But the company subsequently lost the title as Enron and WorldCom collapsed in scandal.</p>
        <p>The fact pattern at Cendant would prove to be similar to the later rush of accounting fraud cases. The chief financial officer first denied anything was wrong, then confessed and agreed to testify against his boss. But orders to falsify books, if they were given, were given orally and documents were scarce.</p>
        <p>In the WorldCom trial, the jury believed the chief financial officer and convicted Bernard J. Ebbers, the former chief executive. At HealthSouth, the jury chose not to believe a series of financial officers and acquitted Richard M. Scrushy, the former chief executive.</p>
        <p>Now, two former Enron chief executives, Kenneth L. Lay and Jeffrey K. Skilling, are on trial in Houston, with Andrew S. Fastow, the former chief financial officer, expected to be a star prosecution witness. The strategy chosen by lawyers for the former Enron bosses is radically different, arguing that there really were no crimes and that the company failed because negative publicity caused a loss of confidence.</p>
        <p>In the Forbes trial, Cosmo Corigliano, the former chief financial officer, testified that the books were cooked for years at Mr. Forbes's direction, and that every quarter he and Mr. Forbes discussed how much money would be taken from inflated reserves and used to increase profits to meet targets. Over the three-year period covered in the indictment, $250 million was thus added to profits.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forbes denied that the conversations took place, and he also said he had never seen the ''cheat sheets'' that Mr. Corigliano said were shown to him each quarter, detailing how much the profits were being inflated.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forbes, who has an M.B.A. degree from Harvard, as well as bachelor's and master's degrees in journalism from Northwestern University, testified he knew little of accounting and never paid any attention to how the profit figures were compiled.</p>
        <p>To some extent, the case came down to a ''he said, he said'' battle between the men. Brandon Sullivan, Mr. Forbes's lawyer, branded Mr. Corigliano a liar and said there had to be at least a reasonable doubt whether he was telling the truth.</p>
        <p>But the prosecution pointed to other inconsistencies in the testimony. Steven Kernkraut, an analyst from Bear Stearns, testified that he had held discussions with Mr. Forbes regarding how merger reserves were set, and why the reserve for one merger was increased months after it was completed.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forbes said that was wrong. ''I never had a conversation with him after the deal was announced'' regarding the reserves, he testified.</p>
        <p>He also denied testimony from Mike Monaco, the HFS chief financial officer, that Mr. Forbes had fought to keep Ernst &amp; Young as the auditor of CUC's books after the merger, even proposing that the company have two auditors.</p>
        <p>Mr. Forbes said he never heard of such an idea, although he acknowledged that he was at a meeting whose minutes said the idea was discussed and rejected. Ernst had failed to spot the fraud, and the prosecution claimed Mr. Forbes wanted to keep the firm because he thought it could continue to be fooled.</p>
        <p>Although the charges at the trial covered just three years, Mr. Corigliano told the court, when he pleaded guilty in 2000, that the fraud had been going on since the early 1980's, when he joined the company from Ernst &amp; Whinney, a predecessor of Ernst &amp; Young.</p>
        <p>An accounting official, who said he followed Mr. Corigliano's orders to cook books, said he had followed similar orders from Mr. Corigliano's predecessor, Stuart Bell, who left the company in 1995. Mr. Bell, who was not charged with any crime, did not testify.</p>
        <p>In describing his own role at CUC, Mr. Forbes said he was a visionary who mapped strategy and guided the company into mergers that enabled it to grow. But even there, he said, he avoided the details.</p>
        <p>''I knew it was a strategic fit,'' he said in discussing one large acquisition, ''but I never actually visited the company or met the principals.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Forbes said he was ''stunned and shocked'' when he first heard there were problems with the books. But he soon agreed to step down as chairman in return for a $47 million severance package that he promised to return to the company if he were convicted of a crime.</p>
        <p>He quickly transferred many of his assets to his wife, but said he did not remember a warning from his lawyer that such an action would be viewed by prosecutors as an admission of guilt. At his first trial, he said the lawyer advised him there was nothing wrong with the transfer. At the second trial, the lawyer denied telling him that.</p>
        <p>Those contradictions did not bother all the jurors, at least not enough to produce a conviction. Unless the government is willing to force a third trial, Mr. Forbes will have prevailed with his defense of not having any idea what was happening at the company he ran, just as Mr. Scrushy did.</p>
        <p>News Analysis</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
