<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="19FSUM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1294554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B00EFD81F3AF93AA25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1208" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Suicide Bomber Kills 5; Israeli Jets Retaliate  A Palestinian suicide bomber killed at least 5 Israelis and wounded more than 100 at a bustling shopping mall in the coastal town of Netanya. Israel retaliated by sending warplanes to strike targets in the West Bank and Gaza Strip for the first time since the 1967 war, killing at least nine Palestinians. A sixth Israeli, an army officer, was killed in the West Bank. It was the deadliest day of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict this year.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>INTERNATIONAL</p>
        <p>A3-7</p>
        <p>Suicide Bomber Kills 5; Israeli Jets Retaliate  A Palestinian suicide bomber killed at least 5 Israelis and wounded more than 100 at a bustling shopping mall in the coastal town of Netanya. Israel retaliated by sending warplanes to strike targets in the West Bank and Gaza Strip for the first time since the 1967 war, killing at least nine Palestinians. A sixth Israeli, an army officer, was killed in the West Bank. It was the deadliest day of the Israeli-Palestinian conflict this year.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Secretary of State Colin L. Powell appealed for ''an unconditional cessation of violence,'' but said the time was still not ripe for the United States to sponsor peace negotiations.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Brazil Orders Energy Cuts  The government ordered businesses and consumers to cut electricity consumption by 20 percent or prepare for California-style blackouts.</p>
        <p>A4</p>
        <p>Colombia Car Bomb Kills Eight  A feud between right-wing paramilitary forces and criminal gangs was blamed for a car bomb that exploded in a Medellin park on Thursday, killing 8 people and injuring 137.</p>
        <p>A5</p>
        <p>Corruption Trial Accusations  Loïk Le Floch-Prigent, a former head of France's state-owned oil company, who is being tried on corruption charges, told two newspapers that paying millions of dollars a year in ''secret commissions'' was a routine part of his job and that it had the approval of the Elysée Palace.</p>
        <p>A6</p>
        <p>Polish Trial Delayed  The trial of the former military ruler Gen. Wojciech Jaruzelski on charges that he ordered the shooting of protesters in 1970 was delayed a month by his lawyers' sudden resignation.</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>World Briefing</p>
        <p>A7</p>
        <p>SCIENCE/HEALTH</p>
        <p>Chicken Virus in Hong Kong  Officials ordered the slaughter of 1.2 million chickens and other poultry to halt the spread of a flu virus, as chickens continued to die by the hundreds and public alarm mounted, even though the virus was not thought to threaten humans.</p>
        <p>A3</p>
        <p>NATIONAL</p>
        <p>A8-11 ;A14</p>
        <p>U.S. Weighing Response To Refinery Pollution  At least half the country's 152 oil refineries may be violating air-pollution laws, officials say, but with the refineries operating near their capacities, the Bush administration is debating how hard to crack down. A report by Vice President Dick Cheney's energy task force directs the E.P.A. and the Justice Department to review their enforcement of pollution laws in light of the potential for discouraging refinery expansion.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Political Fallout Over Energy  Gov. Gray Davis of California faulted President Bush for not ordering caps on wholesale power prices, assailed previous governors for not having had more power plants built, accused power companies of gouging the state, and announced the hiring of two former aides to Al Gore. An opinion poll showed Mr. Davis's approval rating falling below 50 percent.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Effort to Save Nomination  White House officials, worried by an impasse over the nomination of Theodore B. Olson for solicitor general, pressed Senate Republicans to offer concessions to Democrats, like providing them with some of the documents they had requested.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Inquiry Into Transition Pranks  A manager at the G.A.O., an investigative arm of Congress, said accounts of vandalism by departing Clinton aides were overblown.</p>
        <p>A11</p>
        <p>Mulling a Run for Governor  Former Attorney General Janet Reno, 62, said she was seriously considering running for governor of Florida next year, which could pit her against Gov. Jeb Bush.</p>
        <p>A9</p>
        <p>Ruling on Prison Crowding  An Alabama judge gave the state prison system a month to find room for nearly 2,000 inmates now crowded into county jails across the state.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>Bomb Plotter's Suspicions  A lawyer for Terry L. Nichols, Timothy J. McVeigh's conspirator in the Oklahoma City bombing, told the Supreme Court that he suspected the F.B.I. was still holding back investigative material.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>NEW YORK/REGION</p>
        <p>B1-6</p>
        <p>Rise in Dealer Violence Undercuts Marijuana Image  The New York City police, who spent years battling a crack scourge that sent the murder rate soaring, say they now see increasing violence among dealers of marijuana, a drug that they say no longer fits its laid-back image. The reasons behind the transformation of the marijuana trade include higher prices that ever more potent strains fetch and lesser penalties for dealing marijuana than for harder drugs, like cocaine.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Party Finances Examined  Big donors to the Bergen County Democratic Party in 1996 say their contributions were solicited by representatives of Robert G. Torricelli, then a Democratic congressman representing the county, as well as a Senate candidate. The party spent thousands from that money to pay salaries and other expenses for Mr. Torricelli's successful campaign -- an arrangement that, experts say, may have violated federal election law.</p>
        <p>A1</p>
        <p>Conviction in Student's Killing  David Jamison, 28, was convicted of second-degree murder in the death of Amy Watkins, a 26-year-old graduate student fatally stabbed in a botched street robbery in Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>B1</p>
        <p>EDUCATION</p>
        <p>Finding Teachers Overseas  School systems struggling with a severe teacher shortage are increasingly looking in other countries for candidates to fill teacher vacancies.</p>
        <p>A8</p>
        <p>OBITUARIES</p>
        <p>B7</p>
        <p>SPORTS</p>
        <p>D1-8</p>
        <p>The Raptors Hang On  Toronto beat the Philadelphia 76ers, 101-89, to tie their N.B.A. Eastern playoff series at 3-3.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>The Second Jewel in the Crown  Monarchos, the Kentucky Derby winner, continues his pursuit of the Triple Crown today as the favorite in a field of 11 in the 126th running of the Preakness Stakes.</p>
        <p>D1</p>
        <p>BUSINESS DAY</p>
        <p>C1-14</p>
        <p>Strong Week for the Markets  The Dow rose 53.16 points, to 11,301.74, up 4.4 percent for the week. The Nasdaq gained 5.20 points, to 2,198.88, up 4.3 percent for the week. The S.&amp; P. 500 edged ahead 3.47 points, to 1,291.96, up 3.7 percent for the week. Bond prices were mixed, but gold surged $13.80 an ounce, or 5 percent, to $287.80, an 11-month high.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Big Tax Gains Seen for Top 1%  The tax plans now moving through Congress offer breaks for the wealthiest Americans that gain value over time, while most of the breaks for others lose value, according to supporters and critics of the plans.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Phone Merger Reconsidered  Alcatel and Lucent Technologies, responding to investor concerns, were re-evaluating terms of Alcatel's plan for a takeover of Lucent, with Alcatel likely to drop its offer to $34 billion from $40 billion, executives said.</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>Tire Maker Hits Back at Ford  Bridgestone/Firestone lashed out at Ford for concluding that there are problems with Firestone tires not covered by the recall last August.</p>
        <p>C2</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>C1</p>
        <p>World Business</p>
        <p>W1</p>
        <p>ARTS &amp; IDEAS</p>
        <p>B9-16</p>
        <p>EDITORIAL</p>
        <p>A12-13</p>
        <p>Editorials: A gathering storm in the Mideast; Albany's spring freeze; Verlyn Klinkenborg on the snow's legacy.  Columns: Anthony Lewis.</p>
        <p>Bridge</p>
        <p>B14  TV Listings</p>
        <p>B16  Crossword</p>
        <p>B14  Weather</p>
        <p>A14  Public Lives</p>
        <p>A8</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
