<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Climb; Gold Prices Set 11-Month High</title>
    <meta content="19STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/05/19/business/19STOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1294550"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Industrial Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Gold</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Gold</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Futures and Options Trading</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Government Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">United States</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Lehman Brothers Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Reuters Group Plc</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Credit Suisse First Boston (USA) Incorporated</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Reuters</org>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mercantile Exchange</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Tocqueville</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010519T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE4D81F3AF93AA25756C0A9679C8B63" item-length="917" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Climb; Gold Prices Set 11-Month High</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JONATHAN FUERBRINGER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Fuerbringer, Jonathan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stocks finish positive week by moving slightly higher; Dow Jones Industrial Average's 11,301.74 close is up 53.16, or 0.5 percent; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index's 3.47 point, or 0.3 percent, rise takes it to 1,291.96; Nasdaq composite's close at 2,198.88 is 5.20 points, or 0.2 percent, higher; bond prices are mixed; Treasury's 10-year note's yield slips to 5.40 percent, from 5.41 percent May 17; its price rises 2/32, to 97; gold prices set 11-month high; table of key rates; charts (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks moved slightly higher yesterday, finishing a positive week highlighted by a big rally on Wednesday, the day after the Federal Reserve made its fifth half-point rate cut of the year. And a new public offering of an electronic stock market, Instinet, went well.</p>
        <p>In commodity markets, the price of gold for June delivery surged $13.80 an ounce, or 5 percent, to an 11-month high of $287.80. Some analysts say that the move could signal a change in the fortunes for gold, which has been struggling just to stay above 20-year lows.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks moved slightly higher yesterday, finishing a positive week highlighted by a big rally on Wednesday, the day after the Federal Reserve made its fifth half-point rate cut of the year. And a new public offering of an electronic stock market, Instinet, went well.</p>
        <p>In commodity markets, the price of gold for June delivery surged $13.80 an ounce, or 5 percent, to an 11-month high of $287.80. Some analysts say that the move could signal a change in the fortunes for gold, which has been struggling just to stay above 20-year lows.</p>
        <p>The Dow Jones industrial average, which climbed above 11,000 for the first time since September on Wednesday, closed up 53.16 points, or 0.5 percent higher at 11,301.74. It was up 4.4 percent for the week. The Nasdaq composite index, which rose 4.3 percent for the week, ended the day 5.20 points, or 0.2 percent, higher at 2,198.88. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index rose 3.47 points, or 0.3 percent, to 1,291.96.</p>
        <p>In the bond market, prices were mixed. The yield on the Treasury's 10-year note slipped to 5.40 percent, from 5.41 percent on Thursday, as the price, which moves in the opposite direction, rose 2/32, to 97.</p>
        <p>The yield on the federal funds futures contract for June, which is a barometer of rate cut expectations, was unchanged but still indicates that some investors are betting on a quarter-point reduction when Fed policy makers meet in June.</p>
        <p>Investors seem confident, based on the performance of both stocks and bonds, that the Fed's rate cuts will lead to an economic recovery in the the second half of the year.</p>
        <p>Jeffrey M. Applegate, the chief United States strategist at Lehman Brothers, said that based on the history of Fed interest rate cuts back to the early 1970's, the stock market has reached a bottom, on average, about three months after the first rate cut. The current lows for the three main indexes were hit in March and April. After a fifth rate cut, he said, the main market indexes have not dropped below that bottom.</p>
        <p>But the recovery of the technology sector, whose plunge led the stock market into bear territory, still lags that of many old-economy stocks.</p>
        <p>While the Dow is over 11,000 again, the Nasdaq composite index, despite this week's rally, is still 4.1 percent below where it was before the first Fed rate cut on Jan. 3.</p>
        <p>This split is also reflected in recent data of flows into equity mutual funds. According to AMG Data Services, investors put $825 million of new money into stock funds in the week ended Wednesday. But most of it went into growth and value funds. There were outflows from technology and Internet funds. In April, when nearly $15 billion moved into domestic equity funds, after a $13.2 billion decline in February and March, only $500 million went into technology funds.</p>
        <p>In its first day of trading, Instinet, which is controlled by Reuters Group P.L.C., rose $3.15, or 22 percent, to $17.65 from its initial offering price of $14.50. The price got as high as $19.50. There were 32 million shares sold in the offering led by Credit Suisse First Boston and Deutsche Banc Alex. Brown.</p>
        <p>The Instinet offering came as the market for initial public offerings has slowed to a crawl. In the late 1990's and early in 2000, new dot-coms came to market without any sign of earnings and doubled or tripled in price on the first day. Last year, there were 22 new offerings that quadrupled their price on the first day of trading.</p>
        <p>Instinet, which offers access to 40 securities markets, had earnings last year of $148 million, which accounted for about 25 percent of Reuters' profits.</p>
        <p>The price of gold shot higher, analysts said, after it breached $275 an ounce on the June futures contract traded on the New York Mercantile Exchange. They said this was an important technical level, which set off purchase programs for many money managers. And as these managers acted the price shot higher.</p>
        <p>John Hathaway, the senior portfolio manager at Tocqueville Asset Management, which runs a gold fund, acknowledged that the move came on a Friday when trading was thin, which would exaggerate the jump. But he still says that it is significant.</p>
        <p>''Instead of being in a downtrend, I think we are in an uptrend now,'' he said. One of his reasons for thinking this, he said, is that it appears that a lot of the investors who shorted gold in the past, adding a lot of downward pressure on the price, are out of the market. When shorting, an investor sells borrowed gold in hopes that the price will fall and he can buy it back at a lower price and, thus, profit.</p>
        <p>But gold has flirted with breakouts from the doldrums before, only to fall again. It reached $294.30 last June before falling to $256.60 in April.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
