<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Stocks Fall After Greenspan's Comments Dash Hopes for Rate Cut</title>
    <meta content="Y01STOX" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/03/01/business/01STOX.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1274513"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="THE MARKETS: STOCKS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dow Jones Industrial Average</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Standard &amp; Poor's 500-Stock Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Berenson, Alex</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Greenspan, Alan (Chmn)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">interest_rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">united_states_economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Credit</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nasdaq Composite Index</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Monetta</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Nasdaq</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Dow Jones</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Morgan Stanley Dean Witter &amp; Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">act</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Treasury</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Greenspan, Alan</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=950DE7D81E38F932A35750C0A9679C8B63" item-length="791" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Stocks Fall After Greenspan's Comments Dash Hopes for Rate Cut</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALEX BERENSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Berenson, Alex</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Stocks slump again after Federal Reserve chairman, Alan Greenspan, dashes investors' hope for immediate cut in short-term interest rates; Nasdaq composite index drops 55.99 points, or 2.5 percent, to 2,151.83; Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index falls 18 points, or 1.4 percent, to 1,239.94, and Dow Jones industrial average declines 141.60 points, or 1.3 percent, to 10,495.28; graph; chart; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Stocks slumped again yesterday after Alan Greenspan held out little hope for an immediate cut in short-term interest rates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan, the chairman of the Federal Reserve, said in testimony to Congress that the economy had been stronger in January and February than it was at the end of 2000. With that outlook, the Fed is unlikely to cut rates again before its regularly scheduled meeting on March 20, analysts said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Stocks slumped again yesterday after Alan Greenspan held out little hope for an immediate cut in short-term interest rates.</p>
        <p>Mr. Greenspan, the chairman of the Federal Reserve, said in testimony to Congress that the economy had been stronger in January and February than it was at the end of 2000. With that outlook, the Fed is unlikely to cut rates again before its regularly scheduled meeting on March 20, analysts said.</p>
        <p>Wall Street, which has watched many companies report lower-than-expected earnings and announce layoffs since last fall, would have preferred an immediate rate cut to help shore up the economy and the stock market. Lower interest rates are usually considered good for stocks because they lower the cost of borrowing and make bonds a less attractive alternative investment.</p>
        <p>With prospects for a quick cut fading, investors sold stocks, hitting technology and financial companies especially hard.</p>
        <p>After opening higher, the Nasdaq composite index finished the day down 55.99 points, or 2.5 percent, to 2,151.83. The Standard &amp; Poor's 500-stock index fell 18 points, or 1.4 percent, to 1,239.94, and the Dow Jones industrial average sank 141.60 points, or 1.3 percent, to 10,495.28.</p>
        <p>The day's biggest losers included Oracle, which fell $2.69, to $19, and Morgan Stanley Dean Witter, which sank $4.53, to $65.13.</p>
        <p>The overall declines ended a dismal February. For the month, the S.&amp; P. 500 fell more than 9 percent, while the Nasdaq plunged 22 percent, its third-biggest monthly decline ever. Since reaching its record high last March, the Nasdaq has dropped 57 percent. The S.&amp; P. 500 is now down 19 percent from its March high, just short of the 20 percent drop that indicates a bear market.</p>
        <p>After rallying briefly in January, when the Fed cut rates twice, stocks have sagged again on reports of sharply declining consumer confidence and job cuts. The bad news continued yesterday, as Gateway, the  maker of personal computers, said that profits for its first-quarter would fall short of expectations and that it might close some stores.</p>
        <p>''There was quite a bit of disappointment among investors who expected Fed chairman Greenspan to just wave his wand and make all the pain go away,'' said Ed Yardeni, chief investment strategist of Deutsche Banc Alex. Brown. ''His statements did not support the view that we should expect a rate cut before the March 20 meeting.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Yardeni said he hoped Mr. Greenspan would act again before the Fed's regular meeting. ''In an environment where there is a potential for forces to spiral to the downside, having the Fed act more quickly is warranted,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Robert Bacarella, manager of the $170 million Monetta mutual fund, said he thought investors had overestimated Mr. Greenspan's ability to turn the economy quickly. ''We don't know where the bottom is,'' he said. ''I think the market is trying to suggest to us the slowdown might be a lot worse than what the Fed thinks.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bacarella said he did not particularly care whether the Fed cut interest rates immediately or in three weeks. He says many technology stocks have fallen to attractive prices, but he does not want to invest aggressively until he sees the economy growing again, he said.</p>
        <p>''It takes time for these things to filter through,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Charles Pradilla, chief investment strategist at SG Cowen, said investors should not expect a quick turn for earnings. ''Everybody's gotten it wrong, including Greenspan,'' Mr. Pradilla said. ''Nobody expected sentiment and the economy to decelerate so rapidly, and companies to take such very, very quick action.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Pradilla said investors had some reasons for hope. Long-term interest rates have fallen sharply over the last year, with the yield on the 10-year Treasury note falling to 4.9 percent from 6.6 percent in January 2000, he said. That could provide a foundation for higher stock prices if companies can start their earnings rising again, he said.</p>
        <p>But investors will have to be patient, he said. ''I don't think Nasdaq can get out of its own way until the summer,'' he added.</p>
        <p>THE MARKETS: STOCKS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
