<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Airports, Seaports and Mideast Peace</title>
    <meta content="02WED2" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="919868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Israel</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Gaza</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">West Bank</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Netanyahu, Benjamin (Prime Min)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Arafat, Yasir</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Palestinian Authority</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/West Bank</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Israel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel Restrictions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Airports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Palestinians</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E7D61F3AF931A35757C0A961958260" item-length="467" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Airports, Seaports and Mideast Peace</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Editorial contends that rebuilding some mutual confidence between Israeli Prime Min Benjamin Netanyahu and Palestinian leader Yasir Arafat is essential condition for resuming progress toward peace in Middle East; maintains that for Israelis, confidence hinges mainly on curbing terrorism; asserts that for Palestinians, restoring confidence requires translating Oslo agreement's promises of autonomy into everday reality and enhancing economic opportunities to build better life; urges Israel to allow opening of Palestinian airport and seaport in Gaza, and to establish transportation corridors to let Palestinians travel freely though Israeli territory between Gaza and West Bank (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rebuilding some mutual confidence between Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, is an essential condition for resuming progress toward peace in the Middle East. Their relationship has been battered by Israeli construction in East Jerusalem, disputes over Israeli withdrawals in the West Bank and, most seriously, Mr. Arafat's ambiguous attitude toward Hamas suicide bomb attacks.</p>
        <p>But rescuing hopes of a lasting peace from the drift toward violence requires rebuilding broad public confidence on both sides as well. For Israelis, confidence hinges mainly on curbing terrorism. Two explosions near Jewish settlements in Gaza  yesterday may have been abortive suicide bombing attacks. Israel is entitled to demand a concerted effort by Mr. Arafat to quell terrorism.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rebuilding some mutual confidence between Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu of Israel and the Palestinian leader, Yasir Arafat, is an essential condition for resuming progress toward peace in the Middle East. Their relationship has been battered by Israeli construction in East Jerusalem, disputes over Israeli withdrawals in the West Bank and, most seriously, Mr. Arafat's ambiguous attitude toward Hamas suicide bomb attacks.</p>
        <p>But rescuing hopes of a lasting peace from the drift toward violence requires rebuilding broad public confidence on both sides as well. For Israelis, confidence hinges mainly on curbing terrorism. Two explosions near Jewish settlements in Gaza  yesterday may have been abortive suicide bombing attacks. Israel is entitled to demand a concerted effort by Mr. Arafat to quell terrorism.</p>
        <p>For Palestinians, restoring confidence in the peace effort requires translating the Oslo agreement's promises of autonomy into everyday reality and enhancing economic opportunities to build a better life. Before the latest breakdown, negotiations had begun on several measures that could make the benefits of self-rule more tangible to ordinary Palestinians. These include allowing the opening of a Palestinian airport and seaport in Gaza, and establishing transportation corridors to let Palestinians travel freely through Israeli territory between Gaza and the West Bank. There has also been talk of relaxing other economically punishing restrictions on Palestinian travel.</p>
        <p>Israel's main concern in all these cases is a reasonable one -- protecting its security against terrorists or smuggled weapons. Both sides agree that Israel will continue to control the airspace over Gaza. Negotiations have focused on ground-security issues at terminals and along land corridors.</p>
        <p>These matters are similar to the border-crossing questions that were among the most difficult in the Oslo negotiations. The solution reached then allowed Israeli security forces full scrutiny of travelers and their belongings. But the Israelis agreed to operate discreetly, so that many Palestinian travelers would directly encounter only Palestinian security officers.</p>
        <p>Israel insists on applying that same high level of scrutiny to airport, seaport and corridor operations. The Palestinians acknowledge Israeli security needs but would like to see them met with a smaller and less visible Israeli presence.</p>
        <p>The differences between the two sides are reportedly small. A gesture by Israel now -- for example, a conditional opening of the airport --  could help revive the larger negotiating process. It might also pay subtle security dividends of its own, by addressing the disillusionment and even desperation that has set in among many Palestinians as the Oslo process stalled over the past year.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
