<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>5 Are Killed in Attack on a Coptic Monastery</title>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="674236"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CHRISTIANS AND CHRISTIANITY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COPTIC CHURCHES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">EGYPT</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Christians and Christianity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C06E3DF133DF930A25750C0A962958260" item-length="434" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>5 Are Killed in Attack on a Coptic Monastery</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>CAIRO, March 12</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Gunmen believed to be Islamic militants shot and killed two priests and three other Christians outside a Coptic monastery in southern Egypt Friday night, security officials said today.</p>
        <p>The attack was one of the bloodiest against Christians since Muslim militants shot and killed 13 Christian farmers in the southern village of Manchiet Nasser nearly two years ago.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Gunmen believed to be Islamic militants shot and killed two priests and three other Christians outside a Coptic monastery in southern Egypt Friday night, security officials said today.</p>
        <p>The attack was one of the bloodiest against Christians since Muslim militants shot and killed 13 Christian farmers in the southern village of Manchiet Nasser nearly two years ago.</p>
        <p>It was the first time a monastery had been attacked since Muslim militants stepped up their campaign to topple the Government of President Hosni Mubarak and transform Egypt into a strict Islamic state.</p>
        <p>This morning, suspected militants shot and killed two police officers and a civilian in the southern provincial capital of Asyut. Gunmen also opened fire on a train near El Qusiya, which was heading north from the popular tourist town of Aswan. The Interior Ministry reported no injuries in that attack.</p>
        <p>The assault Friday night was on the Moharrak monastery in Qussiya, a militant stronghold 180 miles south of Cairo. An Interior Ministry statement said "unknown" gunmen opened fire on a group of visitors as they tried to enter the gates of the monastery.</p>
        <p>The visitors were told the monastery was closed to mark the start of the 55-day Coptic fast for lent. Nur al-Qums Binyamin, a priest, tried to talk to the visitors. He and three of the visitors were shot and killed immediately.</p>
        <p>Another priest who was wounded died in the hospital today, and three other people were injured in the shooting, a Coptic spokesman said.</p>
        <p>Witnesses said a "young man" pulled up outside the monastery in a pick-up truck and opened fire.</p>
        <p>Muslim militants have gunned down scores of Coptic Christians, and burned churches and Coptic-owned shops and businesses as part of a strategy aimed at fostering instability in Egypt. The violence has driven hundreds of Coptic Christians from villages in the south. Egypt has about 8 million Coptic Christians out of a population of 58 million.</p>
        <p>"They have killed us in the past," the Coptic official said. "But the attack on the monastery is a deviation from their usual methods. All of us are frightened and worried."</p>
        <p>Political violence has claimed over 320 lives and injured over 700 people in the last two years. The militants, headed by the radical Islamic Group, have also killed Government officials, police, intellectuals and tourists in their drive to seize power.</p>
        <p>The attacks have increased over the last month. Gunmen have opened fire on several trains in attacks that have injured eight foreigners, and the Islamic Group has issued warnings to foreigners and investors to leave Egypt.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
