<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Law Offers Relief to Bar-Weary</title>
    <meta content="18SLA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The City Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="872186"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York State Liquor Authority</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Andrew</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pataki, George E (Gov)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Abate, Catherine M (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gottfried, Richard N (Assemblyman)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/The City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Noise</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bars</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960818T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E4DF1F31F93BA2575BC0A960958260" item-length="535" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Law Offers Relief to Bar-Weary</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANDREW JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Andrew</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Law signed by Gov George Pataki gives NYS Liquor Authority ability to clamp down on disorderly bars and discos; rowdy bar bill, co-sponsored by Sen Catherine M Abate and Assemblyman Richard N Gottfried, makes it easier for authority to revoke liquor license of bar that demonstrates 'sustained and continuing pattern of noise, disturbance, misconduct or disorder' (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In recent years, anger over rowdy bars has often edged out homelessness, car alarms and squeegee men as the hot-button topic that fires up neighborhood activists around the city. As a growing number of nightclubs opened in residential neighborhoods, sleep-deprived New Yorkers have been frustrated by the State Liquor Authority's inability to pull the plug on troublesome establishments whose well-paid lawyers easily thwarted the agency's limited policing abilities.</p>
        <p>But a law signed last week by Gov. George E. Pataki gives the authority new teeth to clamp down on disorderly bars and discos. The so-called ''rowdy bar bill,'' co-sponsored by State Senator Catherine M. Abate and Assemblyman Richard N. Gottfried, makes it easier for the authority to suspend or revoke the liquor license of an establishment that demonstrates ''a sustained and continuing pattern of noise, disturbance, misconduct or disorder.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In recent years, anger over rowdy bars has often edged out homelessness, car alarms and squeegee men as the hot-button topic that fires up neighborhood activists around the city. As a growing number of nightclubs opened in residential neighborhoods, sleep-deprived New Yorkers have been frustrated by the State Liquor Authority's inability to pull the plug on troublesome establishments whose well-paid lawyers easily thwarted the agency's limited policing abilities.</p>
        <p>But a law signed last week by Gov. George E. Pataki gives the authority new teeth to clamp down on disorderly bars and discos. The so-called ''rowdy bar bill,'' co-sponsored by State Senator Catherine M. Abate and Assemblyman Richard N. Gottfried, makes it easier for the authority to suspend or revoke the liquor license of an establishment that demonstrates ''a sustained and continuing pattern of noise, disturbance, misconduct or disorder.''</p>
        <p>The Empire State Restaurant and Tavern Association, a lobbying group that helped kill previous versions of the bill, did not try to stop its passage this time. The association's executive director, Scott Wexler, said that unlike other proposed measures, this one does not hold an owner responsible for patrons who ''leave the bar and vandalize property down the block.''</p>
        <p>''It offers more protection for responsible owners,'' Mr. Wexler said, ''and less protection for irresponsible ones.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Abate agreed, pointing out that the law is intended to crack down on bar owners who flout the law because they know there's little the authority can do to stop them. ''There's no reason for bar owners to panic,'' she said, ''but pernicious clubs should definitely take note.''</p>
        <p>Laura Michaels knows what it is like to have a problem bar as a neighbor. For years, Ms. Michaels led a small-scale war against Club Vertigo, a hip-hop club on West 20th Street whose patrons were involved in several shootings and slashings outside. Ms. Michaels took a four-month leave of absence from her job as a graphic designer to start the Flatiron Alliance, an organization dedicated to fighting lawless bars and nightclubs in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Last April, Club Vertigo was evicted for nonpayment of rent, but Ms. Michaels worries that another noisy disco could take its place. ''With a law like this, maybe we won't have to suffer like we did before,'' she said.  While activists praised the law, they warned that enforcement could be hurt by budget cutbacks that have left the authority with 15 investigators for 11 downstate counties, including the city. ''If the S.L.A. has only one or two inspectors for all of Manhattan, there's not a lot they can do,'' said Tim Gay, co-chairman of Community Board 4's quality-of-life committee. ''The new law many give us another weapon to fight obnoxious clubs, but once again, we're going to be doing all the legwork.''</p>
        <p>ANDREW JACOBS</p>
        <p>NEIGHBORHOOD REPORT: NEW YORK UP CLOSE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
