<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Hail to the Former Chief, Picking Up a Sandwich at the Deli</title>
    <meta content="22CHAP" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/01/22/politics/22CHAP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1264948"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <location class="indexing_service">Chappaqua (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nagourney, Adam</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010122T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F00E7DA133CF931A15752C0A9679C8B63" item-length="955" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Hail to the Former Chief, Picking Up a Sandwich at the Deli</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ADAM NAGOURNEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Nagourney, Adam</byline>
      <dateline>CHAPPAQUA, N.Y., Jan. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Former Pres Bill Clinton begins private life in Chappaqua, NY, shaking hands with residents, signing autographs and picking up snack at local deli; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For the last eight years, whenever Bill Clinton wanted to go somewhere -- even out for a cup of coffee -- it turned into a production of armored limousines, vans, ambulances, helicopters, national security advisers, press aides and squads of Secret Service agents carrying submachine guns.</p>
        <p>This morning, when the former president of the United States decided to leave his new white house in the snow-covered suburbs of New York to pick up a cup of coffee for his wife and an egg salad sandwich for himself, the trappings of his short trip suggested just how much his position in life has changed. He arrived at Lange's Little Store, across the street from a Grand Union, in a motorcade of precisely two cars. There was not a helicopter or machine gun in sight.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For the last eight years, whenever Bill Clinton wanted to go somewhere -- even out for a cup of coffee -- it turned into a production of armored limousines, vans, ambulances, helicopters, national security advisers, press aides and squads of Secret Service agents carrying submachine guns.</p>
        <p>This morning, when the former president of the United States decided to leave his new white house in the snow-covered suburbs of New York to pick up a cup of coffee for his wife and an egg salad sandwich for himself, the trappings of his short trip suggested just how much his position in life has changed. He arrived at Lange's Little Store, across the street from a Grand Union, in a motorcade of precisely two cars. There was not a helicopter or machine gun in sight.</p>
        <p>''It must be a slow news day in New York if you have to cover me,'' Mr. Clinton declared, chuckling at the sight of the reporters -- a fairly small bunch, if truth be told, compared with the old White House crowd -- who had come out to chronicle his first day as a private citizen.</p>
        <p>The former president, in a chatty mood, and presumably enjoying the free time he now has on his hands, said he and Senator Hillary Rodham Clinton had spent the morning unpacking books and boxes. Mr. Clinton said he had not read the Sunday newspapers, filled with accounts of the inauguration of his successor, President Bush, or watched the Sunday morning talk shows, though he insisted he never watched those anyway. When one of his new neighbors asked whether he had slept after what turned out to be a rather eventful last week in office, Mr. Clinton responded, ''Like a rock.''</p>
        <p>''So far, it's been wonderful,'' he said, offering an early report on life outside the White House.</p>
        <p>Not that he was able to quite leave his White House years behind him. Mr. Clinton defended his last-day-in-office granting of 140 pardons and said that he and his advisers were studying the way the pardon process was handled, with the intention of presenting a memo of recommendations to Mr. Bush on how to handle future pardon applications.</p>
        <p>''If you look at it, we did some more than President Reagan in the aggregate, but less than President Carter and President Ford did -- even though the population, the eligible population, is probably larger now,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''As long as we live in a world where you never vote again or have full citizenship restored to you unless you get a pardon, then the word 'pardon' is somehow almost a misnomer,'' Mr. Clinton said. ''You're not saying these people didn't commit an offense. You're saying they paid, they paid in full, and they've been out long enough after their sentence to show they are good citizens.''</p>
        <p>At Lange's, Mr. Clinton's arrival on this cold morning set off a frenzy of, well, presidential proportions. Local residents lined up and clamored to shake his hand, or pose for pictures, or get an autograph. (When someone sought to get Mr. Clinton to sign a $10 bill, he shook his head, saying, ''No money.'')</p>
        <p>Grabbing his hand, Sandy Nuffer said, ''I wish you could still be our president!''</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton responded: ''It was an honor to serve. Thank you.''</p>
        <p>He did not respond when someone shouted, ''Hillary in four years?''</p>
        <p>Some people were not quite as taken by the celebrity in their midst. Kathleen Mc Avoy of Mahopac pressed a piece of paper and pen into the hand of her daughter, saying, ''Don't you want to have a president's signature?''</p>
        <p>Her daughter, Siobhan, 11, responded firmly, ''He is not a president.''</p>
        <p>Her mother replied, ''He was a president.'' Siobhan got her autograph.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Clinton stayed at home during her husband's outing. But a few moments before the former president arrived, Chelsea Clinton slipped into the deli with no retinue or fanfare. Ms. Clinton, 20, stood almost unnoticed at the deli counter, until people standing around realized, one by one, who she was. Without exception, they stopped and stared.</p>
        <p>''This is history,'' Jay Schlesinger, a psychologist, whispered urgently to his wife.</p>
        <p>Ms. Clinton then proceeded to greet people in the store, and used the honorific ''mister'' to address even reporters who had covered her parents. When one suggested that that level of formality was not necessary, the former president's daughter demurred. ''I may live in New York, but I'm still from the South,'' she said.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Clinton seemed to be enjoying himself as much as he always did, stretching out the reception for nearly 20 minutes. ''Like your red shoes!'' he said to one young girl. And when one more person expressed regrets that his years in Washington were over, Mr. Clinton smiled appreciatively and said: ''No one gets to stay forever. And it's better to leave when someone wants you.''</p>
        <p>With that, William Jefferson Clinton dug into a brown paper bag to retrieve his egg salad sandwich, climbed back in his two-car motorcade, and headed back to the place that he is now calling home.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
