<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Sheik's Followers Say He Won't Be Silenced</title>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="823964"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ISLAM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOMBS AND BOMB PLOTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ASSASSINATIONS AND ATTEMPTED ASSASSINATIONS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EGYPT</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MACFARQUHAR, NEIL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ABDEL RAHMAN, OMAR (SHEIK)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MUBARAK, HOSNI (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/Egypt</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Assassinations and Attempted Assassinations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bombs and Explosives</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Islam</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960119T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02EFDE1E39F93AA25752C0A960958260" item-length="851" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Sheik's Followers Say He Won't Be Silenced</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By NEIL MacFARQUHAR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MACFARQUHAR, NEIL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Followers of Sheik Omar Abdel Rahman, who was given a life sentence Wednesday for his role in bombing and assassination plots in the United States, said yesterday that prison would become a new pulpit for his attempts to replace the  government of President Hosni Mubarak and make Egypt an Islamic state.</p>
        <p>"The whole trial was to silence the sheik forever, to shut him up," said Ahmed Abd El-Sattar, a close aide to Mr. Abdel Rahman who helped work on his defense. "But the man will never be silenced."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Followers of Sheik Omar Abdel Rahman, who was given a life sentence Wednesday for his role in bombing and assassination plots in the United States, said yesterday that prison would become a new pulpit for his attempts to replace the  government of President Hosni Mubarak and make Egypt an Islamic state.</p>
        <p>"The whole trial was to silence the sheik forever, to shut him up," said Ahmed Abd El-Sattar, a close aide to Mr. Abdel Rahman who helped work on his defense. "But the man will never be silenced."</p>
        <p>Mr. Abdel Rahman's followers said that immediately after Judge Michael B. Mukasey imposed the sentence Wednesday in Federal Court in Manhattan, the sheik  called out "I won, by the Lord of the Kaaba."</p>
        <p>The Kaaba is the shrine at Mecca to which Muslims turn when praying. The phrase dates back 1,400 years, when the original companions of Mohammed who gathered around the Kaaba said each new prosecution invigorated the faith. With  it, his followers said yesterday, the sheik was wrapping himself in the mantel of religious prisoners as varied as the biblical Joseph and Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini, whose years in jail and exile increased their reach.</p>
        <p>"In Iran before the 1979 revolution," Mr. El-Sattar said, "the Shah tried to  bar Khomeini's tapes and the Iranian people managed to get them through anyway."</p>
        <p>But even followers concede that the number of his adherents is shrinking, with lower attendance during his telephone sermons from jail and less interest in buying recorded versions. Although the followers tend to attribute this slippage to the harassment of United States and Egyptian officials, it remains an open question whether Mr. Abdel Rahman's fire-and-brimstone style alone will be sufficient to sustain his message when he is not readily accessible.</p>
        <p>At the area mosques where Mr. Abdel Rahman served as a prayer leader, even the members who found his views extreme expressed dismay at the length of the sentences meted out to him and his nine co-defendants. The cleric and El Sayyid  A. Nosair received life sentences; the others were sentenced to terms ranging from 25 to 57 years.</p>
        <p>Many Muslims have long felt themselves under a siege perpetuated by the extensive involvement of religious militants in the 1993 bombing of the World Trade Center and subsequent plots.</p>
        <p>"The judge did not mean the verdict for Sheik Omar or these nine people alone," said Hamad Nebawy, an Egyptian-born grocery store owner in Brooklyn who  publicly split with Mr. Abdel Rahman over his teachings. "He was attacking Islam through these people."</p>
        <p>There is also a widespread feeling that the 57-year-old cleric was set up by  the Egyptian Government, which has long wanted him behind bars because of his exhortations for the overthrow of President Mubarak, who has been Egypt's leader since the assassination of President Anwar Sadat.</p>
        <p>Even after he was jailed by the Federal Government, Mr. Abdel Rahman has continued to preach over the telephone to followers at mosques in Brooklyn, Jersey City and Los Angeles.</p>
        <p>His Saturday night sermons at the Abu Bakr Mosque in Brooklyn once drew scores of followers. But members of the local community now say that such a sermon might bring in a dozen and that sales of the sheik's tapes have also dwindled. Other mosques asked him to discontinue his telephone sermons, fearing  that he might incite unnecessary bloodshed.</p>
        <p>"We don't want what happened in Algeria to happen in Egypt," said Mr. Nebawy, referring to the civil war between secular and religious parties that has left about 40,000 dead over the past four years. "Sure, there is support for an Islamic government in Egypt," he said, "but we have to do it gradually."</p>
        <p>In Egypt yesterday, the state-controlled media gave the sentencing little or  no coverage. The government has sought to play down the case, although privately officials expressed relief that Mr. Abdel Rahman was out of their hands. The campaign of bombings and shootings initiated by the Islamic Group, the most violent organization inspired by his preaching, has left about 800 people dead since it started in December 1992.</p>
        <p>Mr. Abdel Rahman himself was taken from a Manhattan jail yesterday and flown  to a medical center for Federal prisoners in Springfield, Mo., where he has been isolated from other prisoners since his conviction in October. Penal officials said yesterday that his co-defendants would also be moved from the Manhattan Correctional Center soon.</p>
        <p>Attorneys for the cleric said they were considering filing suit over the conditions in which he was being held. He is barred from attending prayers with  other Muslims, and no one on the prison staff can speak to him in Arabic. Since  he speaks no English and is blind, he is often confused about what is happening  around him, lawyers said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
