<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Arts School Gets A in Looks, F in Leaks</title>
    <meta content="17" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="467502"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY AND ORGANIZATION PROFILES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">HARLEM SCHOOL OF ARTS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ALLEN, BETTY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BLAU, ELEANOR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910817T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE6D6163EF934A2575BC0A967958260" item-length="877" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Arts School Gets A in Looks, F in Leaks</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ELEANOR BLAU</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BLAU, ELEANOR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"This building is falling down around our ears," said Betty Allen. "It's only 12 years old, but there are so many things wrong with it." She was speaking of the Harlem School of the Arts, whose award-winning quarters on Nicholas Avenue near 141st Street opened a few months before she became the executive director.</p>
        <p>The design, by Ulrich Franzen, was fine, she said. The main problem was the execution -- by the sub-contractor, who "disappeared" before completing the job, and the contractor, who, she said, went bankrupt before the school could take him to court.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"This building is falling down around our ears," said Betty Allen. "It's only 12 years old, but there are so many things wrong with it." She was speaking of the Harlem School of the Arts, whose award-winning quarters on Nicholas Avenue near 141st Street opened a few months before she became the executive director.</p>
        <p>The design, by Ulrich Franzen, was fine, she said. The main problem was the execution -- by the sub-contractor, who "disappeared" before completing the job, and the contractor, who, she said, went bankrupt before the school could take him to court.</p>
        <p>Also, construction these days, it seems, isn't what it might be. "What do you want, lady?" she recalled a plumber telling her. "The</p>
        <p>World Trade Center</p>
        <p>leaks!"</p>
        <p>Miss Allen detailed the structure's woes -- ranging from sewage back-ups to a flat roof that was supposed to have been slanted -- while discussing imminent changes at the institution, one of the nation's first major multidisciplined arts schools serving mainly black and Hispanic youngsters.</p>
        <p>She will step down as executive director as soon as a successor is found. In the meantime, she has been named president -- a new title -- to head a capital fund drive whose details are to be announced in the weeks ahead. Career Interrupted</p>
        <p>A mezzo-soprano who appeared in opera houses all over the world, Miss Allen stopped singing publicly in the mid-1980's because of lung problems she traces to the sooty air of Youngstown, Ohio, where she grew up. She hopes to become a consultant for the school when her contract expires in three years.</p>
        <p>Miss Allen said she hoped the new executive director could "pick my brains" and ease into the role while she was still on the scene. That would contrast with her own experience when she took over from the soprano Dorothy Maynor, who founded the school in 1964. Miss Maynor had hoped to help pave the way for Miss Allen but could not do so because of illness.</p>
        <p>At that time there were 500 students, 50 faculty members and a staff of a dozen or less, she recalled. Now there are 1,500 students, 78 teachers and 19 staff members, some of whom occupy offices converted from studios. The yearly budget has increased from nearly $500,000 to $1.8 million.</p>
        <p>Since Miss Maynor began it with a dozen students in a church, the Harlem School of the Arts has educated thousands of youngsters who have gone on to colleges and conservatories all over the country. Some have developed careers in the arts; singers have appeared with opera companies including the Metropolitan and the Glyndebourne Festival.</p>
        <p>Tuition fees are comparatively low and scholarships numerous; no child is turned away for lack of finances, Miss Allen said. About half the students are from Manhattan, mainly Harlem; the remainder are from other parts of the city and the suburbs. They take classes in music, dance, drama and the visual arts, coming in after regular school hours, during "release time" or on Saturdays. They are taught by professionals, most of whom also perform. The students perform, too, at the school and elsewhere, and are tested. "We are not baby-sitting," Miss Allen said. Future Fund Raising</p>
        <p>Thanks to challenge grants, Miss Allen managed to free the school of debt, paying off a $1.6 million mortgage on the $4 million building in 1982. Still, fund raising is going to be a big part of her successor's job.</p>
        <p>Future plans for the school include expansion next door. The city had allotted $3 million for that project a year ago, as part of an effort to upgrade Harlem. But facing its own money problems, it reduced the figure to $2 million, put off to 1994.</p>
        <p>The immediate goal, Miss Allen said, is to "keep the building from falling down" -- which she thinks would cost about $250,000 -- and develop a reasonable cash reserve or endowment.</p>
        <p>As for the building's troubles, Miss Allen began with her own office, whose gray cinderblock walls are marred by water stains, as are walls in the library below. The room was virtually airless when she arrived and has needed repeated work to make it livable. "I firmly believe the ducts are in backward," she said. It was also cold, so radiator covers were removed, revealing only two of the eight units that were supposed to have been installed.</p>
        <p>As for the rest of the building, she said, "Someone in their infinite wisdom made the sewage pipes too narrow." The rugs, which are important for soundproofing, are very worn and need to be replaced, she said, and the whole place needs a serious painting.</p>
        <p>"The library will have to be completely redone," she said. "The rugs are mildewed. It smells like the basement of the House of Usher." Indeed, the smell was dank as she led a visitor there, interrupting a boy's saxophone lesson. His teacher could not use his own studio because it was temporarily occupied by a harpist. Even in summer, when only some 200 students attend, space is at a premium.</p>
        <p>None of the walls of the school are straight; there's "a bend here, a bend there," she pointed out. But that's not a focus of their needs, she said. "I'm talking about heat in winter, being cool in summer, lights to see and you don't have a back-up in your cellar and your roof doesn't leak. This is pretty basic. Anything else is fabulous."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
