<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Vina Appears to Be Mets' Ace in the Hole</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="677221"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK METS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">FREY, JENNIFER</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940328T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E0DB163FF93BA15750C0A962958260" item-length="397" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Vina Appears to Be Mets' Ace in the Hole</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JENNIFER FREY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FREY, JENNIFER</byline>
      <dateline>PORT ST. LUCIE, Fla., March 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Fifteen months ago, Fernando Vina was so expendable that the Mets left him unprotected in the Rule 5 draft and lost him to the Seattle Mariners.</p>
        <p>This spring, the Mets are turning him into their starting shortstop.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Fifteen months ago, Fernando Vina was so expendable that the Mets left him unprotected in the Rule 5 draft and lost him to the Seattle Mariners.</p>
        <p>This spring, the Mets are turning him into their starting shortstop.</p>
        <p>Nothing has been said officially, but Manager Dallas Green did not dispel the notion that Vina had earned the starting spot when asked about Vina's role after the Mets' 9-3 loss to the Yankees today at Thomas J. White Stadium.</p>
        <p>Vina, who was returned to the Mets' organization last June, has started four of the past five games at short and has started seven games there altogether. And, just as noteworthy, he has started in the leadoff spot 14 times this spring. Indeed, it is no secret that Vina's speed and his ability to get on base have caught the attention of the Mets, who opened spring training with no true leadoff candidates. 'Earning the Right'</p>
        <p>"He has earned the right to get out there amongst the other two or three, and get out there on a regular basis," said Green, who is pleased with Vina's hitting and his range in the field. "We'll do that and we'll see what happens." Green added that he still has questions about Vina's ability to make the right decisions in certain situations, particularly on the bases.</p>
        <p>Vina's move to shortstop means that Tim Bogar has once again lost an opportunity to get an everyday job. Bogar, long considered by the Mets to be best-used as a utility infielder, appeared to be the leading candidate to get the starting shortstop job until Vina grabbed the Mets' attention. But when Bobby Bonilla was out with rib problems nearly two weeks ago, Bogar found himself making starts at third base while Vina played short.</p>
        <p>"If the decision comes down to not starting, I hope I find out why," said Bogar, who is hitting .304 this spring. "If it's because he's a leadoff hitter and I'm not, well, there's more to the game than being a leadoff hitter." INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>ERIC HILLMAN struggled with a knot in his shoulder and lasted just three innings, giving up eight hits and four runs. . . . BOBBY BONILLA hit off a tee for 15 minutes Sunday and felt that his sore ribs were getting better. Bonilla hit about 30 balls right-handed and took about a dozen hesitant swings left-handed. The Mets' main goal is to have him ready by opening day. . . . PETE SCHOUREK continues to have gastrointestinal problems.  BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
