<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Way We Eat; Preacher Comforts</title>
    <meta content="02food" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="109" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/02/magazine/02food.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1706388"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="Food"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York City</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Sharpton, Al</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051002T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D03EEDC1530F931A35753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="1440" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Way We Eat; Preacher Comforts</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Way We Eat: Preacher Comforts</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Amanda Hesser</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Al Sharpton, the reverend, politician and social agitator, is the kind of New York City fixture who would not quite fit in anywhere else. He's a little like a disco ball -- great for the dance floor but awkward in the living room or the diner. On the streets, he is as familiar a sight as a yellow taxi or the naked cowboy in Times Square. And when it comes to dining, he gives off the air of someone who is as happy eating pasta at Rao's as he is chomping on a hot dog at Shea Stadium. So I recently asked Sharpton, who is 50 years old: if it was his last day in New York City, where would he go for breakfast, lunch and dinner? And then I dined with him, all day long.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>For Al Sharpton, the ultimate dining experience involves few carbs and plenty of phone calls.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Al Sharpton, the reverend, politician and social agitator, is the kind of New York City fixture who would not quite fit in anywhere else. He's a little like a disco ball -- great for the dance floor but awkward in the living room or the diner. On the streets, he is as familiar a sight as a yellow taxi or the naked cowboy in Times Square. And when it comes to dining, he gives off the air of someone who is as happy eating pasta at Rao's as he is chomping on a hot dog at Shea Stadium. So I recently asked Sharpton, who is 50 years old: if it was his last day in New York City, where would he go for breakfast, lunch and dinner? And then I dined with him, all day long.</p>
        <p>8 a.m.: Breakfast at the Regency Hotel, Manhattan</p>
        <p>The Regency, breakfast temple of boldface names, is not the kind of place you would expect to find Sharpton, but two days after the city primary election, he made his way to his regular banquette, where he joined me, his lawyer, Sanford Rubenstein and his spokeswoman, Rachel Noerdlinger. Although he had already been up for three hours -- running on the treadmill and waking up people with phone calls -- he looked neither bright-eyed nor bushy-tailed. Sharpton isn't the live wire he is on camera; in person, he is more like a reticent uncle, someone you think you know but don't.</p>
        <p>''So, what's up?'' Sharpton said to Rubenstein.</p>
        <p>''I was raving about the omelets,'' Rubenstein said.</p>
        <p>''Oh,'' Sharpton replied, nonplussed that we were actually going to be talking about food. For Sharpton, the restaurant table is nothing more than a desk with linens. He stayed quiet until he spotted Larry King across the room and then hopped up to go see him. He returned to check his cellphone and then, when the menus arrived, Sharpton got up again and disappeared.</p>
        <p>''Some things never change,'' Noerdlinger said as she made her way through the tabloids.</p>
        <p>When Sharpton finally sat down, he ordered two eggs, over easy, with turkey bacon, ''no bread, no potatoes,'' and began slugging back his first of three cups of coffee. It could be a long day.</p>
        <p>''I would eat in Amy Ruth's'' -- a soul food restaurant in Harlem -- ''three times a day, but business requires a place like this,'' Sharpton said. ''Eating in New York is politics. You're not just eating with your lawyer. You work the room. Where else can you eat breakfast and see Larry King and the head of CNN, eat in Brooklyn for lunch, in Harlem for dinner? That's a good day: three meals and covering your bases.''</p>
        <p>2:45 p.m.: Lunch at Marco Polo Ristorante, Brooklyn</p>
        <p>Marco Polo, a scampi and scaloppine restaurant, is strictly old-school. ''Twenty years ago, he would have chosen Junior's,'' Sharpton's daughter Dominique, a sophomore at New York University, said as she sat down. ''We also came here a lot. Almost every night growing up, we ate here.''</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Sharpton was back on the phone. When I asked him what his favorite meal was, he said: ''My best meal is chicken, salad and a cellphone conversation with a good signal. There's nothing worse than a bad connection when you're eating.''</p>
        <p>Over lunch, he got most of his dream meal: cellphone calls and a Caesar salad. Caesar salad is one of his favorite foods, along with baked chicken, cabbage and corn. (When I noted that all of his favorites began with a ''C,'' Sharpton laughed. He later added coleslaw and cookies.)</p>
        <p>He also ordered shrimp scampi, which came with mashed potatoes. ''You can't eat the mashed potatoes if you're on my diet today,'' Sharpton said. He maneuvered around the potatoes, eating only the shrimp and sauce. He downed a Diet Coke.</p>
        <p>The Sharpton of recent months has been more svelte. He shed a lot of pounds when he was in jail for protesting the Navy bombing exercises in Vieques, and he told me earlier: ''I felt better. I'll tell you something. I was talking to Bill Clinton. He lost a lot of weight. You don't have to sleep as much. If I could sleep just one hour a day, I would.''</p>
        <p>Rubenstein added, ''When reverend preaches, he always says, You have time to sleep when you die.''</p>
        <p>10:45 p.m.: Dinner at Amy Ruth's, Harlem</p>
        <p>Sharpton had three ''7 o'clocks'' -- a talk at a church gathering, a speech at Bill Clinton's Global Initiative conference and a stop at the Marc Anthony concert. These, predictably, made him two hours late for dinner. Sharpton arrived in a black limousine, having already ordered food for himself and his lawyer from the car.</p>
        <p>Amy Ruth's was started by Carl Redding, who was once Sharpton's driver and later his chief of staff. The first dish on the menu is called ''The Rev. Al Sharpton.'' It's chicken and waffles, Sharpton explained, ''which I don't eat.'' A fine point, since instead he ordered smothered chicken with corn and cabbage.</p>
        <p>He had his usual side dish -- a cellphone call or two -- and stood, midmeal, to have his picture taken with a diner wearing a T-shirt that said ''Ideal.'' The food here was the most impressive of the day -- fried chicken in a thick gravy, boiled corn and cabbage sautéed with lots of pepper.</p>
        <p>''Eating's not about waving the flag,'' Sharpton said as he dug in. ''Eating's about eating, and about being comfortable. I'm probably the only guy who knows the people at Amy Ruth's as well as I know the people at the Regency.''</p>
        <p>And probably one of the few to arrive at Amy Ruth's in a limousine. Sharpton did focus on eating and seemed comfortable having a real dining experience at last. All that was left on his plate were the bones. And he was out the door by 11:15 p.m.</p>
        <p>Smothered Chicken</p>
        <p>For the gravy:</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon onion powder</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon dried thyme</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon red pepper flakes</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon adobo, with more to taste</p>
        <p>1/4 teaspoon Jamaican hot jerk seasoning sauce</p>
        <p>1 1/2 cubes or 18 grams chicken-flavor bouillon</p>
        <p>1/4 cup plus 2 tablespoons flour</p>
        <p>1/4 cup canola oil</p>
        <p>1 1/2 teaspoons Gravy Master</p>
        <p>For the chicken:</p>
        <p>1 gallon canola oil</p>
        <p>1/2 cup cider vinegar</p>
        <p>2/3 cup flour</p>
        <p>2 chicken breasts with wings and 2 legs</p>
        <p>1 1/2 tablespoons paprika</p>
        <p>1 1/2tablespoons adobo.</p>
        <p>1. Prepare the gravy: In a large pot combine the onion powder, thyme, red pepper, adobo, Jamaican hot jerk sauce and bouillon. Add 4 cups of water and bring to a boil. In a medium bowl, whisk together the flour and oil until smooth. Whisk a little broth into the oil/flour mixture, then whisk this into the pot of broth. Bring to a boil; then reduce to a simmer. Stir in the Gravy Master. Season to taste with adobo.</p>
        <p>2. Prepare the chicken: In a large, deep pot, heat 1 gallon canola oil to 365 degrees.</p>
        <p>3. Pour the vinegar into a large bowl, and in a shallow bowl, pour the flour. Dunk the chicken in the vinegar, season it generously with the paprika and adobo, then roll in the flour. Shake off excess flour. Fry two pieces at a time in the oil for about 12-16 minutes or until well browned and cooked through. Drain on a paper-towel-lined plate. Just before serving, roll the chicken in the gravy. Serve with a few extra spoonfuls of gravy. Serves 4.</p>
        <p>Sautéed Cabbage</p>
        <p>3 tablespoons canola oil</p>
        <p>1 tablespoon chopped garlic</p>
        <p>1 onion, cut into Zv-inch slices</p>
        <p>1 red bell pepper, cut into</p>
        <p>1/4 -inch slices</p>
        <p>1/2 large cabbage, cored and cut into 1/3 inch slices</p>
        <p>1/4 cup shredded carrots</p>
        <p>1/2 teaspoon adobo, more to taste.</p>
        <p>In a large sauté pan, heat the oil over medium-high heat. Add the garlic, then the onions and pepper, and sauté. Once the onions become translucent, add the cabbage. When the cabbage starts to wilt, add the carrots and adobo. Season with more adobo to taste and serve with smothered chicken. Serves 4. Both recipes adapted from Amy Ruth's.</p>
        <p>Food</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
