<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rangers' Thoughts Turn To Possible Clincher</title>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="679170"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOCKEY, ICE</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK RANGERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">THOMAS, ROBERT MCG JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Rangers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940408T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E07E2DA173EF93BA35757C0A962958260" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rangers' Thoughts Turn To Possible Clincher</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT McG. THOMAS Jr.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">THOMAS, ROBERT MCG JR</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With four games to go in the 84-game National Hockey League season, the Rangers are a victory away from clinching the Atlantic Division title, the Devils are a loss away from settling for second place and the Islanders are still riding a four-team playoff bubble so complicated that the idle Islanders had trouble deciding which team to root for in last night's game between the Florida Panthers and the Philadelphia Flyers.</p>
        <p>The Islanders, who play the Dallas Stars at the Nassau Coliseum tonight, knew that a Florida victory would strengthen the Panthers' grip on the eighth and final Eastern Conference playoff berth.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With four games to go in the 84-game National Hockey League season, the Rangers are a victory away from clinching the Atlantic Division title, the Devils are a loss away from settling for second place and the Islanders are still riding a four-team playoff bubble so complicated that the idle Islanders had trouble deciding which team to root for in last night's game between the Florida Panthers and the Philadelphia Flyers.</p>
        <p>The Islanders, who play the Dallas Stars at the Nassau Coliseum tonight, knew that a Florida victory would strengthen the Panthers' grip on the eighth and final Eastern Conference playoff berth.</p>
        <p>As it happened, the Panthers and Flyers tied, 3-3. The 1 point gained by Florida put the Panthers 2 points ahead of the Islanders, 80-78. Philadelphia trailed both with 76 points.</p>
        <p>The Rangers, who need one victory to put them out of reach of the Devils, could clinch the division title and the home-ice playoff advantage that goes with it, as early as tonight, when they play the Toronto Maple Leafs at Madison Square Garden. Gartner Comes Back</p>
        <p>Aside from its potential impact on the division championship and the Rangers' quest for a record for victories and points in a season -- they need one victory to eclipse their total of 50 in the 80-game 1991-92 season, and they need 2 points to tie the record of 109 in the 78-game 1971-72 season -- tonight's game against Toronto has special meaning for the Rangers and their fans.</p>
        <p>Or, as Joey Kocur put it after practice yesterday, "Mike Gartner is coming back to the Garden."</p>
        <p>Gartner, who was traded to Toronto as part of a major player shake-up on March 21, was among the most popular Rangers, a speed-skating prolific goal scorer who is sure to generate an enthusiastic welcome at the Garden.</p>
        <p>Still, for all of Gartner's local popularity and the resentment his trade generated against Coach Mike Keenan, who sought and got a scrappier lineup, it's hard to argue with success. Since the trade, the Rangers have compiled a 6-1-1 record. Devils on Losing Streak</p>
        <p>While the Devils' second-place fate seems largely in the hands of the Rangers, 6 points ahead with four games to go, they will have a chance tonight to reverse a three-game losing streak, their longest of the season, and to avenge Wednesday night's 3-1 loss to the Penguins in Pittsburgh.</p>
        <p>For tonight's rematch at Byrne Meadowlands Arena, however, Coach Jacques Lemaire plans to continue his program of giving his weary players some rest in anticipation of the playoffs. Among those who will get the night off is Martin Brodeur, the rookie goaltender who has lost the last two games after going 9-0-2 in his previous 11. Chris Terreri will get the assignment to face Mario Lemieux and the Penguins, who have been playing their best hockey of the season. Islanders Play Dallas</p>
        <p>The weary Islanders spent the day trying to shake off a discouraging 3-3 overtime tie with the Whalers in Hartford Wednesday night and preparing for tonight's home game against Dallas.</p>
        <p>"We played a great hockey game and I think we should have won the game," said goalie Ron Hextall. Maybe so, but the Islanders missed several scoring opportunities, including six errant shots on goal during overtime, and the defense looked spotty at times.</p>
        <p>That, according to Coach Al Arbour, is only to be expected at this time of year. "We were a little tired," he said, referring to a four-game run, including three overtime games. "Those are tough at this time of the season. That mental edge. We just didn't have it. If we would have been fresh, those goals would have been in."  HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
