<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Question Box</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="506840"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Question</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920210T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1D8163EF933A25751C0A964958260" item-length="739" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Question Box</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RAY CORIO</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Charity Stripe? Forget It</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>On Dec. 27, 1991, Tim Hardaway of the Golden State Warriors missed all 17 of his field-goal attempts to set a National Basketball Association record for one game. What's the record for free throws attempted in a game without making any of them?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Charity Stripe? Forget It</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>On Dec. 27, 1991, Tim Hardaway of the Golden State Warriors missed all 17 of his field-goal attempts to set a National Basketball Association record for one game. What's the record for free throws attempted in a game without making any of them?</p>
        <p>A. It's 10. It was also established by a player wearing a Warriors uniform, and this player who holds the mark for ineptness from the foul line is the same one who holds a good many records for scoring proficiency from elsewhere on the court -- Wilt Chamberlain. On Nov. 4, 1960, Chamberlain, a member of the Philadelphia Warriors, scored 44 points in a game against the Detroit Pistons, but went 0 for 10 from the free-throw line.</p>
        <p>No surprise there. For his career, Chamberlain attempted 11,862 foul shots -- some overhanded, some underhanded, some one-handed, some two-handed. He made 6,057. He missed 5,805. In other words, Chamberlain made 252 more free throws than he didn't make, and the 51 percent career average he achieved with no one guarding him is significantly lower than the 54 percent mark he posted when defenders were draped around him. Home Runs in Vain</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Among those eligible, which</p>
        <p>player has the most career home runs and is not in the Baseball Hall of Fame?</p>
        <p>A. The newly eligible Dave Kingman, 6 feet 6 inches, has elbowed the 6-7 Frank Howard from that distinction, but don't count on either landing a spot in Cooperstown soon, chiefly because of their career batting averages, .236 for Kingman and .273 for Howard. Twice in his career from 1971 through 1986, Kingman led the National League in home runs on the way to a career total of 442. When he became eligible for enshrinement for the first time this year, Kingman also became the only player to reach the seats more than 400 times and not earn a seat in the Hall of Fame.</p>
        <p>Before that, Howard, with 382 career homers, was the most productive slugger shut out of Cooperstown. Now a batting coach for the New York Yankees, Howard swung a menacing bat for the Los Angeles Dodgers, the Washington Senators, the Texas Rangers and the Detroit Tigers from 1958-73. Twice the former Ohio State basketball player led the American League in home runs, but his best showing in Hall of Fame voting was 6 votes in 1979. Pitching in Vain</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>What pitcher has the most career victories and is not in the Hall of Fame?</p>
        <p>A. Among those eligible and among those whose careers began after the pitcher's mound was fixed at 60 feet 6 inches from home plate in 1893, the top-winning pitcher blanked from enshrinement is Jim Kaat. He made his first major league pitch with the Washington Senators in 1959 and his last one with the St. Louis Cardinals in 1983. In between, he won 283 games and lost 237, reaching the 20-victory level in three seasons. For Kaat, a left-hander, the door to the Hall of Fame is still open.</p>
        <p>Not so for Vic Willis, the top-winning right-hander shut out of the hall. Eight times from 1898 through 1910, Willis was a 20-game winner. Twice he was a 20-game loser. And over his 13 years in the National League, with Boston, Pittsburgh and St. Louis, Willis posted a 248-204 record that included 50 shutouts.</p>
        <p>But in 1905, when Willis won 11 games and lost 29 for the Pirates, he set the modern record for defeats in a season by a pitcher. How would that look on a plaque in the Hall of Fame? Hockey's Finest Hour</p>
        <p>Q.</p>
        <p>Is it a rule in the National Hockey League to announce to the players and the fans when</p>
        <p>each period reaches its</p>
        <p>final minute?</p>
        <p>A. It's not in the rule book, but just try skipping it. The custom of publicly announcing "last minute to play in the period" or "last minute to play in the hockey game" evolved in the 1945-46 season among the six franchises in the league -- Montreal, Toronto, Chicago, Detroit, Boston and the New York Rangers. At a time when arena game clocks were difficult to read or even see because of obstructions and poor sightlines, the leaguewide plan was to inform the crowd on hand that the 20-minute period had passed the 19-minute mark. Like tape on a hockey stick, the tradition stuck.</p>
        <p>Readers are invited to submit questions concerning any aspect of sport: statistics or strategies, rules or records. The address is Question Box, SportsMonday, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036. Questions not published cannot be answered individually.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
