<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Relentless Jamison Is the Tar Heels' Leader</title>
    <meta content="24HEEL" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1004561"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="1998 N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ncaa Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">University of North Carolina</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jacobs, Barry</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jamison, Antawn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">NCAA Basketball Tournament</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980324T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0CE1D61338F937A15750C0A96E958260" item-length="895" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Relentless Jamison Is the Tar Heels' Leader</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARRY JACOBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jacobs, Barry</byline>
      <dateline>CHAPEL HILL, N.C., March 23</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article discusses play of North Carolina forward Antawn Jamison in NCAA tournament; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The pin was given to Antawn Jamison by a friend, and he wears it everywhere as a reminder, a touchstone amid the swirl of a college career that has exceeded his loftiest expectations.</p>
        <p>''For some reason it seems like it's completed me, and kind of protected me from harm sometimes,'' Jamison said. ''That's been the story ever since my freshman year. I wear the angel because somebody has to be watching over me.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The pin was given to Antawn Jamison by a friend, and he wears it everywhere as a reminder, a touchstone amid the swirl of a college career that has exceeded his loftiest expectations.</p>
        <p>''For some reason it seems like it's completed me, and kind of protected me from harm sometimes,'' Jamison said. ''That's been the story ever since my freshman year. I wear the angel because somebody has to be watching over me.''</p>
        <p>Certainly the presence of Jamison, a 6-foot-9-inch forward, has proved divine for North Carolina, the only top-seeded team remaining in the National Collegiate Athletic Association tournament. The Tar Heels  (34-3) are making their second consecutive trip to the Final Four, where they face Utah (29-3) on Saturday in San Antonio.</p>
        <p>Jamison has been the bulwark all season for the top-ranked Tar Heels, emerging with relatively little fanfare as one of the great performers in a program that has produced a constellation of stars.</p>
        <p>Jamison, the first Tar Heel named Atlantic Coast Conference player of the year since Michael Jordan in 1984, is averaging 22.4 points and 10.5 rebounds. A junior, he is the only Tar Heel besides Billy Cunningham in 1964 and 1965, and only the eighth player on any team, to pace the A.C.C. in scoring and rebounding in the same season.</p>
        <p>Jamison's scoring average is the highest at North Carolina since Charlie Scott's 27.1 points a game in 1970.</p>
        <p>''I think Antawn is probably going to be the runaway winner as the national player of the year, and it's well deserved,'' said Bill Guthridge, the North Carolina coach.</p>
        <p>Jamison is reminiscent of those earlier players in many ways. A veteran who proudly displays his enjoyment of the game, he laments that so many of his contemporaries feel compelled to scowl and adopt what he calls ''a bad-boy type image.'' He is a physical player who is as likely to help an opponent to his feet as to knock him down.</p>
        <p>He is also an amateur who, despite the imminent lure of a professional career, says of coming to college, ''My main goal was to get a degree.''</p>
        <p>Jamison's approach to playing the game is similarly old-fashioned.</p>
        <p>''He hasn't changed much,'' said his teammate Vince Carter, a frequent one-on-one opponent during the summer. ''He has a tenacious work ethic on the floor, and he plays hard.''</p>
        <p>Jamison shot hundreds of free throws daily during the off season to improve on his 57.9 percent career accuracy at the foul line. This season he has made 67.2 percent.</p>
        <p>''He's relentless,'' Guthridge said. '' 'Relentless' is a good word for him, the way he stays after rebounds and the way he's worked since he's been here.''</p>
        <p>Jamison also arrived at Chapel Hill with rare gifts that Guthridge, then an assistant to Dean Smith, recognized the first time he led the newcomer through an individual workout.</p>
        <p>''I remember, after working with him there for maybe an hour, my reaction was, 'Wow, is he ever quick!' '' Guthridge, whose duties for many years included working with the program's big men, cannot remember anyone quicker.</p>
        <p>That quickness is not limited to Jamison's footwork. When he is shooting, the ball often barely touches his hands before being launched toward the basket, arriving from a variety of odd angles but with 58.6 percent accuracy.</p>
        <p>''I don't think anybody around has ever had as quick a release around the basket as he has,'' Guthridge said. ''He has that uncanny ability. We certainly haven't taught him that.''</p>
        <p>Asked how he controls and launches the ball so quickly, Jamison laughs his easy laugh and admits that even he sometimes does not know.</p>
        <p>Because there is no pretense about Jamison, no one bats an eye when he routinely says he or his team did a ''tremendous'' job of this or a ''great'' job of that. And because he works so hard himself, the player nicknamed Twan is readily accepted by teammates now that he has become a more vocal leader.</p>
        <p>''A lot of players really realize that while you're out there playing in practice, if you're not giving 100 percent, you'd better watch out for Antawn because he's really going to get on your back,'' Jamison said.</p>
        <p>On the other hand, he adds swiftly, ''I'm one of those guys; I give a lot of credit when it's due.'' Just last week, Jamison stopped practice to applaud Brendan Haywood, a 7-foot freshman, for diving after a loose ball. ''The most important thing about me, I just go out there and lead by example,'' Jamison said.</p>
        <p>Now, that leadership has returned the Tar Heels to the brink of the title that eluded them last season, when they lost to Arizona, the eventual champion, after opening their semifinal game with a 15-4 burst.</p>
        <p>Ever a man for symbolic reminders, Jamison wore an Arizona hat throughout this season to keep fresh the memory of last year's failure, and of prizes yet to be won.</p>
        <p>1998 N.C.A.A. TOURNAMENT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
