<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Knicks Send Cavaliers a Little Playoff Message</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="599547"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NEW YORK KNICKERBOCKERS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">CLEVELAND CAVALIERS</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">ARATON, HARVEY</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/New York Knicks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball/National Basketball Association/Cleveland Cavaliers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930402T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7DC103CF931A35757C0A965958260" item-length="789" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Knicks Send Cavaliers a Little Playoff Message</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By HARVEY ARATON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ARATON, HARVEY</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Put Charles Oakley or Anthony Mason on the Cleveland Cavaliers last night, and maybe their game against the Knicks does not have an unmistakable air of inevitability. As it was, the Cavaliers hung around but seemed destined to lose almost every loose ball or big rebound and doomed to lose, by 91-83.</p>
        <p>In a Knick-style game such as this one, as fluid as traffic outside Madison Square Garden at the corner of Seventh Avenue and 34th Street, the Cavaliers are in desperate need of the wide body (with vacuum cleaner hands) they simply don't have. It's not that their front line isn't willing. At this level, tall and skinny simply doesn't make it against muscular and angry.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Put Charles Oakley or Anthony Mason on the Cleveland Cavaliers last night, and maybe their game against the Knicks does not have an unmistakable air of inevitability. As it was, the Cavaliers hung around but seemed destined to lose almost every loose ball or big rebound and doomed to lose, by 91-83.</p>
        <p>In a Knick-style game such as this one, as fluid as traffic outside Madison Square Garden at the corner of Seventh Avenue and 34th Street, the Cavaliers are in desperate need of the wide body (with vacuum cleaner hands) they simply don't have. It's not that their front line isn't willing. At this level, tall and skinny simply doesn't make it against muscular and angry.</p>
        <p>Look at it this way: Beef brothers Oakley and Mason combined for 12 offensive rebounds, 1 less than the entire Cleveland team.</p>
        <p>Look at it another way: The high scorer for the Cavaliers was reserve point guard Terrell Brandon with 16 points.</p>
        <p>Either way, the Cavaliers were not going to beat the Knicks, who won their 15th consecutive home game, when their two best players are shooting a combined 6 for 20. If the Cavs are supposed to have anything going for them against the Knicks, it is at point guard and center, with Mark Price breaking down the Knicks' defense and Brad Daugherty at least complicating Patrick Ewing's life.</p>
        <p>Neither much happened last night, when Price and Daugherty were no more All-Stars than Tate George and Rick Mahorn. Drought for Daugherty</p>
        <p>Daugherty had two fouls after four minutes and did not score a point until the first minute of the third quarter. Price made his first shot and then, harrassed by Doc Rivers, among others in the Knick swarm, was 3 for 10 the rest of the way. He also committed 5 of the Cavs' 10 first-quarter turnovers, several of which Coach Lenny Wilkens wasn't giving the Knicks any credit for.</p>
        <p>"It's not defense when you're throwing it away with no one on you," said Wilkens.</p>
        <p>The problem for the Cavs is that they haven't shot well against the Knicks, against whom they were 4-0 last year, all season. In losing three of four to the Knicks, the Cavs never shot better than 45 percent. Against the rest of the league, they are over 50.</p>
        <p>That the Knicks themselves shot only 39 percent and still were never in serious trouble underscores their improvement as a team which plays better team defense than last season and has players -- Ewing, John Starks and Doc Rivers last night -- who make big shots.</p>
        <p>Their own sloppiness helped keep the game close, as they led 22-18 after the first quarter. Behind Ewing, who scored 30 points, and Starks, who had 22 points and 11 assists, they gradually built a 45-32 halftime lead.</p>
        <p>Brandon led the Cavs on a 10-2 run to start the fourth quarter, but every time it looked like they might break through, a loose ball or an offensive rebound or a turnover held them back. Rivers would hit from outside. Starks would crash the lane and drop in a neat lefty layup. Ewing, light on his feet, would lower his right shoulder into the lumbering Daugherty and score fading back.</p>
        <p>The closest the Cavs would come was 78-72, with the ball. But John Battle missed an open jumper and Starks settled the issue, first with a driving layup and then, on the fast break, with a stutter-step drive and ensuing free throw.</p>
        <p>"To win three of four against them is big," said Starks. "We want the edge in case we play them in the playoffs."</p>
        <p>Wilkens has other problems than the Knicks right now, as Pat Riley noticed. "They've backed up on Boston," said Riley, meaning that the streaking Celtics are contesting the Cavs now for third place in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>That's quite a comedown for the Cavs, who two weeks ago were entertaining thoughts of catching the Knick and the Bulls. That's when the Knicks marched into the Richfield Coliseum outside Cleveland and beat the Cavs so badly that Wilkens, Daugherty and Larry Nance were ejected, and Craig Ehlo requested that the officials spare him the final minutes of a dreadful, embarrassing blowout.</p>
        <p>Wilkens at least was in a better mood last night. "Our effort was there tonight," he said. "We're just not shooting well, but that'll come."</p>
        <p>Based on the season series, he may not want to count on that, if the Cavs meet up again with the Knicks sometime down the playoff road. REBOUNDS</p>
        <p>PATRICK EWING was named National Basketball Association player of the month for March, the league announced yesterday. Ewing averaged 27.3 points, 11.1 rebounds and 2.07 blocked shots in leading the Knicks to their winningest month (12-2) in 20 years. "I don't care about player of the month," he said. "I'm happy we won." . . . Knicks are three home victories from tying their record (35-6 in 1972-73 and 1988-89.)  PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
