<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Star Inspires Young Singers</title>
    <meta content="11CHOR" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1008805"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Young People's Chorus of New York</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Nyamsi, Adrienne</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tommasini, Anthony</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9906E0DC123DF932A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="743" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Star Inspires Young Singers</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANTHONY TOMMASINI</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Tommasini, Anthony</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Article on Young People's Chorus of New York focuses on visit by Metropolitan Opera star Adrienne Nyamsi to one of Concert Choir's informal performances at recital room of Maximiliaan's House of Grand Pianos in Manhattan; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Young People's Chorus of New York, an acclaimed performance-based choral program that draws some 150 children aged 8 to 18 from all areas, economic groups and ethnic cultures of the city, has sung for some illustrious guests, including the pop singer Celine Dion, the composer Marvin Hamlisch and Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>But the chorus's artistic director, Francisco J. Nunez, said few guest listeners had inspired the choristers as much as the mezzo-soprano Denyce Graves, who heard an informal performance by the Concert Choir, the 40 members in the senior division (aged 14 to 18), on Wednesday night in the low-ceilinged, concrete-walled recital room at Maximiliaan's House of Grand pianos on Lexington Avenue.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Young People's Chorus of New York, an acclaimed performance-based choral program that draws some 150 children aged 8 to 18 from all areas, economic groups and ethnic cultures of the city, has sung for some illustrious guests, including the pop singer Celine Dion, the composer Marvin Hamlisch and Hillary Rodham Clinton.</p>
        <p>But the chorus's artistic director, Francisco J. Nunez, said few guest listeners had inspired the choristers as much as the mezzo-soprano Denyce Graves, who heard an informal performance by the Concert Choir, the 40 members in the senior division (aged 14 to 18), on Wednesday night in the low-ceilinged, concrete-walled recital room at Maximiliaan's House of Grand pianos on Lexington Avenue.</p>
        <p>The performance space was bare, but the excitement over Ms. Graves's visit was palpable. The radiant Metropolitan Opera star ''really connected with our singers,'' 32-year-old Mr. Nunez said. Many of them are afraid of the musical world, which can seem rarefied and out of reach, he said. But Ms. Graves, who grew up poor in a tough neighborhood in southwest Washington, is clearly a role model to the young choristers, many of whom also come from disadvantaged backgrounds.</p>
        <p>Ms. Graves knows the value of choral groups. During her childhood, it was singing in her Baptist church choir that got her excited about music. On Wednesday night, as the Young People's Chorus sang selections, including a Czech folk song, a selection from Bernstein's Mass and a gospel-inflected piece, ''Heaven Bound Train,'' by the Canadian composer Stephen Hatfield, Ms. Graves sat front-row center, listening intently, swaying to the music and clearly moved.</p>
        <p>When Mr. Nunez turned to her for comments, she said little. ''I just wanted to be here and see the gifts you have to offer,'' she said. ''You are clearly an exceptional group of singers. Everybody was jazzed and really excited. I really have little to say except, sing some more.''</p>
        <p>The next selection, however, did provoke some detailed coaching from Ms. Graves. Adrienne Nyamsi, a 16-year-old chorister, sang a solo, the wistful signature song of Billie Holiday, ''God Bless the Child,'' with Mr. Nunez at the piano.</p>
        <p>Ms. Nyamsi's performance was lovely but tentative, and Ms. Graves clearly identified with the shy, polite adolescent. ''Your voice is gorgeous,'' Ms. Graves told her. ''But I know it can be better. Now what does the song mean to you? Those first lines: 'Them that's got shall get, them that's not will lose.' What does it say to you?''</p>
        <p>''Well,'' Ms. Nyamsi answered, ''it seems to be saying that the rich get richer, the poor get poorer, and the Bible tells us it has always been this way and always will be.'' So, she added, ''God bless the child that's got his own.'' Then she looked expectantly at Ms. Graves.</p>
        <p>''There is no right or wrong answer,'' Ms. Graves said. ''There is only what you believe. But look how much more animated your body became when you explained the song to me in words. You must have a reason to make this music happen.'' Then, she said, to much laughter, ''Do you understand where I'm going, or do I just sound like a crazy lady?'' When Ms. Nyamsi tried the song again, her singing was noticeably more open and personal.</p>
        <p>Mr. Nunez founded the chorus in 1990 under the auspices of the Children's Aid Society of New York. But he wanted the group to reach the outer boroughs, and to ''shoot more toward high standards of artistry,'' he said, ''and the kids agreed.'' So the ensemble became independent. It is now in residence at the 92d Street Y, which provides rehearsal and office space. Its annual budget is over $200,000, and fund-raising is a constant concern.</p>
        <p>The chorus performs some 40 concerts a year. Scheduled events include an appearance on April 30 at St. Bartholomew's Church and a ''Voices of the World'' concert on May 20 at the 92d Street Y.</p>
        <p>On Wednesday, after some more music-making, the choristers chatted with Ms. Graves about her own life over cookies and punch. Ms. Nyamsi summed up the mood of everyone when she said: ''This whole thing, this whole thing. Wow!''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
