<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rebuffed, Yeltsin ReoffersHis Premier to Parliament</title>
    <meta content="Y11RUSS" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1008830"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Russia</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Yeltsin, Boris N (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kiriyenko, Sergei N</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bohlen, Celestine</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Russia and the Former Soviet Union</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Russia</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980411T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E3D8123DF932A25757C0A96E958260" item-length="932" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rebuffed, Yeltsin ReoffersHis Premier to Parliament</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CELESTINE BOHLEN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Bohlen, Celestine</byline>
      <dateline>MOSCOW, April 10</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Russian Pres Boris Yeltsin resubmits name of Sergei N Kiriyenko for post of Prime Minister, less than hour after Kiriyenko is rebuffed by lower house of Parliament; has two more chances under Constitution to win approval of nominee; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Insisting that he has no other candidate up his sleeve, President Boris N. Yeltsin today resubmitted the name of Sergei N. Kiriyenko for the post of Russian Prime Minister, less than an hour after the 35-year-old former banker, political novice and Acting Prime Minister was rebuffed by Parliament's lower house.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiriyenko's loss in the first round of balloting had been widely expected, even by the Kremlin. At a news briefing today, Mr. Yeltsin's spokesman, Sergei Yastrzhembsky,  described the results of the secret balloting as ''acceptable and not bad for a start.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Insisting that he has no other candidate up his sleeve, President Boris N. Yeltsin today resubmitted the name of Sergei N. Kiriyenko for the post of Russian Prime Minister, less than an hour after the 35-year-old former banker, political novice and Acting Prime Minister was rebuffed by Parliament's lower house.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiriyenko's loss in the first round of balloting had been widely expected, even by the Kremlin. At a news briefing today, Mr. Yeltsin's spokesman, Sergei Yastrzhembsky,  described the results of the secret balloting as ''acceptable and not bad for a start.''</p>
        <p>With major opposition parties, including the Communist Party, refusing even to take part, Mr. Kiriyenko's nomination was rejected 186 to 143, leaving him 83 votes short of the majority needed for confirmation in the 450-seat lower house. But with characteristic understatement, Mr. Kiriyenko brushed off his first-round defeat, saying he had expected even less support.</p>
        <p>Under the Constitution, Mr. Yeltsin has two more chances to win approval for his nominee for the  Government's top job. If his candidate is rejected on the third try, the President is empowered to disband Parliament and set new elections -- a gamble that few members of the lower house, who hold their seats until 1999, are eager to contemplate.</p>
        <p>The political drama set in motion on March 23 by Mr. Yeltsin's sudden dismissal of the Government headed by Viktor S. Chernomyrdin is also running into another deadline: On April 18 Mr. Yeltsin is due to set off for a two-day visit to Japan, a trip that has already been postponed once because of the government crisis, and the Kremlin has made clear that it expects a new Government in place before Mr. Yeltsin leaves the country.</p>
        <p>Between now and then, political analysts expect to see some political bargaining between Mr. Yeltsin and the opposition parties that hold a  majority in the lower house, the Duma. Gennadi Seleznoyov, the Duma's Speaker, has called on Mr. Yeltsin to present other candidates, an option the President explicitly ruled out in a radio address this morning.</p>
        <p>Defending Mr. Kiriyenko as a ''professional manager who can work as part of a team, who shuns self-promotion and cheap populism,'' Mr. Yeltsin said the deputies should make up their minds about his nominee as quickly as possible, ''because I have no other candidate.''</p>
        <p>Members of the opposition have used Mr. Kiriyenko's youth and inexperience as a wedge in what is widely seen as a broader attack against the politics of economic reform. ''We are voting today not so much on the head of the Government but on the course to get out of this crisis,'' said Gennadi A. Zyuganov, leader of the Communist Party.</p>
        <p>But last-minute defectors, like Vladimir V. Zhirinovsky, the arch-nationalist, said Mr. Yeltsin's choice was inappropriate.</p>
        <p>''You can't turn a first grader into an academician, or make a sergeant a marshal,'' said Mr. Zhirinovsky whose Liberal Democratic Party had been expected to vote for Mr. Kiriyenko today. ''Otherwise, there will be failure and destruction.''</p>
        <p>But Mr. Zhirinovsky also said he had backed out of his promises to support Mr. Kiriyenko once it became clear that his party was not going to get any seats in a new Cabinet. The final vote, however, suggested that many members of the opposition had broken ranks to vote for Mr. Kiriyenko.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, Mr. Kiriyenko, who in two weeks has leapt from obscurity to center stage, was saying today that he was not available for politics as usual. ''I am absolutely independent, and I am not going to listen to anyone except President Boris N. Yeltsin,'' said Mr. Kiriyenko, who has had only one year's experience in government. ''Neither old acquaintances nor friendship will matter.''</p>
        <p>''It is our duty to overcome the people's mistrust of the Government and their estrangement from it,'' he said, as he straddled a fine line between defending the Government he served, and calling for one that will be better managed and more open.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kiriyenko has already indicated that four key ministers will stay in their current jobs, including Foreign Minister Yevgeny M. Primakov, Defense Minister Igor D. Sergeyev, Interior Minister Sergei V. Stepashin and Finance Minister Mikhail M. Zadornov.</p>
        <p>In a 30-minute speech to Parliament, Mr. Kiriyenko delivered a harsh summary of Russia's economic situation. He said Russia now spent 30 percent of its budget servicing a foreign debt of $122 billion -- up from 13 percent in 1996 -- at a time when revenues have shrunk because of the drop in world oil prices. The gross domestic product has stopped growing, he said, and almost one-third of all Russians are living at or below the poverty line.</p>
        <p>''Over the past half a year, the Government has said the economy is growing,'' he said. ''But why has not a single resident of the country felt this?''</p>
        <p>Such blunt talk was rarely heard from Mr. Chernomyrdin, the longtime Prime Minister whose ouster by Mr. Yeltsin remains a political puzzle in Moscow. Now a declared candidate for the presidential elections in 2000, Mr. Chernomyrdin, at a celebration on Thursday of his 60th birthday attended by both Mr. Yeltsin and Mr. Kiriyenko, told guests that he had no regrets. ''I never retreated, never betrayed anyone and always knew what I was doing and why,'' he said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
