<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Finding Equal Opportunity For the Musicians to Shine</title>
    <meta content="02JONE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Ideas/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/02/02/arts/dance/02JONE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1364239"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="DANCE REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Jones, Bill T/arnie Zane Dance Company</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kisselgoff, Anna</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dancing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jones, Bill T</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20020202T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07EFDE143DF931A35751C0A9649C8B63" item-length="807" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Finding Equal Opportunity For the Musicians to Shine</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Finding Equal Opportunity for the Musicians to Shine</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANNA KISSELGOFF</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Kisselgoff, Anna</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anna Kisselgoff reviews joint program presented by Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center and Bill T Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Co at Alice Tully Hall; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>At heart the experimental dance choreographer Bill T. Jones is a storyteller. His tales have included danced memoirs, but more often they are hermetic and buried within musical or theatrical images.</p>
        <p>On Thursday the enigma acquired a new and vibrant dimension in a joint evening presented by the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center and the Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company at Alice Tully Hall.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A joint evening presented by the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center and the Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company was advertised as a "visionary fusion of dance and music."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>At heart the experimental dance choreographer Bill T. Jones is a storyteller. His tales have included danced memoirs, but more often they are hermetic and buried within musical or theatrical images.</p>
        <p>On Thursday the enigma acquired a new and vibrant dimension in a joint evening presented by the Chamber Music Society of Lincoln Center and the Bill T. Jones/Arnie Zane Dance Company at Alice Tully Hall.</p>
        <p>The program, which runs through tomorrow with one different piece, was advertised as a ''visionary fusion of dance and music.'' Visionary was perhaps debatable. Mr. Jones's use of live musicians both onstage and in the pit for four dance premieres is part of an honored practice. But as a collaboration of a more earthly sort, the evening was a resounding success.</p>
        <p>Music and dance were indeed equal partners. The Orion String Quartet, the quartet in residence of the Chamber Music Society, was the featured musical attraction, although string players associated with the Society performed separately or with Orion.</p>
        <p>The two string quartets in the pit during ''Black Suzanne'' were on equal ground with Mr. Jones's explosive, brilliant choreography for jousting dancers in red gym suits on a red gym mat.</p>
        <p>The musicians countered with an exciting performance of Shostakovich's Prelude and Scherzo for String Octet (Op. 11).</p>
        <p>The experimental music of a modern composer, Gyorgy Kurtag, could have stolen the show with bits of short fragmentary phrases and silences. Mr. Jones's choreography, titled ''WorldWithout/In,'' met the challenge with a startling disassociation from the music.</p>
        <p>Instead of a severe streamlined play with form the piece was a theatrical fable for grotesque characters in masks. Two Kurtag compositions (String Quartet (Op. 1) and ''12 Microludes'' (Op. 13) were played by musicians incorporated into the choreography.</p>
        <p>The promised fusion was exemplified best in the program's first work, ''Verbum,'' to one of Beethoven's late quartets (Op. 135), played in the pit by Orion's members. They were Daniel Phillips, Todd Phillips (violins), Steve Tenenbom (viola) and Timothy Eddy (cello).</p>
        <p>What was originally billed as a musical interlude performed by Orion onstage was indeed a shimmering account by the quartet of two movements from Ravel's quartet in F. An unscheduled addition was an asymetrically shaped solo danced by Eric Bradley at the other side of the stage.</p>
        <p>In recent years Mr. Jones's dance vocabulary has become increasingly eclectic. His dancers have a natural look, and conventional steps are interpolated as unexpected throw-away lines.</p>
        <p>''Verbum'' uses a Latin title signifying word and activity. It sends its dancers wiggling and tumbling onstage early on. Bjorn Amelan's fine set consists of what could be three empty standing mirror frames. Robert Wierzel's silvery light on the frames echoes Liz Prince's silver jump suits for the dancers.</p>
        <p>Toshiko Oiwa, a slim woman with a propulsive dynamism, enters first, followed by seven dancers performing independently of one another until unexpected incidents occur: Ayo Janeen Jackson dives daringly into the hooplike arms of Daniel Russell Kubert. The frames are moved around, sometimes adding a thematic hint about illusion and reality.</p>
        <p>In the quiet third section, Ms. Oiwa's solo often keeps her with back to the audience. Finally she walks her fingers along an arm, her evocative dejection superseded by the merriment of the final section's headstands. The superb dancers included Mr. Bradley, Asli Bulbul, Leah Cox, Wen-Chung Lin and Malcom Low.</p>
        <p>Mr. Amelan's set for ''WorldWithout/In'' is a pyramid staircase with a flowery altar below. The musicians are in white: Ruggero Allifranchini and Timothy Fain, violinists; Sophie Shao, cellist; and Hsin-Yun Huang, a pregnant violist. All moved around the stage from time to time. Ms. Cox and Catherine Cabeen are the priestesses with Ms. Oiwa as the fox-masked goddess atop the steps.</p>
        <p>The characters, mainly masked, come and go. Ms. Bulbul is a greedy female dwarf, Ms. Jackson a troublemaker who drops dollar bills, Mr. Kubert a self-flagellating terrorist in a ski mask. However forced, this fantasy-ritual does not bore.</p>
        <p>''Black Suzanne'' has Ms. Jackson and Ms. Oiwa standing upright in the palms of opposing units.</p>
        <p>The zigzags of the music propel the dancers into a tournament with a variety of feats. An excellent work.</p>
        <p>The program, commissioned by the Chamber Music Society and Hancher Auditorium in Iowa City, will be repeated next Friday at Tilles Center in Greenvale on Long Island.</p>
        <p>DANCE REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
