<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Wealth of Talent, Dearth of Funds</title>
    <meta content="29WASH$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="BASEBALL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="933188"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">George Washington High School (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Glickson, Grant</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interscholastic Athletics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970529T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B06E5DA123AF93AA15756C0A961958260" item-length="1242" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Wealth of Talent, Dearth of Funds</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By GRANT GLICKSON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Glickson, Grant</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>George Washington High School baseball team is 40-2 this season and ranked No 1 in nation in Easton Sport Original National High School Poll; team, which began its playoff run by routing Columbus, 11-0, on May 27, is short of funds; players wear old uniforms, and they cannot afford to take batting practice because of lack of baseballs; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was just one play in a lopsided regular-season game, but it summed up the season for George Washington High School's baseball team.</p>
        <p>The Trojans were leading Stuyvesant, 9-0, in a game earlier this month when Vicente Rosario noticed that the Stuyvesant pitcher was slow in his delivery and the catcher was not paying much attention to him on third base. So on the next pitch, Rosario, who holds the national high school record for stolen bases in a season, broke for home plate and the batter, Sharbel Torres, leaped out of his way as Rosario slid in safely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was just one play in a lopsided regular-season game, but it summed up the season for George Washington High School's baseball team.</p>
        <p>The Trojans were leading Stuyvesant, 9-0, in a game earlier this month when Vicente Rosario noticed that the Stuyvesant pitcher was slow in his delivery and the catcher was not paying much attention to him on third base. So on the next pitch, Rosario, who holds the national high school record for stolen bases in a season, broke for home plate and the batter, Sharbel Torres, leaped out of his way as Rosario slid in safely.</p>
        <p>''Now that's rubbing it in just a little bit,'' the opposing first baseman told George Washington's first-base coach.</p>
        <p>Maybe so, but opponents of George Washington should be used to it by now. The school, located in the Washington Heights section of upper Manhattan, has been so dominating over the last three seasons -- posting a 120-9 record and winning by an average 11 runs a game -- that Coach Steve Mandl has been forced to use regular-season games to allow the players to work on their skills. Often he will pull his starters after only a few innings to avoid embarrassing the opposing team, but when the players are on the field, they are given the green light to swing away, steal bases, hit-and-run and light up the scoreboard.</p>
        <p>''I understand why people get upset,'' Mandl said. ''But I'm not doing it to rub anybody's face in the dirt. I have to get my team ready to try and win a championship. I need to know that my players can hit-and-run, bunt and steal home if I need them to. If they don't do it during the regular season, how do I know if they could do it in the playoffs?''</p>
        <p>George Washington, 40-2 and ranked No. 1 in the nation in the Easton Sport Original National High School Poll, began its playoff run on Tuesday by routing Columbus, 11-0. The Trojans, who will take on Morris (16-5) today, are determined to return to Shea Stadium on June 10 and avenge back-to-back losses to Tottenville in the Public School Athletic League final.</p>
        <p>''Losing the last two years gave us a lot of experience,'' Rosario said through an interpreter.''We feel we have the stuff to win a championship.''</p>
        <p>But while George Washington is rich in talent, the Washington Heights school struggles financially. The Trojans wear uniforms that are three years old, and they can not afford to take batting practice because of a lack of baseballs, which cost $60 a dozen and would require about 20 dozen ($1,200) to get through the season. They also play inferior local competition because they do not possess the funds to cover travel expenses to play a national schedule.</p>
        <p>George Washington had to turn down an invitation to the Dole Classic in California this year and will have to pass on a trip to the Powerade tournament in Florida next season unless it can raise $10,000 by the end of next month. The only fund- raising the team does is done by Mandl, who sends letters to alumni and old friends to solicit financial support.</p>
        <p>''We play so many games and a lot of these kids have to work to help support their families,'' Mandl explained. ''So I'm not going to ask them to spend their free time selling chocolate bars.''</p>
        <p>Manny Ramirez of the Cleveland Indians, George Washington's most famous recent player, provided the team with spikes and gloves (through his Nike contract) in the 1996 season and chose George Washington to be the recipient of a $1,000 donation for his part in a home run derby in the 1995 All-Star Game. Ramirez, who is in the second year of a four-year $10.15 million contract with the Indians, has yet to sign another deal with Nike. Meanwhile, George Washington still has not received spikes or batting gloves for the 1997 season and players are wearing the same uniforms that Ramirez provided them with in 1995.</p>
        <p>''I'm disappointed that he hasn't done more,'' Mandl said. ''But I also understand that he is being pulled from every direction. Everybody wants something from him: his time and his money.''</p>
        <p>Ramirez was not available for comment. But his agent, Jaime Torres, said: ''Nobody has ever asked Manny for any money or approached him about participating in any fund raisers. It's not a ballplayer's job to think of ways for a school to raise money. If someone was to approach him, I'm sure Manny would be happy to help them out.''</p>
        <p>On the team's threadbare Astroturf diamond, Washington's most sparkling jewel is Rosario, a 19-year-old center fielder who is projected as a first-round draft choice in Major League Baseball draft next Tuesday.</p>
        <p>In a baseball season that is celebrating the 50th anniversary of Jackie Robinson, Mandl has nicknamed Rosario ''Jackie'' for his aggressive style of play and his penchant for stealing home. The 5-foot-11-inch, 180-pound Rosario has scored five runs that way this season and three last year. Rosario, who came to New York from the Dominican Republic four years ago, stole 81 bases this season as George Washington stole 315 bases over all in 42 games. In 1996 he stole 96 bases, shattering the national record..</p>
        <p>In four seasons Rosario, a switch hitter, has hit .518, with 41 home runs, 179 runs batted in and 213 stolen bases.</p>
        <p>''I like to steal home the best because it motivates me,'' Rosario said. ''I have it in my blood.''</p>
        <p>Joining Rosario in the outfield are two talented juniors.</p>
        <p>In right field, Junior Ramirez, 17, no relation to Manny, arrived on the national scene last summer as a member of Team USA in the Goodwill Games in Australia. Scouts were impressed with Ramirez's exceptional bat speed, power potential, speed on the base paths, range in the outfield and strong arm. Ramirez enters today's playoff game batting .486, with 8 homers, 27 r.b.i. and 24 stolen bases.</p>
        <p>In left field, Evaristo Torres, 17, also gained national acclaim in the Goodwill Games last summer. Torres is a line-drive hitter, with quick hands and fast feet.</p>
        <p>''Our outfield is the best in the city,'' Torres said. ''Every one of us wants to make the play.''</p>
        <p>However, no matter how good the Trojans' outfield stacks up against the rest of the city, George Washington knows well that the P.S.A.L. title will be won on the mound. And Washington has two of the best righty-lefty throwers in the area. Enmanuel Ulloa, a 6-2, 190-pound right-hander, was outdueled two seasons ago in the final by Tottensville's Paul Stabile.</p>
        <p>Last year, Manuel Olivera, a 5-10, 186-pound lefty, was bested by the Atlanta Braves' first-round pick, Jason Marquis, who struck out 15 enroute to a 5-1 triumph.</p>
        <p>Both George Washington pitchers are confident that they will win this time.</p>
        <p>''We have the fire in us to win that final game,'' Olivera said. ''We've worked hard to make that happpen.''</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
