<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rookie Propels Liberty to No. 2 Seeding</title>
    <meta content="20LIBE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/20/sports/basketball/20liberty.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1612987"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="PRO BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Liberty</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Mystics</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Williams, Lena</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Liberty</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Washington Mystics</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040920T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B02E1DC1539F933A1575AC0A9629C8B63" item-length="476" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rookie Propels Liberty to No. 2 Seeding</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Liberty's Top Draft Pick Gets It Done</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LENA WILLIAMS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Williams, Lena</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Liberty defeats Washington Mystics, 79-75 (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The smile on Shameka Christon's face said it all yesterday.</p>
        <p>Christon, a relatively unknown player from the University of Arkansas, showed the 15,698 fans at Madison Square Garden why the Liberty had made her the team's No. 1 draft pick.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Shameka Christon scored a career-high 18 points to help the Liberty clinch the No. 2 playoff seeding in the Eastern Conference.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The smile on Shameka Christon's face said it all yesterday.</p>
        <p>Christon, a relatively unknown player from the University of Arkansas, showed the 15,698 fans at Madison Square Garden why the Liberty had made her the team's No. 1 draft pick.</p>
        <p>With her mentor, forward Crystal Robinson, on the bench for most of the second half with a sprained right big toe, Christon scored a career-high 18 points to help the Liberty clinch the No. 2 playoff seeding in the Eastern Conference and homecourt advantage in the first round with a 79-75 victory over the Washington Mystics.</p>
        <p>Having vacated Madison Square Garden because of the Republican National Convention, the Liberty played its first game there after going 5-1 at Radio City Music Hall.</p>
        <p>The Liberty will open the two-of-three-game series against the Detroit Shock, the defending champion, in Auburn Hills, Mich., on Friday. Game 2 will be Sunday at the Garden.</p>
        <p>Game 3, if necessary, will be played Tuesday at the Garden.</p>
        <p>The loss was the Mystics' first in four games against the Liberty this season and dropped them to the fourth seeding.</p>
        <p>Christon, who wears No. 20, was nearly upstaged by another No. 20, Alana Beard, the player Christon affectionately refers to as her high school nemesis.</p>
        <p>Beard, the Mystics' No. 1 draft pick and the former Duke star, scored 21 of her game-high 23 points in the second half.</p>
        <p>Beard scored 19 of the Mystics' first 21 points after intermission.</p>
        <p>It was a battle between teams that have faced adversity: the Liberty fired Coach Richie Adubato at the beginning of July, and the Mystics lost the All-Star forward Chamique Holdsclaw to an undisclosed illness.</p>
        <p>The game was close down the stretch, but Becky Hammon hit a 3-pointer with 35 seconds left and added a foul shot with 26 seconds remaining.</p>
        <p>Hammon finished with 18 points, Elena Baranova had 16 points and Bethany Donaphin added 10.</p>
        <p>After the game, Robinson beamed with pride at Christon's big game.</p>
        <p>''My protégé,'' she said, nodding in Christon's direction. ''If I had as much athletic ability like Shameka. Wow. She is going to be great.''</p>
        <p>Christon, who has averaged 4.8 points and 16 minutes a game this season, saved her best game for last. Throughout the season, Christon, a 6-foot-1 forward, had shown only flashes of the scoring ability that had propelled her to second on the Arkansas career list with 1,951 points. ''Blaze always told me, 'Shameka this is a simple game,''' Christon said, referring to Carol Blazejowski, the senior vice president and general manager for the Liberty.</p>
        <p>''I think I put too much pressure on myself. Thinking I had to do the same thing I did at Arkansas, being the biggest scorer. My teammates and coaches told me to have that confidence and to play within myself. Today I was able to do that.''</p>
        <p>PRO BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
