<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Broad Changes Sought to Solve Hospital Crisis</title>
    <meta content="14hospitals" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Health; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/07/14/nyregion/14hospitals.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1687252"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Healthcare</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Transplants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hospitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New York State</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Health Department</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Pataki, George E</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Gottfried, Richard N</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20050714T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C04E1DF1330F937A25754C0A9639C8B63" item-length="1129" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Broad Changes Sought to Solve Hospital Crisis</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Closings Alone Won't Solve Hospitals' Troubles, Panel's Chairman Says</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARC SANTORA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A commission created by New York State to reorganize its hospital system took a broad view of its mandate yesterday at its first meeting, with its chairman saying that simply closing down hospitals would not be enough to solve the current financial crisis.</p>
        <p>Although the commission will almost certainly recommend widespread closings, the chairman, Stephen Berger, said it would also look at consolidating areas of specialty in certain hospitals to provide more expertise and to prevent duplication of care, even if doing so means more travel for patients. In the past, health officials have tried to confine certain procedures like organ transplants to specific hospitals, but a variety of issues, including patient demand, made that goal hard to achieve.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Although the commission will almost certainly recommend widespread closings, its chairman said it would also look at consolidating areas of specialty in certain hospitals.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A commission created by New York State to reorganize its hospital system took a broad view of its mandate yesterday at its first meeting, with its chairman saying that simply closing down hospitals would not be enough to solve the current financial crisis.</p>
        <p>Although the commission will almost certainly recommend widespread closings, the chairman, Stephen Berger, said it would also look at consolidating areas of specialty in certain hospitals to provide more expertise and to prevent duplication of care, even if doing so means more travel for patients. In the past, health officials have tried to confine certain procedures like organ transplants to specific hospitals, but a variety of issues, including patient demand, made that goal hard to achieve.</p>
        <p>He said the panel would also consider changing the way hospitals are reimbursed by public and private insurance programs, hoping to even out the wide variations in the amounts paid for specific procedures.</p>
        <p>''I assume we will have hospital closings,'' Mr. Berger said in an interview. ''But the answer is not just closing institutions. It is restructuring the delivery of health care.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger, a former executive director of the Port Authority of New York and New Jersey, said the panel will look broadly at the general structure of hospitals, suggesting that not every function needs to be available under a single roof. Instead, he said, the responsibilities of some hospitals could be narrowed into ambulatory care centers or other roles.</p>
        <p>The commission was established to make hard choices for the hospital system, which has been plagued by financial difficulties. Much like a federal commission on the closing of military bases, it is intended to recommend which hospitals are no longer necessary, a politically charged task that lawmakers have traditionally been loath to undertake. It will also examine nursing home finances.</p>
        <p>The recommendations are to be made by December 2006. Gov. George E. Pataki, who appointed the majority of the commission, and the Legislature would have to approve the proposals before they could become law. Suggestions that are accepted are supposed to be carried out by 2008.</p>
        <p>Any recommendations will be made only after more than a year of meetings and studies. Since the hospital industry is the state's largest business, significant proposals are likely to be bitterly disputed.</p>
        <p>If the commission does take on some of the underlying causes of the financial crisis New York's hospitals find themselves in, the results could drastically change the way health care is delivered.</p>
        <p>Mr. Berger is no stranger to dealing with complicated and troubled financial institutions. During the height of New York's financial crisis in 1976 and 1977, he was responsible for supervising the city's budget and helped devise a plan to get the city back into the credit markets.</p>
        <p>There has been skepticism about the commission's goals and its ability to change the system. Some politicians and advocates for the poor and uninsured have expressed concern that the commission will ultimately eviscerate hospitals in financially troubled sections of the state and New York City.</p>
        <p>Assemblyman Richard N. Gottfried, a Manhattan Democrat and chairman of the Health Committee, was actively involved in setting up the commission but said he doubted it would tackle the system's underlying problems. ''I don't think they see those issues as being on their agenda,'' he said, predicting the group would primarily help to close unnecessary hospitals.</p>
        <p>Judy Wessler, the director of the Commission on the Public's Health System, an advocacy group, said she was nervous about the state commission's intentions.</p>
        <p>At the commission's meeting yesterday in Harlem, she watched as its members discussed the four large books of data they had been given by the Health Department. When one panelist explained that only one of the thousands of pages presented dealt with the large number of uninsured people in the state, she scoffed. ''This is not about people,'' she said.</p>
        <p>But no one doubts that the industry is in crisis. Last week, the state's largest Catholic hospital system, Saint Vincent, sought bankruptcy protection after years of heavy losses. In a rare sign of unity, politicians, the health care unions and the industry were all in agreement on the need to form a commission and possibly close hospitals. Because of that agreement, the commission has been given wide latitude in the areas it can delve into.</p>
        <p>The state also has a large pot of cash available to make its recommendations reality. This year's state budget has $1 billion set aside to reorganize health care facilities. Governor Pataki is also hoping to receive $1.5 billion more from the federal government for the same purpose.</p>
        <p>As a result, many in the field say they believe the commission's work could be a defining moment.</p>
        <p>''There is no single body that we have seen of recent vintage that has been dedicated to a holistic view of the health care system,'' said Kenneth E. Raske, the president of the Greater New York Hospital Association. ''This is a real opportunity to tackle some of those thorny issues that have not been addressed.''</p>
        <p>But he cautioned that if it was not careful, the commission could do more harm than good. ''If you have incomplete knowledge, you will not only have incomplete answers, you will have wrong answers,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Dennis Whalen, executive deputy commissioner of the State Health Department, said it had been decades since the state appointed an independent body with such broad reach. He compared it to the Folsom commission, appointed in the 1960's by Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller. That commission's work led to major changes in hospital financing, including one that put hospitals under the Health Department's authority.</p>
        <p>''This commission will be dealing with just as an important a set of issues,'' he said in an interview.</p>
        <p>One of the most important and complex areas to be addressed by the panel involves the state formulas under which hospitals are reimbursed for their work by public and private insurance. Mr. Berger called the reimbursement system ''cockeyed,'' saying it made no sense for hospitals to receive $30,000 for a procedure that used to be rare but is now common, while other common medical problems that send people to emergency rooms bring minimal reimbursements.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
