<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>At an industry gathering, the emphasis is on reasserting the power of brand-name products.</title>
    <meta content="14ADCO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2002" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/10/14/business/14ADCO.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1431866"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2002"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Association of National Advertisers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Marketing and Merchandising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Generic and Brand Name Products</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Association of National Advertisers</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Deutsch, Donny</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20021014T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E7D8103AF937A25753C1A9649C8B63" item-length="1101" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>At an industry gathering, the emphasis is on reasserting the power of brand-name products.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Emphasis Urged on Pushing Brands</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <dateline>NAPLES, Fla.</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Anxiety among consumer marketers over sputtering economy is evident at annual meeting of Association of National Advertisers, Naples, Fla; speakers offer unusually-frank admonitions to concentrate scarce corporate resources on reasserting power of name-brand products (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE anxiety among consumer marketers over the sputtering economy was palpable throughout the 2002 annual meeting of the Association of National Advertisers here, as speaker after speaker offered unusually frank admonitions to concentrate scarce corporate resources on reasserting the power of name-brand products.</p>
        <p>''Too much marketing is done by rank amateurs,'' said Charles B. Strauss, chairman of the Unilever North American division of Unilever, in a speech at the conference, which began on Thursday and ended Sunday, and as a result ''so many companies have mismanaged their brands.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anxiety among consumer marketers over the economy was palpable throughout an industry gathering that reasserted the power of brand-name products.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE anxiety among consumer marketers over the sputtering economy was palpable throughout the 2002 annual meeting of the Association of National Advertisers here, as speaker after speaker offered unusually frank admonitions to concentrate scarce corporate resources on reasserting the power of name-brand products.</p>
        <p>''Too much marketing is done by rank amateurs,'' said Charles B. Strauss, chairman of the Unilever North American division of Unilever, in a speech at the conference, which began on Thursday and ended Sunday, and as a result ''so many companies have mismanaged their brands.''</p>
        <p>''In a more demanding world, our brands must become stronger and more valuable,'' he added. ''We must focus our very best talents on our very best brands.''</p>
        <p>To that end, Unilever is culling its myriad product lines, Mr. Strauss said, to 400 brands from 1,600, with ''my best guess, an eventual focus on 200.'' Among the survivors in the United States are All, Dove, Q-Tips and Wisk, but among the casualties are two of Unilever's oldest soap brands, Lifebuoy and Lux, both formerly heralded by classic ad campaigns that demonized ''B.O.,'' for the body odor that Lifebuoy fought and lionized Hollywood stars for their Lux complexions.</p>
        <p>''We're very pragmatic,'' Mr. Strauss said, particularly in trying to balance the benefits of scale of selling brands globally with the familiarity with consumers achieved by brands marketed locally.</p>
        <p>''The goal is global knowledge being applied to satisfy local consumer needs,'' he added, and ''we say to our agencies, 'We want the clout that comes with global brands and the relevant intimacy the strongest local brands have.' ''</p>
        <p>Mr. Strauss's speech was among the best-received by attendees of the conference, which was the 92nd annual meeting of the association, the trade organization for major marketers. Reflecting the skittish feelings about the econony, attendance, initially estimated at 400, was actually closer to 250; there were 220 people at the opening dinner on Thursday.</p>
        <p>Whatever the number, those marketers who did attend represented some of the nation's largest spenders on advertising and promotion, including AT&amp;T, ConAgra, Johnson &amp; Johnson, Kraft Foods, Procter &amp; Gamble, Wendy's International and the Wm. Wrigley Jr. Company.</p>
        <p>Two other speakers with messages of tough love also came from the ranks of those major marketers, in effect putting their ad dollars where their mouths are. They were Douglas R. Conant, president and chief executive of the Campbell Soup Company, and Thomas G. Stemberg, chairman of Staples, the office supply retailer.</p>
        <p>''Today's market place is more Darwinian than ever before,'' said Mr. Conant, who spoke from the experience earned by grappling with continued sluggish sales of Campbell's flagship brand, its condensed soups with the red-and-white labels. ''You either differentiate or die; there really is no in-between.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Conant acknowledged that Campbell had ''lost our competitive edge'' and outlined a four-step, three-year ''transformation'' plan undertaken in July 2001. The plan, whose eventual success or failure Wall Street is following closely, includes what Mr. Conant described as ''a significant increase in reseach and development financing, because quite frankly we had allowed competitors to narrow the gap in quality'' between their brands and Campbell's, as well as a ''major increase'' in advertising and promotional spending.</p>
        <p>In some instances, Mr. Conant said, the plan is already yielding results, listing among them increased sales of the Campbell's Chunky and Campbell's Select soup brands as a result of campaigns that ''sharply delineated to consumers'' the attributes of those products like improved ingredients and redesigned packaging. The company has high hopes for new products, he added, like Soup at Hand, sold in heat-and-serve microwaveable cups, and ''we are moving forward confidently in the upcoming soup season.''</p>
        <p>Still, Mr. Conant confessed, ''we do have more work to do'' on the mainline red-and-white soups, promising that significant changes in that brand ''will flow into the market in the next 18 months.'' Whether impatient investors and hungry competitors will allow the company's ambitious efforts to come to a boil, or yank the pot off the stove before it heats up, remains to be seen.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stemberg, in his speech, outlined the aggressive steps being taken to remake the Staples brand as rivals like Office Depot and Office Max -- not to mention Wal-Mart, warehouse chains and even supermarkets and drug stores -- co-opt its original differentiating selling point to customers, lower prices.</p>
        <p>Because ''everybody's got low prices,'' Mr. Stemberg said, ''we're now going to appeal to the consumer's need for simplicity, convenience and an effortless shopping experience, and take a much more empathetic tone.''</p>
        <p>That change of voice, though still ''leavened with traditional Staples humor,'' reflects the ''kinder, more compassionate'' approach consumers insist on, he added, after the scandals stemming from ''the petty greed of a few C.E.O.'s that has humiliated all of corporate America'' and eroded their trust in what companies tell them.</p>
        <p>Mr. Stemberg showed two humorous new Staples commercials meant to convey that ''we appreciate, we know, we understand that saving time is as important as saving money,'' he said, which represents ''a greater risk'' than simply promising lower prices because ''we're asking our customers to have faith we'll not disappoint them on immeasurables that are not easily checked on like low prices.''</p>
        <p>To assure that ''the expectations we raise must be met,'' Mr. Stemberg said, Staples is backing the brand makeover with a chainwide program called ''Back to Brighton'' after its first store in Brighton, Mass. The program includes time-saving steps like ''four ordering stations'' in each store, he added, linked to the Staples Web site (www.staples.com), so that shoppers can order online any merchandise they do not find in stock and have it ''delivered free the next day.''</p>
        <p>The speaker who made the attendees laugh most was Donny Deutsch, representing the point of view of the Madison Avenue agencies that they hire. Mr. Deutsch, chairman and chief executive at Deutsch in New York, part of the Partnership division of the Interpublic Group of Companies, offered marketers 16 rules he would follow ''if I were a client.''</p>
        <p>Here are some of the Deutsch dictates:</p>
        <p>*''If you cannot look in a mirror and say you have the best marketing thinking in your competitive set, if someone else is doing it better, fire your agency and hire theirs.''</p>
        <p>*''Creative awards are immaterial and stupid because great work is work that moves your business.''</p>
        <p>*''Beware of the schmooze. If your agency is schmoozing you, it's probably not that good. Take that out of the equation. Say, 'Let's spend the time working.' ''</p>
        <p>*''If you're not having fun with your agency, find another agency.''</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
