<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TRANSACTIONS</title>
    <meta content="06TRAN$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1000142"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">List</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980306T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D06E3D61E31F935A35750C0A96E958260" item-length="784" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TRANSACTIONS</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BALTIMORE ORIOLES -- Reassigned C Charles Alley, RHP Kevin Gallagher, INF David Lamb, OF Daell McDonald, LHP John Parrish, RHP Francisco Saneaux and C Jayson Werth to their minor-league camp.  MINNESOTA TWINS -- Renewed the contract of OF Matt Lawton. Agreed to terms with RHP LaTroy Hawkins, LHP Travis Miller, RHP Dan Naulty, RHP Todd Ritchie, INF Denny Hocking and OF Alex Ochoa.  YANKEES -- Renewed the contracts of SS Derek Jeter, RHP Mariano Rivera and C Jorge Posada. Agreed to terms with RHP Ramiro Mendoza on a one-year contract.  TRONTO BLUE JAYS -- Renewed the contracts of RHP Robert Person and RHP Chris Carpenter. Agreed to terms with OF Jose Cruz Jr. and OF Robert Perez on one-year conracts. Reassigned RHP Billy Koch, RHP Mark Sievert, RHP Shannon Withem, INF Jeff Patzke, INF Santiago Henry, INF Jossephang Bernhardt and C Luis Rodriguez to their minor-league camp.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
        <p>American League  BALTIMORE ORIOLES -- Reassigned C Charles Alley, RHP Kevin Gallagher, INF David Lamb, OF Daell McDonald, LHP John Parrish, RHP Francisco Saneaux and C Jayson Werth to their minor-league camp.  MINNESOTA TWINS -- Renewed the contract of OF Matt Lawton. Agreed to terms with RHP LaTroy Hawkins, LHP Travis Miller, RHP Dan Naulty, RHP Todd Ritchie, INF Denny Hocking and OF Alex Ochoa.  YANKEES -- Renewed the contracts of SS Derek Jeter, RHP Mariano Rivera and C Jorge Posada. Agreed to terms with RHP Ramiro Mendoza on a one-year contract.  TRONTO BLUE JAYS -- Renewed the contracts of RHP Robert Person and RHP Chris Carpenter. Agreed to terms with OF Jose Cruz Jr. and OF Robert Perez on one-year conracts. Reassigned RHP Billy Koch, RHP Mark Sievert, RHP Shannon Withem, INF Jeff Patzke, INF Santiago Henry, INF Jossephang Bernhardt and C Luis Rodriguez to their minor-league camp.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
        <p>National Basketball Association  PORTLAND TRAIL BLAZERS -- Waived F Dontonio Wingfield. Signed G Gary Grant to a 10-day contract. Placed G Vincent Askew on the injured list.</p>
        <p>FOOTBALL</p>
        <p>National Football League  ATLANTA FALCONS -- Signed QB Eric Zeier to an offer sheet.  BUFFALO BILLS -- Signed RB Sam Gash to a three-year contract.  MIAMI DOLPHINS -- Re-signed QB Craig Erickson to a two-year contract.  NEW ORLEANS SAINTS -- Traded CB Eric Allen to the Oakland Raiders for an undisclosed 1998 draft pick.  SAN FRANCISCO 49ERS -- Announced the retirement of OL Kirk Scrafford.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
        <p>National Hockey League  NHL -- Suspended Philadelphia Flyers F Daniel Lacroix for three games and fined him $1,000 for a cross-check against New York Islanders D Rich Pilon in a March 3 game.  ANAHEIM MIGHTY DUCKS -- Assigned LW Kevin Todd to Long Beach of the IHL. Recalled RW Frank Banham and LW Mike Leclerc from Cincinnati of the AHL.  COLORADO AVALANCHE -- Assigned RW Christian Matte to Hershey of the AHL.  EDMONTON OILERS -- Assigned D Scott Ferguson and D Craig Millar to Hamilton of the AHL.  PHILADELPHIA FLYERS -- Recalled RW John Druce from Philadelphia of the AHL.  VANCOUVER CANUCKS -- Reassigned LW Darren Sinclair to Raleigh of the ECHL.</p>
        <p>SOCCER</p>
        <p>Major League Soccer  MLS -- Allocated MF Marquinho to the Colorado Rapids.</p>
        <p>COLLEGE</p>
        <p>AKRON -- Named Bob Morris passing-game coordinator and Joe Palmisano defensive coordinator.  ARMY -- Announced the resignation of Lynn Chiavaro, women's basketball coach.  CHOWAN -- Named Steve Lee football coach.  FLORIDA STATE -- Announced G Devonaire Deas has left the men's basketball team.  HOLY CROSS -- Named Richard M. Regan Jr. athletics director, effective July 1.  NORTH TEXAS -- Named Bruce Bell running backs coach.  PURDUE -- Named Lori Litzelman athletic promotions coordinator.  SOUTHERN METHODIST -- Named Greg Briner offensive coordinator and quarterbacks coach; Eric Schumann assistant head football coach, defensive coordinator and secondary coach; Randy Williams offensive line coach and recruiting coordinator; and Warren Belin and Derek Dooley assistant recruiting coordinators.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
