<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>PREMIER OF INDIA MEETS SIKH LEADER</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="411596"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDEPENDENCE MOVEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SIKHS (SECT)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">INDIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PUNJAB STATE (INDIA)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHEKHAR, CHANDRA (PRIME MIN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MANN, SIMRANJIT SINGH</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/India</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sikhs (Sect)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Religion and Churches</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901229T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE2DB1438F93AA15751C1A966958260" item-length="679" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>PREMIER OF INDIA MEETS SIKH LEADER</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BARBARA CROSSETTE, Special to The New York Times</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">CROSSETTE, BARBARA</byline>
      <dateline>NEW DELHI, Dec. 28</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Prime Minister Chandra Shekhar, looking for a political formula for containing a spreading separatist movement in Punjab, met tonight with an increasingly radical Sikh political leader who believes he can serve as a bridge to armed militants.</p>
        <p>The Punjabi leader, Simranjit Singh Mann, is the spokesman for several major factions of the only nonviolent political movement with any influence left in Punjab State, the Sikhs' Akali Party. About 3,800 people have died in violence in the state this year in connection with a campaign for more autonomy or independence.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Prime Minister Chandra Shekhar, looking for a political formula for containing a spreading separatist movement in Punjab, met tonight with an increasingly radical Sikh political leader who believes he can serve as a bridge to armed militants.</p>
        <p>The Punjabi leader, Simranjit Singh Mann, is the spokesman for several major factions of the only nonviolent political movement with any influence left in Punjab State, the Sikhs' Akali Party. About 3,800 people have died in violence in the state this year in connection with a campaign for more autonomy or independence.</p>
        <p>The Akali Party had until this week been badly divided and under increasing pressure from underground militant leaders who want it to declare an independent Khalistan, or Sikh homeland. Mr. Mann, who was chosen spokesman for several of the Akali factions this week, resigned his seat in Parliament this year because he was not allowed to carry a large Sikh sword called the kirpan, into the house, and refused to exchange it for a permissible one that is smaller.</p>
        <p>No details of the talks were available from either side tonight.</p>
        <p>In an interview this afternoon before meeting with Mr. Shekhar, Mr. Mann, a former police officer who left government service after Indian troops invaded the Sikhs' Golden Temple in the city of Amritsar in June 1984, said "self-determination" was his goal in the talks. But he said that that could be accomplished "within the ambits of the Indian Constitution." Threats by Militants</p>
        <p>"The whole gamut of Hindu-Sikh relations must be discussed," Mr. Mann said. "If we make a breakthrough, then the militants can be called in."</p>
        <p>In the last month, Punjabi separatists in shadowy underground organizations have demanded that they no longer be called terrorists in the press, have begun to threaten government employees who do not use the Punjabi language and have ordered women to wear traditional Punjabi dress -- a long overblouse, baggy trousers and a shawl.</p>
        <p>India's national news agency, the Press Trust of India, now calls them militants. After the assassination of a radio station director in Punjab, most Indian radio and television broadcasters have also adopted the new terminology.</p>
        <p>Mr. Mann, who was imprisoned for five years during the administration of Prime Minister Rajiv Gandhi on vague charges that were suddenly dropped as Mr. Gandhi left office, today accused the Indian Army of "surrounding Punjabi villages" in recent weeks. Concessions Are Opposed</p>
        <p>"They are searching the haystacks, and billeting their troops in our schools and hospitals," he said, adding that under those circumstances there were reservations about talking with the Government.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Shekhar has the confidence of many Sikhs because he was forthright in his criticism of Prime Minister Indira Gandhi's decision to invade the Golden Temple in search of armed militants. Sikhs assassinated her four months later.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Shekhar, heading a very unstable minority Government that is under attack from almost all sides on a variety of issues, will have trouble getting a national consensus on a political solution for Punjab if it involves -- or is seen to involve -- any concessions to a religious minority.</p>
        <p>Tonight the Bharatiya Janata Party, which is now regarded as the voice of an aroused Hindu majority, cautioned the Government against any attempt to "go beyond the Constitution" in finding a solution.</p>
        <p>A party member in the upper house of Parliament said that any move toward autonomy in Punjab would not be acceptable.</p>
        <p>Militant Hindu organizations that back the Bharatiya Janata Party are keeping pressure on the Government not to concede anything to Muslim Kashmiris or to the defenders of the Babri Masjid, a mosque in the holy city of Ayodhya that Hindus want to pull down to build a temple to the mythological god-king Rama.</p>
        <p>Today, the Vishwa Hindu Parishad, which is leading the temple campaign, dismissed out of hand a collection of documents it had been given to study by a Muslim committee attempting to disprove Hindu claims to the site.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
