<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Boy's Parents Threatening To File Suit Vs. Coach</title>
    <meta content="01TEAM" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/03/01/nyregion/01TEAM.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1468681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Washington Township (NJ)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hanley, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Branco, Cheryl</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Branco, Joseph</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Branco, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Branco, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Selby, Steve</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coaches and Managers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE3D7103CF932A35750C0A9659C8B63" item-length="529" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Boy's Parents Threatening To File Suit Vs. Coach</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Boy's Parents Threatening to File Suit Vs. Coach</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT HANLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hanley, Robert</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Cheryl and Joseph Branco, parents of Washington Township High School (NJ) student David Branco, threaten to sue basketball coach Steve Selby for not allowing son to play on school's basketball team when he is good enough to play for Amateur Athletic Union all-star team; Brancos contend that Selby is punishing David for complaints they filed about coach's treatment of his athletes when their older son Joe played on team (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Branco started playing basketball in second grade. Now 15 and 6-foot-3, he has a substitute's role on a polished Amateur Athletic Union all-star team that has played in recent months in Las Vegas, Atlanta and Canada. Yet he has failed to make his high school basketball team in Washington Township, N.J., in both his freshman and sophomore years.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Flemming, superintendent of schools in Washington Township, a Gloucester County community about 10 miles southeast of Camden, said the explanation was simple.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>David Branco started playing basketball in second grade. Now 15 and 6-foot-3, he has a substitute's role on a polished Amateur Athletic Union all-star team that has played in recent months in Las Vegas, Atlanta andCanada. Yet he has failed to make his high school basketball team in Washington Township, N.J., in both his freshman and sophomore years.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>David Branco started playing basketball in second grade. Now 15 and 6-foot-3, he has a substitute's role on a polished Amateur Athletic Union all-star team that has played in recent months in Las Vegas, Atlanta and Canada. Yet he has failed to make his high school basketball team in Washington Township, N.J., in both his freshman and sophomore years.</p>
        <p>Thomas J. Flemming, superintendent of schools in Washington Township, a Gloucester County community about 10 miles southeast of Camden, said the explanation was simple.</p>
        <p>''The competition is very keen,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Wrong, said David's mother, Cheryl, who is vice president of the town's school board. She said her son had been cut by a vindictive head coach with a personal vendetta against her.</p>
        <p>The disagreement has set off an unusual legal wrangle that runs deeper than the customary parental grumbling about a coach's decision.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Branco and her husband, Joseph, have filed a formal notice threatening to sue the coach, Steve Selby, the school board, and the school district for violating their son's civil rights, causing him emotional distress and harming his chances of playing basketball in college.</p>
        <p>The document said Coach Selby's only reason for cutting David was to gain revenge for Mrs. Branco's complaints to the school board about his coaching style when her older son, Joe, played on the Washington Township High School team in the late 1990's.</p>
        <p>''There was constant verbal abuse,'' she said this week. ''I could not allow this treatment of kids to continue. It wasn't just my son. It was everybody's son. It was a very nasty environment. I'm sure I'll look bad in the newspapers. But I did the right thing.''</p>
        <p>Customarily, superintendents or high school athletic directors handle parents' complaints about coaches, said Boyd A. Sands, executive director of the New Jersey State Interscholastic Athletic Association. ''As far as we know, nothing has ever reached the level this case seems to be reaching,'' Mr. Sands said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Branco said a final decision whether to sue for financial damages would be made in coming weeks.</p>
        <p>Because of the possibility of legal action, Mr. Flemming, the superintendent, said only he, and not Mr. Selby, could talk publicly about the case. Over the last five years, Mr. Flemming said, he and a previous superintendent have reviewed Mrs. Branco's complaints about verbal abuse and found no reason to take action against Mr. Selby, Washington High's coach for 15 years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Flemming called Mrs. Branco's new argument about a vendetta groundless. ''If it does go to court, it will be found without merit,'' he said.</p>
        <p>The team's current record is 8-15. Mrs. Branco said she and her husband believe that David, now a sophomore, could have helped the team.</p>
        <p>For now, she said, he is playing in a recreational league, averaging 17 points a game, and preparing for another season with the A.A.U. team, called the Gym Rats.</p>
        <p>Why fret, then, about David's lost chance with the high school team?</p>
        <p>''High school still helps,'' she replied. ''It keeps him in shape all season, and it gives him exposure.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
