<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Stage, and Off</title>
    <meta content="21BROA" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="21" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="On Stage, and Off" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="910281"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="On Stage, and Off"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Actors Studio Free Theater</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Theater Workshop</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Actors Equity</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Penn, Arthur</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Larson, Jonathan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mcteer, Janet</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ibsen, Henrik (1828-1906)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Rent (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Doll's House, A (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features/People/Henrik Ibsen</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970221T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9903EFD8143EF932A15751C0A961958260" item-length="1109" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Stage, and Off</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>London production of A Doll's House to open on Broadway following successful negotiations with Actors' Equity; Janet McTeer stars; her photo; cast of Rent to perform songs by the musical's composer, the late Jonathan Larson, to benefit New York Theater Workshop; Arthur Penn, president of Actors Studio, has created new theater company, Actors Studio Free Theater, to produce six new plays annually (On Stage, and Off column) (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>From the West End, With a Snag</p>
        <p>Like a supplicant hoping to get into a hot nightclub, the London production of ''A Doll's House'' has survived the cool, appraising look and made it past the doorman. It's in, but just barely.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>From the West End, With a Snag</p>
        <p>Like a supplicant hoping to get into a hot nightclub, the London production of ''A Doll's House'' has survived the cool, appraising look and made it past the doorman. It's in, but just barely.</p>
        <p>The play, which begins an 18-week run at the Belasco Theater on March 26, won rapturous reviews in London. Its star, Janet McTeer, who plays Nora opposite Owen Teale (Torvald), John Carlisle (Dr. Rank) and Peter Gowen (Nils Krogstad), won an Olivier Award for best actress, and yesterday, the same distinction from the Critics'  Circle in London..</p>
        <p>Bill Kenwright, who had brought ''Blood Brothers,'' ''Medea'' and ''An Ideal Husband'' from London, anticipated an easy move this time under the exchange program established by Actors Equity and British Equity in the early 1980's to guarantee an equal balance of trade. After all, ''An Ideal Husband'' breezed in under the program. So did ''Stanley,'' now at Circle in the Square with four undeniably English stars.</p>
        <p>''A Doll's House'' ran into trouble, however, underscoring the still-touchy nature of the special relationship between Broadway and the West End. In theory, producers can bring in a play with British actors who do not qualify as stars (a separate category) if they agree to provide American actors the same number of roles in Britain, in the same kind of production, for the same length of time, at Broadway pay scales.</p>
        <p>Since 1981, more than 100 actors have been involved in the British-American exchange program, and 20 in other parts of the world, accounting for about 3,000 workweeks on each side of the Atlantic.</p>
        <p>Actors Equity twice rejected Mr. Kenwright's proposal to bring the play in and guarantee three exchange roles for Americans. (Ms. McTeer holds a green card and does not require Equity's permission to work in the United States.) The matter went to Equity's executive council before Ibsen got the green light.</p>
        <p>''It's very difficult to know how Equity will react,'' said Stuart Thompson, the general manager of ''An Ideal Husband'' and ''A Doll's House.'' ''With 'An Ideal Husband,' permission was granted in one letter.'' This time around, the negotiations were ''surprisingly protracted,'' Mr. Thompson said.</p>
        <p>It was somewhat familiar territory for Mr. Thompson, who encountered Equity resistance to ''Skylight'' when the play's star, Michael Gambon, insisted on bringing Lia Williams, his co-star.</p>
        <p>With ''A Doll's House,'' Equity played the Norwegian card. ''We said, 'Why do you need three English actors to play ''A Doll's House,'' which is not indigenous to your country?' '' said Alan Eisenberg, the executive director of Actors Equity. ''Stanley,'' Mr. Eisenberg said, was specifically English, a fact that Equity took into account in approving an exchange.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Kenwright and Mr. Thompson had some arguments of their own. ''A Doll's House'' would provide about a dozen Equity jobs for American actors and 18 weeks of work for other Americans at a theater that would otherwise be dark. ''They said they were not going to bring it in,'' Mr. Eisenberg said. ''We deferred.''</p>
        <p>The Star, on Her Role</p>
        <p>Ms. McTeer, an imposing six-footer, arrived at the role a little reluctantly. ''To be perfectly honest, I thought I was too tall and too big,'' she said. ''But when I did it on radio, I realized it was about someone made to be a littler person than they were, and that size did not matter.''</p>
        <p>The size issue aside, Ms. McTeer had a few of her own ideas about the play itself, which she took to Thelma Holt, the play's producer in England. Ms. McTeer wanted to do it with a younger Torvald, and she wanted a greater sense of complicity between the two.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to do the play as written,'' she said. ''It isn't a feminist drama, although you can draw feminist conclusions from it.'' The play, she said, is much more complicated and ambiguous than standard interpretations have let on. ''I'm not saying other productions are wrong, only that my way is more interesting,'' she said. ''Of course, I think that because it's my idea.''</p>
        <p>Ms. McTeer, 35, grew up in York, studied at the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art and earned her Equity card at the Nottingham Playhouse, where her fellow actors included Hugh Grant. She is well known to British theater audiences for her Yelena in ''Uncle Vanya'' at the National Theater and her Beatrice in ''Much Ado About Nothing'' in the West End. American audiences have seen her on ''Masterpiece Theater'' as Vita Sackville-West in ''Portrait of a Marriage.'' Her go-for-broke performance as Nora, however, has propelled her into full-fledged stardom. ''It was always going to be dangerous, not a standard revival of a classic,'' she said. ''When you do that, you either win by a mile or miss by a mile.''</p>
        <p>Benefit With More Larson Songs</p>
        <p>For most theatergoers, the complete works of Jonathan Larson have been onstage in ''Rent,'' the musical that Mr. Larson completed before dying suddenly a year ago. On March 3 at the Nederlander Theater, audiences will be able to hear more.</p>
        <p>In a benefit for the New York Theater Workshop, the cast of ''Rent'' and artists including Richie Havens and Mary Chapin Carpenter will perform about 18 songs by Mr. Larson, many of them not heard in public before.</p>
        <p>''He was composing all the time,'' said Tim Weil, the musical director of ''Rent.'' ''He always said, 'I like to write a song before breakfast.' I'd like to write a good song before I'm 65.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Larson left a sheaf of songs in various stages of completion, and in styles covering the same wide range found in ''Rent.'' ''He was determined to find ways of writing songs that communicated in a theatrical way,'' Mr. Weil said. ''It was always done with dramatic intent first and foremost.''</p>
        <p>For information: (212) 780-9037.</p>
        <p>A New Theater Company</p>
        <p>Arthur Penn, the president of the Actors Studio, has created a new theater company, the Actors Studio Free Theater at Raw Space, to produce about six new plays annually.</p>
        <p>There's a hook. The plays will be presented free of charge, the actors will receive precisely nothing for their labors and the theater will retain no rights to the plays.</p>
        <p>Each production will receive four weeks of rehearsal and run for 24 performances. The first production, Jay Presson Allen's ''Major Crimes,'' begins performances on Wednesday at Raw Space, a theater at 529 West 42d Street.</p>
        <p>On Stage, and Off</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
