<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>GREAT COOKS: Linda McCartney; Lots of Smidgens, But Hold the Meat</title>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Living Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="710686"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VEGETARIANISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RECIPES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCARTNEY, LINDA</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MCCARTNEY, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">FRANEY, PIERRE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">MILLER, BRYAN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetarianism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Recipes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940907T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E0DF1138F934A3575AC0A962958260" item-length="2704" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>GREAT COOKS: Linda McCartney; Lots of Smidgens, But Hold the Meat</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BRYAN MILLER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MILLER, BRYAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>"ARE you a veggie?" is the usual salutation of Linda McCartney, cookbook author, photographer, musician and wife of Paul McCartney, the songwriter and performer.</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCartney recently went to the East Hampton, L.I., home of the chef Pierre Franey to discuss her passion for vegetarian cooking and to prepare a meal from her cookbook, "Linda McCartney's Home Cooking" (Arcade Publishing, 1989). Traipsing behind her was her vegetable-loving husband, wearing baggy plaid shorts, sandals and a blue sweatshirt and carrying a guitar.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>"ARE you a veggie?" is the usual salutation of Linda McCartney, cookbook author, photographer, musician and wife of Paul McCartney, the songwriter and performer.</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCartney recently went to the East Hampton, L.I., home of the chef Pierre Franey to discuss her passion for vegetarian cooking and to prepare a meal from her cookbook, "Linda McCartney's Home Cooking" (Arcade Publishing, 1989). Traipsing behind her was her vegetable-loving husband, wearing baggy plaid shorts, sandals and a blue sweatshirt and carrying a guitar.</p>
        <p>"I grew up in a family that loved good food, but I was the one who really liked to cook," she said while quickly getting down to business by chopping onions, carrots and leeks for a vegetable soup. "When I was growing up in Scarsdale, we had a cook. Maybe because of my insecurity or whatever I used to hang around the kitchen and watch her."</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCartney, 52, disarmingly earthy and outgoing, has been married to the ex-Beatle for 25 years and has four children: Heather, 31 (from a previous marriage); Mary, 25; Stella, 23, and James, 17.</p>
        <p>She was wearing blue jeans and a colorful peasant blouse -- "I'm a peasant cook," she said -- that set off her straw-colored hair and pellucid green eyes. Mr. McCartney, also 52, watched his wife buzz around the kitchen for an hour before quietly carrying his left-handed Martin acoustic guitar into the den for -- what else? -- a songwriting session.</p>
        <p>"Don't mind me," he said. "I'll watch for a while, then go into another room to play a little." The McCartneys spend a few weeks each summer in East Hampton, near Mrs. McCartney's stepmother, Monique Eastman.</p>
        <p>"Paul really is a great bread maker," Mrs. McCartney said while assembling her soup. "During the bread strike in England he made it every day at home."</p>
        <p>Mr. McCartney said: "My best dish is mashed potatoes. A little milk, some chopped onions -- that's the Liverpool version."</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCartney's devotion to meatless cooking goes beyond her household south of London. Three years ago she introduced in England a line of frozen vegetarian entrees: lasagna, pasta, burgers, pot pies, goulash and more. Today the line, which bears her name, carries 18 items and has more than $40 million in sales annually. Once the initial investment is recouped, she said, she plans to give the profits to charity.</p>
        <p>In this country, Linda McCartney's Homestyle Cooking entrees, produced by Fairmont Foods outside Minneapolis, were test-marketed in the Midwest this year and are to be introduced on the West Coast next month and on the East Coast by year-end. Single-portion entrees will cost about $3 each.</p>
        <p>For the meal at Mr. Franey's home, Mrs. McCartney prepared vegetable soup, an eggplant casserole laced with fresh herbs, coleslaw and applesauce cake.</p>
        <p>"Most people don't know how good vegetarian food can be," she said.  "Look at this vegetable soup. You know where the flavor comes from? Sauteing the vegetables in a little oil first."</p>
        <p>The McCartneys, who raise sheep for wool and have an organic farm two hours south of London, in Berkshire, have been vegetarians for more than 20 years. An abhorrence of animal slaughter is at the root of the couple's aversion to meat.</p>
        <p>"It really all started with the animals," Mr. McCartney said. "We were sitting home having dinner one day, and there were some lambs running around outside on our farm.  They were so cute, and we were sitting there eating meat. Before that it never occurred to us that maybe we should look into another way."</p>
        <p>He added that for the first year of their meatless lives, "there was this big hole in the middle of the plate, you know, because we were so used to meals built around meat."</p>
        <p>"Then gradually," he continued, "Linda started filling that hole by cooking vegetables in interesting ways."</p>
        <p>At the drop of a scallion Mrs. McCartney cites statistics on animal carnage and on the global economic efficiency of vegetarianism. And she never misses an opportunity to underscore her beliefs. When she spotted some ceramic figurines of pigs and cows on Mr. Franey's windowsill, she remarked, "Oh, those are cute, but they sure look different when they're murdered."</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCartney refers to meat as "flesh" or when giving extra emphasis to a point, "a slab of fear." The McCartney children, all raised without meat, poultry or fish, have remained vegetarians.</p>
        <p>"When the kids were growing up I said: 'Hey, we're going veggie. I don't want to cook meat anymore,' " she recalled. "If they wanted to eat differently out of the house, fine. But as it turned out, they were all sympathetic."</p>
        <p>Even though all the children except James are now on their own, the McCartneys describe themselves as homebodies. "We don't get out that much, unless we're on tour or something," Mr. McCartney said.</p>
        <p>"Yes, but the house is always full," Mrs. McCartney said. "The kids come by; we have friends over." At their East Hampton rental house the week before, they had entertained guests -- including Paul Simon, Lorne Michaels and his wife, Alice -- with a vegetarian dinner.</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCartney noted that she was working on an updated vegetarian cookbook. Her current book has sold more than 250,000 copies worldwide, she said.</p>
        <p>As she spoke, she sliced fat late-summer eggplant for the casserole, which was liberally seasoned with fresh basil and oregano and onion.  She is hardly Julia Child-like when it comes to precision with ingredients.  Everything is added in handfuls, pinches, smidgens. Her favorite measurement is "lots of."</p>
        <p>"Linda, should I add half a tablespoon of oregano or a whole tablespoon?" Mr. Franey said.</p>
        <p>"Go ahead, throw it all in, Pierre," she replied with a wave of her hand. Mr. Franey chuckled and followed orders.</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCartney clearly enjoys serving flavorful food. She undertook a daunting challenge two years ago while on a world tour with her husband's band (she played keyboards and sang) and road crew, a total of 140 people.</p>
        <p>"Before the tour the promoter told us that we had to pay for our food on the road," Mr. McCartney said. "We thought, wow, we have to think about how to do this." Mrs. McCartney decided that it would be a good idea for both health and economic reasons to do a vegetarian tour.</p>
        <p>Working with a caterer, Mrs. McCartney devised menus for every day, with several choices for each course listed on a blackboard.</p>
        <p>"The food was so good that most people didn't miss meat at all," Mr. McCartney said. "We even got a few converts by the time it was over."</p>
        <p>Mr. McCartney then indulged in some Beatles culinary nostalgia. "When the Beatles were starting and playing in clubs around Liverpool," he said, "my father, on his days off, would make a batch of mashed potatoes and stuff and bring it down so we would have something to eat."</p>
        <p>Mrs. McCartney placed her eggplant casserole in the oven, then started on the applesauce cake. "Lots of lemon zest gives it flavor," she said while running a lemon over a grater. The simple, semisweet and moist cake was redolent of cinnamon and nutmeg and studded with Mr. McCartney's favorite nuts, pecans.</p>
        <p>"Pierre, do you have any organic eggs?" Mrs. McCartney asked Mr. Franey, prompting a surprised look, as if he had been asked to sing a few bars of "Penny Lane."</p>
        <p>While the nonorganic cake was being assembled, Mr. McCartney ducked into the den with his guitar to work on a song. Reading lyrics scribbled on a sheet of paper, he ran through two verses of a sweet-sounding ballad having to do with a poor boy in love.</p>
        <p>"I do it very simply at first, just to get the feeling," he said. "It's just like cooking, you know -- a simple expression can be the best."</p>
        <p>Back in the kitchen, Mr. Franey turned to Mrs. McCartney and said, "Mademoiselle, did you put the timer on before you put the cake in the oven?"</p>
        <p>"No," she replied, unconcerned."We'll know when it's ready."</p>
        <p>Aside from her culinary pursuits, Mrs. McCartney is a well-known photographer of rock stars and other subjects. In the mid-1960's, when she was known as Linda Eastman (no connection with the Eastman-Kodak Company), the daughter of a prominent New York entertainment lawyer, Lee Eastman, she worked as a receptionist at Town &amp; Country magazine.</p>
        <p>"One day, an invitation came in to the editors for an event called Meet the Rolling Stones," she recalled. "I snagged the invitation and put it in my drawer. I got caught, but they didn't want to go anyway, so they said I could go."</p>
        <p>Carrying her Pentax camera and trying to look like a professional, she went to a pier on Manhattan's West Side, where the party was being held on a boat.</p>
        <p>"When I got there they told me that there was not enough room on the boat for all the journalists and all the photographers, so they turned to me and said, 'O.K., you will be the only photographer on the boat.' "</p>
        <p>The photographs she sold to magazines around the country instantly established her reputation. Mrs. McCartney used her newfound stature to photograph dozens of leading rock musicians in the 1960's and 70's -- including Paul McCartney, whom she met while photographing the Beatles in 1967. They were married two years later. In 1992 she published a coffee table book of her musician portraits and had a traveling exhibition of her work in the United States.</p>
        <p>Back at Mr. Franey's, the finished meal was arranged on a table outside. Mr. McCartney eagerly strode out, sat down and tucked a napkin into the neck of his sweatshirt.</p>
        <p>"You don't mind having photos taken?" his wife asked.</p>
        <p>"Not if I get some soup," he replied.</p>
        <p>Later, as the last of the apple cake was consumed, Mr. Franey declared the meal a great success: the soup was full flavored and perfumed with summery herbs, the eggplant well textured and tasty, the coleslaw bright and fresh and the applecake homey and moist. Mr. Franey had to concede that he initially had harbored doubts about Mrs. McCartney's free-form style of cooking.</p>
        <p>"Next time, I want to invite you here and I will cook my own version of a vegetarian dinner," he said to Mrs. McCartney.</p>
        <p>"Wonderful!" she replied.</p>
        <p>"We're going home on Tuesday," her sated husband said. "Maybe we could do it before then?"</p>
        <p>THE following recipes are adapted from "Linda McCartney's Home Cooking" (Arcade Publishing, 1989).</p>
        <p>Vegetable Soup  Total time: 1 hour 30 minutes  3 tablespoons olive oil</p>
        <p>1 large onion, peeled and chopped</p>
        <p>2 cups trimmed (greens included), cleaned and sliced leeks</p>
        <p>2 cups chopped celery</p>
        <p>1 clove garlic, crushed</p>
        <p>1 1/2 cups unpeeled, sliced carrots</p>
        <p>1 cup shredded cabbage</p>
        <p>2 cups unskinned cubed new potatoes</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon fresh thyme</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon fresh rosemary</p>
        <p>1 teaspoon fresh parsley</p>
        <p>6 cups vegetable stock (fresh or canned)</p>
        <p>8 medium tomatoes or 1 16-ounce can of crushed tomatoes</p>
        <p>Salt and freshly ground pepper to taste.</p>
        <p>1. Heat the oil in a soup pot over medium flame, and saute the onions, leeks, celery and garlic for 5 minutes.  Do not brown the garlic.</p>
        <p>2. Add the carrots, cabbage and potatoes. Stir well. Add the thyme, rosemary and parsley. Cover with vegetable stock and simmer, covered, for 1 hour. Stir occasionally, adding water if evaporation is excessive.</p>
        <p>3. If you are using fresh tomatoes, place them on top of the simmering liquid for about 2 minutes, or until their skins can be easily peeled away.  Remove the tomatoes with a slotted spoon, and when they are cool enough to handle, remove the skins. Gently crush the whole skinned tomatoes and stir them into the soup. If you are using canned tomatoes, stir them, liquid and all, into the soup.</p>
        <p>4. Season to taste. Serve hot.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 230 calories, 9 grams fat, 0 milligrams cholesterol, 145 milligrams sodium (before salting), 7 grams protein, 35 grams carbohydrate. Eggplant and Herb Casserole  Total time: 2 hours  2 1/2 pounds ripe plum tomatoes (or 1 28-ounce can crushed imported tomatoes)  10 tablespoons olive oil  1large onion, peeled and chopped  2 tablespoons minced garlic  1 6-ounce can tomato paste  1 tablespoon chopped fresh oregano (or 1/2 tablespoon dried)  1 tablespoon chopped fresh basil ( 1/2 tablespoon)  1 teaspoon chopped fresh thyme (or 1/2 teaspoon dried)  Salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  3/4 cup all-purpose flour for dredging  2 eggplants, about 1 pound each, sliced1/4 inch thick on a slight bias  8 ounces whole milk mozzarella, thinly sliced.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 350 degrees, and lightly grease a baking dish or gratin dish (14-by-9 1/2 oblong or 10-by-6 rectangular).</p>
        <p>2. If using fresh plum tomatoes, plunge them into a pot of boiling water for 10 seconds, lift out with a slotted spoon and remove the skins.  Core and cube them to yield 4 cups.</p>
        <p>3. Heat 1 tablespoon of the olive oil in a saucepan, and saute the onion and garlic. Cook, stirring, for 1 minute. Add the plum tomatoes (or canned tomatoes), then the tomato paste. Add the oregano, basil and thyme.</p>
        <p>4. Stir well, and bring the sauce to a simmer. Cook, covered, over low heat for 30 minutes, adding salt and freshly ground pepper if necessary.</p>
        <p>5. Meanwhile, place the flour in a bowl. Dredge the eggplant slices in the flour. Use the rest of the olive oil, little by little, to saute the eggplant slices over medium heat -- about 2 minutes per side, or until lightly browned.</p>
        <p>6. Pour a layer of tomato sauce over the bottom of the baking dish, and layer some cooked eggplant over that. Alternate the rest of the sauce and eggplant in layers. Arrange eggplant slices over the top. Cover with sliced mozzarella. Bake for 1 hour or until the surface is golden brown.</p>
        <p>Yield: 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 360 calories, 25 grams fat, 20 milligrams cholesterol, 320 milligrams sodium (before salting), 10 grams protein, 30 grams carbohydrate. Coleslaw  Total time: 10 minutes  3/4 of a small head of cabbage, sliced as thinly as possible  5 ounces olive oil (extra virgin preferred)  4 ounces red wine vinegar  Juice of one lemon  Salt and freshly ground pepper to taste  1/2 cup chopped fresh parsley.</p>
        <p>1. Place the sliced cabbage in a large mixing bowl.</p>
        <p>2. Combine the remaining ingredients, and blend thoroughly. Season to taste. Pour over cabbage, and toss well.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 185 calories, 20 grams fat, 0 milligrams cholesterol, 11 milligrams sodium (before salting), 1 gram protein, 4 grams carbohydrate. Applesauce Cake  Total time: 1 hour 50 minutes  Butter for greasing cake tin  4 Rome apples, cored, peeled and sliced  4 tablespoons water  1/2 cup sugar  1/4 teaspoon cinnamon  1/2 teaspoon chopped lemon peel  Juice of half a lemon  4 ounces softened butter  1/2 cup light brown sugar  1 teaspoon vanilla  1 egg  2 cups all-purpose flour  2 teaspoons baking soda  2teaspoons baking powder  Pinch of salt  2/3 cup chopped pecans  1 cup raisins  1/2 teaspoon freshly grated nutmeg  1/8 teaspoon cinnamon.</p>
        <p>1. Preheat oven to 350 degrees, and lightly grease an 8-inch cake tin.</p>
        <p>2. In a deep saucepan over medium heat, combine the apples, 4 tablespoons water, 1/2 cup sugar, 1/4 teaspoon cinnamon, chopped lemon peel and lemon juice. Barely cover with water, bring to a boil, reduce heat to a simmer and cook, stirring, until the mixture reduces and thickens -- about 20 minutes. Mash the mixture to a smooth consistency.</p>
        <p>3. Meanwhile, in a mixing bowl, cream together the butter and brown sugar. Add the vanilla, and beat well; then the egg, and beat well.</p>
        <p>4. Add butter mixture to the apple mixture. Into a separate bowl, sift together the flour, baking soda, baking powder and salt.</p>
        <p>5. Add the pecans, raisins, nutmeg and cinnamon. Stir well.</p>
        <p>6. Add the dry mixture to the apple mixture and stir to make a smooth batter. Transfer to the greased cake tin. Smooth the top with a spatula or knife, and bake for about 1 hour and 35 minutes, or until a toothpick inserted in the middle comes out clean.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings.</p>
        <p>Approximate nutritional analysis per serving: 550 calories, 20 grams fat, 65 milligrams cholesterol, 635 milligrams sodium, 6 grams protein, 85 grams carbohydrate.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
