<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Animation's Bad Boy Returns, Unrepentant</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Arts &amp; Leisure Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="540834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="FILM"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMATED FILMS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">DIAMOND, JAMIE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BAKSHI, RALPH</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">COOL WORLD (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animated Films</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE0DD1031F936A35754C0A964958260" item-length="1626" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Animation's Bad Boy Returns, Unrepentant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAMIE DIAMOND;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">DIAMOND, JAMIE</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AN EXHAUSTED ANIMATOR stands at the door of the director Ralph Bakshi's office. "Come see if you can live with this," he says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakshi rises. He is so tense that he is calm. Only five days remain until he has to surrender "Cool World," his $28 million live-action/animation feature, to Paramount. In the manner of a bear roused from hibernation, Mr. Bakshi lumbers into a dark, overly air-conditioned editing room and watches a cartoon cat being flattened by a falling anvil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AN EXHAUSTED ANIMATOR stands at the door of the director Ralph Bakshi's office. "Come see if you can live with this," he says.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakshi rises. He is so tense that he is calm. Only five days remain until he has to surrender "Cool World," his $28 million live-action/animation feature, to Paramount. In the manner of a bear roused from hibernation, Mr. Bakshi lumbers into a dark, overly air-conditioned editing room and watches a cartoon cat being flattened by a falling anvil.</p>
        <p>There's a glitch, all right. Instead of splattering nicely on the sidewalk, the cat bounces along, the way a magic carpet might. Mr. Bakshi gives one of his hacking coughs, lights up his hundredth Marlboro of the day and says: "Put a screeching sound under it. We can live with that."</p>
        <p>Twenty years ago, when Mr. Bakshi introduced to the screen another animated feline, Fritz the Cat, he created the first X-rated cartoon. Public reaction to the film, with its overt sex and religious and racial caricatures, was intense -- and negative.</p>
        <p>Still, many people welcomed Mr. Bakshi's irreverence, and "Fritz" went on to become a moneymaking cult classic. Mr. Bakshi forged on, inventing more audacious, adult-themed cartoons -- among them "Heavy Traffic" in 1973 and "Coonskin" in 1975.</p>
        <p>After a lukewarm reaction to "American Pop" in 1981, Mr. Bakshi quit the film business to devote himself to painting. Now, at age 55, he returns with "Cool World," which opens Friday and stars Kim Basinger, Gabriel Byrne and Brad Pitt. This time, Mr. Bakshi is hoping to make another big splash -- with considerably less controversy.</p>
        <p>"When you paint in a studio by yourself, you get very lonely," Mr. Bakshi says of his decision two and a half years ago to abandon canvas for a time and return to celluloid. "I got nostalgic for all the problems you have when you make a movie. 'Roger Rabbit' had come out; animation was hot. I made 1,500 bucks in 10 years of painting; I thought it would be nice to pick up a piece of change. So I called my lawyer, who was still speaking to me because no one ever leaves Hollywood, and asked him where I should go to sell a movie."</p>
        <p>The movie Mr. Bakshi had in mind was an animated horror film, and his lawyer sent him to a master of the genre, Frank Mancuso Jr., who had worked on seven of the eight "Friday the 13th" films.</p>
        <p>"But," says Mr. Mancuso, the producer of "Cool World," "I'd gotten my fill of horror films and was feeling trapped by them. So we started talking about what happens when someone creates a world, becomes defined by it, and then can't escape. And we got the idea of making a film about being trapped by your own creation."</p>
        <p>Mr. Bakshi took the idea farther. "I came up with the premise of a girl who was a cartoon character who didn't want to be one anymore -- an obvious correlation to my not wanting to paint anymore," he says. To complete the scenario, he added a cartoon artist, Jack Deebs (played by Gabriel Byrne) who, because he is literally trapped in a prison, creates not only the cartoon girl, Holli Would (played in the live action sequences by Kim Basinger), but a wild, sensual place called Cool World into which he can escape. Soon Jack Deebs enters the world he created, falls in love with Holli and battles Frank Harris (Brad Pitt), the detective who tries to keep real people and "doodles" apart.</p>
        <p>" 'Roger Rabbit' used familiar cartoon characters, so it wasn't a stretch to put a live guy in that world," says Mr. Mancuso. "But no one knew what our world would look like. We were starting from scratch." A year after the initial green light, armed with a script by Michael Grais and Mark Victor and about 30 paintings of Cool World, Mr. Mancuso and Mr. Bakshi got the final go-ahead.</p>
        <p>The director's long journey to the make-believe land of "Cool World" began in 1937. Born in Palestine, he moved with his family to Brooklyn when he was a year old. "In Palestine, my father worked in construction as an undersea diver; he earned his living by wearing one of those big fat helmets over a rubber suit," says Mr. Bakshi, who wears sneakers and a shapeless T-shirt over what appears to be the pants from a suit.</p>
        <p>How did his father earn a living in Brooklyn? "Well . . . ." Pause. "A man like that should never have left his homeland."</p>
        <p>What did he do? Mr. Bakshi twists his hair. "He was a brilliantly intellectual man who was forced to work in a factory; he worked in a sheet metal shop, and my mother worked in the garment center."</p>
        <p>Almost as if he himself were trapped inside his parents' gloomy workplaces, Mr. Bakshi sought escape, as Jack Deebs does, in the world of comic strips. "They offered this liberating sense of freedom and anarchy." Soon he began drawing his own comics. "I was very insecure, and drawing allowed me to sit in a room by myself and hide."</p>
        <p>Not academically inclined, Mr. Bakshi won a space in the cartooning program of Manhattan's High School of Industrial Art. After he graduated in 1956 with an award in animation, he began to work at an animation studio in New Rochelle, called Terrytoons, where he remained for the next 10 years. During those years, he married, had a son, separated from his wife and became the head of the studio.</p>
        <p>During those same 10 years, 1956 to 1966, America was undergoing a major social and cultural upheaval. Mr. Bakshi's former influences -- John Coltrane, Jack Kerouac, Jackson Pollock -- had been replaced by Bob Dylan, Ken Kesey, the sexual revolution, psychedelics and underground comic books. "Suddenly, children's cartoons bored me," he recalls. Acquiring the rights to R. Crumb's raunchy Fritz the Cat comic strip and getting $100,000 in seed money from Warner Brothers, Mr. Bakshi proceeded to animate a sample sequence.</p>
        <p>"I did Big Bertha chasing Fritz through the junkyard; she was bare-breasted, and he had just gone to bed with a black woman and caused a riot in Harlem," he says nonchalantly. Warner Brothers immediately withdrew from the project. But Mr. Bakshi raised the necessary $750,000 (he met a willing independent producer in the elevator after his disastrous meeting with Warner Brothers) and made "Fritz the Cat" anyway.</p>
        <p>The X-rated feline who uttered onscreen profanities considerably stronger than "oh, fiddlesticks," stirred up a hornet's nest of controversy. "Two animation companies took out an ad in Variety that said we don't need people like you, and there was talk about if I were a pornographer or not," says Mr. Bakshi with an equal mix of horror and pride.</p>
        <p>"What I did was anti everything animation was about," he adds. "I had stumbled into something to go against, like Picasso and Cezanne and Matisse had something to go against," says Mr. Bakshi, who has never been accused of modesty.</p>
        <p>Although Mr. Bakshi "stumbled" into his medium, he thinks that animated characters can elicit more powerful emotions than flesh-and-blood actors. "Look at the death of Bambi's mother," he says. "I'm sure there are lots of live action movies with similar situations. But there you were, wide open to those little deer, and suddenly, you're hit by what motherhood and death and loss all mean. Animation disarms people."</p>
        <p>In 1975, Mr. Bakshi touched off more deep feelings when he made "Coonskin," the first animated feature to depict black characters -- well, O.K., they were drug dealers. CORE boycotted the film to protest its unflattering portrayal of blacks, and Paramount refused to distribute it. (Later, it was independently released.)</p>
        <p>Weary of refuting charges of moral turpitude and racism, Mr. Bakshi turned his pen to two traditional animation projects, "Wizards" (1977) and "Lord of the Rings" (1979). Thunderbolts did not fall from the sky and strike him dead. Instead, a fair sum of money poured in at the box office. In 1981, he made "American Pop," a social history about four generations of Jewish American immigrants that met with a lukewarm reception.</p>
        <p>Then he quit, moved his second wife and their three children back to New York, and started to paint.</p>
        <p>Why did he abandon the medium in which he was a founding father? "I wanted to graduate from cartooning to art. I was in my 40's; it was time to put my money where my mouth was." But after nearly a decade of painting -- some of it abstract, brightly colored collages -- that resulted in a few gallery shows in the East Village in Manhattan, Mr. Bakshi was eager to make waves in Hollywood again.</p>
        <p>What was different this time around? "He was much more sure of himself," says Louise Zingarelli, a layout artist who has worked with Mr. Bakshi for the past 16 years. "Most people would say he's mellowed."</p>
        <p>Sounding more than mellow a few days after delivering "Cool World," Mr. Bakshi says the studio was happy with his picture and his two-and-a-half-year effort was worth it. "I got the opportunity to shoot live action with A-plus actors, and for the first time I had a real budget, $28 million, as opposed to my previous all-time high of $4 million," he says. "When the studio supports you with this kind of budget, there's no cop-out area. You can't say, 'Well, I did the best I could with the money they gave me.' "</p>
        <p>Still, a big studio investment guarantees other problems. "In live action, the studio can look at rushes and immediately judge how the film is going. But in animation all they have to look at are pencil drawings, and they have to trust you. By the bitter end, and it usually is a bitter end, they are very, very nervous."</p>
        <p>Now that the film is finished and the studio no longer nervous, what is Mr. Bakshi's next move?</p>
        <p>"I'm getting in my car and driving back East."</p>
        <p>Hasn't he heard of planes?</p>
        <p>"I want to get out on the road and see what this country's about," he says. "Haven't you heard of Beatniks?"  FILM Jamie Diamond, a contributing editor of Lear's magazine, writes about movies for Premiere and Entertainment Weekly.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Jamie Diamond, a contributing editor of Lear's magazine, writes about movies for Premiere and Entertainment Weekly.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
