<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Executive Computer; Michael Dell Says He's More Than Ready for a Good Fight</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="540713"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPANY REPORTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">DELL COMPUTER CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">LEWIS, PETER H</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DELL, MICHAEL S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Biography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company Reports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDF1F3DF936A35754C0A964958260" item-length="1333" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Executive Computer; Michael Dell Says He's More Than Ready for a Good Fight</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Peter H. Lewis</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">LEWIS, PETER H</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>While much of the personal computer industry struggled through the last two years, and giants like I.B.M. and Compaq reported their first quarterly losses, the Dell Computer Corporation was recording quarterly sales gains of 75 percent or more. The company, which started less than a decade ago in a dormitory room at the University of Texas, is expected to report sales this year of $1.7 billion.</p>
        <p>At the helm sits Michael Dell, now 27 years old. His business plan has not changed much: He builds innovative computers, prices them below most of the competition, sells them directly to customers who call Dell's toll-free number, and, according to a succession of surveys of corporate buyers, offers the best after-sale service and support of any computer maker. Many rival executives who ridiculed his approach are no longer around, and their companies are struggling to copy his success.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>While much of the personal computer industry struggled through the last two years, and giants like I.B.M. and Compaq reported their first quarterly losses, the Dell Computer Corporation was recording quarterly sales gains of 75 percent or more. The company, which started less than a decade ago in a dormitory room at the University of Texas, is expected to report sales this year of $1.7 billion.</p>
        <p>At the helm sits Michael Dell, now 27 years old. His business plan has not changed much: He builds innovative computers, prices them below most of the competition, sells them directly to customers who call Dell's toll-free number, and, according to a succession of surveys of corporate buyers, offers the best after-sale service and support of any computer maker. Many rival executives who ridiculed his approach are no longer around, and their companies are struggling to copy his success.</p>
        <p>Now married and a father, Mr. Dell no longer works the 16- to 18-hour days that marked his early years as chairman of PC's Limited, the company that later became Dell. But he is not exactly taking it easy. Last year he got rid of his office desk and chair and now works standing up. "I've discovered that I think faster on my feet," he said.</p>
        <p>In a recent interview, Mr. Dell was preparing for war, because the Compaq Computer Corporation, Dell's historical rival, had just slashed prices. Mr. Dell's strategy is to keep up the pressure on Compaq and the International Business Machines Corporation, while fighting off incursions from the second tier and third tier clone makers that have grown by imitating Dell.</p>
        <p>Question: What's going on?</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell: For Compaq, it is clearly survivor mode. They've basically said, "O.K., we're not going to win this game by pricing way off in outer space, so what we're going to do is price ahead of where we would price in the normal profit model." They've said they're prepared to make no money, or 1 percent, 2 percent net income, and get their business back in a "healthy" mode by pumping a lot of volume, and better amortizing their cost structure.</p>
        <p>Q. Do you think they can pull it off?</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell: Well, it's a very difficult challenge. Let's say there's a 25 percent reduction in their average selling price. So what do you have to do in that scenario to get a 10 percent increase in revenues? You've got to get a 50 percent increase in units, which is conceivable but very, very challenging. The other thing, of course, is that they're taking the approach on distribution that "we can't go direct because it's too much of a change to our distribution system, so let the dealers fight it out." Their distribution strategy, as far as we can tell, is anybody, everywhere, anything.</p>
        <p>Q. What will be the effect on other companies?</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell: If you take the pie chart of companies -- I.B.M., Packard-Bell, Tandy, Compaq and Dell, and "others," well, "others" is certainly in jeopardy. And the companies that are sitting on the sidelines, sort of with one foot in the business and one foot out, like Hewlett-Packard, DEC and those guys, I can imagine them two months from now having a meeting and saying, "Gee, what should we do?" And it's already too late! They've already missed the chance to do something. For us, it's not a wait-and-see game. If Compaq is bold, we have to be bold plus 40 percent.</p>
        <p>Q. You don't look as though you're losing any sleep over Compaq, which seems to have been your focus in ads for the last few years.</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell: It was really an I.B.M.-Compaq focus, but Compaq was a better target. You have to think twice before you go out in public and say, "Hey, we're going to get I.B.M." There's a lot of heritage and Americana there. Compaq was more of a pure play in terms of picking a fight.</p>
        <p>Q. So what's your response?</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell: We're still focused on gaining share, and what you're going to see from us are new products and pricing and services that will position us to continue to have the momentum we've had the last few years. Relatively speaking, we're likely to do better than other companies, given that we're pretty lean, know how to do products, know how to satisfy customers, have a good channel, and have a strong balance sheet. But only relative to other companies. If I.B.M. and Compaq decide to make no money, then we're going to make some money, but probably not as much as we would if they decided to make money.</p>
        <p>If you look at Compaq, I think one of the reasons they got in trouble is that they built the business around this 10 percent net income model, which is clearly a mistake. If they had thought it through carefully enough, they would have said, "Gee, some smart guy is going to figure out how to compete beneath us, and build a business that plays off the inefficiency of the fact that we are making 10 percent, that we're not in the most effective channel, and that we spend all this money doing this and that and the other thing." And that's exactly what's happened.</p>
        <p>Q. So now what's going to happen?</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell: Our cost structure is lower than Compaq's, and they're selling through a dealer. Let's say the dealer adds 7 to 10 percent. It costs them 15 percent more to get a product to the customer with the right service and everything. If they're going to price the same as you, and it costs them 15 percent more, what's going to happen? Well, either you're going to lower your price, or they're not going to make money, or maybe both. Clearly that pricing relationship is going to change very quickly.</p>
        <p>Q. What about other companies?</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell: If you compare Compaq's new Prolinea line to Gateway, Compaq is maybe 5 percent lower. So what happens to Gateway up here? What happens to Zeos up here? Northgate, Everex. This is not a good situation for the tier-three" companies and not a good situation for the marginal tier-two companies, and not a good situation for the reluctant participants like Olivetti, Zenith, DEC, H-P. It's going to get very brutal.</p>
        <p>Q. What's this mean for the PC buyer?</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell: In the short term, what you'll have is Dell, Compaq and all these other guys being more aggressive, so it'll be a good time to buy. That's the good news. Mid term, companies that decide to accept lower profitability may cut back on things that are important to customers, like product innovation, support. That's bad news. Long term, if the market consolidates and there are fewer companies, the customer could have fewer choices.</p>
        <p>Q. You mentioned improving your service and support, which is already regarded as the best in the industry. What can you do better?</p>
        <p>Mr. Dell: It starts with the key information that knowledgeable customers are getting. If you have a person or a thing standing in the way of them getting this information, that's inefficient and wasting money. That's exactly what we're working on, a customer connection tool. They can get technical information, order products, get new product information, news, converse with people.</p>
        <p>There are hundreds of interactions going on all day long between "ABC Megacorp" and Dell, and if the company had the right tool to interact with us, it could be done a lot better.</p>
        <p>We're building that tool and have a first release later this summer. It's a diskette -- you plug it in your machine and you become a node on a massive, diverse network of machines. As you want info, it comes to you. Basically we extend the relationship with the customer to include much better data going back and forth.</p>
        <p>Instead of some customer saying, "Gee, I heard you have this new notebook that weighs three and a half pounds," he clicks on a Dell icon. Here's a description, here's a picture, spin it around, here are the specs. It's a Windows front end.</p>
        <p>Ultimately the idea is that the customer can get any information, anything, any transaction in the way they want it. It's another way to communicate. You can use smoke signals, send us a fax, call us on the phone, click on an icon -- we'll talk to you any way you want.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
