<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Fugitive Kidnaps 2 and Eludes Search</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="540778"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRISONS AND PRISONERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRISON ESCAPES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">KIDNAPPING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">CALIFORNIA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">ARIZONA</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">GRAND CANYON NATIONAL PARK</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">HORNING, DANNY RAY</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">JOHNSON, DIRK</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./West</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona/Grand Canyon National Park</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Arizona</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/California</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prison Escapes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Kidnapping</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Prisons and Prisoners</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DA113FF936A35754C0A964958260" item-length="936" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Fugitive Kidnaps 2 and Eludes Search</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIRK JOHNSON,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JOHNSON, DIRK</byline>
      <dateline>GRAND CANYON, Ariz., July 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A prison escapee who has eluded searchers for weeks in the forested hills and gulches near the rim of this magnificent chasm, kidnapped two women today and slipped out of the national park, officials said.</p>
        <p>The escapee, Danny Ray Horning, a 35-year-old convicted bank robber who is wanted for questioning in a California slaying, kidnapped the women and forced them to drive out of the park in their rented vehicle, said Maureen Oltrogge, a spokeswoman for the National Park Service.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A prison escapee who has eluded searchers for weeks in the forested hills and gulches near the rim of this magnificent chasm, kidnapped two women today and slipped out of the national park, officials said.</p>
        <p>The escapee, Danny Ray Horning, a 35-year-old convicted bank robber who is wanted for questioning in a California slaying, kidnapped the women and forced them to drive out of the park in their rented vehicle, said Maureen Oltrogge, a spokeswoman for the National Park Service.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horning tied the women to a tree near Red Lake, about 45 miles south of the park, Ms. Oltrogge told The Associated Press. She said the women, who are in their 30's, freed themselves and contacted the authorities.</p>
        <p>The police caught up with Mr. Horning about 30 miles south of Flagstaff. He crashed the rental car into a tree during a 19-minute chase and ran into woods, Ms. Oltrogge said. New Search Begins</p>
        <p>It was not known how Mr. Horning was able to get past the authorities who were checking vehicles leaving the park, said Ms. Oltrogge and Lieut. Ron Anderson of the Coconino County Sheriff's Department.</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Anderson told the A.P. that the new search was centered near Lake Mormon. Mr. Horning had twice previously eluded the authorities in that area since he was first sighted in the state's high country on May 27.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horning has twice taken hostages and later released them with notes of apology in which he described himself as a "freedom fighter."</p>
        <p>Disguised in a doctor's smock, Mr. Horning walked out of the Arizona State Prison in Florence on May 12 and has foiled searchers in the longest manhunt in state history.</p>
        <p>He has left taped messages and notes for the police in stolen vehicles demanding the release of his brother, Jerry Horning, 40, who is serving a 29-year prison sentence for sexual misconduct with a minor.</p>
        <p>An Army veteran with training in reconnaissance, Mr. Horning is an expert in surviving in the wilderness. He has evoked comparisons with the movie character Rambo.</p>
        <p>On Thursday night, the bloodhounds detected Mr. Horning's scent at Grand Canyon Village, a cluster of tourist shops and restaurants, and led searchers on a chase that proved fruitless. The scent was a few hours old, said Sheriff Joe D. Richards of Coconino County. But the clue lent credence to the dozens of reports of sightings of Mr. Horning by tourists.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horning is 5 feet 8 inches and weighs about 140 pounds. The authorities believe he may have shaved the beard he wore in prison and dyed his dark hair blond. He is believed to be carrying a .44 magnum.</p>
        <p>The Grand Canyon, the giant chasm that cuts a mile deep in a low mountainous region of the Kaibab Plateau, lies within 1,904 square miles of national park in northern Arizona, and the dense growth of juniper and pine had provided an ideal hiding place for the convict.</p>
        <p>About 400 officers had been deployed in the search at the Grand Canyon, including agents for the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Border Patrol and tactical units of the National Park Service. Warning to Park Visitors</p>
        <p>About 18,000 people visit the park every day, and attendance had dipped only slightly, Ms. Oltrogge said. She said the Park Service had been warning visitors of Mr. Horning and giving them sketches of the convict.</p>
        <p>Mr. Horning had been hiding in Flagstaff, about 70 miles south of here, when he kidnapped a couple at gunpoint on June 25 and forced them to drive to the Grand Canyon in their four-wheel-drive truck. The three of them spent the night in a lodge and the next day he ordered them to take him shopping, then to return to the park.</p>
        <p>The next night he had them drive to a parking lot, where he attempted to abduct another family. But the family's young son shouted "kidnapping," alerting Park Rangers nearby. Mr. Horning then fled with the couple he abducted in Flagstaff in their truck, firing at least two shots through the back window at Park Rangers before the vehicle disappeared.  'Tried to Live in Peace'</p>
        <p>Later, Mr. Horning left the couple handcuffed in the truck with a note of apology. "Hey Bud," he wrote to the truck's owner, "I am sorry I had to do this to you."</p>
        <p>"I have tried to live in peace yet they keep coming after me," Mr. Horning wrote of the police. "That causes me to have to steal from people like you."</p>
        <p>He asked the couple he had abducted to keep them in his prayers and advised them to check the truck's transmission. "I really ran it rough so you'll want to give it a good check," he wrote.</p>
        <p>On Monday, he abducted another couple, who were on vacation from Oregon, fleeing with them in their station wagon. He soon abandoned the vehicle, leaving the couple unharmed, and fled into the woods near the south rim of the canyon.</p>
        <p>In the legends of the Old West, outlaws have traditionally been viewed as exciting figures and the daring of Mr. Horning has apparently won admirers. But after the escaped convict fired at the Park Rangers, some of the romantic appeal faded.</p>
        <p>"Residents throughout the state began to see him as something of a folk hero," The Flagstaff Daily Sun said in an editorial. "But now he's nothing more than a desperate terrorist frightening most of northern Arizona's inhabitants.</p>
        <p>For vacationers in recreational vehicles, cabins and tents, the manhunt has provided fodder for the kinds of scary late-night stories that are a staple for trips in the wilderness.</p>
        <p>"You never know, he could be disguised and walking around among us," said Mike Weynand, a tourist from Wisconsin, who reminded his wife, Mary, and their two young children to stay close at all times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
