<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Notes Woth Pleasure</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Book Review Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="23" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="540736"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BOOKS AND LITERATURE</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DA153CF936A35754C0A964958260" item-length="972" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Notes Woth Pleasure</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Artist of the Ordinary</p>
        <p>For Franz Kafka, the real, modest features of the world were in fact true signs of the marvelous, according to his friend Milena Jesenska. She is quoted in "The Nightmare of Reason: A Life of Franz Kafka," by Ernst Pawel (Noonday/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, paper).</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Artist of the Ordinary</p>
        <p>For Franz Kafka, the real, modest features of the world were in fact true signs of the marvelous, according to his friend Milena Jesenska. She is quoted in "The Nightmare of Reason: A Life of Franz Kafka," by Ernst Pawel (Noonday/Farrar, Straus &amp; Giroux, paper).</p>
        <p>For  [ Kafka ] , life is something altogether different from what it is for ordinary people. Above all, things such as money, the stock market, foreign exchange or a typewriter are utterly miraculous (as indeed they are, only not to the rest of us). . . . Is his work at the office, for instance, anything like an ordinary job? To him the office, including his own part in it, is as mysterious and wonderful as a locomotive is to a small child. Have you ever been to the post office with him? Watched him compose a telegram, shake his head while he picks a window he likes best and then, without the least notion of why and wherefore, starts wandering about from one window to the next? . . . No, this entire world is and remains a mystery to him, an enigmatic myth. . . . His books are amazing. He himself is far more amazing. Calling Art by Its True Name</p>
        <p>Frequently, the use of the term "folk art" is used to diminish or dismiss serious, complex works of art, according to Martin Williams in "Hidden in Plain Sight: An Examination of the American Arts" (Oxford University).</p>
        <p>In traditional European culture, a culture with a landed gentry, a courtly aristocracy and a peasantry, the distinction between "fine" art -- a "courtly" or "elite" art -- and a folk culture, reflects realities, and therefore makes sense as a way for scholars to approach and research that culture. In a democracy like ours, it seems to me that it does not make sense. . . . Any researcher who assumes that our country has a "folk" and an "elite" puts himself in danger not only of making scholarly blunders but also of assuming a patrician stance and, most dangerous of all, of imposing his unconscious assumptions about noble savages on other people, of molding his ideas about their lives and their culture after his own unconscious and unacknowledged needs. The Fellowship of the Land</p>
        <p>Why do people still ranch? And why, lately, have more ranchers started to write poetry about their lives? William Kittredge suggests some reasons in "Hole in the Sky: A Memoir" (Knopf).</p>
        <p>People stick to ranching because they love the feel of a quick little horse moving intently after cattle, or the smell of greasewood after summer rain or new-cut alfalfa on a spring morning, or the stretch of damp rawhide as they work at braiding a riata, or the look of a mother cow as she trails her dusty way back to her calf after a long walk to water. People stick to it because they enjoy the feel and smell and sound of things, and because they share those mostly unspoken loves with other people they can trust as being somewhere near to decent.</p>
        <p>All over the American West, cowboys and ranchwomen . . . have been gathering to declaim their verse to one another. . . . These are celebrations of things ranchland people respect and care about most deeply -- the land they have chosen to live on, their work, and, right at the center, one another, this companionship. The Sacred Subway</p>
        <p>Speculating on how archeologists in the future may explain the Paris subway system, Lawrence Osborne reminds us that time can turn even mundane objects into mysteries. This is from "Paris Dreambook: An Unconventional Guide to the Splendor and Squalor of the City" (Vintage, paper).</p>
        <p>The Metro is above all a system of names, names which are a thousand times more secretive than the places they supposedly denote. Filles du Calvaire, Bel-Air, Crimee, Danube, Pyramides. . . . The Metro names will be remembered in the future as a schoolchild's mnemonic for the ancient history of Europe or as a crazy hieroglyphic inscription. . . . It will be concluded, of course, that the Metro was an idea, a religious idea, perhaps, or a pan-humanitarian one, but never a public transport system. . . . The Metro was an idea in the mind of 20th-century man and the astrological map around which his archaic spirituality revolved. In it he tried to express his yearnings for unity and harmony in the face of the chaos of his history, and if people wished to drive around in trains along the configurations appointed by this divine map of reality that only shows how deeply the people of this age felt their pan-humanistic rituals. Across the Ocean of Time</p>
        <p>Describing a childhood summer spent by the ocean, Josephine Herbst reminds us of the subtle, essential ways in which adults pass on a sense of continuity, of a family persisting through time, to a child. This is from "The Starched Blue Sky of Spain" (Harper Perennial, paper).</p>
        <p>It was at night, in the light of the big campfire of driftwood, where the burning splinters fell in sparks the color of the rainbow or shot into tiny sulfurous spurts or foundered in pools of verdigris green, that the magicians and the apprentices played their true roles. . . . The very sound of the ocean and the sight of the sky, where the stars were bright buoys floating on their own watery deep, made you feel gently suspended in water, rocking in the vast hammock of the night. The voices of the grown-ups, slow, sometimes quietly breaking into laughter, communing over things dead and gone . . . cast long lines backward in time and across a continent.</p>
        <p>There</p>
        <p>became</p>
        <p>here</p>
        <p>and</p>
        <p>then</p>
        <p>was</p>
        <p>now</p>
        <p>. The magicians might have been casting lines across an ocean covering buried towns and farms, so dreamlike was the world they called to life, so haunting the images, so watery the night, so true the history that branched its coral islands to you, by right, because it had belonged to them.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
