<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kazoos at Katonah Herald a Family Series</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="540689"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="MUSIC"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUSIC</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">SHERMAN, ROBERT</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PREVIN, ANDRE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BATTLE, KATHLEEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Music</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Music</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DA153AF936A35754C0A964958260" item-length="1115" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kazoos at Katonah Herald a Family Series</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT SHERMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SHERMAN, ROBERT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>KAZOOS at Katonah, Peter and a Pumpkin Eater at Lyndhurst, Russian dancers in Yonkers, Camp Granada in Mamaroneck: quite a family entertainment week is shaping up in Westchester.</p>
        <p>Youngsters are urged to bring their own kazoos, although whirly tubes, triangles and drums will be provided as the Saturday Brass Quintet leads audience members in fanfares and other "participatory adventures in brass" at the first set of three family programs at Caramoor. These will be held on Friday and Saturday at 11 A.M. and 1 P.M. both days. The quintet will add its own set of marches, dances and probably a bit of ragtime, too.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>KAZOOS at Katonah, Peter and a Pumpkin Eater at Lyndhurst, Russian dancers in Yonkers, Camp Granada in Mamaroneck: quite a family entertainment week is shaping up in Westchester.</p>
        <p>Youngsters are urged to bring their own kazoos, although whirly tubes, triangles and drums will be provided as the Saturday Brass Quintet leads audience members in fanfares and other "participatory adventures in brass" at the first set of three family programs at Caramoor. These will be held on Friday and Saturday at 11 A.M. and 1 P.M. both days. The quintet will add its own set of marches, dances and probably a bit of ragtime, too.</p>
        <p>The family series will continue on July 17 and 18 with Paul Peabody's Old-Fashioned Marionette Theater and on July 24 and 25 with the storyteller Alice Eve Cohen. More details can be obtained by calling 232-1252.</p>
        <p>That favorite musical legend, Prokofiev's "Peter and the Wolf," is a feature of the Philharmonia Virtuosi's "Sunset Serenades" program Saturday at 6 P.M. at the Lyndhurst estate in Tarrytown. Candice Agree of radio station WNCN is the narrator, and the other pieces are selections from music that proved popular with children at the Philharmonia Virtuosi's "Cushion Concerts," like Vivaldi's "Bullfinch" Flute Concerto and Robert McBride's whimsical "Pumpkin Eater's Little Fugue." The number to call for more information is 693-5595.</p>
        <p>The Untermyer Performing Arts Festival begins its 15th summer of free concerts Saturday when the Russian Partners Dancing Team of Voronezh (the folk dance division of that city's Choreographic Academy) comes to Untermyer Park in Yonkers. Dressed in re-creations of traditional peasant costumes, these student-artists re-create ancient dance traditions of various regions in the former Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>Contemporary dance is the focus of the Shapiro-Smith Company as the Festival continues on July 18. The Haydn-Mozart Chamber Orchestra returns to Untermyer on Aug. 1 (without Haydn or Mozart, oddly enough: the program lists Bach, Handel, Telemann and Vivaldi). The Bread and Puppet Theater makes Aug. 8 another family evening, and the Aug. 15 finale is Opera Northeast's full-scale production of Donizetti's "Lucia di Lammermoor."</p>
        <p>All Untermyer events begin at 8 P.M., and should the weather require it, they move indoors to Saunders Auditorium. More information is available by calling the County Parks Department at 377-6441.</p>
        <p>Camp Grenada was immortalized in Allan Sherman's "Hello Muddah, Hello Fadduh," which is now the title of a new musical based on a whole group of the late comedian's wacky song parodies. A hit in its first tour of the West, the Off Broadway-bound show moves into the Emelin Theater for a three-week stand beginning Wednesday at 8 P.M.. More information can be obtained by calling the box office at 698-0098.</p>
        <p>A vocal component graces three of the four concerts at Caramoor this week, starting today at 5:30 P.M. when the Ensemble for Early Music includes Sephardic songs, Italian carnival pieces and Burgundian polyphonic motets in its explorations of 15th-century music.</p>
        <p>Thursday's 4:15 matinee at Caramoor finds the winds of St. Luke's Chamber Ensemble playing an all-instrumental program of Vivaldi, Haydn, Beethoven (the rarely heard Octet in E flat) and the world premiere of Robert Baksa's "Etudes and Chorale for Wind Septet," but when St. Luke's returns to the Spanish Courtyard for Friday's 8:30 P.M. recital, it will be with the renowned baritone William Sharp in de Falla's "Seven Popular Spanish Songs" and a group of chansons by Faure. Mr. Sharp will be accompanied by the pianist Colette Valentine.</p>
        <p>Another distinguished singer, the Metropolitan Opera soprano Kathleen Battle, performs at Caramoor on Saturday at 8:30 P.M., singing Barber's "Knoxville: Summer of 1915" and a new composition by Andre Previn with the intriguing title of "Honey and Rue." Mr. Previn, in the first of six Caramoor Festival appearances this summer, will conduct the Orchestra of St. Luke's in two works by Ravel, "Le Tombeau de Couperin" and the "Mother Goose" Suite. The Caramoor reservations number is 232-1252.</p>
        <p>Opera is the subject of "An Event in Two Acts -- An Evening of Love and Jealousy," sponsored by the Hudson Opera Theater and directed by Franco Gratale.</p>
        <p>The first part of the gala on Saturday at 8 P.M. at the State University of New York at Purchase will be devoted to love duets from "La Boheme," "Otello," and "Don Giovanni," among other favorites. Charles Rosekrans will conduct the orchestra, and several young soloists, among them James Dietsch and Eugenie Grunewald of the New York City Opera, will sing.</p>
        <p>After intermission, Eve Queler, the director of the Opera Orchestra of New York, will lead a semi-staged performance of Mascagni's one-act opera "Cavaleria Rusticana" with a cast headed by Paul Lyon, recently returned from his debut at La Scala.</p>
        <p>The number to call for reservations and (at additional charge) a meet-the-artists reception is 251-6200 or 633-2929.</p>
        <p>For those who would rather do the singing themselves, the Pleasantville Cantata Singers has reserved space at the Mount Pleasant Public Library on the remaining Wednesday evenings in July, starting at 8:15.</p>
        <p>John Daly Goodwin leads this week's impromptu reading of Haydn's "Mass in Time of War" and the Cherubini Requiem. Allen Crowell conducts Handel's "Messiah" on July 15. The Cantata Singers' founding director, Ludwig Sheffield, has chosen the English version of "A German Requiem" by Brahms for his score on July 22, and the program for the final Summer Sing on July 29 will feature the Mozart C minor Mass under the direction of Paul Echols.</p>
        <p>Listeners as well as singers are welcome, and music will be provided. Those who have their own scores, however, are asked to bring them. More information is available by calling 769-2314 in the evening.</p>
        <p>The Summer Jazz series is still several weeks away, scheduled to open on July 24, but music lovers need not wait until then to enjoy other special events at the Hudson River Museum in Yonkers. Wednesday at 1:30 P.M., for instance, a "Music Under the Stars" recital finds the Manhattan Wind Quintet performing in the Andrus Planetarium, one of seven "Seniors and the Arts" events sponsored by Mobil and available to the elderly without charge.</p>
        <p>Two days later, the museum ushers in the first of its "Fantastic Fridays," which from now until Sept. 11 means free admission every Friday from 5 to 9 P.M. and an assortment of other enticements: five free planetarium shows, a reception, previews of summer art exhibitions, discounts at the museum cafe and sunsets over the Hudson. More details can be obtained by calling 963-4550.  MUSIC</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
