<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Where They Stand on the Deficit</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="17" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="560941"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: CANDIDATES ON THE ISSUE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BUDGETS AND BUDGETING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTION ISSUES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION OF 1992</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">UNITED STATES</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">CLINTON, BILL (GOV)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PEROT, ROSS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE3DB143DF936A35753C1A964958260" item-length="1139" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Where They Stand on the Deficit</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID E. ROSENBAUM</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROSENBAUM, DAVID E</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The annual Federal budget deficit, the difference between what the Government spends and the tax revenue it receives, is now about $330 billion and is projected to rise to $500 billion by the turn of the century. The deficit began mushrooming in the 1980's because income taxes were cut deeply under Ronald Reagan, while spending increased substantially, especially for Medicare and Medicaid.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The annual Federal budget deficit, the difference between what the Government spends and the tax revenue it receives, is now about $330 billion and is projected to rise to $500 billion by the turn of the century. The deficit began mushrooming in the 1980's because income taxes were cut deeply under Ronald Reagan, while spending increased substantially, especially for Medicare and Medicaid.</p>
        <p>Some economists on both the left and right ends of the political spectrum play down the importance of the deficit. But most economists in the mainstream hold that the deficit is gradually crippling the country by forcing the taxpayers of the future to pay for today's consumption. THE RECORDS</p>
        <p>BUSH: As Vice President, Mr. Bush was in the Administration under which the deficit growth began, and in his own Presidency it has more than doubled. The increase under Mr. Bush was not all his fault. Some was caused by the savings-and-loan bailout. Some was a result of the lower tax revenues and higher spending that grew out of the recession.</p>
        <p>The budget agreement Mr. Bush and Congress negotiated in 1990 kept matters from getting even worse. Congress rejected some of the spending cuts Mr. Bush proposed, but over all, Congress appropriated less money than Mr. Bush requested.</p>
        <p>The main reason the deficit has risen so much is that although Government spending increased during the Bush Presidency by an average of 7.5 percent a year, after adjusting for inflation (as against 1 percent under Ronald Reagan), Mr. Bush refused to support offsetting tax increases.</p>
        <p>CLINTON: Bill Clinton's record as Governor of Arkansas is not directly comparable to that of the President. The Arkansas constitution requires a balanced budget, and to comply with that Mr. Clinton has backed increases in the sales tax and taxes on cigarettes, insurance premiums and gasoline.</p>
        <p>He tried to raise the state income tax but was blocked by the legislature. Thousands of the poorest Arkansas residents were given exemptions from state income taxes. Only eight states have lower taxes.</p>
        <p>The state's budget under Mr. Clinton more or less doubled in size, partly because of inflation and partly because of increased spending for education and other programs.</p>
        <p>PEROT: Mr. Perot has never held public office. THE PHILOSOPHIES</p>
        <p>BUSH: Controlling the deficit is important but not so important as keeping taxes low as a way of generating economic growth and jobs.</p>
        <p>CLINTON: Controlling the deficit is important but not so important as "investing" money to improve highways, communications networks and other installations, as a way of generating economic growth and jobs.</p>
        <p>PEROT: The Federal deficit must be eliminated, not just lowered, before the nation's other problems can be dealt with. THE PROPOSALS</p>
        <p>BUSH: In July, Mr. Bush offered a program that he said would reduce the deficit to $118 billion by 1997, but since then, he has proposed more than $140 billion in additional tax cuts. He insists he will not raise taxes in any circumstances.</p>
        <p>His deficit-cutting measures are grounded in his plan to limit the growth in mandatory programs like Medicare, Medicaid, food stamps and veterans benefits, excluding Social Security. Mr. Bush has never said how the limits would be imposed. He has also proposed freezes on other domestic spending programs, a reduction in Federal subsidies to some affluent Americans like wealthy farmers and a lowering of the military budget.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush favors a Constitutional amendment requiring a balanced budget, but he has never offered a balanced budget himself nor explained what specific steps he favors to reach such a goal.</p>
        <p>CLINTON: Clinton promises to cut the deficit to about $140 billion by 1996. That is based in part on the assumption that the economy will grow somewhat faster than most economists believe is likely. The main deficit-reduction elements are tax increases of about $150 billion and cuts in military spending about $40 billion deeper than those proposed by President Bush.</p>
        <p>About two-thirds of the increased tax revenue would come from higher income taxes on the wealthiest 2 percent of Americans (joint annual incomes over $200,000), a surtax on incomes over $1 million and a higher minimum tax on wealthy taxpayers with large deductions. Taxes would be cut for families with annual incomes below about $90,000 and for some businesses.</p>
        <p>Mr. Clinton also proposes better collection of taxes from foreign companies, a 3 percent reduction in administrative costs and more efficiency in the savings-and-loan bailout. With a goal of generating economic growth and jobs, Mr. Clinton would increase spending by about $220 billion over four years. This "investment" would go to things like education, job training and public works.</p>
        <p>PEROT: Mr. Perot promises to balance the budget after five years. The gasoline tax would be raised 10 cents a gallon each year for five years. The top tax rate would be raised to 33 percent from 31 percent for couples making more than about $90,000. Taxes would be raised on the Social Security benefits received by upper-income taxpayers, and benefits from other Government programs would be taxed. Employers would be taxed on health-insurance premiums worth more than $335 a month.</p>
        <p>Deductions of mortgage interest would be limited to mortgage amounts of $250,000 or less. Federal spending on programs other than the military, mandatory programs and interest on the debt would be cut by 15 percent by eliminating "unnecessary and outdated" Government programs. Military spending would be reduced by $40 billion below the level proposed by Mr. Bush. The capital-gains tax would be eliminated for small businesses, and businesses would get other tax breaks for investment and research. An additional $70 billion would be spent over five years for public works. SCORECARD</p>
        <p>The deficit will be a major problem facing the next President. But neither Mr. Bush nor Mr. Clinton has made it a central campaign issue, and neither has a credible plan for dealing with it. Both candidates have promised to revamp the health-care system. But neither has explained how he would meet the increased cost to the Government, which could run to tens of billions of dollars a year. The only way to reduce the budget deficit is to raise taxes on most Americans, cut popular spending programs or both, and neither Mr. Bush nor Mr. Clinton has proposed doing so. Mr. Perot's proposed tax increases would raise hundreds of billions of dollars over five years, but the spending cuts he offers are less precise and less realistic. He has not developed a plan for limiting medical costs, identified the unnecessary programs he would abolish or explained how some programs like, say, the air-traffic-control system, could be cut by 15 percent without doing grave damage.</p>
        <p>THE 1992 CAMPAIGN: CANDIDATES ON THE ISSUE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
