<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS DIGEST</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="560985"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19921005T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7D61030F936A35753C1A964958260" item-length="614" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS DIGEST</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>Congressional negotiators agreed on a tax bill offering $27 billion in tax breaks and investment incentives in the next five years, many of them meant to aid depressed cities, help the housing industry and encourage personal savings and industrial investment. The measure, which the House and Senate will vote on today or tomorrow, puts President Bush in a political bind: should he sign or veto a bill that cuts some taxes and raises others?  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>Lacking other ideas, economists have turned to the consumer, that abiding American hero, to provide the push the economy needs. All that is needed, these experts say, is a surge in confidence. Then people would loosen the purse strings and start spending again, awakening the economy.  [ D1. ]</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The Economy</p>
        <p>Congressional negotiators agreed on a tax bill offering $27 billion in tax breaks and investment incentives in the next five years, many of them meant to aid depressed cities, help the housing industry and encourage personal savings and industrial investment. The measure, which the House and Senate will vote on today or tomorrow, puts President Bush in a political bind: should he sign or veto a bill that cuts some taxes and raises others?  [ Page A1. ]</p>
        <p>Lacking other ideas, economists have turned to the consumer, that abiding American hero, to provide the push the economy needs. All that is needed, these experts say, is a surge in confidence. Then people would loosen the purse strings and start spending again, awakening the economy.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>The Midwest is seen as the bright spot in an elusive economic recovery, for all its dependence on manufacturing. Unemployment in most Midwestern states is at or below the national average, production outpaces the rest of the nation. And real estate, which never boomed, has not gone bust.  [ A1. ]</p>
        <p>Federal Reserve policy makers meet tomorrow to decide whether to lower interest further. Because so many strategists expect an easing, bonds are already priced as if the central bank had cut its rates.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Congress required that 10 percent of Sematech's $100 million 1993 budget be used for environmental research.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Bill Clinton said he endorsed the free-trade pact with Mexico and Canada, but said he would not sign it unless agreements were reached to require tougher environmental standards and improved conditions for workers in Mexico.  [ A1. ] International</p>
        <p>Why did no crisis erupt when the dollar plunged recently to record lows against the yen? Why did a huge crisis erupt when the pound slipped a few percent against the mark? The answer holds plenty of pointers about the future of Europe's -- and the world's -- monetary system. News Analysis.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>A look at the last quarter illustrates the twinned risks of foreign recessions and currency market convulsions. Britain? Stock prices were about even, but the pound's decline gave American investors a 6.4 percent loss. Germany? Stocks were off so sharply as the economy slowed that the mark's strength merely limited American losses to 9.6 percent.  [ D3. ] The Media Business</p>
        <p>At NBC, daytime programming is under pressure. "We're not really a network anymore," Warren Littlefield, president of NBC Entertainment, said of daytime operations.  [ D1. ]</p>
        <p>Does the British invasion of top magazine editors' jobs reflect better language skills, snob appeal or what? Deirdre Carmody: Magazines.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>Kmart is undertaking an intensive effort to sell fashion amid aisles of appliances, weed killer and toothpaste. Stuart Elliott: Advertising.  [ D7. ]</p>
        <p>How street book peddlers get their wares and how they manage to sell them for such low prices is a mystery that has vexed city authorities and bookstore owners. Street merchants say they buy their books legitimately and just make smaller profits.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>The success of Details, the two-year-old men's fashion magazine, came even though it broke the No. 1 rule for success by repeatedly changing its identity.  [ D6. ]</p>
        <p>New York Telephone plans to transmit television programs over telephone lines next year in a venture with Liberty Cable Television. The system would be the first in the nation.  [ B3. ] Today's Column</p>
        <p>Sears should be a company whose stock is riding high, after agreeing to sell a large portion of its financial network. So, what's the problem? The answers seems to be that many investors are uncomfortable. Kurt Eichenwald: Market Place.  [ D4. ]</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
