<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>G.M. to Open Doors of On-Line National Showroom</title>
    <meta content="01UGEE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Circuits" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="G" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1050569"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Internet and World Wide Web</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">General Motors Corp</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Ford Motor Co</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Chrysler Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Krebs, Michelle</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology/Circuits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Technology, Telecommunications and Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Road Trips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Automobiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C07E6D71638F932A35753C1A96E958260" item-length="602" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>G.M. to Open Doors of On-Line National Showroom</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHELLE KREBS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Krebs, Michelle</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>General Motors Corp hopes to become first auto maker to offer nationwide Internet shopping for cars and trucks sitting on participating dealers' lots; company's GM Buy Power, Web site, will start operating in first quarter of 1999, enabling customers to do everything over Internet except actually buy and take delivery of vehicle, which must still be done at dealership; GM notes that unlike other on-line buying services, GM Buy Power will not limit consumers to shopping a specific geographic area; both Ford Motor Co and Chrysler Corp plan to upgrade their Web sites (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE burgeoning Internet has often been compared with the automobile industry in the early days of mass production. Now the big auto makers want to take more of their business on line.</p>
        <p>The General Motors Corporation intends to become the first auto maker to offer nationwide Internet shopping for the cars and trucks sitting on participating dealers' lots.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE burgeoning Internet has often been compared with the automobile industry in the early days of mass production. Now the big auto makers want to take more of their business on line.</p>
        <p>The General Motors Corporation intends to become the first auto maker to offer nationwide Internet shopping for the cars and trucks sitting on participating dealers' lots.</p>
        <p>The company announced this week that GM Buy Power (www. gmbuypower.com), a Web site, would start operating in the first quarter of 1999, enabling customers to do everything over the Internet except actually buy and take delivery of a vehicle, which must still be done at a dealership.</p>
        <p>The on-line customer will be able to schedule a test drive, ask the dealer to hold or locate a specific vehicle, find out the dealer's best price on a selected vehicle and apply for pre-approved financing from the General Motors Acceptance Corporation. The Web site will list all vehicles in inventory at dealers participating in the service, with the list updated daily.</p>
        <p>Unlike such other on-line buying services as Autobytel and Microsoft's Carpoint, GM Buy Power will  not limit consumers to shopping a specific geographic area, giving them a wider choice, a spokesman for G.M. said.</p>
        <p>G.M. dealers will not pay a monthly subscription fee to participate in the service and, for the first nine months of 1999, G.M. will not charge dealers an enrollment fee. Other services require a monthly fee in return for limiting the number of dealers in an area who can participate.</p>
        <p>All G.M. dealers can be part of GM Buy Power if they agree to certain customer standards; install required computer hardware, which costs about $1,000, and send a dealership manager through training.</p>
        <p>G.M. research shows that customers want the time needed to buy a vehicle at a dealership to be an hour to an hour and a half instead of the usual three to five hours, said Ron Sobrero, the Chevrolet general sales and service manager who is a leader of the national roll-out of the site.</p>
        <p>The Internet is becoming too popular with car shoppers for auto manufacturers to ignore.</p>
        <p>Nearly 25 percent of vehicle shoppers search the Internet for information before buying, a number that is likely to rise to 50 to 60 percent in 2000, according to a recent study by J. D. Power and Associates of Agoura Hills, Calif.</p>
        <p>G.M.'s decision to take the on-line shopping service nationwide follows a successful test started in October in four Western states: California, Oregon, Washington and Idaho. In the test, the Buy Power site received more than 670,000 visits in its first 10 months, with users spending an average of 11 minutes there, making it one of G.M.'s most active sites. More than 60 percent of the dealers in the region participated in the service, and consumers made more than 300,000 on-line searches for GM Buy Power dealers.</p>
        <p>Both Ford Motor Company and the Chrysler Corporation plan to upgrade their Web sites (www2.Ford. com) and (www2.Chryslercorp. com) to offer similar listings of dealer inventory and the ability to find out a dealer's best price. Both currently offer model specifications (but not listings of specific vehicles) and the ability to get a quote from a dealer on a car or truck via phone or E-mail.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
