<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Freedom Center Is Still a Somewhat Vague Notion</title>
    <meta content="24FREE$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="24" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="The Arts/Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/06/24/arts/design/24FREE.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20040629T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1591720"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Freedom Center (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernstein, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Pogrebin, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Museums</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Freedom and Human Rights</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">World Trade Center (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Office Buildings and Commercial Properties</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (NYC)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Lower Manhattan Development Corp</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Bernstein, Tom A</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040624T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A04E1DB1139F937A15755C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1402" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Freedom Center Is Still a Somewhat Vague Notion</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Freedom Center Is Still a Somewhat Vague Notion</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN POGREBIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Pogrebin, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Developer Tom Bernstein, in interview, comments on what he expects Freedom Center, one of cultural institutions that will occupy part of ground zero, to be; Bernstein, longtime friend of Pres Bush, says center's organizing principle will be 'looking at different parts of the world transitioning from tyranny to freedom' and will focus on people who have played important role in that process; others involved in project comment; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The people behind the Freedom Center, one of the cultural institutions chosen this month to occupy ground zero, have spent much of their time so far insisting on what the nascent museum is not.</p>
        <p>It is not an arm of the Bush administration, despite the longtime friendship of its creator, the developer Tom A. Bernstein, with President Bush. It will not be a palace of pro-American propaganda, Mr. Bernstein says, or a place for sentimentally commemorating victims of the Sept. 11 terrorists.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>It is still unclear what the Freedom Center, one of the cultural institutions chosen this month to occupy the World Trade Center site, might include.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The people behind the Freedom Center, one of the cultural institutions chosen this month to occupy ground zero, have spent much of their time so far insisting on what the nascent museum is not.</p>
        <p>It is not an arm of the Bush administration, despite the longtime friendship of its creator, the developer Tom A. Bernstein, with President Bush. It will not be a palace of pro-American propaganda, Mr. Bernstein says, or a place for sentimentally commemorating victims of the Sept. 11 terrorists.</p>
        <p>What is less clear is what the institution will be.</p>
        <p>''We're a work-in-progress,'' Mr. Bernstein said in a recent interview at his office at Chelsea Piers, the sports and entertainment center he built with his partner and fellow presidential friend, Roland W. Betts. (Both men were partners with Mr. Bush in the Texas Rangers baseball team.) ''We have a very strong concept, we have a very strong team and we have a lot of work to do.''</p>
        <p>The center's organizing principle will be ''looking at different parts of the world transitioning from tyranny to freedom,'' Mr. Bernstein said, citing South Africa and the former Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>It will also focus on people who have played important roles in that process. One potential exhibit, for example, might be ''Freedom Beyond Bars,'' in which visitors would walk through prison cells representing those that housed Susan B. Anthony, Mother Jones, the Rev. Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., Nelson Mandela, Vaclav Havel and Natan Sharansky.</p>
        <p>The Freedom Center is ''the one institution that was born of the events of Sept. 11 and links them into a broader theme,'' said Kevin Rampe, president of the Lower Manhattan Development Corporation, which selected it and three other institutions for the World Trade Center site.</p>
        <p>Paula Grant Berry, who lost her husband, David, in the towers and is on the development corporation's Families Advisory Council, said the center suited the site and dovetailed with the memorial, which she helped select. ''I see the memorial as the heart and the Freedom Center as the mind,'' she said.</p>
        <p>The corporation has given the groups six months, starting July 8, to come up with programming, a business plan and a schematic design for their buildings.</p>
        <p>During that period, Mr. Bernstein said, he will ''put together teams of historians, curators and storytellers to develop narratives'' for the center, which is expected to open in 2009. It is modeled, he said, on the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum in Washington and the National Constitution Center in Philadelphia, which feature videos, archival photographs and artifacts. It will also draw on the success of experiential exhibits like those at the Lower East Side Tenement Museum, where visitors walk through the rooms of a former tenement building.</p>
        <p>In the last two and a half years Mr. Bernstein has recruited some 40 scholars and others for the center's planning and advisory committees. These include Bob Kerrey, president of New School University in Manhattan and the former governor and senator from Nebraska; Henry Louis Gates Jr., the chairman of the African and African-American studies department at Harvard; Walter Isaacson, chief executive of the Aspen Institute and author of a recent biography of Benjamin Franklin; and Theodore C. Sorensen, who worked in the Kennedy administration.</p>
        <p>''The danger is that it gets captured by partisan politics,'' said Thomas S. Johnson, who lost his son in the terrorist attack and is on the development corporation board. ''If it is to be a quality institution, it can't be jingoistic and just patriotic.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein points to the range of people on the board as evidence that the center will be nonpartisan. He often mentions in particular Anthony Romero, executive director of the American Civil Liberties Union, and John Raisian, the director and senior fellow of the Hoover Institution.</p>
        <p>''Democrats and Republicans will come and go,'' Mr. Bernstein said. ''This institution will stand.''</p>
        <p>While the advisory committee has not met face-to-face, the planning committee has gathered to discuss what the Freedom Center might include.</p>
        <p>Planning for the center is also being overseen by Peter W. Kunhardt, a documentary filmmaker who was a co-producer of the eight-hour PBS series ''Freedom: A History of US,'' the PBS series ''The American President'' and the ABC series ''Lincoln.''</p>
        <p>Initially the center planned to have four floors, each with its own focus: the terrorist attacks, New York City, the nation and the world. It has moved away from that configuration without yet settling on an alternative.</p>
        <p>The New-York Historical Society applied for a place at ground zero that would focus on the city, but Kenneth T. Jackson, who this month stepped down as president, ended up on the Freedom Center's advisory board instead. ''There was part of me that really wanted the New-York Historical Society to do it,'' Mr. Jackson said. ''But to be honest, I just want it done.''</p>
        <p>The Freedom Center is expected to cost about $250 million to build and $25 million a year to operate, Mr. Bernstein said. He hopes to raise the operating money largely from membership dues and a nominal admission fee. Five to 10 million people are expected to visit the site each year.</p>
        <p>Ruth J. Abram, the director of the Lower East Side Tenement Museum, who is on the planning committee, said the center should start by having ''conversations all over the world'' about what belongs in a freedom center.</p>
        <p>Alex Boraine, the founder and president of the International Center for Transitional Justice, who is on the center's committee of scholars and advisers, said he had stressed to Mr. Bernstein the importance of making the center about more than America. ''Freedom is essentially a universal quest,'' said Mr. Boraine, who was deputy chairman of the post-apartheid Truth and Reconciliation Commission in South Africa. ''It really ought to be representative of the struggle of mankind rather than of one particular nation.''</p>
        <p>Others involved in the planning said it was important that the center not whitewash the struggles on the road to freedom. ''There will be a focus on the creation of America and the writing of the constitution and the founding of the first great Western democracy,'' said Fareed Zakaria, a Newsweek columnist who is an adviser to the center. ''But there will also be a focus on the peculiar way liberty was defined to exclude blacks and to exclude women.</p>
        <p>''It will be more thought-provoking and produce a greater sense of reflection, rather than something that creates a sense of veneration,'' he added.</p>
        <p>The center, which starts out without any collections or holdings, plans to develop exhibitions, lectures, film series and educational programming in partnership with institutions like the Aspen Institute, New York University, WNYC Radio and New Visions for Public Schools, which aims to improve New York City's public schools.</p>
        <p>It will also borrow exhibits from organizations like the International Center for Transitional Justice and the International Coalition of Historic Site Museums of Conscience, whose members include the Gulag Museum at Perm 36 in Russia and the District Six Museum in South Africa.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bernstein said he had ''grown up in the world of human rights'' as the son of Robert L. Bernstein, the founding chairman of Human Rights Watch. He is the board president of Human Rights First, formerly the Lawyers Committee for Human Rights, and is on the executive committee of the Holocaust Museum.</p>
        <p>His advisers, meanwhile, say they are keenly aware of the need to guard against allowing the center's program to veer into cheerleading for America.</p>
        <p>''It could so easily be taken over and made into this flag-waving, rah-rah thing,'' Mr. Boraine said. ''We have to make sure the politicians don't take over and use it for their own ends.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  June 29, 2004, Tuesday  An article in The Arts on Thursday about the Freedom Center, a planned cultural attraction chosen for ground zero in Manhattan, included a name supplied by the organizers erroneously on a list of historic figures whose political imprisonment may be depicted in an exhibit. Susan B. Anthony was not held in a prison cell; after her arrest for illegal voting in the 1872 presidential election she was placed under the custody of a United States marshal.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: June 29, 2004, Tuesday</p>
        <p>An article in The Arts on Thursday about the Freedom Center, a planned cultural attraction chosen for ground zero in Manhattan, included a name supplied by the organizers erroneously on a list of historic figures whose political imprisonment may be depicted in an exhibit. Susan B. Anthony was not held in a prison cell; after her arrest for illegal voting in the 1872 presidential election she was placed under the custody of a United States marshal.</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
        <p>&lt;br&gt;</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
