<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>N.F.L. Promotes Art Shell To Senior Vice President</title>
    <meta content="26SHEL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="7" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/26/sports/football/26shell.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1584707"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">George, Thomas</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shell, Art</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Appointments and Executive Changes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Shell, Art</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DEFD7153EF935A15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="488" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>N.F.L. Promotes Art Shell To Senior Vice President</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Art Shell Is Named a Top N.F.L. Executive</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By THOMAS GEORGE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">George, Thomas</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>NFL names Art Shell senior vice president for football operations (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Art Shell was named the National Football League senior vice president for football operations and development yesterday.</p>
        <p>Shell will supervise all league football operations, N.F.L. Europe, the league's relationship with college football and youth football activities. He will serve as a nonvoting member of the competition committee.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Art Shell was named the National Football League senior vice president for football operations and development.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Art Shell was named the National Football League senior vice president for football operations and development yesterday.</p>
        <p>Shell will supervise all league football operations, N.F.L. Europe, the league's relationship with college football and youth football activities. He will serve as a nonvoting member of the competition committee.</p>
        <p>He replaces John Beake, who recently retired.</p>
        <p>Shell, 57, played offensive tackle for the Oakland/Los Angeles Raiders from 1968 to 1982, was coach of the Raiders from 1989 to 1994 and was inducted into the Hall of Fame in 1989. He was the first African-American coach in pro football's modern era.</p>
        <p>Shell will report directly to Commissioner Paul Tagliabue.</p>
        <p>''In his playing and coaching career and in the past two years at league headquarters, Art Shell has demonstrated the ability to successfully manage a wide range of responsibilities,'' Tagliabue said in a statement. ''We are pleased to have an executive with his expertise and talent in this key position.''</p>
        <p>For the past two years, Shell worked in the league's appeals office for player discipline. The year before, he worked for the league office in handling college relations.</p>
        <p>''This is a job that covers a lot of areas,'' Shell said in a telephone interview from his N.F.L. office. ''Most of my adult life has been spent working in the National Football League. I relish this opportunity. It says a lot for African-Americans, that if you put forth the effort you can get an opportunity like this. I will especially enjoy working with youth football, to give back to the youth in teaching the game not just to boys but also girls.''</p>
        <p>Shell joins Harold Henderson, the league's executive vice president for labor relations and the chairman on the N.F.L. management council, as the highest ranking African-American executives in the N.F.L.</p>
        <p>Shell played in 207 regular-season games and in Super Bowls XI and XV, and he was an eight-time Pro Bowl selection. As Raiders coach, he was 56-41 and gained three playoff berths.</p>
        <p>Cyrus Mehri, counsel for the Fritz Pollard Alliance, a group promoting the hiring of minorities to coaching, scouting and management positions, applauded Shell's appointment.</p>
        <p>''Art Shell has been a great pioneer in N.F.L. history,'' Mehri said in a telephone interview from his Washington office. ''His pioneering effort as an N.F.L. head coach and the understated way he handled himself before and after his head-coaching job is commendable. We are delighted to learn of this opportunity, and it is a further example of leadership by Commissioner Tagliabue of getting minorities into positions of prominence in the N.F.L.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
