<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Kerry Says He Would Clear the Air With American Allies</title>
    <meta content="26KERR$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/05/26/politics/campaign/26kerry.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1584681"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Draft and Recruitment (Military)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Iraq</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Toner, Robin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Northwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Foreign Policy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/National Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East/Iraq</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Iraq</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Kerry, John F</person>
        <person class="online_producer">Bush, George W</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040526T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F06EED8153EF935A15756C0A9629C8B63" item-length="921" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Kerry Says He Would Clear the Air With American Allies</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Kerry Says He Would Clear the Air With U.S. Allies</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN TONER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Toner, Robin</byline>
      <dateline>PORTLAND, Ore., May 25</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John Kerry denounces Bush adminstration for conducting foreign policy of 'arrogance and ineptness' and argues that only a new president can 'clear the air' with America's allies, speech in Portland, Ore; also asserts that if elected president, he would have foreign policy that 'absolutely makes it unnecesary to have a draft in this nation'; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John Kerry, the presumed Democratic presidential nominee, denounced the Bush administration here on Tuesday for conducting a foreign policy of ''arrogance and ineptness'' and argued that only a new president could ''clear the air'' with the United States' allies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry also asserted, in response to a question from a high school student about the possibility of another military draft, ''If you elect me president of the United States, I will give us a foreign policy that absolutely makes it unnecessary to have a draft in this nation.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Senator John Kerry, in Oregon, denounced the Bush Administration for conducting a foreign policy of "arrogance and ineptness."</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Senator John Kerry, the presumed Democratic presidential nominee, denounced the Bush administration here on Tuesday for conducting a foreign policy of ''arrogance and ineptness'' and argued that only a new president could ''clear the air'' with the United States' allies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry also asserted, in response to a question from a high school student about the possibility of another military draft, ''If you elect me president of the United States, I will give us a foreign policy that absolutely makes it unnecessary to have a draft in this nation.''</p>
        <p>He accused the Bush administration of ''running a kind of clandestine draft'' that ''turned the National Guard and the Reserve into almost active duty.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry's comments came at a forum billed as a discussion of high gasoline prices and the need for energy independence. He asserted that drivers were paying a ''Saudi-George Bush gasoline tax'' because of the administration's mishandling of energy policy. But the audience quickly turned its questions to Iraq, one day after President Bush began a new effort to explain and justify his policies there, in the face of continued turmoil in the region and doubts at home.</p>
        <p>Steve Schmidt, a spokesman for the Bush campaign, denounced Mr. Kerry's remarks as another ''in a series of gratuitous political attacks'' intended to cover up his lack of a vision for Iraq. ''John Kerry, rather than explaining his indecision and vacillation regarding the war on terror, routinely resorts to political attacks,'' Mr. Schmidt said.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry told his audience that in fact he had no personal quarrel with Mr. Bush, whom he described as ''a nice man.'' But he asserted that the stakes could not be higher in this election, nor the choices starker.</p>
        <p>When one man asked if it was realistic to think that a new president could begin anew in the Middle East, Mr. Kerry responded, ''I believe it will take a new president of the United States to clear the air, to re-establish American credibility in the world and to be able to reach out to leaders not just in the Middle East but all over the world.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry said that after 20 years in the Senate, particularly on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee, he had had many relationships with leaders around the world. ''I believe I could sit down with them at a level of trust that would allow us to begin an entirely new dialogue,'' he said.</p>
        <p>This trip to Portland and Seattle marked Mr. Kerry's second visit to the Pacific Northwest in a little over a week, reflecting the region's political importance to the Democrats.</p>
        <p>At a fund-raiser in Portland on Tuesday night, before a cheering crowd of several hundred Democratic donors, Mr. Kerry continued his attack, egged on by shouts of ''Throw him out!'' as he made his case against Mr. Bush. ''We're proud of our troops,'' the senator said. ''And we're proud of what they're doing for their country. But they deserve leadership that's as good as they are.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry said he believed that ''this is the most arrogant, reckless and ideological foreign policy ever pursued in the modern times of our country.'' He also declared that ''not for one instant am I going to let these armchair patriots in Washington define for us our rights and our ability to question the direction of this nation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry crossed a milestone Tuesday, officially launching the new, and larger, campaign plane that will carry him through November. At a rally at Ronald Reagan Washington National Airport Tuesday morning, before heading west, Mr. Kerry compared his new plane to the aircraft that he and other soldiers used to see flying overhead in South Vietnam, ferrying troops into the country, carrying the lucky ones home again. The soldiers called them ''freedom birds,'' he recalled.</p>
        <p>''This is my freedom bird now,'' Mr. Kerry said.</p>
        <p>Despite his lacerating criticism of Mr. Bush's foreign policy, Mr. Kerry shied from direct questions about Mr. Bush's speech on Iraq. He said he would have more to say on the subject later and noted that he would deliver a major speech on foreign policy and national security later this week.</p>
        <p>That speech, much anticipated by Mr. Kerry's fellow Democrats, is expected to begin what his campaign described as an 11-day focus on ''security and strength for a new world.''</p>
        <p>David Wade, a campaign spokesman, said meanwhile that Mr. Kerry would make a decision ''soon'' on whether to delay accepting the Democratic presidential nomination.</p>
        <p>The Associated Press reported Tuesday that Mr. Kerry was under pressure from other Democrats to decide quickly, although Mr. Wade said there was ''no timetable.''</p>
        <p>Last week, some Democrats floated the idea of postponing his acceptance of the nomination to even the financial playing field with Mr. Bush. Both candidates plan to use federal money for the general election campaign, meaning each must abide by a spending cap of about $75 million.</p>
        <p>That cap begins once they are formally nominated -- late July for Mr. Kerry, but not until early September for Mr. Bush -- and will give Mr. Bush a significant financial advantage.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
