<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; For Japanese chip makers, a boom time mixed with caution.</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="10" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="759791"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COMPUTER CHIPS</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">JAPAN</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">POLLACK, ANDREW</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/Japan</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computer Chips</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950503T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE4DB143AF930A35756C0A963958260" item-length="593" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; For Japanese chip makers, a boom time mixed with caution.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Andrew Pollack</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">POLLACK, ANDREW</byline>
      <dateline>TOKYO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MUCH of Corporate Japan is closed this week for the so-called Golden Week holidays. But semiconductor factories will keep operating. Demand for computer memory chips continues to soar, defying predictions that the chip shortage would turn to glut this year.</p>
        <p>But good news for chip producers here does not necessarily mean good news for their stocks. Indeed, while the shares of American chip companies have generally outperformed a strong American stock market, the shares of Japan's big chip makers have generally performed worse than the slumping Japanese market.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MUCH of Corporate Japan is closed this week for the so-called Golden Week holidays. But semiconductor factories will keep operating. Demand for computer memory chips continues to soar, defying predictions that the chip shortage would turn to glut this year.</p>
        <p>But good news for chip producers here does not necessarily mean good news for their stocks. Indeed, while the shares of American chip companies have generally outperformed a strong American stock market, the shares of Japan's big chip makers have generally performed worse than the slumping Japanese market.</p>
        <p>One reason is that most American semiconductor companies, like the Intel Corporation and Texas Instruments Inc., specialize in chips and gain directly from a booming market.</p>
        <p>The major Japanese semiconductor companies, however, are large conglomerates, like Hitachi Ltd. and the Toshiba Corporation, that make everything from televisions to turbines. While semiconductor sales might be strong, the other businesses of these companies are being hurt by the weak economy in Japan and by the appreciation of the yen against the dollar.</p>
        <p>Another factor has been the fear that demand for chips, which has been fueled by strong worldwide sales of personal computers, may end at any time. Recently, those fears have been ebbing.</p>
        <p>"I don't think we are done buying PC's," said Steven Myers, an analyst with Jardine Fleming Securities in Japan. "I don't see any sign that this is suddenly going to come to an end." He said that with prices relatively high for memory chips, Japanese companies could still make money on them even at the current exchange rates of roughly 84 yen to the dollar.</p>
        <p>With stocks weak and chip demand strong, there should be a way to invest. Mr. Myers recommends the NECCorporation, among the big chip makers. It has led the other companies in moving semiconductor manufacturing overseas, insulating it somewhat from the effects of the strong yen.</p>
        <p>Taketoshi Yamamoto, an electronics analyst at Morgan Stanley &amp; Company in Tokyo, has "strong buy" recommendations on two specialized stocks -- the Kyocera Corporation and the Rohm Company -- whose fortunes are more closely tied to the semiconductor market than those of the big conglomerates.</p>
        <p>Kyocera is the world leader in ceramic packages for microprocessors and other sophisticated chips. It is also heavily involved in the fast-growing mobile telephone business in Japan. Rohm is a maker of specialized semiconductors for video processing and some niche markets.</p>
        <p>Yet another approach is to invest in companies that make the equipment used to make semiconductors. Peter Wolff, an analyst at CS First Boston in Tokyo, likes Tokyo Electron Ltd., which is Japan's largest vendor of such equipment and has a huge order backlog. Mr. Myers of Jardine Fleming likes Tokyo Electron and the Advantest Corporation, Japan's leader in semiconductor testing equipment.</p>
        <p>But Joseph Osha, an electronics analyst with Smith New Court (Japan) Ltd., says it is already too late to invest in semiconductor equipment companies. He argues that growth in sales of chips will slow in 1996. That slowdown will spook semiconductor companies into cutting back on capital spending in 1996, slicing the profits of companies like Tokyo Electron and Advantest.</p>
        <p>"It is not necessary to assume that the world semiconductor market will collapse in 1996 to believe that capital spending will weaken," Mr. Osha wrote in a recent report. As for stocks of semiconductor equipment manufacturers, he said, "the time to sell is now."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
