<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>From Suspect To Samaritan For Youth, 16</title>
    <meta content="10SHOO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="986554"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New York City</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dawkins, Raheem</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Roane, Kit R</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Giuliani, Rudolph W (Mayor)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">O'Shea, Michael (Police Officer)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Safir, Howard (Comr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Law Enforcement and Security</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Attacks on Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Transit Systems</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Police</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980110T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E04E4DE1739F933A25752C0A96E958260" item-length="792" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>From Suspect To Samaritan For Youth, 16</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KIT R. ROANE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Roane, Kit R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>16-year-old Raheem Dawkins is visited in hospital by Mayor Rudolph Giuliani and Police Comr Howard Safir and praised as good samaritan, eight days after being shot by off-duty police officer he was trying to save from beating or worse and was initially viewed as possible suspect; incident, which occurred on January 1 after Officer Michael O'Shea was attacked by four men in Canal Street subway station, described; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Eight days after being shot by an off-duty police officer he was trying to save from a beating or worse, a 16-year-old police buff was visited at his hospital bedside by Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and praised as a good Samaritan in a case in which he was initially viewed as a possible suspect.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to give him something to show our appreciation,'' the Mayor said after meeting the youth, Raheem Dawkins, at St. Vincent's Hospital and giving him a Police Department cap. ''As soon as he recovers we will do something for him at City Hall, give him some official recognition of his acting as a good Samaritan.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Eight days after being shot by an off-duty police officer he was trying to save from a beating or worse, a 16-year-old police buff was visited at his hospital bedside by Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani and praised as a good Samaritan in a case in which he was initially viewed as a possible suspect.</p>
        <p>''We wanted to give him something to show our appreciation,'' the Mayor said after meeting the youth, Raheem Dawkins, at St. Vincent's Hospital and giving him a Police Department cap. ''As soon as he recovers we will do something for him at City Hall, give him some official recognition of his acting as a good Samaritan.''</p>
        <p>The accolades were in sharp contrast to the treatment Mr. Dawkins received after the shooting. In the original police report of the incident, which occurred on Jan. 1 after Officer Michael O'Shea was attacked by several men at a Canal Street subway station, Mr. Dawkins was described as a ''possible suspect,'' a definition one investigator in the case privately called ''outrageous.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dawkins was eventually cleared of any wrongdoing. After initially failing to provide any information about the incident, the department released a report on the shooting yesterday morning, after being questioned about it by a reporter from The New York Times.</p>
        <p>According to the police report, Officer O'Shea, 31, was off duty and traveling north on the No. 4 line with his girlfriend after celebrating New Year's Eve when he spotted four men smoking marijuana and rough-housing in his subway car. One of the men walked up and struck the officer's girlfriend in the head, said Lieut. Dennis Cirillo, a department spokesman. He said an argument then took place, with Officer O'Shea identifying himself as a policeman before he and his girlfriend fled onto the subway platform at Canal Street.</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Cirillo said the suspects followed, shouting, ''Get his gun, get his gun'' as they struggled with Officer O'Shea in front of the token booth. During the fight, Mr. Dawkins arrived. The report then states that Officer O'Shea's gun discharged and a  bullet struck the youth in the thigh.</p>
        <p>The report does not say that Mr. Dawkins was trying to help Officer O'Shea. But Mayor Giuliani did, and Mr. Dawkins and his family were pleased by that.</p>
        <p>''We are happy that the Mayor has acknowledged Raheem,'' said his brother, James Dawkins, a security guard. ''It's a good gesture by the city and took the stigma of possible perpetrator off of him.''</p>
        <p>He added that Mr. Dawkins felt no ill will toward the officer who accidentally shot him, or toward the Police Department he had grown up admiring. Mr. Dawkins, a sophomore at South Shore High School in Brooklyn, used to play with his brother's badge, and for the last three years has done community work with police officers through the 73d Precinct's Law Enforcement Explorers Program. His dream has been to become an officer himself, his family said.</p>
        <p>''Raheem knows that Officer O'Shea didn't mean for this to happen, and we want him to know that our prayers are with him,'' James  Dawkins said.</p>
        <p>Police Commissioner Howard Safir said there may someday be a place for Mr. Dawkins in the police force.</p>
        <p>''From what I have seen, he is exactly the kind of young man we would like,'' he said.</p>
        <p>''Physically fit, energetic, he didn't hesitate to help a police officer,'' Mr. Safir said. ''A very positive attitude.''</p>
        <p>He also defended the Police Department for initially failing to release any information about the shooting to reporters, even though the department routinely informs news organizations of incidents in which officers fire their weapons.</p>
        <p>''It was an omission,'' he said, blaming the mistake on miscommunication between detectives working on the case and the department's public information office. ''There was nothing conspiratorial about it.  They just made a mistake.''</p>
        <p>In Mr. Dawkins's hospital room yesterday, flowers and cards from well-wishers were abundant. Mr. Dawkins wore a Correction Officer cap, which he quickly removed when Mayor Giuliani offered him a New York City Police Department cap in trade.</p>
        <p>''I suggested that he alternate them,'' the Mayor said. He said Mr. Dawkins beamed when Mr. Safir also handed over a Police Department T-shirt.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
