<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Review/Film;   She's Plain, She's Plump; In Short, She's Perfect</title>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="15" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="330973"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MOTION PICTURES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">REVIEWS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FESTIVALS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">CANBY, VINCENT</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">TOO BEAUTIFUL FOR YOU (MOVIE)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">NEW YORK FILM FESTIVAL</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Festivals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900302T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEFD81738F931A35750C0A966958260" item-length="757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Review/Film;   She's Plain, She's Plump; In Short, She's Perfect</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: ''Too Beautiful for You'' was shown as part of the 1989 New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Vincent Canby's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Sept. 22, 1989. The film, in French with English subtitles, opens today at Cinema Studio, Broadway at 66th Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: ''Too Beautiful for You'' was shown as part of the 1989 New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Vincent Canby's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Sept. 22, 1989. The film, in French with English subtitles, opens today at Cinema Studio, Broadway at 66th Street.</p>
        <p>''Too Beautiful for You'' was shown as part of the 1989 New York Film Festival. Following are excerpts from Vincent Canby's review, which appeared in The New York Times on Sept. 22, 1989. The film, in French with English subtitles, opens today at Cinema Studio, Broadway at 66th Street.</p>
        <p>Bernard (Gerard Depardieu), a prosperous garage owner and automobile salesman, is in a Continental fix. He is married to the beautiful, model-chic Florence (Carole Bouquet) when he develops an inexplicable passion for the sweet, plain, somewhat overweight Colette (Josiane Balasko), a temporary secretary not in the bloom of youth.</p>
        <p>It's a situation that is best appreciated by French audiences more serious than Americans are about husband-wife-mistress triangles, especially as defined in boulevard farce. Bernard has somehow got the cart before the horse. He is married to the woman who should be his mistress and in love with the woman who should be his wife.</p>
        <p>In ''Too Beautiful for You'' (''Trop Belle Pour Toi''), Bertrand Blier takes this rather slim irony and develops it into an exceptionally rich romantic comedy. Though ''Too Beautiful for You'' has its share of scenes in which people pop into the wrong bedrooms, and though the characters pretend to know what they're doing from start to finish, the slick funniness has a somber edge to it.</p>
        <p>The film is the dark other side of the kind of classic bedroom farce in which people never successfully make it to the bed.</p>
        <p>The new film will disappoint anyone who has delighted in the nerviness that has characterized the Blier work in the past. Yet ''Too Beautiful for You'' is as risky and full of wit as anything the writer and director has done. It is short on plot and plays fast and loose with the conventions of movie reality.</p>
        <p>Many scenes are simply the fantasies of the characters, though Mr. Blier doesn't waste time identifying them as such. At times the actors address the camera directly, as if they were in the sort of novel in which the author goes into a character's mind whenever convenient. This literary quality will offend purists who believe that movies should be seen and not heard, though much of what is heard here is wonderfully muddled and self-serving. There are reminders of both Eric Rohmer and Alain Resnais in the screenplay.</p>
        <p>Mr. Blier has described ''Too Beautiful for You'' as a film primarily concerned with women. He is correct up to a point: that is, to the point at which one considers the gargantuan presence of Mr. Depardieu. Even in a role that is comparatively passive, Mr. Depardieu cannot help being an aggressive force, a figure of such active confusion that his Bernard is the most riveting character in the movie.</p>
        <p>Bernard is a self-made man, still amazed at his good fortune in having married the somewhat better-born Florence. She is magnificent to look at, a perfect mother to their two children and deeply in love with him. In one of the film's most comic and moving moments, Florence tells the guests at their wedding dinner that though she has been with other men, ''They flew over me.'' Her love for Bernard, she says, will hurt.</p>
        <p>With Colette he feels at ease. There are no subtleties in their relationship. Their lovemaking is flat-out eroticism, which Mr. Blier records with steamy humor and truth. Colette, after one such rendezvous, full of what the sex manuals used to call afterglow, approaches a strange man on a railway platform. ''I have just spent three hours making love,'' she says to his bewilderment, for no other reason than that she has never been so satisfied.</p>
        <p>Miss Balasko is superb as the pliant but utterly direct Colette, though she's never quite the frump the movie makes her out to be. After her first surprise at meeting Florence, whom Bernard wants to abandon in her favor, Colette seizes her opportunity and throws herself into the affair with abandon. She's no middle-aged waif but a womanly woman without disguises or defenses.</p>
        <p>Her opposite is Miss Bouquet's Florence, whose God-given beauty sets her off from everyone else. It intimidates. Florence is also intelligent enough to realize that it can be boring. ''What's left to desire when you have perfection?'' Bernard says at one point.</p>
        <p>Though ''Too Beautiful for You'' doesn't worry much about what will finally happen, it moves effortlessly, briskly, from beginning to end at the clip of an iceboat sailing across a perfect surface. It knows that love is a serious business, and that it can also be very comic to anyone looking on from the outside.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
