<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Art of Memory: What Rooms Reveal</title>
    <meta content="23POLI$14" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="23" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="House &amp; Home/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Home and Garden; Style; Books" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/08/23/garden/23POLI.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20010830T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1319350"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Havana (Cuba)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">Cuba</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Polidori, Robert</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Faxas, Luisa</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Robert Polidori: Havana (Book)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Home and Garden</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Books</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Engineering and Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba/Havana</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Caribbean and Bermuda/Cuba</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Photography</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Architecture</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Buildings (Structures)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Books and Literature</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010823T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05EEDC1431F930A1575BC0A9679C8B63" item-length="1898" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Art of Memory: What Rooms Reveal</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">The Art of Memory: What Rooms Reveal</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM L. HAMILTON</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Interview with Robert Polidori, photographer who specializes in interior subjects; his photographs of interior of 12-room, turn-of-the-century house in Havana, Cuba, owned by Senora Luisa Faxas, as well as other dwellings in city, will be published in September by Steidl Press as Robert Polidori: Havana; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>ROBERT POLIDORI, a photographer, has the gaze of a blind man. His face appears to listen rather than look. Mr. Polidori's camera is his sight.</p>
        <p>''One word comes to mind -- acceptance,'' he said of his photograph of the grand salon of Señora Luisa Faxas in Havana.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The photograher Robert Polidori turns a lens on architecture's interior life</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>ROBERT POLIDORI, a photographer, has the gaze of a blind man. His face appears to listen rather than look. Mr. Polidori's camera is his sight.</p>
        <p>''One word comes to mind -- acceptance,'' he said of his photograph of the grand salon of Señora Luisa Faxas in Havana.</p>
        <p>''Acceptance of her condition,'' he recalled. ''Laissez-faire.''</p>
        <p>Beneath a Murano-glass chandelier hanging from a falling ceiling, an office desk, stacked with broken books, has skidded into a corner. A painting of a regal hunting scene, slit and stained, swings on a wall that looks streaked by tears. It is as though the elegant neoclassical room has been literally shaken by events -- Castro's socialist coup in 1959.</p>
        <p>''She was born in Spain -- Barcelona, Catalonian,'' Mr. Polidori continued, speaking of Señora Faxas. ''She had two or three children, who came to the U.S., and she hasn't seen them since. She wouldn't go to the U.S. -- bourgeoisie came to the U.S. Aristocrats wouldn't come.''</p>
        <p>With an archaeologist's as much as an artist's eye, Mr. Polidori, 50,  said that he photographed the 12-room, turn-of-the-century house for the same reasons that he has dwelt upon architectural and interior subjects for 20 years, a specialist's field where he is now well respected as an exceptional witness. His work has included the restoration of the palace at Versailles, tenement apartments on the Lower East Side in New York left vacant by the deaths of their tenants, empty snipers' nests in Beirut and, in May, the control rooms at the Chernobyl-4 reactor -- both operational and burnt. Mr. Polidori's views of Havana will be published next month as ''Robert Polidori: Havana'' (Steidl, $75).</p>
        <p>''Rooms are metaphors and catalysts for states of being,'' he said. ''This room is psychologically naked. Señora Faxas lived in unique circumstances -- living in exile from Spain, then living in the memories of what her exile used to be. She was dedicated to this. She actually enjoyed seeing, day by day, the decay of the past she treasured.</p>
        <p>''They say how poor the Havanans are. Most of this water damage could have been prevented simply by putting plastic sheeting on the roof. Señora Faxas watched the house degrade. She loved my being there photographing. It was her work of art.''</p>
        <p>Visited at his apartment on the Upper West Side, Mr. Polidori offered a chair. The apartment, on the 32nd floor, has a panoramic view south and west across the Hudson River. Inside, the apartment barely has a place to sit.</p>
        <p>''You want to sit in a nice chair?'' he asked, indicating a plywood side chair.</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori's interest in architecture might well describe his New York apartment. ''What interests me in architecture is not so much the architecture itself, but the way people reappropriate it,'' he said. ''How they actually use it -- how they inhabit it.''</p>
        <p>For Mr. Polidori, home is a serviceable hotel. Steel shelving, yellow photographic-print boxes, developing equipment and a huddle of luggage furnish the living and dining rooms. The bathroom looks like a bathroom in a medical suite. The kitchen's refrigerator houses film supplies.</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori lives alone. He travels six months of the year. ''I'm fascinated by the world,'' he said. ''Being an Aquarian, I can say probably I suffer from the fault of loving the world more than people.''</p>
        <p>By background Corsican and French Canadian, born in Montreal, Mr. Polidori is blunt and courtly -- a bit of a Joseph Mitchell character, like the residents in ''Up in the Old Hotel.'' He has a casino card-dealer's dry demeanor. It is frequently drollery in disguise. His observations, on subjects from astrology to assumptions of espionage by international organizations like Unesco, which sponsored a trip to Libya, are opinions calculated to disrupt. In speech, he might be Damon Runyon teaching college.</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori keeps an apartment in Paris, where he lived for 14 years. He moved back to New York in 1997. ''You make more money in America,'' he said. ''They pay you on time. France is fun to live in -- working is bad. Work here is good -- living is bad. But you don't get paid to live.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori studied experimental filmmaking in the 1960's and 70's, making seven short films and working for Jonas Mekas at the Anthology Film Archives. His photography, shown at the Pace/MacGill Gallery in New York, is included in the collections of the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Bibliothèque Nationale. His photographs of Havana, published in The New Yorker, received an Alfred Eisenstaedt Award for magazine photography in 1999. He has been a staff photographer there since 1988.</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori said he segued into still photography because ''I thought there was room to move.''</p>
        <p>''I didn't think anybody was any good. It seemed to me so easy, and so cheap.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori typically uses a view camera with large-format film, but has no favorites. ''For me a good camera is a dead camera -- no personality,'' he said. ''But, I am emotionally attached to certain lenses.'' Mr. Polidori uses Schneider lenses, which have a ''wide image circle,'' he said, important for perspective in photographing architecture.</p>
        <p>Elisabeth Biondi, visuals editor at The New Yorker, whose responsibilities include the magazine's photography and who hired Mr. Polidori, said that she thought the strength of the work was not technique. ''It's interpretive rather than documentary,'' she said, ''which, when you look at traditional architectural photography, is often missing. He's interested in archaeology and history, and his curiosity makes him probe and interpret. But it's a lyrical romantic quality founded on fact, not just sweet romantic sentiment. He's journalistic about it.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori has visited archaeological sites, like Leptis Magna, the 2,000-year-old Roman ruin in Libya, as a student of history and as a photographer. He considers his photography an archaeological art. ''I like seeing time,'' he explained. Even rooms, like Señora Faxas' salon, revealed ''levels of time -- like archaeology,'' he said. ''Rooms deal with memory.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori said he was influenced strongly by a book, ''The Art of Memory,'' by Frances A. Yates, which discusses mnemonic systems in antiquity.</p>
        <p>The ''art of memory,'' invented by Simonides, a Greek lyric poet, employs architectural features in a space as devices to recall abstractions like ideas. Mr. Polidori's photographs could be modern memory systems; details like an unopened bottle of Champagne on a Louis XVI-style desk in Señora Faxas' library conjure concepts like hope for an irretrievable past.</p>
        <p>''You're seeing indices of somebody's personal values,'' he said. ''How they feel about themselves.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori has photographed new ruins like the reactor at Chernobyl-4 and the adjacent town of Pripyat, evacuated during the nuclear accident on April 26, 1986, which killed 30 people. ''I think this is a world-important site, a modern pilgrimage site,'' said Mr. Polidori, who visited Chernobyl for five days, comparing it to Leptis Magna in cultural, if cautionary, significance.</p>
        <p>''Two days after the accident, they took everybody out,'' he said, speaking of Pripyat. ''After the sarcophagus was built around the reactor and the initial cleanup, they let people come back and take some of their belongings away. People took kids' dolls and rugs, and they found out later that they were making people sick.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori photographed a schoolroom in Pripyat, which looks slowly exploded by disuse and decay. On the blackboard is written, in Russian: ''There is no way back. Farewell Pripyat. 28 April 1986.''</p>
        <p>He also took photographs of the technicians working in Control Room 2 -- the only part of the Chernobyl-4 complex still in operation. ''They're the last of the Mohicans in this place,'' Mr. Polidori said. ''These guys are right near the sarcophagus.'' In the photographs, radiation badges that register the day's exposure are clearly visible on the breasts of each white uniform. The men, in their white caps, could be pastry chefs.</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori also photographed Control Room 4, which was incinerated -- a stark portrait of a burn victim. ''That pink stuff is an antiradiation spray,'' he said of the rosy char of the walls. This year is the 15th anniversary of the incident.</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori's sense of place is often also a sense of loss -- whether the violence of an event like Chernobyl or lives bled by circumstances like those of the people in Havana. A couple who asked not to be named in his book posed in their new, neat, ornately furnished five-room house. Their family home, the Villa Isabel, a 15-room colonnaded house with 20-foot ceilings, once a cultural center and now vacant, is pictured on a previous page.</p>
        <p>''They weren't forced out,'' Mr. Polidori said. ''They hadn't the money to keep it. They bought a modest house, and a few sentimental items came with them. They had a small Rembrandt.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori called possessions in photographs ''the detritus of a person's life.'' He said he lived in his own apartment like a hotel guest because he couldn't build the house of his dreams.</p>
        <p>''I just want to work,'' he said. ''By the time I had the money, I'd be too old. Here, I can draw you my dream house right away.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Polidori suddenly started a sketch with a pencil on paper -- a piece of stationery from the Golden Ring Hotel in Moscow -- like someone scraping away at a lottery ticket. The drawing had a mosque-like courtyard with a fountain and balconies and palms, in a mixture of Islamic and Roman and Ottoman tastes.</p>
        <p>Like the rooms in a blind man's house, it was rich with imagination.</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 30, 2001, Thursday  An article last Thursday about the architectural photography of Robert Polidori, whose book about Havana is to be published next month, misstated the year in which he joined The New Yorker magazine. It was 1998, not 1988.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 30, 2001, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article last Thursday about the architectural photography of Robert Polidori, whose book about Havana is to be published next month, misstated the year in which he joined The New Yorker magazine. It was 1998, not 1988.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
