<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>TEARING APART EASTERN AIRLINES</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="36" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="195249"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Terms not available</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881106T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE0DA1F3CF935A35752C1A96E948260" item-length="4610" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>TEARING APART EASTERN AIRLINES</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Stockton: William Stockton is an assistant financial news editor for The New York Times.</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: One Thursday afternoon recently, an Eastern Airlines L-1011 jumbo jet took off from New York bound for Miami with 37 passengers on board. ''We have a new class of service today,'' the chief flight attendant announced to her colleagues as they stared at the near-empty cabin. ''If you can find 'em, serve 'em.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: One Thursday afternoon recently, an Eastern Airlines L-1011 jumbo jet took off from New York bound for Miami with 37 passengers on board. ''We have a new class of service today,'' the chief flight attendant announced to her colleagues as they stared at the near-empty cabin. ''If you can find 'em, serve 'em.</p>
        <p>One Thursday afternoon recently, an Eastern Airlines L-1011 jumbo jet took off from New York bound for Miami with 37 passengers on board. ''We have a new class of service today,'' the chief flight attendant announced to her colleagues as they stared at the near-empty cabin. ''If you can find 'em, serve 'em.'' She repeated the joke several times, laughing nervously at each telling, but no one laughed with her.</p>
        <p>To the crew of Flight 17, the sea of empty seats was a pointed reminder of their precarious state of affairs. At Eastern, one of the nation's oldest and once most-prestigious airlines, labor unions and management have become so embroiled over their respective visions of its future that they have been systematically tearing it apart, chasing passengers away and causing enormous financial losses. Thousands of Eastern employees have been laid off, service in more than a dozen cities has been closed down, routes have been dropped, airplanes mothballed and lucrative pieces of the airline sold.</p>
        <p>At the center of this dismantlement are two strong-willed men headed for a showdown in coming months - or weeks - that will not only decide the fate of the troubled airline, but also probably have a profound effect on shaping the structure of the nation's air transportation industry. On one side is Francisco A. Lorenzo, the intense head of the Texas Air Corporation, the holding company that owns Eastern, Continental Airlines and the remnants of Frontier Airlines, People Express and New York Air. Facing him is Charles E. Bryan, the folksy head of the machinists' union at Eastern, who began at the airline three decades ago and rose through the union ranks.</p>
        <p>On the surface, the issue appears simple: Eastern is hemorrhaging money and Lorenzo contends he must have major wage and work-rule concessions from the unions - particularly from the machinists - if bankruptcy and oblivion are to be avoided. To keep Eastern afloat in the face of losses totalling hundreds of millions of dollars, he has sold Eastern's computerized reservation system for $100 million to his own Texas Air (Eastern then leased back use of the system) and the Eastern shuttle, the airline's crown jewel, which New York real estate developer Donald Trump bought several weeks ago for $365 million. Lorenzo calls this dismemberment process a ''downsizing,'' a selling of assets that is necessary to shrink Eastern to a profitable core.</p>
        <p>The unions contend it is blatant financial chicanery in which Eastern's assets are being siphoned into Texas Air's coffers, a process known as ''upstreaming cash.'' They say this money is going to sustain nonunion Continental, which is also losing money, and to enrich Lorenzo and Texas Air, while at the same time making Eastern look financially sicker and increasingly in need of union concessions. The unions have fought the downsizing and upstreaming by waging battles in the Federal courts and on Capitol Hill. They have even engaged in a form of employee guerrilla warfare, frightening off passengers with allegations of unsafe conditions. This has pushed Eastern's losses even higher.</p>
        <p>FOUNDED IN 1928, EASTERN WAS THE first major airline to ply the north-south routes along the Eastern seaboard, as opposed to east-west transcontinental routes that the other carriers, American, T.W.A and United, had carved out. This gave Eastern a lock on service to Miami and the Caribbean. There were innovations, too, such as Eastern's shuttle flights between New York and Washington, begun in the early 1960's (and later extended to Boston.) The shuttle, which took no reservations and guaranteed a seat to anyone who showed up, became an institution that bound the two cities together more tightly.</p>
        <p>One of Eastern's earliest pilots was Eddie Rickenbacker, the World War I ace, who became the airline's president in 1938 and remained until 1963. Eastern employees still refer to him as Captain Eddie.</p>
        <p>The airline, however, has been anemic for most of the past 20 years. In the view of many industry analysts, Eastern's lackluster performance is due partly to poor management and partly to the airline's particularly recalcitrant labor unions. To be sure, the unions, who see themselves as members of a family who have been victimized by successive cadres of bad managers, have made concessions as management lurched from one financial crisis to another. But the concessions, according to financial analysts, have never gone deep enough.</p>
        <p>''The fundamental problem at Eastern has been that each time management received concessions from the unions they never cut deep enough,'' says Richard Bilotti, an analyst at Prudential-Bache. ''They gave a little here and a little there, but each time management has had to come back again and ask for more.'' So often has each side accused the other of being the problem that, over the years, a lack of mutual faith has become deeply ingrained in the corporate culture.</p>
        <p>Wall Street has looked on aghast at Eastern's most recent troubles. The metaphors that airline-industry financial experts use are of scorched-earth policies on both sides; of Lorenzo and Bryan chained together, resolutely dragging one another over a cliff.</p>
        <p>''TEXAS AIR AND FRANK LORENZO ARE NOT GOING over any cliff,'' Lorenzo snapped when I mentioned this description to him. We were talking in the sparse offices Texas Air maintains in New York City's Rockefeller Center for executives' use when they are away from the Houston headquarters. He is a humorless man with the gaunt frame of a runner and a pallor that makes him appear worn out by his struggles.</p>
        <p>Lorenzo now controls 20 percent of the airline industry in this country; by some measures, Texas Air is the largest airline company in the Western world, exceeded in size only by Aeroflot, the Soviet Union's state-run airline.</p>
        <p>Described by colleagues and enemies alike as brilliant, pragmatic and crafty, Lorenzo has made a specialty of acquiring distressed airlines and turning them around financially. In 1979, when Continental had begun to lose money, it was Lorenzo who precipitated a bitter takeover battle in which Continental's chief executive eventually committed suicide. Four years later, Lorenzo took Continental into bankruptcy, abrogated the unions' contracts and cut wages in half. But when he resumed operations with some of the lowest fares available, the rest of the industry was left scrambling to keep up.</p>
        <p>Lorenzo bristles at being called a corporate raider. ''The unions say Lorenzo is just a wheeler-dealer finance guy who doesn't get involved in operations, in running an airline,'' he says. ''I am not a finance guy. I spend most of my time in marketing, in operations. I have been in the airline business for 16 years.''</p>
        <p>His standard operating method over the years has been to take over companies and then establish tight control of them through complex machinations in which holding companies are nestled within holding companies. He is a master at leverage -borrowing to the hilt to buy and letting his lenders take the financial risk. To a number of Wall Street experts, he appears to have created a particularly intricate corporation in which special deals involving Texas Air and its subsidiaries, Eastern and Continental, are common and, when the bottom line is scrutinized, Frank Lorenzo seems to be looking out mostly for himself.</p>
        <p>His unsuccessful plan to have Eastern sell its shuttle to a Texas Air subsidiary - essentially to sell it to himself - was a classic example. Documents filed with the Securities and Exchange Commission show that Lorenzo's private holding company, Jet Capital, was to receive a $1.25 million fee for advising Texas Air on the plan to buy the shuttle, a sort of finder's fee. When the deal fell through, S.E.C. papers indicate, Eastern had to pay Texas Air a $4 million fee.</p>
        <p>Eastern and Continental both pay an assortment of fees to Texas Air for such things as management, airplane rental and fuel. Commission filings show that Texas Air has agreed to help Eastern keep running in the event of a strike, but in return Eastern must pay all costs involved, plus ''insurance'' fees for Texas Air's availability. As of last December, those fees were listed at $22.5 million; the total for the first six months of 1988 was $12 million. When Texas Air bought Eastern's reservations system, Eastern received a $100 million note that pays a mere 6 percent interest a year. In another arrangement, Texas Air still owes Eastern $16 million in expenses connected with the acquisition of the airline. Eastern can call for payment any time, but so far has not done so. Meanwhile, Texas Air pays no interest on the sum.</p>
        <p>Union members are outraged at the prospect of pay cuts when they see such maneuverings that seem to be bleeding their airline to death. In a recent letter published in the Eastern pilots' union newsletter, Jan C. Williams, an Eastern pilot, spoke out angrily against wage concessions: ''As long as money is flowing up into a tornado called 'Jet Capital,' I see no reason why I or any other employee should feed this whirlwind with money out of our pockets.''</p>
        <p>CHARLIE BRYAN DOES NOT SEE HIM-self and his union being dragged over a cliff, either. The laid-back and discursive president of the Eastern machinists' union works out of the local's cluttered offices in a cluster of warehouses under the approach to one of Miami International Airport's runways.</p>
        <p>Hanging on the wall is a photograph of him in a shouting match at an Eastern shareholders' meeting a few years ago. Bryan quotes a remark made to him by an unnamed former Eastern executive, laid off by Lorenzo in a round of cost-cutting: ''They thought they had this little guy at the machinists they could roll right over. And instead, there was Charlie Bryan, an 800-pound gorilla.'' Publicly, Bryan eschews the idea that he might actually want to run the airline himself, but he leaves no doubt that he thinks he could do it better than anyone else. He has been far more successful than his counterparts at the pilots' and flight attendants' unions at maintaining wages, benefits and working conditions for his rank and file. As a result, he wields enormous power within the machinists' union, whose contract expired last Dec. 31, but whose members continue to work while negotiations proceed.</p>
        <p>In 1984, during one of Eastern's periodic fiscal crises, workers were given a block of stock and seats on the board of directors in return for concessions. It was a heady time for Bryan, rubbing shoulders with the likes of Laurance A. Rockefeller at board meetings. Bryan never spelled out specifically how he thought Eastern should be run, but he was fond of lecturing the board and Frank Borman, then Eastern's chairman. ''I used to get on my soapbox quite often with the board of directors and tell them if we all set an example, if we all had but one goal, and that was to produce the absolutely best airline seats in the industry, there is nobody in this industry who could touch Eastern Airlines,'' Bryan recalls.</p>
        <p>It was Bryan's vehement opposition to Borman three years ago that led the board of directors to accept Lorenzo's $600 million offer to buy Eastern - an irony that isn't mentioned very often within the ranks of the machinists' union. Lorenzo's reputation for ruthless cost-cutting was well known, but so disenchanted had the machinists become with Borman that Lorenzo seemed at the time to be the lesser of two evils. Bryan's error became quickly evident. Now, rebuffed and badgered by Lorenzo, Bryan is maneuvering to have him ousted, too.</p>
        <p>The options for both management and the union have narrowed in recent weeks. With the sale of the shuttle, some industry analysts now estimate that Lorenzo and Texas Air have a war chest of nearly $1 billion in cash. Should the machinists go out on strike, that money would enable Eastern to hold on for months, perhaps longer, and probably break the union. Bryan wants to avoid a strike, so his only hope is to find someone to buy Eastern from Texas Air, a ''white knight'' with whom he can cut a deal that would preserve at least a part of his union's pay scale and benefits. Bryan has even been courting the head of Trans World Airlines, Carl C. Icahn - the corporate raider's corporate raider.</p>
        <p>L AST JANUARY, leaders of two key Eastern unions, the Transit Workers Union Local 553 and the International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers District 100, met to map strategy for a public campaign against Lorenzo. They outlined their plan in a memorandum recently unsealed in one of the many Federal court suits that Eastern and its unions have filed against one another.</p>
        <p>The union objective, according to the memorandum, would be to ''Make Frank Lorenzo the issue. Personalize the conflict to one between him (i.e. the man who's the pillager of the American Dream; the man who'd cut any corner to make a buck; the man who's a brutal, unscrupulous corporate autocrat) and us (ordinary working people, fathers and mothers; people just like you and your neighbors).'' The goal would be to force Lorenzo to ''sell a restored Eastern to its employees; or, alternatively, sell it to an acceptable third party.''</p>
        <p>This, then, is the real issue - not wages and work rules, but who is to be in charge. ''We have an agreement among us to do whatever is necessary to support an employee-owned company,'' Bryan says. ''Our position was to get majority ownership long before Frank Lorenzo appeared. We just want Eastern to be run properly.''</p>
        <p>Lorenzo's troubles with the unions date almost from the day he took over Eastern in November 1986. One of his early actions was to throw some of the union representatives, including Bryan, off the Eastern board. And the work force was allowed to shrink dramatically, both from layoffs and attrition. The number of employees has dropped from 43,300 in 1986 to 29,500 in September. By the machinists' reckoning, there were 35 disciplinary firings of their members in the year before Lorenzo arrived and 362 in the first year after. The pilots and the flight attendants expected Lorenzo to show appreciation for the 20 percent wage concessions they had made and to focus on the machinists, who had given up nothing. ''Instead, he started pushing all of us and wouldn't let up,'' says Jack Bavis, head of the pilots' union. ''He left no room. He gave us no hope.'' So the battle was joined. Some of the pilots began to burn more fuel than necessary. A stringent safety campaign was instigated in which pilots scrutinized every aircraft, looking for what they considered safety problems. When one was found, a scratched windshield, for example, the pilot filled out four postcards detailing the problem. They were sent to Congressional committees, and to officials at the Department of Transportation and the Federal Aviation Administration. There was a flood of postcards to Washington.</p>
        <p>Pilots also used their discretionary powers as aircraft commanders to insist that backup navigation or safety equipment be replaced if it was found to be inoperative, thus taking airplanes out of service and often causing flight cancellations. In other times, the pilots might have gone ahead with many of these flights.</p>
        <p>Such tactics increased passenger complaints. Unruly passengers besieging an Eastern ticket counter after the cancellation of a flight became a familar airport sight. Passengers began defecting to other airlines.</p>
        <p>Union members undertook an intense lobbying effort, writing hundreds of letters and buttonholing Congressmen and their staff members, urging an investigation into Texas Air. Finally, the unions went before the National Mediation Board claiming that Texas Air was operating its Eastern and Continental units as a joint airline, despite separate names, schedules and work forces. The issue is far from settled, but if the board agrees with the unions' contention, it could lead to Eastern's unions representing Continental.</p>
        <p>Lorenzo fought back. Eastern began massing capital with which to weather a possible strike by the machinists, and struck a deal with nonunion Continental in which the sister airline is to supply 500 pilots to fly Eastern craft in the event of a machinists' strike and a decision by the pilots not to cross picket lines. It also made agreements with airline service companies to provide necessary ground support in case of a strike.</p>
        <p>Last February, Lorenzo, ever the adroit corporate maneuverer, announced a plan whereby Eastern would spin off its lucrative shuttle operation, selling it to Texas Air for $225 million. The unions went to Federal court and won a ruling calling for union bargaining in any attempt to spin off the shuttle.</p>
        <p>By this point, however, Lorenzo's tactics were focusing attention on his own labyrinthine financial activities, seeming to confirm the unions' contentions that he is a brutal, unscrupulous corporate raider. The Transportation Department ordered an unprecedented investigation of Texas Air's financial stability and its management, and the Federal Aviation Administration ordered an immediate safety inspection of the entire Eastern fleet - an order subsequently extended to Continental's aircraft as well. The unions rejoiced, but the announcement also further eroded the flying public's confidence in Eastern. Even more travelers, particularly business flyers, stayed away.</p>
        <p>Ironically, Lorenzo's fortunes began to turn around again with the Federal inspection, after which F.A.A. Administrator T. Allan McArtor announced that ''an unsafe condition does not currently exist among the carriers.'' In June, Jim Burnley, Secretary of Transportation, stated that the examination of Texas Air finances and management had resulted in a clean bill of health. However, the department said it would continue to closely monitor the situation, and called for regular meetings between Eastern employees and management to discuss safety questions. Then, a few days later, a Federal appeals court set aside the lower court's ruling calling for union participation in negotiations for the shuttle, paving the way for its sale.</p>
        <p>Still, Eastern's massive financial losses continued. In July, the airline announced it would close operations in 14 cities, mainly in the West, and lay off 4,000 employees. Again, the unions went to court and won a restraining order, successfully arguing that the move had to be negotiated with them. But again, an appeals court ruled in Eastern's favor.</p>
        <p>Lorenzo now says Eastern lost $100 million in the most recent quarter. The virtually empty L-1011 flight to Miami was grim evidence of the airline's sea of red ink. Texas Air's stock, which soared to the $50-a-share range after the Eastern acquisition, now trades in the $15 range.</p>
        <p>THREE WEEKS AGO, Carl Icahn, chairman of Trans World Airlines, telephoned Lorenzo to report that he would not be making an offer to acquire Eastern Airlines. Icahn had just completed a round of talks over the weekend with Eastern's union leaders to determine whether they would support such an acquisition. He had sought wage and work-rule concessions from the unions, particularly from the machinists, similar to those sought by Lorenzo. The unions had said no, that they cut too deep.</p>
        <p>According to Lorenzo, Icahn told him, ''Frank, I see what you're up against with your unions.'' Of course, Icahn might be back. Astute corporate takeover specialists are ever alert for a distress sale, and paradoxically, Eastern's sustained losses -which depress the potential price of the company while having no effect on its many assets - continue to make it an attractive target.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, Icahn's decision reflects a perception widely held on Wall Street: if Eastern is to survive, the unions must give the owners - whoever they may be -significant concessions. The biggest ones must come from the machinists, who in the past two years have received an 8 percent pay increase provided for in their contract, while all others on the Eastern workforce were dealt a 20 percent cut.</p>
        <p>Basically, Eastern wants two things from the machinists: a pay cut that approximates that 28 percent disparity, and significant work-rule changes. Typically, employees now making about $15 an hour would drop to $10. But under the airline's proposal, the most highly skilled mechanics, who now make nearly $19 an hour, would lose only about $1 an hour. Those employees taking large pay cuts who qualified would be given free retraining, with full pay, to become mechanics.</p>
        <p>The work-rule changes include the freedom to hire part-time employees on ground crews; permitting ticket agents - rather than ramp-service workers - to operate the jetway when an airliner arrives at the gate, and having union members perform a variety of jobs, known as ''cross-utilization.''</p>
        <p>''We don't have a single part-time employee among the  [ International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers ]  workforce, and there isn't another airline in the country where the ramp service guy has to drive the jetway,'' says Joseph B. Leonard, Eastern's chief operating officer, fuming. ''You have an agent there to open the airplane door. They can drive the jetway. It's grossly inefficient.'' Leonard says the givebacks, extended over three years, would save Eastern about $500 million. The machinists' union has countered with requests for wage increases of 4 to 6 percent a year over several years (though they would take a first-year wage freeze). The union has also rejected Eastern's work-rule changes.</p>
        <p>ALTHOUGH THE EX-tent of Icahn's wage and work-rule concession demands were not revealed, the unions' unwillingness to go as far as he wanted them to makes it unlikely that others will be willing to take on Eastern and its problems. Although some union leaders and the investment bankers advising them have hinted that other investor groups might come forward - for example, a cash-rich insurance group or Canadian investors, all unnamed -none have materialized.</p>
        <p>Moreover, Lorenzo's sale of the shuttle, one of the airline's few profitable operations, makes it even less attractive. And Lorenzo and his closest advisers have hinted that purchasing Eastern would cost dearly - as much as $1 billion. Further complicating a sale is Eastern's status as a subsidiary of Texas Air. A hostile takeover of Eastern alone would not be possible, since its stock does not trade publicly. So a hostile takeover campaign would have to be launched against the parent company, Texas Air. A successful campaign would win not only Eastern, but Continental Airlines too, which has also been losing money recently. Who would be that foolhardy, except, perhaps, the employees of Eastern and Continental themselves? ''We have actually looked at a hostile takeover, to borrow on our pension funds,'' Jack Bavis of the pilots' union says. ''There is a way to do it, but we saw that it would be too much of a risk. Our pensions are all we have. Any takeover has to be friendly.'' At this point, the unions' fervent hope is that Lorenzo might become so sick of Eastern, its unions and its losses, that he would throw in the towel and sell.</p>
        <p>If a strike occurs at Eastern, it could become one of the most bitter affairs in airline history. Under the Railway Labor Act, enacted in the 1920's to keep strikers from crippling a national transportation industry, a contract with the unions continues in force even though it has expired.</p>
        <p>If labor and management are unable to reach an agreement, the National Mediation Board can invoke a 30-day cooling-off period, after which management is free to impose new wages and working conditions and labor can either accept them or strike. When the machinists' contract expired at the end of last December, Eastern's management had hoped the mediation board would start the 30-day clock ticking in the spring. Then, after the Federal inspection was concluded, it hoped for board action in the early fall. Now, it seems unlikely the clock will be started until after the new year.</p>
        <p>''It's clear to us that Charlie Bryan will never begin seriously negotiating until his feet are put to the fire, until he has a deadline,'' says Philip J. Bakes, Eastern's president and chief executive officer.</p>
        <p>Bryan refuses to speculate. ''At this point, it is a very delicate process we are in, and I would never make any assumption about it,'' he told me. Meanwhile, the pilots' contract also has expired and is subject to a separate 30-day clock if negotiations reach an impasse.</p>
        <p>Indeed, the pilots' suspicion of the machinists, now well established, could turn out to be one of Lorenzo's trump cards. Despite periodic vows of solidarity between the two unions, the pilots are deeply resentful of the pay cuts they have taken. Many pilots also blame Bryan's intransigence at the fateful Eastern board of directors meeting for the airline's falling into Lorenzo's hands in the first place.</p>
        <p>So if Lorenzo could reach an agreement quickly with the pilots, he would have a powerful lever against Bryan. With an agreement in hand and no white knight in sight, many pilots would likely cross machinist picket lines in the event of a strike.</p>
        <p>Until now, the unions have dragged their feet in negotiations, hoping to delay the clock and searching for a friendly buyer. ''There is an enormous amount of Eastern and Texas Air debt out there and a lot of important business people holding that debt,'' Bryan says wistfully. ''I would think the forces behind the scenes would at some point say there must be a better way of running this 20 percent of the airline industry.''</p>
        <p>As veteran labor negotiators know, the egos that participants bring to the bargaining table can have a profound effect on negotiations, and both Lorenzo and Bryan have large egos. Is there any room left for compromise?</p>
        <p>''Frank Lorenzo's reputation on Wall Street is not going to be changed if he is a successful union buster,'' says Frank Lorenzo. ''Doing good for investors is what makes points on Wall Street. I'm not a guy associated with a lot of ego. I'm results-oriented. When you say ego, do you mean are we prepared to make a public deal that saves Charlie Bryan's face? Absolutely.''</p>
        <p>Bryan says the same thing. ''I'd do anything in the world for public perception to make it look like he won or he beat us,'' he says. ''I don't give a damn about how it looks or what anyone thinks about it if we can get results. Anything at all, as long as it is absolute and gets results.''</p>
        <p>Near the end of last month, the two men met in Houston for a private dinner. Afterward, Lorenzo said he would consider the possibility of giving all Eastern employees some stock as part of a quick settlement of the labor dispute. If the equity stake were large enough, or if Bryan were to drive a hard enough bargain, the union leader might even return to a seat in a boardroom. Before he met with Bryan for dinner that night, Lorenzo told me sardonically, ''Perhaps the solution is to just give Charlie a seat on our board.''</p>
        <p>Clearly, the unions and Lorenzo are both aware that Eastern's survival is at stake. For the consumer, the airline's disappearance, or its takeover by another carrier, would further the move to oligopoly that has developed during the decade of deregulation. The field has already been reduced to half-a-dozen major airlines, and they have increasingly been dividing routes among themselves so they compete less with one another. Many industry analysts say this is why air fares have been rising lately.</p>
        <p>Frank Lorenzo contends Eastern must survive in order to sustain industry competition. Charlie Bryan does not disagree with that.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
