<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>NEWS SUMMARY</title>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="333532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Summary</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900310T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CEEDD123CF933A25750C0A966958260" item-length="1361" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>NEWS SUMMARY</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-6</p>
        <p>Efforts to interdict drug shipments are being beefed up by the Pentagon. Reconnaissance flights over the Caribbean are increasing, and a new radar network is being built across the southern United States.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>A plan to disband the contra rebels and use U.N.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD:</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-6</p>
        <p>Efforts to interdict drug shipments are being beefed up by the Pentagon. Reconnaissance flights over the Caribbean are increasing, and a new radar network is being built across the southern United States.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>A plan to disband the contra rebels and use U.N.</p>
        <p>International</p>
        <p>2-6</p>
        <p>Efforts to interdict drug shipments are being beefed up by the Pentagon. Reconnaissance flights over the Caribbean are increasing, and a new radar network is being built across the southern United States.</p>
        <p>Page 1</p>
        <p>A plan to disband the contra rebels and use U.N. peacekeeping troops was proposed by the U.S., but Vice President Quayle and the leaders of Spain and Venezuela failed to agree on how quickly the rebels should be demobilized.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>The contras are a threat to peace in Nicaragua, said President Daniel Ortega. He warned that if the contras were not disarmed he could not guarantee a peaceful transition of power in April.</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>General Pinochet fears prosecution for the political killings and torture that occurred during his rule over Chile and has pressed President-elect Patricio Aylwin for assurances that no charges will be brought.</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Lima journal: ''Concrete pants'' protect Peru's power pylons</p>
        <p>4</p>
        <p>Haitians march again to demand resignation of President Avril</p>
        <p>5</p>
        <p>The German border is dissolving even before reunification. In towns like Wernigerode, East Germany, business and social cooperation has spilled across a dividing line that was painfully and arbitrarily drawn.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>The East German Communist Party, all but written off a few weeks ago, has restyled itself and found a new voice as the champion of East Germans fearful of West German dominance.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Mitterrand says Germanys must recognize Poland's borders</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Margaret Thatcher's tough line on German reunification has prompted much derision of her in British and West German newspapers, even though her stance is close to that of the United States, France and the Soviet Union.</p>
        <p>6</p>
        <p>Anger has greeted Britain's poll tax, which takes effect in England and Wales on April 1. The tax, which replaces property taxes, has sparked violent protests and eroded Prime Minister Thatcher's power.</p>
        <p>2</p>
        <p>General Aoun offered to negotiate with Syria and its Muslim allies in Lebanon to end the country's 15-year civil war. He said his war with a rival Christian militia is over.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>Iran's President mocked the U.S., calling it ''the biggest bully on earth.'' President Rafsanjani also ridiculed President Bush for being duped by a telephone call from a hoaxer posing as the Iranian President.</p>
        <p>3</p>
        <p>National</p>
        <p>7-9, 26</p>
        <p>The N.F.L.'s television contract will earn the league $3.6 billion from five television partners in the next four years. With the addition of $752 million from NBC, it is the most lucrative contract in television history.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Oliver North testified in the trial of John Poindexter. Often appearing hostile, Mr. North said he never hid his efforts to aid the Nicaraguan contras from Mr. Poindexter and always worked under his direction.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Workplace day care for the elderly is being offered by the Stride Rite Corporation in Cambridge, Mass. While many companies offer child care, Stride Rite is the first to offer care to elderly relatives of workers.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Three pilots' licenses were revoked by the Federal Aviation Administration, which accused them of making a Northwest Airlines flight on Thursday while under the influence of alcohol.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>By the way, smoking ban on planes doesn't apply to pilots</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Anti-abortion law is passed by Idaho lawmakers</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>The economy generated more jobs in February than analysts had expected, but the growth did not affect the civilian unemployment rate, which held steady at 5.3 percent.</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Treasury prices fall after unemployment report</p>
        <p>34</p>
        <p>Burger King is charged with child-labor violations</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>Greyhound bus with 29 aboard hit by three bullets in Ohio</p>
        <p>8</p>
        <p>The teacher strike in West Virginia has shut down more than half of the state's schools for the third day. Governor Caperton said teachers returning to class on Monday would not be punished or have to forfeit pay.</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Senator Simpson delivers sharp personal attack on Gephardt</p>
        <p>7</p>
        <p>Human skull is flown on two space shuttle missions</p>
        <p>26</p>
        <p>Report of plan to oust Alan Greenspan is denied</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>G.M. unit pleads guilty to obtaining Pentagon documents</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Zenith is betting its life on new television technology</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Regional</p>
        <p>27-30</p>
        <p>News analysis: Joseph Fernandez, the Schools Chancellor, is using his forceful personality and political cunning to tap the public's widespread dismay and induce swift changes in the educational system.</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>New Jersey's best education bargain may be the West Windsor-Plainsboro school district, which ranks high in scholastic tests but spends below the state average per student.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Students at Rutgers reap the rewards of taking a test</p>
        <p>30</p>
        <p>The task of rescuing Covenant House from its ''mess'' will be undertaken by the Archdiocese of New York, said Cardinal O'Connor. Meanwhile, the charity's chairman acknowledged that the board of directors had ''failed.''</p>
        <p>1</p>
        <p>Dr. Prego will receive $1.35 million for dropping her lawsuit against the city's Health and Hospitals Corporation, the judge in the case said, reversing his order not to disclose the amount of the settlement.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>The risks of AIDS to health workers has created much fear in hospitals. And yet almost a decade after the epidemic began, hospitals are only now taking steps to protect workers from exposure to the virus.</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>A New York hospital calls to ask how you're doing</p>
        <p>28</p>
        <p>Woman in the news: Barbara Sabol, Mayor Dinkins's choice to head the Human Resources Administration, has a lot of experience and is liked by both her employees and welfare advocates.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>Mario Cuomo mailed vitriolic letters at taxpayer expense to 20,000 homes in State Senator Joe Bruno's district. The Governor's unusual way of rebuking an opponent has surprised Democrats and made Mr. Bruno a celebrity among Republicans.</p>
        <p>27</p>
        <p>About 6,000 mourn trooper killed in Lower East Side shooting</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>New York thruway will replace most highway restaurants</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>Condominium developer ordered to offer refunds to investors</p>
        <p>29</p>
        <p>Business Digest</p>
        <p>31</p>
        <p>Arts/Entertainment</p>
        <p>Rauschenberg show in East Berlin</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>A director's life imitates his art</p>
        <p>11</p>
        <p>Artists encounter grant restrictions</p>
        <p>17</p>
        <p>Theater: ''Cahoots,'' a comedy with murder</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Film: ''The Last of the Finest''</p>
        <p>15</p>
        <p>Music: New Del Tredici work</p>
        <p>12</p>
        <p>Jazz in concert form</p>
        <p>14</p>
        <p>Book: ''Appetite for Change''</p>
        <p>16</p>
        <p>Consumer's World</p>
        <p>50</p>
        <p>Safety panel acts on baby pillows</p>
        <p>Hidden costs of overseas purchases</p>
        <p>Coping with building a fence</p>
        <p>Electronic ID for pets</p>
        <p>Guidepost</p>
        <p>Sports</p>
        <p>Baseball: Lockout hits a milestone</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>Basketball: Syracuse beats Pittsburgh</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Georgetown tops Providence</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Virginia, Clemson and Duke gain in A.C.C.</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Nets lose to Pistons</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>Villanova tops St. John's</p>
        <p>47</p>
        <p>Gather's family plans to sue</p>
        <p>47</p>
        <p>Column: Berkow on Valvano</p>
        <p>45</p>
        <p>Tennis: Capriati stuns Sukova</p>
        <p>46</p>
        <p>Obituaries</p>
        <p>10</p>
        <p>Elmer T. Klassen, led American Can and Postal Service</p>
        <p>Ron Wolin, an antiwar advocate</p>
        <p>Mordecai Gorelik, theatrical designer and playwright</p>
        <p>Editorials/Letters/Op-Ed</p>
        <p>Editorials</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>The Court's deadly new rules</p>
        <p>Iran squirms on human rights</p>
        <p>Plain speaking in the market</p>
        <p>Roger Starr: Israel and trade</p>
        <p>Letters</p>
        <p>24</p>
        <p>Flora Lewis: No time for politics</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Russell Baker: Fading fast, doctor</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>William Treanor: Rebuild, don't fix, Covenant House</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Eugene Rochberg-Halton: A memorial for cold war victims</p>
        <p>25</p>
        <p>Clyde Prestowitz: George and Toshiki - the odd couple</p>
        <p>25</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
