<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Increasingly, American-Made Doesn't Mean in the U.S.A.</title>
    <meta content="19MANU$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/19/business/worldbusiness/19manufacture.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1567555"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Foreign Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">China</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Behlen Manufacturing</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Commerce Department</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raimondo, Anthony F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kerry, John (Sen)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Raimondo, Anthony F</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bush, George W (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Uchitelle, Louis</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/US Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Trade</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Issues/Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/George W Bush</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/Candidates/John F Kerry</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Manufacturing, Operations and Logistics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Asia/China</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Election Issues</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Factories and Industrial Plants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Production</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Steel and Iron</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hiring and Promotion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Election of 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Trade and World Market</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidential Elections (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Presidents and Presidency (US)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Butler Manufacturing Company</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Commerce Department</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040319T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE2D61331F93AA25750C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Increasingly, American-Made Doesn't Mean in the U.S.A.</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Increasingly, American-Made Doesnt Mean in the U.S.A.</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Uchitelle, Louis</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sales from overseas operation of American-controlled companies have continued to grow, generating jobs abroad, but not at home; most American manufacturing companies contend that such moves are essential to keep American industry competitive in global market; Anthony F Raimondo, chief of Behlen Manufacturing, defends setting up production plant in China, but criticism from campaign of Sen John Kerry, who is likely Democratic presidential nominee, cost Raimondo job of assistant secretary of commerce for manufacturing in Bush administration; graphs; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Anthony F. Raimondo, a Nebraska business executive, was all set to become President Bush's manufacturing czar until he was caught in a political firestorm last week after John Kerry's campaign suggested that Mr. Raimondo was a ''Benedict Arnold C.E.O.'' for moving jobs from the United States to China.</p>
        <p>But it's not that simple. What Mr. Raimondo's company did, experts of all stripes say, has become standard business practice in response to domestic and international pressures.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Hundreds of American companies own facilities abroad that produce for overseas customers rather than for shipment back home.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Anthony F. Raimondo, a Nebraska business executive, was all set to become President Bush's manufacturing czar until he was caught in a political firestorm last week after John Kerry's campaign suggested that Mr. Raimondo was a ''Benedict Arnold C.E.O.'' for moving jobs from the United States to China.</p>
        <p>But it's not that simple. What Mr. Raimondo's company did, experts of all stripes say, has become standard business practice in response to domestic and international pressures.</p>
        <p>Hundreds of American companies, among them Mr. Raimondo's Behlen Manufacturing of Columbus, Neb., own facilities abroad that produce goods and services for overseas customers rather than for shipment back home. Indeed, these overseas sales, which have risen to more than $2.2 trillion annually in recent years, dwarf the nation's exports of roughly $1 trillion.</p>
        <p>Should American companies turn so quickly to production abroad, rather than export from the United States -- particularly in China, where sales are growing at two or three times the rate in any other country?</p>
        <p>Mr. Raimondo says yes and he is far from alone. He and the chief executives of most manufacturing companies contend that such moves are essential to keep American industry competitive in the global marketplace.</p>
        <p>Behlen's story is telling. The company got its start in China by exporting from Nebraska prefabricated steel framing for commercial buildings, particularly factories.</p>
        <p>Its biggest Chinese customer was a company that made automotive glass. ''We shipped all the steel framing for four 250,000-square-foot factories,'' Mr. Raimondo said.</p>
        <p>In 2000, however, his big Chinese customer shifted to one of Behlen's competitors, Butler Manufacturing of Kansas City, Mo., which offered a lower price from a factory it had opened in China in 1996 to manufacture the heavy steel products closer to where they would be used. Behlen responded to this competition by shifting from exports to production in China, at a new plant that opened last year in Beijing.</p>
        <p>''We think ours is the ideal dynamic model for American manufacturers,'' Mr. Raimondo said in a telephone interview. ''I talked at length with the Department of Commerce and the White House, and they agreed that Behlen's competitive response is a tremendous message for all manufacturing. We do not outsource in the sense of bringing product back to the United States.''</p>
        <p>The nation's manufacturers have shed 2.7 million American jobs since Mr. Bush took office. In a bid to deflect the political reaction from so much industrial job loss, the White House announced that Mr. Bush would appoint an assistant secretary of commerce for manufacturing. Mr. Raimondo got the nod, only to have his appointment go down in flames last week after a barrage of criticism from Senator Kerry's camp.</p>
        <p>Even after abandoning him, the Bush administration has reasserted its faith in Mr. Raimondo's strategies.</p>
        <p>''For American companies to be competitive on a global basis, they need to be able to have the freedom to establish a beachhead overseas that allows them to expand their sales abroad,'' Grant Aldonas, the Commerce Department's under secretary for international trade, said. ''That is what Tony did.''</p>
        <p>Nearly 2,500 American companies are involved in production abroad for overseas customers, according to the Commerce Department's Bureau of Economic Analysis, and they go overseas by one of two routes. Some companies start out by setting up factories or offices abroad, without ever exporting. Many others, like Behlen and Butler, shift from exporting to production abroad to remain competitive.</p>
        <p>Jobs are lost at home in the process, Mr. Raimondo acknowledged, but they would have been lost anyway if Behlen had stuck with an export strategy and thus sacrificed orders to lower-cost competitors with plants in China. ''Most of the disadvantage is transportation cost,'' Mr. Raimondo said. ''Shipping steel across the Pacific is expensive.''</p>
        <p>That sort of business decision was hard to explain as the presidential campaign heated up. In a press release, the Kerry camp noted that Behlen laid off 75 workers at its American factories in 2002 as its factory in Beijing neared completion. The press release never said the two were connected, but the implication was clear -- and false, Mr. Raimondo contends.</p>
        <p>The American layoffs in 2002 were in response to weak demand in the United States for Behlen's products, he said. Over a three-year period, he actually laid off 500 of his 1,500 American employees as sales fell to $135 million last year from $186 million in 2000.</p>
        <p>Mr. Kerry offered a different explanation. In a speech, he linked the Behlen layoffs to the shifting of work to China. The administration's ''manufacturing czar, the person they chose, has been a poster person for the very depths of their policy that has affected millions of Americans negatively across our country,'' Mr. Kerry said.</p>
        <p>Sara Bianchi, Kerry's policy adviser, acknowledged yesterday that competitiveness requires that some overseas customers must be supplied from production facilities abroad. But the Bush administration has allowed this process to go too far, she said.</p>
        <p>''Bush is not doing enough to keep jobs here,'' Ms. Bianchi said. ''Fewer of these companies would have to make these kinds of decisions if we had a president who fought to keep manufacturing in this country through tax incentives, lower health care costs and enforcement of our trade laws.''</p>
        <p>Worldwide, sales from overseas facilities in which American companies control ownership rose at an average annual rate of just over 10 percent from 1989 through 2001, the latest year for which data are available. The steady expansion spanned Democratic as well as Republican administrations, reaching a total of $2.2 trillion in 2001. By comparison, shipments of goods and services to the United States -- like auto parts, computer programming and call center services -- totaled only $272 billion in 2001. Yet that is an aspect of offshoring that has become hotly disputed in the campaign.</p>
        <p>Behlen's joint venture with three Chinese companies, employing 180 people, is the first overseas operation for the company, which is privately owned.</p>
        <p>Until the factory opened last summer, exports from Behlen's four American plants brought in only 7 percent of the company's $140 million in annual revenues. Steel building frames had accounted for nearly half of the export revenue. Mr. Raimondo acknowledged that the company's production in Beijing for the China market had eliminated 20 to 30 jobs in Nebraska -- far fewer than Mr. Kerry contended and the jobs disappeared only after the factory opened.</p>
        <p>Behlen also exports prefabricated grain silos to China, and makes parts of the silos in China. Sales have risen for these silos, so production has also risen for the portion made in Nebraska, mainly thin steel siding. Three or four workers, as a result, have been added at Behlen's factory in Columbus. Still, the China strategy has resulted in a net job loss, and that loss might rise as Behlen's new factory in China expands production to serve customers there.</p>
        <p>''The China market is so large, it justifies going there,'' Mr. Raimondo said. ''I even see us opening a second plant there. Every other market we can export to, but not China. We have to be there. I wouldn't call that export substitution.''</p>
        <p>He also said he did not intend to engage in import substitution, shipping steel frames or silos back to the United States, but he qualified that statement. One product that Behlen makes in the United States is metal farm gates, used in livestock enclosures. Companies in China are beginning to ship similar gates to the United States and Mr. Raimondo says that in the worst case, Behlen might have to do the same.</p>
        <p>''We don't think the Chinese can sustain these shipments,'' Mr. Raimondo said. ''The gates are heavy to ship and they involve very little labor cost. But if the shipments were sustained, we would have to figure out some technology to automate more, and if we could not do that, we might have to find other ways to compete.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
