<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>BUSINESS TRAVEL: ON THE GROUND -- In Johannesburg; Antelope Steaks and Some African Drama</title>
    <meta content="28GROUND" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Travel; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/10/28/business/28ground.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20031030T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1530824"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="On the Ground"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Johannesburg (South Africa)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Simon, Bernard</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/On the Ground</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Business Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Asia Pacific</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa/Cape Town</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Africa/South Africa/Johannesburg</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geographic Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Geography</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">South Africa</location>
        <location class="online_producer">Cape Town (South Africa)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20031028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9405E2D71E31F93BA15753C1A9659C8B63" item-length="752" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>BUSINESS TRAVEL: ON THE GROUND -- In Johannesburg; Antelope Steaks and Some African Drama</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">In Johannesburg, Antelope Steaks and Some African Drama</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BERNARD SIMON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Simon, Bernard</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Travel article on Johannesburg, South Africa, as business destination; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LONG before the end of apartheid, white-owned businesses were fleeing the center of Johannesburg, South Africa's biggest city. Even the Johannesburg stock exchange has relocated to Sandton, eight miles north of downtown and now the main business and shopping hub.</p>
        <p>Though Johannesburg is generally a pleasant and hospitable city with modern amenities, crime remains high. Visitors should observe some basic precautions, like locking car doors at all times and not driving at night without clear directions.</p>
        <p>AIRPORT</p>
        <p>Johannesburg International Airport, 15 miles southeast of Sandton, is a privatization success story for the post-apartheid government. Run by the Airports Company of South Africa, which is partly owned by the Italian company Aeroporti di Roma, the airport has been transformed over the last decade. The international terminal is often congested in the early evening, when most overseas flights depart.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Though Johannesburg is generally a pleasant and hospitable city with modern amenities, crime remains high.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LONG before the end of apartheid, white-owned businesses were fleeing the center of Johannesburg, South Africa's biggest city. Even the Johannesburg stock exchange has relocated to Sandton, eight miles north of downtown and now the main business and shopping hub.</p>
        <p>Though Johannesburg is generally a pleasant and hospitable city with modern amenities, crime remains high. Visitors should observe some basic precautions, like locking car doors at all times and not driving at night without clear directions.</p>
        <p>AIRPORT</p>
        <p>Johannesburg International Airport, 15 miles southeast of Sandton, is a privatization success story for the post-apartheid government. Run by the Airports Company of South Africa, which is partly owned by the Italian company Aeroporti di Roma, the airport has been transformed over the last decade. The international terminal is often congested in the early evening, when most overseas flights depart.</p>
        <p>Taxis and public transportation are generally unreliable in Johannesburg. Arriving passengers who are not being met by a local contact should pick up a rental car at the airport.</p>
        <p>HOTELS</p>
        <p>Rex McLennan, chief financial officer of Placer Dome, a Canadian gold producer, chooses either the SANDTON SUN AND TOWERS INTERCONTINENTAL (011-27-11-780-5000, $260 and up) or the MICHELANGELO (011-27-11-282-7000, $270) on his regular visits to Johannesburg. Both are connected to shops, restaurants and cinemas. Mr. McLennan says he especially likes the fitness center at the Sandton Sun. (To call Johannesburg from the United States, dial 011, followed by 27-11, then the number.)</p>
        <p>When Placer Dome held a board meeting in Johannesburg two years ago, its directors stayed at THE SAXON (292-6000, $590), set in six acres of gardens in a quiet residential neighborhood.</p>
        <p>Christine Qunta, a Cape Town lawyer, said that staff members at the GRACE HOTEL (280-7200, $350) ''really bend over backwards to meet every demand.'' She recalls them ordering in soya milk powder to make her a soya smoothie.</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
        <p>Marlin Hitzeroth, general manager of Thengisa Media, a publishing group, describes the curries at BUKHARA (883-5555, $40 for dinner for two, including wine, tax and tip) as ''absolutely phenomenal.'' Mr. Hitzeroth, especially likes the rogan josh, which is subtly spiced but not too hot.</p>
        <p>Monica Singer, chief executive of Strate, the stock exchange's electronic settlement arm, likes the outdoor patio at THE BULL RUN (884-1400, $50), opposite the exchange. ''With the South African weather, it's the ideal place to have lunch for at least seven months a year,'' she says.</p>
        <p>The more intimate -- and pricier -- LINGER LONGER (884-0465, $75) is known for its preparations of guinea fowl, ostrich and kudu, a kind of antelope. Tables can be booked in the restaurant's private garden.</p>
        <p>Melville, a neighborhood midway between Sandton and downtown, has a cluster of popular restaurants, wine bars and clubs. Herbert Mkhize, executive director of Nedlac, which mediates negotiations involving government, business and labor, says the area has transcended South Africa's cultural differences. One of his favorite eating spots there is SAM'S CAFÉ (726-8142, $40).</p>
        <p>ENTERTAINMENT</p>
        <p>Innovative South African repertory can often be seen at the MARKET THEATER (832-1641), in a former fruit and vegetable market on the western fringe of downtown. Almost next door to the theater is MUSEUM AFRICA (833-5624), depicting South African culture and history. The new Nelson Mandela Bridge has improved access to the area, though it is best to have a companion with local knowledge, especially at night.</p>
        <p>The APARTHEID MUSEUM (309-4700), a 25-minute drive from Sandton, is especially enlightening for visitors with little knowledge of the darkest period of South African history.</p>
        <p>For an insight into the daily lives of most black South Africans, several companies offer tours of Soweto, the sprawling residential area on the southwestern outskirts of Johannesburg. TALK TOURS (487-1798) is run by a nonprofit agency. IMBIZO TOURS (838-2667) picks up customers from Sandton and Rosebank hotels.</p>
        <p>WANDIES PLACE (982-2796) is a popular, though somewhat tourist-oriented, bar and restaurant in the Dube district of Soweto. Besides Western fare, the buffet includes traditional African dishes like oxtail stew, tripe and maize porridge. Again, a companion who knows the area is recommended.</p>
        <p>This feature about places to stay, eat and visit in leading business destinations appears every Tuesday.</p>
        <p>On the Ground  Correction:  October 30, 2003, Thursday  The On the Ground column in the Business Travel pages on Tuesday, about Johannesburg, misspelled the given name of a local company executive who recommended an Indian restaurant. He is Marlon Hitzeroth, not Marlin.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: October 30, 2003, Thursday</p>
        <p>The On the Ground column in the Business Travel pages on Tuesday, about Johannesburg, misspelled the given name of a local company executive who recommended an Indian restaurant. He is Marlon Hitzeroth, not Marlin.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
