<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Productivity Fell in Quarter But Rose Sharply in 2002</title>
    <meta content="Y07ECO$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/02/07/business/07ECON.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1462913"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Unemployment Insurance</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Labor Department (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Federal Reserve System</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Leonhardt, David</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Unemployment Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Productivity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Records and Achievements</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Fringe Benefits</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Layoffs and Job Reductions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Wages and Salaries</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Unemployment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Labor</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030207T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9505EEDD143BF934A35751C0A9659C8B63" item-length="770" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Productivity Fell in Quarter But Rose Sharply in 2002</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Productivity Fell in Quarter but Rose Sharply in 2002</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID LEONHARDT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Leonhardt, David</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Labor Department reports productivity fell at annual rate of 0.2 percent in fourth quarter, but grew 4.7 percent in 2002; says average labor costs, including salary and benefits, increased at annual rate of 4.8 percent in quarter, but fell record 1.7 percent in 2002; first-time claims for unemployment insurance fell to 391,000 from 402,000 previous week; number of people receiving jobless benefits rose to 3.35 million from 3.3 million; Federal Reserve announces it is laying off 400 workers; graphs (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Companies stopped becoming more efficient in the final three months of last year as a slowing economy caught many by surprise, according to government figures released yesterday. The productivity gain for all of 2002 was still the best in more than 50 years, however.</p>
        <p>The report helped send stocks lower as investors worried that corporate America's profit slump would continue, analysts said.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Companies stopped becoming more efficient in the final three months of last year as a slowing economy caught many by surprise.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Companies stopped becoming more efficient in the final three months of last year as a slowing economy caught many by surprise, according to government figures released yesterday. The productivity gain for all of 2002 was still the best in more than 50 years, however.</p>
        <p>The report helped send stocks lower as investors worried that corporate America's profit slump would continue, analysts said.</p>
        <p>The productivity decline suggested that the exceptionally rapid gains of the last two years would probably not be sustained, confirming the predictions of some economists. But most emphasized that the report probably overstated the slowdown and that companies found themselves temporarily unable to keep costs from rising more quickly than revenue when the economy weakened late last year.</p>
        <p>''In the fourth quarter, demand just dried up,'' said Mark Vitner, a senior economist at the Wachovia Corporation. ''Businesses were unable to immediately react.''</p>
        <p>Productivity -- the amount that the average worker produces in one hour -- fell at an annual rate of 0.2 percent in the nonfarm business sector during the final three months of 2002, the first decline since early 2001. It grew 4.7 percent over the year, according to the Labor Department, as companies cut workers while increasing output.</p>
        <p>A numerical blip may also have played a role in the fourth-quarter decline, analysts said. The Labor Department report showed a rapid rise in the number of hours worked by the self-employed, even as the economy was slowing. Many economists predicted that the government would eventually revise the data, lowering the number of hours worked and thus raising productivity.</p>
        <p>''The one-quarter swing is partly a statistical artifact,'' said Richard B. Berner, the chief domestic economist at Morgan Stanley. ''The surprising thing to me is still that productivity has been as strong as it has been.''</p>
        <p>New technologies and business strategies will probably help productivity grow more quickly in coming years than it did from the mid-1970's to the mid-90's, when it increased about 1.4 percent a year, analysts say. That slowdown caused great concern among economists and policy makers and was seen as a chief reason that wages stagnated.</p>
        <p>But productivity growth accelerated to slightly more than 2 percent a year in the late 1990's, allowing both corporate profits and wages to rise as companies were able to produce goods more efficiently.</p>
        <p>Economists credit improved technology, increased spending on it by businesses and new management techniques intended to compete in an increasingly globalized and deregulated economy.</p>
        <p>''When it all comes out, we will have considerably slower growth of productivity than we did in the late 90's,'' said Dale W. Jorgenson, a Harvard economist. ''But I'm still very sanguine.''</p>
        <p>Productivity gains improve a society's standard of living by allowing it to choose between more goods and more leisure, although the benefits can flow unevenly across the population. During the last two years, the ability of companies to increase output while cutting jobs has helped create the worst employment decline in almost 20 years.</p>
        <p>Even the Federal Reserve is trying to become efficient, announcing yesterday the layoff of 400 workers.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department also reported yesterday that the number of people filing for jobless benefits was little changed last week. A surge in layoffs during late 2002 seems to be ebbing, but few companies are adding to their payrolls.</p>
        <p>First-time claims for unemployment insurance fell to 391,000, from 402,000 the previous week. The number of people receiving jobless benefits rose to 3.35 million from 3.3 million.</p>
        <p>Average labor costs, including salary and benefits, increased at an annual rate of 4.8 percent in the fourth quarter, according to the productivity report, but many analysts said they expected that number to be revised as well. For the full year, labor costs fell 1.7 percent, the biggest decline on record, according to Salomon Smith Barney.</p>
        <p>The Labor Department will release its monthly jobs report for January this morning. Economists expect that employment will have grown by about 60,000 to 80,000 jobs, after having fallen by more than two million since March 2001, and that the unemployment rate will remain at about 6 percent.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
