<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Expos Make Most Of 2 Hits In Inning</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="31" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="702827"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASEBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FLORIDA MARLINS</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">MONTREAL EXPOS</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Kansas City Royals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Florida Marlins</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940730T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DEED71739F933A05754C0A962958260" item-length="838" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Expos Make Most Of 2 Hits In Inning</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By The Associated Press</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Expos 8, Marlins 4 Montreal broke open a tie game with a four-run seventh inning on only two hits as the Expos beat the Florida Marlins, 8-4, in Miami.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Expos 8, Marlins 4 Montreal broke open a tie game with a four-run seventh inning on only two hits as the Expos beat the Florida Marlins, 8-4, in Miami.</p>
        <p>Larry Walker's single drove in Rondell White with the tie-breaking run. The  Expos also scored on a walk, a hit batsman and Sean Berry's sacrifice fly, all with the bases loaded.</p>
        <p>The Expos, who have won 9 of their past 10 games, maintained a lead of two and a half games over Atlanta in the National League East.</p>
        <p>Braves 5, Phillies 2</p>
        <p>Fred McGriff's two-run single capped a three-run fifth inning and Javier Lopez hit a two-run homer an inning later as host Atlanta snapped Philadelphia's four-game winning streak.</p>
        <p>The rally from a 1-0 deficit kept Danny Jackson (13-5) from becoming the N.L.'s second 14-game winner this year. Montreal's Ken Hill is the only pitcher  in the league with 14 victories.</p>
        <p>Reds 4, Padres 1</p>
        <p>Jeff Branson hit a two-run homer and Bret Boone went 3 for 4 with two r.b.i.  as visiting Cincinnati defeated San Diego. Cubs 8, Cardinals 3</p>
        <p>Jim Bullinger (6-2) pitched eight solid innings and Steve Buechele hit a two-run homer and an r.b.i. triple to lead Chicago over host St. Louis.</p>
        <p>Royals 5, Twins 3</p>
        <p>Gary Gaetti hit two solo home runs and made a sparkling defensive play to power host Kansas City past Minnesota for the Royals' longest winning streak in  five years.</p>
        <p>Their seventh straight victory, combined with Cleveland's 5-2 loss to the Yankees, brought the Royals within four and a half games of the lead in the American League Central. Kansas City had not won seven straight since a nine-game streak in August 1989.</p>
        <p>Jose DeJesus (2-0), the fourth man the Royals have tried as their No. 5 starter this year, went seven innings for the victory. He gave up seven hits, struck out three and walked two.</p>
        <p>Red Sox 7, Brewers 2</p>
        <p>Mo Vaughn homered twice and Tim VanEgmond pitched a five-hitter for his first major league victory as host Boston beat Milwaukee.</p>
        <p>Vaughn, who also had an r.b.i. groundout in the first, led off the sixth with a 425-foot drive into the right-field stands and hit a two-run homer into the screen atop the Green Monster as Boston scored four in the seventh. Vaughn, who  has 24 home runs, has homered twice in a game four times this season.</p>
        <p>Blue Jays 4, Orioles 3</p>
        <p>Joe Carter homered and Al Leiter pitched six solid innings as Toronto defeated host Baltimore for the first time this season. Paul Molitor had two hits and scored twice for Toronto, which snapped a three-game losing streak. The Blue Jays were 0-6 against Baltimore, managing only 8 runs in 54 innings.</p>
        <p>Toronto got half that in the opening three innings, scoring twice in the first before Carter hit a two-run homer off Jamie Moyer in the third to make it  4-0. It was his 23d home run of the season and second in two nights, the sixth time this year he has homered in successive games. White Sox 5, Mariners 4</p>
        <p>Alex Fernandez (11-5) won his fifth game without a loss in July, leading Chicago past visiting Seattle.</p>
        <p>Ken Griffey Jr. and Frank Thomas, the top two home-run hitters in the A.L., did not add to their totals. Griffey, who has 36 homers, went 0 for 3 and Thomas, with 35 homers, was 1 for 3 with a sacrifice fly.</p>
        <p>Rangers 5, Angels 3</p>
        <p>Rusty Greer and Dean Palmer hit two-run homers and Roger Pavlik notched his first victory in almost two months as host Texas beat California for its fourth  victory in five games.</p>
        <p>Athletics 6, Tigers 4</p>
        <p>Ruben Sierra hit his 22d home run, breaking an eighth-inning tie and sending  visiting Oakland over Detroit. Seven A's pitchers combined on a four-hitter. Bob Welch (3-6) won in relief and Dennis Eckersley got his 17th save. AROUND THE MAJORS</p>
        <p>Colorado Rockies first baseman ANDRES GALARRAGA underwent surgery on his broken right hand yesterday, and team officials said he will be out at least eight weeks. The Rockies said Galarraga had five screws and a plate implanted in his hand. He fractured the fifth metacarpal bone when he was hit by a pitch thrown Thursday night by San Francisco Giants reliever DAVE BURBA.</p>
        <p>The Chicago Cubs placed right-handed starter ANTHONY YOUNG on the 15-day disabled list yesterday with a strained right elbow. Young is 4-6 this season with a 3.92 e.r.a. in 20 games.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
