<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Highlights of Criticism and Defense of Starr</title>
    <meta content="Y20HIG$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1063611"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: TACTICS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clinton, Bill (Pres)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Starr, Kenneth W</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lowell, Abbe D</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Conyers, John (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Waters, Maxine (Repr)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewinsky, Monica S</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DB1230F933A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1411" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Highlights of Criticism and Defense of Starr</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Nov. 19</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Highlights of criticism and defense of Kenneth W Starr at Judiciary Committee impeachment hearing; photo of Abbe D Lowell, Democratic counsel, and Reprs John Conyers and Maxine Waters (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The independent counsel Kenneth W. Starr answered a broad range of queries about the tactics of his prosecutors, his motives and evidence he gathered. The quotations were provided by the Federal News Service, a private transcription agency.</p>
        <p>The Tone of His Report</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr defended his impeachment referral to Congress after the Democratic counsel, Abbe Lowell, noted that the report of the Watergate prosecutor, Leon Jaworski, was simply a compilation of information that drew ''no accusatory conclusions'' and rendered ''no moral or social judgments.'' Mr. Lowell said Mr. Starr's report betrayed a hostile attitude toward the President.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The independent counsel Kenneth W. Starr answered a broad range of queries about the tactics of his prosecutors, his motives and evidence he gathered. The quotations were provided by the Federal News Service, a private transcription agency.</p>
        <p>The Tone of His Report</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr defended his impeachment referral to Congress after the Democratic counsel, Abbe Lowell, noted that the report of the Watergate prosecutor, Leon Jaworski, was simply a compilation of information that drew ''no accusatory conclusions'' and rendered ''no moral or social judgments.'' Mr. Lowell said Mr. Starr's report betrayed a hostile attitude toward the President.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr responded that he ''stood behind every word of it,'' and described the report as a tool for the Judiciary Committee to use or ignore as it saw fit. He said the report represented his best judgment of the evidence gathered in months of grand jury testimony.</p>
        <p>''What we tried to do in this referral,'' Mr. Starr told Mr. Lowell, ''was to assemble in an organized form, rather than sending you simply truckloads of unorganized information, give it coherence. And then it is your judgment. And thus if it is the judgment that this referral has not in fact stood the test of your close examination -- did we get the facts wrong? -- then, of course, you should come to your own judgment and your own assessment.''</p>
        <p>Dealing With Ms. Lewinsky</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr came under fire repeatedly for the tactics of his inquiry, particularly his agents' treatment of Monica S. Lewinsky and other potential witnesses and targets.</p>
        <p>Mr. Lowell said that Ms. Lewinsky had been held for hours against her will at a Ritz-Carlton hotel in suburban Virginia and discouraged from contacting her lawyer or her mother. He said Ms. Lewinsky felt threatened by the agents and was frightened by their manner.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr insisted that Ms. Lewinsky had been free to leave at any time and had never been mistreated or threatened.</p>
        <p>''I think her perception was incorrect,'' Mr. Starr said. ''We made it clear to the witness that she was, in fact, free to leave. And the Ritz-Carlton, shall I say, is a fairly comfortable and commodious place.</p>
        <p>''We will show you -- I am sure you have them -- telephone records that indicate she reached out to Mr. Carter, her attorney, in a totally different matter; she called her mother; she, in fact, went for a walk, she went to a restaurant and the like.  And all these were important because, Mr. Lowell, what the office was being accused of was somehow overbearing her will. And she didn't need to make a decision, because -- here's the other side of the picture -- she was encouraging others to join her in committing perjury. She was, as the information came to us, a felon in the middle of committing another felony.''</p>
        <p>Determining Perjury</p>
        <p>Several Republicans asked Mr. Starr to assess Mr. Clinton's truthfulness. Representative Elton Gallegly, Republican of California, asked: ''But briefly, Judge Starr, if we could revisit the Jones deposition, the President was asked whether he had ever given any gifts to Miss Lewinsky. Does evidence gathered indicate that the President gave false or misleading testimony when he answered, 'I don't recall'?'' Mr. Starr replied: ''Yes. Our assessment -- and this was an assessment shared by the very experienced and career prosecutors -- was that the events of Dec. 28, 1997, must have been so clear and vivid in any reasonable person's recollection that the President would naturally have recalled that on Jan. 17, 1998, less than one month later, given the nature of the events, which are undisputed, of what happened during that Oval Office visit by Ms. Lewinsky to the President over the holiday period.</p>
        <p>''So the recollection was so clear -- or the events were so clear -- that to suggest that one doesn't recall a Rockettes blanket and the like, the various gifts that were shared between the two, just in our view defied credulity, especially in light of the fact that we did have testimony, which is now before you, that the President is blessed with one of the most powerful memories that many people who have come in contact with a wide variety of people have ever seen. So we are told the President's memory is extremely strong.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Gallegly then asked Mr. Starr, ''Would you say that it would be reasonable to say that might be selective recall?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr replied, ''Well, I don't like to get into characterization, but I would simply say I would not resist such a characterization.''</p>
        <p>Tactics of the Inquiry</p>
        <p>Representative Maxine Waters, Democrat of California, berated Mr. Starr for the tactics of his investigation. ''I have been one of your harshest critics, and you know it,'' Ms. Waters said when given her chance to question the independent counsel. ''I have been appalled by what I consider the gross unfairness of the procedure, of the way in which you have conducted yourself.''</p>
        <p>She cited the case of Julie Hiatt Steele, a friend of Kathleen Willey, who accused the President of groping her in a hallway adjacent to the Oval Office. Ms. Waters said that investigators asked Ms. Steele for her tax records, telephone records, bank receipts and information about her adoption of a child.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr said that his office followed normal investigative methods to determine whether a witness is telling the truth.</p>
        <p>''We have asked, through F.B.I. investigators, a variety of questions to individuals that, in the judgment of professional, experienced investigators, have a bearing on the witness's credibility,'' Mr. Starr said.</p>
        <p>Ms. Waters then asked about a subpoena served at an Arkansas high school on the 16-year-old son of one witness in the Whitewater investigation.</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr said that no subpoena had been served but that an investigator had in fact gone to a school to question a potential witness. He acknowledged that it was an error.</p>
        <p>''That was in the Arkansas phase of our investigation,'' Mr. Starr said. ''The individual in question, we believed, had relevant information. No subpoena, as I understand it, was in fact served, but the agent in question did go to the school. In my judgment, that was a misjudgment.''</p>
        <p>On His Motivation</p>
        <p>Representative Mary Bono, Republican of California, asked Mr. Starr about his motivations. ''Do you have this bone to pick with the President, or this personal vendetta?'' she asked. ''Do you hold personal animosity toward him, and has that affected the job you've done?</p>
        <p>Mr. Starr thanked her for the question, and said: ''I hold no animosity and I would love to be back in private life. I received questions today with respect to, well -- didn't you accept a deanship at Pepperdine and look who made a contribution -- so, you're right. I would prefer to be almost your constituent. A little bit farther West. I would like to be -- and I'd even looked at a house in Malibu Country Estates; that's where I would like to be.</p>
        <p>''I would like to be living my life with my family, and I tried to do that because I had a view that I could, in fact, lay down the mantle long before Monica Lewinsky ever walked into the nation's life, and pass the mantle on to someone else because of what I had tried to create, and I talked about it today, which is that this Office of Independent Counsel should, in fact, reflect the experience and practice of the Justice Department.''  TESTING OF A PRESIDENT: TACTICS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
