<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>On Stage and Off; House Hunting Can Be Tricky</title>
    <meta content="20BROA$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Movies, Performing Arts/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1063520"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theaters (Buildings)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Helen Hayes Theater (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Times Square Theater (NYC)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Times Square and 42d Street (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Livent Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New 42d Street (Orgn)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Markinson, Martin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mckinley, Jesse</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bernhard, Sandra</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tepper, Arielle</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Wendt, George</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hirsch, Judd</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Morton, Joe</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Cahan, Cora</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Band in Berlin (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Wit (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">This Is Our Youth (Play)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">I'M Still Here...damn It! (Show)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Art (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/On Stage and Off</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Music, Theater and Dance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restoration and Rehabilitation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEEDE1530F933A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="1078" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>On Stage and Off; House Hunting Can Be Tricky</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Jesse McKinley</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Mckinley, Jesse</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Battle over Helen Hayes Theater ends with announcement that Band in Berlin, new musical about singing troupe in Nazi Germany, will open there in February; decision by theater owner Martin Markinson disappoints two Off Broadway hits, Wit and This Is Our Youth, which have sought Broadway house; collapse of Livent deal to renovate Times Square Theater may doom plans for new performance space; New 42d Street president, Cora Cahan, comments; Arielle Tepper, 26, is youngest producer on Broadway, sharing top billing on Sandra Bernhard's I'm Still Here...Damn It!; Tepper photo; Waiting for Godot and Stop Kiss report strong Off Broadway sales; next Art cast will be George Wendt, Judd Hirsch and Joe Morton (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The battle over the Helen Hayes Theater ended this week with the announcement that ''Band in Berlin,'' a new musical about a singing troupe in Nazi Germany, would open there in late February.</p>
        <p>The decision by the theater's owner, Martin Markinson, to book the musical was a heartbreaker for two Off Broadway hits vying for a Broadway house: ''Wit,'' Margaret Edson's acclaimed drama, and ''This Is Our Youth,'' a dark comedy by Kenneth Lonergan.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The battle over the Helen Hayes Theater ended this week with the announcement that ''Band in Berlin,'' a new musical about a singing troupe in Nazi Germany, would open there in late February.</p>
        <p>The decision by the theater's owner, Martin Markinson, to book the musical was a heartbreaker for two Off Broadway hits vying for a Broadway house: ''Wit,'' Margaret Edson's acclaimed drama, and ''This Is Our Youth,'' a dark comedy by Kenneth Lonergan.</p>
        <p>But by the end of the week there was a happy ending for at least one of the shows. Negotiations were completed yesterday to bring ''Wit'' to the Union Square Theater, a 499-seat house where ''Visiting Mr. Green'' closes on Sunday. ''Wit'' will finish its current run on Dec. 13 at the 99-seat MCC Theater before reopening later that week in the larger space.</p>
        <p>''We're totally thrilled,'' said Bernard Telsey, who will produce the show along with Daryl Roth and the Long Wharf Theater. ''It's going to be the same intimate experience but for 500 people a night.''</p>
        <p>''This Is Our Youth,'' meanwhile, was also looking at a move, from its current home at Second Stage to the Minetta Lane, where ''Primary English Class'' is folding after a rude reception from critics. At the Helen Hayes, Mr. Markinson said he hoped ''Getting and Spending,'' the current occupant, would last into 1999. But don't count on it; weekly grosses are hovering around $70,000, an estimated weekly loss of more than $60,000.</p>
        <p>For ''Band in Berlin,'' the move to Broadway comes as a pleasant surprise. The show was to open in November at the Union Square but was bumped when f ''Visiting Mr. Green'' was unexpectedly extended. ''The Helen Hayes was always my dream,'' said Robert V. Straus, a producer of ''Berlin.'' ''I didn't really want any other theater.''</p>
        <p>Something's Coming</p>
        <p>When Livent was chosen in August to renovate the Times Square Theater on West 42d Street, it triumphed over higher bidders because it planned a new theater for the space. But now that the deal has collapsed, live performance may not be in the cards for the 78-year-old landmark.</p>
        <p>Cora Cahan, the president of New 42d Street, which oversees the space, said this week that of the half-dozen candidates for the renovation, most made it clear they were not interested in building a performance space. The theater poses several problems for productions, ranging from its age to potential noise problems, to its lack of an adequate lobby.</p>
        <p>''It's not really great for theater in its current state,'' Ms. Cahan said.</p>
        <p>A real estate executive who has seen the proposals said candidates included past also-rans like Empire, a Roman gladiator-theme restaurant, and the Laugh Factory, a comedy club, as well as the Manhattan Theater Club and the producer Alexander H. Cohen, who has a proposal for a vaudeville theater. Ms. Cahan said she hoped for a decision by the end of the year.</p>
        <p>Experience Optional</p>
        <p>With all due respect, most Broadway producers are a, well, mature breed. And manly, too.</p>
        <p>Not Arielle Tepper. At 26, she is by far the youngest producer on Broadway today, sharing top billing on Sandra Bernhard's ''I'm Still Here . . . Damn It!''</p>
        <p>The show is Ms. Tepper's second on Broadway; her first was John Leguizamo's ''Freak,'' which she produced with Gregory Mosher and Bill Haber. Off Broadway, Ms. Tepper is involved in ''Villa Villa,'' at the Daryl Roth, and ''Trainspotting,'' at the Player's Theater. Not bad for a woman whose first professional producing experience was in March 1997, putting on an unknown musical in a small theater in Chicago.</p>
        <p>''I took a job after my freshman year in college in a production office,'' Ms. Tepper said, speaking from a cellular phone from the set of an independent film she's producing in Yonkers. ''Within 24 hours I knew this was what I wanted to do.''</p>
        <p>Though her age and sex may set her apart, she shares the common traits of money and pedigree with her producorial predecessors. Ms. Tepper grew up in a wealthy family on the Upper East Side of Manhattan and attended the tony Dalton School before studying lighting design at Syracuse University.</p>
        <p>Like her idol, Cameron Mackintosh, she has experienced both success and something less. While ''Freak'' was a hit, and ''I'm Still Here'' is showing promise, ''Trainspotting'' has had a rough time with the critics. Still, Ms. Tepper seems undeterred. ''If I've figured one thing out,'' she said, ''it's the only way to learn is to do it.''</p>
        <p>'Godot' Has Arrived</p>
        <p>Add ''Waiting for Godot'' and ''Stop Kiss'' to the growing list of Off Broadway productions showing strong sales.</p>
        <p>''Godot,'' which opened on Wednesday at the 180-seat Classic Stage Company on East 13th Street, has sold out almost all its six-week run, through Dec. 20. Barry Edelstein, the artistic director of the theater, said that it had held back 500 seats, and that those tickets would go on sale today at $45, up from $35.</p>
        <p>With apologies to Beckett, the obvious draw has been the cast: John Turturro, Tony Shalhoub and Christopher Lloyd. ''People want to see actors they know are great,'' Mr. Edelstein said. ''And in our theater, you're sitting five feet away.''</p>
        <p>The appeal of ''Stop Kiss'' is less easily explained. The play, which began previews at the Papp Public Theater on Tuesday, has sold about 85 percent of the tickets for its five-week run.</p>
        <p>The reaction has flummoxed the playwright, Diana Son, whose most recent work had a brief Off Off Broadway run earlier this year. ''Stop Kiss'' concerns the repercussions in the lives of two women after they kiss. ''I think people have heard it's a comedy about New York, a drama about gay bashing and a love story, and it really is all of those,'' said Ms. Son, 32. ''I guess people want to see if we can pull it off.''</p>
        <p>You Know His Name</p>
        <p>The next cast for ''Art'' -- George Wendt, Judd Hirsch and Joe Morton -- will take over on Dec. 22. It will be the Broadway debut for Mr. Wendt, the former ''Cheers'' star who just finished a 14-week run of ''Art'' in London. ''The idea of opening in London as an American was a little scarier,'' he said. ''This is kind of a lateral move in terms of scariness.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
