<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>CABARET GUIDE</title>
    <meta content="20CABA$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="20" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Leisure/Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="50" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="E" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1063510"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NO INDEX TERMS FROM NYTIMES</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Schedule</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19981120T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C05E2DE1530F933A15752C1A96E958260" item-length="2388" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>CABARET GUIDE</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stephen Holden</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Here is a selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Here is a selective listing of new or noteworthy cabaret shows in Manhattan this weekend. * denotes a highly recommended show.</p>
        <p>* ''L'AMOUR, THE MERRIER,'' Kaufman Theater, 534 West 42d Street, Clinton, (212) 239-6200. Starring Steve Ross, with Karen Murphy. Mr. Ross, debonair to the nth degree, and Ms. Murphy, a brassy, playful theater singer who knows how to curl seductively atop a grand piano, portray a loquacious urbane couple serenading each other, and sometimes bickering, in sophisticated song. The many composers include the Gershwins, Irving Berlin, Lerner and Loewe, Frank Loesser, Stephen Sondheim and, above all, Cole Porter. It was said of Fred Astaire and Ginger Rogers that she gave him sex and he gave her class. A similar chemistry is at work here. Tonight at 8; tomorrow at 3 and 8 P.M.; Sundays at 3 and 7 P.M. Through Nov. 22. Tickets: $30 and $35.</p>
        <p>JUDI CONNELLI, Firebird Cafe, 363 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 586-0244. A big-voiced Australian contralto who emotes with overwrought operatic gestures, Ms. Connelli favors weepy warhorses by the likes of Andrew Lloyd Webber, Jerry Herman and Michel Legrand (with lyrics by Alan and Marilyn Bergman). The voice, although impressive, tends to crush all but the most dramatic numbers. Two songs that stand up to her approach are ''Could I Leave You?'' from ''Follies,'' and ''As If We Never Said Goodbye'' from ''Sunset Boulevard.'' On up-tempo material, the light touch eludes her. Tuesdays through Thursdays at 9 P.M.; Fridays and Saturdays at 9 and 11 P.M. Through Nov. 28. Cover: $30; two-drink minimum.</p>
        <p>* BLOSSOM DEARIE, Danny's Skylight Room, 346 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 265-8133. The ageless bohemian singer, songwriter, pianist and wit with the blond pixie is cabaret's reigning minimalist and makes the tiniest vocal inflections, hesitations and dynamic shifts count. Such is her mastery of timing that the smallest gesture can be laugh-out-loud funny. Or it can just as easily put you into a wistful trance. Expect to hear such signature songs as ''I'm Hip'' and ''Peel Me a Grape,'' along with numbers in a bossa-nova groove. Ray Kilday and Luiz Peralta offer seamless support on bass and percussion. A must-see. Through December. Tonight and tomorrow night at 9:15; Sunday night at 6:15. Cover: $20; $10 minimum.</p>
        <p>* ''SECRETS EVERY SMART TRAVELER SHOULD KNOW,'' Ibis Theater, 321 West 44th Street, Clinton, (212) 799-4599. Among the dozen songwriters who have contributed to this witty early-60's-style revue spoofing the perils of travel, the show's musical director, Stan Freeman, and its bass player, Jay Leonhart, have provided several of the best bits. Mr. Freeman's ''Paradise Found'' extols the highly questionable pleasures of roughing it in Uzbekistan. Mr. Leonhart's ''Customs'' is the complaint of an explorer detained in customs with his menagerie. The level of humor is not as scattershot as in most such shows. The cast includes Ray DeMattis, Maribeth Graham, Denise Nolin and Nick Santa Maria, with Mr. Leonhart on bass and Charlie Alternman on piano and vocals. Open-ended run. Reopens tomorrow at 2:30 and 8 P.M.; Sunday at 3 and 7:30 P.M., and Monday, and Wednesdays through Fridays at 8 P.M. Tickets: $20 to $47.50.</p>
        <p>* BOBBY SHORT, Cafe Carlyle, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. The eternally ebullient Bobby Short is back at Cafe Carlyle, and the chemistry between the singer-pianist and his band is clicking more harmoniously than ever. The unfussy, swinging arrangements featuring three brasses and three reeds bring out the exuberant belter in Mr. Short, who turns the cafe every night into a euphoric private party in which he shouts out popular chestnuts with the enthusiasm of a roue who hasn't lost touch with the little boy inside. Tuesdays through Saturdays at 8:45 and 10:45 P.M. Cover: $50; no minimum.</p>
        <p>* JULIE WILSON, Michael's Pub, at the Park Restaurant, 111 East 56th Street, (212) 758-2272. The elegant 73-year-old cabaret legend has reunited with her longtime accompanist and occasional vocal partner, William Roy, to revive a brilliant Gershwin show that they first performed 12 years ago at the Algonquin Hotel. Ms. Wilson, as usual, finds surprisingly emotional subtexts in Gershwin's airy songs by infusing them with her life experience. ''But Not for Me,'' ''The Man I Love,'' ''He Loves and She Loves,'' ''Someone to Watch Over Me'' and ''Isn't It a Pity?'' are among the numbers she turns into pointed dramatic monologues by fixing on just the right phrase from which to approach them as personal reflections. Tuesdays through Saturdays at 9 and 11 P.M. Music charge: $25 Tuesday through Thursday and $30 on Friday and Saturday; $15 minimum for all shows.</p>
        <p>BEMELMANS BAR, Carlyle Hotel, 35 East 76th Street, (212) 744-1600. Barbara Carroll, singer-pianist. Tuesdays through Saturdays from 9:30 P.M. to 12:30 A.M. Through Dec. 31. Cover: $10.</p>
        <p>DON'T TELL MAMA, 343 West 46th Street, Clinton, (212) 757-0788. Tonight at 7, Beverly Bonner, comedy; at 8, Julia Wade, singer; at 9, Jojit Fernandez, singer; at 10, Jamie deRoy and friends. Tomorrow night at 4, Anika Altman, singer; at 5, Trent Blanchard; at 6, Jennifer Callan, singer; at 7, Marlene Young; at 8 and 10:30, comedy with Ron Poole and Rob Pitaccio; at 9, Fast Forward Comedy. Sunday at 3 P.M., Beth Velenti, singer; also at 3, Marlene Young, singer; at 5, Mark Corpron, singer; at 5:30, Jack Poggi, singer; at 7, Trent Blanchard, singer; at 8, Gina Caruso, singer; at 9, Christine Pedi, musical comedy; at 10, William Youmans and Emily Loesser in ''I Want to Be Happy,'' musical revue. Cover: $8 to $20; two-drink minimum. No credit cards.</p>
        <p>EIGHTY-EIGHT'S, 228 West 10th Street, West Village, (212) 924-0088. Tonight at 6, Mary Lou Schreiber, singer; at 8, ''For the Fun of It,'' musical comedy; at 11, Musty Chiffon, singer and characterization. Tomorrow night at 8:30, Tom Andersen; at 11, Patrick DeGennaro. Sunday at 5:30 P.M., Claiborne Cary, singer; at 8, Heather MacRae, singer. Cover: $12 to $15; two-drink minimum. No credit cards.</p>
        <p>RAINBOW AND STARS, Rainbow and Stars, 30 Rockefeller Plaza, 65th floor, (212) 632-5000. The singer Karen Akers, tonight and tomorrow at 8:30 and 11 P.M. Through Dec. 5. Tuesdays through Saturdays. Cover: $40. Dinner,  at 6:30 P.M., is required for the early show; one-drink minimum for the late show.</p>
        <p>SUPPER CLUB, 240 West 47th Street, (212) 921-1940. ''The Joint Is Jumpin,' '' with the singers  Vivian Reed and Kevin Ramsey, in a tribute to big-band music. Fridays and Saturdays at 9 P.M. Cover: $20, plus the cost of dinner.</p>
        <p>UPSTAIRS AT ROSE'S TURN, 55 Grove Street, West Village, (212) 366-5438. Tonight at 8, the Improvoholics, an improvisation troupe; at 10, ''Three Sheets to the Wind,'' musical comedy. Tomorrow night at 8, Rick Crom's ''Our Life and Times,'' musical revue; at 10, Red Shag, improvisational-comedy. Sunday night at 6, Rick Crom's ''Our Life and Times; at 8, ''The Seth Rudetsky Show,'' variety. Cover: $5 to $12; two-drink minimum. No credit cards.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
