<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Germans To Have One Team</title>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="365983"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">OLYMPIC GAMES (1992)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SUMMER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WINTER GAMES (OLYMPICS)</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WEST GERMANY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">EAST GERMANY</location>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Olympics 2004</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Europe/Germany</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Games</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Olympic Games</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19900705T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE5DA143BF936A35754C0A966958260" item-length="393" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Germans To Have One Team</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">AP</byline>
      <dateline>EAST BERLIN, July 4</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: There will be a unified German team for the Winter and Summer Olympics in 1992, the presidents of the two national Olympic committees announced today.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: There will be a unified German team for the Winter and Summer Olympics in 1992, the presidents of the two national Olympic committees announced today.</p>
        <p>There will be a unified German team for the Winter and Summer Olympics in 1992, the presidents of the two national Olympic committees announced today.</p>
        <p>It will be the first time since the 1964 Summer Olympics in Tokyo that a unified German team will compete.</p>
        <p>Willi Daume, president of the West German Olympic Committee, and Joachim Weiskopf, president of the counterpart East German organization, said the two national committees would merge in December to oversee the formation of a single team.</p>
        <p>The union will follow the political merging of the two German states, expected in early December.</p>
        <p>No Dissension</p>
        <p>''We had no dissenting opinions whatsoever,'' Daume said. ''The unification will be completed by the two Olympic committees in an orderly fashion. We will be working intensively together in the coming weeks.''</p>
        <p>The first appearance by a united German team in international sports would probably be at an international competition at the world indoor track championships in Seville, Spain, March 8-10, 1991, sports authorities in East Berlin said.</p>
        <p>''We're moving ahead quickly for the sake of the athletes,'' Weiskopf said. ''A fast merger is important in order to remove any uncertainty about who will make the team.</p>
        <p>''As the two Germanys grow together there has been great concern over whether the athletes would feel shorted out of the competition for fewer places. We find great support among our sportsmen for forming one team from one country.''</p>
        <p>The two Olympic committee presidents said there was complete agreement between the two organizations about the decision.</p>
        <p>Questions Remain</p>
        <p>Weiskopf said it was not clear how the team would be selected and how funds would be raised to finance it. He also said the international sports governing bodies would need to decide how a single German team would be represented in qualifying competitions for world and Olympic events.</p>
        <p>Separate teams representing both national Olympic committees have already participated in qualifying events in some sports.</p>
        <p>In addition, both Olympic Committee presidents said they supported the choice of Berlin as site of the Olympics in 2000.</p>
        <p>The groups, with active participation by athletes, will develop concrete plans for the formation of a team for the 1992 Winter Games in Albertville, France, and the Summer Olympics in Barcelona, Spain.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
