<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Renter-to-Owner Ratio Shifts, and With It the Political Climate</title>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="593532"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="METRO MATTERS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">HOUSING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RENTING AND LEASING</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">ROBERTS, SAM</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Columns/Metro Matters</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Real Estate/Locations/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Housing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Renting and Leasing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930301T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE7D9133DF932A35750C0A965958260" item-length="926" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Renter-to-Owner Ratio Shifts, and With It the Political Climate</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Sam Roberts</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ROBERTS, SAM</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IF reports of its death are greatly exaggerated, liberalism may be ailing in New York City because of shifts in a sensitive sociological index: the ratio between condos and condoms.</p>
        <p>A larger proportion of New Yorkers now own their homes or apartments than at any time in the 20th century. And owners, rendered less mobile physically and less liquid fiscally by their stakes in real estate, tend to be more politically conservative than renters. Liberal leadership also has been diluted by divisions between black and Hispanic politicians and between white liberals and blacks and by the ascendancy of white liberals in the political establishment.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IF reports of its death are greatly exaggerated, liberalism may be ailing in New York City because of shifts in a sensitive sociological index: the ratio between condos and condoms.</p>
        <p>A larger proportion of New Yorkers now own their homes or apartments than at any time in the 20th century. And owners, rendered less mobile physically and less liquid fiscally by their stakes in real estate, tend to be more politically conservative than renters. Liberal leadership also has been diluted by divisions between black and Hispanic politicians and between white liberals and blacks and by the ascendancy of white liberals in the political establishment.</p>
        <p>As the share of property owners has grown, the city has been riven by conflicts over what are loosely described as traditional social values -- values that have been put to the test as government usurped New Yorker's personal prerogatives by making condoms available to public school students, teaching tolerance and acceptance of gay and lesbian life styles, and ordering that a gay and lesbian group be allowed to march behind its own banner in the St. Patrick's Day parade.</p>
        <p>That those decisions have provoked a vocal backlash could mean several things: the group that once proclaimed itself the silent majority has found its voice again; the group is not a majority at all but has just become louder for the time being than other minorities; New York's reputation for liberalism, like the reports of its demise, has been greatly exaggerated, a possibility raised by the conflicts that culminated in last month's 4-to-3 vote by the Board of Education to dismiss Schools Chancellor Joseph A. Fernandez, or it could mean all of the above.</p>
        <p>The board's voting majority, blithely dismissed by some critics as a Gang of Four, "probably reflects where that population is," Gov. Mario M. Cuomo acknowledged the other day.</p>
        <p>"I don't think New York City was ever as liberal as its reputation," Mr. Cuomo said. "I don't think that was ever true. Manhattan has always been very liberal. Queens is not. I will grant you that political power has been mostly Democratic, but I would not say that it has been overwhelmingly liberal."</p>
        <p>Not since John V. Lindsay has a self-avowed liberal running with the imprimatur of the ideologically accommodating Liberal Party been elected Mayor. "I do not know what else Mr. Lindsay's victory established," said William F. Buckley Jr., the Conservative Party mayoral candidate whom Mr. Lindsay defeated in 1965, "than that people do scare easily and that New York is a very 'liberal' community."</p>
        <p>The following year, though, New Yorkers disproved the second part of Mr. Buckley's thesis, rejecting a referendum on Mr. Lindsay's decision to place civilians on the board that reviews complaints against the police. And in 1969, Mr. Lindsay was re-elected only because a Republican from Staten Island and a conservative Democrat who lived on the Bronx border (one of his home telephone numbers was listed in Westchester, giving a new dimension to the dismissive phrase "outer borough") split the opposition. That conservative Democrat, Mario A. Procaccino, had bitingly dubbed Mr. Lindsay's supporters the "limousine liberals" who, from their economic isolation in Manhattan, preached dogma for others to practice.</p>
        <p>Mr. Procaccino, who, in defending his record on racial tolerance, once boasted, "my heart is as black as any man's," was considered more conservative than Abraham D. Beame of Brooklyn, the Democrat whom Mr. Lindsay defeated in 1965 and who succeeded him in 1973. That they were actually closer ideologically on many social issues, if not in stature, had been suggested earlier by Mr. Buckley. The differences between the diminutive Mr. Beame and the statuesque Mr. Lindsay, he had said, "are biological, not political."</p>
        <p>Four years later, New Yorkers elected Edward I. Koch, a self-described "liberal with sanity" -- a characterization that his critics questioned on both counts. In 1989, Mr. Koch lost to David N. Dinkins, who, like his once and future Republican rival, Rudolph W. Giuliani, strained to depict himself as Mr. Lindsay's spiritual heir. But Mr. Dinkins, a proud product of Harlem's Democratic machine, also embraced a typically conservative totem -- law and order -- in promising to be the city's toughest mayor on crime.</p>
        <p>What is a liberal, anyway? To Irving Kristol's definition of a neoconservative as a liberal who was mugged by reality, Tom Wolfe countered that "a liberal is a conservative who has been arrested." In a 1992 New York Times/CBS-TV News poll last fall, most New York City adults described themselves as politically moderate. About the same proportion called themselves conservative as liberal. Last fall, New York Democrats, tired of losing, embraced a presidential candidate who failed or fudged the customary liberal litmus tests.</p>
        <p>Party loyalty and philosophy have been subsumed again by concerns over government's ability to deliver services and to butt out of matters in which it may not belong. That is neither new nor unique.</p>
        <p>If any major city rivals New York's reputation as a liberal bastion, it is San Francisco. In the last municipal election there, the liberal establishment and its incumbent Mayor were defeated by a former police chief who promised to get tough with problems ranging from panhandlers to potholes. His election was a vivid reminder that even in a progressive city, concerns about condos and condoms may mean that pragmatism in the defense of property and pristine puberty is no vice.</p>
        <p>METRO MATTERS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
