<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>I.M.F. Report Forecasts 3% Growth</title>
    <meta content="25" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="440479"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ECONOMIC CONDITIONS AND TRENDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FORECASTS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">INTERNATIONAL MONETARY FUND (IMF)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910425T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE3DD163DF936A15757C0A967958260" item-length="822" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>I.M.F. Report Forecasts 3% Growth</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LOUIS UCHITELLE,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">UCHITELLE, LOUIS</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, April 24</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The International Monetary Fund predicted today that the world's economies would rebound briskly in 1992 after weak growth this year -- but the rebound might never materialize if the United States recession fails to end soon.</p>
        <p>The I.M.F., in its semiannual outlook report, said worldwide economic growth was likely to slow to an average of 1.2 percent in 1991 -- barely enough to avoid recession -- from 2.1 percent last year. But the fund predicted an average growth rate of nearly 3 percent next year, mainly on the strength of recoveries in the United States, Britain and Canada. All are now in recession.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The International Monetary Fund predicted today that the world's economies would rebound briskly in 1992 after weak growth this year -- but the rebound might never materialize if the United States recession fails to end soon.</p>
        <p>The I.M.F., in its semiannual outlook report, said worldwide economic growth was likely to slow to an average of 1.2 percent in 1991 -- barely enough to avoid recession -- from 2.1 percent last year. But the fund predicted an average growth rate of nearly 3 percent next year, mainly on the strength of recoveries in the United States, Britain and Canada. All are now in recession.</p>
        <p>"If the United States recession lasts longer than we anticipate, then, yes, the whole world will be adversely affected," Ernesto Hernandez-Cata, director of the outlook report, said at a news conference. "But I think the recession will be a short one. You can say you heard that here."</p>
        <p>The fund attributed the 1991 slowdown, involving virtually every region of the world, to disruptions resulting from the Persian Gulf crisis, the North American and British recessions and sharply falling output in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe.  Recovery Expected Soon</p>
        <p>Economic growth in the United States will average only two-tenths of 1 percent this year, down from 1 percent last year, the fund estimated. But with a recovery starting this summer, the nation's gross national product, covering all of the goods and services produced each year, would rise to an average of 2.7 percent in 1992 -- a forecast roughly in line with the Bush Administration's projections and those of many private forecasters.</p>
        <p>Indeed, as the basis for its optimism about the United States, the monetary fund cited many of the reasons that American economists have put forward to support a widely held view that the recession will end by this fall, roughly a year after it began. Interest rates have fallen sharply in recent months, encouraging consumers to borrow and spend again, and inflation is easing, the fund said.</p>
        <p>Fund officials also noted that inventories in the United States are low, which means that production to restock shelves can resume almost as soon as consumers step up their buying. American exports, key to a recovery from the recession, are also likely to remain strong, the fund said, even though the economies of two major importers of American goods, Japan and Germany, are weakening a bit.</p>
        <p>American exports fell in March, partly because of weakening overseas economies. "There is a slump in Europe," Mr. Hernandez-Cata acknowledged. "But these countries are still strong enough to absorb enough American exports."  Endorsement of Fed Policy</p>
        <p>Expecting an upturn, the Federal Reserve Board has become reluctant in recent weeks to continue pushing down interest rates as a means of stimulating the economy and insuring the expected upturn. Jacob Frenkel, the I.M.F.'s research director, in effect, endorsed the American central bank's monetary policy.</p>
        <p>"This is not the time for an activist monetary policy," Mr. Frenkel said. He said the Fed should take its cue from the marketplace. If rates fall naturally because the American economy weakens unexpectedly or inflation becomes less and less of a problem, "then the Fed should not resist also lowering rates," he said.</p>
        <p>The report said the currencies of the United States, Germany and Japan were roughly in the proper alignment. The report suggested that none of the three should alter interest rates to change the value of their curriences. "The dollar has recovered markedly since February, and this has alleviated concerns about the weakness of the dollar," the report said.</p>
        <p>The report also included these major points:</p>
        <p>*World trade will shrink this year because of the economic slowdown, and rebound strongly next year. The United States' share of total world output has declined, partly as a result of the recession, "while the shares of Japan, West Germany and the newly industrialized countries of Asia, where growth remains robust, have increased."</p>
        <p>*The shifting growth rates are expected to reduce the United States trade deficit and also the trade surpluses in Germany and Japan -- in effect, narrowing the differences among these countries, not only in trade but also in their current accounts, which cover all international transactions, including trade.</p>
        <p>*Oil prices, which averaged $16 a barrel last July, before the Persian Gulf crisis, and rose to as much as $40 a barrel in September, will average just over $17 a barrel in 1991, eliminating a source of inflation.</p>
        <p>*Foreign debt among all of the developing countries rose by 6 percent in 1990, to a total of $1.3 trillion, and is likely to rise again this year and next, in every region of the world except, perhaps, the Western Hemisphere.</p>
        <p>With Germany, Eastern Europe, and the Mideast drawing capital to rebuild, the developing world might have difficulty getting loans.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
