<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>United Nations Journal; Rome, My Dear Watson, Was Not Built in a Day</title>
    <meta content="Y22NOB$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Foreign Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="World" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19980827T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1040734"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Nobel Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dag Hammarskjold Medal</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">United Nations</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Lewis, Paul</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Nobel Prizes</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Awards, Decorations and Honors</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980822T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DE4D6113DF931A1575BC0A96E958260" item-length="856" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>United Nations Journal; Rome, My Dear Watson, Was Not Built in a Day</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAUL LEWIS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Lewis, Paul</byline>
      <dateline>UNITED NATIONS, Aug. 21</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mystery of what happened to $339,000 that United Nations received with Nobel Peace Prize in 1988 is cleared up when it turns out that it was bureaucratic indecisiveness about what to do with money that accounted for its apparent absence; Nobel Peace Prize check will be spent on a memorial at United Nations headquarters in New York commemorating fallen peacekeepers, as well as any peacekeepers who may die in years ahead; United Nations will issue Dag Hammarskjold Medals to relatives of all slain peacekeepers, paid for out of its own budget; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The mystery of the disappearing Nobel Peace Prize is about to be solved, my dear Watson, almost 10 years after that check for $339,000 first went missing.</p>
        <p>The check was last seen briefly at a ceremony in the hall of Oslo University on the wet and chilly morning of Dec. 10, 1988, when Javier Perez de Cuellar, then the United Nations Secretary General, stuffed it into his breast pocket after formally accepting that year's Nobel Peace Prize on behalf of the 10,500 blue-helmeted peacekeeping soldiers his organization had sent to keep order in trouble spots around the world.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The mystery of the disappearing Nobel Peace Prize is about to be solved, my dear Watson, almost 10 years after that check for $339,000 first went missing.</p>
        <p>The check was last seen briefly at a ceremony in the hall of Oslo University on the wet and chilly morning of Dec. 10, 1988, when Javier Perez de Cuellar, then the United Nations Secretary General, stuffed it into his breast pocket after formally accepting that year's Nobel Peace Prize on behalf of the 10,500 blue-helmeted peacekeeping soldiers his organization had sent to keep order in trouble spots around the world.</p>
        <p>It was cashed, deposited. But then the money itself simply seemed to vanish from view. For almost a decade, the United Nations uttered not a word about what it had done, or planned to do, with the money. That was decidedly odd for an organization perennially strapped for cash.</p>
        <p>Naturally, some suspected a fiendish purloining of funds. But the truth is far more prosaic. Put 5,000 international civil servants from 185 countries into a 38-story skyscraper and what do you get? A recipe for indecision. The United Nations simply could not make up its mind.</p>
        <p>Sir Marrack Goulding, the Warden of St. Anthony's College at Oxford University, who was in charge of United Nations peacekeeping when the Nobel Prize was awarded, said the Secretary General wanted to use the money for a high-profile essay competition that would encourage young people to take interest in international affairs.</p>
        <p>''It was an idea I was sympathetic towards myself,'' Sir Marrack said. But it fell victim to the Curse of Babel, he explained.</p>
        <p>If the essays were to be written in English, Anglophones would enjoy an unfair advantage. But if all languages were allowed, the cost of translation would be prohibitive.</p>
        <p>Commanders of peacekeeping forces naturally wanted the money spent on a shiny new medal for their soldiers to wear. But once again the United Nations' passion for evenhandedness thwarted agreement.</p>
        <p>Clearly it would be unfair to give such a medal only to present and future peacekeeping soldiers. But the United Nations doubted that it could track down all those who had served under its flag in the past.</p>
        <p>The fate of the money was still unresolved when Boutros Boutros-Ghali took over as Secretary General in 1992. He favored using the check to build a wall-like monument to those killed on peacekeeping duty, similar to the Vietnam War Memorial in Washington. But who exactly would be commemorated? Would peacekeepers killed in drunken-driving accidents be eligible, or those who died of natural causes? And what about civilian staff members, like secretaries, cooks and interpreters? Once again indecision carried the day.</p>
        <p>Five years later when Kofi Annan became Secretary General, he embarked on another quest for a good cause to spend the money on. And now his officials believe they finally have one.</p>
        <p>That same year, the Security Council entered the picture by adopting Resolution 1121, which created a Dag Hammarskjold Medal, named after the organization's most famous Secretary General, to be awarded to the families of the more than 1,500 people, civilian and military, who have died on peacekeeping missions, no matter what the circumstances.</p>
        <p>So on Oct. 6, when the United Nations celebrates the 50th anniversary of its first peacekeeping operation -- organized in 1948 to oversee the truce ending the first Arab-Israeli war -- the Secretary General plans to announce a double initiative.</p>
        <p>First the United Nations will issue Dag Hammarskjold Medals to the relatives of all slain peacekeepers, paid for out of its own budget.</p>
        <p>Then the Nobel Peace Prize check will be spent on a memorial at the United Nations headquarters in New York commemorating those fallen peacekeepers, as well as any who may die in the years ahead.</p>
        <p>Since the Dag Hammarsjkold Medal will go to civilians as well as soldiers, the Secretary General has chosen an egg-shaped crystal object designed by the New York firm of Louis Nelson Associates that could be displayed, say, in a living room. It will carry the dead peacekeeper's name, the United Nations logo and the words, in English and French, ''In the Service of Peace.''</p>
        <p>''We are interpreting the word medal loosely,'' said Shashi Tharoor, the Secretary General's communications director. Fittingly, the first recipient will be the family of Mr. Hammarskjold, who died in a mysterious plane crash in 1967 while trying to restore peace in the Congo.</p>
        <p>But the United Nations has not chosen a design for the peacekeeping memorial, so it remains uncertain just when, and indeed whether, that Nobel Prize check is finally going to be spent.</p>
        <p>Meanwhile, the good news is that the $339,000 that Secretary General Perez de Cuellar pocketed almost a decade ago has grown to about $700,000 today, thanks to the miracle of compound interest. Indecision, my dear Watson, has its own rewards. Now where did I put my violin?</p>
        <p>Correction:  August 27, 1998, Thursday  An article on Saturday about the fate of the cash award from the 1988 Nobel Peace Prize, which was given to United Nations peacekeepers, misstated the year of Secretary General Dag Hammarskjold's death. It was 1961, not 1967. The article also referred incorrectly to the Oxford college where the warden is Sir Marrack Goulding, who was in charge of peacekeeping when the prize was awarded. It is St. Antony's, not St. Anthony's.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 27, 1998, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Saturday about the fate of the cash award from the 1988 Nobel Peace Prize, which was given to United Nations peacekeepers, misstated the year of Secretary General Dag Hammarskjold's death. It was 1961, not 1967. The article also referred incorrectly to the Oxford college where the warden is Sir Marrack Goulding, who was in charge of peacekeeping when the prize was awarded. It is St. Antony's, not St. Anthony's.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
