<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Good Looks Quickly Fade for Islanders</title>
    <meta content="13ISLE$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="13" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1001834"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Washington Capitals</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Bashir, Tarik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/Washington Capitals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980313T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E4D71F30F930A25750C0A96E958260" item-length="527" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Good Looks Quickly Fade for Islanders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARIK EL-BASHIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Bashir, Tarik</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., March 12</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Washington Capitals defeat New York Islanders, 2-1; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Two trades. Different owners. Now, a new coach.</p>
        <p>There have been many changes made on Long Island this season, but none has inspired the Islanders. General Manager Mike Milbury, who made his season debut as coach tonight, had the Islanders looking like a different team. But in the end, the look was all that was different.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Two trades. Different owners. Now, a new coach.</p>
        <p>There have been many changes made on Long Island this season, but none has inspired the Islanders. General Manager Mike Milbury, who made his season debut as coach tonight, had the Islanders looking like a different team. But in the end, the look was all that was different.</p>
        <p>Despite Milbury's radical changes, the Islanders lost by 2-1 to the Washington Capitals at the Nassau Coliseum.</p>
        <p>In Milbury's second day back on the job, he scrambled the lines and defensive pairs. He used a trap. He played Bryan Berard, one of the most talented offensive defensemen in the league, on left wing with Zigmund Palffy and Bryan Smolinski.</p>
        <p>''We have nothing to lose by trying some different things,'' said Milbury, who speculated after the game that the team may be out of shape. ''So we're going to keep on trying them.''</p>
        <p>For the first nine minutes, Milbury's changes were effective. The trap was working. The new lines and defensive pairs looked good. Berard scored his first goal since Dec. 29 on a give-and-go from Palffy, and the Islanders led by 1-0 at 7 minutes 19 seconds of the first period.</p>
        <p>But the Capitals' Peter Bondra, who scored both of his team's goals tonight, put one in short-handed moments later to tie the game, 1-1. The Capitals were no longer tricked by Milbury's illusions.</p>
        <p>Berard has played wing before, on the United States Olympic team in Nagano, Japan, last month and once as punishment for neglecting his defensive duties while Milbury was the coach early last season.</p>
        <p>''I don't plan on staying up there,'' Berard said.</p>
        <p>Bondra's second goal, his 41st of the season, came on a drive from the point early in the second period. The Islanders goalie Tommy Salo was screened by defenseman Scott Lachance.</p>
        <p>With tonight's loss, the Islanders, who were 0 for 9 on the power play, remained 9 points behind the Ottawa Senators for the eighth and final playoff spot in the Eastern Conference.</p>
        <p>''How many games do we have left?'' Berard asked. ''Eighteen? That's a lot of points to make up.''</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>RICK BOWNESS spoke to reporters Thursday for the first time since he was dismissed Wednesday. Bowness, who survived a 10-game losing streak earlier this season, said he was surprised by the timing of General Manager MIKE MILBURY's decision. ''We went 6-4-2 the last 12 games and took 5 of 8 points from the Flyers, Colorado and the Sabres,'' Bowness said. ''It's a better team than it was in December.'' Bowness said he had no immediate plans. ''I'm going to get away from coaching for bit,'' he said. . . . J.J. DAIGNEAULT separated his right shoulder in the second period and did not return.  . . . ROBERT REICHEL played in his 500th National Hockey League game.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
