<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Seeking Clemency in a Labyrinth That Varies by State</title>
    <meta content="T04CLE$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="992898"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="EXECUTION IN TEXAS: LEGAL DEBATE"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Texas</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hoffman, Jan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Tucker, Karla Faye</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Southwest</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Texas</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Capital Punishment</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A0CE2D6163DF937A35751C0A96E958260" item-length="1162" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Seeking Clemency in a Labyrinth That Varies by State</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JAN HOFFMAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hoffman, Jan</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Case of Karla Faye Tucker, woman executed in Texas for murder, underscores how nearly impossible it is for death row inmates to win clemency; Supreme Court has never directly spoken about whether state has to offer basic due process in discretionary clemency proceedings; clemency proceedings vary greatly from among states (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The case of Karla Faye Tucker underscores how nearly impossible it is for death row inmates to win clemency. The right of a ruler to reach over the heads of a judge and jury may be as old as the Bible, but in modern American death penalty law, the quality of that mercy has varied from state to state and governor to governor, often proving to be quixotic, subject to political winds, and very strained.</p>
        <p>Clemency is actually an umbrella term, encompassing a pardon, the most powerful grant of forgiveness of a crime and a prison sentence; commutation, which means changing a sentence from death to life, and a reprieve, a short stay of sentence for a specified time. The Constitution grants only the President, as Chief Executive, the power of pardon; governors derive their clemency powers through their state constitution.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The case of Karla Faye Tucker underscores how nearly impossible it is for death row inmates to win clemency. The right of a ruler to reach over the heads of a judge and jury may be as old as the Bible, but in modern American death penalty law, the quality of that mercy has varied from state to state and governor to governor, often proving to be quixotic, subject to political winds, and very strained.</p>
        <p>Clemency is actually an umbrella term, encompassing a pardon, the most powerful grant of forgiveness of a crime and a prison sentence; commutation, which means changing a sentence from death to life, and a reprieve, a short stay of sentence for a specified time. The Constitution grants only the President, as Chief Executive, the power of pardon; governors derive their clemency powers through their state constitution.</p>
        <p>And so because the Supreme Court has never directly spoken about whether a state has to offer basic due process in a discretionary clemency proceeding, the states have concocted highly individual means for inmates to request mercy.</p>
        <p>In Texas, for example, Ms. Tucker had to apply to a board, which did not have to offer her a face-to-face hearing, and chose not to do so -- one reason her lawyers asked the Supreme Court to declare the process unconstitutional. Only upon the board's recommendation could Gov. George W. Bush have then granted clemency; without that recommendation, he could have only given her a 30-day reprieve.</p>
        <p>Since 1976, 29 men and 6 women have been granted clemency. Of the 38 death penalty states, 17 have a system similar to Texas', 14 give governors exclusive responsibility and power over clemency and 6 give those powers exclusively to a board.</p>
        <p>There is hardly an extensive body of law governing clemency standards and procedures. The Supreme Court last ruled on how clemencies are rendered in a 1981 Connecticut case, and said that a defendant was not entitled to a written decision on why his appeal was rejected. In a 1993 Texas case in which a death row inmate asked the Supreme Court whether he could appeal his conviction. The inmate, Lionel Herrera, was denied clemency and was executed.</p>
        <p>In December, the Supreme Court heard arguments on an Ohio death row clemency case. In Ohio, death row inmates must have their clemency appeals heard by a state board before they have finished their appeals in the state and Federal courts. Lawyers are asking the Supreme Court to articulate the basic level of due process allowed inmates.</p>
        <p>David M. Young, a lawyer with the Washington Legal Foundation, a conservative law organization that often litigates on criminal justice questions, said his group did not oppose the institution of clemency. But since clemency exists at the behest of the executive branch, and not the courts, inmates are not entitled to the full-blown rights that they had at trial, Mr. Young said.</p>
        <p>But Adele Shank, a lawyer from Columbus, Ohio, who argued the case before the Supreme Court, said: ''Clemency under a monarchy or a dictatorship is different than clemency in a democracy.'' Clemency exists in a democracy, Ms. Shank said, to acknowledge that error can occur in individual cases or that mercy has its place in unusual circumstances.</p>
        <p>Who gets clemency in a death penalty case and why is an even murkier issue. States do not generally issue guidelines, and decisions are left to the conscience of individual boards and governors. In ''Public Justice, Private Mercy,'' Edmund G. Brown, the former Governor of California, wrote a searing account of his death row clemency cases, noting that mental illness became an important criterion for him.</p>
        <p>By contrast, when Bill Clinton was Governor of Arkansas, he approved the execution of Rickey Ray Rector, a murderer whose own suicide attempt by shooting had destroyed much of his brain: on the evening of his death, by one account, he asked that his pecan pie be set aside so he could enjoy a snack before bed.</p>
        <p>In the case of Ms. Tucker, her supporters made much of her born-again Christian faith as a reason for commuting her execution. But what has been generally overlooked is that Ms. Tucker not only admitted her remorse for a double murder but cooperated with prosecutors by testifying against her boyfriend. She had nothing to gain, for she had already been sentenced to death.</p>
        <p>''I don't know of any other case in which a person testified for the state after receiving the death penalty with no deal,'' said Rusty Hardin, a Houston lawyer who prosecuted Ms. Tucker's former boyfriend, Daniel Ryan Garrett.</p>
        <p>For much of this century, clemency was an important feature of death row administration -- in some states, upward of 30 percent to 40 percent of convicts saw their sentences commuted from death to life in prison. But since 1973, when legislatures began approving death penalty laws that passed modern Supreme Court tests, the number of successful clemency appeals dropped precipitously.</p>
        <p>Prosecutors argued that convicts now had so many chances to appeal their cases in state and Federal courts that clemency was no longer needed to remedy mistakes made at trial.</p>
        <p>And, mindful that an electorate had grown frustrated by those protracted appeals, governors became increasingly reluctant to risk political capital on a capital case.</p>
        <p>Ms. Shank, the Ohio lawyer, pointed out that testing popular opinion in such important decisions was as old as clemency itself. Jesus had been found guilty of blasphemy, a capital offense, by the priests and council elders, and was taken before Pontius Pilate, governor of Judea, who had the power to commute a sentence at Passover. In his own version of polling, Pilate appealed to the masses on behalf of Jesus' life. But the crowd wanted Jesus crucified and asked that another criminal's life be spared. So Pilate declined to grant Jesus clemency and washed his hands of the affair.</p>
        <p>In the modern death penalty era, as of Jan. 1, there have been 432 executions, and only 35 convicts have had their sentences commuted, usually because of powerful evidence of outright innocence or other unusual circumstances.</p>
        <p>By contrast, in 1989, Gov. Guy Hunt of Alabama declined to give clemency to Michael Lindsey, saying he did not want to alter the decision of the jury and the courts. But Alabama is one of a handful of states in which a trial judge can override a sentencing jury's decision. Mr. Lindsey's trial judge turned aside the jury's life sentence and ordered the death penalty.</p>
        <p>Daniel T. Kobil, a professor of constitutional law at Capital University in Columbus, said that modern clemency decisions in the United States amounted to a bait-and-switch scheme.</p>
        <p>''Justice systems tend to operate on the assumption that clemency is available,'' Mr. Kobil said, ''and so we can have capital punishment because of this safety valve.''</p>
        <p>But, he added, there is no insurance that the safety valve works.</p>
        <p>EXECUTION IN TEXAS: LEGAL DEBATE</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
