<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The Tour No Longer Belongs to Indurain</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="13" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="866492"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="CYCLING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BICYCLES AND BICYCLING</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TOUR DE FRANCE (BICYCLE RACE)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">ABT, SAMUEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">RIIS, BJARNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">INDURAIN, MIGUEL MIGUEL INDURAIN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Biking</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Race</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tour De France (Bicycle Race)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Bicycles and Bicycling</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806E1DB1639F931A15754C0A960958260" item-length="912" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The Tour No Longer Belongs to Indurain</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SAM ABT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ABT, SAMUEL;</byline>
      <dateline>PARIS, July 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Bjarne Riis rode across the last finish line of the Tour de France today with his arms raised in a V and some big questions in his slipstream.</p>
        <p>First, how did Riis, a 32-year-old Dane who leads the Telekom team from Germany, become the dominating winner of the three-week Tour after he floundered in two races half that long just a month ago?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Bjarne Riis rode across the last finish line of the Tour de France today with his arms raised in a V and some big questions in his slipstream.</p>
        <p>First, how did Riis, a 32-year-old Dane who leads the Telekom team from Germany, become the dominating winner of the three-week Tour after he floundered in two races half that long just a month ago?</p>
        <p>Second, what happened to Miguel Indurain, also 32, a Spaniard who rides for  Banesto and who won the five previous Tours before he slid to 11th place this year, 14 minutes 14 seconds behind Riis?</p>
        <p>Indurain appeared to have been the victim of many factors, including age, weather, a weak team and, most startlingly, a lack of peak condition.</p>
        <p>"Last year he looked ripped," said Frankie Andreu, an American with the Motorola team, referring to Indurain's lean and muscular physique. "You looked at him and said, 'Holy cow, man, he can rip the cranks off the bike.' This year  you didn't see that kind of definition. During the race, you could see he was suffering a little bit more, struggling."</p>
        <p>The first 10 days after the start in 's-Hertogenbosch, the Netherlands, were  marked by incessant cold rain and even snow in the Alps. Indurain prefers heavy  heat, which came too late, and he was unable to shed a bit of extra weight he brought to the Tour.</p>
        <p>While it was no more than about three pounds, which he expected to lose quickly in the usual Tour heat, even that little makes a major difference in the mountains to a rider of Indurain's size: 6 feet 2 inches and 176 pounds.</p>
        <p>The weight and the bad weather, combined with a team lacking the usual locomotives to help Indurain over the first climbs in the mountains, reduced his chances of a record sixth victory in the Tour.</p>
        <p>So did the odds. Four men -- Jacques Anquetil, Eddy Merckx, Bernard Hinault and Indurain -- have each won the Tour five times and only Indurain has won it five times consecutively.</p>
        <p>None of them won the world's greatest bicycle race at the age of 32 or older.</p>
        <p>So how did Riis emerge at that age, beaming as a French military band launched into "There Is a Lovely Country," his national anthem, to salute the winner?</p>
        <p>Apparently the Dane is a late bloomer. Fifth in the 1993 Tour and third last  year, he did not assume the many responsibilities of a team leader until this year.</p>
        <p>Before that he was a support rider and a lieutenant in France and Italy. Although he has won daily stages in the Giro d'Italia and the Tour de France, his overall victory in this 83d Tour was his first major one in a 10-year professional career.</p>
        <p>When he joined Telekom this season, he announced that his only goal was to win the Tour. He started on that path slowly and was still unimpressive last month.</p>
        <p>"In the Dauphine and Tour of Switzerland," where he was left far behind in June, "I was sick," Riis has said. "Not until the championship of Denmark did I  find my best form."</p>
        <p>He won that race and for the first nine days of the Tour wore the red jersey  with white cross of the Danish champion. Then he donned the luminous yellow jersey of the overall leader of the Tour, never to lose it during the rest of the 2,423-mile journey.</p>
        <p>In today's sprint finish on the Champs-Elysees, Fabio Baldato, an Italian with MG, was first across the line among the 129 riders remaining of the 198 who started the Tour. Second was Frederic Moncassin, a Frenchman with Gan who won two previous sprint stages, and third was Jeroen Blijlevens, a Dutchman with TVM.</p>
        <p>A festive crowd estimated at half a million saw Baldato end the 91.5-mile roundabout spin from the town of Palaiseau in 3 hours 30 minutes 44 seconds, for an average speed of 26 miles an hour. In a change of itinerary, the riders not only traversed the Champs-Elysees eight times as usual but also passed the Invalides, the Place de la Bastille and the Place du Chatelet, among other tourist attractions.</p>
        <p>Tens of thousands of Danes, all of them exuberant and some possibly sober, traveled to Paris in buses plastered with Riis banners to help celebrate the first victory by a Dane since the Tour began in 1903. It has been interrupted only by world wars.</p>
        <p>In second place over all, 1:41 behind Riis, was his 22-year-old teammate Jan  Ullrich, a German. Ullrich trailed by 3:59 until he easily won a long time trial Saturday, finishing 56 seconds ahead of Indurain in second place and 2:18 ahead  of Riis in fourth place.</p>
        <p>Third over all was Richard Virenque, a Festina rider, who became the first Frenchman since 1989 to stand on the final podium as one of the top three finishers.</p>
        <p>For his victory, Riis collected 2.2 million French francs (about $400,000) from a total prize pool of more than 12 million francs.</p>
        <p>CYCLING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
