<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Getty's Burger Dress</title>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="70" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="620868"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <series series.name="ENDPAPER/LIFE AND TIMES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VOICE RECOGNITION SYSTEMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">NEWS AND NEWS MEDIA</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">BARRON, JAMES</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Sound</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Media</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">News and News Media</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19930711T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CEED6113FF932A25754C0A965958260" item-length="1126" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Getty's Burger Dress</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By James Barron;</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BARRON, JAMES</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Horsepower and seven years ago our fathers brought four on this continent a new nation, conceived in liberty and dedicated to the proposition that Coleman are created equal.</p>
        <p>Just think how different things would be if it had come out that way when Lincoln said it. The crowd at Gettysburg, settling in for a three-hour stemwinder instead of a three-minute back-of-the-envelope scribbling, would have been completely confused. Who's this Coleman, anyway, and why is he plural?</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Horsepower and seven years ago our fathers brought four on this continent a new nation, conceived in liberty and dedicated to the proposition that Coleman are created equal.</p>
        <p>Just think how different things would be if it had come out that way when Lincoln said it. The crowd at Gettysburg, settling in for a three-hour stemwinder instead of a three-minute back-of-the-envelope scribbling, would have been completely confused. Who's this Coleman, anyway, and why is he plural?</p>
        <p>Not only that, I wouldn't have had a famous opening line to try out on a voice-recognition computer. The kind that turns spoken words into written ones.</p>
        <p>Maybe if I had paid more attention when they taught us enunciation in elementary school, Tangora, as the machine is called, would not have muffed it.</p>
        <p>Hey, I'm no Abe Lincoln.</p>
        <p>Ask not what your country can do 42, ask when you can do cross-country.</p>
        <p>I'm no Jack Kennedy, either.</p>
        <p>I am one of a growing number of writers, editors and news clerks with R.S.I. -- repetitive strain injury. R.S.I. used to hit people like jackhammer operators or hairdressers or concert pianists. But with the arrival of the information age and computers on every desk top, R.S.I. became a problem for office-bound workers too. We got it while doing the same old things we had always done to put out a newspaper: typing too much and too fast, hunching over our desks instead of sitting up straight, cradling the phone against our shoulders while jotting down notes, taking too few breaks.</p>
        <p>Medical experts aren't sure what causes R.S.I., why it wasn't widespread in the hunt-and-peck days of manual typewriters or why the person who sits next to you, doing essentially the same work, may be symptom-free. Better physical shape? Plain old luck? Maybe. With help from a good physical therapist, I'm better. I have also been to a typing doctor, who prescribed warm-up exercises. Yes, warm-up exercises. Maybe by 1996 typing will be an Olympic sport. But for now, I'm not supposed to type more than about 30 minutes at a time.</p>
        <p>THAT'S WHERE TANGORA COMES IN. AH, Tangora: the name sounds like a sweater dipped in gin. And it's, well, just plain cruel to name a computer that you aren't supposed to type on after one of the fastest typists ever -- an average of 147 words a minute. He's even listed in the Guinness Book of Records.</p>
        <p>Using computer to fight computer, I have been reading my handwritten notes from interviews into Tangora. This keeps the typing to a minimum; when I finally sit down at the keyboard, I construct the story around quotes already on the screen. More about that in a minute. But first, this report from here on the front lines of voice recognition, which began in the 1940's but has progressed to where it is letting people do the unthinkable: program their VCR's.</p>
        <p>Voice recognition is complicated, cutting-edge technology, but somehow Tangora has a back-to-the-future quality. My first year at The Times was the last for the old-fashioned Linotypes that cast our words, backward, into metal. Now the composing room has big machines that spit out strips that look more or less like what you see on the doorstep in the morning -- words you can read without a mirror.</p>
        <p>Tangora involves an even more basic form of communication: talking. It's like going back a step, from Gutenberg to Fred and Wilma. And it's still only a vacuum-tube version of a voice-recognition computer. In the same way that ordinary desk-top computers pack more and more into smaller and smaller packages, future Tangoras will no doubt be quicker on the uptake.</p>
        <p>But you cannot rush Tangora. You have to leave at least a fraction of a second of silence between each word. I know radio announcers who can tell when 60 seconds have elapsed without glancing at a clock, but I . . . don't . . . know . . . how . . . long . . . a . . .  fraction . . . of . . . a . . . second . . . is, so I overdo it. The words come out in a monotone machine-gun staccato. Except when I forget, and everythingrunstogether.</p>
        <p>Even when you talk crisply, Tangora -- which took 21 years to develop, making it one of the longest-running research projects in the history of I.B.M. -- doesn't understand that sentences have subjects and predicates. Nor does it know a noun from a verb. Instead, it relies on statistics. It breaks a sentence into small chunks called trigrams -- three-word groups -- and asks itself: Of all the possible strings of trigrams that could ever be formed, which one is the most likely?</p>
        <p>This is also how Tangora chooses between homophones like "writes" and "rights" or "to," "too" and "two": it scans the last few words and makes a guess based on how the 600 million words of text it has scanned from books and newspapers were strung together. Somewhere in that morass of trigrams, it will no doubt find "he went to the store," but never "he went two the store," so it will put "to" on the screen and move on.</p>
        <p>It's good, and new versions are making it better all the time. You can train Tangora to recognize frequently used words, and you can also fix errors as you go along by switching to a keyboard or a mouse. In addition, Tangora can be customized so that mistakes can be corrected by dictating the right spellings, letter by letter. Paul Roossin, who works on the Tangora project at I.B.M., says he has a 98 percent accuracy rate, but it is, after all, only a machine and still far from foolproof. Foreign names seem to confuse Tangora the most. "Bosnian Serbs" can appear on Tangora's screen as "buzzing Serbs," and on any given day the Russian President can be "Boris Elephant" or "Boris Telephone."</p>
        <p>The version of Tangora that I've been using has a 27,000-word vocabulary, but I didn't have to sit around and feed all those words into its memory. All I did was read it a Mark Twain story, with intermissions for 20th-century phrases like "I.B.M." and "G.E." to give it an idea of my speech patterns. Apparently not a good-enough idea. In a memo I dictated a few days later, the words "there always seems to be a line drawing" came across as "there always seems to be a groin crawling." And, in a story about the mighty Wurlitzer at Radio City Music Hall, every time I said Wurlitzer, Tangora printed "Pulitzer."</p>
        <p>Garry Wills won a Wurlitzer -- sorry, a Pulitzer -- for explaining what Lincoln actually said at Gettysburg (and why Lincoln didn't write it on the back of an envelope). My 30 minutes at the keyboard are just about up, so back to Tangora for the this-nation-under-God closing line (and, as the humorist Dave Barry would say, I am not making this up):</p>
        <p>" . . . designation, under Iran-contra, shall have debut of freedom -- and that Government of the people, by people, for people, shall not Parrish from the year."  ENDPAPER/LIFE AND TIMES James Barron is a reporter on the metropolitan staff of The New York Times.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">James Barron is a reporter on the metropolitan staff of The New York Times.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
