<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>San Diego State and Star Tie U.S.C. and Its Star</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="554810"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGE FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SAN DIEGO STATE UNIVERSITY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE2DD113EF935A3575AC0A964958260" item-length="923" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>San Diego State and Star Tie U.S.C. and Its Star</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>San Diego State 31, U.S.C. 31</p>
        <p>SAN DIEGO, Sept. 5 (AP) -- A shootout between two super sophomores, running back Marshall Faulk of San Diego State and quarterback Rob Johnson of Southern California, ended in a 31-31 tie today when the Aztecs' Andy Trakas missed two field-goal attempts in the final 54 seconds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>San Diego State 31, U.S.C. 31</p>
        <p>SAN DIEGO, Sept. 5 (AP) -- A shootout between two super sophomores, running back Marshall Faulk of San Diego State and quarterback Rob Johnson of Southern California, ended in a 31-31 tie today when the Aztecs' Andy Trakas missed two field-goal attempts in the final 54 seconds.</p>
        <p>Faulk carried 27 times for 220 yards and 3 touchdowns for the Aztecs. Johnson completed 20 of 32 passes for 278 yards and four touchdowns, including three to Johnnie Morton as U.S.C. ended a six-game losing streak.</p>
        <p>Southern Cal's Cole Ford, wide on a 47-yard field goal with 10 minutes 23 seconds left in the game, kicked a 32-yarder with 5:36 left.</p>
        <p>Trakas was wide left on a 30-yard attempt with 54 seconds left. After Damon Pieri intercepted Johnson at the San Diego State 47 with 17 seconds left, the Aztecs moved to the Trojan 38 with eight seconds to play. But Keith Williams dropped a pass from David Lowery that would have given the Aztecs the ball at the 23, and Trakas was wide right from 55 yards. Ohio State 20, Louisville 19</p>
        <p>COLUMBUS, Ohio, Sept. 5 (AP) -- Dan Wilkinson disrupted a 2-point conversion attempt inside the last minute and an encroachment penalty spoiled another late Louisville scoring opportunity as Ohio State escaped with a victory.</p>
        <p>Trailing by 20-13, Louisville drove 67 yards for a touchdown, which came on Ralph Dawkins's 2-yard run with 33 seconds to play.</p>
        <p>On the conversion, quarterback Jeff Brohm rolled left but came under heavy pressure from Wilkinson, a tackle who broke into the Louisville backfield virtually at the snap. Brohm threw to the end zone just as Wilkinson hit him, and the ball floated beyond Dawkins's reach.</p>
        <p>Ohio State got what proved to be the winning points on Tim Williams's 26-yard field goal with 3:09 left. Notre Dame 42, Northwestern 7</p>
        <p>CHICAGO (AP) -- Rick Mirer's 70-yard touchdown pass to Mike Miller and a 72-yard touchdown run by Reggie Brooks helped Notre Dame break loose in the second half.</p>
        <p>Northwestern quarterback Lenny Williams completed 26 of 40 passes for a career-high 274 yards to keep the Wildcats in contention in Coach Gary Barnett's debut.</p>
        <p>Notre Dame held only a 14-7 lead when Mirer hit the speedy Miller with his 70-yard scoring pass in the third quarter. On the next possession, Jerome Bettis broke loose for a 24-yard touchdown run.</p>
        <p>Williams directed the Wildcats to the Irish 5-yard line midway in the fourth quarter only to have a diving Tom Carter break up a touchdown pass on fourth down to end the drive.</p>
        <p>Five plays later, Brooks ripped off his 72-yard touchdown run. Alabama 25, Vanderbilt 8</p>
        <p>TUSCALOOSA, Ala. (AP) -- Freshman Michael Proctor kicked four field goals in his college debut as Alabama, playing without the suspended star David Palmer, continued its domination of Vanderbilt.</p>
        <p>Proctor kicked three field goals from beyond 40 yards and was just short from 52 yards. He also made a 32-yarder in the fourth quarter to seal the victory.</p>
        <p>Alabama defeated Vanderbilt for the eighth year in a row and improved its record against its fellow Southeastern Conference member to 30-2 since 1960.</p>
        <p>Palmer, a sophomore receiver and kick returner who accounted for 1,113 total yards in 1991, was held out by Coach Gene Stallings because he was arrested on a charge of drunken driving during the off season. Citadel 10, Arkansas 3</p>
        <p>FAYETTEVILLE, Ark. (AP) -- Defensive end Judson Boehmer returned a fumble 34 yards for a touchdown as The Citadel spoiled Arkansas's football debut in the Southeastern Conference.</p>
        <p>The Division I-AA Bulldogs were down, 3-0 in the fourth quarter, when E. D. Jackson was hit by Garrett Sizer and fumbled. Boehmer picked up the ball and scored untouched. Texas A&amp;M 31, L.S.U. 22</p>
        <p>BATON ROUGE, La. (AP) -- A&amp;M's Jeff Granger passed for 196 yards and a touchdown and ran for another score.</p>
        <p>The Aggies wore out the Tigers in the final quarter with a 22-yard touchdown run by Rodney Thomas and a 12-yard score by Clif Groce. Thomas and fellow sophomore Greg Hill combined for 194 rushing yards.</p>
        <p>Texas A&amp;M took the lead for good in the final minute of the third period when Terry Venetoulias kicked a 44-yard field goal for a 17-14 advantage. Clemson 24, Ball State 10</p>
        <p>CLEMSON, S.C. (AP) -- Tim Jones's fourth-quarter interception set up Howard Hall's run for the Tigers' go-ahead score.</p>
        <p>Jones's 10-yard return of a pass from Mike Neu and a 5-yard face mask penalty gave Clemson possession at Ball State's 18. After five runs by Rodney Blunt, Hall scored from the 1 for a 17-10 lead with 10:26 left.</p>
        <p>Ronald Williams, who hadn't scrimmaged during the preseason because of a knee injury suffered last year, scored on a 17-yard run to make it 24-10 with 6:44 left.</p>
        <p>Williams, who was listed as doubtful for the game, finished with 58 yards on 8 carries. Blunt had 96 yards on 20 carries. N. Carolina 35, Wake Forest 17</p>
        <p>WINSTON-SALEM, N.C. (AP) -- Mike Faulkerson had the best day of his career with three touchdowns as the Tar Heels won their opening Atlantic Coast Conference game for the first time in five seasons.</p>
        <p>The 240-pound senior fullback scored on a pair of 1-yard runs in the second quarter and a 2-yard plunge in the third. California 46, San Jose State 16</p>
        <p>BERKELEY, Calif. (AP) -- California's Russell White ran for 216 yards, and Dave Barr, in his starting debut, threw three touchdown passes to Sean Dawkins.</p>
        <p>White, a 1,000-yard rusher in each of the past two seasons, ripped San Jose State for runs of 48 and 40 yards.  COLLEGE FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
