<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Putting on the Ritz: Beans?</title>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Long Island Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="13LI" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="554637"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="FOOD"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COOKING AND COOKBOOKS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BEANS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Long Island</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920906T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE7DF173AF935A3575AC0A964958260" item-length="1091" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Putting on the Ritz: Beans?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By FLORENCE FABRICANT</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FABRICANT, FLORENCE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Dried beans, those inexpensive, nutritious pantry-shelf staples have acquired new-found glamour. Bean dishes, once lowly sustenance for people who had little else, are now being featured on pricey menus. People who can afford truffles are ordering beans.</p>
        <p>It's understandable. When properly prepared, beans are deliciously toothsome, lush in texture and able to sop up flavor. They are an excellent foil for fatty foods like sausages and offer an irresistible richness when spiked with garlic and drizzled with some peppery green extra-virgin olive oil.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Dried beans, those inexpensive, nutritious pantry-shelf staples have acquired new-found glamour. Bean dishes, once lowly sustenance for people who had little else, are now being featured on pricey menus. People who can afford truffles are ordering beans.</p>
        <p>It's understandable. When properly prepared, beans are deliciously toothsome, lush in texture and able to sop up flavor. They are an excellent foil for fatty foods like sausages and offer an irresistible richness when spiked with garlic and drizzled with some peppery green extra-virgin olive oil.</p>
        <p>For people who have not spent a lifetime cooking and eating beans, they seem to be a pain in the neck to prepare, the better to let a chef do the work. But recipes that require overnight soaking and an hour or more of cooking are somewhat off the mark.</p>
        <p>First of all, four hours is all the soaking that most beans need. So if you want beans for dinner and forget to put them on to soak the night before, there is still plenty of time. A shortcut method of bringing them to a boil for two minutes, allowing them to soak for one hour, then draining them and cooking them in fresh cold water is another route to take. A pressure cooker will reduce the cooking time to about 20 minutes.</p>
        <p>And even if soaking time is factored into total preparation time, the beans do not require watching while they soak, allowing the cook hours to tend to other tasks or to relax.</p>
        <p>Some dried beans -- French flageolets, for example, or lentils -- need no soaking at all. And if your dried beans are fresh, that is, from the most recent crop and kept well wrapped, they probably would need no soaking either. Freshness is important with dried beans and some packers have started putting the dates on the boxes.</p>
        <p>It is essential that beans not be salted while they cook because that will prevent them from becoming fully tender. Another bean-cooking tip is to allow them to cool in their cooking water if you have time. This improves the texture and keeps them from splitting.</p>
        <p>Then there are also the canned beans to use in emergencies. Canned black beans, black-eyed peas and chick peas are the best varieties. Red kidney beans are acceptable but others, like Italian white cannellini beans tend to be too soft. Always rinse canned beans before using them.</p>
        <p>And even though beans fortify some hardy cold-weather classics like baked beans and cassoulet, they can also be used cold, to bolster warm-weather salads. Warm Italian Bean Salad Total time: 2 to 5 hours (including soaking)  1 1/2 cups dried white cannellini beans (about 9 ounces)  4 medium-size ripe tomatoes, peeled, seeded and chopped  2 teaspoons finely chopped garlic  2 ounces prosciutto, in one piece  2 sprigs fresh rosemary  1/4 cup chopped fresh Italian parsley  1/3 cup extra-virgin olive oil  Juice of 1 lemon  1/2 teaspoon salt, or to taste  Freshly ground black pepper.</p>
        <p>1. Unless the beans are fresh enough to need no soaking place them in a bowl with water to cover to a depth of two inches and allow to soak at least four hours. Alternatively, place them in a saucepan with the water, bring to a boil and cook two minutes. Remove them from the heat and allow them to soak for one hour.</p>
        <p>2. Drain the beans, cover them with fresh cold water, bring to simmer and cook, partly covered, about 45 minutes, until they are tender but still hold their shape. If possible allow them to cool in the cooking liquid. Otherwise drain the beans well and place them in a mixing bowl.</p>
        <p>3. Gently fold in the tomatoes and garlic. Dice the prosciutto and strip the rosemary leaves from the stems. Add the prosciutto and rosemary along with the parsley and all but two tablespoons of the oil. Allow the beans to cool to room temperature, then fold in the lemon juice and season with salt and pepper.</p>
        <p>4. Transfer to a serving dish and drizzle with the remaining oil before serving.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings Curried Lamb and Bean Salad Total time: 2 to 5 hours (including soaking and marinating)  3 large garlic cloves, chopped  1/2 small onion, chopped  1/4 cup curry powder  Salt  1/4 cup extra-virgin olive oil  4 tablespoons fresh lime juice  1 pound boneless lamb steak  1/2pound dried kidney beans  4 medium-size ripe tomatoes, peeled, seeded and chopped  1 medium red onion, chopped  1 small red bell pepper, cored and minced  1 teaspoon minced fresh hot chili pepper  1 cucumber, peeled, seeded and chopped  2 tablespoons chopped fresh mint.</p>
        <p>1. Combine the garlic, onion, two tablespoons of the curry powder and one-half teaspoon salt in a blender or food processor. Add two tablespoons of the olive oil and one tablespoon of the lime juice and process until smooth. Rub this mixture over the lamb, place in the refrigerator and marinate one to four hours.</p>
        <p>2. While the lamb is marinating place the beans in a bowl, cover with cold water to a depth of two inches and allow to soak for four hours. Alternatively, bring the beans to a boil in a saucepan, cook two minutes, then set aside to soak one hour.</p>
        <p>3. When the beans have finished soaking drain them, place them in a saucepan with cold water to cover to a depth of two inches, bring them to a boil and simmer about 45 minutes, until they are tender. If possible allow them to cool in the cooking liquid. Otherwise, drain them and transfer to a mixing bowl.</p>
        <p>4. While the beans are cooking, light a grill or broiler. When it is hot, grill or broil the lamb three to four minutes on each side, to medium or medium rare. Place the cooked lamb on a cutting board.</p>
        <p>5. Place the tomatoes, red onion, peppers and cucumber in the bowl with the beans. Fold in the remaining olive oil and lime juice. Season to taste with salt and fold in the mint.</p>
        <p>6. Cut the lamb into thin slices and cut the slices into one-inch length. Add the meat to the salad, toss gently and check seasonings. Serve at once.</p>
        <p>Yield: 6 to 8 servings Chick Pea and Olive Dip Total time: 15 minutes  1 cup cooked or canned chick peas, drained  1 garlic clove, finely minced  2 tablespoons minced scallions  Juice of two lemons  1 tablespoon black olive paste or 6 Italian black olives, pitted and very finely chopped  1 tablespoon extra-virgin olive oil  Toasted pita bread or unsalted corn chips.</p>
        <p>1. Combine all the ingredients in a food processor and process until smooth.</p>
        <p>2. Transfer to a serving bowl and serve with pieces of toasted pita or chips for dipping.</p>
        <p>Yield: 4 to 6 servings.</p>
        <p>FOOD</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
