<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>49ers Decide to Add Diversity to Training Camp</title>
    <meta content="08NINE$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/08/sports/football/08niners.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1595129"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="PRO FOOTBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">San Francisco 49ers</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Hack, Damon</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League/San Francisco 49ers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Pro Football/National Football League</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Homosexuality</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">National Football League</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0DE0D7153BF93BA35754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1332" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>49ers Decide to Add Diversity to Training Camp</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">49ers Decide to Add Diversity to Training Camp</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAMON HACK</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Hack, Damon</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>San Francisco 49ers hold diversity training seminar, which team says it will try to use as competitive edge this season, after two incidents involving homosexuality created public relations and internal problems for organization; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It was the final minute of the final day of spring minicamp last month. The San Francisco 49ers wanted to go home.</p>
        <p>Instead, team officials summoned the players to a meeting room at their practice facility in Santa Clara, Calif. The players sat down.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Last month, two strangers presented the 49ers with a seminar on diversity, including race, gender, ethnicity and sexual orientation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It was the final minute of the final day of spring minicamp last month. The San Francisco 49ers wanted to go home.</p>
        <p>Instead, team officials summoned the players to a meeting room at their practice facility in Santa Clara, Calif. The players sat down.</p>
        <p>''Let's get this thing done so we can get out of here,'' one player announced.</p>
        <p>Ronnie Heard, a free safety, sank into his seat, not wanting to stay either.</p>
        <p>''My mind-set was: 'Oh, man, not another meeting; I want to go home,''' Heard recalled in a recent telephone interview. '''I don't want to do this. I don't want to have anything to do with this.'''</p>
        <p>For the next two and a half hours, two strangers presented the 49ers with a seminar on diversity, including race, gender, ethnicity and sexual orientation. They saw an instructional film from the 1970's, in which blue-eyed students were told to pick on brown-eyed students. During part of the seminar, the players were asked to call out the names of celebrities of different races and sexual orientations.</p>
        <p>Many 49ers, after initially resisting the presentation, remained seated long after it ended to discuss what they had learned.</p>
        <p>''It was powerful,'' Heard said. ''It broke up cliques and brought us together as a team.''</p>
        <p>Cedrick Wilson, a wide receiver, agreed.</p>
        <p>''At first, a lot of the guys wanted to go home, but it was an awesome class,'' he said. ''You got a chance to meet and greet different guys on the team, guys you had met before but not really found out about what he and his family have gone through.''</p>
        <p>Some of the players said they wanted the meeting to remain a secret from the other N.F.L. teams. The workshop, they said, might give them a competitive edge during the coming season by bringing the players closer together.</p>
        <p>The 49ers conducted the workshop as a result of two incidents.</p>
        <p>In 2002, 49ers running back Garrison Hearst said in an interview with a columnist from The Fresno Bee that he would never accept a gay teammate. Hearst later apologized for the comment. He is no longer with the 49ers.</p>
        <p>In February, Lindsy McLean, who retired as the 49ers' head trainer before last season, said in an interview with ESPN the Magazine that he was gay, which had been known inside the 49ers organization by many players and team officials. In the article, McLean said he had endured taunts and humiliation from players at times during his 24 years with the 49ers. That included, he said, harassment from one player who would sometimes grab him in the training room and simulate a sex act while other players stood by.</p>
        <p>After the article appeared, team officials met with San Francisco's Lesbian Gay Bisexual Transgender Advisory Committee. The idea of having diversity training was born.</p>
        <p>''We want everybody to be fans of the 49ers,'' said Guy McIntyre, the team's player development director and a former 49ers offensive lineman who won Super Bowl rings for the 1984, 1988 and 1989 seasons.</p>
        <p>''We can't go around doing anything that is going to harm that relationship. The organization did the right thing. We're setting a precedent in the league. It's very diverse in many different ways -- not just sexual orientation, but in gender, ethnicity and culture, and we have to be respectful of that because we are growing.''</p>
        <p>The 49ers, who say they expect to hold more diversity seminars, are not the only team to bump up against the issue.</p>
        <p>Miami Dolphins linebacker Junior Seau made a remark about sexual orientation during an acceptance speech at a team banquet last month, when he was given a leadership award. Seau apologized, calling his comments stupid.</p>
        <p>The next week, Bill Parcells, the Dallas Cowboys' coach, used an ethnic slur to describe surprise plays used in practice. He apologized the same day.</p>
        <p>Greg Aiello, an N.F.L. spokesman, said in an interview last week that the league was exploring how to conduct diversity workshops, perhaps similar to the one the 49ers used, on a wider basis.</p>
        <p>Last week, Esera Tuaolo, who retired in 1999 after nine seasons as an N.F.L. offensive lineman and who revealed in 2002 that he is gay, spoke to nearly 200 N.F.L. employees at the league office in Manhattan about his life as a professional athlete.</p>
        <p>Tuaolo encouraged the league to put out a message of tolerance and acceptance so that a gay player could feel comfortable discussing his sexual orientation and still coexist in an N.F.L. locker room.</p>
        <p>Aiello said the league might target its rookie symposium, which all incoming players must attend, as a way to promote tolerance.</p>
        <p>''We are clearly evaluating that idea and how it can be done,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Many in the 49ers organization say they believe that they have a head start because of their workshop, which was run by Stan Johnson and Charles Whitcomb. Johnson conducts diversity programs for the National Collegiate Athletic Association and other organizations; Whitcomb, the vice provost for administration and personnel at San Jose State, has also worked on diversity for the N.C.A.A.</p>
        <p>The 49ers' meeting included a discussion of the death of Matthew Shepard, a gay University of Wyoming student who in 1998 was beaten unconscious in Laramie, Wyo., and died in a hospital five days later.</p>
        <p>Johnson and Whitcomb also talked about how jokes in the locker room can lead to fissures that the players do not even realize exist.</p>
        <p>''No one knows who has a gay brother or, in the case of Dallas, who has a Japanese wife,'' Johnson said, referring to Parcells's comment. ''It creates mistrust. All of a sudden you don't want to play with that individual or you don't trust that individual.</p>
        <p>''We're trying to create an environment where we can talk about these things and eliminate the problems and violence that can take place, help them understand that they can create an environment that people can work in, even if they are different. You don't have the right to come to work and discriminate and hurt people. And sometimes people are unaware that they may be hurting individuals.''</p>
        <p>Whitcomb added: ''Homophobia is no different than racism or any other 'ism.' But times change. Seventy-five years ago, there was never a thought that we would see a black quarterback.''</p>
        <p>But have times changed enough that players would be willing to accept an openly gay teammate, as Tuaolo and others wonder?</p>
        <p>''I could play with somebody being gay,'' said the 49ers' Heard, who grew up outside Houston and attended the University of Mississippi. ''Would it be weird at the beginning? Yeah, but I can't hate him as a person. You don't have to agree biblically, but what kind of example am I setting for my kid if I'm an activist for blacks and I discriminate toward gays?''</p>
        <p>Wilson, who was born in Memphis and attended Tennessee, said that the reality was that other players might be gay. But, he said, if he is a good player and ''his sexuality happens to be different, I could care less.''</p>
        <p>''The person that you put down could be the person that saves your life,'' Wilson said. ''That diversity class showed me that.''</p>
        <p>Brandon Moore, a 49ers linebacker, said he was unsure how an N.F.L. locker room would react.</p>
        <p>''Football is such a macho sport, based around masculinity and testosterone,'' said Moore, who grew up on Long Island and went to Oklahoma. ''As much as one person might hate another because of one thing, they seem to hate more because of sexuality.''</p>
        <p>Moore said he thought that the day of playing with an openly gay teammate could arrive, but ''I just don't think it is close.''</p>
        <p>PRO FOOTBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
