<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Mets Slug Their Way To a Game Out of First</title>
    <meta content="08METS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2004" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2004/07/08/sports/baseball/08mets.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1595205"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2004"/>
      <series series.name="BASEBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jenkins, Lee</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Philadelphia Phillies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/New York Mets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Baseball</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">New York Mets</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Philadelphia Phillies</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20040708T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9806EFDF123BF93BA35754C0A9629C8B63" item-length="1087" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Mets Slug Their Way To a Game Out of First</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Mets Playing for First Place Tonight</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LEE JENKINS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jenkins, Lee</byline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, July 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New York Mets defeat Philadelphia Phillies, 10-1; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>A team that lost 95 games last year, that was supposedly stuck in a rebuilding mode and that was projected to finish no higher than fourth in its division this season will play for first place Thursday night.</p>
        <p>Through much of the past week, the Mets have looked like a first-place team, played like a first-place team, and with one more victory, they can finally capture a share of first place. The Mets need only beat the Philadelphia Phillies at Citizens Bank Park on Thursday night, and so far that task has been easier than anyone could have anticipated.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Appearing almost flawless in every phase, the Mets blew away the Phillies in a performance that made a statement about their intentions in the National League East.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>A team that lost 95 games last year, that was supposedly stuck in a rebuilding mode and that was projected to finish no higher than fourth in its division this season will play for first place Thursday night.</p>
        <p>Through much of the past week, the Mets have looked like a first-place team, played like a first-place team, and with one more victory, they can finally capture a share of first place. The Mets need only beat the Philadelphia Phillies at Citizens Bank Park on Thursday night, and so far that task has been easier than anyone could have anticipated.</p>
        <p>The Mets have played six games at Citizens Bank Park this season and have won five of them. They were utterly dominant and appeared almost flawless in every phase Wednesday night in a 10-1 victory, a performance that made a statement about their intentions in the National League East.</p>
        <p>The Mets set a season high with 18 hits, matched a season high with four home runs, made a handful of defensive plays that could wind up on highlight shows and received a quality start from Steve Trachsel. More important than all of that, the Mets are three games over .500 for the first time since the summer of 2002.</p>
        <p>Holding their ground in the gridlocked N.L. East, the Mets are now alone in second place, one game ahead of the defending World Series champion Florida Marlins, a half-game up on the defending division champion Atlanta Braves and just one game behind the favored Phillies.</p>
        <p>''We win tomorrow and we're where we want to be,'' Mets Manager Art Howe said.</p>
        <p>His team set a vicious tone from the outset Wednesday, hitting three home runs in an inning for the first time in four years. Cliff Floyd led off the second inning with his fifth homer in the past nine games, Ty Wigginton recorded his fourth in the past six games and Mike Cameron hit his first of two homers, just one day after returning from a knee injury.</p>
        <p>Twenty-four hours removed from a homerless game at Citizens Bank Park -- only the second in the stadium's brief history -- the Mets worked every part of the grandstand. Floyd sent a homer to right field, Wigginton to left, Cameron to right-center and to left-center, giving the Mets a 10-0 lead by the fifth inning.</p>
        <p>After Wigginton's home run, a fan threw the ball back and nearly hit Philadelphia left fielder Pat Burrell on the head. After Burrell hit a solo homer in the seventh, accounting for the Phillies' run, a fan threw that one back, too.</p>
        <p>The locals had reason for outrage. Philadelphia's starting pitcher, Brett Myers, allowed nine hits and six runs, and recorded just 10 outs. Remarkably, his replacement was even less effective. Geoff Geary started the fifth by letting the Mets hit for an unusual kind of cycle -- a single by Richard Hidalgo, a triple by Wigginton, a double by Jason Phillips and a home run by Cameron.</p>
        <p>Wigginton, Cameron and Howe all supplied the same comment: ''It's getting contagious.''</p>
        <p>The top of the Mets' batting order, a symbol of this team's potential, is spreading the virus. Kazuo Matsui slapped three hits for the second game in a row and José Reyes had two hits, including a double that could have been a triple if he were not protecting his right hamstring. Reyes scored because Floyd legged out a fielder's choice, finding the extra gear that Reyes could not.</p>
        <p>Every starter, except Mike Piazza, had a hit Wednesday.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, Hidalgo had little to do with the onslaught. In the rare game that Hidalgo did not produce any run-scoring extra-base hits, he showed off one of the strongest arms in baseball and demonstrated why he led major league outfielders in assists last season.</p>
        <p>After Hidalgo threw out Jason Michaels at home in the third -- Phillips made a lunging tag on the play -- Cameron snared a drive over his head in the deepest part of the park in the fifth. Then Floyd ran across the left-field foul line and plowed into the fence to make a catch with the outcome already decided.</p>
        <p>Apparently, the hitting bug is not the only contagion. Matsui grabbed a tough liner, Wigginton made a diving play and, after Piazza could not handle a short-hopped throw to first base, he fetched the ball and retired Placido Polanco in a rundown.</p>
        <p>''If you want to call that a complete game, I'd say it,'' Cameron said.</p>
        <p>Coming into Philadelphia, Trachsel had a 1.59 earned run average at home and 7.88 on the road, but he took a little of Shea Stadium with him. Buttressed by a few thousand fans chanting for the Mets, Trachsel logged six shutout innings before Burrell finally touched him for a homer in the seventh. He allowed five hits and two walks.</p>
        <p>Asked about the path to first place, Trachsel said: ''I'm not even going to go there. This thing will get decided in the last week of the season.''</p>
        <p>As the final inning faded away, Piazza, Matsui and Hidalgo were relaxing on the bench, enjoying a rare blowout. To start the day, the Mets sat through a 1-hour-34-minute rain delay, which reminded them of their last trip to Philadelphia, when they endured two rain delays totaling 3:40.</p>
        <p>The Mets have become a patient team. They have waited all year for the opportunity that now presents itself.</p>
        <p>INSIDE PITCH</p>
        <p>Catcher VANCE WILSON was activated from the disabled list and TOM WILSON was optioned to Class AAA Norfolk. The Mets also expect to activate outfielder KARIM GARCIA from the disabled list on Friday in Florida.</p>
        <p>BASEBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
