<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Standard Schnauzer Is Best at Westminster</title>
    <meta content="12DOGS$08" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="19" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="DOG SHOW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="908482"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="DOG SHOW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dog Shows</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Westminster Kennel Club</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Finn, Robin</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Dogs</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970212T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6D91F3CF931A25751C0A961958260" item-length="891" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Standard Schnauzer Is Best at Westminster</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBIN FINN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Finn, Robin</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ch Parsifal Di Casa Netzer, standard schnauzer, is named best in show at Westminster Kennel Club dog show; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The king of dog shows, the Westminster Kennel Club show, crowned its king of canines at Madison Square Garden: Ch. Parsifal Di Casa Netzer, the standard schnauzer who skipped last year's show because his handler's father, Roy Holloway, judged best in show, rebounded in full glory last night.</p>
        <p>Pa, as the dignified dog is known around the house of his ecstatic handler, Doug Holloway, accepted his accolade with barely a blink of his bristly gray eyebrows. He seemed, in fact, to expect it. Co-owned by Rita Holloway, the handler's wife, and his breeder, Gabrio Del Torre, Pa was imported from Italy three years ago expressly for this purpose: to make him an international star of his breed by capturing this title.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The king of dog shows, the Westminster Kennel Club show, crowned its king of canines at Madison Square Garden: Ch. Parsifal Di Casa Netzer, the standard schnauzer who skipped last year's show because his handler's father, Roy Holloway, judged best in show, rebounded in full glory last night.</p>
        <p>Pa, as the dignified dog is known around the house of his ecstatic handler, Doug Holloway, accepted his accolade with barely a blink of his bristly gray eyebrows. He seemed, in fact, to expect it. Co-owned by Rita Holloway, the handler's wife, and his breeder, Gabrio Del Torre, Pa was imported from Italy three years ago expressly for this purpose: to make him an international star of his breed by capturing this title.</p>
        <p>''It came down to making a dream come true, and the wait was worth it,'' Doug Holloway said. ''Nothing can takes its place.''</p>
        <p>Before strutting to the championship of the 121st Westminster show, Pa was a banner for his breed. He accumulated 376 bests of breed, 157 groups and 65 bests in show.</p>
        <p>Of the seven group winners, five were comparative rookies, but the judge, Dorothy Collier, the wife of Westminster's president, seemed initially unwilling to overlook the prodigies in favor of the proven. The retirement-bound Dalmatian Ch. Spotlight's Spectacular was a three-time national specialty winner with 66 bests; the standard schnauzer came in with 65 bests and had captured top-dog honors in 1996 by defeating 93,725 others. Both are the top dogs in the history of their breeds.</p>
        <p>''But I wanted to be sure all seven had an equal chance,'' Collier said of her keeping the place on tenterhooks. When it came time to choose the nation's ultimate canine, Collier looked longest and last at Pa.</p>
        <p>''It was his performance; it was perfect,'' she said. ''He's a showman from beginning to end, and tonight he was everything he's always been. He's the consummate champion.''</p>
        <p>Last night's group competition was rigorous for some, disappointing to others.</p>
        <p>The winner of the hound group, the wirehaired dachshund Ch. Starbarrack Malachite SW, had to defeat a legend to advance to the best-in-show competition. That group's outcome brought a less-than-stellar close to the stellar show career of the most outstanding Afghan in the breed, Ch. Tryst of Grandeur. Expected to be a threat for top-dog honors, Tryst finished third in the group.</p>
        <p>The top-winning hound in history, the 6-year-old black bitch, her handler Michael Canalizo said, will switch from showing off the profile that earned 133 bests in show to producing litters of future champions.</p>
        <p>''I like her a great deal; she's dramatic, exquisite and exotic,'' said Gloria Reese, the group's judge. ''But I just loved this other dog more in that ring. You have to make a decision with your heart as well as your head, and coming or going, I just couldn't fault that dachshund.''</p>
        <p>Handled by Robert Fowler, a veteran with 45 years in the business but no group victory at Westminster until now, Ben, as the dog is known, handled his assignment with the aplomb of a much bigger dog.</p>
        <p>Dr. Bernard McGivern Jr., who judged the sporting group, said that competition came down to a matter of attitude, too. He selected the Gordon setter Ch. Bit O Gold Titan Treasure as the best of the bunch. The flashy black and gold setter, whose call name is Kirby, turned 5 yesterday and is, in the slightly prejudiced opinion of his handler, Ken Murray, ''probably the best Gordon setter who's ever lived.''</p>
        <p>The sporting dog who finished in second place was the Brittany spaniel Ch. Brittany's Ramblin' Mr. H Bogart JH, a 6-year-old sprite who proved his hunting instincts by fishing a yellow teddy bear from his handler's bag as they left the ring.</p>
        <p>McGivern liked the spirit demonstrated by both.</p>
        <p>''You look for three things: type, soundness, and attitude,'' he said. ''And since all these dogs are champions, it's pretty easy to find the first two qualities. But attitude is tougher. I felt the Gordon and Brittany gave me a lot of attitude. They looked like they wanted to be out there.''</p>
        <p>In the herding group, another newcomer to the big time, the Shetland sheepdog Ch. Zion's Man About Town, captivated the judge, Mrs. Norton Moore, with his savvy. His handler, Linda Guihen, said he is not yet 3 and began campaigning last April. With his 100th best of breed, he broke a breed record for youngsters.</p>
        <p>Nicole Madrigrano, an 11-year-old from Dousman, Wis., is presumed to be the youngest handler to win a best-of-breed class at this show. She and her golden retriever Mini, a k a Ch. Goodtimes Singing in the Rain, did not place in the group but made the initial cut.</p>
        <p>AROUND THE KENNEL</p>
        <p>The evening began with the championship for junior handlers, and the winner was 14-year-old CASANDRA CLARK of Tustin, Calif.</p>
        <p>DOG SHOW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
