<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The G.O.P. and the N.R.A.</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="30" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="762065"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FIREARMS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES POLITICS AND GOVERNMENT</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FRINGE POLITICAL MOVEMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TERRORISM</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">NATIONAL RIFLE ASSN (NRA)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">DOLE, BOB (SEN)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">LAPIERRE, WAYNE</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">WASHINGTON, THOMAS</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Firearms</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Terrorism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DE163EF931A25756C0A963958260" item-length="542" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The G.O.P. and the N.R.A.</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It always irritates the brass of the National Rifle Association when public figures talk sensibly about guns. In times past, the N.R.A. has aimed its churlish demagoguery at police chiefs who favor the assault-weapons ban and at Jim and Sarah Brady for their advocacy of a waiting period on handgun purchases. Now they are accusing former President George Bush of acting hastily in turning in his N.R.A. card in disgust.</p>
        <p>The president of the N.R.A., Thomas Washington, accused Mr. Bush of abandoning his "previous passion for justice and fairness for all law-abiding citizens." In a wacky five-page letter, Mr. Washington argued that upcoming hearings in Congress will provide evidence that the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms are the "jackbooted thugs" in "Nazi bucket helmets and black storm troopers uniforms" that an N.R.A. fund-raising letter claims they are. On this basis, Mr. Washington argued, the President should hold his resignation in abeyance.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It always irritates the brass of the National Rifle Association when public figures talk sensibly about guns. In times past, the N.R.A. has aimed its churlish demagoguery at police chiefs who favor the assault-weapons ban and at Jim and Sarah Brady for their advocacy of a waiting period on handgun purchases. Now they are accusing former President George Bush of acting hastily in turning in his N.R.A. card in disgust.</p>
        <p>The president of the N.R.A., Thomas Washington, accused Mr. Bush of abandoning his "previous passion for justice and fairness for all law-abiding citizens." In a wacky five-page letter, Mr. Washington argued that upcoming hearings in Congress will provide evidence that the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco and Firearms are the "jackbooted thugs" in "Nazi bucket helmets and black storm troopers uniforms" that an N.R.A. fund-raising letter claims they are. On this basis, Mr. Washington argued, the President should hold his resignation in abeyance.</p>
        <p>It is a source of unending amazement that the N.R.A. can speak such nonsense and still wring money from otherwise sensible citizens and intimidate otherwise forceful politicians. Even now, Senator Bob Dole and other Republican Presidential candidates are cowering before Mr. Washington and Wayne LaPierre, the N.R.A. executive vice president in charge of defamatory blather.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush, for his part, can be faulted for taking too long to repudiate the N.R.A., but he certainly has figured this situation out correctly. Other Republican members of the N.R.A. can show their awareness that the organization is out of control and their respect for their party's former leader by following Mr. Bush's example in resigning.</p>
        <p>Mr. Bush's letter implicitly points up an important distinction that the N.R.A. ignores in its unconscionable effort to depict Federal agents as enemies of the law. The A.T.F. has been beset with managerial problems. It has made errors of judgment in law enforcement. But as Mr. Bush points out, it insults both intelligence and the factual record to condemn A.T.F., Secret Service and Federal Bureau of Investigation personnel as fascist thugs.</p>
        <p>Slowly but surely, the rantings of Mr. LaPierre are driving reasonable people out of the organization. Senator Ben Nighthorse Campbell resigned last year, and Representative John Dingell, an avid hunter, quit his seat on the board. Their actions undercut the N.R.A. lie that gun control represents a threat to people who want to use guns for target shooting and hunting. Richard Riley, a gun dealer who was president of the N.R.A. from 1990 to 1992, predicts that other members will resign because the present leadership's extremist tactics have damaged the N.R.A.'s image to the point that "now we're cast with the Nazis, the skinheads and the Ku Klux Klan."</p>
        <p>With the N.R.A. convention starting in the next few days, this would be an excellent time for average citizens to follow Mr. Bush's leadership. So should those who want to follow him in office. Come on, Bob Dole, stand up for the "sense of decency and honor" defined by George Bush and turn in your N.R.A. card too. Maybe then Senator Phil Gramm will get brave enough to cancel his speech to the N.R.A. convention in Phoenix on May 20.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
