<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Disney and Developer Are Chosen To Build 42d Street Hotel Complex</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="762025"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">AREA PLANNING AND RENEWAL</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW YORK CITY</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">TIMES SQUARE (NYC)</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DISNEY DEVELOPMENT CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">TISHMAN URBAN DEVELOPMENT CORP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">KENNEDY, SHAWN G</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York/New York City</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Area Planning and Renewal</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE1D9173FF931A25756C0A963958260" item-length="945" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Disney and Developer Are Chosen To Build 42d Street Hotel Complex</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By SHAWN G. KENNEDY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">KENNEDY, SHAWN G</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In the first tangible sign that the long-awaited redevelopment of a tawdry stretch of Eighth Avenue is more than a pipe dream, the Disney Development Company and a large New York developer were chosen yesterday to build a huge hotel, entertainment and retail complex on 42d Street at Eighth Avenue.</p>
        <p>The $303 million project is the centerpiece of state and city efforts to transform 42d Street between Seventh and Eighth Avenues from a seedy strip with its ever-present hustlers and sex shops into a glitzy family-oriented entertainment center.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In the first tangible sign that the long-awaited redevelopment of a tawdry stretch of Eighth Avenue is more than a pipe dream, the Disney Development Company and a large New York developer were chosen yesterday to build a huge hotel, entertainment and retail complex on 42d Street at Eighth Avenue.</p>
        <p>The $303 million project is the centerpiece of state and city efforts to transform 42d Street between Seventh and Eighth Avenues from a seedy strip with its ever-present hustlers and sex shops into a glitzy family-oriented entertainment center.</p>
        <p>The developers, who still have to line up financing for the project, hope to break ground sometime in 1996 and complete the project in three to four years. The development will include a 680-room hotel, a multilevel entertainment and retail arcade and perhaps a 100-unit time-share hotel.</p>
        <p>The city put up $35 million to condemn and acquire the site at the northeast corner of 42d Street and Eighth Avenue. In return, city officials said, the city and the state will receive about $56 million in taxes and leasing fees over a 20-year period. In addition, the project is expected to generate 3,000 construction jobs and 1,400 permanent jobs.</p>
        <p>But perhaps of even more value is the Disney name. In its effort to turn around a neighborhood long synonymous with urban danger and degradation, the city now has a partner that is a symbol of wholesome entertainment worldwide.</p>
        <p>While Disney has been pushed to the front of the stage as the star of the project, as a development partner it will serve as a supporting player.</p>
        <p>Disney's partner, Tishman Urban Development Corporation, will build the hotel, raise funds for the project and operate the hotel or find a company to do so. Disney will be responsible for developing the retail and entertainment portion of the project.</p>
        <p>Disney already has a growing presence in New York. In addition to the project announced yesterday, the company is close to completing a deal with the city to renovate the New Amsterdam Theater, just to the east of the hotel site. According to David L. Malmuth, vice president for corporate real estate at the Disney Development Company, the company is also developing a superstore on Fifth Avenue and 55th Street.</p>
        <p>And of course the Disney musical "Beauty and the Beast" is still drawing crowds on Broadway.</p>
        <p>The selection of the winning developers from several competitors was a closely guarded secret until the announcement yesterday, which itself had a theatrical air. In the presence of Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani, Gov. George E. Pataki, state officials and executives from Tishman and Disney, smoke was blown across a darkened stage in the Academy Theater on 43d Street as a gold curtain was raised to reveal a spotlighted model of the planned hotel project.</p>
        <p>Charles Gargano, the chairman of the State Urban Development Corporation, said the developers were selected for the spirit and sophistication of their design.</p>
        <p>"Times Square represents the vibrancy, creativity and soul of New York and is worth preserving," Mr. Gargano said, "It is the town square of America and tourists come from all over the world to drink up the atmosphere."</p>
        <p>Still to be arranged is the financing for the $303 million project. John L. Tishman, chairman and C.E.O. of Tishman, said that money for the retail property will probably come from a commercial bank after some leases have been signed. Financing for the hotel and time-share project, Mr. Tishman said, will likely come from several equity investors.</p>
        <p>The Eighth Avenue hotel is only one part of the Times Square redevelopment project. Another key property in the 10-year-old effort to redevelop Times Square and 42d Street still in the works is the development of four office towers around the intersection of Seventh Avenue and 42d Street.</p>
        <p>Last August, the developers of that property, the Prudential Insurance Company of America and Park Tower Realty, retained their stake in the project by agreeing to pay more than $20 million to refurbish storefronts in the buildings that have been condemned and emptied of tenants in preparation for redevelopment. In the meantime the space will be leased to interim tenants while the developers wait for the office market to rebound.</p>
        <p>The design for the hotel and entertainment complex, which will replace a string of derelict buildings diagonally across the Port Authority Bus Terminal, is an eye-popping mix.</p>
        <p>The 47-story hotel, designed by Arquitectonica, a Miami-based architectural firm, was designed to appear as if it split into two parts by a streak of light on its facade. The 615,000-square-foot hotel will have its main entrance on 43d Street.</p>
        <p>The part of the project that will hold the proposed time-share units is a 10-story building with a glass-mosaic facade featuring postcard images of New York. At street level, running 400 feet along 42d Street, will be the retail and entertainment portion of the project, and it will include the renovation of the Case Building. Disney will be an anchor tenant of this part of the project and Sega, the entertainment company, has expressed an interest in leasing 28,000 square feet in the basement of one of the buildings.</p>
        <p>There will also be a two-story, 12,000-square-foot restaurant on the Eighth Avenue corner of the project.</p>
        <p>As required by the design guidelines for the project, there will be 10 to 12 huge signs scattered at various heights throughout the project.</p>
        <p>The Tishman-Disney team won the right to develop the project over seven applicants that included two other finalists, Marriott International and Triarc Equities, and Milstein Properties and Weiler Arnow Management.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
