<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Making Moves at Paramount; A Chief's Solution Involves People as Well as Pictures</title>
    <meta content="06paramount" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="6" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Movies; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/02/06/business/media/06paramount.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1737641"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Executive</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Studios</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Movies/News and Features/Studios/Paramount Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Executives and Management</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Motion Pictures</classifier>
        <org class="online_producer">Paramount Pictures</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Grey, Brad</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060206T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9506E6DC173EF935A35751C0A9609C8B63" item-length="2149" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Making Moves at Paramount; A Chief's Solution Involves People as Well as Pictures</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Making Moves at Paramount</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA M. HOLSON</byline>
      <dateline>LOS ANGELES, Feb. 5</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brad Grey may have an image problem, but he says it is not something that has him terribly worried.</p>
        <p>In March, Mr. Grey, the former talent manager who is now chairman and chief executive of Paramount Pictures, was criticized for the way he handled the ouster of a well-liked senior executive. In the fall, some producers complained he was not developing movies quickly enough to fill Paramount's 2006 slate.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Brad Grey has a plan for reviving Paramount, which includes buying good scripts and betting heavily on talented executives and filmmakers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Brad Grey may have an image problem, but he says it is not something that has him terribly worried.</p>
        <p>In March, Mr. Grey, the former talent manager who is now chairman and chief executive of Paramount Pictures, was criticized for the way he handled the ouster of a well-liked senior executive. In the fall, some producers complained he was not developing movies quickly enough to fill Paramount's 2006 slate.</p>
        <p>And last month, staffers were upset after an article in Variety revealed that Paramount executives were poring over employee rosters of the newly acquired live-action unit of DreamWorks SKG, deciding who could stay and who would be let go. After the article appeared, one DreamWorks executive, who asked not to be identified, fearing a reprisal from Paramount, described the company's actions as a ''human bake sale.''</p>
        <p>In an interview, Mr. Grey dismissed such criticisms as idle Hollywood gossip. Paramount now has about 20 new films scheduled for production. It is attracting new filmmakers to the lot, including Oliver Stone and Jared Hess, the director of ''Napoleon Dynamite.'' And of the disgruntled former employees who lost their jobs, he said, ''I would not expect those who were let go or moved on to agree with me.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grey believes he has a plan for reviving Paramount, which in 2004 ranked seventh in domestic box-office receipts. And the plan is similar to the one he had as a talent manager aggressively guiding the careers of A-list actors like Brad Pitt or developing television shows like ''The Sopranos'': he will buy good scripts, bet heavily on talented executives and filmmakers and, he hopes, watch the money follow.</p>
        <p>''Some people would say, 'Come in with a flamethrower,' and others would take a more measured approach,'' Mr. Grey said in his office on the Paramount lot last week. ''I quickly realized I had to have my own style and strategy and find my own way. I don't lack confidence. I don't sweat. I don't want to get too Zen on you, but I have to run my own race.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grey, 48, who had never managed a movie company before, will need more than confidence if he expects to turn Paramount into a vibrant studio for the MTV generation. The studio is a division of Viacom, which recently split with CBS. Now, as a larger part of a smaller company, the pressure to perform is greater than before as the movie industry faces challenges on several fronts: piracy, lagging movie attendance and slowing DVD sales.</p>
        <p>He conceded that Paramount had yet to find its footing, nearly a year into its revamping. And many of the executives he has hired lack the experience of their competitors or the people they replaced.</p>
        <p>But most of all, with more pink slips to be handed out this week at both Paramount and DreamWorks, it may be difficult for Mr. Grey to quell the attacks on the company that have persisted for nearly a year. Even studio executives agree they are not likely to end unless the movies Mr. Grey has championed are hits.</p>
        <p>As Edward Jay Epstein, the author of ''The Big Picture: The New Logic of Money and Power in Hollywood,'' put it, ''Brad Grey doesn't just need to make movies. He needs to make movies that people want to see.''</p>
        <p>In 2004, Paramount took in $636 million at the domestic box office after releasing lackluster remakes of ''The Manchurian Candidate'' and ''The Stepford Wives.'' The previous year was even more disappointing. ''Beyond Borders,'' with Angelina Jolie, took in only $4 million domestically. And the studio missed the mark with the sequel to ''Lara Croft: Tomb Raider,'' which brought in $65 million at the domestic box office and which executives said ended the franchise.</p>
        <p>Those numbers led Tom Freston, chief executive of Viacom, to hire Mr. Grey last year. He joined Paramount on March 1. Sherry Lansing, who was studio chairwoman for 12 years, declined to talk about her tenure. But Mr. Grey said the studio needed a complete overhaul, both in how the business was run and in its culture.</p>
        <p>''If an opportunity presented itself, we were going to be aggressive about that,'' he said. He did not waste time. Eight months after Mr. Grey joined Paramount, almost every top executive who had worked for Ms. Lansing was gone. And now that the DreamWorks merger is completed, about 10 percent of employees at the combined companies will lose their jobs, said Paramount.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grey sought to change not just people, but process. Rob Moore, a former partner at Revolution Studios who was hired by Mr. Grey to oversee worldwide distribution, marketing and operations, recalled getting a call in November from an executive, Brad Weston, asking for weekend box-office estimates for the film ''Get Rich or Die Tryin'.''</p>
        <p>Such information is widely distributed at other studios. But when Mr. Moore approached a colleague about getting the numbers for Mr. Weston, the colleague resisted. ''It was a 'don't ask, don't tell' policy,'' said Mr. Moore. The colleague finally relented.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grey's boldest move was buying the live-action unit of DreamWorks for $1.6 billion in December, outbidding NBC Universal. Mr. Grey said the deal gave Paramount a trained international marketing and distribution staff, as well as rights to distribute films produced by DreamWorks Animation.</p>
        <p>Others, though, in Hollywood and on Wall Street, saw a more pressing need for the acquisition. The studio was facing a shortfall in its 2006 and 2007 slates. ''They were desperate,'' said Mr. Epstein, the author, who has written about Paramount.</p>
        <p>In response to such comments, Mr. Grey said, ''Did we need it? O.K. I won't argue that. But it fit into what I want to do for this studio.''</p>
        <p>A year ago, Mr. Grey was visited by an executive recruiter, James M. Citrin, who sent the Paramount chief a copy of his book, ''You're in Charge. Now What?'' Mr. Grey said he read the book, but he shrugged his shoulders when asked what lessons he learned. Instead, his eyes lighted up when discussing Harvey Weinstein, the co-founder of Miramax Films and his first boss in entertainment industry.</p>
        <p>''I learned no detail was too small,'' said Mr. Grey. ''It was all about the details.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grey's office is a study in detailed elegance, like a page out of a Restoration Hardware catalog, but the David Smith paintings are real and the furniture more expensive. In his office one morning last week, Norah Jones was playing on his stereo and he served coffee with half-and-half on the side. (Other Paramount executives offer packets of Coffee-mate.) There were hints of cardamom and cedar in the air, and chopped wood was artfully displayed in an unused fireplace.</p>
        <p>Like Mr. Weinstein, friends and colleagues say Mr. Grey is a fearless entrepreneur with a taste for self-promotion. Mr. Grey laughed at the comparison. ''We have different styles,'' Mr. Grey said. ''With me you are not going to get a bloody nose.''</p>
        <p>The encounters, though, can seem just as painful. Last March Mr. Grey was criticized for the way he handled the dismissal of Donald De Line, Paramount's president. Mr. De Line was on a business trip in Europe when he learned that Mr. Grey was courting Gail Berman, a Fox television executive with no movie experience, to take his job. According to several people who talked to Mr. De Line, the executive's friends saw the report online and called him. Mr. De Line, who declined to comment on the incident, promptly quit and became a producer at Warner Brothers.</p>
        <p>What upset many in Hollywood was that Mr. Grey did not tell Mr. De Line first, according to more than a dozen Hollywood executives, long-time producers and past and present Paramount executives.</p>
        <p>It was not the only incident. In December Mr. Moore and Mr. Grey were criticized for how they handled the dismissal of Wayne Lewellen, a 33-year Paramount veteran who oversaw distribution. In this case, timing was the issue; he was let go a few days before Christmas. Mr. Lewellen did not return a call seeking comment.</p>
        <p>''If it begins to look like a pattern, it is poor practice on the part of management,'' said Jerry Porras, a professor emeritus at the Stanford School of Business and the author of ''Built to Last: Successful Habits of Visionary Companies.'' ''You have to deal with people leaving in a humane way. It's not only right for the people who are leaving, but it's also the right thing to do for the people who are left behind.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Moore, who was Mr. Lewellen's boss, said that decision was discussed with Sumner M. Redstone, Viacom's chairman, before he talked to Mr. Lewellen. ''Once we made the decision I informed Wayne and told him that we would take care of him financially,'' said Mr. Moore.</p>
        <p>Mr. Grey said he did not regret letting the executives go. ''Change is difficult,'' he said. ''Could the company have handled the changes more elegantly? We could have. And we will try to do things different in the future.''</p>
        <p>In an interview last week, Ms. Berman seemed perplexed by recent news reports swirling around Hollywood that she was sparring with her staff.</p>
        <p>''I heard this last week from another studio executive. He said, 'People tell me you are so straightforward,' '' Ms. Berman said. ''To be honest, I wasn't sure if that was a compliment or not.''</p>
        <p>Last month, Variety published an article suggesting a rift between Ms. Berman and Alli Shearmur, co-president of production, who shares responsibility with Brad Weston. ''We heard about the rumors and talked,'' said Ms. Shearmur. ''We addressed our group and told them it's not true.''</p>
        <p>One longtime producer said agents and others in Hollywood were more willing to believe the news reports because of what happened to Mr. De Line. But Mr. Weston warned that some of these rumors could be coming from envious peers. Ms. Berman has had the job only since June, and she and her team have not yet released any of their movies. ''We come from an aggressive background and we are playing to win,'' he said. ''Our competitors see us coming.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Berman is new to the movie business but has been an entertainment executive for nearly two decades, overseeing hits like ''24'' and American Idol'' at Fox. Still, several talent agents said it was hard to guess what she wants.</p>
        <p>Ms. Berman said that anyone who wanted to understand her taste had only to consider the coming movies she has championed. These include a sequel to the hit ''Jackass''; ''Nacho Libre,'' a comedy about a priest turned wrestler starring Jack Black; and the drama ''World Trade Center,'' directed by Mr. Stone.</p>
        <p>''I approach movie making from a personal gut level. 'Do I like it? Is it resonating for me?' '' said Ms. Berman. ''I try to put everything else aside. That has served me well in life creatively.''</p>
        <p>One of Ms. Berman's tasks is to exploit Viacom's other brands, including making movies for the MTV, Nickelodeon and BET networks. But that, like many things at the studio, is a work in progress. ''It's an ever-evolving situation,'' said Albert Berger, founder of Bona Fide Productions, who is one of a group of producers who signed deals at Paramount last year. ''There is opportunity. But they are not yet going in a direction that is completely defined.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Grey said Ms. Berman had his support so far. ''She's working hard and it's early,'' he said. In fact, he says he finds the Hollywood speculation about Paramount's future somewhat amusing.</p>
        <p>When told about the most recent rumor about him taking a corporate job at Viacom, Paramount's parent, he laughed. ''What does that mean?'' he said. ''Am I being named emperor?''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
