<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>College Football Notebook; Garrett Signs Guide Princeton</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1988" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="20" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="192259"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1988"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FOOTBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Baseball/Major League/Detroit Tigers</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Football</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19881028T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=940DE2DA163BF93BA15753C1A96E948260" item-length="740" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>College Football Notebook; Garrett Signs Guide Princeton</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By WILLIAM N. WALLACE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">WALLACE, WILLIAM N</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>LEAD: When Princeton lines up for its first offensive play at Palmer Stadium tomorrow, the destiny of the game and the Ivy League championship will seem to be in the hands of No. 17, Jason Garrett, quarterback and captain.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>LEAD: When Princeton lines up for its first offensive play at Palmer Stadium tomorrow, the destiny of the game and the Ivy League championship will seem to be in the hands of No. 17, Jason Garrett, quarterback and captain.</p>
        <p>When Princeton lines up for its first offensive play at Palmer Stadium tomorrow, the destiny of the game and the Ivy League championship will seem to be in the hands of No. 17, Jason Garrett, quarterback and captain.</p>
        <p>The opponent is Penn, unbeaten but vulnerable. The six teams the Quakers have defeated have won only seven of 38 games and Penn's Ivy League lead is one game over Princeton and Cornell, whom the Tigers have defeated.</p>
        <p>If Garrett can steer his team to victory, the road to Princeton's first Ivy championship since 1969 will be open. The Tigers will have only weak Yale and Dartmouth teams as future foes.</p>
        <p>Garrett is the commander. The selection of the next play for most teams is made on the sideline and then signaled in to the quarterback, who dutifully nods. Not Garrett, said Mike Hodgson, the receivers' coach who does the signaling with hand and arm gestures. 'Coach on the Field'</p>
        <p>''Because there isn't time to change, Jason doesn't exactly shake off the signal like a baseball pitcher if he doesn't like the call,'' Hodgson said. ''But he's not above signaling back a play for us to think about calling next, one he likes. It's just like having another coach on the field and no wonder with his background.''</p>
        <p>The background is heavy with football. His father, Jim Garrett, has been a coach and scout in college and professional football for three decades, and all four of his sons have been fine players. There is half a football field in the backyard of the family home at Monmouth Beach, N.J., and the sport is a subject of family conversations.</p>
        <p>Jason's younger brother, Judd, is the Tiger tailback, and his brother John played end on last year's team, the first one to have a winning record at Princeton since 1981.</p>
        <p>Jason is a football student. He is around the coaches' offices almost every day and, said Hodgson, he studies film for hours. ''When he leaves, Jason always has a film can with him,'' the coach said.</p>
        <p>As with the play calling, Princeton's game plan is done by committee, and Garrett contributes. ''He's got good suggestions to make, good ideas,'' Hodgson said.</p>
        <p>Garrett can also play this game. He has completed 65 percent of 171 passes this season without an interception, a Division I-AA record.</p>
        <p>In addition, he is an effective runner and blocker on a team with limited offensive tools. If, for example, there were four speedburners to play wide receiver then he could do a lot more.</p>
        <p>Garrett's brief college career of 20 games has only four more to go. He started at Princeton in 1984, transferred to Columbia in 1985 when his father was coach there for one season, and returned to Princeton in 1986. He was ineligible that fall and was quarterback of the scout team, imitating the upcoming opponent.</p>
        <p>If there has been a disappointment it was being the victim when Columbia broke its 44-game losing streak three games ago.</p>
        <p>Aided by Garrett's pragmatic leadership, the Tigers shook off that stigma and rebounded with victories over Bucknell and Harvard. ----New Quarterback for Brown Brown broke in a new quarterback, Dan Rukamp, this week after Danny Clark suffered a severe ankle bruise. Clark, who had provided most of the offensive punch, will be out indefinitely and the team plays at Harvard tomorrow. Both have lost five straight.</p>
        <p>Dartmouth is going to throw the ball and Yale will run with it at the Yale Bowl because neither has much choice. The Green's Mark Johnson had 53 pass attempts, a school record, in the loss to Cornell last Saturday, while Buddy Zachery, a former backup, has rushed for over 100 yards in three straight games for the Elis.</p>
        <p>Lehigh lost its quarterback, Mark McGowan, for the season with a knee injury and so the senior Jim Harris, whom McGowan had supplanted, got to play for the first time in two years. He passed for 383 yards and four touchdowns against Towson State and the target at home tomorrow is Columbia, listless since beating Princeton.</p>
        <p>Lafayette, the best in the Colonial League, plays Cornell, which may yet be the Ivy's best, at home. Of the 13 Colonial-Ivy games to date, the Colonials have won eight.</p>
        <p>In Division III competition mighty Wagner might get some competition from C. W. Post, the Liberty Conference leader. Iona will be ready for Fordham tonight at Mount Vernon, and the New Jersey Athletic Conference title will probably be decided tomorrow night when Montclair State hosts Trenton State, both 6-1 and 3-0.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
