<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Producers Defend Reviled Cable TV Show</title>
    <meta content="01ROCH$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="954478"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Women Against a Violent Environment (WAVE)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Time Warner Communications</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Supreme Court (US)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">National Organization for Women</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Loce, Tom</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Richter, Ed</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Life Without Shame (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pornography and Obscenity</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Suits and Litigation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19970901T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F04E3DF1F31F932A3575AC0A961958260" item-length="767" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Producers Defend Reviled Cable TV Show</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>ROCHESTER, Aug. 31</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Women Against a Violent Environment (WAVE), affiliate of National Organization for Women, is trying to get Life Without Shame, offensive cable television show in Rochester, NY, off air; Time Warner Communications in March prohibited producers from broadcasting any shows on network for six months, acting in wake of 1996 Supreme Court ruling that allows cable operators to restrict obscene programs on leased-access TV; producers Tom Loce and Ed Richter have filed suit in Federal District Court to lift ban (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Tom Loce and Ed Richter will tell you with pride that they produce the most offensive cable television show in Rochester's history -- aptly named ''Life Without Shame.''</p>
        <p>For episodes called The Bum Olympics, they rounded up homeless men who competed for a bottle of liquor by stuffing themselves into heavy-duty garbage bags, giving their best begging speech and simulating sex with a blow-up doll.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Tom Loce and Ed Richter will tell you with pride that they produce the most offensive cable television show in Rochester's history -- aptly named ''Life Without Shame.''</p>
        <p>For episodes called The Bum Olympics, they rounded up homeless men who competed for a bottle of liquor by stuffing themselves into heavy-duty garbage bags, giving their best begging speech and simulating sex with a blow-up doll.</p>
        <p>For other shows, they videotaped strippers from Rochester clubs as they slithered out of their clothes and performed lap dances.</p>
        <p>But it was the nonstop jokes about rape and domestic violence that galvanized a 50-member women's group and touched off a public debate on freedom of speech that will reach the courtroom this week.</p>
        <p>The group, Women Against a Violent Environment, or WAVE, an affiliate of the National Organization for Women, decided last year to fight to get the program off the air.</p>
        <p>It put together a 10-minute video of snippets from ''Life Without Shame'' to show to public groups. On it, Mr. Loce remarks, ''Nearly 60 percent of all rapes are committed against girls younger than 17.''</p>
        <p>''Well, of course,'' responds Mr. Richter. ''You don't want to rape someone that's 35 years old. She'd probably like it. You've got to get someone more docile.''</p>
        <p>WAVE members and several church groups denounced the show's sponsors and organized a demonstration against one, a family-owned pizzeria. The restaurant eventually pulled its advertising.</p>
        <p>Under mounting pressure, Time Warner Communications, the local cable company, vetoed two shows earlier this year and then in March prohibited the producers from broadcasting any shows on the network for six months, acting in the wake of a 1996 United States Supreme Court ruling that allows cable operators to restrict obscene programs on leased-access TV -- local cable stations that turn a profit from advertising.</p>
        <p>Mr. Richter and Mr. Loce say their First Amendment rights have been violated, and they have filed suit in Federal District Court to lift the ban. The New York Civil Liberties Union has joined in the lawsuit in support of the show's producers. A hearing is scheduled for Friday.</p>
        <p>The producers assert that the show is all in good fun and they make no apologies. ''If you believe half the stuff on the show, you have problems,'' Mr. Richter said.</p>
        <p>The show, which began in 1993, is still broadcast on a public access channel in Rochester, which cannot be restricted, according to the same Supreme Court ruling, because public access channels do not depend on advertising revenue. But gone are the days when Mr. Richter and Mr. Loce could charge $300 a minute for advertising and could afford to reach beyond Rochester to thousands of viewers in Syracuse, Binghamton, Utica, Rome and Albany.</p>
        <p>''We're losing our shirts, but we're doing it in the name of the First Amendment,'' said Mr. Richter, who is married and holds a master's degree in film production. Both he and Mr. Loce make a living selling movie memorabilia.</p>
        <p>Time Warner declined comment, but Neil Goldberg, general counsel of the National Cable Television Association, pooh-poohs the suit. ''The Supreme Court ruled and said it was constitutional to limit indecent material'' on leased-access stations, he said. ''You don't get much higher than the Supreme Court.''</p>
        <p>WAVE has filed a petition for friend-of-the-court status. With the petition, which cites experts who have studied men's violence toward women and children, the women's group hopes to help the court reach a decision favorable to Time Warner.</p>
        <p>''I think they do see themselves,  right now, as First Amendment champions,'' said Barbara Kasper, a co-founder of the group and a college professor. ''But not all speech is protected. You can't yell, 'fire' in a crowded movie theater.''</p>
        <p>WAVE members say they are now being harassed for exercising their own First Amendment rights.</p>
        <p>Ms. Kasper says she has received threatening phone calls at home, and the WAVE answering machine has been jammed with obscene messages. ''Life Without Shame'' producers have also registered WAVE as a business name and intend to order the group to stop using it. Mr. Richter said, ''We felt they overstepped the boundaries.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
