<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Capitalist Venturing in the World of Computers and Religion</title>
    <meta content="03KHOS$03" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165743"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/World Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0DEFD81138F930A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="1971" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Capitalist Venturing in the World of Computers and Religion</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAURA M. HOLSON</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a late Friday afternoon in December, when most Silicon Valley executives were heading to their Napa Valley estates for the weekend, Vinod Khosla was tucked away in his office in Menlo Park, Calif., talking about God.</p>
        <p>As an 11-year-old growing up in his native India, he says, he came to believe that organized religion was just a centuries-old form of social control; a fear of God was the only way to make an unruly population behave.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a late Friday afternoon in December, when most Silicon Valley executives were heading to their Napa Valley estates for the weekend, Vinod Khosla was tucked away in his office in Menlo Park, Calif., talking about God.</p>
        <p>As an 11-year-old growing up in his native India, he says, he came to believe that organized religion was just a centuries-old form of social control; a fear of God was the only way to make an unruly population behave.</p>
        <p>But such notions now are outdated, he says, adding that in the next 100 years ''traditional religion will be as relevant as witch doctors are today.'' That is especially true, he continues, for religious leaders like the pope, who  ''chooses to talk about gays, abortion and priests not being women, when he could use his power in better ways.''</p>
        <p>Such ideas from one of Silicon Valley's premier venture capitalists are not standard dot-com fare. But then, Mr. Khosla, a partner in Kleiner Perkins Caufield &amp; Byers, is far from typical. In the 15 years he has been a Kleiner Perkins partner, he has had little time for small thoughts.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khosla started his first company at age 25. Two years later, he co-founded Sun Microsystems. At age 44, his vision has turned metaphysical, to a time when human thought melds with computer intelligence, blurring the lines between people and machines.</p>
        <p>But four years ago, ideas of a more immediate and practical nature resulted in his most ambitious project to date. He was struck by the notion that as the Internet was transformed into a mass medium, telecommunications companies would soon need equipment to push data over  fiber optic networks faster and more cheaply. No such technology existed at the time. So Mr. Khosla, who typically concentrates on investing in promising companies, set out to find a team of entrepreneurs to create the next generation of computer networking.</p>
        <p>Last year, optical networking, as the idea came to be known, was one of the hottest new areas in the technology sector, reaping rich rewards for Mr. Khosla, Kleiner Perkins and the companies they had backed. To name just the highlights, the Cerent Corporation was sold to Cisco Systems for $7.3 billion in stock, the most ever paid for a private technology company; Siara Systems, which has yet to test a product, announced in November it was being sold to Redback Networks for an astounding $4.3 billion in stock, and Juniper Networks, a maker of optical networking equipment, has seen its shares jump 900 percent since it went public in June, giving it a market value of more than $17.5 billion.</p>
        <p>But Mr. Khosla's personality both attracts and repels.</p>
        <p>''He is probably the biggest thinker I have ever seen,'' said Joe Kraus, a co-founder of Excite, the Kleiner Perkins-backed search engine that merged last year with another of the firm's companies, the high-speed cable Internet service @Home. ''But the challenge is in the presentation.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Khosla is often described as abrasive and overbearing, a busybody who is loath to let entrepreneurs run their own show. But loyalists say his strength is the ability to spot opportunities that others miss.</p>
        <p>''People say I can be too 'in love' with my companies,'' he says. ''But I've earned the freedom to be honest and more blunt.'' On his desk sits a Beanie Baby rhinoceros given to him by his four children as a reminder of how bruising he can be. But ultimately the only thing that matters, he says, ''is whether entrepreneurs come back or not.''</p>
        <p>And come back they do, if only because his laser-like focus commands attention in a Valley filled with white noise and hype.</p>
        <p>Carl Russo, Cerent's former chief executive, said some in Silicon Valley use a Hollywood metaphor to describe Mr. Khosla: ''Vinod is the worst director of movies, but he is the best picker of scripts.''</p>
        <p>Still, many who have worked closely with Mr. Khosla say they would consider it again. Among them is Mr. Kraus, who met Mr. Khosla, an early backer of Excite, in 1994. ''I'd need a vacation before I decided to do that again,'' allows Mr. Kraus, now a senior vice president of content at Excite@Home. ''But I'd do it.''</p>
        <p>This from a man whose ideas Mr. Khosla once described as ''amateur hour.'' Worse, on April Fool's Day in 1996, Mr. Khosla tricked Mr. Kraus, then 25, into believing that Excite's public stock offering had been cancelled hours before the stock began trading. (Mr. Khosla said he let Mr. Kraus stew for a half-hour before letting him in on the joke.)</p>
        <p>But in the summer of 1996, their relationship nearly ended. Mr. Kraus recalls one afternoon when Mr. Khosla had chided him once too many times about an executive Mr. Khosla disliked. ''I absolutely lost it,'' Mr. Kraus says of the incident. ''I hung up on him. After that, I sat there stunned in my chair.''</p>
        <p>Almost immediately, Mr. Kraus's cellular phone rang. ''Vinod was on the phone, laughing,'' Mr. Kraus recalls. ''He said, 'That's so good.' ''</p>
        <p>''There is this characteristic of unrelentingness,'' says George Bell, the president of Excite@Home. ''At the end of the day, you just want to give up.''</p>
        <p>Such tales make Mr. Khosla cringe. For him, playing devil's advocate -- no matter how painful it can be -- is essential to helping entrepreneurs think critically. ''I like having impact,'' he says. ''They'll also tell you that they didn't doubt my loyalty or my passion.'' Still, to make sure entrepreneurs he has not worked with know what is in store, he demands that they speak to past colleagues.</p>
        <p>Mr. Khosla grew up in New Delhi, where he earned a degree in electrical engineering from the Indian Institute of Technology. In 1976, he moved to the United States with his childhood girlfriend, now his wife, Neeru, and got a master's degree in biomedical engineering from Carnegie-Mellon University. He then moved to Palo Alto, Calif., where he earned an M.B.A. at Stanford University in 1980.</p>
        <p>That year he co-founded his first company, Daisy Systems, a now-defunct concern that specialized in computer-aided design. But more importantly, he began formulating his ideas about networking computers. He wanted to build a workstation that would handle the complex operations that a mainframe computer could, but that was inexpensive and easy to assemble.</p>
        <p>In 1981, a Stanford secretary suggested that Mr. Khosla meet a German graduate student, Andreas Bechtolsheim, who was then licensing such a computer design for $10,000 to local companies. Mr. Khosla suggested they build it themselves, and in February 1982, Sun Microsystems was born. Mr. Khosla became chief executive.</p>
        <p>While the two men remain close friends, Mr. Khosla's intensity was too much for the corporate suite, say former associates. Scott McNealy, a friend who shared a townhouse with Mr. Khosla and his wife at one time, had joined Sun at Mr. Khosla's urging and was later named president. But while Mr. Khosla was credited with the vision to build a Fortune 500 company, he was not as smooth as Mr. McNealy. So in 1984, Mr. Khosla  was replaced by his former roommate. Friends say he was devastated.</p>
        <p>Today he says, ''I think I helped in some way to change the way computing was done.''</p>
        <p>Six months later, Mr. Khosla, then a 30-year-old multimillionaire, joined Kleiner but also indulged in a number of diversions. He took up skydiving and whitewater rafting, undertook a worldwide search to find an architect to build his Portola Valley home in the style of Frank Lloyd Wright, threw away his calendar for a year and started renovating a vineyard on his property. Today, his Three Dog Vineyards, named for his pets, makes 1,000 bottles of cabernet sauvignon a year.</p>
        <p>Not all his early Kleiner ventures were blessed. One troubled company was the Go Corporation, which in the late 1980's promised the first pen-operated computer. After spending six years and more than $75 million, Go went bust. He also had a hand in the 3DO Company, a game maker that has survived but failed to deliver as promised.</p>
        <p>Many in the Valley say Mr. Khosla most excels at networking -- and they're not just talking about a system for connecting computers. For example, Mr. Khosla met Pradeep Sindhu, the entrepreneur behind Juniper Networks, through Mr. Bechtolsheim in early 1996. At the time, he says, Mr. Sindhu was trying to figure out how to make cheaper routers. Mr. Khosla suggested he try to make them more efficient instead and provided $200,000 in seed money.</p>
        <p>The discussions helped crystallize Mr. Khosla's ideas about optical networking. Later that year, he met another entrepreneur who wanted to increase network efficiency. That relationship spawned two companies:  Cerent, which now makes boxes to increase traffic over networks, and Siara, which is still developing a product. And Mr. Khosla says he is backing several other companies in the optical networking field.</p>
        <p>If Mr. Khosla cherishes anything besides work, which he calls his ''hobby,'' it is his children. ''I still cut my 11-year-old daughter's hair,'' he says, giggling with delight. ''I love taking the girls shopping for clothes. I like to hear them talk.'' The walls of his office are plastered with their photographs, and his assistant keeps a log of how many times he misses dinner with his family. Last June was a bad month; he was away eight nights.</p>
        <p>He often loads the family into their GMC Suburban, he says, and heads to Big Sur, where he built a house with stunning views of the Pacific. Like most Silicon Valley tycoons, he has a trophy car, a Lamborghini, but the car, like his personal wealth, is not discussed. Whatever the accuracy of Forbes magazine's estimate that he is worth more than $1 billion, Mr. Khosla's good life includes annual family trips to Aspen, Hawaii and Deer Valley.</p>
        <p>By the end of a two-hour interview, Mr. Khosla has steered the conversation to what inspires him most -- the future of technology. One day, human thoughts will be downloaded into computers, he predicts. ''Experience is a collection of memories and rules that get imbedded in the brain,'' he observes. ''So when is a human not a computer?''</p>
        <p>He then falls silent, in a rare moment of self-consciousness. ''I should shut up,'' he says finally. ''I don't want to sound weird.''</p>
        <p>But such notions are already legend among those who know him well. Mr. Bechtolsheim says his friend's fascination with the relationship of religion and computers drives him professionally as well as personally.</p>
        <p>''He's impressed by the power of the pope and is probably trying to see how he can replicate it at a high tech company,'' Mr. Bechtolsheim chuckles. ''It's the ultimate leverage.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
