<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>MEDIA: Gambling Heavily on the Tried and the True; Three Ad Giants Plan to Join Forces</title>
    <meta content="MB011809" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2000" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="11" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1165841"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2000"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20000103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9900E6D91E38F930A35752C0A9669C8B63" item-length="327" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>MEDIA: Gambling Heavily on the Tried and the True; Three Ad Giants Plan to Join Forces</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By STUART ELLIOTT</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Some of the most powerful names in advertising are betting that three heads will be better than one -- or even two.</p>
        <p>Three giant agency companies are planning to join forces to create the world's No. 4 advertising behemoth in revenue, at $1.8 billion, and No. 5 in billings, at more than $13 billion. The deal would unite the two largest privately held agency companies, the Leo Group in Chicago and the MacManus Group in New York, as Dentsu, the biggest agency in Japan, invests an undisclosed amount of cash to acquire about a 20 percent stake in the merged operation.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Some of the most powerful names in advertising are betting that three heads will be better than one -- or even two.</p>
        <p>Three giant agency companies are planning to join forces to create the world's No. 4 advertising behemoth in revenue, at $1.8 billion, and No. 5 in billings, at more than $13 billion. The deal would unite the two largest privately held agency companies, the Leo Group in Chicago and the MacManus Group in New York, as Dentsu, the biggest agency in Japan, invests an undisclosed amount of cash to acquire about a 20 percent stake in the merged operation.</p>
        <p>The goal is for the combined agency company -- so new that it has only a tentative name, BDM, for Burnett, Dentsu and MacManus -- to sell stock at some point this year. That is in itself a considerable gamble, assuming that the bull market on Wall Street for communications stocks roars on long enough for a lucrative initial public offering to proceed.</p>
        <p>There is also no assurance that merging Leo and MacManus, even with a cash infusion from Dentsu, will be sufficient to start closing the gaps in revenue and billings with the Big Three agency companies: the Interpublic Group of Companies, the Omnicom Group and the WPP Group.</p>
        <p>''Dentsu is huge in Japan, but minuscule in the U.S.,'' said Alan J. Gottesman, who follows Madison Avenue for West End Communications/Consulting in New York. ''And Burnett is huge in Chicago, kind of O.K. in other places in the U.S. and not really there in places outside the U.S.''</p>
        <p>Finally, there is no guarantee that the cultures of the myriad agencies being brought under the BDM umbrella will mesh rather than clash. They include N. W. Ayer &amp; Partners, Leo Burnett, D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles Communications, the Kaplan Thaler Group, Mediavest and Starcom.</p>
        <p>STUART ELLIOTT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
