<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Spirited Cafe Reaches for the Next Decade</title>
    <meta content="18REST$04" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="18" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Dining In, Dining Out/Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="F" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Dining and Wine; Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/18/dining/18REST.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1310211"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <series series.name="RESTAURANTS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Park Avenue Cafe (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Grimes, William</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Columns/Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Dining and Wine/Restaurant Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Restaurants</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Coffee</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cooking and Cookbooks</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Manhattan (New York)</location>
        <org class="online_producer">River Cafe</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Leach, Richard</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010718T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E2DA1E3BF93BA25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Spirited Cafe Reaches for the Next Decade</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Stylish Cafe Reaches for the Next Decade</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By William Grimes</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Grimes, William</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>William Grimes reviews Park Avenue Cafe on Upper East Side; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>AT the upper end of the market, popular Manhattan restaurants tend to live through three stages. At the outset, they make their mark with innovative, high-quality cooking. They bask in the warm glow of flattering reviews. The chef becomes famous. The crowds line up.</p>
        <p>After the first flush of excitement, the restaurant goes about the business of being in business. It does what it does, night after night, and if the kitchen and management are dedicated enough, the energy level and commitment to quality outlive the reviews, even after the founding chef moves on.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>When the kitchen is on, Park Avenue Cafe evokes memories of the heady days when its chef made American flavors speak with a new fluency and energy</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>AT the upper end of the market, popular Manhattan restaurants tend to live through three stages. At the outset, they make their mark with innovative, high-quality cooking. They bask in the warm glow of flattering reviews. The chef becomes famous. The crowds line up.</p>
        <p>After the first flush of excitement, the restaurant goes about the business of being in business. It does what it does, night after night, and if the kitchen and management are dedicated enough, the energy level and commitment to quality outlive the reviews, even after the founding chef moves on.</p>
        <p>Eventually, most restaurants enter their third and final stage. The performance begins to sag. The food that seemed innovative now feels a little old hat. The money is still there, so the staff shows up and goes through the motions. It's like ''Cats'' after the first decade.</p>
        <p>Park Avenue Cafe, which opened to great fanfare in January 1992, is deep into the second phase and showing some signs of crossing the threshold into the third. It's still a good restaurant. When the kitchen is on, it evokes memories of the heady days when David Burke, its chef, made American flavors speak with a new fluency and energy. But after a decade, the restaurant feels a little past its prime.</p>
        <p>This does not seem to bother the Upper East Siders who treat it as a beloved neighborhood fixture, a cafe in spirit as well as name, where they can plop down on a banquette, relax in a fully realized J. Crew environment and eat sanely reinterpreted, high-spirited American food.</p>
        <p>Mr. Burke, a distinguished graduate of the River Cafe whose classmates included Charlie Palmer and Larry Forgione, now serves as corporate chef for the Smith &amp; Wollensky Restaurant Group, which owns the restaurant. The menu is his, but his place in the kitchen has been taken by Neil Murphy, formerly of Aureole.</p>
        <p>The spirit of the place remains unchanged. The signature ''swordchop,'' one of Mr. Burke's early attention-getters, still holds its place on the menu, a mighty slab of swordfish attached to the collarbone, and it still comes with a numbered tag. The restaurant has served more than 50,000 of them.</p>
        <p>A Mediterranean accent now inflects the cooking, a reminder that globalization is creating a borderless free-trade culinary economy in which pasta, to take a prime example, seems as much American or French as it does Italian. The American flag still waves proudly, but fitfully. Two plump quail, surrounded by a bright red slick of chili-fired barbecue sauce and set on a johnnycake, has a Fourth of July picnic feel to it. But it competes with appetizers like artichoke ravioli with arugula, roasted tomatoes and figs wrapped in prosciutto and cavatelli with wild mushrooms and white truffle oil. Both pastas are among the best dishes on the menu. The artichoke filling is suavely creamy, the ravioli casing firm to the bite. The concentrated sugar and salt of the fig and prosciutto work their way into the flavors with a pleasurable insistence.</p>
        <p>The cavatelli and mushrooms would easily rate as the most sinfully indulgent experience on the menu if it were not for the formidable terrine of foie gras, served folksy style in a glass jar with fig jam smeared on the hinged lid. This is the whole hog, so to speak. The jar is filled to the brim with pink, chunky, dangerous-looking liver, sealed in place with a nice layer of yellow fat. Only one to a customer, please.</p>
        <p>Gazpacho with avocado, with a fierce vinegar burn to it, comes with a crisp roll billed as a shrimp quesadilla, but more like a fried spring roll. It is delicious. A shrimp tail sticks out from each end, making it look like a stylized bull head, which supports the Spanish theme of the dish. Sautéed sweetbreads, not very flavorful and decidedly tough, share plate space with preserved peaches, a tomato-onion salad and an odd truffle-bacon vinaigrette. Many competing flavors add up to one big mess.</p>
        <p>The famous swordchop is still juicy and big-flavored, served with tomato ditalini and lemon broth. It has been joined by a second gimmick dish, Duck, Duck, Duck!, which quick-witted diners will realize is duck prepared three ways, two of them suspect. The roasted breast comes through in fine fashion, but duck meatloaf is obnoxiously herbed with sage and rosemary, and a tall cake of cornmeal wrapped around foie gras mousse has an off-putting richness.</p>
        <p>Richard Leach, the mad scientist whose desserts bristling with sugar antennas and Gehry-esque curved planes put him on the far edge of the architectural school, is still at work. But the productions seem dated now. The pendulum has swung back, and pastry chefs are more likely to aim for the perfect, pared-down apple tart. They taste good, though, especially the cherry tart with almonds and vanilla mascarpone, and the beautifully realized chocolate cube, a thin wall of chocolate containing a solid espresso mousse that you want to move your fork through in slow motion, just for the sensation.</p>
        <p>The restaurant's signature dessert, the admittedly ridiculous Park Avenue Park Bench, really does succeed as theater. With its chocolate slatted bench and leaning lamppost topped by a white chocolate globe, it exudes a strange, twilight melancholy. You almost expect a four-inch Frank Sinatra to stroll over, take a seat and start crooning.</p>
        <p>It's a subversive dessert, at odds with the prevailing mood of the restaurant, which looks like a Cracker Barrel made over by Martha Stewart. Fun American folk art enlivens the interior; green checkerboard upholstery and napkins send a wholesome message; and the hapless waiters wear silly ties with a hideous American flag pattern. It's an impressive display of nerdsmanship. While the rest of Manhattan sweats day and night honing its hip edge, the Park Avenue Cafe sails on, like Wrongway Peachfuzz, in the opposite direction. It does what it does, and well enough, to prosper. But the sassy, amusing restaurant of a decade ago is a bit of a plodder now.</p>
        <p>Park Avenue Cafe  **  100 East 63rd Street (near Park Avenue); (212) 644-1900</p>
        <p>ATMOSPHERE: New American cuisine in a cheery dining room decorated with American folk art.</p>
        <p>SOUND LEVEL: On the loud side of medium, but conversation is possible.</p>
        <p>RECOMMENDED DISHES: Quail with barbecue sauce and johnnycake, artichoke ravioli, cavatelli with wild mushrooms, swordfish chop, cherry tart, chocolate cube.</p>
        <p>SERVICE: Friendly but haphazard and sometimes inattentive.</p>
        <p>WINE LIST: A reasonably priced if not terribly adventurous list of more than 200 wines with emphasis on California.</p>
        <p>PRICE RANGE: Lunch, appetizers, $9 to $16.50; entrees, $19.50 to $28.50; desserts, $5 to $8.50. Dinner, appetizers, $11.50 to $16; entrees, $19.50 to $42; desserts, $9 to $12. Three-course prix-fixe, $65.</p>
        <p>HOURS: Lunch, Monday through Friday, 11:30 a.m. to 2:30 p.m. Dinner, Monday through Thursday, 5:30 to 11 p.m.; Friday and Saturday, 5:30 to midnight; Sunday, 5:30 to 10:30 p.m.</p>
        <p>CREDIT CARDS: All major cards.</p>
        <p>WHEELCHAIR ACCESS: One step up at entrance, six steps to restrooms.</p>
        <p>WHAT THE STARS MEAN:</p>
        <p>(None) Poor to satisfactory  * Good  ** Very good  *** Excellent  **** Extraordinary</p>
        <p>Ratings reflect the reviewer's reaction to food, ambience and service, with price taken into consideration. Menu listings and prices are subject to change.</p>
        <p>SPECIAL FEATURE: A video visit to the restaurant:  http://www.nytimes.com/restaurant</p>
        <p>PAST REVIEWS: Restaurant reviews from The New York Times, with additional capsule reviews by Times critics, are available on New York Today:  www.nytoday.com</p>
        <p>RESTAURANTS</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
