<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Two forecasters predict spending on Madison Avenue should remain robust next year.</title>
    <meta content="Y09ADC$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1997" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="979041"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1997"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Mccann-Erickson Inc</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Zenith Media Worldwide</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Elliott, Stuart</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Coen, Robert J</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Perriss, John</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Advertising (Times Column)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Marketing and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Marketing, Advertising and PR</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Forecasts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Advertising and Marketing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Economic Conditions and Trends</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19971209T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A01E3DB173CF93AA35751C1A961958260" item-length="927" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Two forecasters predict spending on Madison Avenue should remain robust next year.</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Stuart Elliott</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Elliott, Stuart</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Robert J Coen, senior vice president and forecasting director at McCann-Erickson USA, and John Perriss, chairman and chief executive of Zenith Media Worldwide, see 1998 as year of somewhat slower--but still strong--growth in advertising industry (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>TWO executives whose twice-yearly forecasts of advertising spending are closely followed along Madison Avenue see 1998 as a year of somewhat slower -- but still strong -- growth.</p>
        <p>Robert J. Coen, senior vice president and forecasting director at McCann-Erickson U.S.A. in New York, and John Perriss, chairman and chief executive of Zenith Media Worldwide in London, offered their optimistic predictions at the opening session of the 25th annual Paine Webber Media Conference, which began yesterday morning at the McGraw-Hill Building in midtown Manhattan. It continues through Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>TWO executives whose twice-yearly forecasts of advertising spending are closely followed along Madison Avenue see 1998 as a year of somewhat slower -- but still strong -- growth.</p>
        <p>Robert J. Coen, senior vice president and forecasting director at McCann-Erickson U.S.A. in New York, and John Perriss, chairman and chief executive of Zenith Media Worldwide in London, offered their optimistic predictions at the opening session of the 25th annual Paine Webber Media Conference, which began yesterday morning at the McGraw-Hill Building in midtown Manhattan. It continues through Friday.</p>
        <p>The outlooks of Mr. Coen and Mr. Perriss are important because their forecasts, which they issue every summer and fall, are considered barometers of marketer behavior. The predictions of Mr. Coen are typically more rosy than Mr. Perriss's, but the two executives echoed each other yesterday in declaring that ad spending is likely to remain robust, despite moderation of the American economic expansion and problems in the Asian-Pacific region.</p>
        <p>''The momentum is very favorable for another good year for advertising in 1998,'' said Mr. Coen of McCann, part of the Interpublic Group of Companies.</p>
        <p>''It may be tough to make gains on top of the gains made in 1997,'' he added, ''but on balance most of the evidence is that the media marketplace is holding up pretty well.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perriss of Zenith, a unit of Cordiant P.L.C., said: ''Ad spending is slowing down in growth terms, but still growing. We think we've gone through the peak of the current economic cycle. But there are no horror shows anywhere.''</p>
        <p>One reason for the positive prognostications about next year is the stimulative effect of the Winter Olympics and election campaigns on demand for commercial time and advertising space. Another reason is continuing growth in competitive categories like automobiles, computers, cosmetics and toiletries, drugs and remedies, financial products, liquor and travel. A third reason is an increasing national presence among advertisers that had once been locally focused; among them are retail drug chains and direct response marketers.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coen predicted that advertisers would spend a record $198.4 billion in the United States in 1998, an increase of 6.2 percent over the $186.8 billion that he now forecasts for 1997. The 1997 figure represents a 6.6 percent gain from the $175.2 billion that was spent in 1996.</p>
        <p>In terms of advertising as a percentage of gross domestic product, $198.4 billion next year would come in just shy of 2.35 percent, which was the record set in 1987 and matched in 1988. That would compare with 2.31 percent for 1997 and mark the sixth consecutive gain since a bottom was touched at 2.12 percent in 1992.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coen's figure for 1997 of $186.8 billion has been raised a tad from a forecast of $186 billion he made in June. Mr. Coen, who has been keeping track of media and marketing trends since 1948, changes his figures from one presentation to another, based on updated spending or economic data.</p>
        <p>And the American ad spending forecast of $198.4 billion for next year has been increased slightly from an initial estimate of $196.5 billion that Mr. Coen offered in June.</p>
        <p>Among the national media that Mr. Coen expects to draw more ad dollars in 1998 are cable television, radio, telephone directories and newspapers. Among the local media, he lists retail and classified newspaper advertising.</p>
        <p>Internationally, Mr. Coen forecast ad spending of $236 billion for 1998, up 5 percent from a revised figure of $224.8 billion for 1997. Next year's figure is down from a prediction of $240.5 billion made in June; the decrease was attributable to uncertainties related to the economic problems in Asian-Pacific markets like South Korea and Thailand, which had been growing strongly until recently.</p>
        <p>Mr. Coen's worldwide total for 1998, then, is $434.4 billion. That would represent an increase of 5.5 percent from a revised worldwide total of $411.6 billion for 1997 -- the first time it has surpassed the $400 billion milestone. The 1997 figure marks a gain of 5 percent from the $387.3 billion spent in 1996.</p>
        <p>Mr. Perriss offered somewhat different totals from Mr. Coen because he focuses his predictions on major media like television, newspapers, magazines and radio.</p>
        <p>Ad spending in major North American media will reach $117.3 billion in 1998, Mr. Perriss said, up 5 percent from the $111.6 billion he expects for 1997. For 1999, he projected $122.7 billion, an increase of 4.6 percent from his 1998 figure, and for 2000, he projected $128.2 billion, up 4.5 percent from 1999.</p>
        <p>As for overseas ad spending, Mr. Perriss forecast $200.5 billion in major media in 1998, up 7.2 percent from the $187.1 billion he expects for 1997. In the Asian-Pacific region, he said, the banking and currency crisis ''is expected to impact on consumer confidence much more than on the economic fundamentals.''</p>
        <p>Mr. Perriss's prediction for ad spending overseas in 1999 is $214.1 billion, up 6.8 percent from 1998. His prediction for 2000 is $229.3 billion, up 7.1 percent from 1999.</p>
        <p>For the worldwide 1998 total, then, Mr. Perriss's forecast is $317.8 billion, an increase of 6.4 percent from $298.8 billion in 1997. His 1999 worldwide total is $336.8 billion, up 6 percent from 1998. And his 2000 worldwide total is $357.5 billion, up 6.1 percent from 1999.</p>
        <p>THE MEDIA BUSINESS: ADVERTISING</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
