<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Crunchy Menu For a Youthful Crowd</title>
    <meta content="27COMP$12" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="27" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Style Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Style" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/04/27/fashion/27COMP.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1484287"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="GOOD COMPANY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dunham, Lena</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Dolan, Deirdre</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Style/Fashion and Style</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Food and Wine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Desserts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Vegetarianism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Vegetarianism</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Desserts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Parties (Social)</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Food</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Brooklyn (NYC)</location>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030427T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9504E5DE143DF934A15757C0A9659C8B63" item-length="918" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Crunchy Menu For a Youthful Crowd</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">A Crunchy Menu for a Youthful Crowd</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DEIRDRE DOLAN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Dolan, Deirdre</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Good Company column on vegan dinner party hosted by Lena Dunham for fellow students from St Ann's school in Brooklyn; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE invitation was explicit: ''Barefoot formal -- evening gowns, jewelry and no shoes!'' And so, on a recent rainy Friday night, 12 girls from St. Ann's, a private school in Brooklyn, pulled on their raincoats and headed over to the home of their friend Lena Dunham on College Place in Brooklyn Heights, where they left shoes and socks in puddles in the foyer.</p>
        <p>''I just thought it was sort of Bohemian-seeming,'' said Ms. Dunham, a 16-year-old junior whose parents, both artists. were hanging out in another room. As a devout vegan, Ms. Dunham also had other motives: ''I also knew that everyone's shoes would be leather, so I figured if I banned shoes that was kind of making everyone vegan as they walked in the door.''</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a recent rainy Friday night, 12 girls from St. Ann's, a private school in Brooklyn, headed to a barefoot formal, vegan dinner party.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE invitation was explicit: ''Barefoot formal -- evening gowns, jewelry and no shoes!'' And so, on a recent rainy Friday night, 12 girls from St. Ann's, a private school in Brooklyn, pulled on their raincoats and headed over to the home of their friend Lena Dunham on College Place in Brooklyn Heights, where they left shoes and socks in puddles in the foyer.</p>
        <p>''I just thought it was sort of Bohemian-seeming,'' said Ms. Dunham, a 16-year-old junior whose parents, both artists. were hanging out in another room. As a devout vegan, Ms. Dunham also had other motives: ''I also knew that everyone's shoes would be leather, so I figured if I banned shoes that was kind of making everyone vegan as they walked in the door.''</p>
        <p>Feet bared, the guests gathered near a table heaped with vegan hors d'oeuvres prepared by Rebecca Aaron, a St. Ann's junior and a proficient vegan cook. She had devoted an entire week to the food, including four dips -- white bean with garlic and rosemary, roasted red pepper, creamy spinach (with vegan sour cream), artichoke sunflower-seed -- baba ghanouj, mushroom pâté tartlettes, biscotti and two cakes.</p>
        <p>The girls devoured the hors d'oeuvres and talked of college. ''I just want it to be over,'' said Lucy Kaminsky, a senior who is still pondering her options and who was wearing a lavender floor-length prom dress.</p>
        <p>''All any adult who talks to you for these two years wants to know about is college,'' said Sara Rafksy, who wore socks to cover an infected toe. ''You know, am I a person? Or am I a school?''</p>
        <p>At about 8:30 everyone lined up at the vegan buffet. Along with garlic mashed potatoes with mushroom gravy, and string beans with roasted carrots and walnuts, there was ''beef'' Wellington (made with soy and grains), all from Veg-City Diner in Manhattan.</p>
        <p>The girls approached warily. Aside from the hostess and Ms. Aaron, this was clearly a double-bacon-cheeseburger kind of crowd. ''I don't like vegan food very much,'' said Julia Frydman, a sophomore, a bit apologetically. ''I think people aren't really used to eating like this.''</p>
        <p>With her guests seated at two dining tables set with glasses of Martinelli's sparkling apple juice, Ms. Dunham toasted everyone for coming.</p>
        <p>Soon the conversation turned to current events. ''The day they started bombing Iraq, this girl stood up and started screaming that if you were going to your therapist that day that you should go to the rally instead,'' Ms. Dunham said. ''Half the kids were, like, 'That's really offensive!' ''</p>
        <p>Everyone laughed hysterically.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dunham continued: ''I was, like, ah . . . 'I'm going to therapy!' ''</p>
        <p>Dessert was announced. Everyone crowded into the kitchen for Ms. Aaron's vegan strawberry shortcake and vegan chocolate almond midnight cake with raspberry sauce. While Ms. Dunham and Hallie Cooper-Novack danced to the Justin Timberlake CD ''Justified,'' several glasses of forbidden 2 percent milk were sneaked out of the refrigerator.</p>
        <p>''I would like to go on record that no one else in this room actually owns the Justin Timberlake CD,'' Ms. Rafksy said. ''At St. Ann's we're too cool for popular culture.''</p>
        <p>''But it's so uncool, it's cool to like Justin Timberlake,'' Ms. Kaminsky explained.</p>
        <p>The party spread into the living room, where everyone discussed whether to go to another party in the neighborhood.</p>
        <p>''I go to one party every five months,'' Ms. Dunham said. ''I watch everyone get drunk and I'm really freaked out. I enjoy it, but then I don't want to see it again for five months.''</p>
        <p>Olivia Scheck, a sophomore, described a new St. Ann's tradition: charging for parties. ''There's a group of senior guys that will buy beer and clean up your house if you're having a party,'' she said.</p>
        <p>Sophie Pauze, a junior, added, ''They party-proof it, basically. They set up and they clean up, tape doors and get rid of valuables.</p>
        <p>''People have mixed feelings, but I think it's a good cause,'' she continued. ''Their motivation is they're going to Europe this summer. That seems like a good one, right?''</p>
        <p>Around midnight the girls started changing into jeans. ''We gotta bounce,'' Ms. Frydman said, hugging Ms. Dunham goodbye and heading out for party No. 2.</p>
        <p>Lena Dunham's Vegan Favorites</p>
        <p>Meat was easy to give up, cheese, almost impossible, Ms. Dunham said. One year into a totally vegan diet, she has become a soy connoisseur. Besides French fries and peanut butter and jelly, here are some of her favorite foods (available in most health food stores).</p>
        <p>*Gardenburger Riblets made from soy with barbecue sauce</p>
        <p>*Lightlife ground soy sausage.</p>
        <p>*Soy Boy ravioli ''Filled with really good fake ricotta.''</p>
        <p>*Tofurky and Tofurky giblet gravy. ''Little roasts that you marinate and bake.''</p>
        <p>*Yves soy hot dogs</p>
        <p>*Ener-G Egg Replacer</p>
        <p>*Soy  smoothies</p>
        <p>*Dark chocolate</p>
        <p>*Silk Vanilla Soy Milk. ''The best.''</p>
        <p>GOOD COMPANY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
