<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rabies Scare Elicits Clinics and Hot Lines</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="444763"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">RABIES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">PETS AND PET FOODS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ANIMALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">VACCINATION AND VACCINES</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">WESTCHESTER COUNTY (NY)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">MELVIN, TESSA</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Rabies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Wildlife</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New York</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Rabies</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Pets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Animals</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Diseases and Conditions</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Medicine and Health</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE1D91438F931A25756C0A967958260" item-length="996" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rabies Scare Elicits Clinics and Hot Lines</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TESSA MELVIN</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">MELVIN, TESSA</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THREE weeks after the Westchester Board of Legislators declared a rabies health emergency, confirmed reports of the disease among animals are increasing. With concern growing about the threat in the suburbs, pet owners are lining up outside clinics to have their animals vaccinated.</p>
        <p>By midweek, 13 confirmed cases of rabies had been reported in Westchester since April 4, officials at the County Health Department said. Ten of the diseased animals have been raccoons; the others were two foxes and a skunk.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THREE weeks after the Westchester Board of Legislators declared a rabies health emergency, confirmed reports of the disease among animals are increasing. With concern growing about the threat in the suburbs, pet owners are lining up outside clinics to have their animals vaccinated.</p>
        <p>By midweek, 13 confirmed cases of rabies had been reported in Westchester since April 4, officials at the County Health Department said. Ten of the diseased animals have been raccoons; the others were two foxes and a skunk.</p>
        <p>State health officials said the number of wildlife rabies cases statewide has reached a 30-year high. Through May 3, 204 cases had been reported, compared with 225 for all of last year and 54 in 1989.</p>
        <p>So far in the local epidemic, there have been no reported cases of humans contracting the disease, although two dogs that bit people are being quarantined in Weschester, as are two in Putnam County. The four dogs, none of which had been vaccinated against rabies, are being observed at the owners' expense to see whether they are carrying the disease. Rabies Hot Line</p>
        <p>In Westchester, the Health Department has set up a rabies-information hot line: 285-5210. Among other measures, the department is warning residents to keep their pets inside as much as possible, particularly for feeding; use leashes when walking dogs, and make sure garbage lids are secure so as not to attract raccoons.</p>
        <p>Wild animals that are seen exhibiting unusual behavior or acting unusually aggressive, sluggish or friendly -- especially animals spotted during daylight hours -- should be reported to the Health Department through its 24-hour number: 285-5100.</p>
        <p>Under terms of the health emergency declared last month, county residents must vaccinate their cats and dogs against rabies or face penalities of $25 for noncompliance -- $1,000 if the pet attacks anyone and has not been immunized.</p>
        <p>Officials have estimated that as many as 500,000 dogs and cats live in Westchester, half of which have not been immunized. If such pets bite someone, the owners will be given the choice of destroying the animal or subjecting it to a four-month quarantine, which could cost several thousand dollars, said Mary Landrigan, a spokeswoman for the Health Department. Vaccinations for $10</p>
        <p>A county clinic and several private ones that have been set up are vaccinating pets for $10. The turnout indicates that the public is responding to the health emergency. At the Palmer Animal Hospital in Larchmont last week, for example, a special four-hour clinic drew 400 people with their pets, which included at least one rabbit.</p>
        <p>Despite the response, county officials are considering a measure that would mandate the licensing of cats which, because they wander more than dogs, are more likely to contact raccoons -- the most common carrier of rabies. Dog licensing, which has long required proof of a rabies vaccination, has proven to be an effective mechanism for protecting dogs and their owners, Ms. Landrigan said.</p>
        <p>Rabies, a viral infection that is a form of encephalitis, is spread through the bite or saliva of infected animals and poses a serious threat to humans and household pets. Treatment, if begun immediately is invariably successful, Health Department officials say, but without such treatment, rabies is almost always fatal.</p>
        <p>Once contact is made with a diseased animal, "it is important for people to respond right away," Ms. Landrigan said. Survivors No Longer Functional</p>
        <p>"If they wait until they feel sick, it's too late," she said. The few victims who survive a rabies attack, she added, "do so with such severe symptoms they are no longer functional."</p>
        <p>Treatment for human rabies victims consists of four shots administered over the course of a month. Unlike in the past, when the injections were given in the patient's stomach, the current method involves shots in the arm -- except for an injection of gamma globulin, blood serum that contains antibodies. The gamma globulin injection accompanies the first rabies shot and is administered in the buttock. The entire course of treatment is expensive, costing about $800.</p>
        <p>A precautionary vaccination is recommended for people who work regularly with animals, including veterinarians, trappers and wildlife experts. The vaccination, three shots of a lesser dosage than the actual rabies treatment, costs about $100. County health officials have ordered Parks Department employees likely to encounter wild animals to receive the precautionary treatment.</p>
        <p>In Putnam County, a horse that had not been vaccinated was destroyed after it killed a rabid fox that had wandered into its paddock. As a result of that incident, health officials in both counties are also urging residents to immunize livestock against rabies. 75% of Raccoons Could Die</p>
        <p>Although rabies can affect any animal, it is most common among raccoons. Health officials, who estimate the Westchester raccoon population at 80,000, predict that the rabies epidemic could destroy 75 percent of those raccoons by the end of the summer. But the cyclical nature of the disease, they say, could keep rabies in the area for at least 30 to 40 more years.</p>
        <p>Wildlife experts are unable to explain how the current outbreak began, but many believe it is a consequence of overpopulation among the raccoons, which are threatened by few natural predators but can quickly transmit the disease among themselves. The disease can also be passed from mother raccoons to their babies through saliva and breast milk.</p>
        <p>The county-sponsored rabies vaccination clinics for pets will continue at the Animal Emergency Hospital in Greenburgh, at 193 Tarrytown Road. An appointment is required and may be arranged by calling 285-5100. Clinics will be held May 17, 22 and 31 and June 7, 19 and 21.</p>
        <p>Private clinics offering $10 vaccinations for pets include the Palmer Animal Clinic in Larchmont (834-9000) and Guiding Eyes for the Blind in Yorktown (245-4024).</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
