<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>All About/Computer Retailers; Superstores Force PC Chains to Reinvent Themselves</title>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1991" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="444872"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1991"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">DATA PROCESSING (COMPUTERS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INDUSTRY PROFILES</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Industry Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19910512T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE5D8113BF931A25756C0A967958260" item-length="1699" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>All About/Computer Retailers; Superstores Force PC Chains to Reinvent Themselves</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LAWRENCE M. FISHER</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">FISHER, LAWRENCE M</byline>
      <dateline>SAN FRANCISCO</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>For personal computer sellers looking ahead, the future suddenly offers very few alternatives: get big, get specialized or get out.</p>
        <p>The entry of a new breed of warehouse-sized superstores is putting the squeeze on traditional computer retailers. As do their predecessors in home furnishings, consumer electronics and toys, the PC superstores offer selection, discounts and convenience.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>For personal computer sellers looking ahead, the future suddenly offers very few alternatives: get big, get specialized or get out.</p>
        <p>The entry of a new breed of warehouse-sized superstores is putting the squeeze on traditional computer retailers. As do their predecessors in home furnishings, consumer electronics and toys, the PC superstores offer selection, discounts and convenience.</p>
        <p>Unable to compete on price with these behemoths, many traditional resellers are closing their retail outlets to concentrate on direct sales to corporate accounts. Here, they say they can sell their "value added" services, like network installations. But by retreating to this higher ground, chains like Computerland, Businessland and MicroAge are, in effect, conceding the home and small-business market to the warehouse stores.</p>
        <p>"There has been an evaporation of the middle ground," said Ed Anderson, president of Computerland U.S.A., in Pleasanton, Calif., the nation's largest franchise chain. "You have to make a choice: either go the superstore route for retail, or to a much smaller operation offering networking and service. If you stay in the middle, you're going to die."</p>
        <p>Independent dealers and franchisees used to be able to make a good living in the middle ground by offering service with the sale, for which they were able to charge a premium price over the deep discounters and mail-order houses. But the growing sophistication of the customer and the relentless efforts of personal computer manufacturers to make their machines easier to use have eroded the demand for service.</p>
        <p>"All of the changes we're seeing are representative of the fact that the customer has changed," said Seymour Merrin, a Palo Alto, Calif.-based PC retailing consultant. "The customer is no longer intimidated by the technology and is no longer willing to pay a premium for hand-holding."  Supermarket Concept  Will Big Inventories Become a Handicap?</p>
        <p>There are only a few dozen superstores scattered across the country, but each one that opens can lead to the closing of several traditional computer stores. Of the 5,000 computer dealers in the country today, experts expect that by 1995, 2,000 will convert to specialized business sales or superstore formats, while an additional 1,000 will probably go out of business.</p>
        <p>Retail consultants say the most apt model for the emergence of the PC superstore is the stereo industry. When stereo, or "hifi" as it was then called, was a specialized interest, thousands of independent stores served a mostly hobbyist market. As stereo, and later video, equipment became a must-have for most families, the mass merchandisers moved in. The independents that survived, became boutiques, selling high-end products to a small group.</p>
        <p>"The PC industry is undergoing a change that other segments of retailing already have undergone," said Nathan Morton, president and chief executive officer of CompUSA Inc. in Dallas. "All our company really did was to put all these products in one place and behave much like the supermarket," he said. With 17 stores, CompUSA, which recently changed its name from Soft Warehouse, is the largest superstore operator.</p>
        <p>"One of the reasons we've had the opportunity is the existing resellers have essentially abandoned the retail business," Mr. Morton said. "All the talk about retail being dead in PC's is very much untrue."</p>
        <p>Not everyone agrees that superstores are the best answer, however. With 20,000-square-foot stores in high traffic locations, the superstore operators' fixed costs are high, and they must maintain a large inventory at all times. And most superstores, including CompUSA, are not franchised by I.B.M., Compaq or Apple, so they sell mostly clones, and clones do not build customer loyalty the way name brands do.</p>
        <p>"It is going to be a much tougher battle for them than it is running a Circuit City," said Albert Bates, president of the Profit Planning Group, a retail consulting firm based in Boulder, Colo. Personal computers still need active selling, and the technology changes often, which can be disaster for a store sitting on a large inventory, he said.</p>
        <p>CompUSA does offer full service, and can configure computers to meet customers' needs. In that respect it is more like the established computer resellers than the mass merchandisers.</p>
        <p>And now the real mass merchandisers, warehouse clubs like Price Club, CostCo and Sam's, are getting into PC retailing as well. Mr. Merrin estimates that warehouse clubs, which offer no service or support, nevertheless sold more than $700 million in personal computers in 1990 and will hit $1.5 billion this year. The warehouse clubs can offer a high-powered clone, based on Intel's 486 chip, with a large capacity hard disk for $2,999 -- about 25 percent less than the name brands.  End of the Retailer  Instead, Direct Sales To Big Business</p>
        <p>The days when a customer could drive to the neighborhood Businessland or MicroAge store to look at PC's may be gone for good.  The established computer resellers are closing expensive storefronts as fast as they can to focus on specialized business sales. With profit margins on PC's razor thin, they see more money to be made on service, support and the systems engineering needed to create complex networks of PC's.</p>
        <p>"We closed our last retail store Dec. 31," said Tom Pelandini, a spokesman for Businessland in San Jose, Calif., once the largest company-owned retail computer chain. "You can no longer walk into a Businessland store and buy a computer." He sees Businessland's future in direct sales to major corporate customers. Of the superstores, he said:"We are not going to, nor can we compete with those kinds of places."</p>
        <p>Similarly, MicroAge, based in Tempe, Ariz., has replaced its storefronts with "2,000 sales people knocking on doors," said Jeffrey McKeever, president and chief executive officer. "Retail stores got a black eye because as people began looking for more complex solutions, nobody could help them," he said. "It's impossible to clerk a store with highly knowledgeable technical people; the economics don't work."</p>
        <p>One company that has successfully managed both ends of the market is the Tandy Corporation, based in Fort Worth, which is both a manufacturer and a retailer. Tandy sells to corporations through its Grid Centers, which are more like sales offices than stores, and sells to home and small- business users through its Radio Shack stores. Tandy computers cost more than the no-name clones, but typically offer more built-in software and other features.</p>
        <p>"Our object is to not be just a clone," said John Roach, Tandy's chairman and chief executive officer. In addition, "there is a comfort factor in knowing we're going to be in business."</p>
        <p>Another tack the established resellers are taking is to "unbundle" sales and service. They note that 90 percent of the $40 million in personal computer sales is to large corporations, many of which have large internal computer support staffs and are only interested in the lowest price. For businesses without internal computer staffs, they offer a range of services at a fee, from loading software to complete support.  Software Sellers More Competition From Discounters</p>
        <p>Before there were superstores, there were software-only stores, which undercut computer dealers on price by selling in volume.</p>
        <p>"Unfortunately for them, the superstore is primarily a software store," said Mr. Anderson. "What's happening to them is what they did to the traditional dealer channel."</p>
        <p>But Egghead Discount Software, based in Issaquah, Wash., the largest software-only chain, has been able to return to profitability by increasing its emphasis on outside sales and continuing an emphasis on service and selection, said Matthew Griffin, Egghead's president and chief executive officer. "While we are still significantly discounted from retail we are slightly higher than the warehouses," he said. "We believe our customers will pay slightly more to have our selection and service."  BEATING THE CLONES ON PRICE</p>
        <p>"The retail channel will never be the same," said Seymour Merrin, a leading PC retail consultant, referring to Compaq's across-the-board price cuts announced April 16. Responding to a raft of clones with similar features and lower price tags, Compaq slashed prices on its entire product line by as much as 34 percent.</p>
        <p>Computer resellers have long griped that if I.B.M., Compaq and Apple had lower prices, the clone makers and warehouse stores might never have come to be. Apple introduced a new line of lower-priced Macintosh models last year, which have rapidly become its best-selling products ever. And on April 23, I.B.M. lowered prices on its models.</p>
        <p>The result of these price drops should be a leveling of the playing field between traditional computer stores, which mostly sell the big three, and superstores, which mostly sell clones, Mr. Merrin said. Corporate buyers would rather buy from I.B.M., Compaq or Apple, but were no longer willing to pay a 30 percent price premium. Now they won't have to.</p>
        <p>"What Compaq did -- and this is the single most conservative and deliberate company in our industry -- was not just to meet the competition but to beat the competition," Mr. Merrin said. "They are literally putting their prices below the clones. It's a guerrilla marketing tactic."</p>
        <p>One interesting aspect of the Compaq price cut is that the actual price cut to the dealer was not nearly as large as the drop in the suggested retail price. This means that Compaq's own profit margins will suffer little, but it also means that the gap between what the dealer pays and what the customer pays has narrowed. That should make picking Compaq over a clone an easier choice.</p>
        <p>Surprisingly, dealers do not mind the apparent shrinkage of their profit margin; this is because most of them were giving it away in discounts to customers anyway, and they believe the lower suggested retail price will bring in added sales. "It was all vapor margin anyway," said Computerland's Ed Anderson. "The truth is that in most major markets, hardware margins were really only 15 to 18 percent."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
