<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Rutgers Chief Said to Plan End To Separate Women's College</title>
    <meta content="07rutgers" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2006" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/03/07/education/07rutgers.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <meta content="CORRECTION APPENDED" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="20060309T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1744881"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2006"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Dormitories</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">Rutgers University</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Douglass College</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Jones, Richard Lezin</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Koblin, John</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccormick, Richard L</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mergers, Acquisitions and Divestitures</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Colleges and Universities</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">New Jersey</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Rutgers University</org>
        <org class="online_producer">Douglass College</org>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20060307T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9401E1D91531F934A35750C0A9609C8B63" item-length="450" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Rutgers Chief Said to Plan End To Separate Women's College</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Rutgers Chief Said to Plan End to Separate Women's College</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By RICHARD LEZIN JONES and JOHN KOBLIN; Richard Lezin Jones reported from Trenton for this article, and John Koblin from Newark.</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Jones, Richard Lezin; Koblin, John</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, March 6</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Rutgers University president Richard L McCormick plans to suggest merger of Douglass College, university's women's college, and four other undergraduate liberal arts schools into one college of arts and sciences; critics of move say that opportunities for women will be more limited under plan; there are no plans to change coursework or dormitory arrangements, but name of Douglass College will no longer be on degrees (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The president of Rutgers University will suggest on Tuesday the merger of the university's women's college into a larger school, according to two faculty members who have been involved in discussions of the president's plan.</p>
        <p>The proposal would consolidate Douglass College and the university's four other undergraduate liberal arts schools into one college of arts and sciences. The idea has been debated on campus since last summer, when an independent task force recommended the move as a way to streamline what critics have said is the university's cumbersome academic and administrative structure.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The proposal would consolidate Douglass College and the university's four other undergraduate liberal arts schools into one college of arts and sciences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The president of Rutgers University will suggest on Tuesday the merger of the university's women's college into a larger school, according to two faculty members who have been involved in discussions of the president's plan.</p>
        <p>The proposal would consolidate Douglass College and the university's four other undergraduate liberal arts schools into one college of arts and sciences. The idea has been debated on campus since last summer, when an independent task force recommended the move as a way to streamline what critics have said is the university's cumbersome academic and administrative structure.</p>
        <p>Each of the university's five colleges has its own budget and administration, though students from all five take classes together. Supporters of the merger plan said the moves would make the university operate more efficiently. Critics, including members of the New Jersey Assembly -- which passed a nonbinding resolution two weeks ago that opposes the plan -- said it would undermine the legacy and tradition of the nation's largest publicly financed all-women's college.</p>
        <p>Rutgers officials scheduled a news conference for Tuesday morning to announce the college reorganization plan.</p>
        <p>In a telephone interview on Monday, the university's president, Richard L. McCormick, declined to discuss the particulars of his plan, which he is expected to recommend formally to the university's board of governors on Friday.</p>
        <p>Dr. McCormick acknowledged that he was following some of the recommendations set forth by the task force. ''But I'm not slavishly following them,'' he said.</p>
        <p>Under the plan, women at Rutgers would still have the option of living in all-women's dormitories on campus, according to the faculty members, who were granted anonymity because of the confidential nature of internal university discussions.</p>
        <p>Douglass College's 3,000 students could also continue coursework centered on women's issues.</p>
        <p>But the school would no longer grant degrees bearing the imprint of Douglass College.</p>
        <p>Separate academic requirements would also be eliminated for Douglass and its fellow colleges -- Livingston, University, Rutgers and Cook -- which accommodate the 27,000 undergraduate students at the university's New Brunswick campus.</p>
        <p>Plans to merge Douglass College into a larger college of arts and sciences sparked protests on campus over the past few months, and a demonstration last week at the State House. Legislators who opposed the consolidation plan were disappointed that Dr. McCormick had endorsed it.</p>
        <p>''It would be a disgrace,'' Assemblywoman Linda Stender, a Democrat from Union County, said of the prospect of closing Douglass.</p>
        <p>''There's a collective resentment at doors closing for women,'' Ms. Stender said. ''We've made some wonderful strides the last 15 years, but ask most women and they'll say that the glass ceiling is still there. It's just harder to see.''</p>
        <p>Correction:  March 9, 2006, Thursday  An article on Tuesday about a proposed reorganization of the New Brunswick, N.J., campus of Rutgers University misstated the number of its schools of liberal arts that would be combined into one college of arts and sciences. Four of the five schools -- not all of them -- would be consolidated; the fifth, Cook College, would become a school of environmental and biological sciences.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: March 9, 2006, Thursday</p>
        <p>An article on Tuesday about a proposed reorganization of the New Brunswick, N.J., campus of Rutgers University misstated the number of its schools of liberal arts that would be combined into one college of arts and sciences. Four of the five schools -- not all of them -- would be consolidated; the fifth, Cook College, would become a school of environmental and biological sciences.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
