<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>What's a 6-Letter Word for Detective?</title>
    <meta content="OLIVER$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Television" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="COVER STORY" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="880398"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="COVER STORY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Biographical Information</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Television</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bates, Alan</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Bates, Alan (Biographical Sketch)</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Mystery! (TV Program)</object.title>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">Oliver's Travels (TV Program)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A00E6DA103CF93AA1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1377" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>What's a 6-Letter Word for Detective?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MEL GUSSOW</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Mel Gussow profile of Alan Bates, English stage and screen actor who stars in Oliver's Travels, a new four-part BBC mini-series on PBS's Mystery series; photos (L)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE title character in ''Oliver's Travels,'' a new four-part BBC miniseries on Mystery, is a compulsive solver of crossword puzzles and an expert anagrammatician. Words are his preoccupation. He is even more intellectual than Morse or Dalgleish. An academic turned sleuth, Oliver journeys through England on the trail of a murderer, drawing clues from the daily crossword.</p>
        <p>The series seems made to order for Alan Bates. He was not, however, the original choice of the author, Alan Plater. He dedicated the novel, ''Oliver's Travels,'' to his childhood friend, Tom Courtenay, and wanted him to play the character. The BBC insisted on Mr. Bates, as it turns out, with cause. Oliver seems typically Batesian. With his quick wit and air of absentmindness, he is related to many of the actor's other characters: writers, artists and teachers.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE title character in ''Oliver's Travels,'' a new four-part BBC miniseries on Mystery, is a compulsive solver of crossword puzzles and an expert anagrammatician. Words are his preoccupation. He is even more intellectual than Morse or Dalgleish. An academic turned sleuth, Oliver journeys through England on the trail of a murderer, drawing clues from the daily crossword.</p>
        <p>The series seems made to order for Alan Bates. He was not, however, the original choice of the author, Alan Plater. He dedicated the novel, ''Oliver's Travels,'' to his childhood friend, Tom Courtenay, and wanted him to play the character. The BBC insisted on Mr. Bates, as it turns out, with cause. Oliver seems typically Batesian. With his quick wit and air of absentmindness, he is related to many of the actor's other characters: writers, artists and teachers.</p>
        <p>These roles include Simon Hench in Simon Gray's ''Otherwise Engaged''; the title professor in Mr. Gray's ''Butley''; and, on television, the surrogate for John Mortimer in ''A Voyage Round My Father,'' and Guy Burgess in ''An Englishman Abroad'' by Alan Bennett.</p>
        <p>When it is suggested that there is a common thread through these characters, beginning with their choice of profession, Mr. Bates looks abashed. ''Yes, I suppose there is,'' he says. ''I seem to be drawn to things that are not straight down the line. Oliver is offbeat.'' Oliver is a master of tergiversation, changing his mind in mid-sentence and rambling away on tangents. He is a born wanderer, mentally and geographically, and something similar might be said about Mr. Bates.</p>
        <p>He regards his career as ''maverick'' because ''it has to do with what comes along at the moment.'' He says, ''Occasionally I do things against my inner voice, but you really should go for the thing that touches you most even if you don't quite know why it does.''</p>
        <p>In contrast to many of his peers, Mr. Bates has moved reflexively among the media, building a body of work in each field while maintaining his independence and his unpredictability. Theater remains his preferred profession. This summer he acted in two plays in England, ''Simply Disconnected,'' a sequel, 25 years after, to ''Otherwise Engaged,'' and ''Fortune's Fool,'' a dramatization of a Turgenev story. Featured in both plays is the actor's son Benedick. Mr. Bates toured them in anticipation of moving one or both to London and perhaps, later, to Broadway.</p>
        <p>He was on the road with ''Simply Disconnected'' in the town of Malvern. Leaving the theater after the matinee, he was surrounded by fans, who had seen him in the play and also remembered him from his other performances, as long ago as ''Women in Love'' and as recently as ''Oliver's Travels,'' which was presented on English television last year.</p>
        <p>In a nearby cafe, he searched the menu. ''What's a melon boat?'' he asked the waitress, who answered, ''A boat of melon. I think there might be a cherry in it.'' Then she announced that the kitchen was closed from 3 to 5 and she was only serving crumpets, toasted tea cakes and hot croissants. ''Oh, crumpets would be great,'' said the ever amenable Mr. Bates. ''You've got crumpets?'' The waitress said no, and, crestfallen, the actor changed his order: ''Tea, tea cake, toasted please. If we're here at 5, I might order a melon boat.''</p>
        <p>The dialogue was begining to sound like a scene from ''Oliver's Travels,'' which blends humor with whimsy. In this mischievous comic caper, Oliver, a lecturer in comparative religion, is made redundant by his university and casually embarks on a trip across England to find his favorite crossword puzzlemaker, who goes by the name of Aristotle. Stumbling on a murder, Oliver is carried away by his curiosity. He is joined by an inquisitive policewoman (Sinead Cusack), and, naturally, romance follows the mystery.</p>
        <p>An incessant player with language, Oliver says that the anagram for his name is the French word voiler, meaning to cloak, veil or conceal. That just about sums up the character, who reveals little about himself while insistently probing others. Even when he is on the run, he always seems to be preparing the next day's lecture notes, or instructing Ms. Cusack in some arcane subject.</p>
        <p>''It's a nice original piece,'' Mr. Bates said. ''I liked it when I read it and I liked doing it. It's quite ingenious, with a thriller running through it. The thriller is tied into the crossword. It's quirky, but it's also got a philosophy and a love of history and place, a real sense of the past.'' It is the historical aspect of the series that he found especially appealing.</p>
        <p>While searching for the identity of the killer, Mr. Bates and Ms. Cusack travel as far north as the Orkney Islands, with stops at Hadrian's Wall and Eilean Donan Castle at the Kyle of Lochalsh. ''Oliver'' did not pass through Derbyshire, where Mr. Bates lives (and where he was born 62 years ago). He said that one of the best things about ''Oliver'' - and about acting - was the travel: ''It was a great odyssey. I'm ashamed to say that we went to places in my own country that I've never been to before.''</p>
        <p>On the road to the Orkneys, there is enough local color to fill a ''Rough Guide.'' In the supporting cast are a wise old gravestone cutter (Peter Vaughan, who was the grandfather on ''The Choir''), a ubiquitous stranger (Bill Patterson) and the devious Baron Farquhar (Miles Anderson) named for the Restoration playwright George Farquhar, whose play, ''The Recruiting Officer,'' provides the series with a motif. As the plot thickens, the souffle lightens. Mr. Plater has described his work as ''low-key comedy, charred at the edges with melancholy,'' and that is precisely the tone that is captured.</p>
        <p>With an evening performance coming up, Mr. Bates also had the character of Simon Hench on his mind. In the new play, Simon's emotions are still otherwise engaged. He is, the actor said, ''a man in reclusion.'' As in the earlier Gray play, people keep coming to him to solve their problems. He prefers not to. ''You can't lead someone else's life for them,'' said Mr. Bates. ''You can only be an observer and a listener.''</p>
        <p>Is there any connection to Oliver? In the beginning, Oliver is such a noncommital character.</p>
        <p>He thought for a moment, then said, ''Oliver's past is barely referred to, something about a wife who left him at a football match. He's just letting the world be. I know people like that. They've got a strength in the fact that they can survive alone. By simply not pushing life and forcing events, he ends up with the right person,'' meaning Ms. Cusack's character. ''She happens to be rather an attractive policewoman.''</p>
        <p>Asked how he played such interiorized characters, he said, ''I'm not really sure because I don't know how ou act in the first place.'' The director of ''Simply Disconnected'' offered him some helpful advice: ''He said, 'No acting, let the characters come over you, don't reach to them.''' When Mr. Bates acts, the character becomes him. ''I think actors are privileged,'' he said. ''Acting feeds you.''</p>
        <p>Realizing that it was after 5, he ordered a melon boat (without the cherry) and nut and mushroom fritters. When the food arrived, he ate it with evident relish. ''If you ever come here again,'' he said, ''I recommend the fritters.'' The actor spoke with enthusiasm, just like Oliver when he solves a difficult crossword, or a murder mystery.</p>
        <p>COVER STORY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
