<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>We Are Still Only Human</title>
    <meta content="PAGE166HO" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Magazine Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="166" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Magazine" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="880055"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Magazine</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9B0DE5D9173CF93AA1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1054" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>We Are Still Only Human</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Verlyn Klinkenborg</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Klinkenborg, Verlyn</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Verlyn Klinkenborg article on outlook for future discusses human nature and rejects view that 20th century atrocities are aberration in human history; holds humanity is capable of being governed, but largely incapable of governing itself (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>I was raised to be polite, and I am polite, by default. I have learned to depend on my politeness and to hate it, because it so often feels like a hand clutching my windpipe. The politeness that afflicts me is not civility, which is an urbane quality compatible even with cynicism. To be polite in the manner of my Midwestern upbringing is to believe that humans should be judged not by their deeds but by their best intentions. And so I grew up believing in a polite past, the untainted progress of decent men and women tilling a ripe but virgin soil, building stainless, heroic cities. I was taught to imagine a polite future, too: a universal Iowa of the 1950's, but with more efficient appliances and extra longevity and even nicer people. There are worse imaginable futures, and they are all more probable.</p>
        <p>For in reality this is a brutally impolite world where bad intentions frequently prevail, and nothing is going to change that, certainly not the passing of another 100 years. It is common to talk about the 20th century as though it were an aberration in human history, unique in the suffering it has created. It is common to cite the Armenian massacres in the early century, the world wars, the Holocaust, to adduce Stalin's crimes and to name Bosnia and Rwanda as evidence of this century's peculiar offenses against humanity. But only the tools have changed. All of human history has been an offense, of one kind or another, against humanity. What's shocking about this century isn't the evil or the unusual efficiency of its most malevolent actors. It is the collaboration in indifference, the spiritual profiteering of the intentionless masses who are pav-ing a road to hell with politeness.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>I was raised to be polite, and I am polite, by default. I have learned to depend on my politeness and to hate it, because it so often feels like a hand clutching my windpipe. The politeness that afflicts me is not civility, which is an urbane quality compatible even with cynicism. To be polite in the manner of my Midwestern upbringing is to believe that humans should be judged not by their deeds but by their best intentions. And so I grew up believing in a polite past, the untainted progress of decent men and women tilling a ripe but virgin soil, building stainless, heroic cities. I was taught to imagine a polite future, too: a universal Iowa of the 1950's, but with more efficient appliances and extra longevity and even nicer people. There are worse imaginable futures, and they are all more probable.</p>
        <p>For in reality this is a brutally impolite world where bad intentions frequently prevail, and nothing is going to change that, certainly not the passing of another 100 years. It is common to talk about the 20th century as though it were an aberration in human history, unique in the suffering it has created. It is common to cite the Armenian massacres in the early century, the world wars, the Holocaust, to adduce Stalin's crimes and to name Bosnia and Rwanda as evidence of this century's peculiar offenses against humanity. But only the tools have changed. All of human history has been an offense, of one kind or another, against humanity. What's shocking about this century isn't the evil or the unusual efficiency of its most malevolent actors. It is the collaboration in indifference, the spiritual profiteering of the intentionless masses who are pav-ing a road to hell with politeness.</p>
        <p>Looking back over this century, you realize that humanity is capable of being governed but largely incapable of governing itself. Most visions of the future I have come across, utopian and dystopian alike, have tended to look like pure projections of will, of self-governance, not projections of drift. But any vision of the future that depends on the collective, interdependent self-governance of this species is essentially a delusion, for what most people contribute to their own governance is resignation. Humanity is the occasion of its own suffering. It suffers far more capably than it reasons. It endures more readily than it acts. It seems to abide without changing. The illusion of the future is that it will contain things no one has ever seen before instead of the very things we have chosen not to notice or remember. But the future will be erected from the same raw materials as the past, and whether that prospect depresses you or not depends on how you assess our native substance.</p>
        <p>I sometimes wonder just whom the idea of the future is meant to placate -- that imaginary time beyond our life span, beyond the life span of our proximate descendants. It is, I think, a luxury afforded mainly to those whose livelihoods seem pretty secure, who have a little leisure for daydreaming, though it may be a sop for the desperate, too. But the future is really the province of politicians, the men and women who speak so unrelentingly of ''our children's children.'' Who are the children whose children are going to usher in the future? Are they the 30 percent of American children now living in poverty? What kind of future are they imagining? The beauty of making a political trope of our children's children is that it allows you to look beyond the impoverished generation on whom an insufferable present is being inflicted, to pretend that that generation -- already undernourished and undereducated -- will have no bearing on the shape of what's to come.</p>
        <p>There will be no getting out of the 20th century without carrying it with us. You will hear, as the new year in the new century in the new millennium approaches, an enormous sigh of relief and optimism, as though something shameful had been left behind and some deliverance or retribution were now at hand. The old canard -- that he who forgets the past is condemned to repeat it -- will be sent aloft again, almost flightless, as a caution against anyone who is a little too relieved at the onset of the 21st century.</p>
        <p>It would be just as true to say that she who remembers the past is condemned to repeat it. It has become conventional to speak of memory as though it were an anodyne, to speak of the past as though its moral were apparent. But some of the most hideous acts of this century have been committed in the name of memory, and the past, as Orwell knew, is as pliable in its uses as the future. Without memory, a species is relegated to instinctive behavior. With memory, it sometimes seems, the human species has the limited advantage of contemplating its instincts at leisure without being able to do anything about them.</p>
        <p>But I can hear my politeness welling up. It sounds like well-shod footsteps in the narthex of a Methodist church. Where is the good news, it wonders? Well, there are several varieties of good news, none of them transparently consoling. The atomic dust of which we are made is extremely ancient. We are kin to everything living on this planet. In the adaptation of our minds to the universe in which we live there is a kind of sublimity. There is beauty even in suffering.</p>
        <p>Not consoling enough? Then try this. There is no mechanism that will somehow redeem or reform this species within the course of its secular history. Not divine grace, not the progress of science, not evolution, not even the arrival of aliens from a remote planetary system. But there is an opening, a life, allowed to each one of us, an interval of consciousness and action. What is possible is possible only within that clearing, not in some distant future. That clearing is the present, which rolls forward through the calendar, year by year, century by century. Its texture -- the specificity and density of human experience -- entirely outstrips the capacity to predict it.</p>
        <p>Verlyn Klinkenborg is a frequent contributor to the Magazine. He wrote about the drought in the Southwest in the Sept. 1 issue.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
    <body.end>
      <tagline class="author_info">Verlyn Klinkenborg is a frequent contributor to the Magazine. He wrote about the drought in the Southwest in the Sept. 1 issue.</tagline>
    </body.end>
  </body>
</nitf>
