<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>A Great Name Like Eskimo Pie Can't Lose. Or Can It?</title>
    <meta content="29ESKI" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="4" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="INVESTING IT" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="880223"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="INVESTING IT"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Eskimo Pie Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Clark, David V</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Vickers, Marcia</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice Cream</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Company and Organization Profiles</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ice</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Corporations</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19960929T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9502E0D7153CF93AA1575AC0A960958260" item-length="1383" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>A Great Name Like Eskimo Pie Can't Lose. Or Can It?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MARCIA VICKERS</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Vickers, Marcia</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Eskimo Pie Corp, 75-year-old maker of famous chocolate-covered ice cream bar; chairman-chief executive David V Clark has resigned amid disappointment over earnings and plummeting stock price; photos; map; critics point to unprofitable new ventures, such as new line of low-fat, artificially-sweetened Eskimo Pies (S)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THE Eskimo Pie Corporation, maker of a tasty slice of Americana, has had its share of troubles recently. But to some investors the company may be just as alluring as the treat's one-time jingle -- ''Why not try a gen-u-ine Eskimo Pie?'' -- has been to the sweet of tooth.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, some people are giving a chilly send-off to the company, which is based in Richmond. First, there was that bane of the entire frozen-novelty business: unusually cool temperatures this spring and summer. Then, last week, the chairman and chief executive, David V. Clark, 56, resigned amid disappointment over earnings. And the company's stock has plummeted in 1996, from about $22 in May to $16 on Friday.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THE Eskimo Pie Corporation, maker of a tasty slice of Americana, has had its share of troubles recently. But to some investors the company may be just as alluring as the treat's one-time jingle -- ''Why not try a gen-u-ine Eskimo Pie?'' -- has been to the sweet of tooth.</p>
        <p>Nevertheless, some people are giving a chilly send-off to the company, which is based in Richmond. First, there was that bane of the entire frozen-novelty business: unusually cool temperatures this spring and summer. Then, last week, the chairman and chief executive, David V. Clark, 56, resigned amid disappointment over earnings. And the company's stock has plummeted in 1996, from about $22 in May to $16 on Friday.</p>
        <p>Critics also say the company, which had revenues of $84 million in 1995, has neglected its famous chocolate-covered ice cream bar for other not-too-fruitful activities. For example, the recent $13 million purchase of Sugar Creek Foods, a maker of soft-serve frozen yogurt mix, has not been as profitable as expected, said David Katz, chief investment officer at Matrix Asset Advisors in New York, a major shareholder in Eskimo Pie.</p>
        <p>Another fumble: The company's focus on  a new line of low-fat, artificially sweetened Eskimo Pies. While many of its competitors have such products on the market, some observers think the company has overreacted to the threat, and did so just as the product celebrates its 75th year.</p>
        <p>''I can't find Eskimo Pies where I live,'' said Myra Patner, a shareholder who lives in Potomac, Md. ''Instead there are only ones made with Nutrasweet, which I don't eat.''</p>
        <p>Kurt Funderburg, a research analyst with Ferris, Baker, Watts, a brokerage firm in Washington, does not find this consternation surprising. ''Most people who buy frozen novelties are doing it as an indulgence and don't necessarily want the low-fat or low-sugar content,'' he said. ''So if you can't find the traditional Eskimo Pie, you're going to buy a Dove Bar or a Klondike Bar.''</p>
        <p>Then there was the passage in 1994 of the  Nutritional Labeling and Education Act, under which the company had to jettison its large inventory of old packages and print new ones. Given the law, the company's preoccupations elsewhere and other factors,  revenues of Eskimo Pies -- both the real and the diet-conscious varieties -- have dropped substantially. They fell 8.8 percent from 1993 to 1994, and about the same percentage from 1994 to 1995.</p>
        <p>''When you see a revenue deterioration as you've seen with the Eskimo Pie brand name, obviously there's a problem,'' Mr. Funderburg said.</p>
        <p>The drop is reflected in earnings, which  will be an estimated 70 to 90 cents a share this year, analysts say. That is down from  $1.46 a share in 1995.</p>
        <p>''We missed out on some things,'' agreed  Arnold H. Dreyfuss, 67, a director who will be chairman and chief executive until the company replaces Mr. Clark.</p>
        <p>But should investors abandon a company that represents such a delicious bit of heritage? While it faces tough competitors in the $3.4 billion frozen-novelty business, including giants like Unilever and Nestle, some people say no. Mr. Katz, for instance, says the stock is worth $20 to $25 a share.</p>
        <p>A big reason for the bullish attitude, analysts say, is Eskimo Pie's strong brand name. While the company has had trouble,  Eskimo Pie is still one of the most widely recognized and most often mentioned of  frozen-novelty products, according to studies by the Gallup Organization and other market researchers.</p>
        <p>Also, the company has made a bold foray in recent years into the marketing of other companies' frozen-novelty foods, from fruit pops to ice cream to yogurt. Under the licensing agreements, it is marketing and selling well-known names like Welch's, Weight Watchers, Realfruit and two Nabisco brands, Snackwell's and Oreo.</p>
        <p>''Long term, the licensing concept -- especially with Nabisco -- should be quite profitable,'' Mr. Katz said. ''Eskimo Pie is a good marketer and the Snackwell's brand name will be a nice engine for growth for the company.''</p>
        <p>In fact, the license deals have already helped. While they accounted for just 32 percent of the corporation's revenues in 1994 and Eskimo Pies accounted for 53 percent, the shares were flopped last year: The license deals were responsible for 50 percent of sales and Eskimo Pies produced only 35 percent.</p>
        <p>Analysts also like the company's limited role in its one proprietary product, the Eskimo Pie. The company does not manufacture or distribute Eskimo Pies but contracts out those functions to 20 dairies across the country. Because the company has no manufacturing, it has low capital expenditures and can focus on marketing and new development, Mr. Katz said.</p>
        <p>This licensing approach also gives the company's stock a reassuring debt-to-capitalization ratio of 28 percent. Generally, analysts start to worry when the ratio rises above 45 percent.</p>
        <p>Moreover, now may be a doubly good time to buy the stock. Ice cream is a cyclical product, and the stocks behind such products are often cheaper in the off-season. Second, with the year's cool weather,  ''you're buying an ice cream company after a very poor ice cream season,'' Mr. Katz said. Between the two effects, not only Eskimo Pie, but also companies like Ben &amp; Jerry's and Dreyer's Grand Ice Cream, are now trading close to 52-week lows. And after Ben &amp; Jerry's said it would report disappointing third-quarter earnings, the chief executive, Robert Holland Jr., announced on Friday that he would resign.</p>
        <p>Other ''summer stocks'' are down, too; Fedders, the air-conditioner maker, closed at $5.875 on Friday after reaching $7.375 in May.</p>
        <p>Eskimo Pie stock is trading at less than 13 times earnings while the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 has an average multiple of nearly 20. ''Without a doubt, it meets a value criteria,'' said Mary Manderfeld, vice president of research at Heartland Advisors in Milwaukee, another large Eskimo Pie shareholder.</p>
        <p>For all these reasons, Eskimo Pie stock looks attractive to cost-conscious investors. ''Looking at how cheap the stock is now,'' Mr. Katz said, ''there can't be much of a disappointment.''</p>
        <p>Some Eskimo Pie bulls also focus on the departure of Mr. Clark, who had been with the company for 18 years. ''I think everybody saw some handwriting on the wall regarding Dave,'' Mr. Dreyfuss said. ''This management change will give us the opportunity to clean out anything that is not as positive as we'd like it to be.''</p>
        <p>Some people particularly like what the change suggests about the company's board. ''My take is that the board was not pleased with the company's performance and pro-actively acted to improve the situation, which from an investors' standpoint is very positive,'' Mr. Katz said.</p>
        <p>What kind of changes might the future bring? ''Getting the company in order may mean putting the Eskimo Pie name on other products,'' said Mr. Dreyfuss, who is a former chairman and chief executive of Hamilton Beach/Procter-Silex. ''To me it's simple arithmetic. You've got the best, most recognizable name in the world. Why not license it in other areas that fit into the business, such as cakes and candies?''</p>
        <p>Mr. Dreyfuss also said the company needed to reach younger customers. ''What's frightening is that most of our customers are my age -- around 104,'' he said.</p>
        <p>These plans may be hard to realize if, say,  Unilever or Nestle get aggressive. In terms of market share, the three companies do not seem so far apart. Unilever, which makes Popsicles, has 18 percent of the frozen-novelty market, Nestle has 8 percent and Eskimo Pie has 7.5 percent. But the former two are huge. ''They have all the money to throw at distribution and marketing and Eskimo Pie doesn't,'' Mr. Funderburg said.</p>
        <p>But those behemoths don't have the gen-u-ine article, either.</p>
        <p>INVESTING IT</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
