<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>It's Politics, So Everyone Must Be Corrupt. Right?</title>
    <meta content="01DOME" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Cultural Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="12" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts; Theater" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="THEATER REVIEW" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="880533"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="THEATER REVIEW"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Reviews</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Brantley, Ben</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Rebeck, Theresa</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Poe, Richard</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Gibson, Julia</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">View of the Dome (Play)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Review</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Reviews</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Theater/Plays</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Theater</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0DE3D8113CF932A35753C1A960958260" item-length="701" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>It's Politics, So Everyone Must Be Corrupt. Right?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By BEN BRANTLEY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Brantley, Ben</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Ben Brantley reviews Theresa Rebeck comedy View of The Dome, at New York Theater Workshop; photo of Richard Poe and Julia Gibson (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Rage, properly channeled, can definitely give birth to good, even great theater. Disgust, a more passive and distancing emotion, is far less likely to. (Would you rush to play called ''Look Back in Queasiness''?)</p>
        <p>''View of the Dome,'' Theresa Rebeck's new comedy at the New York Theater Workshop, is so steeped in disgust at the state of American politics that it appears to have been written while its author was holding her nose. This doesn't leave much room for the sort of oxygen that lets a play come to life. Instead, what emerges onstage is a flip, weary exercise in knee-jerk cynicism, an attitude that is all too pervasive in this election year.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Rage, properly channeled, can definitely give birth to good, even great theater. Disgust, a more passive and distancing emotion, is far less likely to. (Would you rush to play called ''Look Back in Queasiness''?)</p>
        <p>''View of the Dome,'' Theresa Rebeck's new comedy at the New York Theater Workshop, is so steeped in disgust at the state of American politics that it appears to have been written while its author was holding her nose. This doesn't leave much room for the sort of oxygen that lets a play come to life. Instead, what emerges onstage is a flip, weary exercise in knee-jerk cynicism, an attitude that is all too pervasive in this election year.</p>
        <p>''View'' is the dismally familiar story of a young attorney named Emma (Julia Gibson), a Candide-like naif in the nation's capital who persuades her former law professor, Arthur Woolf (Richard Poe), a man of lofty rhetoric, to run for Congress.</p>
        <p>Ideals, of course, shrivel in the Washington air. Arthur is swept into an insider's circle that includes Geoffrey Maddox (Jim Abele), a leering, power-drunk Senator (is there any other kind?) with a yen for Emma, and Annabeth Gilkey (Candy Buckley), a slinky Southern power broker who specializes in kingmaking and oral sex.</p>
        <p>A seating contretemps in a fancy restaurant (Emma is exiled to her own table) leads to hurt feelings that escalate into an all-out war. Emma turns a love affair with the Senator into an occasion for presenting herself as a martyr of sexual manipulation, a cross between Anita Hill and Gennifer Flowers, and becomes a poster girl for the religious right.</p>
        <p>The play's not very surprising lesson can be summed up simply: corruption is contagious and unavoidable. It is framed with an uneasy retrospective wistfulness, as Emma re-imagines how the restaurant scene might have played differently and looks back to moments when her life seemed more innocent and the people around her -- including her alcoholic boyfriend, Tommy (Patrick Breen) -- seemed to have character.</p>
        <p>The sentimentality is as facile as the irony. An elderly couple Emma meets on an Alaskan cruise are first presented with dismissive contempt and then as an enviable example of a long-term domestic union. (Both points of view are equally patronizing.)</p>
        <p>When a real character shows up (fleetingly), in the form of a conservative Christian struggling with his homosexuality (Mr. Breen), you grab on as if he were a life preserver. Otherwise, there are jokes aplenty for an opening monologue by Jay Leno, but the characters who deliver them are worth only a few chuckles and the empathy commanded by figures in editorial cartoons.</p>
        <p>The production has been mounted with stylishness and a certain bounce by its director, Michael Mayer, and set designer, Neil Patel. And the actors, all of whom play multiple roles except for Ms. Gibson, bring a punchy verve to their assorted incarnations. Ms. Gibson, an enchanting actress under most circumstances, here seems slightly embarrassed by her role, and you can feel her working overtime to sustain our interest.</p>
        <p>Ms. Rebeck, whose many plays include the well-received ''Family of Mann,'' also writes for the movies and television and here takes a few broad swipes at them, even working in a reference to her own screenplay for ''Harriet the Spy.'' Her particular target is a drunken, egomaniacal screenwriter (is there are any other kind?), E. T. Black (Tom Riis Farrell), whom Emma meets in a bar and asks, ''Do you think people are good?'' His answer: ''Have you ever been to Hollywood?''</p>
        <p>Obviously, Ms. Rebeck has.</p>
        <p>VIEW OF THE DOME</p>
        <p>By Theresa Rebeck; directed by Michael Mayer; sets by Neil Patel; costumes by Michael Krass; lighting by Frances Aronson; sound by Darron L. West; production stage manager, Lisa Iacucci; assistant stage manager, Charles Means. Presented by New York Theater Workshop, James C. Nicola, artistic director; Nancy Kassak Diekmann, managing director. At 79 East Fourth Street, East Village.</p>
        <p>WITH: Jim Abele (Senator Geoffrey Maddox), Patrick Breen (Tommy), Candy Buckley (Annabeth Gilkey), Tom Riis Farrell (E. T. Black), Julia Gibson (Emma), Dion Graham (David) and Richard Poe (Arthur Woolf).</p>
        <p>THEATER REVIEW</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
