<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Cable, Cable, Who's Got The Cable?</title>
    <meta content="01PERI$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1996" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Tuesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Science Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Technology; Science; Health" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="PERHIPHERAL" name="column_name"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="880531"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1996"/>
      <series series.name="PERHIPHERAL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Computers and Information Systems</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Dell Computer Corp</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Shannon, L R</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Science</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Technology</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Computers and the Internet</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19961001T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E6D9113CF932A35753C1A960958260" item-length="839" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Cable, Cable, Who's Got The Cable?</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By L. R. SHANNON</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Shannon, L R</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>L R Shannon column on large number of cables involved in setting up home computer, citing his experience installing Dell Dimension P166s, which has 14 separate cables (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>IN print advertisements and television commercials, computer systems always look so neat. A square-jawed man or perky-nosed woman with hands on keyboard or mouse stares with satisfaction at the screen while . . . Wait a minute! How can there be anything on the screen? There are no wires or cables in the picture.</p>
        <p>In real life, there is always a huge mess of cables. The first-time buyer may be surprised; the 10th-time buyer, like me, should not be. But once the wires are tucked away behind monitor and desk, they are easy to forget about. A new computer was an unpleasant reminder.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>IN print advertisements and television commercials, computer systems always look so neat. A square-jawed man or perky-nosed woman with hands on keyboard or mouse stares with satisfaction at the screen while . . . Wait a minute! How can there be anything on the screen? There are no wires or cables in the picture.</p>
        <p>In real life, there is always a huge mess of cables. The first-time buyer may be surprised; the 10th-time buyer, like me, should not be. But once the wires are tucked away behind monitor and desk, they are easy to forget about. A new computer was an unpleasant reminder.</p>
        <p>In the last column, I mentioned that I had ordered a new 166-megahertz Pentium-based machine, but I did not give its brand name. Several readers called or wrote to ask. Today I will give the brand name, but it must be emphasized that there is no substantial difference between P.C.'s, assuming the specs are similar and the manufacturers or resellers are reliable and responsive.</p>
        <p>It also should be stressed that although I bought by mail order, the first-time or insecure or rushed buyer might well buy from a local merchant. If you ask a lot of questions before whipping out a credit card, you can get some sense, perhaps illusory, of how the seller will respond if there is a problem. And always buy with a credit card; the issuer may go to bat for you if you wish to return the gear.</p>
        <p>The new system, a Dell Dimension XPS P166s, arrived in two huge boxes and one small one weighing 93 pounds in all. Since I was unwilling, perhaps unable, to carry two boxes weighing around 40 pounds each up a flight of stairs, I opened them on the ground floor and carried the pieces one or two at a time up to the second-floor home office.</p>
        <p>First went the main unit, a ''minitower'' (my spelling checker wondered if that should be ''minotaur'') about 17 inches tall and deep, then the ''15-inch'' (13.7 viewable inches) Trinitron monitor. Following the clearly pictured instructions on the five-language ''Getting Started'' sheet, I attached power cords to the two components and plugged them into a power strip. That is two cables. Next, the monitor was connected to the tower, with one more cable, and then the Performance 104-key keyboard and Microsoft mouse, two more cables for a total of five.</p>
        <p>Next came the pair of Altec Lansing speakers, requiring five cables to attach them to each other, to the tower itself and to a subwoofer that is considerably bigger and heavier than my Macintosh Powerbook 540c, but improves the tinny sound.</p>
        <p>But where were the speaker and subwoofer cables? A careful search of the original boxes, and numerous foam inserts, which by now were in the basement, yielded nothing. So I called Dell's customer service 800 number. After going through the usual interminable tree of ''press ones'' and ''press twos,'' I waited nearly 10 minutes for a human being. She said sweetly that she would be only too pleased to send the missing cables, but had I looked under the bottom foam insert? I said that I had, but would do so again if she waited the three or four minutes it would require because the boxes were in the basement. Again, she was pleased. So I went to the cardboard box the speaker system had come in, looked in the box beneath the insert, and saw nothing in the box. Then, for the first time, I looked on the underside of the insert itself, and there the cables were, in a slot in its bottom.</p>
        <p>After thanking Ms. Dell, who thanked me back, I attached the sixth, seventh, eighth, ninth and tenth cables. I plugged in the printer cable (11) and, forgoing for the time being hooking up the U.S. Robotics 33.6 modem and microphone to the telephone line (13 and 14), I pressed the power buttons and everything worked, swiftly indeed with 32 megabytes of SDRAM, 256-kilobyte Pipeline burst cache and two-megabyte Virge 3-D video card.</p>
        <p>That was not all, though. The Dell Dimension comes with a considerable amount of software, most of it already on the hard disk and also on CD-ROM's (the system contains an 8x Sony CD-ROM drive), and Windows 95 and Microsoft Office Pro 7.0 require you to enter your name and the product identification number from the Certificate of Authenticity pasted on each jewel box. I cannot pretend that I have tried all the software yet. It is a good thing the computer has a 3.2-gigabyte hard drive. I had ordered it with a 2.2-gig drive; Dell upgraded it without telling me and I did not complain.</p>
        <p>Dell's number for orders is (800) 474-3355. The company's Web address is www.dell.com.</p>
        <p>PERHIPHERAL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
