<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Without Werdann, Redmen Pull Together</title>
    <meta content="3" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="B" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="497745"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <series series.name="BASKETBALL"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BASKETBALL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COLLEGE ATHLETICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">ST JOHN'S UNIVERSITY (NYC)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">VILLANOVA UNIVERSITY</org>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/College Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Basketball</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">College Athletics</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920103T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE1DD1339F930A35752C0A964958260" item-length="494" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Without Werdann, Redmen Pull Together</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <dateline>PHILADELPHIA, Jan. 2</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>The starting center was on the bench in street clothes tonight, and he watched his St. John's teammates beat Villanova and come up with something new this season -- 40 quality minutes from the center position.</p>
        <p>With Robert Werdann sidelined because of a pulled muscle in his right calf, St. John's seemed uncharacteristically aggressive and creative underneath the offensive glass. The result was a 79-69 road victory for the Redmen at DuPont Pavilion.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>The starting center was on the bench in street clothes tonight, and he watched his St. John's teammates beat Villanova and come up with something new this season -- 40 quality minutes from the center position.</p>
        <p>With Robert Werdann sidelined because of a pulled muscle in his right calf, St. John's seemed uncharacteristically aggressive and creative underneath the offensive glass. The result was a 79-69 road victory for the Redmen at DuPont Pavilion.</p>
        <p>Malik Sealy led St. John's with 26 points and Jason Buchanan added 16. But the deciding factor in the Big East opener for both teams was the threesome of Shawnelle Scott, Mitchell Foster and Lamont Middleton, all of whom filled in for the 6-foot-11-inch Werdann in the pivot and combined for 31 points.</p>
        <p>"I thought they played well without Werdann," said Rollie Massimino, the Villanova coach, whose team dropped to 2-6. "The other inside people did a terrific job on the offensive glass. And Sealy, of course, is a terrific player." Finally, Redmen Pass a Big Test</p>
        <p>This was the third big test of the young season for St. John's (7-2), which had failed the first two by losing to Duke and Indiana.</p>
        <p>"This is not the easiest place in the world to play," said Lou Carnesecca, the St. John's coach. "I really just came in here hoping for the best but expecting the worst. But I was very happy. We did a very good job."</p>
        <p>St. John's, which led at halftime, 28-27, broke open the game midway through the second half with an 18-0 run.</p>
        <p>The Redmen were leading by 37-34 with 14 minutes 42 seconds to play when they got the run going with a jumper in the lane by Buchanan.</p>
        <p>St. John's simply dismantled the Villanova attack during their surge, playing their toughest man-to-man defense of the season and moving the ball smartly on offense.</p>
        <p>St. John's finished its run with 7:49 left in the game when Middleton hit a short jump shot from the right baseline to give the Redmen a commanding 55-34 lead.</p>
        <p>In all, St. John's shot 25 for 48 from the floor, for 52 percent. The Redmen also committed 15 turnovers. The Wildcats, who are off to their worst start in years, made just 25 of 65 field-goal attempts, for 39 percent, and were also hurt by 21 turnovers. Praise for the Redmen</p>
        <p>"You just can't turn the ball over and shoot poorly," Massimino said. "I think we're playing a little nervous right now, a little apprehensive."</p>
        <p>Massimino went on to praise St. John's.</p>
        <p>"They have big, tough, strong kids," he said, alluding to the fill-ins for Werdann. "They are a very powerful team. Not only in the Big East, but nationally."</p>
        <p>Foster finished with 12 points, 5 rebounds, 2 blocks. Middleton had 10 points, 4 rebounds and 1 block. Scott scored 9 points and had 8 rebounds and 1 block.</p>
        <p>Werdann, whose success this season has been sporadic, watched the game in a sweater and jeans. If he heals, he'll have a chance to put on his uniform on Saturday when St. John's takes on Miami at Alumni Hall.</p>
        <p>BASKETBALL</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
