<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>U.S. ECONOMY GREW AT BRISK 3% RATE IN FIRST QUARTER</title>
    <meta content="28" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="689980"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ECONOMY</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEADING ECONOMIC INDICATORS</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Leading Economic Indicators</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940528T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E05E0D7143BF93BA15756C0A962958260" item-length="959" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>U.S. ECONOMY GREW AT BRISK 3% RATE IN FIRST QUARTER</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ROBERT D. HERSHEY Jr.,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HERSHEY, ROBERT D JR</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, May 27</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a recalculation of first-quarter growth, the Government reported today that the economy expanded at a steady 3 percent annual clip during the winter because spending by consumers, business and the Federal Government was more than had originally been thought.</p>
        <p>The surprising upward revision, from a preliminary estimate of 2.6 percent, touched off a decline in the bond market as investors reacted to fears that the stronger growth could cause inflation and erode the value of fixed-income securities.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a recalculation of first-quarter growth, the Government reported today that the economy expanded at a steady 3 percent annual clip during the winter because spending by consumers, business and the Federal Government was more than had originally been thought.</p>
        <p>The surprising upward revision, from a preliminary estimate of 2.6 percent, touched off a decline in the bond market as investors reacted to fears that the stronger growth could cause inflation and erode the value of fixed-income securities.</p>
        <p>The figures coincided with Congressional testimony by Alan Greenspan, the chairman of the Federal Reserve, who said the economy was not yet reflecting any of the restraining effects from the four increases in short-term interest rates since early February.  [ Page 35. ]</p>
        <p>The latest figures -- while showing only half the growth rate of the fourth quarter of last year -- pointed to further solid expansion, with analysts predicting a rate of perhaps 4 percent in the April-to-June quarter. After that, they expect the economy to settle back to a pace it can sustain without risking revived inflation -- roughly 2.5 percent.</p>
        <p>"Three percent G.D.P. in the face of the California earthquake and unusually severe weather is pretty darn impressive," said Joshua N. Feinman, an economist at the Bankers Trust Company. Like most economists, he had been anticipating a modest decline, not an increase, in the Commerce Department's revision of figures, a recalculation the agency performs twice each quarter as it obtains more complete information.</p>
        <p>With the quickened first-quarter growth in mind, traders and economists began to focus on the release next Friday of the Government's figures on the job market in May. The employment report is considered the most important single gauge of economic conditions.</p>
        <p>"Recent comforting hopes that the expansion is slowing significantly were undermined today by an upward revision to first-quarter G.D.P.," John Lipsky, chief economist at Salomon Brothers, told his clients. "Such hopes could vanish altogether next week if job growth remains strong. Robust hiring would remind markets that a 125-basis-point increase in the Federal funds rate will not be sufficient to dramatically slow economic growth."</p>
        <p>As a result, Mr. Lipsky suggested, a resumption of Federal Reserve moves to raise short-term interest rates could seem "much less distant."</p>
        <p>Although the growth rate for the first quarter was a good deal less than the boomlike 7 percent rate in the final three months of 1993, it was higher than the 2.5 percent or so that analysts generally consider to be sustainable in the long run without sparking a surge in inflation. This estimate is based on the assumption of an annual rise of 1.5 percent in productivity, combined with growth of 1 percent in the work force.</p>
        <p>Perhaps the most important element in the revision of the G.D.P.  reported today was the growth in final sales -- spending and investment without regard to what happens to inventories -- at a rate of 2.2 percent, more than double the rise of nine-tenths of 1 percent reported for the quarter in the first G.D.P. report in late April. Consumer Spending Up</p>
        <p>Spending by consumers was raised to a rate of 4.6 percent, from 3.8 percent, with purchases of nondurable goods like clothing up substantially while spending on services and on cars and other durable goods was modestly higher.</p>
        <p>Business investment was higher than first estimated and the import-export sector was less of a drag, the department also found.</p>
        <p>But the most startling change -- and the biggest after the increase in personal consumption -- was in nonmilitary spending by the Federal Government, which now shows an 18.3 percent rate of advance instead of a 7.6 percent rate of decline.</p>
        <p>The biggest negative influence, though widely expected, was that inventories rose much less than previously estimated -- at a rate of $19.1 billion instead of $30.5 billion. But while this adjustment cut into first-quarter growth, it implied more potential demand for production in subsequent months as merchants replenished shelves and warehouses.</p>
        <p>G.D.P., which measures the output of all goods and services in the country, counts everything produced regardless of whether it reaches the ultimate user. Decline in Savings Rate</p>
        <p>As a result of continued heavy spending by consumers, combined with modest income growth and an end to a huge push of mortgage refinancings, the personal savings rate is now calculated at an unusually low 3.5 percent. This compares with 3.7 percent last month and 4 percent for the final 1993 quarter.</p>
        <p>The dwindling amount of cash freed up by refinancing is one reason to expect some slackening of economic growth, said John E. Barnds, director of business and banking analysis at the NBD Bank in Detroit. He projects expansion at a rate of 2.75 to 3 percent in the second half of the year.</p>
        <p>Today's report also brought an upward revision in inflation, to a 2.6 percent annual rate from 2.3 percent, as measured by the fixed-weight price index for gross domestic purchases. Analysts expressed no particular concern, however, noting that another inflation statistic in the report, the G.D.P. deflator, remained at the previously reported rate of 2.6 percent. The deflator takes account of changes in the composition of output.</p>
        <p>Corporate profits, in today's first estimate for the quarter, fell $33.5 billion at a seasonally adjusted annual rate after rising $39.4 billion in the fourth quarter of last year. About $29 billion of the decline was attributed to the Los Angeles earthquake in January, which caused insurance companies to pay out benefits and led companies to take write-offs of uninsured damage to their property.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
