<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Advisory Panel Backs Easing Rules For Title IX</title>
    <meta content="31TITL$02" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="31" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2003" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Education; Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2003/01/31/sports/othersports/31TITL.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1461002"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2003"/>
      <series series.name="COLLEGES"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Schemo, Diana Jean</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Other Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Legal</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Education</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Washington, D.C.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Discrimination</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Athletics and Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Law and Legislation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Education and Schools</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Washington (DC)</location>
        <person class="online_producer">Keegan, Lisa Graham</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20030131T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9D0CE0DE1738F932A05752C0A9659C8B63" item-length="1441" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Advisory Panel Backs Easing Rules For Title IX</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Advisory Panel Backs Easing Rules for Title IX</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DIANA JEAN SCHEMO</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Schemo, Diana Jean</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 30</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Commission on Opportunity in Athletics adopts series of recommendations that would significantly ease requirements for satisfying Title IX; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>In a final meeting today marked by exasperation and confusion, a Bush administration commission recommended easing some standards for satisfying Title IX, the law that expanded opportunities for girls and women in sports.</p>
        <p>The Commission on Opportunity in Athletics pulled back from several more explosive options under debate today. But it adopted a series of smaller recommendations that, taken together, could spell major changes in the way access to sports is divided between boys and girls at high schools and colleges across the country.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>A Bush administration commission recommended easing the standards for satisfying Title IX, the law that expanded opportunities for girls and women in sports.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>In a final meeting today marked by exasperation and confusion, a Bush administration commission recommended easing some standards for satisfying Title IX, the law that expanded opportunities for girls and women in sports.</p>
        <p>The Commission on Opportunity in Athletics pulled back from several more explosive options under debate today. But it adopted a series of smaller recommendations that, taken together, could spell major changes in the way access to sports is divided between boys and girls at high schools and colleges across the country.</p>
        <p>The meeting was not without difficulties. Some commission members said they did not have enough information to make informed votes. Others said their proposals had been hastily offered. And one key vote wound up tied when a commission member missed it because she was at the meeting of another committee.</p>
        <p>The 15-member commission will forward its report to Education Secretary Rod Paige, who has already indicated his interest in an approach to enforcing Title IX that would not penalize men's teams. Critics of the administration say the report could provide Dr. Paige with political cover for making changes in the way Title IX is enforced, even if they were only incremental.</p>
        <p>Once the commission delivers its final report in February, Dr. Paige will consider its recommendations. The changes the commission has proposed could, by and large, be accomplished without any changes to the law, but instead by rewriting the Education Department's regulations enforcing the law or the guidance it offers high schools and colleges. Those elements would be subject to public comment before they become final.</p>
        <p>Today's outcome drew mixed reaction.</p>
        <p>Michael Moyer, executive director of the National Wrestling Coaches Association, whose lawsuit against the Department of Education over Title IX prompted creation of the panel eight months ago, called the recommendations ''a great first step'' that would ''certainly stem further loss of programs.''</p>
        <p>Women's and civil rights groups opposed the process and outcome. ''It's as bad as we thought it would be,'' said Lisa Maatz, director for public policy and government relations at the American Association of University Women.</p>
        <p>Title IX, which was passed in 1972, prohibits discrimination based on sex in public and private schools that receive federal funding, as almost all do. It covers many areas, but the commission looked only at athletics.</p>
        <p>The commission recommended calculating opportunities in sports by counting positions available on sports teams, rather than actual players.</p>
        <p>It also approved expanding the role of surveys of students' interest in participating in sports in judging schools' compliance with Title IX. That approach has come under attack by civil rights and women's groups, who have won some court rulings on the matter.</p>
        <p>The commission rejected a proposal to eliminate the use of numerical formulas altogether in measuring whether a school was discriminating.</p>
        <p>Thanks to the one member's scheduling conflict, the commission tied on a vote that would have changed the way equal access to sports was gauged. The proposal, on a standard known as proportionality, would have changed the basis from the current requirement -- that the percentage of women in athletics mirrors the enrollment, which at colleges nationally is 56 percent -- to 50-50. Women currently make up 42 percent of college athletes.</p>
        <p>In a statement tonight, Dr. Paige praised the commission and emphasized the areas in which there was unanimity. These included votes reaffirming the importance of a commitment to equal opportunity by the Education Department and urging it to enforce Title IX uniformly and aggressively.</p>
        <p>The Education Department should also advise schools that cutting men's teams to achieve equality, as many do, is ''not a favored practice,'' the commission said.</p>
        <p>But behind the issues on which there was consensus, the lines were sharply drawn.</p>
        <p>The National Wrestling Coaches Association contends that colleges have cut men's teams in wrestling, gymnastics and other sports solely to satisfy the proportionality standard under Title IX. While he was generally pleased with today's recommendations, Moyer, the group's executive director, said there was ''still more opportunity for flexibility.''</p>
        <p>''We're confident that there'll be a more fair and reasonable interpretation of the law,'' Moyer said.</p>
        <p>Jocelyn Samuels, vice president for education at the National Women's Law Center, expressed alarm. ''The kinds of proposals the commission made today authorize the secretary to make radical and very damaging changes to existing Title IX policies,'' she said, ''and undermine fundamental principles of civil rights laws.''</p>
        <p>The commission was first convened in June, when Dr. Paige charged it to examine ways ''to strengthen enforcement and expand opportunities to ensure fairness for all college athletes.'' Women's and civil rights groups saw the charge as a threat to Title IX, which was originally designed to expand opportunities for women, noted Birch Bayh, the Indiana Democrat who was one of its original sponsors when he was in the Senate.</p>
        <p>The commission voted today on some 24 recommendations. Several panel members distanced themselves from proposals that carried their names, saying the request for ideas on policy at their last meeting in December in Philadelphia took them by surprise. The results, they said, were little more than spur-of-the-moment thoughts.</p>
        <p>Debbie Yow, the athletic director at the University of Maryland, had suggested in Philadelphia that schools split the spots on sports teams 50-50 between men and women, with a margin of 5 to 7 percentage points. Today, however, she said that margin seemed ''too large'' and scaled it back to 2 to 3 percentage points. ''I did the best I could'' at the time, she said.</p>
        <p>Several commission members complained that they could not make informed votes because they had not received any independent or government analysis of the probable results of various suggestions to alter the proportionality standard. They also complained that they needed additional discussion and information as the co-leaders strained to keep the votes moving along. Frustration bubbled over on all sides.</p>
        <p>''We've got to move forward,'' Ted Leland, the Stanford University athletic director, who is a co-leader of the commission, said in exasperation. ''I'm about ready to hit my forehead on the table. I feel like this is the Central Committee of the Communist Party.''</p>
        <p>Other commission members countered, however, that today's decisions represented the heart of the panel's work and would influence future policy.</p>
        <p>Yow's suggestion for setting proportionality with a range around 50-50 came under fire from advocates for female athletes. Yow defended an even split as a simple and logical way of dividing spots.</p>
        <p>Her measure ended in a 7-7 vote because of the absence of one member, Lisa Graham Keegan, a former education commissioner in Arizona. Keegan was serving on another panel, on teacher quality, this morning. Keegan's office said she later told Yow that she would have supported the recommendation.</p>
        <p>As it is, the proposal will still reach Dr. Paige, but without the commission's formal backing.</p>
        <p>Robert Bowlsby, athletic director at the University of Iowa, said his proposal, basing targets for women's participation in college sports on interest at the high school level, was hastily offered as well, and he volunteered to withdraw it altogether. It was voted on anyway, but rejected.</p>
        <p>Current law allows schools to choose one of three avenues for demonstrating compliance with Title IX:</p>
        <p>*Adopting proportionality, under which the number of women in athletics matches their share of student enrollment;</p>
        <p>*Having a history of expanding opportunities in sports for women; or</p>
        <p>*Meeting women's interests in playing sports ''fully and effectively.''</p>
        <p>The panel rejected a proposal today by its other co-leader, Cynthia Cooper, a former professional basketball player who is now chief executive of a sports marketing company, that would have made interest surveys, rather than enrollment, the basis for setting participation targets under the proportionality test.</p>
        <p>But it passed a similar measure, on 10-5 vote, that would allow, rather than require, the Education Department to extend the use of interest surveys to two of Title IX's two bases for proving fairness, through proportionality and by showing a history of steady progress.</p>
        <p>Asked if she thought her measure would replace the proportionality standard, Rita Simon, the sponsor of the recommendation, said, ''I certainly hope so.''</p>
        <p>As the commission members headed home and Leland left the ballroom where they met, he said he was satisfied with the commission's work, despite its rocky beginning and end and despite what he called the inelegant proceedings of the day.</p>
        <p>''All's we are is the first shot out of the cannon,'' Leland said. ''We've made it O.K. to talk about Title IX enforcement. That's all we've done.''</p>
        <p>COLLEGES</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
