<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ohio Bodies Are Those Of Children Slain in 2003</title>
    <meta content="04xbodies" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="12" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="39" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1722485"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051204T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9402E5D61231F937A35751C1A9639C8B63" item-length="713" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ohio Bodies Are Those Of Children Slain in 2003</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By PAM BELLUCK</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>On a desperate quest last summer for the bodies of her murdered children, Teresa Knight searched 650 miles of Midwestern highway and came up empty.</p>
        <p>But word had gotten around: Ms. Knight's children, Philip and Sarah Gehring, 11 and 14, had been killed near their home in New Hampshire in 2003 by their father, Manuel Gehring, and he had buried them somewhere in the Midwest.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>On a desperate quest last summer for the bodies of her murdered children, Teresa Knight searched 650 miles of Midwestern highway and came up empty.</p>
        <p>But word had gotten around: Ms. Knight's children, Philip and Sarah Gehring, 11 and 14, had been killed near their home in New Hampshire in 2003 by their father, Manuel Gehring, and he had buried them somewhere in the Midwest.</p>
        <p>The story reached another mother, Stephanie Dietrich, a cashier at the Acme grocery store in Akron, Ohio, and Ms. Dietrich, who had never had any contact with Ms. Knight, started her own search.</p>
        <p>Six months later, after scouring parts of northeastern Ohio virtually every couple of days, Ms. Dietrich, accompanied by a shovel and her dog, Rico, found the Gehring children. They were buried in a desolate spot in the woods on the outskirts of Hudson, Ohio, in black garbage bags that had been affixed with crosses Mr. Gehring had made out of sticks and duct tape.</p>
        <p>''It was the mother's plea that made me do it,'' Ms. Dietrich, 44, said Saturday evening, shortly after the Summit County medical examiner confirmed with dental records that the bodies found Thursday were Philip and Sarah.</p>
        <p>The children were last seen at a Fourth of July fireworks display in Concord, N.H., with Mr. Gehring, who was embroiled in a custody dispute with Ms. Knight.</p>
        <p>The authorities said autopsies showed that Mr. Gehring had shot Sarah three times in the head and, apparently with another handgun, shot Philip four times, in the head, neck and each arm.</p>
        <p>''I don't think I've really had my real reaction,'' Ms. Knight, who lives in Hillsboro, N.H., said Saturday evening. She said she must have driven within a mile of the Hudson site last summer. ''Overall there's a sense of release. It's almost been like a ball and chain that we had to carry with us, that was part of our life, that we didn't know.''</p>
        <p>On Friday night, before the identities had been confirmed, Ms. Knight said she knew the children had been found when the authorities told her that one of the bodies had braces on its teeth, as Philip did.</p>
        <p>Mr. Gehring, 44, an unemployed accountant, was arrested in California six days after the killings and killed himself in prison last year before his trial. Before he died, he gave investigators a description of where he had buried the children -- off Interstate 80 between Grove City, Pa., and Iowa City under a tree that drooped like a willow and near a wire fence, an old pump and defunct concrete sewer pipes.</p>
        <p>Ms. Dietrich, who has a 21-year-old son and a 23-year-old daughter, said she had never undertaken anything like this before. But she pored over transcripts of Mr. Gehring's description from a Web site about the case. And she packed the trunk of her red Dodge Intrepid with four shovels, a pick axe, mud boots and a flashlight, and set off several times a week.</p>
        <p>''I'd give away as many of my work hours as I could,'' Ms. Dietrich said. ''I couldn't focus at work.''</p>
        <p>Ms. Dietrich said she visited at least six or seven spots over and over again, always with her dog, a Rottweiler-boxer mix, and occasionally with her husband or friends ''to try to show them that I wasn't crazy.''</p>
        <p>Last Tuesday, at the Hudson site on Terex Road, Rico ''kept moving to this spot'' under a tree whose ''branches were hanging down'' like a willow, she said.</p>
        <p>Two days later, she reported it to the Hudson police, but ''I couldn't make myself stay home'' and, digging under the tree, ''I had only to go down about a foot and a half and I hit a black trash bag.''</p>
        <p>In months of searching, Ms. Dietrich never sought attention and never contacted Ms. Knight, who did not even know Ms. Dietrich's name until a reporter told her Saturday night.</p>
        <p>''I didn't want to disappoint her,'' Ms. Dietrich said.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
