<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Army Sergeant Convicted in Slaying of a Female Lieutenant</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="18" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="701009"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MURDERS AND ATTEMPTED MURDERS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">COURTS-MARTIAL</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">FORT BRAGG (NC)</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GRAVES, ERVIN (SGT)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRYANT, LISA N (SECOND LIEUT)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/North Carolina</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Courts-Martial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Murders and Attempted Murders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F03E2DC153EF931A15754C0A962958260" item-length="751" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Army Sergeant Convicted in Slaying of a Female Lieutenant</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By MICHAEL JANOFSKY,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">JANOFSKY, MICHAEL</byline>
      <dateline>FAYETTEVILLE, N.C., July 21</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>An Army sergeant was found guilty today of murdering a female lieutenant who lived several doors down the hall in the same barracks in Fort Bragg, N.C. But because the panel of 12 officers and enlisted people had not voted unanimously, the sergeant was spared the death penalty.</p>
        <p>After deliberations of just two and a half hours, Sgt. 1st Class Ervin M. Graves was found guilty of premeditated murder and murder while attempting a rape in the shooting death last year of 2d Lieut. Lisa N. Bryant of Fairfax, Va.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>An Army sergeant was found guilty today of murdering a female lieutenant who lived several doors down the hall in the same barracks in Fort Bragg, N.C. But because the panel of 12 officers and enlisted people had not voted unanimously, the sergeant was spared the death penalty.</p>
        <p>After deliberations of just two and a half hours, Sgt. 1st Class Ervin M. Graves was found guilty of premeditated murder and murder while attempting a rape in the shooting death last year of 2d Lieut. Lisa N. Bryant of Fairfax, Va.</p>
        <p>Each charge carries a minimum life sentence but could only have led to his execution if the entire panel had agreed he was guilty. Maj. Ken Fugett, a spokesman for the base, said the panel would convene again on Friday to begin deliberations on the sentence. Although Sergeant Graves is assured of a life term, the panel could establish conditions for a parole.</p>
        <p>The military judge hearing the case, Peter E. Brownback 3d, did not disclose how the panel voted.</p>
        <p>Sergeant Graves, a 36-year-old husband and father of two from Omaha, , was also found guilty of attempted rape and assault while attempting rape, charges that have no minimum sentence. He had pleaded not guilty to all four charges, contending that someone else had been responsible.</p>
        <p>The guilty verdicts came after less than four days of testimony, in which Army prosecutors built their case on circumstantial evidence. When the panel's findings was announced, Lieutenant Bryant's mother, Emily, broke down and sobbed. "He killed my baby," she said.</p>
        <p>Mrs. Bryant and her husband, Wilbert, a retired Army officer and close friend of Colin L. Powell, the former Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff, as well as other family members attended each day's session in the small, wood-paneled courtroom. Sergeant Graves's wife and other relatives occupied seats on the other side of the room. At the verdict, Mrs. Graves slumped in her sat and stared at the ceiling.</p>
        <p>Sergeant Graves, who sat quietly at the defense table throughout the week, did not testify, which is not unusual in murder cases because the defendant would be exposed to intense cross-examination by prosecutors. His lawyers were unable to establish an alibi.</p>
        <p>The case raised questions about a relatively new military policy of allowing officers and enlisted soldiers to share activities and living quarters. It also came at a time of heightened sensitivities to sexual relations in the military, following the Navy's Tailhook scandal and the continuing debate over homosexuals serving in the armed forces. Traditional Barriers Softened</p>
        <p>With the end of the cold war leading to the closing or reduction of bases, some like Fort Bragg have reduced operating expenses by softening the traditional barriers that gave officers living accommodations and social opportunities separate from those for lower-ranked personnel.</p>
        <p>Sergeant Graves, who is 36, and Lieutenant Bryant, who was 21 when she died, had lived only doors apart on the second floor in the same barracks, Hardy Hall, for officers and enlisted personnel.</p>
        <p>Lieutenant Bryant's body was found in a pool of blood just outside Sergeant Graves's room on the night of July 10, 1993. She had been shot four times, including once through the right side of her head, with a .357 magnum revolver that was later found to belong to Sergeant Graves.</p>
        <p>Within an hour of the shooting, he was apprehended by military police as he came back to the barracks and tried to reach his room. By that time, investigators had searched his room and found an earring that matched one found close to Lieutenant Bryant's body. They had also found a piece of paper on his closet that identified the serial number of the handgun. The gun was found three days later, and experts determined it had fired the bullets that killed Lieutenant Bryant.</p>
        <p>For Lieutenant Bryant, an honors graduate of Princeton University only two months before her death, it was only to be a short stay, serving in the Army Reserve Officers Training Corps Cadet Command. She had expected to remain at Fort Bragg a few more weeks before leaving for Missouri and additional officer training before starting a three-year tour of duty in Germany.</p>
        <p>Sergeant Graves, who had been in the service since 1980 and was a former member of a unit that guarded Presidents, was in the midst of a two-month stay to instruct cadets.</p>
        <p>Taken into custody the morning after the killing, he was held at Camp Lejeune, N.C., until his court-martial began on Monday.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
