<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Inside Art</title>
    <meta content="22" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Weekend Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="25" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="C" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Arts" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="701107"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ART</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">SHOWS (EXHIBITS)</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TEMPLE OF DENDUR</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">FOREST CITY RATNER CO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">ART INSTITUTE OF CHICAGO</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">METROPOLITAN MUSEUM OF ART (NYC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">VOGEL, CAROL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">TRAVIS, PAUL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">PICASSO, PABLO (1881-1973)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Columns/Inside Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Arts/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Art and Design</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Art</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Trade Shows and Fairs</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940722T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A05E2D7153EF931A15754C0A962958260" item-length="1044" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Inside Art</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Carol Vogel</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">VOGEL, CAROL</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Making Outdoor Sculpture Temporary</p>
        <p>This summer, more outdoor sculpture is cropping up on vacant slices of land in Manhattan, Brooklyn and Queens than ever before. Appearances are deceptive, however.</p>
        <p>While a rough-hewn work of milled cedar or a chair cast in bronze and raised on a wooden column may seem like a permanent new fixture on the landscape, it is often only in place for a year or so.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Making Outdoor Sculpture Temporary</p>
        <p>This summer, more outdoor sculpture is cropping up on vacant slices of land in Manhattan, Brooklyn and Queens than ever before. Appearances are deceptive, however.</p>
        <p>While a rough-hewn work of milled cedar or a chair cast in bronze and raised on a wooden column may seem like a permanent new fixture on the landscape, it is often only in place for a year or so.</p>
        <p>Such temporarily sited sculpture is the wave of the future for cities like New York, says Paul Travis, chief executive officer of Forest City Ratner Companies, developers of the Metrotech Center in Downtown Brooklyn.</p>
        <p>"They provide an important connection between the art world and the public," he said. At Metrotech, Mr. Travis said, he has purposely selected local artists. Vito Acconci, for example, designed a garden close to Flatbush Avenue and Myrtle Street that is entered through a labyrinth of chain-link fencing three-and-a-half feet off the ground. It will be in place until ground is broken on the site for a new building.</p>
        <p>Also at Metrotech is a sculpture by Ursula von Rydingsvard called "Corrugated Rollers," 16 log-like forms a foot in diameter, on the plaza in front of the Dibner Library of Polytechnic University.</p>
        <p>Developers like Forest City Ratner are increasingly teaming up with the Public Art Fund, a nonprofit group that installs art around the city, to commission works that can be temporarily placed.</p>
        <p>"City officials and developers want art for their projects and they think permanent is the only way to go," said James Clarke, executive director of the Public Art Fund. "More and more, however, they're seeing that temporary works can be a good alternative."</p>
        <p>Works that are installed for a year or so can often offset the problem of disgruntled local residents, who are more willing to accept a sculpture they don't like if they know it won't be there forever.</p>
        <p>Sidney Druckman, the director of special projects for Battery Park City, said that while Battery Park usually commissioned only site-specific permanent installations, it had lately joined with the Public Art Fund to install short-term projects on undeveloped land.</p>
        <p>Tyrone Mitchell's "Chair in the Sky" was recently installed behind South Cove. Next month, Barry Flanagan's 16-foot-long leaping hare called "Hospitality" will replace "Cleopatra's Wedge," by Beverly Pepper, at South End Avenue and Liberty Street.</p>
        <p>"We pick an unusual mix of artists," said Ms. Druckman. "We're trying to get away from the expected." Chicago Museum Passes on Picasso</p>
        <p>"Picasso and the Weeping Women: The Years of Marie-Therese Walter and Dora Maar," on view at the Metropolitan Museum of Art until Sept. 4, has so far drawn more than 200,000 visitors, making it the Met's most heavily attended summer show in 16 years. The exhibition originated at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, where it was also a success, attracting more visitors than any show there in three years.</p>
        <p>An impressive track record, to be sure. But not impressive enough to make a difference to the Art Institute of Chicago, which was to have been the show's third and final venue. The Art Institute changed its mind and has canceled the show, omitting it from the museum's impressive list of fall exhibitions.</p>
        <p>"It had to do with the size of the show," said Eileen Harakal, executive director for public affairs at the Art Institute. "It turned out that we wouldn't have gotten the number of works we had understood were to have been in the show. It would have been smaller than the one in Los Angeles."</p>
        <p>Too small, Ms. Harakal said, to have made it worthwhile. In the beginning, there were 60 works scheduled for the Chicago exhibition, but by the time the show was to have opened, some lenders had pulled back, leaving the museum with only about half the original number of works.</p>
        <p>"I think it's unfortunate, but the lenders were exceedingly difficult and the geography of the tour -- going from Los Angeles to New York and then to Chicago -- didn't help," said Stephanie Barron, who is in charge of curatorial affairs at the Los Angeles museum.</p>
        <p>"The Spanish loans were all secured for Chicago, but some of the others were iffy," she said. "If all three museums had tried to help, we could have pulled it off. At the Met, Bill Lieberman and Philippe de Montebello were willing to roll up their sleeves and augment their show. Chicago wasn't willing to do the same. I don't think it was critical for them to do it."</p>
        <p>William S. Lieberman, chairman of the Metropolitan's 20th-century department, chose to flesh out the Los Angeles show substantially for its New York appearance, but these added works were lent to the Metropolitan alone and would not have gone to Chicago.</p>
        <p>Running into trouble with the lenders of artworks isn't the most common reason shows are canceled these days; lack of financing is. But in this case, money wasn't an issue. All three museums had Paine Webber as its corporate sponsor. "This had nothing to do with money," said Ms. Harakal.  Met Redesigning Temple of Dendur</p>
        <p>The Metropolitan Museum's Temple of Dendur, sometimes referred to as the Temple of Dinner for its popularity as a choice party spot, is being redesigned this summer. (But the plans do not include a kitchen.)</p>
        <p>When the project is finished, after Labor Day, there will be an unobstructed view of the only complete Egyptian temple in the Western Hemisphere. The view will be from the entrance to the temple area. The museum is removing the eastern portion of a stone parapet that has surrounded the terrace of the temple since its installation 16 years ago. The architectural firm in charge is Kevin Roche, John Dinkeloo Associates, based in Connecticut, which designed the museum's master plan, its American Wing and its new galleries of 19th-century European paintings and sculpture.</p>
        <p>"In January of this year, we expanded access to the temple, allowing the public to step onto the platform and walk into the first columned room of the temple to see the fine reliefs within," said Mr.  de Montebello. "The next logical step is to enhance the viewing experience by modifying the Nile terrace wall."</p>
        <p>The project is a modest one, Mr. de Montebello added, costing "in the low six figures."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
