<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Oil Is Up. So Is Inflation. What's New?</title>
    <meta content="09mark" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="9" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2005" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Money and Business/Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="5" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/09/business/09mark.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1708438"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2005"/>
      <series series.name="MARKET WEEK"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Week</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Your Money</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Small Business/Finance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Markets</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Interest Rates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Economy</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20051009T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A03E2DF1F30F93AA35753C1A9639C8B63" item-length="520" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Oil Is Up. So Is Inflation. What's New?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Oil Is Up. So Is Inflation. What's New?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By CONRAD DE AENLLE</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>SEEMS like old times. Oil has spiked upward and inflation is back near the top of the list of things that worry Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Economists polled by Bloomberg News estimate that consumer prices, to be reported on Friday, rose by 0.9 percent in September after a 0.5 percent increase in August. When food and energy prices, whose movements are volatile, are factored out, the report is predicted to show a more subdued increase of 0.2 percent, compared with 0.1 percent the previous month.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>Seems like old times. Oil has spiked upward and inflation is back near the top of the list of things that worry Wall Street.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>SEEMS like old times. Oil has spiked upward and inflation is back near the top of the list of things that worry Wall Street.</p>
        <p>Economists polled by Bloomberg News estimate that consumer prices, to be reported on Friday, rose by 0.9 percent in September after a 0.5 percent increase in August. When food and energy prices, whose movements are volatile, are factored out, the report is predicted to show a more subdued increase of 0.2 percent, compared with 0.1 percent the previous month.</p>
        <p>Kathy Bostjancic, senior United States economist at Merrill Lynch, expects both numbers to be ''right at the consensus.''</p>
        <p>''I think the market is pretty much braced for that,'' she said. ''That doesn't mean we can't get some brief knee-jerk reaction, but it will probably take something far higher than that'' to provoke a decline in stocks and bonds.</p>
        <p>The longer-term impact depends on how the gap is eventually closed between the broad inflation rate, known as the headline rate, and core inflation, Ms. Bostjancic said.</p>
        <p>''The real question is: Is the core year-on-year rate going to trend higher toward the headline rate, or will it be the reverse?'' she said. Based on history, she said, it is likely that the lower number -- the core inflation rate -- will prevail. ''The headline rate will trend toward the core rate,'' she said. ''That's what we've seen through history. Nine to 12 months after a spike in oil, the headline number has trended lower.''</p>
        <p>Yields on 10-year Treasury bonds have risen more than three-tenths of a percentage point in the last month. Tamer inflation could reverse that move, sending prices higher.</p>
        <p>''Bonds, particularly long-term bonds, will react positively if inflation stays low,'' Ms. Bostjancic said, ''and the stock market will take its cues from the bond market.''</p>
        <p>DATA WATCH -- After a slow start to the week for aficionados of government economic reports, business picks up on Thursday, when the Commerce Department reports on the nation's trade balance, or lack of it. Bloomberg's poll estimates that imports exceeded exports by $59.5 billion in August, compared with $57.9 billion in July.</p>
        <p>Traders will have less than an hour to digest the inflation data on Friday before two important indicators of the manufacturing economy -- industrial production and capacity utilization -- are announced. Industrial production is expected to show a decline of 0.4 percent in September after a 0.1 percent increase in August. Capacity utilization is forecast to have dipped to 79.4 percent from 79.8 percent.</p>
        <p>A busy Friday continues with the preliminary gauge from the University of Michigan on consumer confidence for October. A post-hurricane bounce is expected to produce a reading of 80, after 76.9 last month.</p>
        <p>MARKET WEEK</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
