<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Justice Dept. and F.D.I.C. to Review Commerce Secretary's Dealings</title>
    <meta content="26" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1995" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="16" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S." name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="739459"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1995"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAXATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TAX EVASION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ETHICS</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">COMMERCE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">JUSTICE DEPARTMENT</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">FEDERAL DEPOSIT INSURANCE CORP (FDIC)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">BROWN, RONALD H (SEC)</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">BRADSHER, KEITH</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">GORE, AL (VICE PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Tax Evasion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Ethics</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19950126T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=990CE3DD1E3CF935A15752C0A963958260" item-length="794" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Justice Dept. and F.D.I.C. to Review Commerce Secretary's Dealings</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By KEITH BRADSHER,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">BRADSHER, KEITH</byline>
      <dateline>WASHINGTON, Jan. 25</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Responding to a flurry of Republican charges, the Justice Department and the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation said separately today that they were beginning reviews of Commerce Secretary Ronald H. Brown's financial dealings.</p>
        <p>Attorney General Janet Reno today forwarded to the Justice Department's Criminal Division for review a recent letter to her by 14 Republican senators asking whether Mr. Brown had avoided taxes or misled Congress. Carl Stern, a spokesman for Ms. Reno, said he expected the division to send the letter to its public integrity section.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Responding to a flurry of Republican charges, the Justice Department and the Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation said separately today that they were beginning reviews of Commerce Secretary Ronald H. Brown's financial dealings.</p>
        <p>Attorney General Janet Reno today forwarded to the Justice Department's Criminal Division for review a recent letter to her by 14 Republican senators asking whether Mr. Brown had avoided taxes or misled Congress. Carl Stern, a spokesman for Ms. Reno, said he expected the division to send the letter to its public integrity section.</p>
        <p>Also today, the chairwoman of the F.D.I.C. ordered an investigation into a loan default by a television company belonging to Mr. Brown's former business partner.</p>
        <p>The White House rallied to Mr. Brown's defense. "I don't know the details of what they're alleging, but I do know Ron Brown," Vice President Al Gore said, adding, "I have great confidence that he will successfully address" the allegations.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown, who has not commented on the accusations since Congressional Republicans began raising questions in recent weeks, defended his actions in long letters today to Senator Larry Pressler, the South Dakota Republican who heads the Commerce Committee, and Representative William F. Clinger, the Pennsylvania Republican who heads the House Government Reform and Oversight Committee.</p>
        <p>"At no time during my tenure as Secretary have I been involved in any matter which would cause a conflict of interest or create an appearance of a conflict of interest," Mr. Brown said in his letter to Mr. Clinger.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown also defended the sale of his stake in First International Inc., a small investment and consulting company, to Nolanda Hill, his former business partner.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hill is also the owner of the Corridor Broadcasting Corporation, the television company that defaulted on a loan owned by the F.D.I.C., at a cost to taxpayers of $23 million.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hill paid off $190,000 of Mr. Brown's debts to various banks late last summer, seven months after Mr. Brown sold his stake to her. Mr. Clinger has questioned why Mr. Brown's financial disclosure statement for 1993 did not show that he would receive more money in 1994, while 14 Republican senators have questioned whether the transaction was structured to help Mr. Brown avoid taxes.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown said in his letters today to Mr. Pressler and Mr. Clinger that Ms. Hill's payment of his bank debts was part of the original sale of his stake in First International and did not need to be disclosed separately. "All payments made to me by First International, including payments made to creditors, were directly related to the terms of our divestiture agreement," he wrote to Mr. Pressler.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown did not discuss the tax issue today, but Carol B. Hamilton, a spokeswoman for him, said that Mr. Brown had not yet prepared his 1994 tax returns and would pay his taxes in full when he did so.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown also did not address in his letters today another issue raised by Mr. Clinger on Monday: that he may hold a stake in another related company, First International Limited Partnership, and never disclosed this.</p>
        <p>Ms. Hamilton said today that Mr. Brown was "looking into it."</p>
        <p>Ricki Tigert Helfer, the F.D.I.C. chairwoman, today ordered James Renick, the agency's acting inspector general to examine the default by Corridor Broadcasting.</p>
        <p>The company told the agency in 1991 that it was unable to repay a $26.3 million loan that the F.D.I.C. had acquired when it took over a failed Texas savings institution. The agency was able to sell the defaulted loan for only $3 million, so the whole transaction carried a cost to taxpayers of $23.3 million.</p>
        <p>"I request that this investigation be given the highest priority and that, consistent with your investigative responsibility, you advise me of the status of the investigation in 60 days," Ms. Helfer wrote to the inspector general.</p>
        <p>Mr. Brown has denied that he has ever had any connection with Corridor Broadcasting, and he did so again today in his letters to the Republican committee chairmen.</p>
        <p>Congressional scrutiny has been growing since the disclosure on Monday that Mr. Brown's former investment and consulting company had owned an $875,000 promissory note from Corridor and continued to receive $12,000 a month in interest and principal from Corridor after the television company defaulted on the loan held by the F.D.I.C.</p>
        <p>Barbara S. Fredericks, an assistant general counsel at the Commerce Department, who has handled Mr. Brown's conflict-of-interest issues, said in an interview on Monday that she had tried to learn from Mr. Brown and his associates last year whether there was any link between First International and Corridor, but that no one had told her about the note.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
