<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>More Women, More Cash In Legislative Campaigns</title>
    <meta content="30" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="10" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1993" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Saturday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Metropolitan Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="645649"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1993"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">FINANCES</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">ELECTIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">LEGISLATURES AND PARLIAMENTS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">WOMEN</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">NEW JERSEY</location>
        <org class="indexing_service">DEMOCRATIC PARTY</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">REPUBLICAN PARTY</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">SULLIVAN, JOSEPH F</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2004/States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/New Jersey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Legislatures and Parliaments</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Women</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Elections</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19931030T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9F0CE5D61E39F933A05753C1A965958260" item-length="823" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>More Women, More Cash In Legislative Campaigns</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By JOSEPH F. SULLIVAN,</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">SULLIVAN, JOSEPH F</byline>
      <dateline>TRENTON, Oct. 29</dateline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Used for years as cannon fodder in hopeless election campaigns and denied nominations in races they could win, this year women are making a determined effort to get through the doors of the New Jersey Legislature, armed with one of the basic weapons of politics: money.</p>
        <p>Now there are only 14 women in the 120-member New Jersey Legislature, several of them Republicans who were transformed from sacrificial lambs to lawmakers in the tax-revolt landslide in 1991 when there were no safe districts for Democrats.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Used for years as cannon fodder in hopeless election campaigns and denied nominations in races they could win, this year women are making a determined effort to get through the doors of the New Jersey Legislature, armed with one of the basic weapons of politics: money.</p>
        <p>Now there are only 14 women in the 120-member New Jersey Legislature, several of them Republicans who were transformed from sacrificial lambs to lawmakers in the tax-revolt landslide in 1991 when there were no safe districts for Democrats.</p>
        <p>This year there are 24 Democratic women running for the Senate and Assembly -- a record -- and 15 Republican women. Close to $100,000 of the money that will be spent on their races will come from state and Federal women's groups that only began to focus on fund-raising as the key to political power in the late 1980's.</p>
        <p>"This state has a lot of highly intelligent, highly educated women who are not tuned into politics," said Kathleen Daly, one of the founding members of Pam's List, a Democratic organization whose name is an acronym for Power and Money. "And there are a lot of women who are interested but who won't write a check or raise money." Updated 90's Group</p>
        <p>"They say they'll lick the envelopes and make the telephone calls but that raising money is man's work." she said. "Because we don't raise money we have no leverage in primary elections."</p>
        <p>Hazel Gluck, who is co-chairwoman of Christine Todd Whitman's campaign for governor, helped found a New Jersey organization called Republican Women of the 80's about 10 years ago. "We began raising money in about 1987 and '88 for legislative and key freeholder and mayoral races," she said. This year the updated 90's group raised $30,000 to help elect Republican women in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>While women are doing a better job raising money, Ms. Gluck said, "It's very tough and when a seat opens up, a woman faces a lineup of guys who feel they've paid their dues."</p>
        <p>Democratic women, meanwhile, are getting help from Senator Bill Bradley. In September he dedicated a weekend to making appearances with all the Democratic women seeking legislative seats, attending fund-raising events in private homes, restaurants and a bowling alley for some and walking neighborhoods or visiting schools with others. Worked With Florio</p>
        <p>"New Jersey ranks 41st in the country in terms of the number of women in the Legislature, and I want to help change that," he said, adding: "Democrats have to lead the way and see that the number of women in the Legislature is more reflective of their numbers in society."</p>
        <p>In mid-October Mr. Bradley campaigned for Pat Royer of Clifton, who was director of consumer affairs for the Florio administration in 1990 and 1991. Mrs. Royer is seeking to unseat Senator Joseph L. Bubba of Wayne, a 12-year legislative veteran who lost a hard-fought campaign for Congress last year to Herbert C. Klein, a Democrat.</p>
        <p>Winning the nomination was not easy, she said. "People were asking me 'Are you tough enough?' " to run against Mr. Bubba, she said. "Well, with two weeks to go, we've gone toe to toe and I'm still here." National Group Financing</p>
        <p>The Pam's List organization, which was founded in 1989, is modeled after Emily's List, the Washington-based Democratic fund-raising committee that raised $6.2 million in 1992. The organization, whose name is an acronym for Early Money Is Like Yeast, contributes to campaigns of Democratic women, including those running for Congress and state legislatures. The only criteria is that the women support a woman's right to choose an abortion and that they have a chance to win their election.</p>
        <p>Mary Beth Cahill, the political director of Emily's List, said $4,500 had been contributed to nine women running in New Jersey Democratic races. "We saw what was potentially a very hot race for governor in New Jersey that would generate great voter interest and provide an opportunity for women to win some legislative seats," she said.</p>
        <p>Pam's List, which has the same requirements for financing, is focusing on the campaigns of 11 candidates in New Jersey.</p>
        <p>Sisters United, a New Jersey organization that supports the candidacies of Democratic black women, grew out of fund-raising efforts for the Clinton-Gore ticket last year. Jackie Thomas, the president, said her group, working with Pam's List, helped raise $100,000 for the Presidential race last year.</p>
        <p>Peggy Anastos, the head of the Hispanic Women's Task Force of the State Democratic Committee, said that over the last two years state Democratic leaders have welcomed women as candidates, not just campaign workers, doing "an excellent job involving us in discussing finances, strategy and the overall campaign game plan before any decisions are made." As a member of the party's Women's Task Force and the leader of the Hispanic Women's Task Force, she said, "I receive the dignity I deserve, and it's not a form of tokenism."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
