<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Devils Beat Revamped Islanders</title>
    <meta content="T08ISLE" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="2" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Sports Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="9" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Sports" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="993982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <series series.name="HOCKEY"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">New Jersey Devils</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">New York Islanders</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">El-Bashir, Tarik</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./Mid-Atlantic</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New Jersey Devils</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey/National Hockey League/New York Islanders</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Sports/Hockey</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Hockey, Ice</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980208T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9A02E1D9113DF93BA35751C0A96E958260" item-length="742" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Devils Beat Revamped Islanders</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By TARIK EL-BASHIR</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">El-Bashir, Tarik</byline>
      <dateline>UNIONDALE, N.Y., Feb. 7</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>New Jersey Devils defeat New York Islanders, 3-2; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Friday was a busy day for Islanders General Manager Mike Milbury. He traded four players, a minor leaguer and a third-round draft pick for four players in deals with two teams. By the day's end, Milbury said he felt that the Islanders were a vastly improved team.</p>
        <p>Maybe, but they were not good enough to earn a victory against the Devils today. After dominating the first period, the Islanders faded in the second and third periods and lost, 3-2, at Nassau Coliseum. The Devils have beaten the Islanders in all four meetings this season.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Friday was a busy day for Islanders General Manager Mike Milbury. He traded four players, a minor leaguer and a third-round draft pick for four players in deals with two teams. By the day's end, Milbury said he felt that the Islanders were a vastly improved team.</p>
        <p>Maybe, but they were not good enough to earn a victory against the Devils today. After dominating the first period, the Islanders faded in the second and third periods and lost, 3-2, at Nassau Coliseum. The Devils have beaten the Islanders in all four meetings this season.</p>
        <p>Today's game was the last for both teams before the 17-day break for the Olympics.</p>
        <p>Martin Brodeur had much to do with the Devils' success, as usual. He made 33 saves, including a couple of spectacular stops in the final two minutes to insure the Devils' third straight victory.</p>
        <p>''Today it was Brodeur,'' Islanders Coach Rick Bowness said. ''He was sensational.''</p>
        <p>The Islanders, skating with two of their four new players, played perhaps their best 20 minutes of the season at the start of today's game.</p>
        <p>Relying on the skill of Zigmund Palffy, who scored the Islanders' second goal, the speed of the newly acquired Joe Sacco, and the goaltending of Tommy Salo, the Islanders outshot the Devils by 12-6 in the first period and took a 1-0 lead on a goal by Kip Miller.</p>
        <p>Miller, who was called up from Utah of the International Hockey League on Friday night, beat Brodeur with a slap shot inside the far post 5 minutes and 51 seconds into the game.</p>
        <p>But the Devils quickly re-established themselves, tying the game at 1-1 on a goal by the rookie Patrik Elias at 1:26. Elias, who leads all rookies in goals with 15, knocked a rebound past Salo, who lay prone after making saves on Scott Neidermayer and Doug Gilmour.</p>
        <p>Doug Bodger and Brian Rolston scored the Devils' other goals.  Bodger scored at 17:17 of the second period after the Islanders twice failed to clear the puck out of their end. He was fed the puck by Dave Andreychuk, skated in from the blue line and fired the puck past Salo.  Rolston scored at 3:40 of the third period on a wrist shot from the top of the left circle, with Salo screened.  Palffy's goal, his 30th, came at 15:29 from the right circle, beating Brodeur under his glove. Brodeur foiled the rest of the Islanders' attempts.</p>
        <p>In the Islanders' first deal on Friday, Milbury sent Bryan McCabe, Todd Bertuzzi and the draft pick to the Vancouver Canucks for forward Trevor Linden. In the second deal, he sent Travis Green, Doug Houda and the minor leaguer Tony Tuzzolino to Anaheim for Sacco, center Mark Janssens and defenseman J.J. Daigneault.</p>
        <p>Linden, who had not played in the Canucks' last six games because of a sprained knee, will not join the Islanders until after the Olympics, in which he will play for Team Canada. When he was announced as a scratch today, he received a loud welcome from the capacity Coliseum crowd. Daigneault, who was not reached in time to leave for New York on Friday, also did not play.</p>
        <p>Sacco, a right wing, created several scoring chances for himself today, and Janssens was a force in the face-off circle.</p>
        <p>''When you get three or four new guys, you're not as sharp,'' Devils Coach Jacques Lemaire said. ''But in a matter of time, they will adjust.''</p>
        <p>In addition to the Islanders' latest improvements, there were hints today from both Milbury and the prospective co-owner Steven Gluckstern that Detroit's unsigned free agent Sergei Fedorov is still in the Islanders' plans.</p>
        <p>''I'd still like to have a very talented center,'' Milbury said. But he said none of the trades made on Friday were made in the hopes of eventually reaching a deal with the Red Wings for Fedorov.</p>
        <p>SLAP SHOTS</p>
        <p>Devils defenseman KEN DANEYKO was cleared by the National Hockey League yesterday to return to play following alcohol rehabilitation. Daneyko, who resumed working out with the team Tuesday, is expected to return to action after the Olympic break.</p>
        <p>HOCKEY</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
