<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Channel Executive Seeks to Build Showtime's Slate of Original Fare</title>
    <meta content="29" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="8" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1994" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Monday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="6" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="Correction Appended" name="banner"/>
    <meta content="19940831T000000" name="correction_date"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="709086"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1994"/>
      <series series.name="THE MEDIA BUSINESS"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">TELEVISION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">BIOGRAPHICAL INFORMATION</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">CABLE TELEVISION</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">SHOWTIME ENTERTAINMENT GROUP</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">HORNADAY, ANN</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">HEWITT, STEVEN</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Media and Advertising</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Media, Entertainment and Publishing</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Cable Television</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Television</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19940829T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503E7DF1F39F93AA1575BC0A962958260" item-length="1251" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Channel Executive Seeks to Build Showtime's Slate of Original Fare</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ANN HORNADAY</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">HORNADAY, ANN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>It's not easy competing with HBO, the cable colossus that perennially boasts the most subscribers, critical acclaim and Emmy Awards among premium channels. But Steven Hewitt says he intends to have fun trying.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hewitt was promoted in May to executive vice president of the Showtime Entertainment Group, the original-programming unit of Showtime Networks Inc. While the channel's staples will continue to be theatrical movies, shown without commercials, Mr. Hewitt's mandate is to raise the channel's profile as a producer of "made for Showtime" films.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>It's not easy competing with HBO, the cable colossus that perennially boasts the most subscribers, critical acclaim and Emmy Awards among premium channels. But Steven Hewitt says he intends to have fun trying.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hewitt was promoted in May to executive vice president of the Showtime Entertainment Group, the original-programming unit of Showtime Networks Inc. While the channel's staples will continue to be theatrical movies, shown without commercials, Mr. Hewitt's mandate is to raise the channel's profile as a producer of "made for Showtime" films.</p>
        <p>"Maybe we don't have a position to protect, so we have more freedom to find the position," Mr. Hewitt said of Showtime's bridesmaid status. "When we find that position, we'll end up having to protect it, and we'll get boring. For now, the sky's the limit here. We can go anywhere." A Negotiating Tool</p>
        <p>Larry Gerbrandt, senior vice president at Paul Kagan Associates, a media research firm, said original programming was important in helping to define a channel's brand identity and in negotiating with Hollywood studios to run their theatrical films.</p>
        <p>"If you're able to produce some of your own programming, you're in a much better position with the studios," he said, referring to the way prices for films are set, "rather than being totally dependent on them for 100 percent of your product."</p>
        <p>For Showtime, a unit of Viacom Inc., there are other bottom-line reasons to create more original programming. Movies can be repackaged for sale in the home-video market, and other television networks or individual stations may buy the rights to rerun them after they have been on Showtime.</p>
        <p>And occasionally a film made for cable ends up in theaters, where it generates more profit. "Hearts of Darkness," Eleanor Coppola's documentary about the arduous making of the movie "Apocalypse Now," ended up on many film critics' "10 best" lists for 1991, but it was originally made for and shown by Showtime.</p>
        <p>Last year Showtime committed $100 million to original programming, up 25 percent from the previous year, and further increases are expected to be announced soon.</p>
        <p>Mr. Hewitt, who is 46, learned a few things about the pay-cable business from HBO. He arrived there as a sports producer in 1976 (the same year Showtime was started) from the Teleprompter Corporation.</p>
        <p>At HBO, Mr. Hewitt created the on-air promotion department and helped design the channel's "interstitial" programming -- the promotions and other odds and ends that fill time between scheduled events.</p>
        <p>In 1978, Mr. Hewitt became director of on-air promotion, then director of specials, for CBS Entertainment. He returned briefly to HBO in 1984, but jumped to Showtime two years later.</p>
        <p>Recalling his parting conversation with the head of HBO, Mr. Hewitt said, "Michael Fuchs said to me, 'Steven, you understand that you're leaving a flat on Fifth Avenue to take a much larger apartment in a bad neighborhood?' "</p>
        <p>"And I thought, 'I want to spread my wings. So, I'll take the larger apartment, and we'll renovate the neighborhood,' " Mr. Hewitt said.</p>
        <p>The renovation continues, and some big-name contractors have been brought in. As part of a slate of 15 original movies to be shown this year, for example, Showtime presented "Lush Life," starring Forest Whitaker and Jeff Goldblum. "Down Came a Blackbird," a Showtime film about the rehabilitation of torture victims starring Raul Julia, Vanessa Redgrave and Laura Dern, will start filming next month in Toronto.</p>
        <p>Other stars -- Tom Hanks, for one -- have been persuaded to take Showtime projects because the channel gave them their first chance to direct a film. Because Showtime clearly cannot win bidding wars with HBO, the channel tries to portray itself as less intrusive than HBO, whose executives have traditionally had a strong say in scripts and casting. A Creative Interest</p>
        <p>And yet Mr. Hewitt is described by many who work with him as an unusually creative executive whose active participation often helped to improve a project. George Zaloom, the producer of "Hearts of Darkness," recalled Mr. Hewitt's suggestion that the film focus more strongly on the director of "Apocalypse Now," Francis Ford Coppola, who had taken Joseph Conrad's "Heart of Darkness" as his starting point.</p>
        <p>"The original story, Francis's story and the making of the film all seemed to mirror each other," Mr. Zaloom said, "and Steve pointed us in that direction."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hewitt, who is the son of Don Hewitt, the executive producer of "60 Minutes," said he originally set out to be an artist. "There was never a moment where I would have considered being in news, because I knew from a very early age that my father was something very different and special," Mr. Hewitt said. "His footprint was like a dinosaur's footprint: you can't walk in it, you just fall in it."</p>
        <p>As a teen-ager, Mr. Hewitt acted in a few television series and commercials. As a member of the first class at the North Carolina School of the Arts in Winston-Salem, Mr. Hewitt said he "learned that I could never be an actor, but I had this great love for cameras."</p>
        <p>So in 1969 Mr. Hewitt and his wife, Pamela, a classical pianist, moved to Manhattan, where he got a job with Teleprompter, then the country's largest cable television company.</p>
        <p>"There is an assumption that because my dad's Don Hewitt that I automatically stepped into where I am," he said, "even though I began as a cameraman trainee in cable TV, which barely existed in 1969. To make ends meet, my wife and I were the supers of a building at 94th Street and Second Avenue."</p>
        <p>Mr. Hewitt's penchant for involving himself creatively in Showtime's projects may have resulted in at least one problem: He is renowned for not returning telephone calls, a habit that some say has caused him to miss opportunities and alienate some important writers and producers.</p>
        <p>"What they don't realize," he said, "is that they are dealing with someone who is not a robot, whose claim to fame is not that he can return 150 phone calls a day. In fact, I might be sitting in the editing room, or sitting with talent, or talking with writers maybe longer than I should."</p>
        <p>For Viacom, Showtime has been "a marginal performer," Mr. Gerbrandt said. "They're in the black, but only marginally so."</p>
        <p>In the second quarter that ended on June 30, the channel reported $9.1 million in earnings on $143.4 million in revenue, said Bill Marchetti, an cable industry analyst for Mr. Gerbrandt's firm. In the comparable quarter a year earlier, the channel posted $8 million in earnings on $141.5 million in revenue.</p>
        <p>While Showtime has more subscribers than ever, with 11.9 million (a figure that includes subscribers to Showtime's smaller sibling, the Movie Channel), each of whom pays $7 to $10 a month, HBO still leads handily with 18 million.</p>
        <p>Are those subscribers really paying to see original programming, or are they primarily interested in seeing big-budget Hollywood fare like "The Bodyguard" or "Basic Instinct"?</p>
        <p>In fact, Mr. Hewitt said, viewers like both categories. "When I first began, the theatrical film was absolutely the selling point and king of premium cable," he said. "The blockbusters that do $50-million-plus at the box office continue to perform beautifully on premium."</p>
        <p>But most Hollywood movies are not blockbusters, he added. "If you take the average rating of films acquired from studios and compare them to the ratings of original movies," he said, "there's only one-point difference."  THE MEDIA BUSINESS  Correction:  August 31, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of a production error, an article on the Media Business page on Monday about Steven Hewitt, the executive vice president of the Showtime Entertainment Group, included several scrambled passages in some copies. Readers wishing corrected copies of the article may write to Production Quality Control, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="correction_text">
        <p>Correction: August 31, 1994, Wednesday</p>
        <p>Because of a production error, an article on the Media Business page on Monday about Steven Hewitt, the executive vice president of the Showtime Entertainment Group, included several scrambled passages in some copies. Readers wishing corrected copies of the article may write to Production Quality Control, The New York Times, 229 West 43d Street, New York, N.Y. 10036.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
