<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Desert Sword: Time for Answers</title>
    <meta content="14" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="11" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1990" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Wednesday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Editorial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="28" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Opinion" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="400583"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1990"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES ARMAMENT AND DEFENSE</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">EDITORIALS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">UNITED STATES INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MIDDLE EAST-INTERNATIONAL RELATIONS-US</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">MIDDLE EAST</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">PERSIAN GULF</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">BUSH, GEORGE (PRES)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Editorial</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Opinion/Opinion/Editorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/Middle East</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Armament and Defense</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">International Relations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Armament, Defense and Military Forces</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19901114T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C0CE4DA1039F937A25752C1A966958260" item-length="493" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Desert Sword: Time for Answers</hl1>
      </hedline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>Suddenly, in the wake of President Bush's declaration of possible war against Iraq, members of Congress clamor to be heard. They're acting not merely within their rights but within their responsibilities.</p>
        <p>President Bush deserved and won wide support for creating Desert Shield in Saudi Arabia. But now, with hardly a justifying word, he has transformed that policy into Desert Sword. Mr. Bush, who has repeatedly left himself open to criticism for failing to articulate America's interests in the crisis, can now be called to account.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>Suddenly, in the wake of President Bush's declaration of possible war against Iraq, members of Congress clamor to be heard. They're acting not merely within their rights but within their responsibilities.</p>
        <p>President Bush deserved and won wide support for creating Desert Shield in Saudi Arabia. But now, with hardly a justifying word, he has transformed that policy into Desert Sword. Mr. Bush, who has repeatedly left himself open to criticism for failing to articulate America's interests in the crisis, can now be called to account.</p>
        <p>Though some members would have preferred a special session of Congress, this purpose can probably be satisfactorily met by the hearings the Senate has now scheduled. It would be folly for the White House to ignore the unease expressed in varying ways by Democratic senators like Sam Nunn, Claiborne Pell and Daniel Patrick Moynihan and Republicans like Richard Lugar of Indiana.</p>
        <p>What all these voices are saying is that Congress has a rightful constitutional share in war-making decisions. Congress and the public need deliberate discussion of:</p>
        <p>* Mr. Bush's abrupt turn from a policy of deter- and-defend to one of offensive capability;</p>
        <p>* His sudden impatience with the effectiveness of the international sanctions against Iraq;</p>
        <p>* His concept of the alliance arrayed against Iraq, for now and in the future.</p>
        <p>Calls for a declaration of war seem premature, as do proposals to invoke the War Powers Act.  Congress chose before adjourning to accept Mr. Bush's claim that American forces in Saudi Arabia were in no imminent danger, thereby avoiding the act's 60-day clock.</p>
        <p>But the newly announced buildup has stretched to the limit the initial rationale for ducking the war powers argument. Well-wishing senators complain that they have been given little more than generalities at briefings in which even the Secretary of Defense deflects legitimate questions, saying lamely, "That's above my pay grade."</p>
        <p>"If ever a blockade might work, it's here," says Senator Moynihan, who has yet to hear a comprehensive appraisal of the effect of United Nations sanctions on Iraq's economy. And there are other questions, like why the new buildup was announced before the U.N. Security Council could adopt a use-of-force resolution.</p>
        <p>The unease is heightened by how much Mr. Bush has vacillated in declaring his objectives. He wanted to deter an Iraqi invasion of Saudi Arabia; free Kuwait, uphold world law, defend the American way of life, protect American lives and build a regional security system that would assure access to gulf oil. Now his Secretary of State proclaims that the real purpose is to save American jobs.</p>
        <p>As a crisis manager, the President has performed admirably; as a mobilizer of political support, he has veered all over the lot. He may well have a solid case but still hasn't made it. A full-dress televised hearing will offer a proper forum, and test. The questions keep reverberating.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
