<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Market Place; Head of Fund Has Soft Spot For Macy's</title>
    <meta content="15" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="5" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1992" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Friday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Financial Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="8" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="D" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="Business" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="528718"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1992"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">STOCKS AND BONDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">MUTUAL FUNDS</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">INVESTMENT STRATEGIES</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">MACY, R H, &amp; CO INC</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">PRICE, MICHAEL</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">ANTILLA, SUSAN</person>
        <object.title class="indexing_service">MARKET PLACE (TIMES COLUMN)</object.title>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Business/Columns/Market Place</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Mutual Funds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Stocks and Bonds</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19920515T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E0CE4DA133BF936A25756C0A964958260" item-length="892" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Market Place; Head of Fund Has Soft Spot For Macy's</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By Susan Antilla</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">ANTILLA, SUSAN</byline>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>MAYBE it has something to do with his father's years of running a chain of clothing stores. Or perhaps it was that first summer job when he worked for a brokerage firm perched in the heart of New York's garment district.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, Michael Price, a mutual-fund manager, has a soft spot for the rag trade. All told, he has losses of $74 million because of investments in Alexander's Inc. and, more significantly, R. H. Macy &amp; Company sideswiping the otherwise shining performance of his three mutual funds.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>MAYBE it has something to do with his father's years of running a chain of clothing stores. Or perhaps it was that first summer job when he worked for a brokerage firm perched in the heart of New York's garment district.</p>
        <p>Whatever the reason, Michael Price, a mutual-fund manager, has a soft spot for the rag trade. All told, he has losses of $74 million because of investments in Alexander's Inc. and, more significantly, R. H. Macy &amp; Company sideswiping the otherwise shining performance of his three mutual funds.</p>
        <p>With the Macy bankruptcy, Mr. Price is thrust into the limelight as a member of the board that will have to decide a range of issues about the future of Macy. He is also a close adviser to Laurence A. Tisch, the CBS chairman who has held sway on the Macy board. Mr. Tisch invested in Macy at Mr. Price's encouragement.</p>
        <p>At 40 years old, Mr. Price is the well-thought-of manager of three mutual funds with respectable records. Investors who plunked money down for any of the three -- Mutual Shares, Mutual Qualified or Mutual Beacon -- would have outperformed most competing funds over the last five years, according to Lipper Analytical Services.</p>
        <p>But his Macy misstep has been a black mark. Mr. Price became intrigued in the early 1980's watching others hit pay dirt when companies went private, and he decided to try the strategy with his funds' money. "Here we were cashing out on stocks while the people we were selling to were making another 10 times on their money," he said.</p>
        <p>With $2.4 billion in assets in 1985 -- up from only $5 million in 1974 -- it behooved Mr. Price to command big positions. Thus in 1985, his funds invested $68 million in the Macy leveraged buyout. With the bankruptcy, though, the 13 million Macy preferred shares have since been written down to only one cent each.</p>
        <p>Until the Macy debacle, Mr. Price was most renowned for his trademark investment strategy of spotting "value" stocks. Unlike "growth" investors who seek out stocks with great earnings promise, value players focus on companies whose assets are worth more than their market capitalization -- stock price multiplied by the number of shares outstanding. The strategy served him well in the 1980's, when he outperformed the Standard &amp; Poor's 500 index in all but one year.</p>
        <p>The drag on performance from Macy, though, can be seen in Mr. Price's rankings in Lipper's growth and income category: in the year ending May 7, Mutual Shares ranked only 64th out of 226 funds in that category. Mutual Qualified and Mutual Beacon lagged even further behind.</p>
        <p>For his part, Mr. Price would be just as happy if the world could forget that he ever put millions into Macy.  "We were sober, had 20-20 eyesight, and knew exactly what we were doing" when the bonds were bought, he said. "It was a mistake," he added, with a fair amount of strain in his voice.</p>
        <p>So far this year, Mr. Price's funds are rebounding, ranking 13th (Mutual Shares), 11th (Mutual Qualified) and 10th (Mutual Beacon) of 248 funds.</p>
        <p>Through May 7, his fund customers enjoyed an average 8.9 percent gain, compared with a far more modest 1.7 percent gain from the average growth and income fund.</p>
        <p>Mr. Price got started in the money management business when he took a summer job working for Max Heine, a legendary Wall Street value player known for his ability to spot companies whose stock prices did not reflect their value. Mr. Price's initiation was a humble one: his main duties included cutting the news tape for his bosses. "Every 10 minutes some guy would yell, 'Get that stuff off the floor,' " he said.</p>
        <p>His timing could not have been better. In 1974, the last excruciating year of a bear market, stocks "were absolutely being given away," he said. Mr. Heine taught him the detective skills of spotting undervalued companies.</p>
        <p>Mutual Shares soared 30.7 percent in 1988, while the S.&amp; P. 500 gained only 14 percent. That year, Mr. Heine died in a car accident, leaving his protege to hold up the funds' record. In fairness to Mr. Price, value investing simply has not been so attractive a strategy since 1989. As investors turned from favoring value stocks to buying stocks that promised speedy earnings growth, the three Mutual Series funds languished.</p>
        <p>Michael Stolper, a consultant who evaluates money managers, said Mr. Price was "suffering from the sin of fidelity -- being faithful to his discipline."</p>
        <p>The recent good results, however, are proof that the patient investor can win by sticking with the value approach, said Kurt Brouwer of Brouwer &amp; Janachowski, a San Francisco firm that invests in mutual funds. Mr. Price's position in Sunbeam Oster, the former Alleghany International, "is worth 10 times what they paid," Mr. Brouwer added.</p>
        <p>Some bankruptcy experts value Mr. Price's Macy preferred stock, which does not trade, at 30 cents to 40 cents a share, substantially higher than the penny a share he wrote it down to. "I'm being conservative but also realistic," Mr. Price said. "It's all upside, no downside,"</p>
        <p>As for Alexander's, "over time, I think the values will come out," he said, although that's little consolation for his fund investors, who today have an investment worth half what Mr. Price paid for it. "It's more than hope," he said. "I will make sure I make money on the stock. I'm 40, and I've got 20 to 30 years to wait around."</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
