<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Ailing Statue: Symbol of Industry or Pork Barrel?</title>
    <meta content="Y19VUL$06" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="19" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="7" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="2001" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Thursday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="National Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="14" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="A" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="U.S.; Washington" name="online_sections"/>
    <meta content="http://www.nytimes.com/2001/07/19/national/19VULC.html" name="alternate_url"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="1310579"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="2001"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <location class="indexing_service">Birmingham (Ala)</location>
        <location class="indexing_service">United States</location>
        <person class="indexing_service">Firestone, David</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Mccain, John (Sen)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/World/Countries and Territories/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S.</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./U.S. States, Territories and Possessions/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/U.S./South</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Washington/Campaign 2008/Candidates</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Banking, Finance and Insurance</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Government, Philanthropy and NGO</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama/Birmingham</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Destinations/North America/United States/Alabama</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="descriptor">Politics and Government,Taxation,Budgets and Budgeting,United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Budgets and Budgeting</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Taxation</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Monuments and Memorials</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Finances</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">United States Politics and Government</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Politics and Government</classifier>
        <location class="online_producer">Birmingham</location>
        <org class="online_producer">Works Progress Administration</org>
        <person class="online_producer">Jones, Stephen</person>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="20010719T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9C01E2DA173AF93AA25754C0A9679C8B63" item-length="1023" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Ailing Statue: Symbol of Industry or Pork Barrel?</hl1>
        <hl2 class="online_headline">Ailing Statue: Symbol of Industry or Pork Barrel?</hl2>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By DAVID FIRESTONE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Firestone, David</byline>
      <dateline>BIRMINGHAM, Ala., July 16</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Sen John McCain attacks $3 million federal grant to restore Vulcan statue in Birmingham, Ala; singles it out as symbol of pork barrel projects in federal budget; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>With his body sliced into pieces and spread ignominiously over an asphalt parking lot, Vulcan looks as if he has already been laid low by Senator John McCain's flashing, budget-cutting sword.</p>
        <p>His 11,000-pound head, frozen in an iron grimace, appears to be maintaining a desperate grip on dignity, averting his eyes from his naked posterior a few yards away that was his best-known feature. The raised arm that once inspired a city to steel-making greatness now lies pockmarked and withered on the ground, awaiting the collection of a mere $12.5 million to point skyward again.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="online_lead_paragraph">
        <p>The Vulcan statue in Birmingham, Ala., has suddenly gone from a symbol of industry to an argument over federal spending, much to the dismay of locals</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>With his body sliced into pieces and spread ignominiously over an asphalt parking lot, Vulcan looks as if he has already been laid low by Senator John McCain's flashing, budget-cutting sword.</p>
        <p>His 11,000-pound head, frozen in an iron grimace, appears to be maintaining a desperate grip on dignity, averting his eyes from his naked posterior a few yards away that was his best-known feature. The raised arm that once inspired a city to steel-making greatness now lies pockmarked and withered on the ground, awaiting the collection of a mere $12.5 million to point skyward again.</p>
        <p>The beloved old statue that loomed over Birmingham for 61 years fell apart fairly naturally, given its age and the strain of eternally holding aloft a torch on top of Red Mountain. Originally built for the 1904 World's Fair in St. Louis, Vulcan was set on a pedestal above Birmingham in 1938 as an icon of the then-booming steel industry in the valley below.</p>
        <p>But it is the use of tax dollars to help put him back together that has infuriated Mr. McCain, who has spent the last week laboring to transform Vulcan, the Roman god of fire, from a symbol of industry into a symbol of pork-barrel spending, to the bewilderment and anger of the statue's many admirers here.</p>
        <p>Birmingham's leaders have been trying to raise the money to restore Vulcan since he was dismantled in 1999 for safety reasons, after city officials began to have nightmares of his limbs falling off and rolling down the mountain into downtown. While about 80 percent of the money will come from private sources, the nonprofit Vulcan Park Foundation asked the federal government to help with about $3 million in restoration money. The money would not only restore the 56-foot statue, but would also return the surrounding park to the rustic look of the Works Progress Administration era.</p>
        <p>Like thousands of other small projects in the federal budget, the grant to the statue was championed by local lobbyists and members of Congress, and seemed on its way to a quiet passage until Mr. McCain, the Arizona Republican better known for his support of a campaign finance overhaul, decided to make an example out of the project and butt heads with Vulcan.</p>
        <p>''While the federal surplus is rapidly dwindling, why should federal dollars pay for a face lift of a statue of a Roman god in Alabama?'' Mr. McCain asked on the Senate floor last Thursday, introducing an amendment that would block federal money for the project.</p>
        <p>''Not one more federal dollar should be spent on this kind of foolishness,'' he said. ''I ask my colleagues to extinguish this Roman god of fire and strike a victory for taxpayers -- and Metis, the goddess of prudence -- by throttling down our insatiable appetite for pork-barrel spending, starting today.''</p>
        <p>Mr. McCain said he knew that his amendment would never pass, and indeed, after passionate speeches in defense of Vulcan by Alabama's two senators, the full Senate approved the money for the statue on a vote of 87 to 12. But after Mr. McCain brought it up again on Sunday in an appearance on the NBC program ''Meet the Press'' and issued a news release calling for an end to federal subsidies to pagans, many Birmingham residents began to get annoyed.</p>
        <p>As every elected official knows, what is pork to 90 percent of the country is a vital or treasured project at home, particularly when covered with a scanty iron loincloth.</p>
        <p>''The senator is a little misinformed,'' said the Rev. Stephen Jones, pastor of Southside Baptist Church, which used to be in the statue's shadow. ''No one thinks of it as a pagan symbol. It's the symbol of our city, and with the economy the way it is, we need our symbol back.''</p>
        <p>Steve Yoder, chairman of the Vulcan Park Foundation, said Vulcan was no less a regional landmark than the Gateway Arch in St. Louis, or the Liberty Bell or -- pointedly -- the Grand Canyon.</p>
        <p>''O.K., maybe the Grand Canyon isn't a fair comparison,'' Mr. Yoder said, ''but there are certain symbols and destinations in this country that rise above simply local interests, and deserve a place in the federal budget.</p>
        <p>''The Vulcan statue represents the economic transformation of the South, and it's every bit as deserving as any other project.''</p>
        <p>Local residents interviewed here said they resented the characterization of their symbol as pork and had no trouble describing the statue's  importance in their lives, although few of them cited the economic transformation of the South.</p>
        <p>''It's where I had my first kiss,'' said Laura Hardy, a waitress at Jim and Nick's Barbecue, citing a common reason for idolatry at the park.</p>
        <p>''I had to stare at it every day in math class,'' said Ellen Bellsnyder, a colleague at the restaurant, whose high school was near the park. ''Now it's just an empty pedestal, and I miss it.''</p>
        <p>Granted, some of the city's affection for Vulcan was rooted in its slightly silly grandiosity, as it lacks the timeless grace of, say, the Statue of Liberty or Michelangelo's David. But there have been worse reasons for spending federal money. As The Birmingham News wrote a few years ago:</p>
        <p>''Sure, he's a green, scantily clad pagan. But at least he's our green, scantily clad pagan.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
