<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>Q&amp;A/Eileen Ogintz; On Taking Vacations With the Children</title>
    <meta content="OGINTZ$01" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Connecticut Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="3" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14CN" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="984965"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
        <person class="indexing_service">Ogintz, Eileen</person>
        <person class="indexing_service">Boyle, Alix</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="types_of_material">Interview</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Connecticut</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Features/Travel/Guides/Activities and Interests/Family</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/Classifieds/Job Market/Job Categories/Hospitality, Restaurant and Travel</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Travel and Vacations</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Children and Youth</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9503EFDD1231F937A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1757" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>Q&amp;A/Eileen Ogintz; On Taking Vacations With the Children</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By ALIX BOYLE</byline>
      <byline class="normalized_byline">Boyle, Alix</byline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Excerpts from interview with Eileen Ogintz, author of newspaper column Taking the Kids, who offers advice to parents planning trips with their children; photo (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>WHILE some travel writers focus on what to take when visiting Bali or the Galapagos Islands, Eileen Ogintz tends to stress the importance of remembering juice boxes and the pediatrician's phone number. Her ''Taking the Kids'' column is carried in more than 50 daily newspapers and on America Online, offering advice on where to go, what to take and what to do if things don't go as planned (and they never do).</p>
        <p>Ms. Ogintz's interest was piqued, she says, when she, her husband, Andy Yemma, and their then-3-year-old son were unceremoniously asked to leave a bed and breakfast after the management learned that the little boy was responsible for the resident cat landing in a goldfish pond.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>WHILE some travel writers focus on what to take when visiting Bali or the Galapagos Islands, Eileen Ogintz tends to stress the importance of remembering juice boxes and the pediatrician's phone number. Her ''Taking the Kids'' column is carried in more than 50 daily newspapers and on America Online, offering advice on where to go, what to take and what to do if things don't go as planned (and they never do).</p>
        <p>Ms. Ogintz's interest was piqued, she says, when she, her husband, Andy Yemma, and their then-3-year-old son were unceremoniously asked to leave a bed and breakfast after the management learned that the little boy was responsible for the resident cat landing in a goldfish pond.</p>
        <p>She was at the time a reporter for The Chicago Tribune and her editor  asked her to write a few articles on traveling with her family. When her third child came along, Ms. Ogintz quit the daily newspaper business to focus on family travel; she has written five children's travel books and one for parents called ''Are We There Yet? A Parent's Guide to Fun Family Vacations'' (HarperCollins, 1996).</p>
        <p>In an interview at her home as she was preparing for a trip to the Caribbean, Ms. Ogintz talked about traveling with children. Following are excerpts from the conversation.</p>
        <p>Q. Why has family travel become so popular?</p>
        <p>A. Because everyone wants to grab that all-too-elusive family time. We can't seem to get enough at home because we're working or at soccer games or we're doing the laundry. When you're away, it's a chance to be away as a family.</p>
        <p>Our philosophy of parenting is a lot different from a generation ago, when kids were supposed to be seen and not heard. Since so many mothers weren't working then, they wanted to go on vacation to get a break from the kids.</p>
        <p>Now, in the majority of families, both people are working, or they're single parents. They don't want to leave the kids behind because it's the only time they can be together. They want the kids to be able to be kids. I'm not saying you want them to be monsters, but an overtired 3-year-old is going to have a temper tantrum.</p>
        <p>I can't tell you how many miserable families I see at Disney World because they think ''Well we're here, we have to do everything.'' Meanwhile the kids are whining, the parents are tired, all they really want to  do is go back to the hotel so the kids can watch ''Rugrats.''</p>
        <p>This generation of parents traveled in their college years: backpacking through Europe, skiing, spring break. Once they became parents, they didn't necessarily want to give that up. Also, grandparents are much younger and more active and probably more well-heeled than a generation ago. They are the ones with the time and the money, so they want to share this with their grandchildren.</p>
        <p>Q. How many families are taking  the kids?</p>
        <p>A. The Travel Industry of America says that there were over 100 million trips last summer just with parents and kids. An astounding number, something like 11 percent, of all business trips, now involve a child. You can't go anywhere these days, even five-star resorts in the Caribbean,  and not see kids.</p>
        <p>The newest wrinkle is adventure trips: kayaking in Alaska, river rafting in Colorado, dog sledding in Minnesota. If you have the money, you can find an adventure. They're taking kids on safari, which can easily be a $20,000 tab for a family of four.</p>
        <p>The travel industry has been forced to respond to this very lucrative market. What parents should remember is that these places need them, so if they don't get what they want, there are plenty of other places who will give them what they want.</p>
        <p>Q. So how do parents get started on a vacation plan?</p>
        <p>A. The first thing is sit down and figure out what they really want. Do they want a kind of experience where the kids are going their own way all day long, like a camp? If they have a 3-year-old, do they want something where they can just get a couple of hours peace? Do they want an evening activity so they can have a quiet dinner?</p>
        <p>And they should include the kids, because even a 4- or 5-year-old can  have a say about what they'd like to do on vacation. You don't have to give the child the choice between San Francisco and Paris, but once you've decided to go to San Francisco, you could give your 4-year-old a choice about whether he wants to go to a science museum and push a lot of buttons or he wants to go to a zoo, or watch fishing boats on the wharf.</p>
        <p>One of the best ways to find information is to look on the Internet, then  call the place directly, and talk to the person in charge of the kids' activities. When you're investing a lot of money, it's worth a few phone calls.  What you're buying is family memories.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the single most important thing to remember when traveling with children?</p>
        <p>A. That things are not going to be perfect. Just like life, it's not going to go as you've planned. Just accept that and grab the sweet moments and remember that the horrible times make the best stories later.</p>
        <p>Q. What are some of your worst vacation stories?</p>
        <p>A. About four Christmases ago I was doing a book on California for kids and we were going to go skiing at Big Bear Lake for a few days. First, we got there and the place was like nothing that had been described over the phone. Then one after another, everybody got this violent stomach flu. So we were in this total  dump without a washing machine and everybody was really sick.  You're all in it together, though, so it adds to the family experience.</p>
        <p>Q. Are people choosing to spend money on vacations rather than other purchases?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, Yankelovich Partners has done some research where people have said they've put off capital purchases in favor of a vacation. And  they're not just traveling over the summer anymore. They're grabbing whatever time they can, whether it's  five days at Thanksgiving or the week of Christmas or spring break.</p>
        <p>Q. Some travel journalists accept free trips. Do you?</p>
        <p>A. No. The major newspapers that run my column don't like me to. You don't get treated the same when you take free trips. When I do my column, I try to write about it warts and all.</p>
        <p>Q. We've all sat next to screaming toddlers on planes. What are your tips for how to minimize screaming?</p>
        <p>A. A bag of surprises is a good bet. Some of my favorites would be Duplos or a couple of their favorite plastic characters. For a preschooler it might be a book and a finger puppet. You want a bunch of different things, because their attention span is really short.</p>
        <p>I want to make a pitch for people to buy a seat for their toddler because even though the F.A.A. won't mandate it, research shows that kids are much safer in safety seats in severe turbulence, never mind a plane crash. If you can't afford a seat, try to fly off-peak time and carry your safety seat to the gate. If the plane is full, they can gate check it. They are supposed to give you a seat for the baby if there is one available.</p>
        <p>Q. What are your tips about ski vacations?</p>
        <p>A. If your kids are little, you don't need to be at premier areas. Again, it's worth investing in a phone call.  You want to find out about the kids' ski school: what's the ratio of teachers to kids, do the teachers have special training in teaching children, and how do you find me on the mountain in an emergency? Virtually every major ski area has kids' programming, but some is better than others.</p>
        <p>If your kids are older, you might want to be in a place where you're going to feel more comfortable letting them go off by themselves, someplace where there's one major base area. You want to look for areas that will have a deal.</p>
        <p>Snowbird in Utah is a great bet, especially for single parents, because two kids 12 or under can ski free with one parent. At Crested Butte in Colorado, kids pay their age. If you're 10, you pay $10 for a lift ticket. If your kids are rank beginners, the Woodstock Inn in Vermont has this program at Suicide Six where they'll give you a lift ticket and ski rental as part of what you're paying for the room.</p>
        <p>As far as little kids are concerned, what ski instructors say is that parents expect too much from the kids. If they're not into it, that's O.K. When they're ready to quit, let them quit.</p>
        <p>Q. What is the most popular destination for families?</p>
        <p>A. Orlando. It's a shame to limit  yourself to that, but there's nothing like it; Orlando is like theme park  heaven, especially with Disney World. It can be exhausting and expensive, but everybody is probably going to do it at least once.</p>
        <p>Q. Is it important for parents to get away without the kids?</p>
        <p>A. Yes, definitely. Even just for a weekend. It's good for the kids to see that parents' entire lives aren't just them. It's good for the parents to get a new perspective on each other. The kids won't feel deprived as long as they have a special time too -- a  favorite preschool teacher watching  them or a sleepover at their favorite cousin's house. As long as you set up some things for them, it's a good thing to do.</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
