<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE nitf SYSTEM "http://www.nitf.org/IPTC/NITF/3.3/specification/dtd/nitf-3-3.dtd">
<nitf change.date="June 10, 2005" change.time="19:30" version="-//IPTC//DTD NITF 3.3//EN">
  <head>
    <title>The View From/Hastings-on-Hudson; Toys That Do More Than Merely Amuse</title>
    <meta content="4VIEW" name="slug"/>
    <meta content="4" name="publication_day_of_month"/>
    <meta content="1" name="publication_month"/>
    <meta content="1998" name="publication_year"/>
    <meta content="Sunday" name="publication_day_of_week"/>
    <meta content="Westchester Weekly Desk" name="dsk"/>
    <meta content="2" name="print_page_number"/>
    <meta content="14WC" name="print_section"/>
    <meta content="1" name="print_column"/>
    <meta content="New York and Region" name="online_sections"/>
    <docdata>
      <doc-id id-string="984982"/>
      <doc.copyright holder="The New York Times" year="1998"/>
      <identified-content>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="indexing_service" type="descriptor">Toys</classifier>
        <org class="indexing_service">Toys For Special Children (Co)</org>
        <org class="indexing_service">Enabling Devices (Co)</org>
        <person class="indexing_service">Kanor, Steven E (Dr)</person>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/New York and Region/Westchester</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="taxonomic_classifier">Top/News/Health/Diseases, Conditions, and Health Topics/Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Handicapped</classifier>
        <classifier class="online_producer" type="general_descriptor">Toys</classifier>
      </identified-content>
    </docdata>
    <pubdata date.publication="19980104T000000" ex-ref="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9404EEDB1231F937A35752C0A96E958260" item-length="1145" name="The New York Times" unit-of-measure="word"/>
  </head>
  <body>
    <body.head>
      <hedline>
        <hl1>The View From/Hastings-on-Hudson; Toys That Do More Than Merely Amuse</hl1>
      </hedline>
      <byline class="print_byline">By LYNNE AMES</byline>
      <dateline>HASTINGS-ON-HUDSON</dateline>
      <abstract>
        <p>Profile of Dr Steven E Kanor of Hastings-on-Hudson, NY, rehabilitation engineer who, through his companies, Toys for Special Children and Enabling Devices, designs and makes toys and devices for disabled children and adults; photos (M)</p>
      </abstract>
    </body.head>
    <body.content>
      <block class="lead_paragraph">
        <p>THIS is the time of year when children are playing with their holiday toys, but there is a group of youngsters for whom the mere act of being able to play at all is something of a miracle.</p>
        <p>Dr. Steven E. Kanor, who lives and works here, is a rehabilitation engineer who prescribes, designs and makes toys for disabled children. He also develops other objects, known as enabling devices, which help children and adults with disabilities. Some are as simple as an easy-to-manipulate switch, which with a single touch can activate a motorized toy; others are as complex as a visual communication system in the form of a combination clock and story board, for those who must express their needs without speaking. In all cases, Dr. Kanor's companies, Toys for Special Children and Enabling Devices, make things easier for people for whom life can be very difficult.</p>
      </block>
      <block class="full_text">
        <p>THIS is the time of year when children are playing with their holiday toys, but there is a group of youngsters for whom the mere act of being able to play at all is something of a miracle.</p>
        <p>Dr. Steven E. Kanor, who lives and works here, is a rehabilitation engineer who prescribes, designs and makes toys for disabled children. He also develops other objects, known as enabling devices, which help children and adults with disabilities. Some are as simple as an easy-to-manipulate switch, which with a single touch can activate a motorized toy; others are as complex as a visual communication system in the form of a combination clock and story board, for those who must express their needs without speaking. In all cases, Dr. Kanor's companies, Toys for Special Children and Enabling Devices, make things easier for people for whom life can be very difficult.</p>
        <p>''We basically are dealing with people who have something missing,'' he said. ''They're neurologically impaired, whether from an accident or a disease like cerebral palsy, and cannot move the body, or they can't see, or can't speak. We are trying to work with whatever is left, to focus on what they do have.''</p>
        <p>One of Dr. Kanor's long-term clients is the Thomas and Agnes Carvel Foundation Children's Rehabilitation Center at St. Agnes Hospital in White Plains. Dr. Kanor meets  regularly with therapists, staff members and children to get ideas for his inventions. He talks to participants, makes a prototype and brings it back to test it out.</p>
        <p>''All children have a right to play; it is considered be to be one of the universal rights of childhood,'' Maureen Tomkiel, director of education at the center, said. ''The play aspect is vital for all children. These are children who, if they were not disabled, would be playing with toys that their parents could pick up simply by walking into a store. But the children at our center can't play with ordinary toys, so they need someone like Dr. Kanor.''</p>
        <p>Even though the purpose of many of the toys is twofold -- for the child's enjoyment and to teach a skill -- the most important thing is for the youngster to enjoy the experience, added Gail Cocciardi, project coordinator at the center. ''The ones we know are real hits are the ones that make the kids' eyes light up,'' she said. ''Then we know we really have something.''</p>
        <p>One of the most basic components of Dr. Kanor's work is the construction of various switches. In his office and workshops, he and his employees make switches that can activate toys and other objects. The switches, which are electronically operated, do not look like ordinary light switches. Depending on need, they may be large and flat, like boards, curved, or textured, to give tactile stimulation. A single touch sends a series of electronic impulses to the desired object.</p>
        <p>In the case of toys that are simply adapted, there are things like Pudgy Piglet, a fluffy pink pig, which oinks and wiggles its tail; Roly Poly Calf, which moos and nods its head, and Floppy Bunny, which hops and wiggles its nose.</p>
        <p>On a more complex level, there are objects like Dome Alone. This is a transparent plastic dome filled with brightly colored bits of confetti. In this instance, the switch is part of the object. A child touches the dome, and, as Dr. Kanor's catalogue explains, ''is rewarded with a tempest of color, vibration and light.''</p>
        <p>Dr. Kanor said, ''It is important to stimulate as many senses as possible to actively stress sensory stimulation.''</p>
        <p>Toward that end, there is also a multi-sensory bead chain with an unbreakable plastic mirror. The beads provide something interesting to touch; the mirror, something to look at. In the version with music, moving the beads activates a built-in music box. There is also a crawl-through design,  developed with input from the St. Agnes team.</p>
        <p>Another object inspired by the St. Agnes group is called a Side-Lyer Compact Activity Center. In the catalogue, it is described as a ''small-scale busy box designed to provide sensory stimulation and cognitive activity for the infant or child whose physical mobility may be limited due to positioning needs.'' In simpler terms, this means it is for someone who can neither stand nor sit, who must lie on his or her side virtually all the time. The object includes a pad, on which the youngster can comfortably rest, and a box, which contains a small bead curtain, a dome with sparkling sequins, a vibrating plate and a wooden ball, which, when pulled, plays music.</p>
        <p>Also from St. Agnes is the interchangeable music puzzle-switch, a puzzle with various shapes and blocks, which the child solves. When it is solved -- an activity which in itself teaches spatial relationships -- music plays. ''We take what the child has, let him use it and then let him see what he has done with his own skill,'' Dr. Kanor said.</p>
        <p>In the nontoy, enabling-device category are objects to promote independence -- or at least a version of it. For those who cannot use their hands or feet, or arms or legs, there is a straw-like tube; a puff of air into the tube can activate a switch that makes a wheelchair move. There is also the Gripper Prehensor, which has been tested by the severely handicapped in workshops. It is a helmet equipped with an electronic ''arm'' that has an electronic claw, which can pick up objects. Dr. Kanor said it has enabled people to work who might not otherwise have any chance for a job.</p>
        <p>Some of Dr. Kanor's objects can even go out on loan. St. Agnes Children's Rehabilitation Center has a toy library; parents can select a toy and take it home with them for a few weeks.</p>
        <p>Among those who have taken advantage of this is Adrienne Arkontaky, whose 6-year-old daughter, Jordan, has cerebral palsy and is visually impaired. Jordan's favorites, Mrs. Arkontaky said, are toys that play music. Although she is largely confined to a wheelchair, has a degree of intellectual impairment and has very bad vision, she does have good hearing. ''She loves music, and so I bring home switch plates, which you touch and music comes on,'' Mrs. Arkontaky said. ''She really likes the music, and, I think, she's beginning to learn a little bit about cause and effect, because when she presses the switch, the music comes on. It really does add to her quality of life.''</p>
      </block>
    </body.content>
  </body>
</nitf>
